<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF19_4</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff19_4_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff19_4_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff19_4_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff19_4_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff19_4_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff19_4_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff19_4_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff19_4_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff19_4_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff19_4_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff19_4_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff19_4_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff19_4_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff19_4_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff19_4_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff19_4_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>An explanatory lecture<lb/>
                For Vayekra<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>To sin err is human&#44; but to acknowledge oneself at fault in error is<lb/> godly.  so I learn from what we my Brethren have jointly read.<lb/>  The high&#45;priest officiating before ministering in the Holy of holies&#44; might involuntarily have<lb/> fallen into errors committed a fault.  He was naturally supposed to be fully conversant<lb/> with the Law&#44; still&#44; he might unawares have acted against in opposition to some ordi&#45;<lb/>&#45;nances and thus led the people astray.  How could that official<lb/> atone for a wrong unintentionally committed&#63; done&#63;  By making an<lb/> open confession&#44; through an offering indicative of his regret.<lb/>  The Senate of the nation&#44; might have arrived at a decision<lb/> conflicting with the words of Holy Writ.  Wisdom was surely<lb/> to have guided that tribunal in its deliberations.  Yet&#44; from<lb/> its midst&#44; grievous mistakes might have issued forth&#44; which<lb/> the community&#44; in ignorance&#44; readily accepted.  Ought the<lb/> dignity of that body&#44; to have prevented a public avowal of its misjudg&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment&#63;  No&#58; a burnt&#45;sacrifice&#44; like that brought by the<lb/> high&#45;priest&#44; when at fault&#44; was to tell all that the legisla&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion assembly had sinned.  Nay&#58; royalty itself was to<lb/> conform with that rule&#59; for&#44; a princely rank is not lowered<lb/> by the acknowledgment of one&#39;s hability to err.  And just be&#45;<lb/>&#45;cause a man raised to a lofty position station is regarded as the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>exponent of the Law&#44; therefore he must own his<lb/> offense shortcomings&#44; when he discovers that he has unwittingly<lb/> failed in his duty.  Thus will he add honor to himself&#44;<lb/> by honoring Truth&#44; for&#44; to sin err is human&#44; but to acknowledge oneself<lb/> at fault is godly.  Such&#44; my Brethren&#44; is the lesson de&#45;<lb/>&#45;rived from the contents of our Parasha.  And the sages commenting<lb/> on it utter the following sentence &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Happy may that age be considered&#44; in which men in power<lb/> being a trespass&#45;offering.&#34;  For&#44; they who are scrupulous about<lb/> unintentional mistakes&#44; will be naturally on their guard against<lb/> a <sic>wilful</sic> departure from the commands of God.<lb/>
                Indeed&#44; so conscientious were some of our ancient Doctors preceptors&#44; that<lb/> lest their conduct be not&#44; at all times&#44; faultless&#44; they shrunk<lb/> from positions of great responsibility.  It is narrated of B.<lb/> Joshua&#44;&#45;&#45;a needle&#45;maker by trade&#44; but a person of broad<lb/> culture&#44; and an astronomer besides&#45;&#45;that on one occasion he <sic>travelled</sic> at<lb/> sea with B. Gambiel&#44; the patriarch&#44; or president of the Sandhe&#45;<lb/>&#45;drin.  The latter had taken bread with the rest of his provision&#44;<lb/> but the former had also supplied himself with articles less apt<lb/> to mould.  Being detained in their voyage&#44; R. Gambiel<lb/> inquired of his companion whether he knew before hand what<lb/> was to happen&#44; that he had brought along what might<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>have seemed at first unnecessary.  R. Joshua answered&#44; that<lb/> he was not sure of the detention&#44; but he had learnt that a<lb/> certain Har&#44; appearing at distant periods and in various di&#45;<lb/>&#45;rections&#44; was had often deceived captains of vessels in their cal&#45;<lb/> &#45;culations&#44; and he wanted to guard against the possibility<lb/> of their having to suffer for with hunger.  The president of the<lb/> Sanhedrin astonished said exclaimed &#34;Are you so learned&#44; and work at a menial<lb/> trade&#63;&#34;  To which the other Rabbi replied.  &#34;You show sur&#45;<lb/>&#45;prise at my doing so mode of living.  Why&#44; I am acquainted with two of<lb/> your pupils who are living in utter destitution&#44; and nevertheless notwithstanding that<lb/> they their among their varied knowledge that which they have of mathematics is cannot be surpassed.&#34;<lb/>  On his return home&#44; B. Gambiel sent after those scholars intending<lb/> they should be entrusted with some lucrative office.  Suspecting<lb/> the object they did not obey the summons.  He sent again&#44;<lb/> and as they hesitated to accept the offer&#44; he made them over&#45;<lb/>&#45;come their diffidence&#44; by saying&#44; that to govern guide a people<lb/> aright is to serve the people&#44; and needing for the task<lb/> just such qualities as they possessed&#44; diligence&#44; patience<lb/> and forbearance.<lb/>
                Now&#44; contrasting the scrupulousness&#44; which the law<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>demands of its representatives&#44; and which so<lb/> influenced the conduct actions of some modest teachers in the days<lb/> of old&#44; with the assurance that some modern interpreters of<lb/> the same law evince&#44; and with their readiness to put on the badge<lb/> of office&#44; I cannot but ascribe the change to an almost<lb/> universal degeneracy.  I mean it in a mental as well as<lb/> in a religious point of view.  For&#44; if Israelites were well<lb/> informed about touching the history and precepts of the Bible&#59; if<lb/> they had not entirely cast aside a knowledge in with which<lb/> they ought to be familiar&#44; many new theories now eagerly<lb/> embraced would be rejected as untenable spurious.  I will illus&#45;<lb/>&#45;trate my assertion by an incident lately brought to my<lb/> notice.  A Hebrew&#44; observant of our practices&#44; conver&#45;<lb/>sing with a preacher of the law&#45;abolishing school&#44; was<lb/> presented with an array of reasonings as to the permission<lb/> of altering the Scriptural commands to suit times and cir&#45;<lb/>&#45;cumstances.  I shall this morning cite only one of<lb/> the arguments advanced&#44; reasoning to myself the privilege<lb/> of dwelling upon others&#44; hereafter.<lb/></p>
            <p>In the book of Leviticus&#44; which we have begun this Sabbath&#44;<lb/> are laid down the rules concerning sacrifices and the kind of food<lb/> of which we may partake.  In the 17th chapter&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>an ordinance is given&#44; which is repealed in Deuteronomy.<lb/>  I will state it.  While our fathers <sic>travelled</sic> through<lb/> the wilderness&#44; they were forbidden to eat meat&#44; unless the ani&#45;<lb/>&#45;mal had been brought first to the door of the Tabernacle&#44; and<lb/> slaughtered there&#44; spilling the blood upon the altar.  The<lb/> motive given alleged is that the children of Israel might not offer<lb/> any more to evil&#45;spirits supposed imagined to haunt deserted places.<lb/>  It must appear obvious to all&#44; that the ordinance meant<lb/> to wean the mind of the people from an idolatrous super&#45;<lb/>&#45;stition&#44; prevalent perhaps in Egypt&#44; and that obedience to<lb/> the behest was not difficult.  For&#44; as the sanctuary<lb/> moved with the congregation in their journeys and rested<lb/> when they stopped&#44; a person might with comparative ease<lb/> have driven there the animal&#44; whose flesh he desired to eat.<lb/>  Besides&#59; in the wilderness few could have been the opportu&#45;<lb/>&#45;nities of indulging in such food&#44; as the complaint made by<lb/> the people&#44; that the manna was their only sustenance&#44; evidently<lb/> shows.  But after the conquest of the holy land&#44; when the<lb/> manna had ceased&#59; when our ancestors settled in cities far apart&#44;<lb/> and the Tabernacle &#40;and afterwards Solomon&#39;s temple&#41; became<lb/> stationary&#44; it was impossible to enforce the prescription carried<lb/> out during the forty years&#39; wandering in uninhabited regions.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Therefore it was necessarily abrogated.  And we read in<lb/> the fifth book of Moses&#44; that our fathers were told they<lb/> might kill animals for their use&#44; wherever they chose&#44; as<lb/> soon as they were established in Palestine&#44; provided they did<lb/> so in a manner that the blood&#44; which is the vitality&#44; be<lb/> spilt on the ground&#44; and never eaten.  Now&#44; upon that<lb/> historical data fact&#44; the preacher above referred to&#44; based one of his<lb/> argument.  He inferred from what I have explained it&#44; that the law was to must ac&#45;<lb/>&#45;comodate itself to circumstances&#59; and that as well as one of<lb/> its rules provisions was abolished&#44; because no longer practicable&#44; so<lb/> might should others be set at naught&#44; when found too irksome.<lb/>  I cannot see the force of such reasoning.  Can you my Brethren&#63;<lb/>  Because the Divine Legislator altered a law rule&#44; which He had<lb/> enacted at one period for a specified purpose&#44; and which&#44;<lb/> changes in time and place&#44; put beyond the means power of hu<lb/>&#45;man performance&#44; therefore we may do away&#44; with at pleasure&#44;<lb/> with what imposes entails privations&#44; or savors makes us too strongly of eastern peculiar.<lb/> practices.  By that line of argument&#44; we are left then abso&#45;<lb/>&#45;lute judges of what may be retained&#44; and what may be rejected<lb/> in the Bible.  And as the sabbath and holidays&#44; stand<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>provokingly in our way&#44; not any less than dietary<lb/> restrictions&#44; we&#44; of the present age&#44; may declare the<lb/> same suspended.  In fact&#44; I am at a loss to understand why<lb/> this doctrine is not at once proclaimed from the pulpit&#44; it being<lb/> clearly logically deducible from the reasoning brought forward by more<lb/> than one preacher.  Perhaps the people are not considered<lb/> sufficiently prepared to accept it.  And as ministers&#44; after all<lb/> are bodily as well as spiritual creatures&#44; and they cannot<lb/> well spare the patronage of the faithful&#44; it may be im&#45;<lb/>polite to startle the flock with extreme views.  But if they&#44;<lb/> whose voluntary calling it is to back judge Judaism&#44; from a<lb/> Biblical and historical&#45;stand point consulted their obligation will<lb/> to their heavenly Master&#44; rather more than the indebtedness pleasures of man of<lb/> to their terrestrial constitutents&#44; they would discover that to<lb/> retrace their steps from a dangerous path&#44; rather than proceed<lb/> farther in its precipitous course is their real interest.<lb/>  For to it many run headlong&#44; in their subserviency to the whims<lb/> and crotchets of an inconstant multitude&#44; and the trespass<lb/> they commit is not of a nature&#44; as that for which our Parasha<lb/> prescribed an expiatory sacrifice.  It comes in the category of<lb/> the presumptuous sins&#44; which nothing&#44; save early repentance<lb/> can atone for.  Because&#44; he&#44; who knowingbeing conversant in the <sic>the</sic> law&#44; interprets it<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>falsely&#44; though he possess sacred learning and social virtues&#44;<lb/> will be cut off from a life everlasting.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>  Our young brother&#44; the Bar Mitzv&#225;h has involuntarily stigmatized unknowingly rebuked<lb/> that manner of teaching. such teachers.  He said in his portion that neither<lb/> leaven nor honey should be mixed in any offering of the Lord.<lb/>  Why should be that exclusion&#63; because the first represents arrogance&#44; the second worldliness&#44;<lb/> two detestable sins&#44; of which they who officiate at the altar should<lb/> specially be free.  For&#44; the effect of swelling with the idea of<lb/> self&#45;importancesufficiency is to override the law&#44; while excessive fondness<lb/> of the sweets of life&#44; <sic>stiffles</sic> the conscience.  Meekness<lb/> and abstinence are recommended by the Sages as distinguishing<lb/> characteristics of a religious instructor&#44; corresponding to the virtues<lb/> of Moses the first and greatest of our preceptors.<lb/></p>
            <p>My youthful dear little friend&#33;  Those traits qualities&#44; though not not so<lb/> vitally important in others as in him who ministers before the Lord&#44;<lb/> are nevertheless essentials in every man&#39;s conduct.  And I am<lb/> glad&#44; that the words repeated today&#44; and which you are not<lb/> likely to forget&#44; can serve as a reminder of the same &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;Of what is leaven or honey&#44; yet shall not<lb/> make an offering by fire unto the Lord&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Understand&#58; Worship God with lowliness of spirit.  Beware of the<lb/> leaven of hypocrisy.  Use moderation in gratifying your<lb/> wishes.  True&#58; Judaism does not forbid the pleasures is not a gloomy religion.  It does not preclude participating in the joys which earthly<lb/> existence presents proffers.  It proclaims that we can serve the Almighty<lb/> even while enjoying delighting in the blessings pleasures within our reach.  But Judaism condemns<lb/> an undue indulgence&#44; which&#44; like the eating of the luscious honey&#44;<lb/> fills to loathing&#44; and injures the body and the soul.  Let it be your<lb/> endeavour to keep body both healthy&#44; and how to do it effectually&#44;<lb/> another sentence you have rehearsed figuratively tells.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Thou shalt not suffer salt&#45;&#45;the symbol of the<lb/> covenant of the Lord Thy God&#45;&#45;to cease from thy offering.&#34;  To season and<lb/> preserve the oblation brought to the altar&#44; salt was indispensable.<lb/>  To maintain your physical and spiritual well&#45;being&#44; for which<lb/> God cares more than for burnt&#45;sacrifices&#44; you must be impregnated<lb/> as it were&#44; with the principles of the Torah.  That is the salt&#44; which<lb/> will hold you in a sounds state&#44; uncorrupt and incorruptible.<lb/>  You have now taken upon yourself the observance of the Law.<lb/></p>
            <p>And you have discernment enough to understand comprehend the consequence of being<lb/> bound to the performance of certain obligations.  <sic>Fulfil</sic> them&#44; at present&#44;<lb/> to the best of your abilities.  More will not be demanded of you.  But<lb/> in proportion as your abilities increase&#44; your obedience of the precepts<lb/> should be greater and more diversified.  For unto whomsoever<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>much is given&#44; of him shall much be required.  May<lb/> you never be found wanting.  But from this hour&#44; may<lb/> a career of usefulness to yourself&#44; of <sic>profitablness</sic> to your<lb/> neighbor&#44; and of credit in to the faith you have publicly<lb/> professed in public brightly open.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
