<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF3_18</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_18_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_18_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_18_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_18_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_18_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_18_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_18_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_18_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_18_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_18_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_18_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_18_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_18_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_18_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_18_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_18_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Post&#45;Biblical Lecture<lb/>
                18th.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  The country which God promised Abraham<lb/> to give his descendants&#44; was exposed at different times<lb/> to the attacks of different peoples.  In the Hebrew<lb/> Bible Scriptures we are shown the rise and fall of Palestine&#44; as<lb/> the invariable accompaniment of the virtues or vices<lb/> of its inhabitants.  After the breaking up of our<lb/> nationality by the arms of the Chaldeans&#44; we are<lb/> made to witness the effects of a return to righteous&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness in the protection granted to our ancestors by<lb/> dynasties which succeeded each other in the East.<lb/>  Later again&#44; the hand laid heavily upon us pointed<lb/> to our trespasses&#44; as to the leading cause of our suffering.<lb/>  A most remarkable period in our Jewish history is that<lb/> in which a single family&#45;&#45;a father and five sons&#45;&#45;&#44;<lb/> possessed of golden qualities&#44; purchased for us power independence<lb/> and deliverance freedom.  but Alas&#33; that within a century&#44;<lb/> the gradual degeneracy of the scions of that noble<lb/> family&#44; lost for us independence and freedom both those invaluable boons.  No<lb/> Mattathias arose after that&#44; but the cruel stranger<lb/> whom the greatest of prophets must have foreseen&#44; moved<lb/> swiftly on to work out our widespread destruction.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>For so Moses predicted&#44; when&#44; casting his<lb/> illumined vision on the distant future&#44; he noted<lb/> down the results of his people&#39;s sins.  &#34;The Lord will<lb/> will bring up a nation against thee from afar&#44;<lb/> from the end of the earth&#44; as the Eagle rushes<lb/> on&#59; a nation whose language thou wilt not<lb/> understand&#59; a nation of bold looks&#44; that will not<lb/> have respect for the old&#44; nor show favor to<lb/> the young.&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>The famous Roman consul and general in chief<lb/> honored with the name of Magnus&#44; was winning the victories of his commonwealth&#44;<lb/> while Judah&#39;s strength was being wasted away in the<lb/> unnatural contest of two Asmonean brothers.<lb/>  Pompey had been had reached the zenith of his glory&#44; and was flushed with success.  He had planted<lb/> his Eagle on the walls of Damascus&#44; the most ancient<lb/> city in the ancient land of Aram.  He had made himself complete master<lb/> of the whole of Syria.  He aspired to the glory triumph<lb/> of going back to Rome and presenting to the august Senate<lb/> all Asia&#44; as his gift.  The ambitious Roman<lb/> could not therefore wish for better tidings than the<lb/> report of the unhappy quarrel between Hyrcanus<lb/> and Aristobulus.  Accordingly&#44; he <sic>despatched</sic> Scaurus<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>his lieutenant&#44; with an order to march immediately<lb/> upon the capital of Judea&#44; and inquire into the<lb/> cause of the contest.  But before Jerusalem<lb/> was entered by the &#34;nation from afar&#34; the &#34;nation of<lb/> bold looks&#44;&#34; two Jewish ambassadors waited upon<lb/> Scaurus.  They represented two opposite parties.<lb/>  Aristobulus II had sent a bagful of gold&#44;&#45;&#45;which<lb/> the avaricious Romans so covetted&#45;&#45;as well as a messen&#45;<lb/>&#45;ger&#44; to plead in his behalf.  Hyrcanus II adopted<lb/> the same course.  Perhaps the bag of gold was of<lb/> smallers size&#44; for Scaurus commanded that the older<lb/> brother and the Arab King&#44; who had come to his assist&#45;<lb/>&#45;ance should disband their armies&#44; and that the young&#45;<lb/>&#45;er brother&#44; relieved from a state of <sic>seige</sic> in which he had &#91;&#63;&#93; was held&#44; be acknowledged<lb/> King of Judea.  Who dared resist the dictation of a Roman<lb/> chief&#63;  But Aristobulus&#44; placed again in<lb/> power by the &#34;nation from afar&#44; a nation of bold looks&#44;&#34; which rushed on like the eagle&#34;<lb/> did not rejoice long over the superiority gained.<lb/>  Pompey heard that Aristobulus had hotly pursued<lb/> the Arabians&#44; who were leaving Judea&#59; that he had<lb/> fought them&#44; and killed seven thousands.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Aristobulus was not then a man not easily<lb/> tamed&#44; not one likely to submit unmurmuringly<lb/> to the demands of Rome.  He had then in his<lb/> veins some of the blood of that Judah&#44; whose re&#45;<lb/>&#45;nown had reached even &#34;the eternal city.&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>Pompey sat at Damascus&#44; triumphantly.  He<lb/> to received the homage of princes and potentates.<lb/>  Egypt&#44; the country of the Pharaohs&#44; and the domains realms<lb/> of the Ptolemies&#44; offered him a costly golden<lb/> diadem.  Aristobulus would ontire all in<lb/> oriental munificence.  He had in his posses&#45;<lb/>&#45;sion a work of art of the rarest value.  It<lb/> had been executed under the reign of his father<lb/> Alexander Janneus.  The It object consisted of a golden<lb/> vine with its branches&#44; leaves&#44; and fruits of the<lb/> same precious metal.  It stood on a ground<lb/> round which various animals&#44; skilfully designed&#44;<lb/> sported in a life&#45;like manner.  That object creation piece<lb/> of superb workmanship&#44; Aristibulus sent by<lb/> means of a scholarly Latin speaker.  Pompey<lb/> graciously accepted the present&#44; and listened to the<lb/> flattering polished address of the ambassador. who set forth the claims of Aristobulus<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>But another man was there&#45;&#45;Antipater.  He<lb/> had ostensibly come to plead for Hyrcanus&#44; and<lb/> remonstrate lament at his having been stripped of all powers&#44;<lb/> but the ulterior motive of the crafty Idumean<lb/> was to further the interests of his own household.<lb/>  Unfortunately&#44; he was helped&#44; without expecting it&#44;<lb/> by the messenger of Aristobulus.  For that incautious<lb/> individual let drop from his lips as unguarded remark reflect&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing on the character of Roman generals.  To say<lb/> that money had been extorted from Aristobulus by<lb/> those officials&#44; was&#44; assuredly&#44; a heinous offence.<lb/>  Pompey who had already formed his opinion of the<lb/> high&#45;spiritedness of Aristobulus&#44; dismissed the embassy&#44;<lb/> without pronouncing a decision.  He ordered in&#45;<lb/>&#45;stead that the two brothers abstain from rangling strife<lb/> and that they should appear in person&#44; the following<lb/> spring&#44; when he would be back sit again in Damascus.<lb/>  The imperious order cut Aristobulus to the quick.<lb/>  Had he followed his own promptings&#44; he would have<lb/> To refused compliance was his first a natural impulse with him&#44; but he had to <sic>yeild</sic> to the press&#45;<lb/>ing requests of friends of and political adherents.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>The spring season arrived.  Hyrcanus<lb/> and Aristobulus came before the self&#45;constituted<lb/> empire of their disputes.  Hyrcanus spoke<lb/> first.  He argued his case with much considerable force.<lb/>  He said&#58; He was older than his brother&#44; who had deprived<lb/> him of his birthright.  He loved peace&#59; he was not<lb/> like Aristobulus given to the practice of making in&#45;<lb/>&#45;cursions with his neighbors&#39; territories by sea or by<lb/> land.  He could bring the testimony of a thousand<lb/> of the most esteemed among Jews&#44; to prove that<lb/> his nation would not have taken up arms and<lb/> fought sect against sect&#44; if the his restless Aristobulus brother<lb/> had not gone about sowing the seeds of contention.<lb/>  When he ceased Aristobulus in his turn spoke little&#44; and will turned to the Roman with<lb/> ill&#45;suppressed anger&#44; at his compulsory humiliation.<lb/>  He briefly said&#58; If I am King&#44; as I have been these past<lb/> years&#44; it is because my brother is unfit to rule.<lb/>  Had I not assumed the government&#44; others to<lb/> whom it does not belong would have usurped<lb/> it.  My title to royalty&#44; is my father&#39;s heritage.&#34;<lb/>  The haughty tone did not please Pompey&#44; and he<lb/> evinced it in a reproachfuling answer.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>But Yet he would not act rashly.  He must<lb/> settle his affairs his affairs with the Arabians&#44;<lb/> then he would visit Jerusalem&#44; and settle Jewish<lb/> quarrels.  So he told the two inimical brothers.  But Aristobulus did not wait for<lb/> not the unwelcome call.  Departing from Damascus<lb/> unceremoniously&#44; he hastened to devise plans for<lb/> self&#45;defence.  Pompey had an intimation of it such a design&#44; and<lb/> turning his legions towards Judea&#44; stationed them<lb/> before Alexandrium&#44; an impregnable fortress&#44; where<lb/> Aristobulus had taken retired with his quarters troops.  The Roman<lb/> general bid the Judean King come forth and explain<lb/> his conduct.  Three and four times Aristobulus<lb/> made an attempt to obey&#44; but he was always forced<lb/> irresistibly back by his instinctive repugnance to submission.<lb/>  Finally he agreed to hold an interview&#44; but Pompey<lb/> bitterly enraged at the delay and vacillation compelled him to surrender the fortress<lb/> and to write to the commanders of all the fortresses<lb/> throughout the land&#44; to place those military strong&#45;<lb/>&#45;holds at the disposal of Rome.  A refusal would<lb/> have been imprisonment and bondage.  Nothing so degrading&#44;<lb/> nothing so suicidal in the mind of a Jew&#44; and that<lb/> an Asmonean&#45;&#45;though guilty of misdeeds&#45;&#45;as that act of subjection.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Aristobulus indignant at his own self for<lb/> having stooped so low&#44; prepared to fight back<lb/> the overbearing stranger.<lb/></p>
            <p>Historians are at variance about the exact account incidents&#44;<lb/> of the events which marked <sic>preceeded</sic> the hostile entrance of the<lb/> &#34;nation from afar&#34; into the inheritance of Abraham.<lb/>  As to myself I will grant even the worst enemies of our people&#44;<lb/> the benefit of a charitable construction.  It may<lb/> be true that the irrepressible temper of Aristobulus&#44;<lb/> incited Pompey to marshall his cohorts into the<lb/> city of David&#44; and to pollute the temple with their<lb/> bold heathen looks.  But was it not confessedly to<lb/> arbitrate a disputed case that Rome had come to Judea&#63;<lb/>  Why did she then let her eagle rush on and tear<lb/> our very entrails&#63;  It may also be true that the Judean<lb/> ruler seeing that the impossibility to cope with a power&#44; which could bring<lb/> myriads of well disciplined soldiers upon the battle field&#44;<lb/> had gone forth to meet the invader and promised at large<lb/> sum to aver the attack onset&#44; and that those attached to<lb/> his party declined acquiescence in his agreement.  All that<lb/> may might be probable undisputed facts&#44; but what can justify the foul treachery of the<lb/> Roman general&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>For Pompey retained the &#91;&#63;&#93; his retaining of Aristobulus as a war prison&#45;<lb/>&#45;er&#44; and bound them thrown into chains as a culprit&#63;  &#34;Woe to the<lb/> powerless&#34; such was the battle cry of insatiable Rome.  It was The artful<lb/> policy of the republic on the seven&#45;hilled city was to take<lb/> advantage of the weakness of empires and kingdoms&#44;<lb/> and crash them out of existence.  Had the Jews&#44;<lb/> like the Arabians&#44; and other nations&#44; allowed them&#45;<lb/>&#45;selves to be denationalized and have become part and parcel<lb/> of the Roman commonwealth&#44; her generals would not<lb/> have brought against Zion their battering rams.  But<lb/> they our people dared confront the mighty legions and measure arms<lb/> with the invincible cohorts.  Annihilation must there&#45;<lb/>&#45;fore be their doom.<lb/></p>
            <p>A cry of horror went up to heaven at the noise of<lb/> treading battalions&#44; and the prancings of fiery studs.<lb/>  She comes from afar&#44; the fierce one&#44; who does not respect<lb/> the old&#44; nor show favor to the young.  The fol&#45;<lb/>&#45;lowers of Aristobulus&#44; the priests of Pharisees Sadducees&#44; en&#45;<lb/>&#45;trenched themselves again behind the fortified walls<lb/> of the Temple&#44; and challenged the heathen foe to<lb/> dislodge them.  The feeble minded Hyrcanus&#44; controlled<lb/> by the hollow&#45;hearted Antipater&#44; opened the gates for the unrighteous<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>to come in enter.  Piso&#44; one of Pompey&#39;s lieutenants&#44; took<lb/> possession of Jerusalem and placed it under military<lb/> law.  The peace party he treated with Roman<lb/> magnanimity.  He ate of their provision&#44; and accepted<lb/> their gold.  The war of party he summoned to sur&#45;<lb/>&#45;render and bend to the will of a superior power.<lb/>  The demand met with a stern refusal.  Aristobu&#45;<lb/>&#45;lus must be freed from the ignominious bondage<lb/> into which he had been ensnared&#44; then will before his<lb/> adherents will parley with the enslavers.  He was their<lb/> king and leader.  The impotent stolid Hyrcanus had<lb/> sworn to the treaty in the sacred Temple&#44; where the holy ark and he would<lb/> have kept faith to it&#44; but had it not been for the egotiscal perfidious schemes<lb/> of an agent of <sic>dissention</sic>.  But Rome was not ac&#45;<lb/>&#45;customed to rebuffs.  Pompey who had pitched<lb/> his text on Mount Olives&#44; came down in person to awe<lb/> the defiant ones into submission.  Deadly engines&#44;<lb/> brought purposely from Tyre&#44; were set against<lb/> the Northern side of the Temple.  A huge wall<lb/> was raised to prevent the escape of the besieged&#44;<lb/> or the possibility of their receiving help from outside sympathizers.</p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>Thus began a tremendous portentous struggle&#45;&#45;the most<lb/> momentous in the annals of mankind.  The poly&#45;<lb/>&#45;theism of Olympus&#44; measuring arms entering the arena with the<lb/> monotheism of Zion.  Appalling was the<lb/> encounter.  Judea fought&#44; till <sic>disjoined</sic> and<lb/> broken she sank from exhaustion.  But she<lb/> fell&#44; still holding fast on the ensign of God&#39;s<lb/> Unity.  When she could rise and be suffered to allowed<lb/> breathe&#44; she carried that holy standard up high<lb/> eighteen hundred years&#44; in the sight of Gentilism.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
