<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF4_10</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_10_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_10_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_10_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_10_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_10_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_10_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_10_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_10_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_10_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_10_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_10_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_10_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_10_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_10_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_10_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_10_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Post Biblical history<lb/>
                30<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>It was once said&#44; that the history of the Jews waits<lb/> for an historian.  I venture the opinion that our<lb/> people&#39;s misfortune is to have had only one historian&#44;<lb/> from whom all necessarily drew their knowledge.  After<lb/> the closing of the Scriptures&#44; which Christians call<lb/> the &#34;old testament&#34;&#45;&#45;an event which that cannot have<lb/> taken place later than in the days of Mattathias the<lb/> Asmonean and his sons&#45;&#45;we were left with but<lb/> few scattered documents telling us what happened<lb/> to our forefathers in Judea and various countries in<lb/> which they had settled.  The two books of the<lb/> Maccabees and some other volumes of the Apocrypha&#44;<lb/> or non&#45;canonical additions to our Scriptures&#44; throw considerable light<lb/> on the subject&#44; but they are tinctured now and then<lb/> with ideas foreign to the Jewish belief&#44; and therefore<lb/> their authority is accepted received with great caution.  The<lb/> &#34;new testament&#44;&#34; indirectly offers information which<lb/> is of historical value to us&#44; but how one sided&#44; how prejudiced<lb/> it is against those who could not conscientiously<lb/> admit the divinity of a man born of our race&#44; I need<lb/> not explain.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>The Talmud is a grand history in itself&#59;<lb/> priceless as a depository of our traditions&#44; and therein<lb/> are treasured up stored the truths and the errors&#44; the learning wisdom<lb/> and the ignorance superstitions of many ten centuries.  There we meet<lb/> incidentally accounts of events in which our people<lb/> played an important part both at home and abroad&#44;<lb/> but those occasional records are too few and detached<lb/> to serve as basis for our social and political his&#45;<lb/>tory.  Greek writers could not be trusted&#44; if they<lb/> had spoken at length about us&#44; for their ill&#45;<lb/>will is proverbially inveterate&#44; and the Roman<lb/> Tacitus&#44; famous as he is&#44; relates such absurdities<lb/> that stamp him at once &#44;as either the the dupe of an inimical party&#44; or a<lb/> <sic>wilful</sic> perverter of facts.  Just think of his stating<lb/> that the Jews had the image of an ass in the<lb/> Holy of Holies&#44; and that their laws taught them<lb/> to care nothing for parents&#44; children and brothers.<lb/></p> 
            <p>We have then none other but Josephus to de&#45;<lb/>pend upon for a consecutive knowledge of whatever concerns<lb/> the state of our ancestors&#44; from the time subsequent to<lb/> Nehemiah to the end of the national war with<lb/> Rome.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>He has been the main source from which all who&#44;<lb/> since his days&#44; have written on our history were com&#45;<lb/>&#45;pelled to draw.  I have called that a misfortune&#59;<lb/> but as Josephus deservedly enjoys a universal renown&#44;<lb/> I must define my meaning.  To make it clear.<lb/>  I need briefly sketch the life &#38; character of that celebrated writer.<lb/>  Joseph son of Matthias the priest&#44; or Cohen born in the year 37 of the vulgar era&#44; descend&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed on his mother&#39;s side from the illustrious Mac&#45;<lb/>&#45;cabees.  Of that he makes special mention&#44; and<lb/> dwells on it with pardonable pride.  His father is described as a<lb/> priest of high standing&#44; eminent for his piety not less<lb/> than for other virtues.  He gave Joseph a thorough<lb/> education&#44; under which the child&#39;s striking brilliant talents<lb/> and extraordinary memory <sic>developped</sic> very fast.  When<lb/> only fourteen years old&#44; he understood the Law and<lb/> traditions so well&#44; that his elders did not hesitate to<lb/> consult him on difficult points.  All of this&#44; mark<lb/> it down&#44; Josephus himself tells us.  At sixteen he<lb/> felt a strong wish to know the differences between<lb/> the three sects then existing in Judea&#44; the Pharisees&#44;<lb/> the Sadducees&#44; and the Essenes.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>He studied them&#44; but as the Essenes would<lb/> not easily admit strangers in their somewhat secret order&#44; he sub&#45;<lb/>&#45;mitted for a long time to severe privations&#44; and<lb/> associated with a certain Banus&#44; who led a life<lb/> of seclusion and did penance in a desert.  At nine&#45;<lb/>&#45;teen he <sic>quitted</sic> that teacher&#44; and went back to<lb/> Jerusalem&#44; convinced that the Pharisees were the most<lb/> sensible in their doctrines&#44; in their practices and man&#45;<lb/>&#45;ner of living.  Now from what has been said hitherto&#44; all can easily<lb/> perceive that Josephus had a will of his own&#44; which he<lb/> would not scruple to gratify at all hazards&#59; all must have also discovered<lb/> that he was not modest&#44; but vain by reason of his extraction and<lb/> his natural abilities.  These faults might<lb/> be overlooked&#44; owing to the incontestable fact that he was from good of excellent<lb/> parentage and that he had become very learned.<lb/></p>
            <p>Aside from his two extensive histories&#44; one on &#34;Jewish<lb/> Antiquities&#34;&#45;&#45;which is said to have been originally written in Hebrew&#44;<lb/>  and then translated into Greek&#45;&#45;and the other on the<lb/> &#34;Wars of the Jews&#34; which is reported to have been first written composed in Syro Chaldaic&#44; and then rendered in Greek&#44; aside also from his own auto&#45;biography&#44; one<lb/> cannot read his defense of our ancient laws and people against from<lb/> the aspersions of Apion the Alexandrian&#44; without noticing admiring<lb/> evidences of an erudition vast and varied&#44; not simply<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>in the sacred literature&#44; but also likewise in the literature of other various<lb/> peoples&#44; particularly of the Greeks.  Yes&#44; Josephus was a splendid scholar&#44; still withal&#44; Yet every<lb/> one who reads will lament that the influence of that<lb/> one man&#44; deprived posterity of the opportunity of hearing seeing<lb/> events described delineated by other pens beside that of as<lb/> person boastful beyond measure&#44; and bitterly prejudiced<lb/> against all who stood in his way in letters or<lb/> politics.  For it must not be supposed that&#44; as<lb/> Josephus would make us believe&#44; he alone possessed<lb/> the qualifications to write histories.  Others under&#45;<lb/>&#45;took that task&#44; but Joseph Cohen&#45;&#45;who in later<lb/> years took the more <sic>euphonius</sic> appellation of &#34;Flavius<lb/> Josephus&#34; to ingratiate himself with <sic>gratiously</sic> granted to him by Vespasian and<lb/> Titus&#44; whose family name was Flavian&#45;&#45;&#44; succeeded<lb/> in having the writings of his rivals consigned to obli&#45;<lb/>&#45;vion.  He cried down one Justus of Tiberias&#59; he so<lb/> abused the author and his work&#44; that he crushed both<lb/> under the displeasure of those in the imperial sun<lb/> shine of whose favor he himself basked to the end of in imperial Rome<lb/> his life<lb/></p>
            <p>But Josephus inflicted a more lasting serious injury upon us&#59;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>an injury which has followed us everywhere.<lb/></p>
            <p>I have already candidly confessed that the war party<lb/> in Judea&#44; or Zealots&#44; the disciples of Judah the<lb/> Galilean who had taught that to pay taxes to a<lb/> foreign power rulers was a crime&#44; did not show moderation&#44;<lb/> that many among them were blood thirsty cruel&#44; dishonest&#44;<lb/> treacherous&#44; but I shall never brand them all<lb/> as assassins.  There were thousands and tens of<lb/> thousands of noble patriots&#44; who gave their life blood<lb/> to their unhappy land.  The struggle was<lb/> indeed unequal.  Before coldly sober&#44; calculating minds it<lb/> was madness.  Neither I will not Not so to those who preferred martyrdom to slavery.  I will not however&#44; assert that all who<lb/> belonged to the peace party were designing traitors.<lb/>  Some of our Sages leaned in towards that side&#44; and advised<lb/> submission to an irresistible force&#44; so as to save shield the<lb/> Temple from ruin&#44; and avert desolation and dispersion.<lb/>  But who that is a Jew&#59; who that is a man will<lb/> revile a people that braves death in the desperate<lb/> effort to save honor and country&#63;  Who will deliver<lb/> such to the contempt of future ages&#44; because they inef&#45;<lb/>&#45;fectually&#44; heroically yet&#45;&#45;though daringly&#45;&#45;stood their ground and inch by inch fought<lb/> the advancing feo foe&#63;  Josephus did us that almost<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>irreparable wrong.  He pictured in the darkest<lb/> colours all his coreligionists and countrymen&#44; who<lb/> made despotic Rome pay the dearest for her conquest of<lb/> for that small people nation and that small land in<lb/> Western Asia.  Josephus&#44; doubtless to please his pa&#45;<lb/>&#45;trons&#44; the conquerors&#44; has furnished the world in sub&#45;<lb/>&#45;sequent ages with a weapon to strike us&#44; as the<lb/> children of those he represented as incorrigible to be have been rebels<lb/> by nature&#44; atrociously wicked.  When we are stigmatised by christian writers&#44; as stubborn and God&#45;forsaken&#44; our historian is quoted for the authority.  Had a Judah<lb/> Maccabee arisen then incorrigible&#44; in that hour of our sore distress&#44; and forced Roman legions<lb/> back to the Tiber&#44; Josephus and mankind at<lb/> large would have sang the praises of <sic>heros</sic> who<lb/> defied the insolent heathen&#44; and stood shoulder to<lb/> shoulder under the lead of their liberating Chief.  But<lb/> salvation kept far away&#44; and Josephus who was<lb/> believed true and therefore entrusted with military powers&#44;<lb/> surely did not contribute to bring salvation new.<lb/>  It will always remain a secret how and where he learned<lb/> the art of <sic>weilding</sic> the sword as he handled the<lb/> pen&#44; but as not history remains to contradict his dispute the authority<lb/> statements&#44; of his records&#44; we must give him the credit of for having<lb/> added to his literary attainments&#44; the genius of as a general<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>the skill of as a statesman&#44; and a courage equal<lb/> to all emergencies.<lb/></p>
            <p>After Agrippa II&#44; the last Jewish king of the Jews lost<lb/> cast with his people by having manifested a cowardly<lb/> disposition&#44; to openly cringing before Rome&#44; the war of independence<lb/> began in dead earnestness.  Near In the neighborhood of the city of<lb/> Massada an arsenal supplied the arms.  A man<lb/> called Meah Menahem&#44; grand son of Judah the<lb/> Galilean attacked the Roman took the lead.  A temporary success<lb/> emboldened the zealots to proceed.  The Romans were<lb/> attacked again and again&#44; and being unprepared for<lb/> so tremendous a revolution&#44; they sustained fearful<lb/> losses.  From all parts the population had arisen&#44;<lb/> and even many who&#44; actuated by interested motives usually preferred<lb/> to remain inactive&#44; swelled up the ranks and files&#44; and ranks&#44; either<lb/> voluntarily or by compulsion.  It was at that time<lb/> that Josephus appeared on the scene of military<lb/> operations.  Three years before&#44; in the twenty<lb/> sixth year of his age&#44; he had gained some notoriety<lb/> for having gone to Rome to intercede plead in behalf<lb/> of a number of Jewish priests&#44; transported and imprisoned<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>there by order of the pitiless tyrannic Felix&#44; governor<lb/> of Judea.  Those priests were Josephus&#39; personal friends&#44;<lb/> and he relates that the more inclined he felt to<lb/> help them&#44; because during their imprisonment they<lb/> had lived only on fruits&#44; so as not to defile them&#45;<lb/>&#45;selves with prohibited food.  By means of a Jewish<lb/> play actor&#44; a favorite of the wife of Nero&#44; Josephus<lb/> succeeded in his mission.  and The priests were released and he returned home with high<lb/> great honors.  Whether that circumstance won for<lb/> him the good will and confidence of his countrymen&#44; or<lb/> whether he concealed his views sufficiently to inspire<lb/> the hope that he would lead his soldiers to victory&#44;<lb/> it is impossible to ascertain&#44; since we have no other<lb/> version account of what took place than that which he chose<lb/> to give.  By him we are told that he was assign&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed the command of Galilee&#44; that his labors always<lb/> aimed to at the welfare of his people those under his guidance&#44; that the<lb/> administered justice&#44; used moderation&#44; and with mere<lb/> raw recruits&#44; he raised a well disciplined army ready<lb/> to defend their friends.  The sequel will show<lb/> that the choice of that commander was unfortunate.<lb/>  Josephus looked the principal elements of a chief&#59;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>he was in wanting in enthusiasm&#44; in a profound<lb/> belief in the righteousness of the cause&#44; for the<lb/> sake of which to die is glory.  Endowed with<lb/> a broad understanding&#44; he may have been able to<lb/> plan a battle&#44; but his heart was not wholly<lb/> given to his country&#59; it was divided between duty<lb/> and the love of life&#44; the ambition to shine as a<lb/> literary star&#44; and the fear of being forgotten among<lb/> the victims of a disastrous war.  Josephus was a<lb/> stranger to that unselfish&#44; pure&#44; noble sublime lofty patriotism<lb/> that sacrifices all to a principle.  Josephus was<lb/> great and was little.  He was great in the extent<lb/> of his learning&#44; little in his vanity&#44; and this egotism made<lb/> him deaf to the dictates of Jewish brotherhood&#44; and<lb/> rendered him a time serving flatterer of despotic Rome&#44;<lb/> of that Rome which trod under its iron hell bleeding Judea&#44; and carried<lb/> the burning torch into the Holy of Holies&#44; and dispersed<lb/> Israel to the four <sic>courners</sic> of the earth.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
