<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF2_8</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_8_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_8_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_8_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_8_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_8_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_8_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_8_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_8_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_8_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_8_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_8_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_8_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>72</p>
            
            <p>An exegetical lecture about the Samaritans<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Dear Brethren&#33;  In my exegetical remarks I<lb/> incidentally alluded last Sabbath to mount Ebal<lb/> towards which the imprecations which that we rehearsed in<lb/> the section of the day&#44; were to be uttered for the aban&#45;<lb/>&#45;donment of the behests of God.  It was my<lb/> intention then cursorily to speak also of the histo&#45;<lb/>&#45;rical importance which the opposite mountain&#44;<lb/> towards which the blessings were pronounced&#44; assumed<lb/> after the first restoration of Israel to their land.  But<lb/> the love of brevity bid me desist.  This mor&#45;<lb/>&#45;ning&#44; however&#44; I will afford those among my hearers<lb/> who are not thoroughly conversant with our post&#45;<lb/>Biblical history&#44; some useful information touching<lb/> the causes that established on mount Gerizim<lb/> a rival worship to that&#44; held at the Temple raised<lb/> upon mount Moriah.  From the<lb/> song of victory which Moses and his liberated brethren<lb/> shouted forth on the shore of the Red Sea&#44; we clearly<lb/> infer that it was God&#39;s design that those He had<lb/> so greatly <sic>benefitted</sic>&#44; should set apart in their<lb/> future country a place for national worship.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>It is only by the admission of that fact&#44; that<lb/> we can understand the glowing words of the poet&#44;<lb/> when piercing into the future&#44; he sees the Samaritan&#44;<lb/> which the hands of the Eternal Lord had established &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Yet nowhere in the Pentateuch<lb/> is the site in which that sacred fane was to have<lb/> been erected&#44; pointed out with exact precision.  Cer&#45;<lb/>&#45;tain passages occurring in that heavenly volume&#44;<lb/> seem to indicate the very spot subsequently chosen<lb/> by King David&#44; but their meaning is not suffi&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciently definite&#44; to be advanced as an irrefutable<lb/> argument.  This defect&#44; which a believing<lb/> Israelite considered of no moment&#44; since tradition<lb/> fully supplies it&#44; emboldened a caste of<lb/> spurious proselytes to Judaism&#44; to rear a Temple<lb/> in opposition to that&#44; which had become the centre<lb/> towards which the hearts of all the faithful converged.<lb/>  The Samaritans&#44; so called because they had been<lb/> transplanted from their native land to Samaria&#44;<lb/> when the rightful inhabitants of it were carried<lb/> into exile by by the Assyrian Monarch&#44; viewed<lb/> with extreme jealousy the royal privileges that<lb/> the enfranchised captives of Babylon had obtained under the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>auspices of Ezra and Nehemiah.  Frustrated<lb/> in their expectation that their claims to a com&#45;<lb/>&#45;munity of religion with the Hebrews&#44; would be<lb/> recognized by the leaders of our people&#44; they<lb/> joined in open antagonism to them.  Stung<lb/> with resentment at by the expulsion of a priest<lb/> who had allied himself in matrimony with a<lb/> daughter of their race&#44; they set up on mount<lb/> Gerizim&#44; which is in Shechem&#44; a temple after<lb/> the model of that&#44; which had just been raised<lb/> anew in the metropolis of Judea.  This act<lb/> of apostacy might have opened an <sic>insuferable</sic><lb/> chasm between them and the followers of tradi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tional Judaism&#44; but they were intent upon swel&#45; aug&#45;<lb/>&#45;menting their number by with the wavering and the re&#45;<lb/>&#45;creants in Israel.  The more easily to reach<lb/> their goal&#44; they betook themselves to the task<lb/> of tampering with the Pentateuch in a manner&#44;<lb/> which might justify&#44; in the eyes of the inexpe&#45;<lb/>&#45;rienced&#44; their baneful heresy.<lb/></p>
            <p>We read last Sabbath&#44; and on a previous occasion<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>also&#44; my dear Brethren&#33; that Moses had desi&#45;<lb/>&#45;gnated mount Gerizim as the place towards which<lb/> blessings were to be pronounced for the faithful<lb/> performance of the law.  Availing themselves<lb/> of the Scriptural preference given to that spot&#44; the<lb/> Samaritans asserted that the messenger of the Deity&#44;<lb/> had designed it likewise for the future sanctuary<lb/> which his prophetic eye had foreseen.  But<lb/> notwithstanding such plausible reasoning&#44; they<lb/> could not ignore that the perfect silence main&#45;<lb/>&#45;tained in the Pentateuch respecting the sanctity of<lb/> the Jerusalem temple&#44; was kept as well in regard<lb/> to their own sanctuary.  They could not cite<lb/> a passage from which it might be obviously<lb/> deduced that the Divinity would vouchsafe<lb/> to irradiate with his spirit the mountain they<lb/> had apportioned for his Tabernacle.  But they had<lb/> resolved not to be foiled in their unrighteous<lb/> undertaking&#44; they therefore had recourse to foul<lb/> means.  Frequently where Holy Writ alludes<lb/> to the settlement of Israel in Palestine&#44; their Scribes<lb/> surreptitiously inserted words that might be interpreted<lb/> as favoring their predilection for mount Gerizim.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Sometimes their audacity impelled them event to alter<lb/> a phrase for another which promoted the object they<lb/> had in vie contemplation.  Thus for instance&#44; in the<lb/> lesson of last week&#44; it is recorded that our forefathers were commanded<lb/> that on entering the land of their possession&#44; they<lb/> should engrave upon huge stones the condensed substance<lb/> of their religious duties&#44; and deposit the same on mount<lb/> Eb&#224;l&#44; where an altar was to be reared in honor to their<lb/> Divine Benefactor.  The Samaritans in order to<lb/> enhance in the mind of their adherents the sanctity<lb/> of their house of worship&#44; substituted the word Gerizim<lb/> for Eb&#224;l&#44; and arrogantly contended that inasmuch<lb/> as the blessings were to be uttered towards the former<lb/> mountain&#44; theirs must undoubtedly be the correct<lb/> copy.  As it may be easily imagined so<lb/> bold an encroachment upon what our ancestors<lb/> had guarded with extreme scrupulousness&#44; widened still<lb/> more the breach which already existed between them&#45;<lb/>&#45;selves and their wily opponents.  Recriminations<lb/> were freely indulged into&#44; and as times were<lb/> propitious to either party&#44; the other was made<lb/> to suffer.  So we read of John Hyrcanus<lb/> razing the Samaritan Temple to the ground&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>and again of its <sic>worshipppers</sic> polluting some<lb/> years after&#44; the hallowed fane of Zion.<lb/></p>
            <p>But it was decreed above that this exotic plant which<lb/> massed the vineyard of the Lord&#44; should not long<lb/> thrive.  After innumerable vicissitudes&#44; which<lb/> I could not attempt in my present lecture to describe<lb/> even succinctly&#44; the ancient denizens of Shechem<lb/> decreased very considerably in number&#44; and with<lb/> that lost the influence they once formerly commanded.<lb/>  Already as far back as in the twelfth century&#44;<lb/> they had been reduced to a small community&#59;<lb/> and in our own days <sic>travellers</sic> can find in the<lb/> East but exceedingly few representatives of the<lb/> once proud sect of the Samaritans.  Yet those<lb/> few still cling to their ancestral error.  They<lb/> deem it legal to offer sacrifices even beyond<lb/> the precincts of their consecrated mountain&#44; and<lb/> when unable to repair thither&#44; they present<lb/> oblations during the festivals&#44; in the city proper of Shechem.<lb/>  They deny the authenticity of the oral law&#44; and scorn<lb/> the idea of that any prophet should have<lb/> arisen after the death demise of Moses.  Hence the<lb/> Pentateuch is the only book which they hold in reverence.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>They are in possession also of a work which professes to<lb/> be a narrative of the events recorded in Joshua&#44;<lb/> but its contents bears evidences of its spuriousness.<lb/>  How grateful ought we then to be&#44; my Brethren&#33;<lb/> that those volumes have been preserved intact&#44;<lb/> which edify and comfort us with the spiritual<lb/> effusions of our seers and sages&#33;  Yes&#44; my<lb/> dear friends&#33;  We must be thankful first to<lb/> God&#44; who saved unscathed that invaluable trea&#45;<lb/>&#45;sure amidst the frequent conflagrations that<lb/> consumed together with the lives of Jacob&#39;s offspring many<lb/> of their learned productions.  And we must likewise<lb/> pay a tribute of respect to the memory of those<lb/> indefatigable men&#44; who though suffering the most<lb/> ruthless persecutions&#44; pursued with unabated ardour<lb/> their pious undertaking&#44; and bequeathed to us<lb/> a work which irrevocably establishes the text of<lb/> the whole Bible&#44; and thus prevents for evermore<lb/> the designing and unfaithful from tampering with the<lb/> sacred Original.  May we profit by the ef&#45;<lb/>&#45;forts of the righteous Massorites&#44; and by meditating on the<lb/> Scriptures in the transcendent language they were written&#44;<lb/> eschew the error into which they fall who set up<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>their fallacious judgments against the word of<lb/> inspiration.  &#34;Happy &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;the men who walketh not in the counsel of the ungodly&#34;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;But whose delight is<lb/> in the law of the Eternal&#44; and in his it he doth me&#45;<lb/>&#45;ditate day and night.&#34;  So may it be with each of<lb/> us.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
