<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF32_5</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet></placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_5_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_5_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_5_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_5_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_5_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_5_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_5_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_5_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_5_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_5_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_5_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_5_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_5_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_5_7v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>83</p>
            
            <p>An explanatory lecture about<lb/>
                the nature of the serpent mentioned<lb/>
                in the book of Genesis<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Dear Brethren&#33;  A time&#45;honored custom demands that the discourse<lb/> delivered by a Jewish preacher on this Sabbath&#44; should altoge&#45;<lb/>&#45;ther be directed to explaining the character of the ensuing<lb/> festival.  I have generally conformed with that goodly<lb/> practice&#44; and whereas on ordinary occasions&#44; I endeavour to<lb/> be brief&#44; at each recurrence of the present&#44; I have been<lb/> wont to expatiate in pointing out the remarkable issues<lb/> of the event which rendered Israel physically and morally<lb/> free.  But the day&#44; I desire that you will allow<lb/> me to deviate from a constant rule&#44; so that I may redeem<lb/> a promise left by circumstances too long unfulfilled.<lb/></p>
            <p>Permit me to solve the last of the three queries&#44; submitted<lb/> to my judgment&#44; by a respect coreligionist.<lb/></p>
            <p>Beloved hearers&#33;  In the course of my exegetical lectures&#44; you<lb/> may have often heard me state that the Hebrew&#44; like its<lb/> kindred languages&#44; abounds in expressions which can bear<lb/> only an allegorical sense.  But as I am aware<lb/> that unless the faculty of discernment by which we may<lb/> distinguish between a simple narrative and a metaphor is<lb/> fully exercised&#44; much confusion will arise even as to determein even<lb/> what belongs to history and what to law.  I would advise extreme<lb/> caution in defining the import of a scriptural text.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>In this respect&#44; I conceive that we may suffer ourselves to<lb/> be guided by the light&#44; which&#44; men possessed of vast erudition and<lb/> sincere piety&#44; have in olden times shed upon the Bible.  At all<lb/> events&#44; by so doing&#44; our religious habits would accord with those<lb/> followed by the community of our brethren&#44; and we would<lb/> not presume to set up our individual opinion against that<lb/> entertained by the house of Israel at large.  However&#44;<lb/> the volumes of inspiration contain certain passages&#44; where no<lb/> ordinance is prescribed&#44; and which form no link in the chain<lb/> of our national history.  On those I think we may freely speculate&#44;<lb/> for&#44; at whatever conclusion we arrive&#44; our religious demeanour<lb/> would not be affected thereby.  Now&#44; my friends&#33; in that<lb/> category may be placed the passage&#44; which I was requested<lb/> to expound&#44; for it will be readily conceded that whether the<lb/> serpent which lured our mother Eve to sin&#44; is regarded<lb/> as the animal bearing that name&#44; or&#44; whether it is considered<lb/> the embodiment of another object&#44; the principles which govern<lb/> us&#44; O children of my people&#33; do not suffer in nay wise.<lb/></p>
            <p>It is not a dogma of Judaism to believe that the effect of the entice&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment has been the entailing of irrevocable misery on the<lb/> whole human race and their spiritual perdition&#44; for&#44; according to<lb/> it the faith we profess&#44; each individual is amenable to the Lord for his own actions&#59;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>nor does the occurrence on which our religious opponents lay so much stress appear to have influenced in aught the<lb/> noble line of our ancestry.  Nay even more&#58; not once throughout Holy Writ&#44;<lb/> except where it properly belongs&#44; is the incident in which the<lb/> serpent played so prominent a part&#44; reverted to.  Hence I conceive<lb/> that the mind of a well&#45;thinking Israelite ought unhesitatingly<lb/> to discard the theory by which the guilt of our first parents is fa&#45;<lb/>&#45;stened on their posterity&#44; and man is condemned to suffer per&#45;<lb/>&#45;petual torments&#44; unless he believes in the efficacy of a vi&#45;<lb/>&#45;carious sacrifice&#44; of which the scriptures speak not.<lb/></p>
            <p>But although the reasons just alleged are sufficiently cogent<lb/> to make us repell any contrary such ideas as untenable and<lb/> false&#44; nevertheless&#44; I feel bound to enlarge on the topic.<lb/>  My querist seems desirous to learn&#44; in what light our own<lb/> authorities regarded the passage under discussion&#44; and there&#45;<lb/>&#45;fore I must unfold to your views&#44; what the volumes of<lb/> antiquity contain.  Among the numberless opinions ad&#45;<lb/>&#45;vanced touching the point at issue&#44; three have found staunch<lb/> advocates.  According to the first&#44; the serpent originally<lb/> stood in the scale of creation between man and inferior beings&#59;<lb/> he was endowed with limited reason and speech&#44; and held an<lb/> erect posture.  Those natural endowments&#44; however&#44; were<lb/> withheld from him&#44; when he maliciously schemed to destroy the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>happiness of those whom God had raised exceedingly above him.<lb/>  They who uphold the second&#44; deny the existence of those powers in the serpent&#44;<lb/> but pretends that he was temporarily invested therewith in<lb/> a supernatural manner&#44; so that the faith of the two denizens<lb/> of Eden might by that means be essayed.  But they who<lb/> hold adhere to the third&#44; see in the whole narrative a myth&#44;<lb/> representing a conflict between reflection and imagination&#44; the<lb/> victory of the latter over the former&#44; and the suffering accruing<lb/> therefrom.  Each of these opinions has engaged the<lb/> serious attention of celebrated commentators&#44; who respectively brought<lb/> to bear on it the weight of strong arguments.  But with<lb/> due deference to the learned&#44; we prefer the first&#44; as that which<lb/> is the least open to objections.  For&#44; if the serpent was really the<lb/> passive agent of a superior power&#44; why was a punishment<lb/> inflicted on him&#44; which has endured from the primordial<lb/> days of the world to the present time&#63;  &#34;Shall not the Judge<lb/> of all the earth do right&#34;&#63;  And if the serpent never<lb/> presented a different form from that which he now possesses&#44;<lb/> and consequently did not suffer by his constra compulsory<lb/> action&#44; how could the Deity address to him words&#44; whose<lb/> import was incomprehensible to an irrational creature&#63;<lb/>  It has been said&#44; and it is believed by a large portion<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>of our fellow&#45;beings&#44; that in the serpent of the book of Genesis&#44;<lb/> Satan is typified&#44; that he assumed that garb&#44; incited by human<lb/> hatred&#44; and that him did God curse and threaten with utter<lb/> destruction through the seed of woman.  I have&#44; my<lb/> friends&#33; in a former lecture&#44; dwelt with all the powers of<lb/> ratiocination at my command&#44; on the popular belief in malign<lb/> spirits&#44; and endeavoured to disprove their existence.  It<lb/> would therefore be supererogatory to say that the above<lb/> interpretation clashes with our mature conclusions&#44; and is<lb/> not admissible.  But waving the subject altogether&#44;<lb/> can we not perceive at a glance&#44; how groundless is the<lb/> theory of our Nazarene&#39;s neighbours&#63;  We could not surely<lb/> attach an allegorical sense to the condemnation against the<lb/> serpent&#44; without conceding it also to those pronounced by God<lb/> against Eve and her life&#39;s copartner&#59; for&#44; all the three&#44; occupy<lb/> an identical position in the sacred pages&#44; and cannot logically<lb/> be disconnected from each other.  Hence&#44; if to bruise the head<lb/> of the serpent &#34;means to annihilate sin&#59; &#34;to bring forth<lb/> children in sorrow&#44;&#34; and &#34;to eat bread in the sweat of the face&#34;<lb/> might be capable of any other signification differing from than that which<lb/> time and experience have proved true.  Again&#44; if the<lb/> first member of the sentence is figurative&#44; the second must<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>need be equally so.  What can then possibly metaphorically be the<lb/> rendering of the phrase&#44; &#34;and thou shalt bruise his heel&#34;&#63;  Or&#44; is the<lb/> action agreeable to the letters applicable at all to an ethereal essence&#63;..Moreover&#44; if<lb/> the divine Messiah&#44; who was to redeem the world from spiritual<lb/> death&#44; succeeded in destroying Satan&#39;s power&#44; how could<lb/> he summon strength again to injure mankind&#63;  Would<lb/> not his downfall have purged the earth of all her inequities&#63;<lb/>  Verily my friends&#33;  The idea is too abhorrent to reason and<lb/> our Bible&#44; ever to be harbored by an Israelite&#63;<lb/>  Nor can we concur in the opinion that the cause of our<lb/> first parent&#39;s disobedience&#44; their fall&#44; and the punishment of<lb/> those involved in it&#44; are intended by the inspired writer&#44; as a lesson<lb/> of a metaphysical nature character&#44; for&#44; such is not the character province of<lb/> the Mosaic legislation revelation.  In no instance does it deal in abstract<lb/> notions.  Facts and positive rules are its tuition.  The law which<lb/> we have inherited O Congregation of Jacob&#33; is not a <sic>phylosophical</sic><lb/> treatise which few only could comprehend&#44; but a legislation<lb/> directed to soften the heart&#44; and guide the mind into the path<lb/> of equity and righteousness.  But irrespectively of this truth&#44;<lb/> we deem it dangerous to religion to change the unsophisticated<lb/> teaching of Holy Writ into abstruse speculations.  It is by fol&#45;<lb/>&#45;lowing such a course&#44; that the Hellenists in olden times&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>and our modern reformers have estranged alienated Israel from their obedience to ancestral<lb/> observances.  It may be totally immaterial in the present case<lb/> how the subject is treated&#44; but what is unimportant in the theme<lb/> under discussion&#44; may greatly affect other passages of the<lb/> heavenly volumes.  We therefore&#44; as already stated&#44; fully<lb/> assent to the opinion&#44; advocated by the renowned Aben Ezra&#44;<lb/> that the serpent originally participated&#44; to a limited extent&#44;<lb/> in the mental faculties of man&#44; and that he likewise walked uprightly&#44;<lb/> for&#44; when we survey the numerous gradations in the scale of<lb/> beings&#44; we cannot style that idea an absurdity&#44; which<lb/> discovers an intermediate rank between a highly intellectual<lb/> creature and the brute.  Thus&#44; And it was the will of<lb/> Him who gave life to every thing which exists&#44; to assign<lb/> that rank unto the serpent.  But envy that rankled<lb/> in his breast&#44; conspired against his own happiness&#44; as it<lb/> marred that of God&#39;s most favored children.  he was hurled down from his high station.  Destitute of<lb/> reason&#44; and crawling upon the earth&#44; as the most vile reptile&#44;<lb/> he would be was to become an object of terror to man.  And while the<lb/> seed of the woman would seek in self&#45;defence to crush<lb/> his head underfoot&#44; he would in turn attack his adversary<lb/> and poison his blood by a bite at his heel.  Such we con&#45;<lb/>&#45;ceive to be the only correct interpretation which the context<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>allows&#44; and which human understanding can admit&#44; consistently<lb/> with the idea of divine justice.<lb/></p>
            <p>It may be2 possibly1 argued&#44; that the qualities we have<lb/> attributed to the serpent are not enumerated in Holy<lb/> Writ&#44; and that consequently our premises and deductions<lb/> are defective&#44; but to that we reply&#44; that the term &#40;&#91;Hebrew&#93;&#41;<lb/> &#34;Ngarum&#34; comprises them all&#44; for&#44; it is not barely signi&#45;<lb/>&#45;ficative of a subtle disposition&#44; but it implies as well<lb/> the possession of intellectual acumen&#44; whether employed<lb/> for a good or an evil purpose.  Thus&#44; Solomon wrote<lb/> &#34;Every one who is Ngarum acts with knowledge&#34;.  And on<lb/> this score&#44; the tempter seemingly exceeded the tempted.<lb/>  It had pleased the Most High to bestow a vast portion<lb/> of his wisdom on the two beings He had formed after his own<lb/> likeness.  By that was Adam enabled&#45;&#45;when all species<lb/> of animals were made to pass in array&#44; as it were&#44; before<lb/> his mind&#44;&#45;&#45;to assign to each an appellation suitable to<lb/> its natural properties.  But their Celestial Ma&#45;<lb/>&#45;ker had mercifully withheld from the fairest couple<lb/> a feeling which only2 could1 be engendered by the abandon&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment of pristine innocence.  To preserve them<lb/> in unspotted parity&#44; He had forbidden their partaking<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>of a fruit&#44; which&#44; through some mysterious power&#44; awake&#45;<lb/>&#45;ned that sentiment.  But a state so felicitous in its<lb/> simplicity&#44; stirred up envy in the breast of the serpent.<lb/>  He would disturb it&#44; were he even to hazard his own hap&#45;<lb/>&#45;piness.  And in order to compass his end&#44; with<lb/> more likelihood of success&#44; he chose the feebler sex as his the<lb/> victim of his craftiness.  He pictured to her in glowing charac&#45;<lb/>&#45;ters the result of following&#44; without restraint&#44; her own in&#45;<lb/>&#45;clination&#44; and by wickedly misrepresenting the design of<lb/> the beneficent Creator&#44; he excited a craving for something<lb/> unknown&#44; which could no longer be suppressed.  The<lb/> veil was flung aside&#59; the eyes of the unwary were<lb/> opened.  They discovered......not the promised<lb/> knowledge&#59; not the hidden paths of sapience&#44; but shame&#44;<lb/> in for that which was not a shame.  The good and evil<lb/> they longed to discern&#44; was not the understanding of that<lb/> which is morally true or morally false&#44; but a distinction<lb/> among things which solely belong to the domains of human<lb/> conventionalities&#44; arising from human defection.<lb/></p>
            <p>I am perfectly aware&#44; dear friends&#33; of my inability to<lb/> elucidate this theme in a manner obvious to every mind&#44;<lb/> but let the little I have said be deeply reflected on by the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>thoughtful&#44; and a new light will break upon them.<lb/>  &#34;Let the wise man hear&#44; and his learning will increase&#34;<lb/> The capacity he will acquire by meditating on our humble<lb/> words&#44; will qualify him to defend the sacred pages from<lb/> the assault of infidels&#44; and likewise to disprove the assertions<lb/> of gentilism.  It will inspire him with additional<lb/> love for the ancestral religion&#44; for&#44; in contrasting the<lb/> unsophisticated imparting of Moses with the mystical dogmas<lb/> of the new dispensation&#44; he will perceive that Israel alone<lb/> is the repository of truth.  Yes&#44; &#34;Israel was saved by the<lb/> Eternal to enjoy an everlasting salvation&#44; they shall never<lb/> be put to shame&#44; nor shall they be confounded while the world exists&#34;<lb/>  And now&#44; beloved hearers&#33; my task is completed.  It has entailed on<lb/> me considerable labor&#44; but if it has <sic>benefitted</sic> others as it improved<lb/> my mind&#44; I shall thank the occasion that called for it.<lb/>  Indeed it would greatly assist the preacher&#44; if questions of moment<lb/> were propounded to him&#44; for&#44; not infrequently is he perplexed<lb/> when in quest of a new topic on which to descant.  Let us then<lb/> work in concert&#44; my dear friends&#33;  Seek ye for knowledge&#44; and I&#44;<lb/> supported by the Lord of wisdom&#44; will enlighten your understanding&#44;<lb/> for&#44; such I deem my stringent duty&#44; and to that goal tend all our my<lb/> efforts.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
