<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF6_11</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_11_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_11_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_11_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_11_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_11_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_11_3v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>5 pages on 2 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For a funeral<lb/></p>
            <p>Fellow Israelites.  May active presence in this fune&#45;<lb/>real hall&#44; is simply the interpreter of<lb/> two sentiments which the All Creating God has<lb/> implanted in the human breast&#45;&#45;sympathy with<lb/> sorrow&#44; admiration for virtue.  Because those inborn<lb/> sentiments stir within my heart&#44; therefore I stand<lb/> here now&#44; not officially&#44; lest I trespass upon<lb/> others&#39; rights&#44; but in obedience to my own emo&#45;<lb/>&#45;tions and in response to the request of appreciative friends.<lb/>  My sympathies urges me to lament that an ir&#45;<lb/>&#45;reparable loss has been sustained.  Those who are within<lb/> reach of my voice may perhaps wonder and ask<lb/> themselves&#58; &#34;Was our deceased brother S. M. pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;eminent in the world of letters&#59; conspicuous in the<lb/> world of science&#44; so socially distinguished to a degree that his<lb/> demise has will have created a void difficult to be filled&#63;&#34;<lb/>  Not so.  My venerable coreligionist was an unosten&#45;<lb/>&#45;tatiously quiet son of our people&#44; one satisfied whose only ambition it was to<lb/> <sic>fulfil</sic> modestly&#44; unpretentiously the duties devolving<lb/> upon him as a man and a Hebrew.  He never<lb/> laid claim to a lofty position in the world of<lb/> learning.  But there is a world&#44; nearer and dearer<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>to than all of us than that in which we seek<lb/> fame honors and celebrity.  There where the affections<lb/> rule&#44; there where <sic>tranquillity</sic> is enthroned&#44; a most<lb/> precious world exists.  The English language<lb/> has a sweet monosyllable expressive of that joyous<lb/> world&#45;home.  Within its walls S. M. met infi&#45;<lb/>&#45;nitely more than he missed by being unable to min&#45;<lb/>&#45;gle widely in social high circles.  For years my friend<lb/> had become incapacitated from following his or&#45;<lb/>&#45;dinary pursuits&#44; but where his children dwelt&#44; he<lb/> enjoyed companionship&#44; comforts&#44; diversions&#59; a mi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tigation to physical and moral ills.  Just because<lb/> he valued those God&#45;given blessings&#59; because he was<lb/> the daily recipient thereof&#44; therefore his absence<lb/> from that home will create a great void and oc&#45;<lb/>&#45;casion deep sorrow.  I sympathise with all<lb/> the children of S. M&#44; but principally&#44; not invi&#45;<lb/>&#45;diously&#44; with his unmarried daughters.  To them<lb/> the constant presence of that father&#44; though feeble weak and in&#45;<lb/>&#45;firm&#44; needing extraordinary care and solicitude was brought<lb/> joy delight&#44; for they realized that&#44; under Providence&#44; their<lb/> filial ministration lengthened his days&#44; and that<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>he returned the filial offices tenfold by a pa&#45;<lb/>ternal recognition&#59; that is by unbounded love.  Nothing<lb/> emanating from a mortal being will allay thate grief experienced&#59; words&#44; however sincere&#44; issued<lb/> from mortal human lips cannot assuage it.  Only the assurances of<lb/> the inspired Psalmist will soften it the pangs of the separation.  When our flesh<lb/> and our hearts are mouldering in the grave&#44; our spirit<lb/> is uplifted to the Rock of all ages.  God will lead us<lb/> on by His counsel&#44; and afterward take us up to glory.<lb/></p>
            <p>But I have said it.  My sympathy is blended<lb/> with admiration.  The occasional visits which I paid<lb/> to the home of my venerable coreligionist&#44; convinced<lb/> me that virtue is a plant still flourishing in<lb/> the soil of Judaism.  It is not withering away&#44;<lb/> as some pessimists would contend.  There is indeed much<lb/> that cannot be commended in the conduct of my<lb/> people&#59; a vast deal that indicates a retrogression&#44;<lb/> not a progress.  We have lost that child&#45;like faith&#44;<lb/> that abiding trust in Providence&#44; that simplicity of man&#45;<lb/>&#45;ners that which distinguished our ancestors&#44; but so long as<lb/> filial dutifulness to parents is exercised&#44; I do not fear a racial<lb/> decay&#59; for home is the world in miniature&#44; and when<lb/> that is pure&#44; our communities cannot never become thoroughly corrupt.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>In my official capacity&#44; I have witnessed<lb/> devotion2 to ones parents aged father with pleasurable frequency&#44;<lb/> but never indeed more touchingly&#44; never more admirably<lb/> than in this home.  The sight made so profound an<lb/> impression upon me&#44; that had I not been asked<lb/> to evince friendship by some utterances on this melan&#45;<lb/>&#45;choly occasion&#44; I would have been impelled spontaneously<lb/> to give expression to my feelings&#45;&#45;so unwearied&#44; so tender&#44;<lb/> so holy was the attention bestowed by those daughters on<lb/> their aged&#59; feeble bodily enfeebled father.  To allay his pains&#44; to<lb/> watch his movements&#44; to anticipate his wishes&#44; to<lb/> suppress heart burnings&#44; that he might not grieve&#44; to<lb/> smile upon him that the sun&#45;shine of their coun&#45;<lb/>&#45;tenances might dispel gloom was the effort of<lb/> each of those children&#44; and when the hour struck and<lb/> death took what belongs thereto&#44; the intensity of<lb/> the distress evinced by the offspring of S. M&#44; was<lb/> a tribute of filial homage which I call godly.<lb/>  Aye&#58; I beheld an altar on which a savory offering<lb/> was laid in honor of the God of Sinai For He who proclaimed<lb/> proclaimed &#34;Honor thy father and thy mother&#34;.<lb/>  Fear not my young kind friends.  Your reward is certain.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>For Moses has declared that the performance<lb/> of the fifth commandment of the Decalogue<lb/> will give happiness here&#44; and happiness felicity here&#45;<lb/>after &#34;Thy days will be long and it will be well with thee&#34;  Weep for the loss that you have sustain&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed&#44; but rejoice that your tears do not flow from<lb/> a source of repentance&#59; from a spring of remorse&#44;<lb/> for at having offended your Creator&#44; by running<lb/> counter to His behest&#44; to rush headlong after<lb/> worldly cravings&#44; and the gratification of egotism.<lb/>  My sympathies are with you&#44; but my admiration<lb/> for virtue&#44; incites me to set you up as an<lb/> ensign to all who have aged old fathers and mothers<lb/> to reverence.  Let the consciousness of having<lb/> done your full duty bring to you contentment.  Look<lb/> back upon this day&#44; not with increasing distress&#44;<lb/> but with the belief that because you <sic>prolongued</sic><lb/> your father parent&#39;s life&#44; the Lord will lengthen yours to<lb/> a sacred purpose&#44; and with the assurance that<lb/> the entrance of your father the dear departed into heaven Paradise&#44; will be greeted<lb/> by a chorus of angels and archangels who sing<lb/> hymns to the Universal Father Parent&#44; our God and Saviour.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
