<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF3_9</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_9_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_9_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_9_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_9_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_9_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_9_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_9_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_9_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_9_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_9_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_9_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_9_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 3 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Sabbath before Purim<lb/>
                on behalf of the Alliance &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  Since my mind arrived at the conviction became convinced&#44;<lb/> that the organization&#44; started in France twenty eight<lb/> years ago&#44; is preeminently educational in its tendency&#44; I<lb/> bestowed upon it some of the most fervent thoughts&#44;<lb/> which I am able to conceive.  Here To them I gave expression at ministerial con&#45;<lb/>&#45;ferences and in synagogues&#44; at children schools and<lb/> in friends&#39; parlors.  I have earnestly presented the<lb/> claims of the Universal Israelitish Alliance&#44; to the<lb/> cooperation of all who wish to see brethren freed from<lb/> the fetters of ignorance which oppression has <sic>rivetted</sic>.  I must<lb/> therefore unavoidably&#45;&#45;though unwittingly&#45;&#45;commit self&#45;plagarism&#44; when refer&#45;<lb/>&#45;ring to the same subject with great frequency.  But<lb/> just because I have repeatedly made it a study&#44; to<lb/> gain familiarity with the its working&#44; of the institution for<lb/> which I plead&#44; I may more readily perhaps secure attention hearing and win for it<lb/> public sympathy.<lb/>
                I cannot exactly quote authority&#44; but I hold as a<lb/> tradition that the non possums &#40;we cannot&#41; of Pius<lb/> IX&#44; which insulted offended nature&#44; was the tocsin which sound&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed the alarm in the camp of Israel&#44; and &#34;we can&#45;so help<lb/> us God&#34; thrillingly echoed forth from our own midst.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>The Alliance was not brought into existence<lb/> till February of 1860&#44; but immediately after the<lb/> atrocious deed at Bologna&#44; in the month of June 1858&#44; at<lb/> Bologna Isidore Cohen&#44; editor of the Archives Israelite<lb/> at Paris&#44; issued a call.  He asked for union&#44; to<lb/> insure the ends which isolated remonstrances could<lb/> not reasonably accomplish.  Our children should not be torn<lb/> from their mothers&#39; arms&#44; without eliciting a jointly dignified<lb/> protest&#44; influencing civilized nations.  Another Mortara&#39;s<lb/> abduction must be rendered an impossibility.  But<lb/> with the shield cast round the lives of individual<lb/> Jews&#44; must be thrown the mighty buckler<lb/> of self&#45;defenseprotection&#44; wrought by a knowledge of inherent<lb/> human rights.  The appeal signed by its<lb/> author&#44; circulated fast through France and Italy with five additional names.<lb/>  through France and Italy You have read them<lb/> in one of the many articles with which the Jewish<lb/> organ of our city teems in this week&#39;s issue.<lb/>  The Purim number edition of the Exponent has given you must have afforded<lb/> also abundant information respecting the creation and<lb/> aims of the Alliance.  We learnt that under the temporary presidency at the outset provisional government of a<lb/> L. J. Koenigswarter&#44; at the outset&#44; central committee&#44; presided over by L. J. Koenigswarter&#44; the association extended.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>It gained in popularity&#44; when in 1863 Adolph Cr&#233;&#45;<lb/>&#45;mieux&#44; the renowned forum and orator and statesman&#44;<lb/> first sat in the presidential chair in 1863 Salomon Munk&#44;<lb/> the prolific invaluable author and erudite Orientalist who succeeded him&#44; added<lb/> lustre to it&#44; and when literature had to deplore<lb/> his death in February 1867 and Cr&#233;mieux resumed<lb/> what he had voluntarily relinquished before&#44; twelve<lb/> consecutive years of usefulness were recorded to the<lb/> honor of the Alliance.  S. H. Goldschmidt<lb/> who had proved its staunch friend always&#44; was by common consent deemed best<lb/> fitted to direct it&#44; after his celebrated coreligionist<lb/> and colleague had passed away from earth.  He<lb/> has presided over the association during the last<lb/> five years with singleness of purpose to enhance<lb/> its interests&#44; and with personal unquestionable evidences of an un&#45;<lb/>&#45;stinted generosity to further benefit it still further.  Just 28 years have gone from the birth&#45;<lb/>day of our Alliance.  But Has that lapse of time lessened the necessity of<lb/> an organization raised to fight with moral arms the<lb/> inveterate foes of our people&#63;  Must it now disband&#44;<lb/> together with its potent auxiliaries&#44; the &#34;Anglo&#45;Jewish<lb/> association&#34;&#44; and the &#34;Allianz zu Wien&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Is the large&#45;hearted munificence of the<lb/> Bischoffsheins&#44; or the Cohns&#44; and or that&#44; surpassing<lb/> all praise&#44; of Baron De Hirsch&#44; who lavishes millions<lb/> as if they were thus&#44; no longer wanted&#63;  I truly really<lb/> feel indignant when I hear would&#45;be liberal boast of<lb/> the rapid progress of the age in which we live and as this calling<lb/> upon us to see look how the murky clouds of prejudice are<lb/> fleeing apace&#44; leaving for our contemplation only the<lb/> brightness of universal toleration.  Why brethren had we no other<lb/> knowledge of the ill&#45;will still nurtured against our race&#44;<lb/> than what we can gather from the monthly and<lb/> semi&#45;annual Bulletins of the Alliance&#44; we would<lb/> possess sufficient data proving that the Messianic<lb/> era&#44; whose advent some fancy to be looming high&#44;<lb/> is far&#44; aye&#58; very far off.  Politically and socially<lb/> the largest majority of our fellow&#45;believers scattered abroad&#44;<lb/> bear the effects of deep&#45;rooted prejudice&#59; therefore Jews<lb/> do stand in need of protectors and guides&#59; of protectors&#44;<lb/> to watch every opportunity&#44; when either directly through<lb/> enlightened governments&#44; or indirectly through personal<lb/> influences&#44; the victims of oppression may suffer less violence<lb/> of guides&#44; to search out for the persecuted a way to self&#45;redemption.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>The Alliance is liberal.  Who dares charge it with narrow&#45;spiritedness&#63;  More than once it<lb/> has contributed to the relief of non&#45;Israelites&#44; when<lb/> humanity appealed pleaded.  In 1860&#44; when in its very incipience&#44; it opened a sub&#45;<lb/>&#45;scription list in aid of the Christians at Lebanon&#44;<lb/> whom Mohammedan fanaticism had delivered to sword<lb/> and famine.  In 1877&#44; during the Russo&#45;Turkish war&#44;<lb/> when Christian fanaticism slaughtered Mohamedans<lb/> with Jews&#44; the Alliance commissioned Chevalier Vene&#45;<lb/>&#45;ziani indistinctly to lend assistance to all the refugees.  But<lb/> the Alliance is not utopian in its tendencies.  It<lb/> does not entertain notions of a false liberalism.  It realizes<lb/> where its working is imperatively&#44; constantly&#44; and<lb/> vigilantly wanted.  The Alliance is Jewish in its<lb/> essential features&#44; because Jews are few and powerless<lb/> in the presence face of multitudes of mighty adversaries.<lb/>  It cannot say to our brethren in Morocco or in South<lb/> Arabia &#34;rise and strike&#34;&#44; for it were like asking one<lb/> whose hands are manacled&#44; to break the iron<lb/> bars of his prison&#59; but it remonstrates against brutality barbarity&#44;<lb/> and educates the unfortunates into a perception of their<lb/> lowliness&#44; that learning self&#45;respect by education&#44; they may even&#45;<lb/>&#45;tually plead for demand challenge the recognition of their manhood&#44; and given eman&#45;<lb/>&#45;cipation.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>I shall not offer a detailed account of its appliances&#44;<lb/> in pursuit of that noble object.  I shall not tell<lb/> of its watchfulness over the interests of European<lb/> Jews and explain that&#44; while battling against the treachery<lb/> of Roumania&#44; and thwarting the Antisemitism of<lb/> Hungary&#44; it plants schools which teach then thou&#45;<lb/>&#45;sand pupils&#44; whose number might easily increase<lb/> to fifty thousand&#44; if adequate means were at<lb/> hand.  I have had occasion often to describe<lb/> the religious and secular instruction imparted under<lb/> the auspices of our comprehensive organization&#59; the<lb/> trades and professions fostered&#44; the needle and house&#45;<lb/>&#45;hold work and habits of industry encouraged among<lb/> girls of our faith&#44; in countries where they females are held<lb/> as beings vulgarly inferior beings&#44; depending in capriceously and vulgarly dependent beings.  Those<lb/> whom I weekly address may perhaps have heard<lb/> me say at this season&#44; how the Alliance in its far&#45;reaching<lb/> aim sought also to rescue our fellow&#45;religionists in Abyssinia&#44;<lb/> to which benighted land it sent Joseph Halevy&#44; and<lb/> from which it brought to Paris a Falasha youth to<lb/> be trained there as a future missionary among his brethren&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>and how disappointed was the Alliance was&#44; when<lb/> the lad irresistibly seized with home sickness returned<lb/> and died on his way back&#59; how a youth from Persia is<lb/> now in the Metropolis of France under instruction&#44;<lb/> and others from distant cities in the distant Orient are bred up<lb/> in a French seminary to assume in turn the task of preceptors to their fellow&#45;believers<lb/> in abjection.  I may also have related how literature<lb/> and science cultivated by our people&#44; receive aid and<lb/> coutnenance from our all embracing association&#45;&#45;ever<lb/> ready to subsidize authors in the publication of their<lb/> labors.  But a subject of very recent date&#44; pe&#45;<lb/>&#45;culiarly American&#44; deserves special reference.  Pseudo&#45;re&#45;<lb/>&#45;form may laugh to scorn the idea of doing Palestine<lb/> reverence&#44; as the centre whence Hebrew doctrines and tra&#45;<lb/>&#45;ditions flowed down to successive ages posterity&#44; but so long as the<lb/> heart is capable of pulsating for what is holy and<lb/> true&#44; Zion will remain an object of veneration.  To elevate<lb/> the condition of its present inhabitants has been the<lb/> study of the right thinking.  For ages the cities in<lb/> which priests and prophets preached the word of God&#44; were<lb/> sought after only as sepulchres for pilgrims.<lb/>  Fruitless meditations absorbed the minds of the latter&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>and their poverty was relieved by the mistaken<lb/> zeal of pious Israelites abroad.  But a new spirit<lb/> awoke&#44; and a wish determination to rejuvenate the land of the patriarchs<lb/> by the activity of their descendants&#44; powerfully seized<lb/> the minds of the reflecting minds.  To that we owe the Jaffa<lb/> agricultural school&#44; founded by Charles Nitter&#59; to<lb/> that we owe three more agricultural colonies&#44; severally<lb/> called Bishon Le&#45;Zijon&#44; Rosh Pinnah and Sumarin&#44;<lb/> struggling hard to win success.  But Palestine of the Sultan&#44; is<lb/> poor and ill&#45;governed.  Jewish immigrants have&#44; more<lb/>&#45;over&#44; another evil against which to contend&#45;&#45;the wiles<lb/> of propagandists who lay the bait to catch the un&#45;<lb/>&#45;wary and tie them to the Juggernaut car of apos&#45;<lb/>&#45;tasy.  Free eating houses and lodging houses and night houses shelters&#44; asylums and<lb/> hospitals are so many nets spread to the feet of<lb/> Jews open to allurements.  We too have in&#45; orga<lb/> stitutions &#45;nizations of the same character&#44; but unequal to the want.<lb/>  The order of Bene&#39; Berith &#40;Children of the Covenant&#41; proposes now to redeem<lb/> the appellation it bears&#44; by helping to retain our<lb/> children in the covenant&#44; where a fear of their eventual<lb/> desertion exists.  An appeal has emanated<lb/> from the District Grand Lodge&#44; urging the <sic>rasing</sic> 5000<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>dollars annually&#44; by a yearly assessment<lb/> of 20 cents per capita&#44; to assist an asylum for Jewish<lb/> orphans at Jerusalem already in operation&#44; and<lb/> a school where our boys learn a trade&#44; founded established<lb/> by the Universal Israelitish Alliance.  The<lb/> proposition met with a violent opposition on at the<lb/> part hands of the Rabbi&#45;Editor and College&#45;President at<lb/> Cincinnati&#44; the &#91;&#63;&#93; noted &#34;Reformer&#34; who believes that his institution must<lb/> have precedence to all else in Judaism&#59; but the<lb/> Bene Berith officials thought otherwise.  They<lb/> have our commendation.  And now&#44; what<lb/> Purim greetings should will you send to the Central<lb/> Committee of our far reaching association&#44; at Paris&#63;<lb/>  Brothers and sisters.  The command of Mordecai<lb/> and Esther points it out &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;Give Lend presents to one another&#44; and donations gifts<lb/> to the needy&#34; points Let the tokens of your sympathy<lb/> for with the unflagging efforts of the Alliance&#44; and your<lb/> compassion for those of your race in oppression and<lb/> ignorance be evinced&#44; by forwarding in their behalf gifts donations to the<lb/> treasurer of our Philadelphia branch&#44; or to him<lb/> who now addresses you from this pulpit.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
