<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF3_14</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_14_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_14_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_14_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_14_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_14_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_14_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_14_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_14_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_14_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_14_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_14_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_14_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>On Sabbath Parah<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;I had pity on my holy name&#44; which<lb/> the house of Israel profaned among the nations&#44;<lb/> whither they have gone&#34;.  Who are they of the house<lb/> of Israel that Ezekiel condemns in his ardent zeal<lb/> for his Master&#63;  Who are they that bring scandal upon<lb/> the Author of our faith&#63;  Jews who misuse a supreme<lb/> trust.  Jews who study the whims and notions of the<lb/> age in which they live&#44; and not sacred duty.  They<lb/> make gentiles cry with a smile of irony and a<lb/> scornful shake of the head &#34;Forsooth such are the<lb/> people of the Lord&#34;.<lb/></p>
            <p>Listen my Brethren.  Brazen gates and wide rivers<lb/> are not impediments to the mind in which God dwells&#44;<lb/> to a mind stirred up by the spirit of prophecy.  Jour&#45;<lb/>&#45;neying on its wings&#44; the man of Chebar&#44; rested his<lb/> far&#45;seeing eye on the time serving and faithless.<lb/>  He beheld them in Judea before the total dispersion.<lb/>  He beheld them again when exiled to the land of the<lb/> Chaldeans.  The false notably occupied responsible<lb/> places&#44; enjoyed high offices.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Ezekiel stood within the courts of the Jerusalem<lb/> Temple.  He looked.  A partition had been cautiously<lb/> raised&#44; as a hindrance to the unintended.  But a voice<lb/> said &#34;Son of man break through and mark the<lb/> seam.&#34;  Lo&#33; the &#91;&#63;&#93; of the nation are engaged<lb/> in an abominable service.  They burn incense not in<lb/> honor to the living God&#44; but to vulgar figures painted<lb/> by a heated imagination.  The Seer averts his eyes<lb/> in dismay from a spectacle so degrading.<lb/>  He goes in search of the lowly among his coreligionists.<lb/>  Surely&#44; they cannot be infected with the sins ram&#45;<lb/>&#45;pant among the socially elevated.  But on his<lb/> way he meets the pastors of an easily led flock.<lb/>  They are fat&#44; and sleek and well covered with the<lb/> wool shorn from off their charges.  Those pampered<lb/> keepers care not if the flock denied wholesome<lb/> food&#44; run over strange fields&#44; and become poisoned<lb/> with noxious weeds.  They can find others more<lb/> ready to fleece.  Ezekiel contemplating that<lb/> scene&#44; pours out a vial of righteous indignation<lb/> &#34;Woe be to the shepherds of Israel....The weak<lb/> you have not strengthened&#44; the diseased you have<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>healed&#44; the broken you have not bound up&#44; the<lb/> strayed ones you have not brought back&#44; the lost<lb/> you have not sought after.  Thus says the Lord&#44;<lb/> I am against the shepherd.  I will require my<lb/> flock form the hand&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  Our Haftorah is a sequel to a series<lb/> of denunciations against men into whose guardianship<lb/> the interest of the Jewish religion was committed&#44; but<lb/> who promoted only their own advantage&#44; men who<lb/> ought to have glorified the olden faith&#44; but let indif&#45;<lb/>&#45;ference drag it into a pit of disgrace.  Has the house<lb/> of Israel&#44; after so many trials and vicissitudes&#44; been rid<lb/> of such individuals&#63;  Are our chiefs&#45;&#45;mainly our so&#45;called<lb/> spiritual leaders&#45;&#45;very chary not to bring scandal upon<lb/> the name we hear&#63;  The question is pertinent on a<lb/> Sabbath like the present.  It speaks of the need of<lb/> purification.  In ancient times the sprinkling of<lb/> water&#44; into which had been cast a handful of the burnt<lb/> ashes of a red heifer&#44; of a piece of cedar wood&#44; a chip<lb/> of hyssop&#44; and a thread of scarlet yarn&#45;&#45;whose colours ty&#45;<lb/>pified sin&#45;&#45;cleansed the Hebrews defiled by contract with polluting objects.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>So purified&#44; they could join the Congregation in the na&#45;<lb/>&#45;tional feast of the redemption from slavery&#45;&#45;the ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;proaching Passover.  We ourselves are nearing<lb/> the important period of our year&#44; and the additional<lb/> portion of the Pentateuch announces it.  But many<lb/> of those who should instruct us to fittingly hold<lb/> the celebration&#44; are sullied and tainted.  They still<lb/> make gentiles derisively exclaim&#44; &#34;Forsooth&#44; such<lb/> are the people of the Lord.&#34;  I remember how just<lb/> twenty five years ago about the season&#44; when an<lb/> Israelitish history&#44; which would tear into shreds&#44; as<lb/> worthless rags the Israelitish history written by Moses<lb/> and the prophets issued from the press&#44; I was accosted<lb/> by a Christian acquaintance.  He remarked&#58; if the<lb/> statements of the author I have now read are correct&#44;<lb/> the Hebrew Scriptures must be a tissue of deceptions&#44;<lb/> but I must believe that your Bible is inspired&#44; I<lb/> must also consider it unwarrantable in your Rabbi<lb/> to represent on a false light what the civilized world<lb/> has accepted as truths at the hands of the Jews.<lb/>  So spoke one not born in the law&#44; to shame those who<lb/> are its sworn keepers&#44; but whom the heresies of untrusty guides<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>led astray.  For&#44; if the military skill&#44; and schemes<lb/> and maneuvering of a shrewd general and not the<lb/> direct interposition of a God who abhors injustice and<lb/> loves goodness purchased our fathers&#39; deliverance&#44; then<lb/> all preparations to solemnize the anniversary of that<lb/> wait in a signal manner&#44; are simply senseless.  Why&#44;<lb/> the very opening of the Decalogue would be an imposition<lb/> on our credulity&#44; an execrable falsehood.  The thought<lb/> is blasphemy.<lb/>
                But what would my gentile neighbor have said at the<lb/> developments of the last quarter of a century&#63;  What at<lb/> the heartlessness of a teacher who&#44; having under his charge<lb/> bright promising youths&#44; instead of enkindling in their<lb/> breasts the fire of enthusiasm&#44; quenches the &#91;&#63;&#93;&#44; first<lb/> sparks of religious fervor&#63;  A teacher who labors to explain<lb/> away whatever discloses the wonderful dealings of the<lb/> Almighty with the seed of his righteous Abraham&#44; and<lb/> brings a Moses to the level of a conjurer and juggler&#63;<lb/>  Oh&#33; call it not heartlessness&#44; my brethren&#44; but crime&#44;<lb/> not unlike that against which Ezekiel exclaimed&#44; when<lb/> he saw the elders of Israel engaged in abominations&#44; in<lb/> the very chamber of the Temple&#44; and the shepherds who let<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>the flock go to destruction.  For infidelity to a<lb/> religious trust is worse than idolatry&#59; the warping<lb/> of children&#39;s minds exceeds the sin of selfishness.  The<lb/> Sages recommended to their scholars extreme caution<lb/> so as not to utter a word capable of misapprehension&#44;<lb/> how then to instill drop by drop a full measure of<lb/> disbelief into the guileless&#44; and then lend then forth<lb/> to engraft upon others the bane they have imbibed&#63;<lb/>  Can anything forebode a quicker ruin to Judaism&#63;<lb/>  I do not assert that it so actually happens&#59; but my<lb/> fears are well grounded.  They are based upon an extraordinary<lb/> utterance of that teacher&#44; made public enough to elicit<lb/> adverse comments.  Formerly one sinning so flagrantly<lb/> would have been <sic>excomunicated</sic>&#44; and disqualified from<lb/> entering the threshhold of God&#39;s sanctuary.  And who would<lb/> have consented to his ascending the pulpit&#63;<lb/></p>
            <p>Unhappily&#44; it is the want of some ecclesiastical disa&#45;<lb/>&#45;pline that threatens incalculable evils.  Not a<lb/> hierarchy&#44; with the power of fulminating anathemas&#44;<lb/> but an advisory board&#44; sanctioned by the leading con&#45;<lb/>&#45;gregations in the land&#44; and the weight of whose moral<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>authority might serve as a check upon individual<lb/> arbitrariness.  We would not then hear that the house<lb/> once dedicated to the worship of what Israelites believe to be a<lb/> Truth&#44; is lent for the performance of that which Israelites believe<lb/> to be a falsehood&#59; that in the same spot the acknowledg&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment of the Unity of God is made upon the Sabbath&#44; and<lb/> of the trinity on Sunday.  Such &#91;&#63;&#93; inconsistencies would<lb/> not be dignified into broad liberality.  It would not obtain<lb/> countenance&#44; and much less the applause for which the<lb/> main actor in that incident sought for&#44; and which he did<lb/> obtain from many a quarter&#45;&#45; the Jewish press over clapping<lb/> hands as to a triumph relieved over narrow&#45;mindedness&#44; just<lb/> as if freedom from prejudice meant indifference to religious<lb/> verities.<lb/></p>
            <p>In like manner&#44; the question of mixed marriages&#44; now so vio&#45;<lb/>&#45;lently agitated in the west&#44; so that a Rabbi wrote to permit<lb/> non&#45;Israelites to enter the house of Israel merely by the denial of<lb/> a triune god&#59; that question might be ventilated&#44; leaving&#44; of<lb/> course&#44; the pen as well as the speech always <sic>untramelled</sic>&#44;<lb/> but the practical application of a theory pregnant with misery<lb/> to families would find <sic>insuferable</sic> hindrances in the Syna&#45;<lb/>&#45;gogue.  The results of the absence of religious identity in the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>contracting party&#44; and the discordant education of the<lb/> children&#45;&#45;besides the destructive tendency to the cause of<lb/> Monotheism&#44; would be placed before the applicant&#44; and<lb/> the marriage would not be celebrated in the congregation<lb/> of Jacob.  Each Rabbi would be made to understand<lb/> that &#34;he is the teacher and not the legislator of the Congre&#45;<lb/>&#45;gation&#34; of the Lord.  I am glad to quote the last sentence<lb/> of mine fro ma lecture just delivered by a Rabbi&#44; who was wont<lb/> to allow himself every latitude.  I am doubly glad&#44; because it<lb/> required an immense deal of moral courage on his part so<lb/> to speak.  A father smarting under the severe stroke inflicted<lb/> by a disobedient child who entered into an alliance prohibited by<lb/> the spirit of the Mosaic laws&#44; as we have read this morning &#34;lest<lb/> thou take of heathens&#39; daughters unto thy sons&#44; and when those<lb/> daughters go astray after their gods&#44; they make thy sons also<lb/> go astray after their gods&#44;&#34; an alliance&#44; I say&#44; forbid explicitly<lb/> by God Ezra&#44; made very stringent by a synod in the days<lb/> of the Asmonean&#44; and enforced by the Rabbis in subsequent ages&#44;<lb/> might have declined answering a query which opened afresh<lb/> a painful wound.  But he replied fairly and squarely&#44; denouncing<lb/> such marriages&#44; and the ministers who dare defy a rule&#44; which the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>which the house of Israel&#45;&#45;much to their happiness&#45;&#45;have<lb/> carried out through a long and wide dispersion.<lb/></p>
            <p>Yes&#58; the establishing of a Board of the character just described&#44; might<lb/> create a little order&#44; where naught but chaos exists.  I advocated<lb/> it years ago&#44; not in the expectation that my poor word would<lb/> immediately effect the desirable end&#44; but in the belief that my<lb/> people would be set thinking&#59; that they would finally demand<lb/> of their ministers fixed rules for guidance&#44; without depending on<lb/> the crotchets of every one&#44; whom a congregation blindly chooses.<lb/>  Perhaps the time is not ripe&#44; but I have faith in the people.<lb/>  I cherish the hope that they will insist upon that or any<lb/> wise measure&#44; holding back the unscrupulous and reckless&#44;<lb/> purging the Synagogue of its defilements.  As in the days<lb/> of antiquity&#44; a sprinkling of typical waters rehabilitated the<lb/> polluted&#44; and they kept in common the anniversary of the national<lb/> birth&#44; so will the tears of the righteous few have accomplished a<lb/> purification.  They will be the first drops of that limped fountain<lb/> promised by God to be opened in our midst and from which<lb/> Israel will receive purification.  As Ezekiel wrote &#34;I will sprinkle<lb/> upon you clean water and you shall be cleaned from all your<lb/> impurities&#44; and from all your abominations will I cleanse you&#34;<lb/>  And so may it be.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
