<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF9_4</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1890-10" source="" attested="yes">October 1890</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_4_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_4_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_4_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_4_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_4_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_4_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_4_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_4_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_4_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_4_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_4_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_4_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. Fifth St.<lb/></p>
            <p>Philadelphia&#44; Oct &#47; 90<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>6<lb/></p>
            
            <p>On laymen preachers<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Brethren.  An experiment has recently been tried<lb/> in the Jewish conservative of the Jewish conservatism of Jewish England.  The new<lb/> departure commends itself well to my understanding.<lb/>  Hitherto only trained ministers&#44; or Rabbis&#44; acknow&#45;<lb/>&#45;ledged as such&#44; would enjoy be allowed the privilege of addres&#45;<lb/>&#45;sing a congregation in the synagogue.  A layman<lb/> on the pulpit was deemed an anomaly not to be<lb/> tolerated.  He might have possessed high qua&#45;<lb/>&#45;lifications&#44; learning&#44; eloquence&#44; piety&#44; a good appear&#45;<lb/>&#45;ance&#44; an enunciation very clear&#44; and a voice of<lb/> wide compass&#44; still his daily pursuits&#44; however honorable&#44;<lb/> debarred him from giving public counsel and instruct&#45;<lb/>&#45;ion in the house of prayer.  That rule so jealously kept&#44; was not&#44; as some<lb/> may suppose&#44; based on sound orthodox grounds.<lb/>  On the contrary&#44; walking in the light of our ancient<lb/> history&#44; I see that rather than a preservation of it is a deviation from the old<lb/> beaten path.  Upon it that path trod prophets and<lb/> Sages&#44; who surely did not wear the distinguish&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing garb of ecclesiastics.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>I notice Amos&#45;&#45;the fearless&#45;&#45;with his shepherd&#39;s crook&#44; and<lb/> the herdsman&#39;s coarse garment&#44; speaking words<lb/> that burned to the people Israel of his time&#44; when the<lb/> spirit of God stirrup stirred up his soul.  Looking<lb/> again I observe that on a the day of a public fast&#44; In Israel<lb/> one who&#44; either by his venerable age or by his<lb/> religious knowledge&#44; could command respect was<lb/> chosen on the spot to address give offer the Congregation &#91;Hebrew&#93; brotherly admonitions.<lb/>  And Hebrews who can search through the Talmud&#44;<lb/> will find how equally in earnest poor alike humble mechanics and<lb/> rich owners of rich estates&#44; were in carrying earnestly eagerly carried messages<lb/> of truth to their brethren.  Now&#44; without pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;suming to act as mentor to the community of Jewish American Jews&#44; I judge that the practice<lb/> which our annals show to have been carefully followed<lb/> by our illustrious Israelites&#44; in the days of old predecessors of ours&#44; might<lb/> be renewed by their successors to great advantage.  Aside from<lb/> other considerations&#44; which may suggest them&#45;<lb/>&#45;selves to thinking minds&#44; a rehabilitation<lb/> of the usage would&#44; at least&#44; break the mono&#45;<lb/>&#45;tony of listening to the same person continually&#44;<lb/> and might probably draw to the Divine<lb/> service many who now determinedly hold aloof.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Aware as I am to resort to irregular means&#44; which&#44; according<lb/> to my views&#44; are irregular&#44; for the purpose of attract&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing crowds&#59; willing as I have ever been to bear<lb/> the censure&#44; even the public reproach of those<lb/> who declare the worship offered tendered here an open false&#45;<lb/> hood and unprogressive and false and hence unpopular by reason of our mode of praying &#38; the character nature of our prayers I would nevertheless<lb/> rejoice&#44; if the influence of preachers after God&#39;s<lb/> heart&#44; though unadorned with a clerical robe&#44; could<lb/> draw secure for us thronged assemblages.  Notably welcome would<lb/> prove the readoption of the olden practice at cer&#45;<lb/>&#45;tain periods of our year&#44; when fresh voices raised to a pitch of enthusiasm telling<lb/> us all of duties neglected&#44; might arouse awaken a sense<lb/> of contrition conducive to righteousness.  I felt<lb/> deeply impressed during last winter&#44; on reading<lb/> that in New York bankers left their offices&#44;<lb/> merchants their warehouses at busy hours&#44; bending to the their steps to spots<lb/> admonitious of steeling sermons of sterling merit were being were delivered.<lb/>  Some called it spasmodic or hysterical excitement&#44;<lb/> short lived and of no practical utility.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>I differed&#59; I conceive that the effect was more<lb/> than fitful&#59; the emphatic exhortations proceeding from distinguishedness genuine earnestness and couched in<lb/> graceful language&#44; could not have been totally lost.<lb/>  In that instance&#44; clergymen only spoke&#44; because<lb/> the Church believes in the doctrine of ordination&#44;<lb/> and might not tolerate non&#45;ordained ministers&#44;<lb/> but we admit of no such distinctions.  To us every <lb/>Jew is the priest of the Lord and can officiate<lb/> in the dwelling of our heavenly Master.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> So our English coreligionists evidently think&#44; and<lb/> therefore they agreed on a new departure.  They have recently invited laymen of character high standing and<lb/> ability to deliver an occasional discourse on the pulpit.<lb/>  Mr Frederic Mocatta&#44; who by descent has a title<lb/> to the good will of British Jews&#44; because his<lb/> father &#40;or uncle&#41;&#63; in his eightieth year gave them a meri&#45;<lb/>&#45;torious translation in the vernacular of the Hebrew<lb/> work book&#44; &#34;Chizzuk Emunah&#34;&#44; or &#34;Faith Strengthened&#34;&#45;&#45;<lb/>a valuable controversial work disproving the claims<lb/> of Christianity&#45;&#45;; Mr Frederic Mocatta who wrote<lb/> a much approved of condensed history of the Spanish<lb/> Inquisition&#59; the same gentleman&#44; who&#44; moved by<lb/> love for his people&#44; visited them recently last year in almost<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>all the places of their dispersion and related their<lb/> sufferings with pathos&#59; that Englishman who by through his social stand&#45; position<lb/>&#45;ing and public spiritedness deserves well of Ju&#45;<lb/>&#45;daism at large&#44; consented to preach in one of the Synagogues&#44;<lb/> and report says that he edified his audience.  Words flowing from<lb/> such a source&#44; enter directly into the depths of the heart&#44;<lb/> because they are free form suspicions which&#44;<lb/> justly or unjustly&#44; Lectures by salaried officials are apt<lb/> to arouse.  The main difficulty lies in<lb/> meeting with Israelites among the laity&#44; whose oratorical skill<lb/> is backed by a life unexceptional of purity consistency.  For unless<lb/> the utterances reflect the innermost sentiments character<lb/> of the speaker&#44; they will sound like empty talk bubbles&#44;<lb/> spoken for mere effect&#44; a they are but frothy language rhetoric.  I have heard<lb/> from Israelites&#44; whose judgment is clear&#44; that London&#44;<lb/> though perhaps not the city of my young days<lb/> in its rigid conservatism&#44; contain can point point nevertheless<lb/> to men&#44; who pride themselves on their faith and take<lb/> pleasure in illustrating it by their pen and<lb/> their speech.  Would that I could say in<lb/> all honesty&#44; Philadelphia abounds with coreligionists<lb/> of mine&#44; whom I may invite on this stand&#44; certain<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>that their lives will not contradict their preaching.<lb/>  Even the Glad indeed would I be to vacate at times my post at intervals&#44; to make room for an occasional a temporary change creating a revival.  But situated as e are&#44; even a ministerial exchanging of pulpits&#44; that some have<lb/> strongly advocated&#44; by way of variety&#44; offers great considerable<lb/> obstacles.  I for instance&#44; could not consistently agree to that<lb/> plan&#44; lest ideas subversive of those which I<lb/> hold as sound&#44; be set forth before my congregants.  That impropriety<lb/> has been committed elsewhere&#44; greatly to the mortification<lb/> of him who had asked a colleague to occupy his<lb/> pulpit.  And I positively know that on the oc&#45;<lb/>&#45;casion of a national thanksgiving day&#44; a certain Rabbi&#44;<lb/> who was courteously asked by a fellow&#45;minister to<lb/> to participates in the exercises&#44; insisted upon ad&#45;<lb/>&#45;dressing the Congregation assemblage bare headed&#44; agasint the rule<lb/> of that religious body and to the annoyance of its<lb/> Pastor.  Yes&#58; on all sides we wherever we turn we are beset with<lb/> with stumbling blocks.  Still I dare not des&#45;<lb/>&#45;pair.  &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;israel and Judah are not widowed of their God&#34;  A few there are yet&#44; whose hearts<lb/> beat responsively to the cry of religion pleadings of their olden true venerated venerable mother&#45;&#45;Judaism&#45;&#45;&#44; a few<lb/> whose breasts swell with love for the ancestral<lb/> faith&#44; now derided&#44; for Hebrew worship and<lb/> Hebrew literature cast sinfully aside.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>The duty incumbent upon all of us all is to make<lb/> the number increase a hundred fold.  How shall<lb/> we attain that devoutly to be wished for result&#63;<lb/>  By encouraging schools&#44; seminaries&#44; all associa&#45;<lb/>&#45;tions of sacred and secular learning&#44; any and<lb/> every organization tending calculated to enlarge the sphere of<lb/> the understanding and mould the feelings of the<lb/> young Jewishly.  The days have gone by<lb/> when the mere chanting of the accepted ritual suf&#45;<lb/>&#45;ficed.  The present generation has greater needs&#45;&#45;<lb/>instruction strengthening the weak in faith&#44; confirm&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing the believers&#44; in religion proving that a religion<lb/> having as which has for its founder a man who left behind<lb/> country and kindred to obey the inner call of his<lb/> soul&#44; which demanded <sic>self&#45;abjurgation</sic>&#44; which required his going both as the<lb/> herald of the Universal Father&#44; proclaiming the<lb/> existence of the One only God&#44; that religion is worth<lb/> preserving in the days of happiness and in time<lb/> of freedom&#44; as it was gloriously guarded from<lb/> extinction in sorrow and persecution.  Oh&#33;  May laymen and ministers band together for that sublime purpose&#33;<lb/>  How reassuring to those who confide in the Lord<lb/> are the promises of a final success as in our Haftorah&#58; God<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>renews the strength of those who hope in Him so that<lb/> they may be labor unweariedly.  Like the eagle<lb/> they shall rise af aloft&#44; for the seed of Abraham&#44;<lb/> girded with might&#44; shall overcome impediments&#44;<lb/> and reach the height which the Rock of all<lb/> ages has destined them to ascend.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;I&#44; the Eternal thy God&#44; hold thee by the right hand&#44;<lb/> I am He who says &#39;fear not&#39;&#44; I am Thy hep keep.&#34;<lb/>  May he ever uphold us in our uphold support us and our<lb/> eyes see His glorious protection our national salvation.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
