<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF4_21</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_21_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_21_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_21_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_21_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_21_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_21_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_21_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_21_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_21_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_21_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_21_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_21_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Post&#45;Biblical<lb/>
                41<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>In speaking in my the last lecture of &#91;&#63;&#93; my series of Johanan Ben Zaccka&#239; and<lb/> of the invaluable services he rendered traditional<lb/> Judaism&#44; I mentioned Jabn&#233; or Jammia&#44; as<lb/> the town on the coast of the <sic>Mediterannean</sic> sea&#44;<lb/> where the Academy of of Jewish learning founded by that Rabbi&#44; flourished.<lb/>  But it must not be thought supposed that because that<lb/> famous master of the Holy Law&#44; searched out and<lb/> found a place of deliverance refuge for the Torah&#44; to<lb/> prevent its extinction at the sad period of our political downfall&#44;<lb/> that in Jammia alone was the flame of sacred<lb/> knowledge kept alive.  Soon after the<lb/> destruction of the Temple by Titus&#44; some of<lb/> the pupils of Johanan set up colleges in other<lb/> towns and disseminated learning taught successfully.  But the<lb/> multiplicity of schools&#45;&#45;generally a decided ad&#45;<lb/>&#45;vantage&#45;&#45;is not always conducive to that religious<lb/> unity which constitutes the soul of Judaism.<lb/>  Occasionally&#44; it happens that the minds of the<lb/> leaders of those respective institutions are not<lb/> in perfect accord&#44; so that the same oral laws receive<lb/> interpretations clashing with each other.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>What had happened already&#44; during<lb/> the latter days of the second sanctuary among<lb/> the disciples of Hillel and Shamma&#239;&#44; was about feared<lb/> to it might occur at the period of our history which I am<lb/> now engaged to discuss.  To guard against such<lb/> a division of opinions&#44; a one Rabbi exercised an iron<lb/> will.  He had succeeded Johanan in the chair of<lb/> the principal Jewish Academy college Academy established at Jammia.<lb/>  In history that chief is known as Gamliel&#44; or Gama&#45;<lb/>liel II&#44; to distinguish him from his grand pa&#45;<lb/>&#45;rent who bore the same name.  The Tal&#45;<lb/>&#45;mud relates that when Vespasian showed a dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;position to favor Ben Zacckai&#44; this Rabbi peti&#45;<lb/>&#45;tioned for the safety of Gamliel&#44; whose father<lb/> &#40;Simeon Ben Gamliel I&#41; had suffered martyrdom at the hands of the Romans because of through and for the Romans his patriotism.<lb/>  The character of Gamliel II has been exhibited<lb/> to view under different aspects.  Some have<lb/> described the sage as austere and arbitrary in the<lb/> extreme&#59; others&#44; again&#44; have tried to explain away<lb/> whatever seems harsh and imperious in his con&#45;<lb/>&#45;duct&#44; and have presented pictured him as gentle tractable and<lb/> just in all his measures.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>I have already stated before that in these lectures<lb/> of mine on the schools of Judea&#44; I intend to be<lb/> very brief&#44; offering mainly a general idea of the<lb/> subject&#59; consequently I cannot relate recount in detail<lb/> events which might give my hearers an oppor&#45;<lb/>&#45;tunity to form by themselves and impartial judgment.  But<lb/> I must am free to say that&#44; without approving in every<lb/> instance of the method adopted by that ancient<lb/> Rabbi to compel obedience to his authority&#44; as<lb/> President of the Synod&#44; or Sanhedrin&#44; I exonerate him<lb/> from the charge of <sic>wilfully</sic> using a despotic rules power.<lb/>  Thus Gamliel exclaimed on one occasion&#44; which<lb/> had caused great hardship &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;sovereign of the world&#44; Thou knowest that what<lb/> I have done is not in honor of my self nor of my<lb/> parentage&#44; but only in honor of Thee&#44; that<lb/> there might exist no disputes about the laws<lb/> of Israel&#34;.  That he was humble&#45;minded and<lb/> not at all vain and vindictive&#44; we have a strong<lb/> proof in the fact that after his opponents suc&#45;<lb/>&#45;ceeded in having him deposed for a time&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>he still attended the public sessions&#44;<lb/> and even allowed his pupils at times occasionally to dispute the ideas<lb/> he advanced.  Gamliel may have erred&#44; and<lb/> have in availing himself of the lofty position he held<lb/> to humble men who honestly differed from him<lb/> about the best mode of preserving the knowledge<lb/> of the traditions&#44; but without if I do not entirely defending endorse<lb/> his course&#44; I nevertheless believe that his unsuccessful at&#45;<lb/>&#45;tempt to create a centralizing power was meant<lb/> for the good of the nation.  He wished to hin&#45; avoid<lb/>&#45;der the possibility of every any unscrupulous man with a stock<lb/> of learning&#44; setting up an opposition school&#44;<lb/> where theories subversive of the oral laws be im&#45;<lb/>&#45;parted.  Or&#44; to say it Talmudically &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;in order that the One Torah be not split in twain&#34;.<lb/>  My sympathies are indeed with Eliezer Ben<lb/> Hyrcanus&#44; with Akabya Ben Mahalalel and<lb/> others&#59; specially with the lowly but highly<lb/> learned needle maker&#45;&#45;the exceptionally good Joshua<lb/> Ben Hananiah&#45;&#45;whom Gamliel brought to grief&#59;<lb/> but in studying the life&#45;work of Gamliel II the latter&#44; I become<lb/> strongly firmly convinced that his motives were pure.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>He loved his faith and his people dearly&#44;<lb/> and showed his affection by undertaking distant<lb/> journeys for the sake of both.  When the brutal<lb/> emperor&#44; Domitian son of Vespasian and successor<lb/> to his brother Titus resolved to exterminate the<lb/> Jews living at Rome&#44; whom he oppressed by heavy<lb/> taxations and shameless indignities&#44; Gamliel&#44;<lb/> accompanied by three celebrated colleagues&#44; hastened<lb/> to Italy.  He strove mightily to avert the threat&#45;<lb/>&#45;ening danger&#44; and his influence enlisted the<lb/> interest of high officials in the capital of the<lb/> empire.  Fortunately&#44; the violent death<lb/> which the ruling monster soon met with&#44; made his<lb/> tyrannical decree null and void.<lb/></p>
            <p>It may not be inappropriate to say tell&#44; in connection<lb/> with that edict of cruel Domitian&#44; that&#44; according to<lb/> historians&#44; he had conceived an irreconcilable hatred<lb/> against the Jews&#44; because some of the most noted<lb/> Romans had embraced Judaism.  Juvenal<lb/> the satirical poet&#44; <sic>lauches</sic> against such his biting<lb/> sarcasm&#44; and calls them vulgar names&#44; because<lb/> they preferred circumcision&#44; Sabbath keeping&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>and Mosaic regulations about food&#44; to the<lb/> worship of heathen gods&#44; and a life of heathen<lb/> pleasures.  A tombstone on which the name of<lb/> an aged rich woman&#44; &#40;Veturia&#41; who lived sixteen years as a<lb/> proselyte&#44; and was known in the synagogues as&#44; mo&#45;<lb/>&#45;ther Sarah&#44; has been discovered.  But the most<lb/> renowned of converts to our faith at that time&#44; was<lb/> Akylas&#44; or Acquila.  This Roman could boast of<lb/> both wealth and learning.  Having become acquainted<lb/> with the sect then called Jewish Christians&#44; or fol&#45;<lb/>&#45;lowers of Jesus of Nazareth&#44; he renounced paganism<lb/> and joined the new belief.  But dissatisfied<lb/> with the dogmas of Christianity&#44; he studied our<lb/> religion and because a entered it as &#91;Hebrew&#93; a righteous pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;selyte in Israel.  To him we owe a Greek tran&#45;<lb/>&#45;slation of the Bible&#44; highly praised by the Talmu&#45;<lb/>&#45;dists.  It is to be regretted that the original is near&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly all lost&#44; for as its author was a thorough<lb/> Hebraist&#44; and as his version is said to have been<lb/> rigorously literal&#44; it might have thrown considerable<lb/> light on obscure passages&#44; rendered so perhaps by<lb/> the error of copyists.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>It would be certainly of greater value<lb/> than the Greek translation&#44; called the Septuagint&#44;<lb/> which is faulty and unreliable.<lb/></p>
            <p>Akylas knew Rabbi Gamliel personally&#44; and not improbably&#44;<lb/> he is the proselyte reported to have evinced marked respect<lb/> for the memory of the Sage by extravagantly burning a<lb/> number of costly objects&#44; according to the senseless<lb/> custom prevailing then at funerals.  In open contrast with<lb/> that custom stated usage was the last will of Gamliel II.  The<lb/> Rabbi had seen that the love of display at burials<lb/> had reached a point beyond all reasonable bounds.<lb/>  Families unable to comply with the excessive immode&#45;<lb/>&#45;ration in vogue&#44; would flee away for shame and leave<lb/> their dead uninterred.  Gamliel studied to remedy<lb/> an inveterate evil.  To legislate against it seemed<lb/> difficult&#59; to preach against it might be to excite<lb/> antagonism.  When about to pass away from<lb/> earth&#44;and naturally anticipating that in honor to<lb/> his his station&#44; the Hebrew community would have bestowed<lb/> large sums on expensive garments to dress him in&#45;&#45;he<lb/> commanded that his body be clothed shrouded in plain white<lb/> linen.  None dared after that&#44; <sic>practise</sic> towards<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>their departed relatives what&#44; a patriarch&#44; a<lb/> sage and a chief of a sanhedrin had tacitly rebuked.<lb/>  It were well that the influence of a Gamliel could<lb/> be brought to bear on American Jews who fancy<lb/> to do their deceased ones honor by arraying them in<lb/> fine suits of black&#44; encasing their corpses in coffins caskets<lb/> of polished wood with silver mountings and silver<lb/> plates&#44; crowned with choice flowers in the shape<lb/> of laurels garlands&#44; of anchors and triangles&#44; with <sic>mottos</sic><lb/> and sentences and monograms and epigrams.<lb/>  How many Synagogues could be freed from a<lb/> degrading and God&#45;offending debt&#44; how many schools and seminaries<lb/> could be fittingly maintained&#44; how many poor<lb/> could be plentifully fed by the gold which is<lb/> thus inconsiderately&#59; wastefully spent.  When<lb/> the cause of religion&#44; of education and of charity<lb/> claims our urgent attention&#44; let Israelites exchange<lb/> senselessness or vanity for reason and humility.<lb/>  The demeanour of an ancient teacher of their<lb/> people should so direct them.  That parting direct&#45; behest<lb/> &#45;ion of Gamliel II would almost suffice to win our respect.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>But we I do mere justice to our a sainted preceptor&#44;<lb/> called to occupy the chair where sat Johanan Ben<lb/> Zaccka&#239;&#44; when I say that Gamliel of Jammia was<lb/> mentally and morally excellent.  To his tradition&#45;<lb/>&#45;al lore&#44; he associated a knowledge of astronomy&#44;<lb/> which he utilized in relation to the observance of<lb/> Jewish festivals&#59; of mathematics which he employed<lb/> about Sabbatical ordinances.  He it was who requested<lb/> a scholar to arrange in logical order the eighteen<lb/> benedictions&#44; which we call Amidah&#44; and if the<lb/> additional benediction one in which imprecations are uttered<lb/> against heretics and informers was composed by his<lb/> direction&#44; we may attribute it to the unhappy<lb/> times&#44; that produced recreants to our faith ready to incite<lb/> the Romans against their former coreligionists.<lb/>  That Gamliel was kind hearted we perceive in<lb/> the circumstance&#44; that he kept mourning as2 for<lb/> a relative member of his household at1 the death of a heathen slave he possessed&#59;<lb/> that he entertained enlarged views is clear from the de&#45;<lb/>&#45;ference he paid to labor.  He was wont to say&#44; that the<lb/> man who has a trade is like a vineyard well guarded by fences &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> while the absence of a mechanical profession leads to ruin. is a field open to devastation.<lb/>  Let us honor the memory of the truly wise president of a Hebrew college&#58; Rabbi Gamliel II.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
