<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF19_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_1_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>71</p>
            <p>About our religious schools<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  You have heard the announcement.  A<lb/> hall has been hired for the reception of children of our<lb/> faith&#44; who&#44; living in a Southern locality at Philadel&#45;<lb/>&#45;hia where sensible training is a desideratum&#44; need gratuitous religious teaching.  May I assume<lb/> a privilege not incompatible with my calling&#63;  Pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;suming that I am allowed to exercise it&#44; I say<lb/> that the place chosen must be considered only a<lb/> make&#45;shift&#44; to use a common expression.  The spot selected is literally and morally too far from<lb/> satisfying our requirements.  Such schools as ought<lb/> to be combined in one building&#44; after the manner that<lb/> I have often explained&#45;&#45;and that which will open<lb/> to morrow is an important one&#45;&#45;must be planted<lb/> in the very midst of the population whom we<lb/> wish to benefit.  In this respect&#44; we can learn<lb/> much from our neighbors of Christian denominations.<lb/>  They industriously search out the purlieus where illiteracy<lb/> and vulgarity have undisputed dominion&#44; and try to give full<lb/> sway there to education and good manners.<lb/>  Thanks to the laws of Moses&#44; that&#44; under the most<lb/> degrading influences&#44; prevented our people from<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>sinking deep into the slough of vice&#44; we are not<lb/> called upon to root out a brood of shameless outlaws.<lb/>  But neither can we lay the flattering unction to<lb/> our souls&#44; that whoever bears the name of Israel<lb/> is a paragon of virtue.  Painfully I acknowledge<lb/> that in convict&#45;cells I have found men and women<lb/> of our race&#59; in houses of refuge and correction I have<lb/> met boys and girls whom I had seen in Syna&#45;<lb/>&#45;gogues&#44; and the daily records of our city&#44; chronicle<lb/> among culprits names whose Hebrew origin may<lb/> easily be traced&#44; even when newspapers do not<lb/> provokingly show it out in plain words.  Now&#44; to ma&#45;<lb/>&#45;lign persons of any nationality&#44; or condition of<lb/> life is abhorrent to my feelings&#44; but I do not<lb/> so sin thus when I point to the increasing foreign po&#45;<lb/>&#45;pulation down town as a main centre towards which<lb/> our educational efforts must converge.  Not<lb/> the parents&#44; whom an accumulation of untoward cir&#45;<lb/>&#45;cumstances brought irremediably low&#44; may we hope to improve&#44;<lb/> but their numerous offspring we must lift up<lb/> for the sake of their own future&#44; and for the honor of the name<lb/> that they share with all of us.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Schools to which the little ones willingly go&#44; should<lb/> exist within an easy walk of the very youngest among<lb/> them.  Seated on the benches&#44; at the head of which<lb/> a sister or brother in faith&#44; American in feelings&#44;<lb/> Jewish in principles&#44; imparts knowledge&#44; lessons will<lb/> be imbibed that elevate and refine.  And here&#44;<lb/> again&#44; we may copy non&#45;Israelites.  They realize<lb/> that the contact of the educated and the sensibly intellectually<lb/> pious with the ignorant and the superstitious&#44; is of<lb/> incalculable benefit advantage to the latter.  But too many of<lb/> us are apt to overlook lose sight of that fact&#44; and we rather designedly to<lb/> shun places distasteful to our habits&#44; because of<lb/> their lowly surroundings.  yet&#44; religion invites us just where<lb/> our presence can raise fellow beings to a high<lb/> standard of morality.  Not as superiors with a look of <sic>condescen&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion</sic>&#44; not with a patronising air&#44; but with friendli&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness and genuine kindness&#44; bent on doing good&#44; we must<lb/> move among the lowly &#91;Hebrew&#93; And this lesson of our<lb/> creed&#44;  I eagerly wish that might notably to be impressed on the minds of the<lb/> women of my people&#44; sure that their intercourse<lb/> with the humbly stationed will be attended with<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>blissful results.  Now&#44; regarding myself&#44; I will tell that<lb/> I find it expedient to alter a plan which I have<lb/> followed for many years.  I devoted an early hour<lb/> on Sunday to Hebrew instruction&#44; and derived<lb/> pleasure from the progress that some of the stu&#45;<lb/>&#45;dents made.  But my class gradually dwindled<lb/> down to a size so very diminutive&#44; as to make render<lb/> its continuance a useless fruitless attempt.  In lieu of<lb/> it&#44; I purpose to bestow more and closer attention<lb/> on the two Sunday Schools&#44; to help the super&#45;<lb/>intendents&#44; to overlook the classes particularly re&#45;<lb/>&#45;quiring Biblical and post Biblical tuition&#44; &#38; to lecture<lb/> familiarly now and then on Scriptural and Rabbinical ethics.  Nor<lb/> do I contemplate abandoning my instruction of the<lb/> Hebrew.  Too dear is the sacred language to my<lb/> heart&#44; that I should turn false to it.  In the face of all drawbacks and hindrances I will uphold uphold it.  Seeing<lb/> that my strenuous labors to foster its cultivation<lb/> in the various ways pursued heretofore&#44; have failed&#59; see&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing that the Sunday morning teaching was annually<lb/> more disappointing&#59; that my inviting youths<lb/> to my house for a nightly instruction&#44; imparting of our literature&#44; met no<lb/> longer with a response&#44; I proposed to an<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>organization allied to another bearing the distinctive appellation<lb/> of &#34;Young Men&#39;s Hebrew Association&#34; a scheme for<lb/> making it the vehicle of an necessary essential revival.<lb/>  After having urgently brought ot its notice explained in a<lb/> course of lectures&#44; the propriety of redeeming the<lb/> name by which it is known&#44; through its advocacy<lb/> of Hebrew learning&#44; a circular was sent&#44; inviting<lb/> all to assemble twice a week at a leisure hour<lb/> in the rooms of the institution.  They would<lb/> hear familiarly in easily comprehended style remarks upon the character of the<lb/> language of our prophets&#44; on the best mode of read&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing it with ease and accuracy of understanding<lb/> its construction&#44; and acquiring a facility for wri&#45;<lb/>&#45;ting it.  I blush to confess that the summons<lb/> was received frigidly.  Not three out of five or a large<lb/> six hundred members heeded it.  Sorrowfully I had to re&#45;<lb/>&#45;linquish all hopes in that direction.  Still&#44; But I have said it&#44; I<lb/> must not forego my intention to hinder a total<lb/> desertion of a Jewish cause.  My mind assures<lb/> me continually&#44; and never so forcibly as during<lb/> the late festivals&#44; that our youths unacquaintance with the<lb/> Hebrew language will be death to the Synagogue.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>With the introduction of the vernacular&#44;&#45;&#45;as very recently projected by an assemblage of men belonging to a sister Congregation&#45;&#45;the mystic<lb/> chain of Jewish solidarity will be broken.  Our<lb/> houses of prayer will cease to form a common<lb/> bond among scattered Israel.  Approximation<lb/> to gentilism&#44; its rituals and practices will fol&#45;<lb/>&#45;low as a an inevitable sequence&#44; which and the logic of events has<lb/> proved it in instances recorded in history.  Judaism<lb/> thus stripped of its peculiar features&#44; will finally be con&#45;<lb/>&#45;founded with the popular belief.  We shall have<lb/> wantonly parted with our Divine trust to en&#45; ponder<lb/> &#45;rich the opponents of Mosaism. to the crotchets of the worldly and the changelings.  Disappointed but<lb/> not despairing I look now to the very element of foreign origin&#44;<lb/> settling vcry fast in a Southern section of Phila&#45;<lb/>&#45;delphia&#44; as a preventive of the evil which I would<lb/> unutterably lament.  Not long ago I was<lb/> asked to assist in dedicating a Hebrew School<lb/> for the use of that population&#44; and I consented.<lb/>  But its close followed quick hard at the heels of its open&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing.  As I had foreseen&#44; neither the teaching<lb/> materials were good&#44; nor the influence of the<lb/> directors could lend the institution the dignity<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>commanding patronage.  But with a spa&#45;<lb/>&#45;cious house&#44; raised by the free will offerings of my<lb/> wealthy intelligent coreligionists&#44; in one of the streets in the afore&#45;<lb/>&#45;cited locality&#44; with a supply of adequate means to broaden the<lb/> sphere of the Hebrew schools now existing under<lb/> the auspices of the Hebrew Education Society&#44; we<lb/> may reasonably anticipate happy results.<lb/>  We dare not restrain satisfied with Concert Hall<lb/> now rented as a substitute for a fitter building&#44;<lb/> nor with the small room occupied above our present Kinder&#45;<lb/>&#45;garten.  We must own a modest but commo&#45;<lb/>&#45;dious structure to hold as many children as will<lb/> avail themselves of our free tuition.  and I promise will deem it<lb/> my duty to supervise its working in any department fal&#45;<lb/>&#45;ling within the line of my vocation.  Philadelphia<lb/> with its preparatory schools and New York with<lb/> its Seminary may&#44; under the guidance of beneficent<lb/> Providence&#44; vindicate the right of our psalmists<lb/> and Seers and Sages to be heard in the language<lb/> which they hallowed with their heavenly inspiration and right&#45;<lb/>&#45;eous aspirations.  Mine will be the joy of<lb/> having labored to a purpose&#44; yours&#44; men<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>women of Israel&#44; whom the Almighty favored with wealth&#44;<lb/> will be the glory of having resuscitated the de&#45;<lb/>caying Sanctuary of the Lord.<lb/></p>
            <p>Brethren.  At the risk of being wearisome&#44; I must<lb/> revert to this same subject&#44; of so vital an im&#45;<lb/>&#45;portance to the perpetuity of our religion in America<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
