<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF2_13</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1878" source="" attested="yes">1878</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_13_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_13_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_13_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_13_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_13_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_13_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_13_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_13_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_13_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_13_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_13_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_13_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>On the 18th anniversary of<lb/>
                the 7th st Synagogue.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Eighteen years have almost changed the looks of our<lb/> venerable Congregation.  Many who constituted it earlier<lb/> than at that period&#44; in which we consecrated was consecrated this house&#44;<lb/> have gone to their lasting reward&#44;&#45;&#45;and we have had cause<lb/> to deplore the departure&#45;&#45;&#44; while many whom we did not<lb/> know then&#44; form now our principal number.  The<lb/> descendants of the men and women who <sic>worshipped</sic> in the<lb/> days of old at the Synagogue&#44; which stood upon the same<lb/> spot very nearly four scores of years&#44; can be easily counted.&#44;<lb/> and We may be thankful indeed on seeing the glowing degeneracy&#44; that any representatives<lb/> of the families who gave stability to the service of Israel&#39;s God<lb/> in Philadelphia&#44; still contribute yet to carry it on.<lb/>  But However&#44; the bulk of its supporters&#44; and&#45;&#45;what is more to<lb/> the purpose&#45;&#45;of its attendants&#44; does not belong to the<lb/> original stock.  It is a foreign element of a compa&#45;<lb/>&#45;ratively recent creation.  To that new infusion<lb/> we mainly owe the preserving of this sacred insti&#45;<lb/>&#45;tution from a gradual decay.  I mean to the accession<lb/> received from time to time of Israelites&#44; unaccustomed<lb/> to the Sephardic Minhag.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>It will be remembered that just as we determined<lb/> to remove to a more fitting edifice&#45;&#45;the raising<lb/> of which burdened us with a debt still unliquidated&#45;&#45;&#44;<lb/> an uncalled for division took place&#44; thinning our ranks.<lb/>  To that melancholy occurrence&#44; was superadded soon<lb/> after the civil war between two sections of this coun&#45;<lb/>&#45;try&#44; and which&#44; taxing the resources of the people&#44;<lb/> reduced our revenue.  But we must record with<lb/> gratification&#44;&#45;&#45;as a bright page in our history&#45;&#45;&#44; that<lb/> through those reverses&#44; and through the violent pres&#45;<lb/>&#45;sure brought against us by the actual unauthorized changes &#91;&#63;&#93;<lb/> in the ritual&#44; and the government of the Synagogue radical and otherwise&#44; our brethren&#44; who joined us<lb/> since we entered this building&#44; have&#44; with scarcely<lb/> any exception worth mentioning&#44; kept attached to<lb/> our Synagogue.  And we may chronicle likewise also<lb/> with unfeigned satisfaction that we finally welcomed that our adherence to principles afforded us at length<lb/> back to it our holy courts the great satisfaction of welcoming back again into<lb/> our holy courts&#44; some who had left the&#44; not from<lb/> any feelings of hostility&#44; but from motives of per&#45;<lb/>&#45;sonal regard to one who had labored diligently<lb/> in <sic>defence</sic> of Judaism.  Let us be grateful&#44; and<lb/> express our inward sentiments before God upon this eighteenth an&#45;<lb/>&#45;niversary of our new Synagogue.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>The Lord who does not forsake those who confide in<lb/> Him in truth&#44; raised deliverers to prevent our hallowed<lb/> structure from becoming a solitude&#44; for want of worship&#45;<lb/>&#45;pers in the manner of old.  Therein have His praises<lb/> continued to resound&#44; and that not only at distant inter&#45;<lb/>&#45;vals&#44; but with greater frequency than where innova&#45;<lb/>&#45;tions of various kinds have been are periodically offered to<lb/> attract a <sic>multytudes</sic>.  The foreign element in<lb/> our midst has been mostly conservative.  It has preferred<lb/> the simplicity of the fathers to the extravagant no&#45;<lb/>&#45;tions of the children&#44; ruinous in their consequences&#44; and<lb/> not at all well accompanied with any a deeper reverence for religion.<lb/>  Even if the service rendered here&#44; did not accord in all its<lb/> parts with the general want ideas entertained&#44; still a sensible opposi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion to capricious alterations&#44; commended the retention of<lb/> the entire form to the mind of the majority.  In<lb/> the absence of emendations carrying upon their face<lb/> the impress sanction of a rightly constituted ecclesiastical authority synod&#44; the attendants<lb/> submitted to that which may not altogether have<lb/> been according altogether to their liking.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>But there is an emendation upon the acceptance of<lb/> which my brethren&#44;&#45;&#45;both the last comers&#44; and the ori&#45;<lb/>&#45;ginal <sic>worshippers</sic> should have insisted.  It is in the<lb/> way style of chanting our prayers.  For&#44; by the admission<lb/> of all who have any sense of harmony in their nature&#44;<lb/> our system&#44; or rather our lack of system militates against<lb/> the interests of orthodoxy.  How can musically trained<lb/> youths join with any spiritual gratification in psalmody<lb/> discordantly sung&#63;  Will they not prefer a short litur&#45;<lb/>&#45;gy&#44; the melody of which affects pleasantly&#44; to a long<lb/> one which assumes the shape of a vocal strife&#44; of a<lb/> rivalry among some determined to be heard the loudest<lb/> and the last&#63;  Understand&#44; the question at issue is not<lb/> about inviting persons by increasing outsiders our number by the allurement of operatic strains&#44; but about<lb/> retaining of our own by avoiding disagreeable impressions.<lb/>  I have had occasion recently to observe in another a neighboring city<lb/> the recitation method.  The reader alone rehearsing<lb/> the psalms in a slow and measured tone&#59; the con&#45;<lb/>&#45;gregation following inaudibly.  To me it sounded<lb/> monotonous I judged it also fatiguing also in the extreme&#44; because un&#45;<lb/>&#45;relieved by lights and shades&#44; and&#44; I judge&#44; wearisome<lb/> to those who listen.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>I confess that in some of my writings advocating uni&#45;<lb/>&#45;formity in the services at the Synagogues throughout<lb/> the United States&#44; I proposed the introduction of recitative<lb/> in several portions now chaunted.  Nor have I arrived<lb/> at a different conclusion since as that one&#44; about regarding the ad&#45;<lb/>&#45;visabilityeness of the plan.  But I have always held that poe&#45;<lb/>&#45;tical hymns or psalms ought to call forth a large vo&#45;<lb/>&#45;lume of sounds&#44; and that in consonance with the rules of<lb/> harmony&#44; so that the effect may be imposing and soul stir&#45;<lb/>&#45;ring.  Who can should attune their voices so effectively<lb/> but a whole congregation moved by devotional sentiments&#63;<lb/>  To the attendants in the house of God&#44; belongs the indisputable right of<lb/> uttering praises and thanksgivings&#44; but each attendant ought to know his<lb/> capacity or his unfitness to join loudly in the worship.<lb/>  The President&#44; and much less the minister&#44; can be expected to<lb/> approach such individuals as persistently continue to disturb the<lb/> harmony&#59; because they are <sic>unware</sic> of their deficiencies with a complaint.  How&#45;<lb/>&#45;ever gentle the remonstrance&#44; it might wound and offend&#44;<lb/> a result which our temporal director and myself would<lb/> equally regret.  But inasmuch as if all of us are inte&#45;<lb/>rested in upholding the dignity of this sacred receptacle<lb/> of conservatism&#44; we ought to study how to guard it against<lb/> any cause for disparagement.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>We ought to check even a pious inclination forcing out<lb/> our high notes&#44; for the sake of exalting the worship&#44;<lb/> and furthering the advantage of this house we dedicated<lb/> eighteen years ago in honor to the Eternal Lord.  Unfortunately&#44;<lb/> either through fondness for self gratification an &#91;&#63;&#93; of self&#45;importance shortsightedness&#44; or through<lb/> misjudgment we are not always so guided in our conduct.<lb/>  And I am sorry that I must&#44; with my usual candor&#44;<lb/> express disapprobation upon this score.  The last public<lb/> act of my Congregation was not calculated to benefit the<lb/> cause we should have at heart.  We absolutely<lb/> need the means to support students&#44; who may be<lb/> trained for the ministry as ministers to serve at the altar of the Unity.  The Maimonides College<lb/> which partly established and maintained sustained to accomplished that end was short&#45;lived&#44; because<lb/> the East failed to appreciate its unselfish working.  Only<lb/> a few public&#45;spirited Philadelphians were left to bear the expense of<lb/> its maintenance.  The West&#44; has shamed us by its the<lb/> formation of an admirable Union promotive of Hebrew education.<lb/>  An institution exists has been created which reckons a hundred con&#45;<lb/>&#45;gregations as its patrons&#44; aside from private donors.<lb/>  It was proposed that we make common cause with the cooperate in extending its<lb/> utility.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>I took an early opportunity to present the pros<lb/> and cons of the proposition.  I advanced recommended caution and con&#45;<lb/>&#45;sideration&#44; but not I did not adorn a peremptory refusal.  Since<lb/> my having so spoken on that topic&#44; I received the an official assurance that<lb/> no undue one&#45;sided influence was exercised upon the minds<lb/> of the students.  That assurance was published<lb/> in a Philadelphia Weekly.  But even if no credence<lb/> was is to be put in it&#44; we learnt that the Board of Delegates&#44;<lb/> in which our body is we are represented&#44; had agreed to take<lb/> proper steps for an amalgamation&#44; under upon terms<lb/> advantageous to the East.  That fact also was<lb/> known to the readers of the Jewish press.  Meanwhile<lb/> quite a number of congregations of all shades of opi&#45;<lb/>&#45;nion had flowed into the Union.  It became very<lb/> evident that the organization would extend spread far and<lb/> wide&#44; and that branches of the principal college must<lb/> unavoidably be established beyond the place where it<lb/> was first started.  All these circumstances ought to<lb/> have had a weight upon the deliberations of my congre&#45;<lb/>&#45;gation.  Had it been decided at the genial last&#45;semiannual meeting that to spread for the love of religious<lb/> learning&#44; we were ready to cooperate work in concert with all Israelites<lb/> irrespective of their ritual tendencies&#44; we might have gained<lb/> some controlling voice power in the general council&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>and the demand upon our treasury would have<lb/> been then nominal.  Now&#44; we have condemned our&#45;<lb/>&#45;selves to inactivity&#44; for&#44; once that the Union consti&#45;<lb/>&#45;tution of the Union is altered&#44;&#45;&#45;as contemplated by the Board of<lb/> Delegates&#45;&#45;&#44; a tax would have to we could be entitled to a representation&#44; unless a tax be imposed on<lb/> each seat&#45;holder&#44; to entitle us to a representation&#44; and such a measure naturally unpopular<lb/> and that unpopular measure could never be enforced.<lb/>  Had we even the pecuniary ability to to cope with the<lb/> gigantic enterprise emanating from originated &#91;&#63;&#93; at Cincinnati&#44; I<lb/> could not have favored exclusiveness&#59; but shortened are<lb/> our circumstances&#59; we may need require the help of the very<lb/> body whose contact we have sunn shunned&#44; to raise tea&#45;<lb/>&#45;chers and ministers in Israel in sympathy with our principles.<lb/>  I shall not discuss here the plea of unconstitution&#45;<lb/>&#45;ality advanced&#44; a plea which has worked mischief al&#45;<lb/>&#45;ready&#44; and which is not very tenable&#44; because the force of time has<lb/> virtually rendered many a clause rule upon on our<lb/> Statute&#45;book a dead letter.  I Nor do I not express myself<lb/> so freely&#44; in order to pass my adverse structures on the conduct of my constituents&#59; but as the eigh&#45;<lb/>&#45;teenth anniversary of our Synagogue came just on the heel<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>of the last public act of my congregation&#44; I<lb/> thought of discharging a duty by a word of<lb/> exhortation.  Let us shake off&#44; my Brethren&#44; the a<lb/> spirit of overweening self&#45;assertion&#59; let us recognize<lb/> merit where it dwells.  That portion of the Jewish po&#45;<lb/>&#45;pulation&#44; known by the name of &#34;Reformers&#44;&#34; has out&#45;<lb/>stripped us in charitable&#44; and in scholastic under&#45;<lb/>takings.  We who retain the title of Orthodox have<lb/> in late years contributed but little to that which<lb/> practically shows attachment to Israel and to its<lb/> laws.  There is something we can profitably copy<lb/> from our coreligionists who have departed from the an&#45;<lb/>&#45;cient landmark.  And we should not hesitate to become<lb/> their coadjutors.  Let us resolve at this solemn<lb/> season of our Pentecost festival&#44; which recalls an event of sin&#45;<lb/>&#45;gular importance to ourselves&#45;&#45;the consecration of a<lb/> stately edifice&#45;&#45;that we will hence forth honor the<lb/> Lord more than by outward worship&#59; that we will<lb/> bestow our thoughts&#44; give largely of our personal activity&#44;<lb/> contribute with the utmost we can afford&#44; so that<lb/> Judaism in America may have a <sic>brodening</sic> influence&#44;<lb/> a permanence and a glory.  And so may it be.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
