<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Voorsanger, Jacob</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx4FF3_29</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Voorsanger, Jacob</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Morais, Sabato</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>San Francisco, CA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1886-11" source="" attested="yes">12 November 1886</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx4ff3_29_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx4ff3_29_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx4ff3_29_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx4ff3_29_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx4ff3_29_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx4ff3_29_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx4ff3_29_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx4ff3_29_2v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>3 pages on 2 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       

                <pb n="1"/>
                <p>2316 California St&#44; San Francisco&#44; Nov 12. 1886<lb/>
                Rev S Morais<lb/></p>
            <p>My dear Sir<lb/></p>
            <p>Time has passed rapidly since I received your valued<lb/> postal before my departure from Houston&#44; now nearly 4 months<lb/> ago.  In all these weeks I have meant to write you but I need not<lb/> tell you how quickly time flies in the endeavor to invest one&#39;s career<lb/> with the character of permanency.  I found so much to do that my<lb/> correspondence has greatly suffered&#44; and I am just now engaged<lb/> in making my peace with my old friends&#44; some of whom seem to<lb/> think that my changed circumstances and advancement have rendered<lb/> me oblivious to past ties.  You&#44; I know&#44; are too liberal minded to harbor<lb/> such a suspicion&#44; and I will therefore only say&#44; that circumstances<lb/> absolutely prevented my writing letters of any character what&#45;<lb/>ever.  But now that I am ready to write I hardly know where<lb/> to begin.  I have questioned many experiences during the past 3<lb/> months&#44; and I have found so much to do in this new field that<lb/> more than ever already I complained &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  I have<lb/> found an open field&#44; with fences ruined.  It will please you to<lb/> learn that &#34;radical reform&#34; has very few sympathizers on this<lb/> coast.  In my own congregation a large and respectable conservative<lb/> element sustains its objections to continued innovation&#44; and this<lb/> Temple Emanuel&#44; which bears the reputation of a radically<lb/> reformed congregation stands&#44; in point of fact&#44; upon the safe<lb/> basis of conservativism&#44; occupied by Jastrow&#44; Szold and other<lb/> advocates of that conciliatory policy.  In this connection let me<lb/> explain to you that the American Hebrew made an unreasonable<lb/> fuss over what it was pleased to call my Sunday movement&#44;<lb/> You doubtlessly read my rejoinder&#44; and since the matter is<lb/> now definitively settled I am in a position to state autho&#45;<lb/>ritatively that my congregation favors Sunday morning<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="2"/>
            <p>lectures <hi rend="underline">once a month</hi> as an experiment to ascertain whether<lb/> there is an <hi rend="underline">honest</hi> popular demand for such lectures.  The Board<lb/> of directors who initiated this movement have to thoroughly circum&#45;<lb/>scribed the proceedings on these mornings that no one&#44; unless he<lb/> is prejudiced and biased will accuse us of Sunday Sabbatarian<lb/> tendencies.  I will send you my first Sunday lecture&#44; to be delivered<lb/> Dec. 5&#44; which will explain my own position in the premises.  It<lb/> will please you to learn that after 3 months labors my original salary<lb/> of &#36;3000 has already been raised to &#36;3600 as a mark of approval<lb/> of my initial labors.  I find that the young people require my utmost<lb/> care and in the enclosed slip you can see that I am not idle<lb/> in this direction but are am making an effort to unite them in a<lb/> movement for intellectual culture.  I would be greatly obliged<lb/> to you to send me a copy of the present constitution of the Y. M. H. A.<lb/> of your city&#44; which will assist me in making the draft more<lb/> complete.  Next Sunday we organize.<lb/></p>
            <p>My dear and venerated friend&#44; tomorrow I will be 34 years of<lb/> age and it is just a decade since I left Philadelphia to struggle and<lb/> battle and&#45;&#45;conquer&#44; God has been merciful to me.  The cares of a<lb/> growing family&#44; the competitions and jealousies of the profession&#44;<lb/> the fluctuations of popular favor&#44; have not stood in my way&#44;<lb/> and I am now nearly at the topmost round of the ladder<lb/> where I hope to reach if God spares me and will still be<lb/> merciful to me.  And after ten years&#44; with a ripened intellect<lb/> and mature experiences I still turn to you with the affection<lb/> of my young days&#44; and ask you to bless my future career&#44; for I<lb/> assure you there will be nothing in it unworthy of you&#44; or<lb/> myself or the honored name of Israel.  I am building up&#44; I<lb/> have no ambition to destroy&#44; let me soon have the pleasure of<lb/> seeing your familiar lines and with best regards to your<lb/> family believe me as ever&#44; faithfully yours<lb/> Jacob Voorsanger.<lb/></p>
                
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>A DRAFT FOR THE ORGANIZATION OF A<lb/> TEMPLE EMANUEL ASSOCIATION.<lb/></p>
            <p>I. OBJECTS.<lb/></p>
            <p>The objects of this organization are<lb/> to be&#58;<lb/></p>
            <p>1. To bring the Jewish youth of Temple<lb/> Emanuel&#44; and all other Hebrews who<lb/> may join them&#44; together for the purposes<lb/> hereinafter described.<lb/></p>
            <p>2. To stimulate religious interest in<lb/> its members&#44; by the aid of measures to<lb/> be mentioned hereafter.<lb/></p>
            <p>3. To develop <sic>titerary</sic> tastes amongst<lb/> the young people.<lb/></p>
            <p>4. To assist in the dissemination of<lb/> useful knowledge&#44; calculated to refine the<lb/> heart and improve the mind.<lb/></p>
            <p>5. To promote sociability amongst its<lb/> members&#44; such as necessarily should ex&#45;<lb/>ist amongst those who unite for the<lb/> furtherance of great ideas and the per&#45;<lb/>petuation of sacred principles.<lb/></p>
            <p>6. To &#91;&#63;&#93; the work generally<lb/> expected of an organization of pronounced<lb/> literary tendencies.<lb/></p>
            <p>7. Generally&#44; to foster religion&#44; science<lb/> and art&#44; thereby aiming at a happy com&#45;<lb/>bination of the good&#44; the true and the<lb/> beautiful.<lb/></p>
            <p>II. HEADQUARTERS.<lb/></p>
            <p>Provided that the Board of Trustees<lb/> of Temple Emanuel consents&#44; the head&#45;<lb/>quarters of the &#34;Emanuel Association&#34;<lb/> shall be in the basement of Temple<lb/> Emanuel&#44; where rooms shall be suitably<lb/> fitted up for the management of the As&#45;<lb/>sociation.<lb/></p>
            <p>III. HOW TO ACCOMPLISH<lb/> OBJECTS<lb/></p>
            <p>1. RELIGION&#58;<lb/></p>
            <p>By the organization of classes&#45;&#45;for the<lb/> instruction of Hebrew&#44; religion&#44; history<lb/> and Jewish literatur&#59; by the institution<lb/> of all measures promoting religious ac&#45;<lb/>tivity that may afterwards be agreed<lb/> upon.<lb/></p>
            <p>2. Literature&#58;<lb/></p>
            <p>By the organization of a literary and<lb/> reading room&#44; such as are generally<lb/> found in literary organizations.<lb/></p>
            <p>3. <sic>Scienc</sic>&#58;<lb/></p>
            <p>By the organization of lecture courses&#44;<lb/> in general science&#44; or its departments.<lb/></p>
            <p>4. Intellectual entertainment&#58;<lb/></p>
            <p>a. Magazines and periodicals of the<lb/> highest order.<lb/></p>
            <p>b. Informal meetings of the Associa&#45;<lb/>tion for the conduct of debates&#44; reading<lb/> &#91;&#63;&#93;<lb/></p>
            <p>c. Classes for the instruction of sub&#45;<lb/>jects agreed upon by any twenty mem&#45;<lb/>bers of the Assocation.<lb/></p>
            <p>d. Monthly public lectures under the<lb/> auspices of the Association.<lb/></p>
            <p>5. <emph rend="italics">Amusement&#58;</emph><lb/></p>
            <p>Musical receptions&#44; entertainments of<lb/> a general character&#44; recitations&#44; declama&#45;<lb/>tions&#44; etc.<lb/></p>
            <p>IV. MANAGEMENT.<lb/></p>
            <p>1. The Association is to be managed<lb/> by a Board of Directors&#44; from amongst<lb/> whom the Association shall select a Pres&#45;<lb/>ident&#44; a Vice&#45;President&#44; a Secretary and<lb/> Treasurer.  Said Board of Directors to<lb/> consist of no less than 15 members&#44; who<lb/> shall be subdivided into committees for<lb/> the proper conduct of the Association&#39;s<lb/> business.  In order to cement proper<lb/> relations between the Emanuel Associa&#45;<lb/>tion and its parent Temple Emanuel&#44; it<lb/> is suggested that the President&#44; Vice&#45;<lb/>President and Rabbi of Temple Emanuel<lb/> shall be ex&#45;officio members of the Board&#44;<lb/> leaving the Association to select 12 mem&#45;<lb/>bers&#44; to serve for a period of years as<lb/> per the following roster&#58;<lb/></p>
            <p>3 for 4 years.<lb/></p>
            <p>3 &#34; 3 &#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>3 &#34; 2 &#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>3 &#34; 1 year.<lb/></p>
            <p>This Board shall conduct the business<lb/> of the Association&#44; whilst the same is<lb/> not in session.<lb/></p>
            <p>The Association shall meet annually&#44;<lb/> and in special session under the rules<lb/> governing such sessions.<lb/></p>
            <p>V. MEMBERSHIP.<lb/></p>
            <p>The Association shall be composed of<lb/> two classes of members&#58;<lb/></p>
            <p>1. ACTIVE MEMBERS&#44; composed of<lb/> ladies and gentlemen of Hebrew faith<lb/> and parentage above 21 years of age&#44;<lb/> who shall pay the advance sum of 5 dol&#45;<lb/>lars per annum to the Association.  Every<lb/> member in this class is entitled to all the<lb/> rights and privileges usually belonging<lb/> to membership.<lb/></p>
            <p>2. ASSOCIATE MEMBERS&#44; composed of<lb/> young Hebrews between the ages of 15<lb/> and 21&#44; who shall have no vote&#44; nor at&#45;<lb/>tend the business meetings of the Asso&#45;<lb/>ciation&#44; but shall otherwise participate in<lb/> all the rights and privileges of member&#45;<lb/>ship.<lb/></p>
            <p><emph rend="italics">Provided</emph>&#44; that the Associate Member&#45;<lb/>ship shall be represented in the business<lb/> meetings of the Association by sending a<lb/> delegate for each 10 Associate Members<lb/> to the same.<lb/></p>
            <p>Associate members pay the sum of<lb/> 3 dollars per annum dues in advance&#44;<lb/> and can become active members upon<lb/> application to the Board of Directors.<lb/></p>  
            <p>The Association demands no initiation<lb/> fee&#44; simply the annual dues in advance.<lb/></p>
            <p>Details to this plan are left to the or<lb/>ganization itself.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>JACOB VOORSANGER&#44;<lb/>
                <del>HOUSTON&#44; TEXAS</del>.<lb/>
                San Francisco&#44; Cal.<lb/></p>
            <p>Rev. S. Morais<lb/>
                546 North Fifth Street<lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">Philadelphia</hi><lb/>
                <hi rend="underline">Pa.</hi><lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
