<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF10_6</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1894-01" source="" attested="yes">1894</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_6_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_6_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_6_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_6_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_6_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_6_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_6_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_6_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_6_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_6_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_6_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_6_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>94<lb/></p>
            <p>About the work<lb/>
                &#34;Isra&#235;l among Nations&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>A book which created a sensation&#44; when it was first<lb/> issued&#44; and to which the translation in our vernacular has<lb/> lent greater prominence&#44; is&#44; &#34;Isra&#235;l chez les nations&#34;&#44; or&#44;<lb/> Israel among the nations.  The volume has already gone<lb/> through four editions and&#44; unless my memory betrays<lb/> me&#45;&#45;a not infrequent occurrence&#45;&#45;I may add&#44; that<lb/> one of the editions was bought by the Israelitish Alliance&#44;<lb/> whose central seat is in Paris.  The object was to let<lb/> the contents of the popular book be read far and wide&#44;<lb/> by means of the numerous branches and patrons of that<lb/> organization.  An English rendition&#44; published in<lb/> New York&#44; elicited a review from two scholarly persons&#44;<lb/> possibly also from more&#44; unknown to me.  One of the<lb/> reviewers&#44; who passed on it a favorable judgment&#44; no&#45;<lb/>&#45;ticed nevertheless&#44; several inaccuracies&#44; due to a lack<lb/> of thorough familiarity&#44; on the part of the author&#44;<lb/> with rules and practices followed by observant Israel&#45;<lb/>ites&#59; the other reviewer equally favorable&#44; still regretted that the author is<lb/> not acquainted with the movement within the syna&#45;<lb/>&#45;gogue in this country&#44; where &#34;Reform&#34; has succeeded<lb/> so well&#44; that it walks untramelled.  That is a great pity&#44;<lb/> in the reviewer&#39;s conception.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>I admire the courage of a Christian Frenchman<lb/> in boldly attacking Antisemitism&#44; where such con&#45; ma&#45;<lb/>&#45;temptible &#45;lignant writings as &#34;La France Juive&#34; and &#34;La libre<lb/> parole&#44;&#34; aiming to injure our people socially and poli&#45;<lb/>&#45;tically&#44; have spread among the masses.  But my<lb/> criticism against the work of on Leroi Beaulieu&#39;s work&#44; so<lb/> universally admired&#44; proceeds from entirely different causes<lb/> than from some flaws met in Biblical or post&#45;Biblic&#45;<lb/>&#45;al quotations&#44; or from ignorance displayed about the<lb/> rapid strides taken by &#34;American Judaism&#34;.  My strictures<lb/> have reference to sentiments expressed by the gifted au&#45;<lb/>&#45;thor.  No doubt&#44; he meant to pay us a compliment<lb/> superlatively great high by the following <sic>epigramatic</sic> sayings&#58;<lb/> &#34;The development of the mind in the Jew&#44; has outstripped<lb/> that of the body.&#34;  And again&#58; &#34;I do not know a more<lb/> intellectual race.  The Jew lives mainly by his head.&#34;<lb/>  But unintentionally&#44; I must judge&#44; the high tribute<lb/> lapses into a debasing accusation.  I apply to it&#44; in<lb/> a measure&#44; the sentence of the book of Proverbs&#44; which<lb/> runs thus&#58; &#34;He who blesses his neighbor with a loud<lb/> voice&#44; rising up early in the morning&#44; the blessing<lb/> shall be counted to him a curse&#44;&#34; meaning&#44; that his stand&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing where very many papers by hear him sound the praises of<lb/> a certain man individual will excite jealousy&#44; rankling in other hearts.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Even worse than that is the effect in the present instance&#44; because<lb/> of the conclusion which Leroi Beaulieu himself draws from<lb/> his premises.  After having extolled the Jew to the<lb/> highest pitch&#44; by reason of his intellectual vigor&#44; he<lb/> continues&#58; &#34;We reproach the Jew for not always sup&#45;<lb/>&#45;porting himself by the labor of his hand&#44; but the<lb/> Jew would often be at a loss to do so&#59; since rarely<lb/> has he muscles enough.&#34;  That is positively untrue.<lb/>  With my own eyes have I seen many a man born<lb/> in our religion endure bodily fatigue with an ease<lb/> perfectly astonishing.  And <sic>travellers</sic> who have<lb/> particularly visited Oriental countries&#44; cannot have<lb/> failed to discover among the children of our race&#44;<lb/> sinewy workmen handling the axe and the hammer<lb/> with almost Samson like facility agility.  I dislike<lb/> exceedingly this extravagant exaltation of the mind in the Jew&#44;<lb/> to the disparagement of the body&#44; for it is misleading<lb/> and mischief breeding&#59; as proved by the very supreme<lb/> laudation which our French author bestows on the us.<lb/> Jew  For&#44; he says&#58; &#34;Deprived of weapons&#44; the Jew<lb/> resorts to the devices of the weak&#59; to cunning&#44; tri&#45;<lb/>&#45;ckery and deceit.&#34;  And in another page&#44; so writes&#58;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>&#34;The Jewish conscience&#44; was never allowed full play&#59;<lb/> the meaning of the world &#39;Honor&#44;&#39; it has never had<lb/> the chance to learn.&#34;  And further on&#44; predicting<lb/> a reaction for the better&#44; he adds&#58; &#34;long suffering Israel<lb/> will witness the <sic>fulfilment</sic> of prophecies&#44; delayed<lb/> for twenty centuries by the blindness of the Scribes<lb/> and the <sic>stubborness</sic> of the Rabbis.&#34;  Now&#44; my<lb/> animadversion against a book which has won the<lb/> loud approbation of my people&#44; who regard it as a<lb/> diadem encircling their brows&#44; may be considered the<lb/> effect of pessimism&#44; or of ill&#45;nature.  It is neither&#44;<lb/> only I could not suppress deep regret on reading<lb/> the remarks which I have just quoted&#58; The blindness<lb/> of the Scribes and the <sic>stubborness</sic> of the Rabbis&#34; have<lb/> retarded our rising equally vigorous in body as in mind.<lb/>  They have stolen from our breasts a sense of honor.  Brethren.<lb/>  Those frequently maligned preceptors of Israel have<lb/> scarcely received so groundless a charge ever before.  I will<lb/> not draw attention to the lesson from the Pentateuch<lb/> and that from the prophets&#44; to prove our ances&#45;<lb/>&#45;tors finished artisans&#44; hardworking laborers&#44; men<lb/> profoundly conscientious&#44; as we read today &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;acting with fidelity&#34; concerning those engaged in repairing the Temple.<lb/>  I will not cite our Bezalel and Aholiab&#44; nor<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>nor the builders and carpenters and diggers in the<lb/> <sic>quaries</sic> in the time of King Joash&#44; for those<lb/> days were comparatively early stages in our na&#45;<lb/>&#45;tional existence.  But I will ask my brethren hearers<lb/> to read Franz Delitzsch&#39;s &#34;Jewish Artisan life.&#34;  The<lb/> author was a staunch believer in Christianity&#44; but<lb/> he was also a ripe scholar&#44; thoroughly versed in<lb/> Jewish literature and he knew well what he spoke wrote<lb/> of about.  A perusal of that work from his prolific pen&#44;<lb/> will convince the most skeptic&#44; that Jews always<lb/> appreciated the instruction of the inspired Psalmist&#44; viz&#44;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;When thou eatest of<lb/> the fruit of thy labor&#44; happy wilt thou be&#44; and it<lb/> will go well with thee&#34;.  Why&#44; the despised Rabbis&#44;<lb/> ventured so far in their hyperbolical talk language as to<lb/> declare him greater who works hard for his living&#44; greater<lb/> than one who fears the Lord &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> And again &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Honorable is<lb/> handicraft&#44; for it ennobles him who practices it.<lb/>  Nor were those Scribes and Rabbis mere theorists.  They<lb/> personally carried out the maxims which they tried to in&#45;<lb/>&#45;culcate.  They did not sit the whole day in Scientific<lb/> Academies&#44; depending on large emoluments derived from<lb/> from Congregations&#44; or communities.  They went forth to earn a living.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>For so they taught.  Moses told us to choose<lb/> life and eschew death.  To choose life signifies to go<lb/> in quest of a trade&#44; to eschew death&#44; signifies to avoid<lb/> idleness which is a canker eating on our vitals.  Were<lb/> I now to attempt to show how many of point out all the Scribes<lb/> and Rabbis&#44; whom Leroi Beaulieu styles blind and<lb/> stubborn gained their daily bread by the sweat of that despite the charge that went about with wide open eyes and careful diligence in search of their<lb/> their brows&#44; daily bread&#44; I could not exhaust the subject in a<lb/> single lecture&#59; for&#44; we meet them in every line of<lb/> workmanship&#44; from needle making to the compound&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing of rare drugs for the restoration of human health.<lb/>  Franz Delitzsch reckons a great many vast number&#44; and in an ar&#45;<lb/>&#45;ticle which I found in a Hebrew Annual&#44; an<lb/> anonymous writer&#44; by whose erudition i discovered<lb/> the renowned Rapoport&#44; mention is made of scores<lb/> of daily labours among men whom in considerateness<lb/> belittles.  As to the sense of honor&#44; which<lb/> the French author of &#34;Israel among nations&#34; denies us<lb/> by reason as a consequence of long continued persecutions&#44; I will simply<lb/> say assert with positiveness that our revered teachers recommended that we<lb/> manifest it in the highest degree.  The Talmud<lb/> which was not redacted till the fifth or sixth century<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>of the Christian era&#45;&#45;an era not very propitious<lb/> to Israel&#45;&#45;teems with sentences demanding unswerving<lb/> obedience to the strictest probity.  We read &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;It is forbidden to <sic>practise</sic> deception<lb/> &#40;in business&#41; even towards non&#45;Israelites.  &#34;Nay&#44;&#34; writes another<lb/> authority&#44; &#34;to steal from a gentile is a heavier sin&#44; for the desecration<lb/> of the name of Israel&#39;s God is added to the theft.&#34;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;  So scrupulous were our preceptors<lb/> in that respect&#44; that they exceeded the required limits.<lb/>  It is related that a certain Rabbi&#44; who was a vine<lb/> grower&#44; lamented before his friends that four hundred casks<lb/> of wine had turned our.  They&#44; in their turn His friends&#44; more candid<lb/> than complimentary&#44; remarked that perhaps it was a<lb/> Divine visitation.  At that the Rabbi appeared displeased<lb/> and asked.  &#34;Do you suspect me of wrong doing.&#34;&#63;  His friend They<lb/> answered.  &#34;We have heard that you refuse to your garden&#45;<lb/>&#45;er a share of the prunings of your plants&#44; as demanded.  Why&#44; retorted the other.  &#34;My<lb/> gardener has stolen steals the produce itself.&#34;  The friends then<lb/> quoted the Rabbinical maxim &#34;<sic>Whosever</sic> steals from a<lb/> thief&#44; is no better than a thief.&#34;  But what strong&#45;<lb/>&#45;er evidence of our scribes and Rabbis&#39; &#91;&#63;&#93; sense of honor<lb/> than the following&#63;&#58; We are told by them&#44; that when sum&#45;<lb/>&#45;moned before the bar of the highest tribunal&#44; the first question<lb/> put is this &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Hast thou dealt honestly&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Brethren.  I deem it a pity&#44; not that Leroi<lb/> Beaulieu needed a better acquaintance with<lb/> with our ceremonial laws&#44; that I overlook&#59; not that he failed<lb/> to appreciate the so called &#34;American Judaism&#34;;<lb/> but that&#44; I care not for&#44; but I deem it a pity that the spirit guiding our Scribes and Rabbis&#44;<lb/> was a star hidden which the heavy which a cloud of Christian prejudice&#44; hid from his sight.  I will ne&#45;<lb/>&#45;vertheless do give the author of &#34;Isra&#235;l Chez les nations&#34; the<lb/> credit of for good intentions&#44; for so he ends such he so concludes his now<lb/> celebrated book&#58; &#34;In writing these pages&#44; cast&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing off from my lips any word of malevolence&#59;<lb/> refusing to believe that difference in blood has<lb/> put an everlasting enmity between the progeny<lb/> of Japheth and that of Shem&#44; I bear the con&#45;<lb/>&#45;sciousness of having contributed a very small<lb/> share towards the work of peace.&#34;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
