<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF6_14</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_14_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_14_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_14_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_14_2v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 1 sheet<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For a funeral<lb/></p>
            <p>Fellow <sic>travellers</sic>&#33;  Have you measured the length of the way&#63;  What distance<lb/> separates us from the borders of eternity&#63;  &#34;I reckon not Life points to a stream of pe&#45;<lb/>&#45;rennial joys.  Into it will I plunge with courage undismayed.  Gloomy thoughts shall<lb/> not obtrude upon my worldly pursuits.&#34;  So speaks yonder youth in the buoyancy<lb/> of his spirits.  It does seem cruel to dampen the ardor ardency of that disposition ardency of nature.  To say to him<lb/> whose heart is glowing with the love of existence.  &#34;Brother&#33;  Thou art enamoured with<lb/> the present.  Yet&#44; it leads thee unawares into the embrace of death.&#34;  That task&#44;<lb/> painful though it be&#44; religion imposes on her servants.  Not that they might darken<lb/> man&#39;s path here below&#44; but that they should lighten the way&#44; which will conduct<lb/> him above.  Dear Israelites&#33;  To enjoy terrestrial blessings is a divinely<lb/> conceded right&#59; but to remember our mortality is a solemn duty.  By that<lb/> means will human inordinate cravings be effectually restrained.  by it we will be upheld<lb/> in virtue&#44; sustained in piety.  I will not strive to overreach my neighbour&#44;<lb/> when I consider that I may soon exchange a temporary habitation for an<lb/> everlasting dwelling.  I will banish from my breast that envious disposition<lb/> that stirs me up against my fellow&#45;creature.  The enmity which I<lb/> have suffered permitted to abide with me this day&#44; shall not lodge with me this night.<lb/>  I shall seek to appease him I have offended.  I will hold out the hand<lb/> of fellowship to him who did me wrong.  For ere the morning dawns&#44;<lb/> I may have quitted all which is earthly&#44; and my soul may stand at the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>bar of the Supreme Judge.  Such is the healthful lesson result derived<lb/> from the thought of our mortality.  But can you&#44; my friends&#33; tell how<lb/> many are so beneficially influenced by that reflection&#63;  Who amid the<lb/> restless longings to enlarge the fleeting present&#44; turn a look to the unending<lb/> future&#63;  Truly&#58; all around us proclaims that our days are like a shadow<lb/> that vanishes.  We do not need the authority of the preacher to be shown<lb/> that &#34;all flesh is grass and all the goodliness thereof is as the flower of the field.&#34;<lb/>  Still man deems all mortal but himself.  It is when put face to face&#44; as<lb/> it were&#44; with death&#44; that we realize the instability of the hours our fancy<lb/> imagined eternal.  When like on the present <sic>woful</sic> occasion&#44; we behold<lb/> the young and vigorous and light&#45;hearted&#44; mowed down with the rapidity<lb/> of a flash of lightning&#44; then we are made to understand that to trust<lb/> ourselves&#44; is to lean for support upon a spider&#39;s web.  You can&#44; my sympathising<lb/> hearers&#33; call to mind that countenance radiant with the smiles of comeliness&#44;<lb/> that stalwart form&#44; which seemed proof against to the sword of the Destroyer.<lb/>  Charles J. Asch but yesterday full of life&#44; lies now before us lifeless.<lb/>  Ought we to bedew his coffin with tears&#63;  Pour forth lamentations because<lb/> he who joyed in existence was cut off in his blooming years.  No&#58; our<lb/> sympathies are with you&#44; bereaved brothers and sisters&#33;  The youngest<lb/> surviving child of your sainted parents&#44; wound himself round your hearts<lb/> with the strongest ties.  Sweet were to you the tokens of his affection.  The<lb/> hope that he would long continue to enliven your home&#59; so repeatedly overspread<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>with gloom&#44; clung to your very souls.  Alas&#33;  Again have your expectations<lb/> been brought to naught.  Another void never to be filled up.  Your<lb/> circle narrowed down still more.  Children of the pious Joseph and<lb/> Clara Asch&#33;  You has the Creator chosen as the exponents of that faith<lb/> which no trial can shake.  Sanctify His name even now and the Congregation<lb/> of His people.  You stand already higher than myriads.  For you<lb/> teach those who refine and murmur under inflictions&#44; how meekly<lb/> you bear the decrees of God can be borne.  Gaze&#44; my Brethren upon the exemplars<lb/> of resignation.  I do not picture to you the philosophy of stoicism un&#45;<lb/>touched by melancholy events.  I direct your attention to tender beings<lb/> feeling most keenly the losses endured&#44; yet wincing a marvellous forti&#45;<lb/>&#45;tude&#44; because immoveable is their belief in the righteousness of the Lord.  Oh&#33; be our instructor&#44;<lb/> this day&#44; bereaved friends&#33;  We have gathered here not simply to offer condolence&#44; but<lb/> to learn from you how to suffer without impugning the justice of the<lb/> Most High&#59; to bend our bodies beneath the chastening rod&#44; and bless the hand<lb/> that strikes.  You grieve that your Charles has left the parental home&#44;<lb/> but with eyes beaming forth faith you look upward&#44; and discover him in<lb/> the celestial abode of security and find some solace.  Wes&#44; chained to the world&#44; fettered by its<lb/> seductive pleasures&#44; chafe and fret and question the wisdom&#44; that has<lb/> deprived us of hidden from our vision objects we regarded as indispensable to our happiness.<lb/>  May your submission to the Divine will&#44; <sic>dispell</sic> our misgivings&#44; re&#45;<lb/>&#45;move our <sic>harrassing</sic> doubts&#44; endow us with an abundance of spiritual strength.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>And if there be any here in our midst who have never mourned&#44; may they also profit<lb/> by the contemplation of the incident&#44; which has added to your sorrows.<lb/>  May they halt&#44; at times&#44; in the race of plentious earthly enjoyments&#44; and remembering<lb/> that death might be close at their heels&#44; moderate their cravings&#44; and<lb/> long mainly to become exalted through human goodness and truth&#44;<lb/> the two winged angels&#44; that will usher man&#39;s spirit into the prese palace<lb/> of the great King.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
