<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF2_4</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1890" source="" attested="yes">1890</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_4_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_4_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_4_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_4_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_4_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_4_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_4_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_4_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_4_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_4_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_4_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_4_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For the Sabbath Teshubah&#47;50<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;  &#34;Be not afraid dismayed because of<lb/> them&#44; lest I confound thee in their presence&#34;.<lb/>  So a heavenly voice addressed Jeremiah&#44; when in his<lb/> youth he was sent forth early in his youth to the performance of an<lb/> tremendous appalling task&#45;&#45;a people&#39;s reformation&#59; nor did he wince and waver in the<lb/> face of overwhelming difficulties&#44; and constant dis&#45; delu<lb/>&#45;appointments &#45;sions.  Now&#44; brethren&#44; if remembering that a man whose<lb/> holiness was exemplified in all his deeds could<lb/> not win back to virtue those who had deliberately<lb/> forsaken it&#59; if that the burning eloquence of a prophet<lb/> did not soften the obdurate&#44; in sinning&#44; was it not<lb/> rash too presumptuous in one like myself to believe<lb/> that I he could convert to God some who did not give<lb/> Him religion a thought&#63;  Yet&#44; in the early spring days of my<lb/> ministerial enthusiasm&#44; I fancied that I could<lb/> accomplish wonders&#59; that at my summons an<lb/> army of gallant defenders to the Torah would rise&#59; that<lb/> I would make hundreds&#44; if not thousands&#44; rally<lb/> round the standard of the ancestral traditions.<lb/>  In my eagerness to do a fulfill a sacred mission&#44; I would then ac&#45;<lb/>cost an Israelite&#44; whose summary of religious duties<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>was conventionally to enter this spot on the Day of<lb/> Atonement.  I would say to him&#58; &#34;Brother.  Your pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;sence in the house of prayer on Kippur at so distant an interval simply<lb/> shows that you have not broken altogether with<lb/> the faith in which you were born and raised reared&#44; but your<lb/> habitual absence from the Synagogue&#44; and your daily<lb/> practices prove you an inconsistent Jew.  Do not let<lb/> your conduct so belie your profession.&#34;  Well&#58; what has<lb/> time produced&#63;  Do you wish me to tell the num&#45;<lb/>&#45;ber of failures I met with in my pastoral under&#45;<lb/>&#45;takings&#63;  Why&#44; they are countless beyond computation&#44; and not surprisingly so.  Just think&#44; that<lb/> I had considered my words of so much weight as to<lb/> crash man&#39;s pride&#44; to compel sinners transgressors to confess<lb/> their shortcomings&#44; to and humbly vow a life in full<lb/> accord with the devotional outpourings of Yom Kippur.<lb/></p>
            <p>I did overrate my influence egregiously.  The zeal<lb/> which I felt for the Law that I was called upon to<lb/> teach and enforce&#44; spent itself in the vain effort<lb/> to reclaim Israelites&#44; who said in their hearts&#44;&#45;&#45;occasion&#45;<lb/>&#45;ally&#44; within my hearing&#45;&#45;as people said of Saul chosen<lb/> to guide them &#91;Hebrew&#93;  &#34;Of what use can this one be<lb/> to us&#34;.  My age did not warrant then my reproving<lb/></p> 
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>older persons&#44; high&#45;toned persons.  Still&#44; I<lb/> do not regret that spite delusions disappointments&#44; I never kept<lb/> silent&#44; even if my grey hairs have has suggested to me<lb/> less rigor in passing judgment on my neighbor&#39;s<lb/> actions&#59; more sobriety&#44; so to say&#44; in private and pu&#45;<lb/>&#45;blic admonitions.  I am not sorry that I gave my<lb/> convictions free scope&#44; because had I shrank from duties<lb/> which my office imposes out of pusillanimity&#44; the ungracious charge thrown<lb/> lately into my teeth&#44; that my ministry has after<lb/> all been rich only of deserters and renegades of every des&#45;<lb/>&#45;cription&#44; would burn like blazing fire in my soul.<lb/>  No&#58; I do not claim to be &#34;the pious pastor of a pious<lb/> congregation&#44;&#34; as a successful&#44; daring &#34;reformer&#34; taunting&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly called me in the press&#44; but neither have I skulked behind<lb/> falsehood&#44; in order not to lose carry popularity favor among with<lb/> influential transgressors.  Like Jeremiah I may say in all humility that I heeded<lb/> the caution&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93;  &#34;Be not afraid dismayed<lb/> because of them&#44; lest I confound thee in their presence&#34;<lb/>  And like the priest of Anathoth I may declare&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;I sat not in the company of mockers<lb/> and enjoyed it.&#34;  Earnestness was my official robe.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>The avaricious who denied their religion and their<lb/> people help&#44; did not receive a curtsey&#59; obeisance at my<lb/> hands.  The hypocrisy of lip worship&#44; I branded<lb/> in the name of the God of truth.  The tyranny of<lb/> such exercised at home over wives and children&#44; and<lb/> their servility <sic>practised</sic> abroad among towards the power&#45;<lb/>&#45;ful&#44; I condemned unsparingly.  I turned away<lb/> as from biting serpents when advised to resort<lb/> to worldly policy&#44; so as to gain followers.<lb/></p>
            <p>I trusted for support and deliverance on Him whose<lb/> mission I had assumed&#44; and He did not shame me<lb/> because of my hope.  If I cannot raise the<lb/> huzzahs which certain ministers spout out&#44; as if<lb/> they redeemed Judaism from extinction&#44; I may<lb/> thankfully say that not all of this venerable<lb/> body have repudiated the cause which I warmly<lb/> espoused.  Among those of the generation that I<lb/> first met&#44; and of the generation born since&#44; some<lb/> hold to the Torah as expounded from this sacred desk.<lb/>  May their fidelity continue as an exemplar&#44; du&#45;<lb/>&#45;ring many returns of this solemn period of our year&#44; in<lb/> which the sincerity of the pious&#44; may&#44; under Providence&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>bring the sinful to repentance.<lb/></p>
            <p>But it is to youths&#44; whose hearts are not tainted<lb/> with the corruption of a materialistic age&#59; to youths<lb/> who have not yet learned to hug the idols of the<lb/> imagination&#45;&#45;gold and luxury&#45;&#45;to them I eagerly<lb/> look for the vindication avenging of this congregation from<lb/> the iniquitous accusation of godlessness.  They will meet fearful obstacles.  The battles<lb/> of the passions is raging&#44; waxing <sic>hoter</sic> every day.<lb/>  To conquer&#44; youths must become heroes.  With less bra&#45;<lb/>&#45;very they also will succumb.  More ridicule faces<lb/> them&#59; to adhere to the Torah is to evince a mind<lb/> still grossing in the darkness of barbarism&#59; there the vicious call a to<lb/> refusal to enter into the pleasures of the game<lb/> of chance and of the exhilarating bowl&#44; is sheer<lb/> cowardice&#44; and then what are the <sic>quams</sic> of conscience<lb/> but childish impressions&#59; what the fear of a super&#45;<lb/>&#45;human punishment&#44; but superstition&#63;  How very<lb/> many have fallen slain in that war between<lb/> high duty and low propensities&#63;  On this Sab&#45;<lb/>&#45;bath devoted to the most serious thoughts&#44; I say<lb/> to my successors.  Friends&#44; when I and others<lb/> my coevals&#44; or of maturer years shall have passed<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>away&#44; you will be our builders.  Let the instrument<lb/> principally handled be the love of virtue&#59; your<lb/> plummet the word of God.  Understand&#58; Judaism<lb/> does not preclude the enjoyment of Divine bounty&#59;<lb/> but it warns against abuse which creates satiety&#44; palls the sense<lb/> of gratification.  Nor does it dispute a right<lb/> to the acquisition of wealth&#44; but it cautions against<lb/> the sacrificing of our noblest instincts to gold.<lb/>  It teaches to apportion our time so&#44; that our body<lb/> may receive the needed rest&#44; our spirit its elevating<lb/> agencies&#44; and all that to one sublime end&#44; to the<lb/> beautifying of our nature&#44; to fit us as worthy ci&#45;<lb/>&#45;tizens of the world&#44; and aspirants of an endless<lb/> immortality.  Youths of my people&#63;  In<lb/> the enthusiasm of your years&#44; raise your undim&#45;<lb/>&#45;med vision to God&#44; at whose hands you have<lb/> obtained the existence in which you delight&#44;<lb/> and sanctify that existence by unswerving integrity.<lb/>  With Ecclesiastes I preach&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Remember your Creator in the days of your<lb/> youth&#44; while evil days have not come&#44; nor have<lb/> the years drawn nigh&#44; when you may say&#58; &#39;We<lb/> have no pleasure in them&#63;  For all dies away&#44;<lb/> except the memory of a well spent life.  Like<lb/> the flower that opens at the genial touch of the<lb/> morning dew&#44; but withers before evening&#44; so will<lb/> strength and comeliness fade away.  But the<lb/> knowledge of having remained uncorrupt&#44; that is&#44;<lb/> of having walked with God&#44; who watches our steps&#44;<lb/> and counts our every pulsation&#44; will become a crown<lb/> of glory.  So have we been assured in the book&#44;<lb/> that presents religion as personified Wisdom &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;She will set upon your hand an<lb/> ornament of grace&#34;.  When verging towards the<lb/> grave&#44; you will behold it and become imparadised<lb/> in the contemplation.  May thus the youths of this<lb/> congregation be diademmed&#44; and in all their seniors who<lb/> believe in the redeeming power of repentance may be<lb/> fulfilled the scriptural sentence &#34;Yet that did cleave to the<lb/> Lord your God&#44; are alive every one of you this day&#34;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
