<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF10_3</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1893-01" source="" attested="yes">1893</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_3_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_3_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_3_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_3_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_3_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_3_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_3_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_3_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_3_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_3_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_3_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_3_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>A criticism &#38; a recommendation&#47;93<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Two statements in the last week&#39;s Philadelphia Jewish<lb/> organ of last week&#39; Philadelphia awakened in me opposite<lb/> feelings&#45;&#45;displeasure at the account of an reported interview<lb/> view&#44; satisfaction at the announcement of a pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;posed conference.  &#91;Inserted from front cover&#44; verso&#58;&#93; Readers of periodicals devoted ostensibly&#44; at least&#44; devoted to Jewish<lb/> interests&#44; cannot fail to have noticed the favorable opinions and conversely the un&#45;<lb/>&#45;favorable strictures passed on a book recently brought to light.<lb/>  Both views have commanded my attention&#44; but I was specially<lb/> attracted by what the Jewish organ of Philadelphia published<lb/> a short time since in connection with the subject.  However two statements in different columns of the same issue&#44; awa&#45;<lb/>&#45;kened within me different feelings&#45;&#45;displeasure at the account<lb/> of a reported interview&#59; satisfaction at the announcement of a<lb/> proposed conference &#91;end insertion&#93; I may perhaps be guilty of<lb/> self&#45;plagiarism&#44; when I say that I do not glory<lb/> over the achievements of those who have issued<lb/> from the stock of Judah&#44; but who voluntarily<lb/> became engrafted upon a foreign stem.  The<lb/> humblest son or daughter of Israel&#44; who chooses<lb/> to bear the ill will of a prejudiced world rather<lb/> than desert the ancestral fold&#59; the lowliest one of us&#44; who labors&#44; as far<lb/> as allowed&#44; both alike physically and mentally for the so&#45;<lb/>cial welfare and religious permanence of all<lb/> born in the belief of Abraham&#44; has the best highest<lb/> title to my undying gratitude.  The fasci&#45;<lb/>&#45;nation of names&#44; great in the domains of art&#44;<lb/> science&#44; commerce&#44; literature or politics&#44;&#45;&#45;that racial pride<lb/>&#45;&#45;I mean&#45;&#45;evinced everywhere among a certain class<lb/> of our brethren in modern times&#44; is not shared<lb/> by me.  Like the Psalmist I prefer to set<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>my eyes on the staunch and true&#44; though lowly unknown to fame&#44; and<lb/> I choose to seek the association of the faithful &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Now&#58; Mr Israel Zangwill&#44; author of the work called &#34;Children of<lb/> the Ghetto&#34;&#44; wields a pen&#44; that promises a fame reputation<lb/> and temporal success&#44; <sic>rivalling</sic> the public re&#45;<lb/>&#45;cognition&#44; which renowned English novelists have<lb/> attained.  But taking as a criterion the<lb/> production which that gifted son of our people&#44;<lb/> was inspired by the Philadelphia Jewish public&#45;<lb/>&#45;ation society centred in Philadelphia to give give for the edification of our young readers&#44; I am<lb/> emboldened to predict his unwillingness to make<lb/> reputation a secondary thought&#44; and the defence of the ancestral<lb/> creed and of all who still suffer for it&#44; a primary<lb/> thought consideration.  I confess it&#58; I was unduly hasty<lb/> on a former occasion&#44; when I represented the<lb/> author writer&#44; as letting a Jewish maiden&#44; who<lb/> figures conspicuously in his work&#44; flee from elope<lb/> home  with her rationalistic lover&#44; the first night<lb/> of Passover&#44; while her pious father was perform&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing the devotional exercises attending the festival.<lb/>  She did not act so unfilially then&#44; but later<lb/> on&#44; I hear her regret that the plan of that flight<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>had not been carried out.  In all truth&#44;<lb/> Were I asked to record in all truth the impression left on my<lb/> mind by the two volumes&#44; now widely perused<lb/> where the English language is spoken&#44; I would<lb/> venture to express myself thus&#58; In the first&#44;<lb/> orthodoxy is given over to made an object forced into the fillory of universal contempt&#59; in the second&#44;<lb/> heterodoxy is promised a sure gladsome reward&#59; while from<lb/> every part of the book&#44; America looms high in sight of<lb/> the changelings&#44; as the happy goal to be reached<lb/> by all&#44; who wish to enjoy the liberty of reject&#45; abjur&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing the Law and traditions.  But I did<lb/> not start with the purpose to offer an adverse criticism upon<lb/> an effort&#44; which unquestionably abounds in literary<lb/> merits.  Besides my censure would be deemed ungracious&#59;<lb/> certainly most assuredly gratuitous.  What I simply desire<lb/> to animadvert upon&#44; is a sentiment advanced by<lb/> Mr. Zangwill in the course of an interview recently<lb/> held with him in London&#45;&#45;a sentiment too generally entertained&#44; to let it pass unnoticed.  Quoting himself&#44;<lb/> the writer author said to his visitor&#58; &#34;Think of the part<lb/> which the Jew has played&#45;&#45;Moses giving the world<lb/> its morality&#44; Jesus its religion&#44; Isaiah its millennial<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>visions&#44; Spinoza its cosmic philosophy&#44; Ricardo<lb/> its political economy&#44; Karl Marx and Lassalle<lb/> its socialism&#44; Heine its loveliest poetry&#44; Mendels&#45;<lb/>&#45;sohn its most restful music&#44; Rachel its su&#45;<lb/>&#45;preme acting&#45;&#45;and then think of the stock&#45;Jew<lb/> of the American comic papers&#33;&#34;  Yes&#44; my<lb/> brethren&#44; think&#44; oh think of the pretension to a realistic present&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment of the jew by the enumeration of men&#44; who<lb/> turned their backs upon the belief that Moses<lb/> confided to the safe&#45;keeping of an everlasting<lb/> people when he so addressed our progenitors &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Hear O Israel&#44; ado&#45;<lb/>na&#239; is our God&#44; Adona&#239; is One&#34;; a belief that Isaiah<lb/> thus arose in the name of His Master thus to declared imprescriptively true.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;I am the first and I am the last&#44; and<lb/> besides Me there is no God&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;I&#44; I am the Lord&#44; and beside Me there is<lb/> no Saviour&#44;&#34; think&#44; my Brethren&#44; oh think<lb/> of blending together Benedict d&#39;Espinoza&#44; the<lb/> pantheistic Hollander&#44; whose god is nature and<lb/> nothing else naught else but Nature&#44; David Ricardo the <sic>wilful</sic> apostate<lb/> Jew of England&#44; and the German Marx and<lb/> Lassalle and Heine and Mendelssohn&#44; all<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>recreants to finally estranged from that faith by which their sires<lb/> swore&#59; think of placing those indifferentists&#44; I say&#44; in one<lb/> category with the man zealous shepherd who under Providence&#44;<lb/> created led a nation aright and gave it formulated statutes by<lb/> which it might live eternally upon earth&#44;<lb/> and or with the Prince of sacred oratory&#44; the glorious<lb/> son of Amoz&#33;  But leaving aside the man of Na&#45;<lb/>&#45;zareth&#44; aside whose mythical existence I will  care<lb/> not to discuss in a Synagogue&#44; and Rachel&#44; the French tragedienne&#44;<lb/> who&#44; at all events&#44; died and was buried in the<lb/> religion of her fathers and was buried accordingly&#44; would fain ask Mr Israel Zangwill<lb/> to point out who among the American Jews of<lb/> comic papers&#44; ought to be classed with the<lb/> inspired author of the Pentateuch&#44; or with the<lb/> Seer&#44; whose lips a Serpah purified.  I know Are the editors<lb/> of none such of the New York Puck&#44; entitled to a privilege so preeminently great&#63;  That this country&#44; toward which<lb/> the Strelizke of Mr Israel Zangwill and his Esther<lb/> Ansell and his Raphael Leon strained their looks&#44;<lb/> as towards a harbor of irreligious safety&#44; does offer every worker<lb/> of faithlessness impunity&#44; I admit&#59; but should that<lb/> be pictured to the young and unsophisticated readers in Israel&#44; as<lb/> a cause of pride&#63;  Is not that portrait&#44; calculated<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>to excite a prominent wish for imitation&#44; wherever<lb/> religious ecclesiastical authority is yet acknowledged&#44; and salaried<lb/> preachers dare not spurn the rules which they are<lb/> expected to respect and to protect&#63;  I let the un&#45;<lb/>&#45;prejudiced answer&#44; after upon mature reflection.  Enough<lb/> of a subject to me very vexatious.<lb/></p>
            <p>Now&#44; what was it that afforded my mind satis&#45;<lb/>&#45;faction among the various reports of last week&#39;s &#91;&#63;&#93; as<lb/> lately conveyed through the Jewish Exponent&#63;  It was<lb/> the proposition of planting a school in the very<lb/> midst of a locality&#44; reeking with the fumes of<lb/> religious falsities denominational unrighteous sacrifices.  That neighborhood has long<lb/> been to me a source of humiliation.  Ought I<lb/> not to leave tried my utmost to roll away the<lb/> reproach that stares us there in the face&#63;  In<lb/> that section of our city&#44; schools undisguisedly de&#45;<lb/>&#45;signed to lure our children away from the ancestral<lb/> fold&#44; increase.  Some I have stealthily visited&#44;<lb/> others I was forbid to enter&#44; but in each little ones<lb/> of a whose tender age&#44; when minds are open to early impressions&#44; are lasting&#44; are made<lb/> to sing the praises of a man&#45;god&#44; and to learn by rote<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>a history antagonistic to the tenets and doctrines<lb/> of Judaism.  What a burning shame&#33; those young<lb/> creatures&#44; born of Jewish Hebrew parents&#44; form nearly al&#45;<lb/>&#45;ways the majority of the attendants in spots&#44;<lb/> that blacken the Jewish soul.  I have met with<lb/> <sic>inseperable</sic> difficulties in procuring a list of such.<lb/>  I have stationed myself in front of those schools<lb/> of propaganda&#44; to ascertain how many issued forth<lb/> at the end of the sessions.  I have remonstrated in<lb/> no uncertain measured terms with wretched fathers and<lb/> unmotherly mothers&#44; who for the sake of a small<lb/> consideration offered us a bait&#44; deliver consign their flesh<lb/> and blood into the nets of spread by wily missionaries.<lb/>  I have begged of the directors of our United<lb/> Charities to refuse assistance to any&#44; suspected<lb/> of or charged with the heinous sin of selling<lb/> thine offspring to the Moloch of apostasy.<lb/>  But the readiest&#44; wisest and most efficacious<lb/> plan appears to be that for the carrying out consummation<lb/> of which a conferred conference was announced&#44; to so<lb/> be soon to that we may soon decide&#44; as to about the means wherewith<lb/> to attain the desired object.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>I may be met with the argument that we have<lb/> already a group of schools&#44; all centred in a build&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing&#44; vast and commodious&#44; commanding the incessant<lb/> attention and restless efforts of public spirited Jews.<lb/>  Surely&#44; I do not could never ignore that comforting fact&#44; but<lb/> our Hebrew population is spreading extending far and wide&#44; and<lb/> the environments lay our children open everywhere open to<lb/> the seductions of unscrupulous conversionists.  We<lb/> must rise equal to the demand.  Largely as some<lb/> of our religious free schools are attended&#44; more room<lb/> could be filled North and South of our city with<lb/> those of our own seed&#44; who need a healthy culture&#44;<lb/> capable of yielding such spiritual fruits as our souls long<lb/> for.  I commend the proposition of a kinder<lb/>garten&#44; close to St. Mary street&#44; to the good<lb/> and true in Israel&#44; who dwell in Philadelphia&#44;<lb/> the proposition of planting a kindergarten and a Sunday afternoon school&#44;<lb/> as close as possible to Saint Mary street.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
