<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF4_3</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_3_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_3_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_3_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_3_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_3_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_3_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_3_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_3_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_3_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_3_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_3_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_3_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_3_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_3_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_3_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_3_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Post Biblical Lecture<lb/>
                23<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Why should mortals allow a monster to lodge<lb/> in their hearts&#44; and tear out of them feelings that<lb/> beneficent nature has implanted&#63;  Why should<lb/> evny ever gain a mastery over our best th selves&#44; and<lb/> make us callous to the sufferings which we<lb/> cause&#63;  Herod was extremely wicked&#44; but<lb/> many of the atrocities which blackened his cha&#45;<lb/>&#45;racter might not have not been committed&#44; if his<lb/> sister Salome had learnt to put some check<lb/> on her envious disposition.  The exquisite<lb/> beauty of her brother&#39;s wife&#44; the high extraction<lb/> of that daughter of the Maccabees and the<lb/> great popularity she enjoyed&#44; were to Salome so many sharp<lb/> points spurring her on to deeds of destruction.<lb/></p>
            <p>Herod had left Palestine to meet Octavious<lb/> Caesar&#44; who was then in Greece&#44; in Rhodes.<lb/>  The king of the Jews presented himself attired<lb/> in magnificent garments&#44; but without bea<lb/> wearing his crown.  In well chosen language&#44;<lb/> he acknowledged his former attachment to Mark<lb/> Antony.  He said&#44; that he would deem himself<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>unworthy of the respect of Octavious&#44; if<lb/> he denied the sentiments which he had cherished<lb/> for a former his Roman benefactor&#44; but&#44;&#45;&#45;he adroitly added&#45;&#45;&#44;<lb/> the same friendship that he had shown the<lb/> triumvir&#44; now dispossessed of all power&#44; he was<lb/> ready to offer in all sincerity to the conqueror&#44;<lb/> if the latter did not disdainfully respected it.<lb/>  Octavious admired the candor and the dignified<lb/> bearing of the speaker.  He asked Herod to<lb/> put on the diadem&#44; and to be assured that Rome<lb/> would not desert him.  While this<lb/> was happening abroad&#44; the Jews at home had hoped and<lb/> prayed for a different result of their King&#39;s vo&#45;<lb/>&#45;yage.  They knew that the closer Herod drew<lb/> to the Romans&#44; the further he moved away<lb/> from the laws and practices of the people over<lb/> whom he ruled.  Alexandra&#44; the mother<lb/> of Marianne&#44; doubtless waited with anxiety for<lb/> the news that her cruel son in law had met<lb/> with adversity&#59; for&#44; she and her daughter had<lb/> been kept under guard in a fortress&#44; during<lb/> his absence.  Their keeper was a foreign<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>officer&#44; called Sohemus&#44; in whom Herod placed<lb/> implicit confidence&#44; and whom he ordered to<lb/> kill both his wife and her mother if Octavious<lb/> should turn his enemy.  He returned safe but how very striking<lb/> was the contrast between the reception which<lb/> Herod had met among heathens&#44; and that which<lb/> awaited him in his own dominions&#33;  No wel&#45;<lb/>&#45;come was extended to the man who studied<lb/> to please Romans&#44; but who had only severe mea&#45;<lb/>&#45;sures and taxation for his Hebrew subjects.<lb/></p>
            <p>But...the wife whom he desperately loved&#44; would<lb/> she not soften towards him&#44; upon hearing of the<lb/> high esteem in which he was held by Octavious<lb/> Caesar&#44; and the notabilities of all Italy&#63;<lb/>  Marianne could not resort to the arts of deception.<lb/>  Too deeply stained with innocent blood was the<lb/> past&#44; that she might erase it form memory.<lb/>  That terrible past stood there before her in the person of her<lb/> husband.  She repelled him.  Giving vent to<lb/> her pent up feelings&#44; she&#44; imprudently perhaps&#44;<lb/> reproached Herod of his crimes against her family.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>For a year&#44; domestic quarrels continued<lb/> without abating&#44; and Salome&#44; joined by her<lb/> mother Cyprus&#44; added fuel to the fire by hints<lb/> and by open accusations.  But shortly<lb/> after Herod&#44; who had gone to accompany Octavious<lb/> to Egypt returned came back&#44; the crisis was reached.<lb/>  One day that he2 sent for Marianne in1<lb/> a spirit of conciliation&#44; she came entered the room&#44; but kept<lb/> at a distance&#44; and met his proffers of affection with<lb/> indignation&#44; and a renewal of the charge of murder.<lb/>  In a paroxysm of anger&#44; he would have struck<lb/> his wife down on the spot&#44; if her matchless counte&#45;<lb/>&#45;nance did not act as a curb to his violence.<lb/>  But Salome had heard the noise.  Quickly she sent<lb/> in a cup bearer&#44; professing to offer the king a<lb/> restorative&#44; but which he was instructed to say&#44; it<lb/> was poison prepared by Marianne.  At that&#44;<lb/> Herod commanded that a faithful servant of the<lb/> queen be put to the rack.  The unfortunate man&#44; in<lb/> order to spare himself insufferable agonies&#44; falsely<lb/> stated that the hatred which the queen harbored against the<lb/> queen&#44; was due to her knowledge of the secret mission.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Which he had given Sohemus.  The latter was imme&#45;<lb/>&#45;diately executed on a horrid suspicion&#44; and Marian&#45;<lb/>&#45;ne was summoned before a tribunal&#44; obedient subservient to Herod&#44;<lb/> and sentenced to die for having attempted to take<lb/> the life of her husband.  We will draw a<lb/> veil over the last moments of the unhappy Marian&#45;<lb/>&#45;ne&#45;&#45;moments the more terrible harrowing&#44; because of the<lb/> revolting hypocrisy of her mother Alexandra&#44; who<lb/> thought of averting the same doom by abusing<lb/> her innocent virtuous daughter&#44; and calling Herod an injured<lb/> man.  In silent dignity&#44; worthy of a Mac&#45;<lb/>&#45;cabean&#44; the victims of Herod&#39;s jealousy and of<lb/> Salome&#39;s envy met her sad fate.  But no<lb/> sooner had that lovely head fallen&#44; than Herod gave<lb/> away to feelings of despair akin to madness.  They<lb/> were aggravated by a pestilence which soon broke out in Judea&#44; and which<lb/> was generally interpreted as a Divine judgment be&#45;<lb/>&#45;cause of the sins of the king.  This&#44; stung with<lb/> remorse&#44; fell dangerously ill.  He was in Samaria&#44;<lb/> when Alexandra&#44; early expecting to hear the news<lb/> of his death&#44; plotted to seize some important fortresses.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>But Herod was not so sick&#44; as to allow<lb/> a conspiring to go unpunished.  Besides&#44; his dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;position always vindictive&#44; had become more rest<lb/> relentlessly unforgiving&#44; since Marianne had been<lb/> sacrificed to it.  Alexandra paid with her life<lb/> for his indiscretion.  The next to feel the effect of<lb/> the king&#39;s displeasure was Costabarus governor of<lb/> Idumea&#44; Salome&#39;s second husband.  That bad woman&#44;<lb/> regardless of the laws of her religion and of decency&#44;<lb/> sent a her husband a bill of divorce&#44; and set her<lb/> brother against him&#44; because he had secreted the<lb/> children of an influential Pharisee&#44; opposed to the<lb/> king and his government&#59; Thus Herod plunged deeper<lb/> and deeper into a sea of blood.<lb/></p>
            <p>But a crime most offensive in the eyes of our an&#45;<lb/>&#45;cestors was Herod&#39;s his introduction of heathen games<lb/> in Jerusalem and other cities&#44; and in territories granted<lb/> him by Octavious Caesar&#44; now emperor Augustus.<lb/>  A theatre was opened in the capital&#44; and an<lb/> amphitheatre in the suburbs&#44; where athletes play&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed on the unbecoming manners of the time&#44; horse<lb/> races took place&#44; gladiators fought with wild beasts&#44;<lb/> and Roman devices&#44; and Roman trophies hung all around.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>The extravagance in dresses and in prizes for<lb/> awarded to the winners of in the games was beyond<lb/> bounds.  These innovations which pleased the<lb/> foreigners who were attracted by them to Judea&#44; became<lb/> objects of abhorrence to observant Jews.  So irresistibly<lb/> bec was the opposition felt&#44; that a plot was made<lb/> to kill the king&#44; while he witnessed the perform&#45;<lb/>&#45;ances at the theatre.  One of the conspirators turned<lb/> informer&#44; but and all were arrested.  Nothing daunted&#44;<lb/> they confessed their intention to ride the country of<lb/> a ruler who insulted the people by defying their<lb/> laws and tenets.  They bore torments with super&#45;<lb/>&#45;human vigor bravery and died under them&#44; but the<lb/> spy was found torn to pieces.  Then Herod&#44; deter&#45;<lb/>&#45;mined to discover the author of that act of ven&#45;<lb/>&#45;geance&#44; set all the engines of torture to work&#44;<lb/> and feeling realizing that he was not safe among his sub&#45;<lb/>&#45;jects&#44; surrounded himself with foreign troops.  Dread&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing a revolt&#44; he built more fortresses from which<lb/> he might hurl destruction around amist against<lb/> the revolutionists&#44; and to curry favor with his patron&#44;<lb/> he Romanized the country by changing the Hebrew<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>names of places for Latin names&#44; and paganized<lb/> the country by audaciously erecting temples in<lb/> honor of Augustus&#44; where homage was paid to the<lb/> emperor&#44; as if he were a god.  It is not sur&#45;<lb/>&#45;prising that the fame of Herod spread far<lb/> throughout the world then known&#44; and possessed<lb/> almost entirely by Rome.  But neither can we<lb/> wonder at his extreme unpopularity at in Judea.<lb/></p>
            <p>Two events&#44; however&#44; disposed an outraged nation<lb/> to relent and think well of their Idumean king.<lb/>  The first was occasioned by a national disaster.<lb/>  In the twelfth year of the reign of Herod&#44; a long<lb/> continued drought brought on famine&#44; and this<lb/> was followed<lb/> by pestilence.  Poverty Destitution and hunger<lb/> stared all in the face.  Herod who had lavished<lb/> the people&#39;s money in costly buildings for his<lb/> own aggrandizement&#44; saw with some compunction&#44; per&#45;<lb/>&#45;haps&#44; the starving and the dying.  He could not<lb/> supply food out of an exhausted treasury&#44; but he melted<lb/> his vessels of silver and gold belonging to him&#44; and bought<lb/> grain in Egypt&#44; with which he fed over fifty thousand persons.<lb/></p>  
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>The second event by which Herod conciliated&#44;<lb/> for a time at least&#44; many among the Jews&#44; was<lb/> the following.  It will be remembered that<lb/> Solomon&#39;s Temple was built with Eastern magni&#45;<lb/>&#45;ficence&#44; but it is known also that after its destruct&#45;<lb/>&#45;ion by the Babylonians those who reconstructed it&#44;<lb/> in the days of the Persian monarchs&#44; had but scanty<lb/> means at their disposal.  The Holy House arose<lb/> again&#44; but in a modest form.  No doubt&#44; from<lb/> time to time it had undergone additions and embel&#45;<lb/>&#45;lishments&#44; but never to a degree that might rival<lb/> the structure for which King David had <sic>ammassed</sic><lb/> untold sums&#44; and on which his favorite son had<lb/> bestowed immense labor.  Besides&#44; during the<lb/> <sic>seige</sic> which Jerusalem sustained at various periods&#44;<lb/> the second Temple must have suffered considerably.<lb/>  By reason of all that&#59; Herod&#44; in the eighteenth<lb/> year of his reign&#44; convened a national assembly&#44;<lb/> and in a discourse which he knew how elegantly<lb/> to deliver&#44; he disclosed his desire to raise the Temple<lb/> on its new foundations&#44; but and with a grandeur that might<lb/> surpass imagination.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>The proposition terrified his hearers.  They could<lb/> not believe in the sincerity of a man who had shocked them<lb/> with his strong leaning to the habits of polythei&#45;<lb/>&#45;stic Rome.  Might he not destroy the habitation of<lb/> the One loving God&#44; to set up on its Ruin a shrine<lb/> to Jupiter or Olympus licentious Venus&#63;  Herod saw the cause of our father&#39;s<lb/> terror consternation and promised that not a stone of the existing<lb/> Temple would be touched&#44; till all the materials for<lb/> the rearing of a larger and a richer one were<lb/> ready.  It took two years only to prepare.<lb/>  A thousand <sic>waggons</sic> were engaged to bring stone of<lb/> a <sic>marvellous</sic> size and rare timber.  Ten thousand<lb/> skilful working men labored inside of the building&#44; and<lb/> one thousand priests were purposely taught handi&#45;<lb/>&#45;craft&#44; that they alone might work in places inac&#45;<lb/>&#45;cessible to persons not belonging to the Aaromite<lb/> family.  By dint of great industry and alacrity the inte&#45;<lb/>&#45;rior of the Temple proper was finished in eighteen<lb/> months&#44; but eight years were spent in outdoor<lb/> work connected with it&#44; and not till long after Herod<lb/> had died&#44; the whole was brought to completion.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>Unworthy of the respect of Octavious&#44; if he The Talmud&#44; which&#44; as it may be easily<lb/> denied the decline supposed&#44; if not partial to the Idumean ruler&#44;<lb/> acknowledges nevertheless his good faith and<lb/> his earnestness in regard to the Temple.  It<lb/> may have been policy&#45;&#45;a wish to pacify of an<lb/> offended people&#45;&#45;it may have been a passing sense<lb/> of repentance&#44; but he certainly displayed genius<lb/> and generosity in that instance.  The architectural<lb/> beauties of the structure was <sic>unequalled</sic> by any<lb/> edifice he had raised.  Herod went in secret of the<lb/> most superb marble&#44; and fitted the sacred fane<lb/> with a sumptuousness&#44; which&#44; according to Tal&#45;<lb/>&#45;mudists&#44; had to be restrained.  Yet&#44; so immutably grave<lb/> it was&#44; that this adage remained to later ages.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Whoever has not seen the building erected by<lb/> Herod&#44; cannot boast of having seen a truly<lb/> handsome building.&#34;  The proud King<lb/> proud of his achievement chose for the day of the dedication&#44; the<lb/> anniversary of his coronation day&#44; and entered with<lb/> apparent zeal into the devotional and joyful<lb/> festivity of that memorable occasion.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
