<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF5_4</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_4_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_4_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_4_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_4_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_4_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_4_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_4_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_4_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_4_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_4_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_4_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_4_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Post&#45;Biblical<lb/>
                47<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>This Sabbath may appropriately suitably engage our attention<lb/> to a subject connected with a work accomplished in the<lb/> Judean schools&#44; to of which I have referred spoken at different<lb/> intervals in the course of my post&#45;Biblical lectures.<lb/>  We have just read an extra section of from the Pentateuch&#44; in&#45;<lb/>&#45;tended as an announcement of the ushering in of the incoming ecclesiastical<lb/> month in during which Passover is kept.  All should know<lb/> that the seasonably correct observance in its proper season of that festival&#44;<lb/> which serves as a guide to all the Jewish holidays of<lb/> the year&#44; is due to the son of Judah II&#44; of to whom<lb/> I last spoke referred in my series.  The decay of paganism and<lb/> the progress of Christianity&#44; through the conversion of<lb/> Constantine&#44; did not improve the condition of our people<lb/> in Palestine.  Heavy taxation drained national resources&#59;<lb/> a systematic oppression weakened mental activity.<lb/>  The cities where learning had flourished&#44; lost much of<lb/> their lustre.  Few&#44; deserving the name of Hebrew<lb/> sages&#44; remained in the once famous Jammia&#44; Lydda Sephoris Lydda and Tiberias&#44;<lb/> and other ancient centres of sacred learning.  Still&#44; from time immemorial a rule had been in force<lb/> which gave the country of our former glory certain pri&#45;<lb/>&#45;vileges bearing on the government of our religious affairs.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>The most important regulation was considered<lb/> that which instructed Israelites how and when to keep<lb/> the festivals unitedly.  There is no doubt that the knowledge<lb/> of calculating time had been largely acquired by the<lb/> Rabbis.  Indeed&#44; they esteemed it so highly that they<lb/> said &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Whoever can cultivate mathematics and astronomy and does<lb/> not do so&#44; neglects a study giving an insight into God&#39;s marvelous handi&#45;<lb/>work.&#34;  But that knowledge&#44; so justly valued&#44; was<lb/> jealously preserved treasured by its possessors.  It was not popularly disclosed.  So long<lb/> as the Sanhedrin&#44; or Synod&#44; could meet in any part of the Holy Land&#44;<lb/> the proclamation of each new moon&#44; and of the<lb/> character of the year&#44; whether bissextite or regular&#44;<lb/> was to emanate from that authoritative body&#44; conformably with traditional ordinances.<lb/>  Witnesses&#44; stationed on a great height&#44; having seen<lb/> the moon at its first appearance&#44; reported it to<lb/> the President of the Sanhedrin&#44; and Rosh Chodesh<lb/> was&#44; accordingly&#44; declared.  To insure a uniform<lb/> observance of the holidays&#44; messengers were expe&#45;<lb/>&#45;ditiously sent to various points&#44; to inform Israelites<lb/> on what day&#44; for instance&#44; was Nissan appointed&#44; so that<lb/> Passover might be kept together on the fifteenth thereof&#59;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>or when Elul was appointed that Jews might know<lb/> when to celebrate their New Year.  The Sanhedrin had<lb/> also a right delegated to it&#44; to add a mouth<lb/> to the year&#44; as often as it was deemed necessary&#44;<lb/> either through because of the backwardness of the season&#44; or for<lb/> other reasons of national interest.  The additional<lb/> month&#44; whenever resorted to&#44; it was made in Adar&#44;<lb/> the month preceding that in which Passover occurred.<lb/>  I will explain the object.  The Jews reckoning<lb/> their months&#45;&#45;as the most natural method&#45;&#45;by the appearance of the moon&#44; and<lb/> the latter showing itself anew in the sky every 29<lb/> days and a half and some minutes&#44; it followed that<lb/> the Jewish year&#44; or 12 moons&#44; would consist of 354<lb/> days and several hours&#44; whereas the year&#44; calculated<lb/> astronomically by the sun&#44; contains 365 days and se&#45;<lb/>&#45;veral hours.  Now&#58; the Bible&#44; speaking<lb/> of the month in which the deliverance form Egypt was<lb/> experienced&#44; calls it &#34;the month of Abib&#34;.  Thus we<lb/> read&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93;  &#34;Observe Watch the month<lb/> of Abib&#44; and celebrate the Passover&#34;.  The word Abib<lb/> means&#44; &#34;springing up&#44;&#34; and refers to the season&#44; in which<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>nature&#44;&#45;&#45;specially in warm climates like<lb/> Palestine&#44;&#45;&#45;shows signs of a revival by new pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;ductions.  But the <sic>yeilding</sic> of the soil depends<lb/> upon the sun which quickens&#44; heats it and fructifies it&#44; conse&#45;<lb/>quently Passover must be kept when the sun has<lb/> begun to ripen vegetable and fruits&#44; or at Spring.<lb/>  Moreover Besides&#44; Israelites were obliged in olden times to<lb/> bring to the altar on the second day of Passover the Omer&#44; or an<lb/> offering of flour made of the barley harvest&#44; which<lb/> was the earliest to mature in Judea.  It is<lb/> obvious clear therefore that Passover must be regulated by<lb/> the sun and not by the moon.  To do so effectually&#44;<lb/> and prevent the festival from going back to winter&#44;<lb/> and additional intercalary month was added introduced every now and<lb/> then before that festival arrived&#44; so as to equalize<lb/> the number of days between the 354 of twelve<lb/> moons and the 365 of the twelve solar months.<lb/>  When the schools of Judea were flourishing&#44; and<lb/> while a competent synod continued lasted&#44; all regulations<lb/> proceeded from thence&#59; but during the fourth century<lb/> of the Christian era&#44; about 358 the schools<lb/> were growing less in importance&#44; and the Synod greatly &#91;&#63;&#93; fast &#91;&#63;&#93; waned greatly in its power.less<lb/> </p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>It was a noble self&#45;denial which led in the Pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;sident of the Sanhedrin&#44; Hillel II&#44; to relinquish<lb/> the exclusive prerogative of regulating the new<lb/> moons and the intercalary month which was exclusively his own&#44; and fix a ca&#45;<lb/>&#45;lendar in which every Jew&#44; wherever he might dwell&#44;<lb/> should have a guide and be not forced to consult apply to<lb/> Rabbinical authority.  That wise and good<lb/> man&#45;&#45;a worthy descendant of his self&#45;sacrificing and<lb/> peace&#45;loving ancestor Hillel I&#45;&#45;&#44; foresaw that with<lb/> the spread of Christianity&#44; and the continuance of<lb/> Israelites in the Holy Land became precarious and<lb/> Judaism was exposed to severe trials.  of Yet&#44; if though the<lb/> dispersion should grow ever so world wide&#44; and the suf&#45;<lb/>ferings still more fearful&#44; the religious unity of<lb/> his people must not be broken up.  So thought<lb/> Hillel&#44; and this pious sentiment suggested the laying<lb/> down of rules for a calendar&#44; which has lasted&#44;<lb/> without a change&#44; since the year 358 of the Christ&#45; vulgar<lb/> &#45;ian era in which it was formulated.<lb/></p>
            <p>It cannot be expected that I shall go into details<lb/> upon this complicated subject.  It is constitutes a study as<lb/> deep as it is interesting&#44; and among those who have<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>enlarged thereon&#44; David Nieto that wrote in Hebrew&#44;<lb/> and in Spanish and in Italian&#44; may be profitably read consulted.  In the En&#45;<lb/>&#45;glish language&#44; a perusal of the introduction by the late Ab&#45;<lb/>&#45;raham De Sola to the Calendar&#44; which he jointly<lb/> issued with Jaques J. Lyons&#44; will prove instructive.<lb/>  But not to dismiss here the topic altogether&#44; I will<lb/> simply say that Jewish months are alternately<lb/> of 29 and 30 days.  Properly speaking&#44; they are<lb/> of 29 days and a half and some minutes each which<lb/> is the length of time occupied by the moon to go<lb/> through its various eight phases and appear anew.  But rather than cal&#45;<lb/>&#45;culate so oddly&#44; we add join two half days each every other<lb/> d month and keep then Rosh Chodesh two days&#59;<lb/> the 30th and the succeeding day.  To dispose<lb/> of the minutes in excess of the days Hillel ordered that the month of<lb/> Heshvan&#44; following our fall autumnal holidays&#44; should occasion&#45;<lb/>&#45;ally be&#44; like the preceding&#44; of 30 days&#44; instead of 29.<lb/>  About the leap years or bissextite years&#44; the Sage<lb/> arranged it so&#44; that there should be seven year<lb/>s containing thirteen lunar months&#44; in a cycle of<lb/> <sic>of</sic> nineteen years&#59; namely&#44; the 3rd&#44; the 6th&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>the 8th&#44; the 11th&#44; the 14th&#44; the 17th&#44; and<lb/> the 19th.  For other reasons needing too lengthy an explanation&#44; he ordered<lb/> that certain holidays should not fall on certain<lb/> days of the week&#44; and that Rosh Chodesh be put<lb/> off to another day&#44; when the conjunction&#44; or the<lb/> meeting of the moon and the sun&#44; takes place<lb/> at certain hours.  The astronomical<lb/> knowledge displayed in the Jewish Calendar has<lb/> won the admiration of scientists in all ages civilized countries&#44; and<lb/> its approach to perfection mathematical precision was made visibly ma&#45;<lb/>&#45;nifest in 1582&#44; when Pope Gregory XIII&#44; felt<lb/> bound to commit the monstrosity of cutting<lb/> down shortening the month of October of that year of full<lb/> ten days&#44; making it a month of 21 days&#44; because Easter&#44;<lb/> which should be regulated like the Jewish Passover&#44;<lb/> was being kept after the prescribed season.  Thus&#44;<lb/> Christianity which indirectly compelled the work of<lb/> Hillel II in the fourth century&#44; virtually accepted<lb/> that work and paid homage thereto in the Sixteenth<lb/> century.  Nemesis arose to do us justice and vindicated the wisdom of our Sages even in<lb/> the department of science.<lb/></p>
            <p>Rabbinical writings tells us scarcely anything of the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>life of our Hillel&#44; beyond giving him and his synod<lb/> the credit of having prepared a thorough Almanac.<lb/>  Some maxims embodied in treatise Aboth&#44; connected<lb/> with his name in the opinion of some Rabbis&#44; would seem to me an more likely to have emanated proceeded<lb/> form his illustrious ancestor Hillel I&#44; famous for his pithy sentences and maxims aphorisms.  But profane<lb/> history makes honorable mention of Hillel II.  The<lb/> Emperor Julian&#44; whom the Christian church calls<lb/> &#34;the apostate&#44;&#34; because he denied the divinity of its<lb/> founder&#44; but whom even his enemies confess to have<lb/> been a brave and well learned man&#44; styled our Sage<lb/> his venerable estimable friend.  In an astonishing letter&#44; full<lb/> of kind expressions to our people&#44; the grand son nephew of Constan&#45;<lb/>&#45;tine&#44; wrote &#34;I have advised my brother&#44; the venerable pa&#45;<lb/>&#45;triarch Hillel to stop the tax paid hitherto&#34;.  All know<lb/> that the reign of Julian lasted no more than two years&#44;<lb/> and that his decree for the rebuilding of Jerusalem and the Temple was<lb/> not carried out.  But though human assistance<lb/> failed us then and too often in subsequent ages&#44; the<lb/> Dweller in heaven who neither slumbers nor sleeps watch&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed over our destiny.  We have lived to this day&#44; and we Jews<lb/> are now preparing to celebrate the greatest event in our<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>annals&#44; keeping the Passover in the month<lb/> of Abib&#44; at the season ordained by our Celestial<lb/> Redeemer&#44; and annually kept with precision observed in religious Union<lb/> through the zealous labors of Hillel II&#44; the good<lb/> and the wise.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
