<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF3_5</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1897" source="" attested="yes">1897</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_5_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_5_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_5_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_5_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_5_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_5_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_5_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_5_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_5_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_5_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_5_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_5_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>97<lb/></p>
            <p>The Sabbath before Purim<lb/>
                on the Alliance<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>This congregation doubtless remembers that I had made it my duty on the Sabbath<lb/> preceding the feast of Purim&#44; I had made it my duty to soli&#45;<lb/>&#45;cit the good will of Philadelphia Jews on behalf of the &#34;Univer&#45;<lb/>&#45;sal Israelitish Alliance.&#34;  Only within late years I discon&#45;<lb/>&#45;tinued that function&#44; when for&#44; I saw that by reason of<lb/> an <sic>imprecedented</sic> influx of foreign Jews brethren&#44; the demands<lb/> on our local institutions of charity increased almost<lb/> beyond the capacity of distributing alms.  But my<lb/> sympathy with that comprehensive organization has<lb/> not waned&#44; because I ceased asking that annual gifts<lb/> be forwarded to it at this season.  How could I<lb/> ever grow indifferent to the Alliance&#44; since its edu&#45;<lb/>&#45;cational work alone extends far and wide in localities&#44;<lb/> where wholesome instruction is most chiefly essentially needed&#63;<lb/>  In the Orient especially&#44; has its influence has proved<lb/> of incalculable benefit.  Upwards of seventy<lb/> schools with an average attendance of over 16400<lb/> pupils owe to it their support.  Boys and girls re&#45;<lb/>&#45;ceive a culture calculated to render them use&#45;<lb/>&#45;ful members of the community at large.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>and besides the encouragement which it gives also to agriculture&#44;<lb/> the Alliance has recently established a Rabbinic&#45;<lb/>&#45;al Seminary at Adrianople in European Turkey.<lb/>  The aim and scope thereof are to raise Rabbis well equipped in<lb/> secular&#44; as well as theological learning&#44; so that they<lb/> may reflect honor on Judaism&#44; and draw the young<lb/> of this generation convincingly to it.  The whole<lb/>&#45;souled Jewess&#44; who <sic>worshipped</sic> with us till God<lb/> called her to a heavenly reward&#44; showed her ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;preciation of the Alliance&#44; by her liberal request.<lb/>  Any of my brothers and sisters in faith enjoying<lb/> affluence would deserve well of practical religion<lb/> by taking copying Ellen Phillips as their a model of human benefaction.  Now&#44;<lb/> as I am alluding to a friend of the Alliance&#44; I surely need not say that the premature death<lb/> of that prince of philanthropy&#45;&#45;Baron Maurice De<lb/> Hirsch&#45;&#45;cast a gloom over the Alliance Institution&#44; though I<lb/> have reasons to believe that the grievous event&#44; did not<lb/> occasion a financial injury to the organization.  The<lb/> latter&#44; however&#44; may congratulate itself on this. because<lb/> When the illustrious Adolph Cremieux passed away<lb/> from earth&#44; the presidency of the Alliance was en&#45;<lb/>&#45;trusted to Mr. S. H. Goldschmidt.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>That generous Hebrew makes his gold flow plentifully<lb/> in aid of the association entrusted committed to his watchful<lb/> care.  Not long ago&#44; he devoted one hundred and<lb/> seventy thousand francs to the erection of a new Jewish<lb/> school at Constantinople.  The attendance has since<lb/> increased to four hundred scholars students daily.  The Alliance grants it<lb/> four thousand francs annually for its current expenses.<lb/>  Now&#58; Quite superfluous it would be to recall the services<lb/> which that far&#45;reaching organization has rendered since<lb/> 1860&#44; and which is still unfortunately obliged to<lb/> render to our maligned and maltreated brethren.<lb/>  Its endeavours are not always crowned with success&#59;<lb/> but at all events&#44; by means of its monthly and semi&#45;<lb/>&#45;annual Bulletins&#44; it keeps the reading world communities acquaint&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed with the iniquities perpetrated against us.  It<lb/> was only last July that the Chief of police at Mo&#45;<lb/>&#45;&#91;&#63;&#93; in Russia&#44; subjected an old and feeble Jew&#44;<lb/> named Hirsch Pewgner to the bastinado.  Accused of<lb/> having spoken of insulting words to a high prelate of the<lb/> Greek Church&#44; the unhappy man was dragged to a place of<lb/> punishment.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>There in the open air before a crowd&#44; he was strip&#45;<lb/>&#45;ped and whipped&#45;&#45;and&#44; as&#44; in by a mistake&#44; of course&#33;&#44;<lb/> instead of fifty lashes&#44; the old Hirsch Pewgner re&#45;<lb/>ceived a hundred&#44; he died soon after having been<lb/> carried conveyed to a hospital.  The brutal Chief of police was<lb/> sentenced to six month&#39;s imprisonment&#44; but<lb/> the case was carried to a higher court and it re&#45;<lb/>&#45;mains yet unsettled.  Such is the justice executed<lb/> under the Christ&#45;like protecting wings of the<lb/> church like Greek Church.  More harrowing instances I<lb/> could cite from the Alliance Bulletins&#44; but my<lb/> object is not to sadden my hearers.  I am only prompted by a wish to<lb/> extoll deservedly praise the incessant exertion of the Alliance on be&#45;<lb/>&#45;half of Israel&#44; so that at all events the Phila branch may not determinate.  I may nevertheless be censured<lb/> by some for extending my condemnation of to a whole<lb/> Greek Church&#44; instead of limiting it my adverse criticism to that of<lb/> Russia alone.  But I simply repeat what I<lb/> positively know.  Not many years have passed<lb/> since in Corfu&#45;&#45;the seat of a Greek archbishop&#45;&#45;outrages were committed against<lb/> some of our coreligionists&#44; through the infamous charge<lb/> of ritual murder about the coming month&#44; when<lb/> the Passover bread is being prepared.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Some of our coreligionists dreading a massacre&#44;<lb/>&#45;&#45;instigated by the Greek Church&#45;&#45;took refuge to Italian cities.  Let it not be<lb/> suspected by my talk that I deprecate the attempt which<lb/> is just now being made by the Hellenes to free<lb/> themselves from Mussulman rule.  By From the instincts of my nature<lb/> and from education I learnt to hail every effort to gain liberty.<lb/>  But as a Jew&#44; guided by the light of history&#44;<lb/> I am obliged to acknowledge that while countries<lb/> which boasted of their superlative Christianity&#45;&#45;whether Catholic or Greek&#45;&#45;roast<lb/>&#45;ed our people alive&#44; or chased them away like pes&#45;<lb/>&#45;tilence&#44; Ottoman Rulers opened wide the gates of<lb/> their empire&#44; offering an asylum to the hapless<lb/> children of Abraham a dispersion.  No wonder then that<lb/> the Central Committee of the Alliance at Paris&#44; re&#45;<lb/>&#45;ceived notice that on the 7th of last January the 7th&#44; Moses Ha&#45;<lb/>&#45;levy Chief Rabbi at Constantinople&#44; addressed<lb/> the following letter to the Minister of Commerce and public works in the<lb/> name of all the Turkish Rabbinate&#58; the following lettered<lb/> &#34;Honored&#34; Sir&#44; believing that the Israelites established in Turkey<lb/> owe the imperial government a debt of gratitude and<lb/> fidelity fealty&#45;&#45;a debt which imposes the sacred duty of liberally<lb/> participating towards the increase of the amount<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>now raised for military purposes&#45;&#45;I have hastened<lb/> to direct all my colleagues and all our community&#44;<lb/> whether at Constantinople&#44; or elsewhere&#44; under<lb/> the beneficent and generous protection of our Sovereign&#44;<lb/> to join&#44; as far as it lies in their power&#44; to in carrying<lb/> out the measures adopted for obtaining the national<lb/> subscription&#34;.  With that letter the sum of fifty<lb/> thousand piasters was forwarded and likewise the promise<lb/> of a general expense from every Jewish congregation.<lb/>  Answering the letter of the Chief Rabbi&#44; the President<lb/> of the Military commission&#44; wrote&#58; Reverend Sir.<lb/>  &#34;I have the honor to acknowledge your esteemed<lb/> epistle in which the grand Rabbinate expresses<lb/> its desire to participate in the subscription to be<lb/> raised&#44; for military purposes&#44; enclosing in its name<lb/> 50&#44;000 <sic>piastres</sic>.  The generous enclosure and the<lb/> patriotic and sentiments that your eminent self and<lb/> associates evince have been reported to his Majesty<lb/> the Sultan&#44; as the most striking testimony of<lb/> the loyalty of your own self and of the Jewish people&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>The entire community of Israelites eagerly responded<lb/> to the appeal of the Turkish Rabbinate&#44; some<lb/> subscribing thousands&#59; others tens of thousand&#44; and<lb/> private individuals sent individual of their their own accord free gifts amounting<lb/> to large vast sums.  Now&#44; I fervently pray that<lb/> the political sky of Europe now surcharged at present with<lb/> murky clouds&#44; may soon brighten up.  War<lb/> is an unqualified unmitigated curse&#44; even when waged in na&#45;<lb/>&#45;tional defense&#44; whether the battle field be redeemed<lb/> with the blood of Christians or Mohommedans&#45;&#45;<lb/> and the pending arbitration treaty&#44; if passed&#44; it will become universal indeed a triumph &#38; a blessing.<lb/>  We&#44; the disciples of the prophets who foretold a<lb/> final universal peace as a summary of divine bene&#45;<lb/>&#45;dictions&#44; should always beseech the Almighty<lb/> for the bestowal of the greatest of blessings to nations<lb/> and families &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  I have cited<lb/> what is happening in the country of Islam merely to show<lb/> that we Jews appreciate the recognition of our man&#45;<lb/>&#45;hood wherever our lot was cast&#59; that we value exceedingly beyond measure<lb/> the inborn right of life&#44; liberty and the pursuit of happiness.<lb/>  And I have also spoken this morning to pronounce give offer a meed of praise to<lb/> the Universal Israelitish Alliance&#44; which has proved<lb/> a shield and a buckler&#44; a master and a guidance.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Faithful to his motto &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> viz&#44; Israel is a solidarity&#44; every member being respon&#45;<lb/>&#45;sible for the conduct of the whole people&#59; faith&#45;<lb/>ful to its significant design&#44; two hands clasped<lb/> in each other together beneath the word &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; the Alliance has tried to make us<lb/> feel that whosoever pronoun proclaims God&#39;s unity &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> is our brother in religion&#44; in history &#38; in hope.<lb/>  May it ever be so.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
