<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF16_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_1_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_1_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_1_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_1_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_1_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>13 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>60</p>
            
            <p>On the attribute of goodness<lb/>
                predicated on a passage in Kittess&#225;<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#34;And he &#40;Moses&#41; said&#58; Show me&#44; I pray Thee&#44; Thy glory&#34;....<lb/> &#34;But he &#40;the Lord&#41; said&#58; Thou canst not see my face&#44; for&#44; no man<lb/> hath seen me&#44; and lived.&#34;  The eager wish of the<lb/> Arch&#45;prophet agitates every deep&#45;thinking mind.  &#34;could<lb/> I but understand the self&#45;existence of Him who speaks to<lb/> me through reason&#44; doubts overcasting my soul&#44; would flee<lb/> before the rising of shining truths.  I would feel beatified<lb/> even while in this tenement of flesh.&#34;  But&#44; an inward<lb/> voice cries &#34;Attempt not presumptuous mortal&#44; to tear<lb/> the veil which denies thy vision an entrance into the<lb/> holy of holies.  A hidden fire would consume thy life.&#34;  No&#58;<lb/> the face visage of the Most High&#44; that is&#44; an open manifestation<lb/> of the Divine Essence can never be perceived.  yet&#44; we can<lb/> know God.  The character of the Artificer may be dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;covered by the grandeur of His work.  &#34;Thou shalt see<lb/> me from the back&#44; but my face cannot be seen&#34;.<lb/>  I have&#44; my Brethren&#44; unfolded the meaning of our text.<lb/>  To see the Creator from the rear parts of His being&#44;<lb/> is to contemplate the traces of His sovereign mind as stamped<lb/> upon His creation.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>For when it pleased the Supreme to call every<lb/> thing into existence&#44; He made His handiwork reflect<lb/> His attributes.  Thus&#44; that immense variety of objects&#44; from<lb/> the planets suspended above to the minerals embedded in<lb/> the earth&#59; that innumerable family of creatures&#44; from<lb/> the smallest animalcule to the hugest elephant&#44;<lb/> like so many links of one chain closely connected&#44; are&#44;<lb/> so to speak&#44; a mirror in which we behold the<lb/> adorable qualities coexisting with the Author of nature.<lb/>  And each object and each being creature&#44; continuing in its assigned<lb/> position&#44; and preserving the order established at the<lb/> beginning&#44; points unerringly to the Lord before whom<lb/> all bend in humble worship.  Struck by this<lb/> visible fact&#44; the shepherd King exclaimed &#34;The<lb/> heavens declare the glory of God&#44; and the firmament<lb/> telleth of his handiwork.&#34;  So likewise&#44; the writer<lb/> of the sublime poem which graces the Scriptures&#45;&#45;the<lb/> book of Job&#45;&#45;this addresses every mortal&#44; &#34;Ask the beasts<lb/> and they shall teach thee&#59; the fowls of the air&#44; and<lb/> they shall tell thee.....Who knoweth not&#44; through<lb/> them&#44; that the hand of the Lord hath wrought<lb/> all this&#63;&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Now&#44; my Brethren&#33;  That which eve objects and creatures<lb/> void of intelligence proclaim by carrying but the laws of<lb/> their Maker&#44; man&#44; whose mind was illumined with the<lb/> ray of a heavenly light must testify by fulfilling his<lb/> high destination.  Man gifted with reason and<lb/> freedom of will must direct thoughts&#44; feelings and actions<lb/> to the attaining of the noble end for which he was created.<lb/>  His worship must mainly consist in rising from nature<lb/> up to nature&#39;s God&#44; and copying the excellencies of the<lb/> Universal Father.  Then the labor he performs on<lb/> earth will clearly reveal the sublimity of the Being&#44;<lb/> whose image he bears.<lb/></p>
            <p>But among the countless attributes of the Supreme&#44; as<lb/> mirrored forth in his handiwork&#44; three sparkle with the<lb/> greatest brilliancy.  They are&#44; power&#44; wisdom and<lb/> goodness.  Power is exercised manifested on the heights and in<lb/> the depths.  In the boundless space and in the unfa&#45;<lb/>&#45;thomable sea.  Divine power displays itself in the clap<lb/> of thunder&#44; and in the all&#45;uprooting hurricane.  It is awfully<lb/> grand on the summit of snow&#45;crowned mountains&#44; and in the up&#45;<lb/>&#45;heaving ocean.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>It exhibits its grandeur in the flight of the<lb/> eagle that rides above the clouds&#44; in the roaring of the<lb/> lion that makes the forest quake.  In short&#44; it is per&#45; discern<lb/> &#45;ceptible &#45;ible in all scenes of nature&#44; terrific and majestic.<lb/></p> 
            <p>Wisdom appears to our vision under so many aspects&#44;<lb/> yet so harmonious&#44; that it may be compared likened to the various<lb/> threads of rich tapestry&#44; which&#44; skilfully interwoven&#44;<lb/> are presented as a whole&#44; charming the eye.  Wisdom<lb/> is that incomparable order by which every object and<lb/> every creature keeps its prescribed station&#44; <sic>fulfils</sic> its<lb/> task without jarring with another&#44; and nothing is<lb/> abandoned to chance.  Divine wisdom is that which<lb/> draws goodly fruits out of the seed of evil.<lb/>
                But goodness surpasses the others in radiance.  It is<lb/> reflected everywhere.  In the munificence of power&#59; in<lb/> the wonders of wisdom and most brilliantly in God&#39;s<lb/> dealing with the mortals.  That celestial attribute<lb/> it is that tempers all things in a manner adapted<lb/> to our senses and faculties.  Thus the blazing sun does<lb/> not strike us blind&#44; nor the intensity of its heat consume<lb/> our bodies.  The air does not oppress us with its weight&#44;<lb/> nor the ground&#45;stretched upon water&#45;&#45;sink beneath our steps.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>It is the same unutterable goodness which places so<lb/> many objects in nature at our disposal&#44; that they may<lb/> minister to so our wants&#44; and promote our mental enjoyment.<lb/>  Hence the Psalmists sang &#34;Thou hast made man a little<lb/> lower than angels&#44; and has crowned him with glory<lb/> and majesty.  Thou hast made him to have dominion over<lb/> the works of Thy hand.  Thou hast put all under his feet&#34;<lb/>  Aye&#58; my Brethren&#33;  We obviously behold that goodness&#44;<lb/> when we look at ourselves&#44; at our frame&#44; at our capacities&#59;<lb/> at our <sic>marvellous</sic> blending in as of the mortal and the immortal.<lb/>  Yet more palpably it is brought to view by the tender sen&#45;<lb/>&#45;timents which stir up our breasts.  When these throb<lb/> with commiseration&#44; and we are irresistibly led forth to<lb/> the help of our fellow&#45;creatures&#44; then is the goodness<lb/> of the Supreme attested by man.  We may therefore con&#45;<lb/>&#45;clude that of the three divine attributes&#44; just faintly<lb/> described&#44; the last&#45;mentioned is more accessible to us&#44;<lb/> and with less difficulty imitated.  And that is the quality<lb/> revealed to the Archprophet in the cleft of Sinai&#59; that is<lb/> what he saw&#44; and felt and heard when the glory of God passed<lb/> by him and cried forth &#34;the Lord God merciful and gracious&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Yes&#44; the power and wisdom of the Supreme&#44; exceed<lb/> ours so infinitely&#44; that the daring thought of daring reaching up to them is alone is ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;palling.  But Divine Goodness&#44; becomes us.  Divine good&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness advances toward us&#44; and wins us to herself.  Like a<lb/> tender mother it she receives the mortals in her embrace&#44; and<lb/> teaches them to copy her deeds.  And verily how could<lb/> man&#44; subject to so many infirmities both of the body<lb/> and of the mind&#59; man that grows like a flower which<lb/> soon withers&#44; that flees like a shadow&#44; and vanishes like<lb/> a dream&#44; how can he resemble in might the incorporeal<lb/> unchangeable and eternal Being&#63;  Or&#44; will<lb/> man perchance by dint of study learn to equal in know&#45;<lb/>&#45;ledge Him who foresees the end of things at their be&#45;<lb/>&#45;ginning&#63;  Will man&#44; born in ignorance&#44; and&#44; despite<lb/> all experience&#44; liable to error&#44; compare with the un&#45;<lb/>&#45;created&#44; and infallible Lord&#63;  Let me again speak in<lb/> the language of Job &#34;Where can wisdom be found&#44; and<lb/> which is the dwelling of understanding&#63;......It is hidden<lb/> from the eyes of all living...God understandeth the way<lb/> thereof&#44; and knoweth its dwelling&#45;place&#34;.<lb/>  But goodness&#44; which is not peculiar to the powerful and the<lb/> &#91;&#63;&#93;; goodness which is an emanation of the Essence of love<lb/> beseems our nature&#44; and can be engrafted thereupon.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Our highest striving to approach the<lb/> supreme Intelligence must needs fall short of the bold<lb/> attempt.  Our feelings can identify themselves with<lb/> the Creator&#44; by the performance of godlike actions.<lb/>  We may therefore consider beneficence the model given to be the most<lb/> us visible trace left by the Deity in His handwork&#44; or&#44; as<lb/> the Bible expresses it&#44; the back of God&#44; even the model given<lb/> us to copy&#44; that we may glorify the Artificer.  By<lb/> it we will draw nigh to that Being who supports<lb/> the living&#44; who is the father of the fatherless&#44; and the<lb/> consoler of the afflicted.  Our efforts to wipe away<lb/> tears of sorrow&#44; the assistance we afford the unfortunate&#44;<lb/> the comfort we bring to the needy&#44; the least act of<lb/> kindness towards our brother in distress will reflect in<lb/> us the qualities of Him who is clothed in mercy.<lb/>  And the satisfaction we derive from the deed&#59; the joy<lb/> we experience at having changed despair into hope&#44;<lb/> grief into contentment&#44; is the word of approval from<lb/> f on high.  In fact&#44; God most just&#44; as He is most<lb/> beneficent&#44; could not have left suffered so many inequalities of<lb/> fortune&#44; without a compensatory agency in the nature of the<lb/> feelings which He implanted and which He wished that might be<lb/> cultivated and brought to maturity.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Ye desolate widows&#44; ye disconsolate orphans&#44; ye all<lb/> that tremble because of the morrow pregnant with evils&#44;<lb/> contemplate the work of the Lord.  He has command&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed goodness to come to your rescue.  That queen<lb/> of virtue casts her shield around your lives.  They<lb/> will not perish.  Hospitals&#44; foster&#45;homes&#44; asso&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciations of charity are the bucklers with which she<lb/> hastens to your protection&#44; when assailed by cruel want&#44;<lb/> and soul&#45;tearing bereavements.  And blessed will<lb/> they be who set a throne to that queen in their inmost<lb/> hearts.  Blessed be they who&#44; contemplating the<lb/> traces of the Most High&#44; imitate the Universal Parent&#44;<lb/> considering His children&#44; the poor&#44; with an eye brimfull of<lb/> compassion&#44; becoming thus the ministers of Providence&#44;<lb/> the representative of His most adorable quality.<lb/>  They attest the glory of our Father that is in heaven&#44; re&#45;<lb/>&#45;cognizing in their feelings His paternal will&#44; which<lb/> bids them to be only the <sic>depositaries</sic> of the means<lb/> possessed&#59; as David was wont to say.  &#34;From thy hand<lb/> all things proceed&#44; and of that which Thou givest&#44; we make<lb/> a return unto Thee&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>But those who are deaf to the voice that speaks<lb/> within us&#44; outrage their own nature&#44; and offend its<lb/> merciful Author.  &#34;Woe unto them that live at ease&#44;<lb/> that lie upon beds of down&#44; and stretch themselves upon<lb/> their couch&#44; that eat the fattest lambs of the flock<lb/> and the choicest calves of the herd&#44; that sing at the<lb/> sound of musical instruments&#44; that drink wine in<lb/> <sic>barols</sic>&#44; perfume themselves with precious ointments&#44; but<lb/> are not grieved for the privations which others endure.&#34;  So<lb/> exclaims the inspired Amos.<lb/></p>
            <p>Dear Brethren who are keenly alive to a sense of pity&#33;<lb/>  At this season when the earnings of the laborers are smaller<lb/> and their necessities greater&#44; now&#44; that indigence has<lb/> entered many a home of the industrious&#59; at the present<lb/> time that the unusual severity of the winter entails<lb/> a large expenditure&#44; and objects indispensable<lb/> to a daily subsistence have enhanced in price&#44; let<lb/> us practice the quality shown to the archprophet<lb/> at Sinai&#44; as that which sparkles with the most<lb/> lustre&#44; and which so well becomes the mortals.<lb/>  We must strengthen those organizations that care for<lb/> the present and make wise provisions for the future.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>They deserve every encouragement.  Our united generosity<lb/> should enrich their treasures.  But let us remember<lb/> that corporate measures cannot always reach indi&#45;<lb/>&#45;vidual sufferings.  In a vast field&#44; small corners<lb/> may have still been left unwatered&#59; so likewise it does<lb/> not infrequently happen that some of the most de&#45;<lb/>&#45;serving among the needy thirst after human sympathy and still pine in solitude and misery.<lb/>  They per prefer destitution to a divulging of their<lb/> unhappy condition.  Brought suddenly low by a<lb/> whim of fortune&#44; they disdain to be recoil at the idea of being blended with<lb/> mendicants.  Those ought we to go in search of&#44;<lb/> and when found&#44; screen from the same which publicity<lb/> will bring.  Charitable bodies are excellent&#44; but<lb/> the pressure of existing circumstances makes it incumbent<lb/> upon every man to supplement their endeavours by<lb/> personal work.  If I have ever deemed my&#45;<lb/>&#45;self endowed with a high privilege&#44; it was at the<lb/> thought that the religious influence which my office<lb/> accords has enabled me occasionally to spare the modest<lb/> poor a blush.  For&#44; they who will not consent shrink<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>to from standing at the gates of the rich&#44; nor crossing<lb/> the <sic>threshhold</sic> of the dwelling of alms&#44; will disclose<lb/> the troubles that <sic>harrass</sic> their minds to the servant of<lb/> God&#39;s holy house&#44; and the receive through his agency aid<lb/> and solace.<lb/></p>
            <p>Generous hearts in which beneficence has her throne&#33;<lb/>  Respond to the cry of indigence&#44; when whisperingly appealed<lb/> to by the trust&#45;worthy.  And as you will never grow<lb/> weary to give&#44; so will he whose brightest attribute you<lb/> copy never cease to shower down copious blessings&#44; to<lb/> irrigate and satisfy your souls.  See&#33; man&#39;s power<lb/> and man&#39;s wisdom in their loftiest flights will not bring<lb/> now nigh to the invisible Lord&#44; but acts similar to<lb/> those of the Being who proclaimed Himself merciful<lb/> and compassionate&#44; will weave silvery chords binding<lb/> you with the Supreme&#44; and after your mission shall<lb/> have been fulfilled on earth&#44; they will draw you up&#45;<lb/>&#45;wards in blissful association with the Essence of Goodness.<lb/></p>
            <p>And you&#44; my venerable brother &#40;Elias Mayer&#41; who&#44;<lb/> I have reasons to believe&#44; have exemplified through a checkered<lb/> life the Divine attribute of goodness&#59; you who have illustrated<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p>religion by practical benevolence&#44; receive the assurance of the<lb/> respect which your age and character rightly claim.<lb/>  The congregation to which you became in late years affiliated&#44;<lb/> have regarded with satisfaction the preference you gave to<lb/> their ancient and historic worship.  And now that you<lb/> have been pleased to add another token of attachment<lb/> thereto&#44; they express their thanks through their servant.<lb/>  The scroll of the Law you have presented has been enshrined<lb/> in the holy ark&#44; and as our reading from its pages this<lb/> day&#44; was meant to signify a due appreciation of the gift&#44;<lb/> so will its countenance there&#44; be a constant reminder of<lb/> the piety of the donor.  May your reward be great.<lb/>  May it be the realization of the sentence of Solomon that he<lb/> follows righteousness and mercy&#44; will obtain long&#45;life&#44; kindness<lb/> and honor.  And let me pray the Lord who upheld your steps<lb/> in the steep ascent of this earthly existence&#44; to accompany you<lb/> in its declivity&#44; till you reach the abode&#44; where pleasures<lb/> everlasting await you&#44; among the saints who have per&#45;<lb/>&#45;formed the command of God and copied His Divine<lb/> attributes of goodness.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
