<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF3_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1891-01" source="" attested="yes">January 1891</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff3_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff3_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff3_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff3_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff3_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff3_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff3_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff3_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff3_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff3_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff3_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff3_1_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff3_1_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff3_1_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff3_1_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff3_1_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 8 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Ladies and Gentlemen  It is not improbable that among my hearers&#44;<lb/> there may be found persons who have heard of the Rabbi&#44; on whose<lb/> life&#45;work I intend briefly to speak.  Still&#44; I presume that<lb/> to Israelites who hail from Northern Europe&#44; he who will form<lb/> the subject of my remarks is not very generally known.<lb/>  For notwithstanding that he was a prolific writer&#44; yet his<lb/> productions&#44; with perhaps a single exception&#44; did not spread<lb/> among our brethren whose language is Teutonic or Slavonic in<lb/> its origin.  His literary labors are household words mostly<lb/> to scholars among our fellow&#45;believers who live in Moham&#45;<lb/>&#45;medan countries&#44; and in a measure also to Italian Jews.<lb/>  Not because&#44; like our distinguished philosophers and comment&#45;<lb/>&#45;ators of the middle ages&#44; he used the Arabic in his compositions&#44;<lb/> or because he was familiar with the idioms of the Tuscans&#44;<lb/> in whose midst he finally took up his abode&#45;&#45;for<lb/> Hebrew alone he employed in whatever issued from his pen&#45;&#45;&#44;<lb/> but because the tenor of his writings was pietistic&#44; and Russia&#44;<lb/> Poland&#44; Austria&#44; Roumenia&#44; abounded with authors of the<lb/> same mental disposition&#44; mainly bent on the dissemination<lb/> of books ascetic or casuistic in their character.<lb/></p>
            <p>I scarcely need say that after the close of that splendid<lb/> era&#44; created in Spain and Portugal by our own celebrities&#44;<lb/> the Jewish world saw but few who occupied themselves<lb/> in the history&#59; the literature&#59; the inner spirit of our religion.<lb/>  The majority of our Rabbis devoted their attention to the&#44;<lb/> external practices of our faith&#44; and to enforce the strict<lb/> performance thereof&#44; were all their efforts. &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Hyam Joseph David Azula&#239; stands foremost among such<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Yet it would be unjust to assert that his merit<lb/> consists in having exclusively brought out of the press<lb/> volumes exhorting to acts of devotion.  For his travels had<lb/> broadened the regions of his intellect&#44; and he could and did<lb/> direct his ripe thoughts to varied and interesting subjects.<lb/></p>
            <p>Born in 1725 of very pious parents&#44; whose progeni&#45;<lb/>&#45;tors had emigrated from Fez of Morocco to Jerusalem&#44; he<lb/> had hardly reached his twentieth year&#44; when his vast<lb/> erudition through the whole range of Talmudical learning&#44;<lb/> won for him the honorable position of President of the<lb/> college in the city of Zion.  In that early stage of his life&#44;<lb/> he showed clear signs of a searching mind by a pamphlet<lb/> in which he demonstrated that many a bibliographer blund&#45;<lb/>&#45;dered in his statements&#44; by reason of a culpable want of<lb/> historical accuracy.  That youthful production&#44; which<lb/> he named E&#39;lim Dabar&#44; is alluded to in other writings sub&#45;<lb/>&#45;sequently given to the press&#44; but it is not now extant.<lb/>  Azula&#239; may not have found the opportunity of transmit&#45;<lb/>&#45;ting it to posterity&#44; for it was only in later times when<lb/> he settled abroad&#44; that every facility was afforded him to<lb/> issue many editions of his productions.<lb/></p>
            <p>In his days the custom of sending a messenger from the<lb/> Holy Land to collect Congregational offerings in aid of the<lb/> poor in Jerusalem was prevalent.  At twenty seven years<lb/> of his age&#44; he was commissioned to travel to Italy&#44; France&#44;<lb/> Germany and Holland in quest of assistance for his<lb/> townsmen in a state of destitution.  That circumstance<lb/> afforded him the occasion of coming in contact with<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>erudite persons and of vising rare libraries.  It is related<lb/> that while in Paris&#44; queen Marie Antoinette&#44; the ill&#45;fated con&#45;<lb/>&#45;sort of Louis XVI&#44; saw him pass.  His handsome appear&#45;<lb/>&#45;ance&#44; heightened by a fine Oriental costume&#44; attracted<lb/> her attention.  She inquired about his nationality and the<lb/> object of his temporary sojourn in the capital of France.<lb/>  Gratified at what was told her&#44; she sent for Rabbi Azula&#239;&#44;<lb/> requested him to bless her child&#45;&#45;the Dauphin&#45;&#45;and gave<lb/> permission that he might remain two hours a day for a<lb/> certain period at the Royal library.  There he met Rabbi<lb/> Israel De Valabronne&#44; librarian and interpreter &#40;Dragoman&#41;<lb/> to the King of France.  The learned man showed our Rabbi<lb/> about twenty five thousand manuscripts in a variety of<lb/> languages&#44; and among them five thousand by Jewish authors.<lb/></p>
            <p>Proceeding to Germany&#44; where he received a hearty wel&#45;<lb/>&#45;come as due to his personal character and vast knowledge&#44;<lb/> he was made specially welcome at the house of Ezekiel<lb/> Landau&#45;&#45;the famous author of Nodang BiYudah&#44;&#45;&#45;on<lb/> Rabbinical queries and responses.  The wife of the celebrated<lb/> host&#44; belonged to that class of women&#44; not at all<lb/> rare in the last century&#44; but almost extinct in ours.  She<lb/> possessed more than an ordinary acquaintance with our<lb/> literature&#44; so that when Azula&#239; put a question to Landau&#44;<lb/> she gave its solution in German to her husband&#44; who repeated<lb/> it to his guest.  The latter&#44; who had understood his host&#45;<lb/>&#45;ess&#44; promptly said&#58; &#34;A woman has conquered.&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>  The first mission of the Palestinian Rabbi to Europe<lb/> proved quite successful&#44; and the messenger returned<lb/> home enriched with the experience of men&#44; of books&#44; and<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>languages.  His ascetic nature led him to change his<lb/> habitation from Jerusalem to Hebron.  To that city had migrated<lb/> two Israelites of high repute&#45;&#45;Aaron Alfanderi and Hyam<lb/> Cohen&#44; who had sought to rest their bones where the pa&#45;<lb/>&#45;triarchs had found a grave.  With those two he plunged<lb/> into Kabbalistical depths&#44; which he had already sound&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed before.  All that have read his multifarious works&#44;<lb/> will at once discover that each of them is tinctured with<lb/> notions drawn from the Zohar and subsequent books of<lb/> the Luria&#44; the Cordovero and the Vital schools.<lb/></p>
            <p>To the praise of Azula&#239;&#44; it must be said that although<lb/> thoroughly embued with the idea that Judaism rests<lb/> on Kabbalistical foundations&#44; and that it must fall<lb/> when those are removed&#44; nevertheless he did not coerce<lb/> others into his views&#59; he tried to win them over to his<lb/> side by persuasive gentleness.  Witness&#44; his dispassionate<lb/> remarks against Jacob Amdea&#44; who assailed the citadel<lb/> of Zoharism&#44; following in the wake of Leon De Modena<lb/> in his Ari Nohem and other anti&#45;Kabbalists.  Azula&#239;<lb/> was a man of deep rooted convictions&#44; and his contact with<lb/> many who did not share his views failed to influence<lb/> his conduct.<lb/></p>
            <p>In 1770&#44; the Hebron Congregations&#44; relying on his ability<lb/> to stir up among our brethren everywhere a wish to<lb/> hasten to the help of multitudes who flocked to that<lb/> city&#44; in what was considered then a holy pilgrimage&#44;<lb/> and to encourage their spending their remaining years<lb/> in studies and prayers&#44; begged that he would travel<lb/> through Turkey&#44; go to Asia Minor&#44; visit the Grecian<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Isles&#44; stop at London&#44; and collect the free will offerings<lb/> of Israelites&#44; who had at heart the welfare of Zion.  In<lb/> the metropolis of Great Britain he experienced the satis&#45;<lb/>&#45;faction of meeting one of his teachers&#44; Rabbi Jacob Kimchi&#44;<lb/> a scion of the celebrated family that enriched our literature<lb/> with Biblical expositions&#44; Grammars and Lexicons and poetical<lb/> effusions.  How long Azula&#239; remained away from<lb/> Western Asia it is uncertain&#44; but having returned there&#44;<lb/> he appeared to yearn for Europe&#44; and notably for an<lb/> Italian city&#44; which had shown him exceptional reverence.<lb/>  Having lost a married daughter&#44; and having sent a son<lb/> of his to Poland&#44; where Talmudism flourished&#44; he settled<lb/> himself at Leghorn in Tuscan Italy&#44; and from thence he<lb/> habitually forwarded the annual contributions obtained in<lb/> aid of the Holy Land.<lb/></p>
            <p>At Leghorn he was afforded all facilities for publishing<lb/> his works at the expense of pious Jews who abounded<lb/> there at the time.  Particularly a certain Jacob Pereyra<lb/> de Leon&#44; made the Rabbi welcome in his house&#44; supplying<lb/> all his wants&#44; providing the prescribed number with whom<lb/> daily to offer prayers&#44; and sparing no means to render<lb/> his stay pleasant and promotive of his literary interests.<lb/>  To that Maecenas Azula&#239; dedicated one of his books on rules<lb/> of piety called Mor&#233; Be Ezbang.  Twenty five years<lb/> he passed away tranquilly in the favorite occupation of<lb/> writing&#44; correcting proofs&#44; answering religious questions con&#45;<lb/>&#45;cerning which he was consulted&#44; and carrying on a far&#45;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>extended correspondence with the learned of his time.<lb/></p>
            <p>G. B. De Rossi&#44; the librarian of the Duchess of Parma&#44; author<lb/> of the Dictionary of Hebrew writers&#44; alluding to an ancestor of<lb/> the subject of my remarks&#44; said&#58; &#34;The grand son is now at<lb/> Leghorn enjoying a far advanced age&#44; and shedding lustre on<lb/> his lineage by his productions&#44; notably his biographies&#44; en&#45;<lb/>&#45;titled Shem Ha&#45;Geodolim&#34;.<lb/></p>
            <p>Rabbi Azula&#239; who held divine services with the requisite num&#45;<lb/>&#45;ber in his dwelling every day of the year&#44; did not attend<lb/> public worship elsewhere&#44; but the tradition at Leghorn is<lb/> that the single exception was on the penitential Sabbath.<lb/>  Then he preached in the largest Synagogue&#44; built by the descend&#45;<lb/>&#45;ants of the refugees of Spain and Portugal.  An immense<lb/> concourse of people&#44; anxious to hear his pulpit teachings<lb/> and admonitions&#44; divided into two rows accompanied him<lb/> from the door of his house to that of the synagogue.  He<lb/> walked in the middle&#44; and his venerable looks attracted uni&#45;<lb/>&#45;versal attention.  More than four score years<lb/> had he lived&#44; when on the 11th day of Adar 5566&#45;1806&#45;<lb/> he departed from earht&#44; receiving the encomiums of the learned<lb/> from near and from far.  Joseph David Zuidheim&#44; noted<lb/> for his writings and for his having participated in the ce&#45;<lb/>&#45;lebrated Sanhedrin convened by Napoleon Bonaparte&#44; pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;nounced a eulogy form the text &#34;Out of Zion proceeds instruc&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion&#44; and the word of the Lord from Jerusalem&#44;&#34; in refe&#45;<lb/>&#45;rence to the birth place of the distinguished deceased and to<lb/> his immense erudition.<lb/></p>
            <p>Candor compels that I shall say how among fifty<lb/> books of larger or smaller size&#44; which issued from the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>pen of our author&#44; only that which he divided into<lb/> three parts&#44; and called Shem Ha&#45;Gedolim possesses much<lb/> interest&#59; the subjects of all the others have a limited value&#44;<lb/> and the style lacks that simplicity which affords pleasure<lb/> to the reader and enchains his attention.  The morality of<lb/> Azula&#239;&#39;s teaching is unexceptionable&#59; the sincerity of his<lb/> belief undoubted&#44; but that vein of Kabbalism running<lb/> through all&#44; and that strained diction which requires study<lb/> to comprehend&#44; detract greatly from the merit of the compositions.<lb/>  His manner of writing has found apologists among persons<lb/> who are fond of double entendre&#44; and Jeu de mots&#44; to which<lb/> the Hebrew language lends itself greatly&#44; but pursuits and<lb/> the lovers of plain and clear expressions&#44; cannot but regret<lb/> that confusion and obscurity which characterize the general<lb/> compositions of Azula&#239;.  Still&#44; a man who <sic>weilded</sic> a pen<lb/> surpassingly flowing&#59; a man who did not subscribe<lb/> to the ideas running through the Palestenian Rabbi&#39;s works&#44;<lb/> wrote a poem to his honor&#44; because he held in high esti&#45;<lb/>&#45;mation the character and scholarship of the deceased&#44; and<lb/> recognized his sterling piety and goodness.  Isaac Samuel<lb/> Reggi of Gorizia inserted in 1825 in an Annual pu&#45;<lb/>&#45;blished at Vienna&#44; and termed Bickur&#232; A&#39;ittim&#44; a poem<lb/> which begins thus&#58; &#34;Soul&#44; temple of all good&#44; crown completion of<lb/> beauty sublimity&#44; that since form the vale of grief thou hast departed&#44;<lb/> among archangels thy throne has been uplifted&#44; a celestial<lb/> robe&#44; a crown of joy enhance thy splendid beauty.&#34;<lb/>  And in this strain the poet proceeds to depict the loos<lb/> which Judaism met by the demise of one so profoundly<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>devout and widely learned.<lb/></p>
            <p>I have said that the moral imparting of Azula&#239; was fault&#45;<lb/>&#45;less and I cannot close my lecture more fittingly than by<lb/> offering a specimen of the high standard of his tuition.<lb/>  In one of his multifarious works&#44; called Berith Olam&#44; which<lb/> is a running comment to Sepher Ha&#45;Chassidim by Rabbi<lb/> Judah son of Samuel who lived in France early in the<lb/> thirteenth century&#44; Azula&#239; writes&#58; &#34;Let man acquire the<lb/> habit of refusing to accept money whenever the receiving<lb/> of it may possibly eventuate in the profanation of<lb/> the name of God.  It is unnecessary to say that such<lb/> a course must be adopted&#44; when so unholy a result<lb/> will surely follow.  Thus&#44; by way of illustration&#44; people<lb/> will censure teachers of religion&#44; who show by their action<lb/> that gain is their principal object.  And the contempt<lb/> felt for the greedy and the covetous&#44; will be experienced<lb/> for the faith they represent&#44; and occasion a disobedience<lb/> of the precepts.  Let him therefore who fears the Lord&#44;<lb/> be extremely watchful&#44; so as to remove a shadow<lb/> of suspicion against his character&#44; which might<lb/> reflect dishonor on our belief&#59; let him put his full<lb/> trust in the Lord and confide in His Providence.&#34;<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <p>&#40;This lecture&#44; delivered before &#34;the Hebrew Literature Society&#34; in Jan.<lb/> 1891&#44; was greatly enlarged upon and somewhat <sic>embelished</sic> in diction&#44; during<lb/> its delivery&#41;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
