<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF2_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1891" source="" attested="yes">1891</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_2_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. Fifth St.&#44;<lb/>
                <emph rend="italics">Philadelphia&#44;</emph>		<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>For the Penitential Sabbath<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Brethren.<lb/></p>
            <p>The book called in Hebrew Aboth&#44; and styled in English<lb/> with striking fitness &#34;the ethics of the fathers&#44;&#34; contains a sentence&#44;<lb/> which is our duty to keep in mind always&#44; but most es&#45;<lb/>&#45;pecially at this solemn period of our year&#44; devoted to a<lb/> reflection of our past conduct&#44; ans to wholesome prepa&#45;<lb/>&#45;rations for our future course&#44; while destined to dwell upon<lb/> earth.  For to that end were the &#91;Hebrew&#93; the ten penitential days instituted.  The sentence to which I have reference reads so in the original&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> meaning&#44; thou wilt be compelled to stand for judgment<lb/> before the Supreme King of Kings&#44; the Almighty&#44;&#45;&#45;a<lb/> Rabbinical saying which agrees precisely with the closing verse<lb/> of the book of Ecclesiastes &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; that is&#59; every deed God will bring<lb/> before His tribunal with every thing hidden&#44; whether good<lb/> or evil bad.  On Rosh Hashanah I cited the<lb/> parting caution of the archprophet&#44; with a view<lb/> to prove that the government of the world is un&#45;<lb/>&#45;der the immediate supervision of a Sovereign Lord&#44;<lb/> both in its entirety&#44; viz&#44; according to nationalities&#44; and<lb/> in its component parts&#44; or according to individuals.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>I designed to show that the idea of a ubiquitous<lb/> Providence is vitally essential for to the permanence<lb/> of society&#44; and that if the belief of our accounta&#45;<lb/>&#45;bility to an Omnipotent Ruler were banished&#44; the<lb/> widest entrance would be opened for all inequities to rush on.<lb/>  Lying and defrauding&#44; unchastity and brutality<lb/> would stalk abroad unchecked and unabashed.  The<lb/> doctrine of our personal responsibility is then not only a great<lb/> truth founded upon the strongest basis&#45;&#45;Holy Writ&#45;&#45;<lb/>but it is the mightiest safeguard against a universal corruption&#59; it is the healthiest moral restraint upon all<lb/> beings endowed with an immortal soul.  And as<lb/> the requital of our deeds&#45;&#45;though surely given also<lb/> here below also in a vast measure&#45;&#45;is not so visibly perceptible by others strangers&#44;<lb/> and it is likely to escape the attention notice of our<lb/> own selves who are its recipients&#44; therefore the<lb/> Sages directed our minds attention principally to the imperishableness<lb/> of the faculties stirring within us&#59; and to They emphasized the inevi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tableness of their our being called to answer for the<lb/> use made thereof our powers in this world&#44; which they style &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#45;&#45;our sphere of action&#44; when summoned to<lb/> a state&#44; which they emphatically significantly term &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> the world of retribution.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Strange Curious as it may seem the train of my thoughts<lb/> while mentally pensively following the serious subject of<lb/> our glory or our shame hereafter&#45;&#45;a subject which<lb/> the penitential days intervening between Rosh Hashanah and Yom Kippur are calculated to suggest&#45;&#45;brought<lb/> back to my mind a Biblical narrative recorded in the<lb/> second book of Samuel.  You may remember it.<lb/>  King David&#44; grateful for the protection asylum&#44; which some of his<lb/> relatives had obtained found in the country of the Ammoni&#45;<lb/>&#45;tes&#44; when he himself was fleeing away&#44; without<lb/> a home&#44; form the implacable anger enmity of Saul&#44; sent<lb/> ambassadors to condole with the reigning Sovereign<lb/> for the demise of his royal parents.  But the message of<lb/> kindness was interpreted at the foreign court&#44; as a pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;text to spy the land&#44; and ascertain where it could best<lb/> be attacked.  Mischievously influenced by his ministers&#44;<lb/> the King of the Ammonites ordered that the Hebrew envoys<lb/> should have their beards shaved on one side of their faces&#44;<lb/> their garments cut short in a most ludicrous manner&#44;<lb/> and be thus exposed to the Jeers and biting jests of all beholders.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>That those men felt overwhelmed with confusion&#44;<lb/> we learn from the circumstance that they refused<lb/> to go back to their own private firesides&#44; and much less to<lb/> appear at the King&#39;s palace &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> says the text&#58; &#34;the men were greatly ashamed&#34; I fancy<lb/> that they would almost have preferred death to their entering<lb/> the capital in that wretched flight&#45;&#45;they&#44; who doubtless<lb/> were notable persons.  But what were the feelings<lb/> which David&#39;s chosen ambassadors experienced at the thought<lb/> of being made the butt of ridicule&#44; in comparison with<lb/> the confusion which will seize us&#45;&#45;if while in a state of defilement pollution<lb/> we were irresistibly forced to stand should be summoned before the Supreme King<lb/> of Kings the Almighty Jug Judge&#59; if irresistibly forced<lb/> to answer in our actual condition to account for a mission received as creatures gifted<lb/> with intellectual powers and as appointed witnesses of God&#39;s<lb/> Unity&#63;  For&#44; wrote the Mishnic Sage &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> In spite of our own will&#44; we shall have to show how<lb/> we employed did apply our faculties.  We Our characters will be placed<lb/> then in a right light&#44; revealing our characters in disclosing their<lb/> real aspect.  The spots which we succeeded in conceal&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing before from human eyes&#44; will be laid bare&#44; and we shall<lb/> stand convicted of evil foul deeds often committed.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Have I lived led a double life&#63;  The sins of my<lb/> hypocrisy will pass in review before my spiritual<lb/> vision &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> say the Talmudists&#58; At the bar of the highest tri&#45;<lb/>&#45;bunal there will be a finger will unerringly pointing<lb/> out our wrong doings and the very time that we be&#45;<lb/>&#45;came guilty thereof.  &#34;On such a day then&#44; who wast<lb/> considered gentle&#44; gavest vent to thy passions&#44; and<lb/> those &#91;&#63;&#93; those whom thou shouldst most care for suffered<lb/> poignant grief.  At the same such a season<lb/> thou madest public pretense of piety&#44; with a fixed<lb/> determination nevertheless to fall back upon thy evil<lb/> ways.  At the same hour when thou hadst a wish<lb/> to appear liberal&#44; thou wouldst begrudge thy nearest<lb/> ones the satisfaction of their very wants.&#34;  And to all<lb/> of that we shall inevitably compulsorily reply &#34;Aye&#44; it is so&#34;.<lb/>  &#34;I am not the man that the world took me for.<lb/>  I did not gain my wealth by the strictest pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;bity.  I have craved for indulgence in wanton plea&#45;<lb/>&#45;sures and unjewish practices.  I am not innocent<lb/> of having envied men in high places&#44; even though to<lb/> reach up to them I might have had to mount up on heaps of corruption.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>And those humiliating acknowledgments we shall be con&#45;<lb/>&#45;strained to make within hearing of the good and those<lb/> who preceded us in the world of spirits&#59; men and<lb/> women whose to enjoy whose favorable opinion you so we<lb/> would have considered deemed a price to enjoy.  Now&#44;<lb/> fellow&#45;Israelites&#44; you may recall the scene at the death<lb/> bed of Rabbi Johanan Ben Zacka&#239;.  his disciples had<lb/> come to ask for the great teacher&#39;s parting blessing.<lb/>  He said&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93;.<lb/>  &#34;May your fear of God be like equal your fear of man.&#34;  Amazed&#44;<lb/> the pupils inquired &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;so far and no more&#63;&#34;  But the illustrious Sage<lb/> understood human nature.  We are may be held back from the down&#45;<lb/>&#45;ward course of transgressions by the thought that human<lb/> eyes are upon us&#44; but not are we we are not so deterred by the belief<lb/> that God is all seeing&#44; and in proportion as the persons<lb/> whose looks are rivetted on watch us <sic>excell</sic> in harming or virtue&#44; so<lb/> will be the restraint upon our actions lest we forfeit their esteem.  Let us then<lb/> imagine ourselves the observed of all observers in a circle<lb/> of the noblest of beings who trod this earth&#59; patriarchs&#44;<lb/> prophets and Sages.  Their looks are <sic>rivetted</sic> upon us&#44; and<lb/> in their presence we are to confess ourselves guilty of vice and irreverence to irreligion.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>No shame greater than that&#44; yet we will be brought<lb/> face to face&#45;&#45;to use a human phrase&#45;&#45;with those whose<lb/> ethereal association we may long for in vain might have been our sweetest reward&#44; but<lb/> from which we our in <sic>wordly</sic> polluters cut us off.  For so<lb/> Not to be gathered to our fathers&#44; or our people&#44; as the<lb/> Scriptures express it the joys of immortal life&#44; is the knowing grief and im&#45;<lb/> &#45;pure deep confusion.  We will look with abhorrence<lb/> upon the years&#44; devoted to hoarding up what could<lb/> not purchase us even an approving smile of the saints<lb/> eternized by virtue rectitude &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; but the past<lb/> is will be then irretrievable.  It is when possessed of all the<lb/> means to redeem our conduct&#44; that we can should<lb/> recover our innocence&#44; washing in the laver of Jewish<lb/> purification.  The God of Israel has laid<lb/> it now within our reach.  He who holds the threads<lb/> of our existence in His hand&#44; may have beneficently<lb/> resolved ordained to lengthen them&#44; and we shall life to rejoice over recu<lb/> our recovery over our recuperation from moral diseases&#44; infirmities.  Sound<lb/> in spiritual health&#44; we shall live to breathe into<lb/> others the breath of the divinity that stirs within us&#59;<lb/> our example and our teachings will bring many<lb/> to righteousness.  We shall become god like.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Still&#44; should another decree have gone forth&#44; we<lb/> will ascend move with a light gait to the spirit&#45;land&#44;<lb/> for assured to meet the welcoming host of the noblest&#44;<lb/> glorified in the vision contemplation of God&#44; for&#44; where the sincere<lb/> repentant will ascend&#44; the perfect righteous themselves will can not<lb/> enter.  Oh may this &#91;Hebrew&#93; effect<lb/> our elevation&#44; and Thou O Lord&#44; in whom we trust&#44;<lb/> take us not hence until we have conquered all our<lb/> enemies&#45;&#45;the passions that mislead us&#44; and the<lb/> fondness of worldly varieties which estrange us from Thee.<lb/>  May a wealth of virtues be amassed by each of<lb/> Thy supplicants during the year which we have just<lb/> entered&#44; and the blessings of those toward whom we<lb/> will exercised our manly qualities&#44; afford us a foretaste<lb/> of heaven upon earth.  Grant O God that the year<lb/> 5651&#44; numerically representing the word &#91;Hebrew&#93; yo<lb/> &#34;you have seen&#34;&#44; cause us to behold the salvation of Thy<lb/> people&#44; when the children of Belial Shah vex them<lb/> no more&#44; and may the banner of freedom wave<lb/> over the oppressed of all nations from one end of<lb/> Thy created world to the uttermost end speedily in our days&#58; Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
