<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF23_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet></placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1897" source="" attested="yes">1897</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff23_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff23_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff23_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff23_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff23_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff23_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff23_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff23_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff23_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff23_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff23_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff23_2_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>68</p>
            
            <p>97<lb/>
                For Kedoshim<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Who would believe that a born Jew&#44; reported to<lb/> have sat at the feet of Joshua Ben Verachya&#45;&#45;a great renowned<lb/> Mishaic Sage&#44; which I was addressing a vast multitude<lb/> of his countrymen&#44; should have fell into a hugely blundered&#63;<lb/>  Did he do so purposely&#63;  We should give Was there a method in his great error&#63;  Was it intended for a particular purpose&#63;  The ques&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion deserves some consideration.  The new testament tells us&#44;<lb/> that among the in the course of his teachings&#44; of the man of Nazareth<lb/> in his sermon at the mount&#44; he alluded to what<lb/> we have read in our Parasha&#44; as follows&#58; &#34;Ye have<lb/> read heard that it was said&#44; thou shalt love thy<lb/> neighbor and hate thine enemy&#44; but I say unto you<lb/> love your enemies&#44; and pray for them that per&#45;<lb/>secute you&#34;.  We may challenge any to search from<lb/> cover to cover what is mistakenly called &#34;the old&#45;<lb/>testament&#44;&#34; and in order to find the second part of the quo&#45;<lb/>&#45;tation&#44; I meaning that we are commanded to hate<lb/> our enemies.  Surely My hearers surely remember that in<lb/> the five books of Moses we are commanded enjoined to assist<lb/> in saving the property of one who hates us&#44; as for<lb/> instance&#44; when his ox or his ass had strayed away&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>or it when it is being crushed under too heavy<lb/> a burden.  Surely&#44; my hearers remember also that<lb/> in the book of Proverbs we are so ordered instructed commanded&#58; &#34;If thine<lb/> enemy be hungry give him to eat&#34; and again&#34; &#34;Re&#45;<lb/>&#45;joice not when thine enemy falls.&#34;  Such sentences are<lb/> household words to every Jew acquainted with<lb/> his scriptures.  How came it then&#44; that<lb/> the teacher&#44; who is looked upon by hundreds of<lb/> millions as infallible&#44; cited Holy Writ wrongly faultily&#63;<lb/>  A possible solution to that query may be found discovered<lb/> in a parable attributed to the same preacher&#44; and<lb/> reported in one of the gospels.  It reads thus&#58; a<lb/> certain lawyer stood up and tempted Joshua Ha&#45;Nozri the man of Nazareth<lb/> saying&#59; Master&#44; what shall I do to inherit eter&#45;<lb/>&#45;nal life&#63;  And the man of Nazareth Joshua said to him&#58; what<lb/> is written in the Law&#63;  How readest it thou&#63;  And<lb/> the other answering&#44; said.  Thou shalt love thy neighbor<lb/> as thyself the Lord thy God with all thy heart&#44; &#38; with<lb/> all thy might soul and with all thy might and with<lb/> all thy strength and thy neighbor as thyself.  And<lb/> the man of Nazareth Joshua said to him&#44; thou hast answered right.<lb/>  Thus do&#44; and thou shalt live.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>But the other questioned again and said&#58; Who is<lb/> my neighbor&#63;  The man of Nazareth made answer and Joshua Ha&#45;Nozri evading a reply to the query said&#58;<lb/> A certain man person man was going down from Jerusalem and to Jeri&#45;<lb/>&#45;cho&#44; and he fell among robbers&#44; that both stripped him<lb/> and beat him and departed leaving him half dead.  And<lb/> by chance a certain priest was going down that way&#44;<lb/> and when he saw that man person man&#44; he passed by on the other<lb/> side.  But And in like manner&#44; a Levite also&#44; when<lb/> he came to that place&#44; and saw the man person man&#44; passed<lb/> by on the other side.  But a certain Samaritan&#44; as<lb/> he journeyed&#44; came where the man was&#44; and when<lb/> he saw him&#44; was moved with compassion&#44; and<lb/> come to him and bound up his wounds&#44; pouring on<lb/> them oil&#44; and he set him on his own beast&#44; and<lb/> brought him to an inn and took care of him.  And<lb/> in the morrow he took out two two pence and gave<lb/> them to the hose and said&#58; Take care of him&#44; and<lb/> whatsoever thou spendest more&#44; I&#44; when I come back<lb/> again&#44; will repay thee.  Which of the three&#44; thinkest thou&#44;<lb/> proved a neighbor unto him that fell among robbers&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>And&#44; the other said.  He that showed mercy on<lb/> him&#59; and the man of Nazareth then&#44; Joshua said to him.  God and do thou<lb/> likewise.  Now brethren&#44; you cannot help to have re&#45;<lb/>&#45;marked the mention purposely made of the<lb/> priest and the birth in a disparagingly manner and of the<lb/> Samaritan with much praise creditably in words of praise.  Why&#44; I ask&#44;<lb/> was a Samaritan pointed out as the impersonation personification<lb/> of Charity&#63;  If the object was to teach us that all<lb/> human beings may be stirred up to do kindness&#44;<lb/> why not choose as illustrations&#44; a Greek&#44; or a Phe&#45;<lb/>&#45;nician&#44; or any heathen&#63;  The following si the reason&#44;<lb/> in according to my mind.  In the sublime nineteenth chapter<lb/> of Leviticus&#44; mainly devoted to moral precepts&#44;&#45;&#45;the chapter which<lb/> forms part of this sabbath&#39;s section&#45;&#45;we are ordered<lb/> not to take vengeance nor bear any grudge against<lb/> the children of our people &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Are we then allowed to do so against others&#63;  I say To that I answer&#58;<lb/> privately personally not&#44; politically nationally yes.  We must<lb/> love our neighbor like ourselves&#44; or to say it&#44; as<lb/> the meek Hillel put it &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;What is unpleasant to thee&#44; never do not unto others.&#34;<lb/>  But what if we are nationally attacked<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>with a malice aforethought&#59; to vex with a determined view to harass us politic&#45;<lb/>&#45;ally and overthrow our country&#44; making common entwining into a league<lb/> cause with foreign oppressors to hasten our destruct&#45;<lb/>&#45;ion&#63;  Now&#44; all of that the samaritans did&#44;<lb/> from the hour that the exiles of Chaldea re&#45;<lb/>turned to their father&#39;s land.  To our foes&#44; they<lb/> swore that they had not connection with us&#44; tho&#39;<lb/> professing to revere the five books of Moses&#44; which they&#44; however&#44; deliberately falsified.  But if<lb/> success happened to perch on our banner&#44; they pretended<lb/> to be part and parcel of our people&#44; in order to<lb/> share in any benefit that might result from it.<lb/>  The man of Nazareth who to prove show liberality associated with Pu&#45;<lb/>&#45;blicans&#45;&#45;the tax gatherers of the Roman pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;consuls that misgoverned and overburdened Judea&#59;<lb/> he&#44; who but who called scribes and Pharisees whitened se&#45;<lb/>&#45;pulchres&#44; and laid the finger of contempt on<lb/> priests and levites&#44; knew well the history of<lb/> Samaritanism in relation to Judaism and our ancient metropolis.  But to him patriotism&#44; was<lb/> a secondary thought&#44; if it ever entered his<lb/> thoughts.  We gather from the new testa&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment&#44; that kingdoms and principalities were in this<lb/> world were of no account to him&#44; compared with the inheritance<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>of heaven&#44; so was he wont to say proclaim.  What&#44;<lb/> if Jerusalem and all of our national heritage was<lb/> reduced to ashes&#44; so long that men could be converted<lb/> to his impracticable ideas&#63;  Priests and Levites were<lb/> not with him&#44; since they were against him&#44; hence<lb/> the <sic>uggly</sic> picture drawn of them.  But the scribes<lb/> and Pharisees whom he maligned&#44; have taught<lb/> that any one obeying God studying the will of God and doing His will it stands<lb/> in the sight of the Almighty as high as the Pontiff<lb/> in the holy of holy &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Furthermore&#44; a Jew is enjoined to<lb/> love the stranger.  In the same chapter&#44; clearly<lb/> misquoted by the supposed author of the new testament&#44; we are imperative&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly ordered to treat the stranger foreigner as a native &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  But the Jew loved<lb/> also his country passionately.  He had not learnt<lb/> to become&#44; what we now call &#34;cosmopolitan&#44;&#34; which<lb/> is surely a misnomer.  for it is impossible&#59; it is un&#45;<lb/>&#45;natural to feel the same depth of affection<lb/> for every corner of the earth&#44; as for the spot<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>in which we first saw the light of day&#44; where our mother lavished upon us her en&#45;<lb/>&#45;dearments&#59; the spot where she taught us to move<lb/> the lips prayerfully&#59; the spot where our earliest<lb/> memories cluster.  Therefore the Jew resisted the<lb/> attempt to rob him of the object closest to his<lb/> heart.  He could not substitute for it the promise<lb/> of a future inheritance beyond our finite conception.<lb/>  He did take revenge and here grudge against his country&#39;s deliberate inveterate foes.<lb/>  But say brethren&#44; has Christianity followed&#44; during the nine&#45;<lb/>&#45;teen y centuries of its existence the infensible theories<lb/> enunciated in the new testament&#63;  Look<lb/> around&#44; and see its adherents battling for a<lb/> piece patch of ground justly or unjustly claimed<lb/> by different parties.  Most positively I assert it&#44; Christianity<lb/> Europe and history bears me out&#44; Christianity does not obey anywhere the command set forth in<lb/> the sermon on the mount&#44; &#34;love your enemies&#44; pray<lb/> for them that persecute you.&#34;  Admit&#58; To follow that<lb/> precept would be to transform altogether the na&#45;<lb/>&#45;ture that which God has moulded&#45;&#45;and that can&#45;<lb/>&#45;not be done.  But wherefore then make boast of what did not and does not exist&#63;  We must obey its our instincts&#44; and in<lb/> this consists lies the remarkable difference between<lb/> Judaism and Christianity.  The latter deals<lb/> in imaginary possibilities&#59; the former in what can<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>always be carried out il into daily practice.<lb/>  Yet&#44; we may meet Jews&#59; more particularly<lb/> Jewesses&#44; who profess to have drawn in&#45;<lb/>&#45;spiration from the new testament&#44; and to<lb/> have been dragged down by the ceremonialism<lb/> of the old&#44; as if&#44; for instance&#44; the our historical<lb/> Passover recently celebrated&#44; loses in comparison<lb/> with Easter&#44; or ostara&#44; a name from which the festivity it is derived&#44;<lb/> in commemoration of the worship anciently tendered<lb/> to a heathen goddess&#59; or as if the feast of weeks&#44;<lb/> soon to be solemnized means less than the Pente&#45;<lb/>&#45;cost of the Christian church&#44; allusive to the alleged<lb/> descent of the holy ghost on the apostles.  Israelites&#44;<lb/> study well&#44; at least&#44; the 19th chapter of Leviticus&#44;<lb/> just perused&#44; and you will find charity of the noblest<lb/> type recommended&#44; answering integrity demanded&#44;<lb/> reverence for age&#44; for acquired experience&#44; for<lb/> practical religion solemnly enjoined.  Take those lessons to<lb/> your various walks of life&#44; and you will reach your<lb/> final destination safe and sound in peace with man&#59; in<lb/> piece&#91;sic&#63;&#93; with God.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
