<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF2_15</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_15_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_15_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_15_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_15_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_15_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_15_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_15_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_15_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_15_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_15_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_15_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_15_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_15_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_15_7v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>On Penitence<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  In the days of old&#44; when a public fast<lb/> was proclaimed to avert some impending cala&#45;<lb/> &#45;mity&#44; our ancestors assembled largely numerously in a<lb/> very spacious place&#44; and chose form their<lb/> midst a person&#44; whose admonitions&#45;&#45;supported<lb/> by the weight of his character&#45;&#45;might beneficially impress<lb/> all hearers and draw them again near to God.<lb/>  That respect man mounting a pulpit&#44;<lb/> thus addressed his audience&#58; &#34;Brethren&#58; neither<lb/> your sackcloth nor your fasting will avail<lb/> you&#44; repentance and virtuous actions will<lb/> effect a purpose.  For&#44; Holy Writ declares that<lb/> the people of Nineveh received God&#39;s pardon<lb/> not by reason of their abstaining from food<lb/> and drink and dressing coarsely&#44; but through<lb/> their good deeds.&#34;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  In the same language&#44;<lb/> those whom Jewish congregations have selected<lb/> as spiritual guides&#44; must now speak with<lb/> all the powers at their command&#44; even now at<lb/> this most solemn time&#44; when God&#39;s sentence is about<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>to be pronounced.  Israelites.  If a<lb/> steadfast determination to conform here&#45;<lb/>&#45;after to the dictates of religion&#44; <sic>impells</sic> you<lb/> to celebrate this soul&#45;stirring season of our year&#44;<lb/> you will benefit yourselves everlastingly.<lb/>  You will be relieved of the burden of former<lb/> trespasses by the mercy of a universal Father.<lb/>  But if a fatal error should lure you into<lb/> the belief that outward worship will com&#45;<lb/>&#45;pensate for shortcomings&#44; you will simply<lb/> add to the weight of that burden.<lb/></p>
            <p>Let me quote the Sages &#91;Hebrew&#93; He that says&#58; I will<lb/> follow my own inclinations whatever they may<lb/> be&#44; for the day of atonement will make it<lb/> all right&#44; is for ever lost.  But I will<lb/> not generalize&#44; when it is my bounden<lb/> duty to enter into particulars.  &#91;Inserted&#58;&#93; We read in the Mishnah&#44; which is the repository of Jewish traditions&#44; that in the days of old&#44; when<lb/> a public fast was proclaimed&#44; our ancestors assembled in large number at a place well fitted for the<lb/> occasion.  A person&#44; the weight of whose character would lent his words great influence would<lb/> be asked to address the multitudes.  What was the nature of the sermon&#63;  No rhetorical flourishes&#44; not<lb/> a display of doctrinary powers distinguished it.  The preacher went straight into the subject without<lb/> preliminary remarks.  He quoted the Bible and showed by what means pardon can be purchased.<lb/>  Not by tearing one&#39;s garments and by weeping&#59; not by putting on sackcloth and submitting to the thirty nine<lb/> stripes&#44; nor even by chastening the body with a privation of food and drink.  The only and sure way to<lb/> bring about a reconciliation between the sinner and his God&#44; is to sin no more&#59; or&#44; to say it in the ex&#45;<lb/>hortative language of Daniel to King Nebuchadnezzar&#44; &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;redeem thy faults by<lb/> righteousness.&#34;  The people of Nineveh upon hearing that a doom was impending&#44; cried loudly&#44; sat<lb/> upon ashes and prayed&#44; but Holy Writ recording those circumstances&#44; urges says nevertheless &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;God saw their actions&#34; namely &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;that they turned away form their evil doings&#34;<lb/>  Nearly in about this manner that man chosen in ancient times to preach penitence&#44; spoke.  In the same lan&#45;<lb/>&#45;guage or very near much like it&#44; persons chosen by Jewish Congregations as spiritual guides must speak<lb/> on this Sabbath preceding the awe inspiring annual fast.  Brethren.  Most consolatory is the in&#45;<lb/>&#45;struction of the prophet on the river Chebar.  In his days&#44; like as in those the days of his predecessors contemporary Jeremiah&#44; our ancestors made use<lb/> of a current proverb&#44; to signify that repentance was of no account absolutely powerless because the children must unavoid&#45;<lb/>ably suffer on account of the iniquities of their parents.  At that&#44; Ezekiel arose with all the power of<lb/> truth to vindicate the justice of God.  Not so&#44; he exclaimed&#58; the soul of the father and the soul of the<lb/> son are mine&#44; the soul that sinneth that shall die.  Every one according to his own ways will<lb/> I judge you&#44; O house of Israel&#44; says the Lord God&#58; Make for yourselves a new heart and a new<lb/> spirit&#44; turn back and live.  Those sentiments which inspiration dictated found expression on the lips<lb/> of the Sages&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  No partition can separate us from God&#44; if we approach<lb/> Him in penitence.  But do you know what is an impenetrable unbroken division&#63;  An error unhappily pre&#45;<lb/>valent among some Israelites.  Never mind our prevarications&#44; never mind our acting the whole year round<lb/> as if the Decalogue had not been delivered&#59; as if the 11th chapter of the book of Leviticus had never been<lb/> written&#44; Yom Kippur will make it set all right.  For by abstaining from two meals&#44; we pay up make in compensation<lb/> for all transgressions and are square again.  No exclaim the Talmudists &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  He who thinks that he can do wrong and the day of<lb/> atonement can rectify all things&#44; will die with black stains on his soul.  But I will not generalize<lb/> when it is my painful duty to descend into particulars.  A falling off in the observance &#38;c &#91;end insert&#93; A falling<lb/> off in the observance of Biblical ordinances is indeed visibly great.  It was once our boast<lb/> that the Mosaic Law acted as a check<lb/> upon immoral wrong practices&#44; but with its gra&#45;<lb/>&#45;dual abandonment there has grown a looseness of principles<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>which sets our coreligionists in a very unenvi&#45;<lb/>&#45;able light.  Were I disposed to offer to<lb/> view what the domestic roof covers up&#44; I might point to husbands who sadden the<lb/> existence of their best friends on earth by<lb/> habits clashing with domestic obligations home duties&#59; I<lb/> might show sons who draw scalding tears<lb/> from the authors and supporters of their earthly<lb/> existence&#44; sisters whose petty quarrels es&#45;<lb/>&#45;trange from each other&#44; brothers whose<lb/> incompatibility of temperament ripened into<lb/> hatred.  But I forbear&#44; not because such<lb/> acts deserve justification in any degree&#44;<lb/> but because thank God their commission is<lb/> neither very prevalent nor so unblushingly<lb/> displayed as some others.  For&#44; I hold it<lb/> as my opinion&#44; that when sin stalks abroad<lb/> with an air of defiance&#44; then are the chosen<lb/> guardians of the faith principally called upon to<lb/> brand it with the stigma of public reproach.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Now&#58; it is notoriously known that of<lb/> all transgressions&#44; the desecration of the Sabbath<lb/> is the most rampant.  Perhaps at no period<lb/> of our history in modern times has that offense<lb/> against the Decalogue been so wide&#45;spread<lb/> and so unconcernedly perpetrated.  I had fancied that our ancestors<lb/> could not have credited predicted that liberty and the<lb/> promulgation at Sinai would have come into<lb/> open collision&#44; and I was once disposed inclined to con&#45;<lb/>&#45;sider a saying common in Talmudical ages&#44;<lb/> as the offspring of gentile ill&#45;will.  &#34;Af&#45;<lb/>&#45;fliction becomes the Jews like a red rose on<lb/> a white horse&#34; was the adage&#59; but noticing how<lb/> very few of the freedom&#45;loving Israelites of<lb/> America submit to the rule of their Sovereign<lb/> Legislator&#44; I changed my mind.  Of<lb/> course&#44; I shrink at the memory of long<lb/> years of persecution&#44; when we were huddled<lb/> up together within narrow quarters and compelled<lb/> to drudge plod for a living&#44; or conceal hide away our earnings<lb/> lest they be plundered&#44; yet when I recall<lb/> the pleasure manifested in those years<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>of oppression at the ushering in of the<lb/> Sabbath&#44; its welcome in our homes&#44; the<lb/> greetings it received at the family table<lb/> with hymns and psalmody&#59; when I contrast<lb/> that enthusiasm with the present cold indifference&#44; I must<lb/> grant that the adage emanated from men<lb/> with of deep wisdom and extraordinary foresight.<lb/>  But is it because the men of Israel evil&#45;<lb/>&#45;fully or compulsorily follow their vocations<lb/> on the sabbath that the women of Israel<lb/> are exonerated from a sacred duty&#63;  Are they<lb/> constrained to forego practices&#44; which cast a<lb/> halo round their firesides&#63;  Must they<lb/> be seen in the market palce&#44; and in tho&#45;<lb/>&#45;roughfares making their purchases so publicly&#44;<lb/> that the act creates scandal much to the<lb/> sorrow of the God&#45;fearing&#63;  Who does not<lb/> know that more than the habits of the fathers&#44; the<lb/> practices doings of the mother have a lasting influence<lb/> upon the young&#63;  Unconsciously&#44; perhaps&#44;<lb/> but surely will the women of my people<lb/> sow impiety by their disregard of an essential<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>tenet of Judaism.  Children losing their<lb/> respect for one of ten commandments&#44; will learn<lb/> to disbelieve in in the Divine origin of any&#44; and be<lb/> goaded on to trample under foot truths on<lb/> which the stability of society and the welfare<lb/> of individuals depend.  Think of it&#44;<lb/> my coreligionists.  Reflect upon it&#44; my sisters<lb/> in faith&#44; and since it lies mainly with you<lb/> to build your homes on solid foundations&#44;<lb/> exercise your powers to that blessed end.<lb/>  The Judge&#44; to whose august presence&#44; we<lb/> know not how soon any of us may be<lb/> summoned&#44; will not ask how finely we<lb/> have provided for the embellishment of our<lb/> domiciles&#44; or for the outward appearance<lb/> of our sons and daughters.  He will inquire<lb/> how far we have striven to imbue them<lb/> our progeny with the truths imparted at<lb/> Horeb&#44; teaching them to trust in God&#44; rather<lb/> than in our schemes and untiring prospects<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>for self&#45;aggrandizement&#44; how far we<lb/> have inspired veneration for His word&#44; and<lb/> a feeling of moderation and contentment.<lb/>  Are we prepared to <sic>fulfil</sic> that parental charge&#63;<lb/>  Are we determined to suppress our will so<lb/> that the will of our Creator be done on<lb/> earth as it is done in heaven&#63;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  Shall our<lb/> living example inspire instill into those to whom we have<lb/> voluntarily given existence a sentiment of respect<lb/> for their ancient creed&#63;  Will our daily practices<lb/> enforce morality&#44; as well as a rigid adherence<lb/> to behests distinguishing consistent Israelites&#63;<lb/>  If the solemnity of this season and the<lb/> charge call of our merciful God who beckons<lb/> us to near to Him&#44; have happily influenced<lb/> our minds&#44; we shall not depart hence<lb/> on Yom Kippur&#44; until we be born again to<lb/> a life of righteousness and everlasting blessings.<lb/>  Oh let us beseech the Donor of all good<lb/> to bestow on us the strength to do right&#44;<lb/> and grant us the inward satisfaction&#45;&#45;more<lb/> valuable than rubies&#45;&#45;of having faithfully<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>performed the task which nature and religion<lb/> impose upon parents.  Let us pray<lb/> that He may bid His angels accompany our<lb/> steps&#44; so that we stumble no more against<lb/> stones which a rebellious disposition raises<lb/> up.  May we proceed forward in an<lb/> even way till we reach the haven of our final<lb/> destruction in peace with our conscience&#44;<lb/> in peace with our saving God.  May we be<lb/> eternized on earth by a progeny of spotless charac&#45;<lb/>&#45;ter&#44; and beatified in heaven by the memorial<lb/> of a well spent life.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
