<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF11_3</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1896-01" source="" attested="yes">1896</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_3_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_3_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_3_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_3_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_3_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_3_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_3_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_3_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_3_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_3_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_3_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_3_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>75<lb/></p>
            
            <p>96<lb/></p>
            <p>The Jewish Publication Society<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>&#34;The Jewish Publication Society of America&#34;&#44;<lb/> whose seat of honor is Philadelphia&#44; deserves all<lb/> the praise&#44; which an intelligent public&#44; from near<lb/> and from far&#44; bestows thereupon.  I was wrong&#44;<lb/> when at the start&#44; I gave utterance to gloomy mis&#45;<lb/>&#45;givings about its final workings.  Delivery that<lb/> it might exercise a wide influence in the interest<lb/> of new fangled doctrines&#44; I deprecated the undertaking.<lb/>  In contrast with it&#44; I had then in my mind&#44; a<lb/> modest endeavour conceived in our city&#44; by members<lb/> of this congregation&#45;&#45;an effort the sudden termination<lb/> of which I witnessed in 1851 at the fire that con&#45;<lb/>sumed the building&#44; which held the property of our<lb/> literary organization.  I remembered that every book<lb/> it had issued&#45;&#45;unpretentious as it was&#45;&#45;had been<lb/> purely Jewish.  Again&#44; I recalled also the<lb/> pleasing fact&#44; that twenty years later&#44; the too short<lb/>&#45;lived attempt to revive the same organization in New<lb/> York&#44; succeeded in furnishing the reader with works<lb/> altogether advantageous to our faith.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Therefore when in 1888 persons&#44; largely connected with<lb/> an association of Jews so named by the accident of<lb/> birth&#44; but not by a consistent adherence to Judaism&#44;<lb/> strongly advocated the formation of the Publication<lb/> Society&#44; I expressed fears and doubts&#44; concerning the<lb/> effects of such advocacy from such quarters.<lb/></p>
            <p>My apprehensions&#44; however&#44; were in the main ill&#45;<lb/>founded.  I qualify my saying&#44; for a different<lb/> reason than that which several men have alleged.  They felt<lb/> sore because an organization emanating from<lb/> America&#44; did not always go in search of writers&#44;<lb/> whose dwelling place is in America.  Now&#44;<lb/> waving the point&#44; whether our own midst could an&#45;<lb/>swer in all respects to the requirement&#45;&#45;a discus&#45;<lb/>&#45;sion idle and perhaps invidious&#45;&#45;I disagree agree&#91;sic&#63;&#93; with the complaints and at all<lb/> events&#44; with the Rabbis in their maxim&#44; that we must<lb/> accept a truth from whatever source it may flow &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  To me it matters nothing&#44; if the author<lb/> be English&#44; French&#44; German&#44; Polish or Russian&#44; provided<lb/> he keeps steadily in view the main object to be attained&#44; viz<lb/> the elevation of our race before a prejudiced world&#44; and the<lb/> broadening of the range of our people&#39;s national learning.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>I cannot honestly declare that the volumes hither<lb/>&#45;to brought forth from the press under the auspices of our organization&#44; have afforded me entire satisfaction<lb/> in their every effort part.  It may be <sic>idiosyncracy</sic>&#44; or<lb/> the consequence of early training&#44; but I have object&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed to some of the teachings in almost every volume&#44;<lb/> still&#44; I have also discovered that none aims to throw<lb/> aside historical Judaism and give the palm to<lb/> groundless Radicalism.<lb/></p>
            <p>But alluding this morning more specially to the last<lb/> production offered to our notice&#44; I wish to say that it<lb/> supplies a fund of information rare and varied.<lb/>  Admit&#58; all the contents thereof may be met interspersed<lb/> through countless books&#44; constituting our literature&#44;<lb/> but Mr Israel Abrahams&#44; has can claim the great merit of<lb/> having methodically arranged in his volume on<lb/> &#34;Jewish life in the Middle ages&#44;&#34; what could not be<lb/> learned&#44; except by consulting the pages of mul&#45;<lb/>tifarious and often inaccessible writings.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Rich is that volume particularly in quotations<lb/> from &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; or the solution of questions propound&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed to noted Rabbis in different lands at dif&#45;<lb/>&#45;ferent epochs&#44; upon a diversity of subjects.<lb/></p>
            <p>I commend Mr Abraham&#39;s literary contribution<lb/> to a the careful perusal of all&#44; surely&#44; of our students of syn&#45;<lb/>&#45;ogogal history&#44; not perhaps in the regular order of<lb/> chapters&#44; lest it may fatigue the mind&#44; but in the<lb/> selection of such chapters&#44; the heading of which forcibly<lb/> invites attention.  The objections that I<lb/> have to some of the ideas advanced in that volume&#44;<lb/> I shall submit to my hearers in another<lb/> lecture of mine.  To day I may tell of the degree<lb/> of satisfaction a remarkable change<lb/> in the standing of our coreligionists in Great Bri&#45;<lb/>&#45;tain must afford.  I have no reference to<lb/> the elevation of a Mr George F. Phillips to the<lb/> position of lord Mayor.  That distinction<lb/> is not singular.  Others of our persuasion<lb/> were made to enjoy it&#44; and they exercised the<lb/> functions of the high offices consistently&#44; more or less&#44;<lb/> with the religion which they professed.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Besides&#44; political preferments attract me<lb/> very little.  What gladdens my heart ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;ceedingly is a revival of Jewish learning<lb/> in the city of London among English speaking<lb/> Israelites.  When in my youth&#44; I sought<lb/> then a livelihood&#44; as a school &#38; private master&#44; I found scarcely<lb/> any of the natives&#44; who cultivated our literature.<lb/>  Attachment to the precepts&#44; I generally dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;covered in the Jews of the metropolis&#44; but religious<lb/> practices were more a habit&#45;&#45;however commendable&#45;&#45;<lb/>than the effect of serious studies in the beauties<lb/> of the sacred language in which we pray and<lb/> on the sublime instruction of our prophets and<lb/> sages.  A change has taken place since then which is most<lb/> admirable.  Mr Gangwill&#45;&#45;no mean<lb/> Judge&#45;&#45;inclines to attribute it to the coming of Mr<lb/> Schechter to London.  For in the opinion of the now<lb/> famous novelist&#44; the our erudite Roumanian brother who lectured<lb/> before us last the year before last under the auspices of the Gratz<lb/> trust&#44; exercises a most powerful agency for good&#45;&#45;he being<lb/> in Mr Zangwill&#39;s conception &#34;perhaps the greatest Hebrew scholar<lb/> in the world.&#34;  I am utterly disqualified to pronounce an opinion<lb/> concerning so decided a judgment.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Doubtless&#44; Mr Schechter&#39;s teachings in Rabbinics<lb/> at Cambridge is the versatility of swift<lb/> mind&#44; evinced by a multiplicity of writings&#44;<lb/> influence beneficially younger men and wo&#45;<lb/>men.  Hence the possibility of establishing a<lb/> &#34;Jewish Quarterly Review&#44;&#34; fraught with<lb/> new names&#44; enrolled in the ranks of our<lb/> literati&#44; counting among them a Miss<lb/> Nina Davis and a Mrs H. Lucas&#44; <sic>vieying</sic><lb/> with each other in translating in flowing English<lb/> rhymes&#44; Hebrew poems.  Yet&#44; recognizing that<lb/> fact&#44; I cannot ignore that even prior to Mr Schechter&#39;s<lb/> settlement in London during the last decade&#44; some <sic>weilded</sic> already a grace&#45;<lb/>&#45;ful pen of the scribe.  I may instance Mr<lb/> Lucien Wolf&#44; an English Jew&#44; editor&#44; biogra&#45;<lb/>&#45;pher and writer of interesting stories.  AS to the<lb/> foundations of Mr Israel Abraham&#39;s learning&#44; I can<lb/> related that I was personally acquainted with his immediate<lb/> predecessors.  They were not English.  Unless I am mistaken<lb/> they hailed from Recessive Poland&#44; but they could be reckoned a&#45;<lb/>mong the very few able to instruct the Author of &#34;Jewish life<lb/> in the Middle ages.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>I possess a Hebrew commentary&#44; which his grand<lb/> father wrote on a volume regarding our method of<lb/> slaughtering animals for our food.  I also sat in com&#45;<lb/>&#45;pany with his father&#44; Bernat Abrahams&#44; forming<lb/> one part of the ecclesiastical Board of the Sephardic con&#45;<lb/>gregation&#45;&#45;a gifted scholar was he.  No doubt&#44;<lb/> Israel Abrahams&#44; better known than either of the two just mentioned in the<lb/> world of letters&#44; must have imbibed lessons that lay<lb/> the foundations basis of his extensive acquirements.  I am<lb/> thankful for the use made thereof.  But in<lb/> order to limit the range of my mental observations&#44; I cast<lb/> a look only on a galaxy of our worthies&#44; now in London. chiefly on a most luminous met star on our horizon in the city beyond over the<lb/> I look and Thames I cannot turn away from contemplating<lb/> a bright star on our horizon. its fast increasing brilliancy.  It is Joseph Jacobs shines star<lb/> brilliantly the that shines so splendidly.  The rising Jew He is confessedly a marvel of literary<lb/> activity.  Scarcely has one work of his teeming brains<lb/> issued forth&#44; when another brimful of knowledge is<lb/> announced.  Mr Jacobs is not a native of London&#44;<lb/> but he is nevertheless English.  Justly does the Mel&#45;<lb/>&#45;bourne &#34;Jewish Herald&#34; pride itself upon the merits of<lb/> that son of Australia.  Joseph Jacobs <sic>weilds</sic> a pen<lb/> so prolific that I may not be charged with<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>exaggeration when I say of him what Johanan Ben<lb/> Zacka&#239; said asserted concerning a famous pupil<lb/> of his.  He is like an exhaustless foundation<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            <p>Brethren.  Next month we will be<lb/> privileged to listen to the rare learning<lb/> of the Australian Jew.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
