<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF9_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1890-05" source="" attested="yes">16 May 1890</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_1_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. Fifth St.<lb/></p>
            <p>Philadelphia&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>On the law of usury<lb/>
                a lecture <sic>remodelled</sic> from an old one delivered<lb/>
                many years ago&#44; but still improved upon in<lb/>
                the course of delivery on Sabbath May 16. 90<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Brethren.  You will agree&#44; that according to the impressions<lb/> which our youths receive concerning the principles underlying<lb/> their ancestral religion&#44; so will Judaism be furnished with either<lb/> earnest ardent or lukewarm followers.  Light should therefore be our<lb/> watchword&#44; light&#44; if we wish that our ranks swell with bright mind&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed and broad large hearted Israelites&#44; not with dwarfs in intellect&#59; puny mor&#45;<lb/>&#45;tals.  I can confidently assert that in many instances ignorance of the<lb/> spirit of Mosaism&#44; and in others prejudices early imbibed by baneful<lb/> surroundings&#44; have robbed us of faithful adherents.  Some will<lb/> argue that we have nothing to fear about the perpetuity of our belief&#59;<lb/> that it will remain eternal&#44; notwithstanding defections&#44; for so<lb/> we were divinely promised.   But without attempting to deny prophecy&#44;<lb/> I insist that to imagine Judaism without intelligently observing<lb/> Jews&#44; is like imagining the existence of a republic in a community<lb/> where all oppose republican ideas.  So true it is&#44; that Moses never<lb/> ceased urging instruction to fit Hebrews as guardians of the Law.<lb/>  He forcibly recommended parental teaching&#44; because it is the<lb/> most effective&#44; forming a mighty link between the past and<lb/> the future.  When he wrote &#91;Hebrew&#93; Thou shalt make<lb/> these &#40;laws&#41; known to thy children&#44; and to thy children&#39;s children<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>he showed how memory intuitively goes back to home asso&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciations&#44; and how powerful are the latter always.  But to lend<lb/> early instruction greater weight&#44; the arch prophet ordered a seventh<lb/> year gathering of all Israelites&#44; that they should listen to a rehearsal<lb/> of the precepts and to a summary of the duties from the lips<lb/> of the Chief ruler of the nation.  The solemnity of the occasion<lb/> would creat a lasting impression upon the youthful attendants&#44;<lb/> and make of them sincere adherents of the Torah through life.<lb/>  As we read &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Assemble the people&#44;<lb/> men&#44; women and children....in order that they may hear and<lb/> learn and fear the Lord your God...And their children who know<lb/> not may &#40;also&#41; hear and learn and fear the Lord your God all<lb/> the days that they live.&#34;  Now&#44; if so much stress was laid<lb/> on the importance of a correct knowledge of the Torah&#44; when<lb/> we formed a distinct nation&#44; having our rulers to watch over<lb/> the preservation of our civil and political statutes&#59; having but<lb/> a limited intercourse with other peoples&#44; how much more essen&#45;<lb/>&#45;tial it must be now when we come in constant contact with<lb/> non&#45;Israelites that we should be thoroughly conversant with our<lb/> tenets to intelligently follow them.  Do we not incessantly<lb/> hear the boast of a later creed having improved immeasurably<lb/> on our code of morals&#44; which was given us because of the hardness<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>of our fathers&#39; heart&#63;  Ignorance is in very deed the enemy which<lb/> Judaism most dreads&#44; and that we must fight&#44; that we<lb/> must conquer&#44; if we wish the religion of Abraham to be more<lb/> than a dead letter&#44; if we want it to be a live religion&#44; full of<lb/> vigor and activity.  To illustrate my assertion&#44; I will draw<lb/> your attention for a few moments to a sentence in the first portion<lb/> of the two which we have perused&#44; the misconstruction of which<lb/> brought interminable odium in our faith and untold suf&#45;<lb/>&#45;fering on our people.  It was thus in the authorized&#44; or King<lb/> James&#39; translation made at the beginning of the 12th century.  &#34;If thy<lb/> brother be wxxen waxen poor and fullen in decay with thee&#44; then<lb/> shalt thou relieve him&#59; yea&#44; though he be a stranger or a<lb/> sojourner&#44; that he may live with thee.  Take then not usury of<lb/> him or increase&#44; but fear thy God&#44; that thy brother may live<lb/> with thee.&#34;  And this rule is amplified in Deuteronomy as<lb/> follows&#58; Thou shalt not lend upon usury to thy brother......<lb/> unto the stranger thou mightest lend upon usury&#44; but unto<lb/> thy brother thou shalt not lend upon usury&#44; that the Lord<lb/> thy God may bless thee in all that thou settest thy hand to&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>This ordinance founded upon equity has been sharply ani&#45;<lb/>&#45;madverted on.  It has been interpreted as an unbecoming par&#45;<lb/>&#45;tiality&#44; setting a line of demarcation between man and man<lb/> in the discharge of a moral duty.  It has been attacked as<lb/> fostering among the Hebrews the practice of taking undue ad&#45;<lb/>&#45;vantage of another man&#39;s <sic>straitness</sic> of circumstances&#44; because<lb/> he happens to descend from an ancestry which does not date<lb/> so far back as the time of our patriarchs.  You will remem&#45;<lb/>&#45;ber that Napoleon I made the question of usury among Jews<lb/> one upon which their emancipation largely hinged&#44; in a great measure&#44;<lb/> and that the Sanhedrin which he convened at the beginning<lb/> of the present century&#44; tried to explain away the difficulties<lb/> lying in the way of its solution.  And I myself still retain<lb/> a vivid recollection of a dispute in which I once engaged with<lb/> a coreligionist of ours&#44; who honestly believed that the rule which<lb/> I have quoted has offered a just cause for the bitter persecution<lb/>to which our race has been exposed during many ages.  He<lb/> contended&#44; that we&#44; who are living in days of enlightenment&#44;<lb/> ought to repudiate it&#44; and adopt another code of morals<lb/> which&#45;&#45;it is claimed&#45;&#45;stands on a higher plane&#44; making<lb/> no distinction between the inhabitants of Jerusalem and<lb/> that of Samaria.  but it never occurred to my opponent&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>and to many similarly impressed&#44; that they were com&#45;<lb/>&#45;pletely unacquainted with the subject of their adverse criticism.<lb/>  They may possibly have been in possession of general learning&#44;<lb/> but they showed themselves evidently deficient in that learning&#44;<lb/> which lies at the basis of sound criticism&#44; in that&#44; I say&#44;<lb/> which alone can enable us to judge correctly of ancient<lb/> writings.  They had not studied the science of words.  I<lb/> will endeavour to explain my meaning briefly but clearly.<lb/>  The English version falls short of our purpose in its rendition<lb/> of the original text.  The Hebrew term &#91;Hebrew&#93; translated &#34;usury&#34;<lb/> and which has occasioned so much obloquy&#44; signifies a bite.<lb/>  The Hebrew term &#91;Hebrew&#93; translated &#34;stranger&#34; signifies a<lb/> wayfaring foreigner of distant countries.  Now&#44; the<lb/> Israelites&#45;&#45;as it is universally <sic>know</sic>&#44; were a pastoral and<lb/> an agricultural people.  The <sic>yeilding</sic> of the soil formed<lb/> their he wealth&#44; the abundance of their cattle consti&#45;<lb/>&#45;tuted their riches.  They dared not part with the land of<lb/> their inheritance.  The heavenly Legislator had said &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;The land shall not be sold<lb/> completely&#44; for the land is mine&#44; ye are strangers and<lb/> sojourners with me.&#34;  Should the unpropitiousness<lb/> of the season&#44; or any unforeseen circumstances have<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>reduced a Hebrew family to poverty and they asked<lb/> for a loan&#44; it was to satisfy their daily wants&#44; until<lb/> they discovered from their lowly condition&#44; which could<lb/> be only temporary.  To demand of such &#91;Hebrew&#93; a bite or rather<lb/> a bit more than what had been lent&#44; was deemed unbrotherly<lb/> unkind and therefore it was rigorously prohibited.<lb/>  Not so with regard to the &#91;Hebrew&#93;  He held no residence<lb/> in Palestine.  He went there&#44; as he betook himself to<lb/> far off climes usually in pursuit of his traffic.  He would<lb/> buy of the Hebrews the surplus of their crop&#44; or give them<lb/> objects he had procured in exchange of their oxen and<lb/> herd.  If he lo borrowed money or produce&#44; he intended to<lb/> enlarge his stock and dispose of it profitably in foreign<lb/> markets.  From such it was allowed to receive a compensa&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion for having given up a portion of our own property for<lb/> a time to the advantage of a wayfaring merchant.  Where<lb/> is then in this ordinance the wrong inflicted upon the stranger&#44;<lb/> where&#44; but in the minds of the unlearned critics&#63;  Need<lb/> we be told in every page of the Pentateuch&#44; that the stran&#45;<lb/>&#45;ger that dwells in our midst must be treated with the same<lb/> degree of consideration as if he had been born in Israel &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Not alone must we forbear from doing him injury&#44; but we must<lb/> love him like ourselves &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  But you<lb/> naturally will inquire how shall we know for certain<lb/> that &#91;Hebrew&#93; represents a wayfaring foreigner of distant lands&#44;<lb/> and that it is not synonymous with &#91;Hebrew&#93; the stranger that<lb/> sojourns in our midst.  In order not to fatigue you with<lb/> many quotations I shall simply remind you of Solomon&#39;s<lb/> prayer in the Temple.  He said &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;And even to the Nochri&#44; who is not of Thy people Israel&#44; but<lb/> cometh out of a far off country&#45;&#45;when he shall come and<lb/> pray at this house&#44; mayest Thou listen in heaven the place of<lb/> Thy dwelling.&#34;  That passage and several others in which<lb/> the term Nochri occurs&#44; leave no doubt as to the meaning<lb/> originally attached to that word.  It signifies solely and<lb/> exclusively a transient visitor in the land of Israel&#44; mainly<lb/> a wayfaring merchant.  But after all in very truth the<lb/> wording of the sentence in Deuteronomy is the clearest vin&#45;<lb/>&#45;dication of the ordinance.  For it reads &#91;Hebrew&#93; To the Nochri thou mayest &#91;&#63;&#93; to give interest<lb/> justly have our Rabbis&#44; who understood perfectly well the<lb/> genius of the Hebrew language said that the commandment<lb/> is a warning to him that asks for a loan &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>for the literal construction of the verb&#44; conveys<lb/> that idea&#44; namely&#44; while we should not suffer<lb/> our brother in need to return to us a bit more than<lb/> what he borrowed&#44; we might receive a compen&#45;<lb/>&#45;sation from a <sic>travelling</sic> foreigner&#44; because of the<lb/> advantage he derives from our loan.  He himself<lb/> of his own accord&#44; for his own benefit offers it to the agricultural&#44;<lb/> Hebrew.  The legitimate calling of the latter&#44; did not encourage<lb/> his indulging in such a a usurious vocation.  Nor does the history of<lb/> that ancient period&#44; prove the Israelites addicted to such<lb/> dealings.  It is not my province&#44; nor is it my purpose<lb/> to discuss the course of action followed by our predecessors during<lb/> the middle ages.  The annals of those centuries of moral dark&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness are written with the blood and tears of our race.  Those<lb/> who understand human nature will not wonder if the Jews&#44;<lb/> most cruelly shut out against all the avenues of industry<lb/> betook themselves to that by which they would at time<lb/> keep back the hand of the fell persecutor&#44; or procure a shelter<lb/> among pitiless tyrants&#44; greedy of Jewish gold.  Nor have<lb/> I the wish to reason before you&#44; whether by our<lb/> altered social condition&#44; when money has become a<lb/> commodity&#44; a staple of commerce&#44; the giving and<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>taking  should ought not to be allowed&#45;&#45;except in the case<lb/> of extreme poverty need&#44; as contemplated in the scriptures&#44;<lb/> namely&#44; when our brother has waxen poor&#44; and fallen<lb/> into decay.  My object was principally to show<lb/> that ignorance misleads many&#44; that a the want of a<lb/> correct knowledge of the Scriptures in their original<lb/> works most banefully against the religion of our<lb/> fathers.  Ignorance is a monster which we must<lb/> fight with the weapons of intellect&#44; sharpened in<lb/> our homes&#44; sharpened in our synagogues&#45;&#45;the laboratory<lb/> of spiritual science.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
