<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF9_5</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff9_5_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff9_5_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff9_5_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff9_5_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff9_5_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff9_5_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff9_5_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff9_5_4v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>6 pages on 2 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For a funeral<lb/></p>
            
            <p>Let none be surprised&#44; that I should perform funeral rites<lb/> over he that lies enshrined within this coffin.  For&#44; she did<lb/> not exclusively belong to a limited number of the house of Jacob.<lb/>  Her actions identified her with the whole community of Israel.<lb/>  The officiating minister of the Synagogue&#44; she mostly frequented&#44;<lb/> will be privileged to recite the sacred prayers of our ritual over<lb/> her mortal remains&#59; but it behooves all who possess a<lb/> knowledge of her sterling qualities to rehearse her praise.<lb/>  And I&#45;&#45;a servant of the God of our fathers&#45;&#45;could not&#44; with&#45;<lb/>&#45;out doing violence to my feelings&#44;&#45;&#45;refrain from exhibiting<lb/> before your vision&#44; what deserves to be set forth as an<lb/> exemplar.  Though not personally enjoying the acquaint&#45;<lb/>&#45;ance of my deceased sister in faith&#44; I learnt sufficiently<lb/> of her character from lips unsullied with falsehood.<lb/>  Sarah Brunswick was represented to me&#44; as a Jewess without<lb/> guile.  What that means I will fr briefly tell.  She<lb/> labored to obtain the approval of her conscience.  Reared<lb/> in the belief that upon the descendants of the men&#44; who<lb/> stood at the foot of Sinai&#44; special duties were divinely<lb/> imposed&#44; she did not presume to cast them aside&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>as intruding upon the Hebrews of America.<lb/></p>
            <p>Thus&#44; by way of illustration&#44; she knew well that to rigidly<lb/> adhere to the dietary laws was to be considered by some behind<lb/> the age&#45;&#45;to employ a vulgar phrase&#45;&#45;; but she consulted the good book.  There she<lb/> found her obligations clearly defined&#44; and those she fol&#45;<lb/>&#45;lowed unswervingly.  Scoffers might also sneer at<lb/> her preparing on the sixth day the food needed for the<lb/> seventh&#44; but she would cheerfully have borne the contumely<lb/> of the whole world&#44; rather than prove faithless to her<lb/> convictions.  Nothing would she permit to pollute her<lb/> dwelling&#44; nothing conflicting with the dictates of the Mosaic<lb/> code and the traditions of the fathers would she admit therein.<lb/>  She aimed at rendering her home&#44; the counterpart of that<lb/> in which she had been bred and educated.  Hence was the<lb/> stranger&#45;&#45;still heedful of the practices of Judaism&#44;&#45;&#45;welcome<lb/> within thes its walls.  And when the solemn seasons arrived&#44;<lb/> instituted as festivals to the Lord&#44; all her surroundings bespoke<lb/> the feelings with which she was inspired.  All betokened<lb/> piety and holiness.  For&#44; it is the wives&#44; it is the<lb/> mothers&#44; that can shed a halo of sanctity round their domiciles&#44;<lb/> and with sorrow I acknowledge that the increasing apathy<lb/> in matters relating to our ancient faith&#44; may partly be ascribed<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>to a degeneracy in the women of Israel.  Much of the simplicity<lb/> of manners which distinguished the sainted beings that gave<lb/> us birth&#44; has been superseded by a fondness for the admiration<lb/> of the worldly&#44; and the latter has engendered the abandoning of<lb/> observances&#44; calculated to keep us distinct&#44; as the missionaries<lb/> of the One adorable God.  Not so&#44; however&#44; with her whose<lb/> loss we bemoan.  She retained to the last&#44; the ancestral charac&#45;<lb/>&#45;teristic.  To be recognized as the disciple of her&#44; whose name<lb/> she bore&#44; of Sarah&#44; concerning whom the Scriptures narrate&#44;<lb/> that she remained in the tent&#45;&#45;formed her highest glory.<lb/>  Therefore have I said&#44; that the congregation over which her husband<lb/> presides&#44; may have a right specially to claim her&#44; yet&#44; she belonged<lb/> to the <sic>entirety</sic> Jewish community.  For&#44; her conduct was a bright<lb/> exponent of habits and principles preserved amid the Hebrew<lb/> race.  But....I am at fault.  That being whose heart<lb/> beats with kindly feelings towards the needy&#44; and who acts<lb/> correspondingly to its promptings&#44; ranges in a sphere of greater<lb/> space than even that which I deemed correct to assign thereto.<lb/>  The social community at large&#44; is the sphere in which<lb/> such a one usefully moves.  Unostentatiously our<lb/> sister went forth to the assistance of her fellow&#45;mortals.<lb/>  But not less effectually did she relieve&#44; because she proceeded<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>noiselessly in her godly task.  Warm were her sympathies<lb/> for those stricken with sickness&#44; for the disease which has<lb/> laid her lifeless before us&#44; was long gnawing on her own vitals.<lb/>  The wailing of the sufferers awakened in her breast sentiments<lb/> of commiseration <sic>equalled</sic> by few.  She yearned towards other<lb/> creatures&#44; because the tenderness showed her assuaged<lb/> her pains.  When agonized by a fatal malady&#44; the melting<lb/> looks of those she who fondly loved her proved a balm.  But greater<lb/> than human love itself&#44; was the restorative she derived from<lb/> communing with her soul.  A profound belief in immorta&#45;<lb/>&#45;lity&#44; calmed her anguish&#44; and prepared her mind for the approach&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing end.  She saw the angel of death draw nigh&#44; and she<lb/> leaned on the arm of her God for safety and salvation.<lb/>  The reliable informant&#44; who supplied the points to which<lb/> I was to refer&#44; related how fervently she appeared to join<lb/> in the prayers he uttered at her bed&#45;side&#44; and the delight<lb/> beaming from her eyes at having been mentioned with<lb/> a blessing before the ark of the holy Law.  Glorious<lb/> belief which smooths the rugged passage leading from<lb/> the terrestrial to the celestial&#33;  Happy thou&#44; my sister&#33;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>who hast traversed it on the wings of faith.  But.....<lb/> my Brethren&#33; would we likewise be ready to take that<lb/> flight&#44; without dreading the future awaiting us beyond<lb/> earthly bounds&#63;  It is not my desire to sadden your hearts.<lb/>  Indeed&#44; the season we celebrate&#44; scarcely warrants dwelling<lb/> upon topics of a sorrowful nature.  For&#44; this month<lb/> memorable for the birth of our natural existence&#44; is commemorative<lb/> also of the erection of the Temple in the wilderness of<lb/> Sinai&#44; and of the munificent offerings brought by the<lb/> princes of our tribes for the service of the Lord.  But&#44; I<lb/> will simply say this&#58; Friends&#33;  Study the lesson taught<lb/> by this coffin&#59; and that which the life of her encased therein&#44;<lb/> has imparted.  Remember that the sun now<lb/> shining brilliantly over our heads may set&#44; while we<lb/> are intent upon following vanity&#44; and a night without<lb/> dawn overtake us unawares.  &#34;Return then to God<lb/> but one day before you die.&#34;  Has that day been re&#45;<lb/>&#45;vealed to thee&#44; my brother&#63;  Dost thou know&#44; my<lb/> sister&#44; how many years you may reckon before you see<lb/> it&#63;  Understand therefore the drift of the Rabbinical<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>aphorism.  Imagine to&#45;morrow to be that day&#44;<lb/> and be ever ready to appear before the bar of divine<lb/> justice with the consciousness of being at peace with<lb/> with your fellow creatures and with your Maker.<lb/>  And you&#44; bereaved husband&#44; you disconsolate children<lb/> of Sarah Brunswick&#44; be comforted in the thought that<lb/> she pi who preceded you to the realms of bliss&#44; has<lb/> left with you abundant riches&#59; aye&#44; a wealth which<lb/> will increase in proportion as you will make use thereof&#59;<lb/> even the inheritance of an excellent example.<lb/></p>
            <p>Follow it.  The practice of virtue will familiarize you<lb/> with habits that shall spiritualize human existence<lb/> will while we are yet in this transitory world.  And when after<lb/> many years of a well spent life&#44; you shall exchange<lb/> the mortal for the immortal&#44; the pious soul&#44; now<lb/> hovering round the throne of the Almighty grace&#44; will greet<lb/> you&#44; exclaiming &#34;Come ye blessed of the Lord&#44; you shall<lb/> not stay outside&#44; for&#44; I did prepare the high place<lb/> wherein ye shall be everlastingly beatified.&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>May this be Thy will O living God.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
