<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF1_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff1_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff1_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff1_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff1_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff1_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff1_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff1_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff1_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff1_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff1_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff1_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff1_1_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>About the authenticity of the Pentateuch<lb/>
                proved by the book of Leviticus.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;<lb/></p>
            <p>The volume of the Pentateuch which we have begun<lb/> this Sabbath is the shortest among the five books of Moses.<lb/>  To ordinary readers&#44; that feature may be rather agreeable.<lb/>  For&#44; with a single exception&#44; Leviticus is merely perceptive&#44;<lb/> that is&#44; it contains an almost unbroken series of rules and<lb/> ordinances.  Nothing intervenes to vary the sameness of its<lb/> character&#44; save the case of a blasphemer&#44; the son of an<lb/> Israelitish women&#44; whom she bore to an idolatrous Egyptian.<lb/>  The history of patriarchal times full of episodes&#44; so touching<lb/> in their simple narrative&#44; as Genesis presents&#59; the stirring<lb/> incidents recorded in Exodus from the birth of the greatest<lb/> lawgiver&#44; to the construction of the first place of Hebrew place&#44; worship&#44;<lb/> whose magnificence contrasted with the plain altar of stone of<lb/> former ages&#59; the description of the twelve tribes moving onward<lb/> under their banners towards the promised land&#44; their &#91;&#63;&#93;&#45;<lb/>march&#44; their fears&#44; their seditions&#44; their derelictions&#44; all<lb/> that which in the book of Numbers enchains the attention&#59;<lb/> the recapitulation of the past as in Deuteronomy&#44; together<lb/> with the fatherly admonitions and parting benedictions of the man<lb/> of God&#44; the perusal of which wins at once the heart&#44; the edifies&#59;<lb/></p> 
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>all of that has no parallel passages in the volumes we<lb/> shall weekly recite in the house of our Lord form this Sab&#45;<lb/>&#45;bath to that which precedes the b week of in which Pentecost falls.<lb/>  Directions about sacrificial rites&#44; prescriptions to remove diseases<lb/> prevalent in the East&#44; regulations concerning agriult agri&#45;<lb/>&#45;culture and rural economy&#44; then&#44; dietary restrictions&#44; the<lb/> appointing of seasons of solemnity and festivity&#44; the enact&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment of moral behests to ensure fair dealings with all persons&#44;<lb/> is what Leviticus mainly comprises.  And yet&#44; inde&#45;<lb/>&#45;pendent of the importance which that volume mus always<lb/> have in the estimation of consistent Israelites&#44; because of<lb/> may of its commands still in force&#44; through the various<lb/> countries of our dispersion&#44; it should elicit deep interest<lb/> as a document sent from on high to certify a truth which<lb/> we hold.  There can be no advantage in disguising a<lb/> fact&#44; which&#44; distastefull though it be&#44; stares us in the face.<lb/>  The criticism of the present age aims to strip the Bible<lb/> of its sanctity&#44; and specially to prove that what we obey<lb/> as the emanation of the inspired wisdom of one man&#44; was<lb/> put together centuries after his death by some unknown<lb/> hands.  That heresy must be fought against by all<lb/> lovers of Judaism.  For&#44; once that our youths have imbibed<lb/> the subversive idea that Moses wrote nothing&#44; or that<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>what he traced might be engraven on twelve stones&#44; the<lb/> believef which has proved a comfort to us amidst the sorest trials&#44;<lb/> and on which our hopes and the hopes of millions besides ourselves<lb/> are built&#44; will be swept away&#59; our offspring will look on<lb/> it with abhorrence as an unmitigated lie.  That heresy must<lb/> be fought against.  In olden times&#44; a son of our race who should<lb/> have pronounced it would have been considered the disturber<lb/> of the public peace&#44; and as such excommunicated.  Denied the<lb/> association of his people&#44; he would either recant and be<lb/> received again into the Synagogue&#44; or he would cease holding<lb/> communion with us altogether&#44; and remain of his own accord&#44;<lb/> outside of our pale.  Just two hundred years ago&#44; a<lb/> philosopher of Jewish parentage&#44; chose the latter course&#44;<lb/> when put under ban for the heterodox views he entertained.<lb/>  But the arms he employed to hurt the cause of religion&#44;<lb/> were sharper than those used by his Rabbi Saul Levy<lb/> Morteira&#44; who sought to save it.  For he reasoned&#44; while<lb/> the other cursed.  We may well be thankful that anathemas<lb/> have lost their power&#59; at any rate among American and<lb/> European communities&#59; for they oppose the spirit of tolerance<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>inherent in our faith&#44; and they are a lamentable abuse<lb/> of authority.  I do not mean to cast reproaches upon<lb/> the Amsterdam ecclesiastical Board that declared Benedict<lb/> Spinoza an individual deserving to be shunned by all<lb/> observant Israelites.  It was the only measure which times<lb/> and circumstances then offered to rid a Jewish Congregation<lb/> of a member whose teachings and example&#44; inculcated Atheisim<lb/> in the shape of Theism&#44; social disorganization under the<lb/> guise of reformation.  To defend verities with the weapons<lb/> supplied by by the intellect&#45;&#45;sound arguments&#45;&#45;was an<lb/> art very little known in those days&#44; and the least practised.<lb/>  But now it is&#44; on the contrary&#44; as it should be the exclusive<lb/> means to which we must resort&#44; in order to repel the attacks<lb/> made on our sacred citadel.<lb/></p>
            <p>Well&#58; My hearers&#33;  Leviticus standing in the middle of<lb/> the Pentateuch&#44; may be compared to an iron bar fastening<lb/> tightly together as an indivisible unity the two preceding<lb/> and the two succeeding books of Moses.  You must have observed noticed<lb/> that the bulk of it is devoted to directions relative to animal<lb/> sacrifices.  I shall not discuss at present whether that<lb/> manner of worship was a concession to the time&#44; as Maimonides<lb/> intimates&#44; or whether it was an institution designed to<lb/> <sic>to</sic> honor the Lord&#44; as much as public fasts&#44; and holy convocations.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Walking in the light of history&#44; I am led to think that<lb/> the immolation of irrational beings upon the altar&#44; either<lb/> as a present to the Deity&#44; or as an expiation for sin&#44; was a<lb/> natural instinct among the ancients&#44; which our religion<lb/> sanctified by surrounding the act with imposing ceremonies&#44;<lb/> and significant symbols.  And being of that opinion&#44;<lb/> I could not consent to abolish every reference in our ri&#45;<lb/>&#45;tual to the Temple service and to its restoration.  But<lb/> what I intend to explain to day is this.  Critics have<lb/> asserted that the Pentateuch ha bears internal evidences of<lb/> being the work of many minds and of different epochs&#44; and<lb/> that blind prejudice alone I can ascribe its composition to<lb/> a single individual.  Against that gratuitous assertion&#44;<lb/> I place the third book&#44; we call&#44; of Moses and principally our<lb/> Parasha&#44; and I wish you&#44; my Brethren&#44; to contrast its contents<lb/> with that of the Haftarah we have just read.  The author<lb/> of the former attaches a high importance to sacrifices&#44; for<lb/> he minutely tells how each should be performed to render<lb/> it acceptable&#59; the author of the latter assures his contem&#45;<lb/>&#45;poraries&#44; who did not willingly bring the prescribed oblations&#44;<lb/> that God was tired of their sins&#44; wearied with their iniquities&#44;<lb/> that He did not care to fatigue them with the presentation<lb/> of sweet perfume&#44; and the choice of the flock&#44; if they deemed it<lb/> a trouble.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>for&#44; when He blotted out their transgressions&#44; ti was through<lb/> His own loving&#45;kindness and not through the blood of<lb/> slaughtered animals.  The question rises spontaneously.<lb/>  Would a writer posterior to the writer of our Haftarah<lb/> have given such prominence to sacrificial rites&#44; as we see in<lb/> our Parasha&#63;  And mark&#44; my hearers&#33; in the instance I<lb/> have quoted Isaiah is not so pronounced about the inefficacy<lb/> of offerings as means of atonement.  In other passages he<lb/> openly declares them incapable by themselves to wash<lb/> away the stains of the soul.  Now&#58; the son of Amoz lived<lb/> full 600 years after the son of Amram&#59; &#40;and though according to<lb/> some who deny him the authorship of 26 chapter of his<lb/> work&#44; what I have perused to&#45;day was penned during the<lb/> Babylonian exile 200 years later&#41;; I ask common sense.<lb/>  Would say that had heard the opinion of Isaiah&#44; or of<lb/> Hosea living about the same century&#44; &#38; who cried &#34;take with<lb/> you words&#44; and return unto the Lord.&#34;....Let us pay for<lb/> steers with our lips&#59;&#34; or of Amos&#44; another contemporary&#44;<lb/> who said in the name of the Lord &#34;though you should<lb/> offer me burnt&#45;offerings....I will not accept them with favor&#59;&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>or if Micah still another coeval with Isaiah&#44; who taught<lb/> that the Almighty is not to be appeased by the immolation<lb/> of thousands of rams&#44; would any&#44; I ask again&#44; have deli&#45;<lb/>&#45;neated a book the main portion of which is to prove the<lb/> slaughtering of animals an acceptable worship&#44; and an<lb/> expiatory agency&#63;  When then was Leviticus penned&#63;  Surely<lb/> not at that period of history in which Isaiah flourished.<lb/>  Did it come to light earlier&#44; when Samuel lived&#58;&#44; Samuel when he lived<lb/> who left us this sublime aphorism &#34;obedience is better than<lb/> sacrifice&#34;; or later in the days of Jeremiah&#44; who adorned<lb/> his people to join the burnt&#45;offerings together with the flesh<lb/> of the beasts that had killed for their own use&#44; and eat all<lb/> together&#63;  Was it perhaps concocted during the captivity&#44;<lb/> when sacrifices dared not be brought&#63;  Oh&#33;  I have<lb/> cornered you O f hypocritic.  Moses alone could have com&#45;<lb/>&#45;posed a book volume&#44; necessary to his polity&#59; essential for the<lb/> conducting of the service of that Tabernacle&#44; which was con&#45;<lb/>&#45;stantly to recall the presence of the Deity among the liberated<lb/> bondmen of Egypt.  Moses composed it in the name of<lb/> His Divine Master that Israel must know and feel that<lb/> when they voluntarily parted with some of their substance<lb/> to bring it as a gift to the house of the Lord&#44; the Bestower<lb/> of all good&#44; was honored by the sentiment which prompted the actions&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>that when they sinned and repented&#44; their contrition symbo&#45;<lb/>&#45;lized by the rites practised at the altar was accepted above.<lb/>  Moses whose glorious song upon the shore of the red&#45;sea&#44;<lb/> showed that to build a Sanctuary for the Lord was&#44; a burning<lb/> wish of his heart.  Moses whose words in the chapter sup&#45;<lb/>&#45;plementing the Decalogue&#59; foreshadowed the ordinance<lb/> of festive offerings.  Moses the leading spirit of what<lb/> is narrated before the book of Leviticus&#44; and afterwards&#44; wrote<lb/> that and all else which bears his n venerated name.<lb/>  Nor is there any antagonism between his teachings and that<lb/> of his disciples&#44; the prophets&#44; regarding the institution of<lb/> animal sacrifices.  It is because what he designed as a<lb/> noble means was <sic>wofully</sic> misunderstood as the final<lb/> end&#44; that he Seers thundered against a worship he<lb/> had established&#59; because the hand which brought an expiatory<lb/> oblation still held the gain of oppression&#44; because the lips which<lb/> made confessions lied and spoke wantonness&#44; because<lb/> hypocrisy characterized the service rendered at the Jerusalem<lb/> Temple&#44; Isaiah and all that gl galaxy of great and good<lb/> men of old&#44; that illumined the Jewish horizon&#44; looked down<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>with noble righteous wrath on a presentation to the altar which<lb/> Israel of old frequently made.  They were reformers&#44; not<lb/> to overthrow but to rebuild upon sound foundations.<lb/></p>
            <p>May we learn from them wisdom.  May we appear into<lb/> the courts of our God not to gratify our personal feelings&#44;<lb/> not to attract the worldly and win the applause of novelty<lb/> seekers&#44; but to humbly beseech the Lord of all flesh to be<lb/> with us in the narrow and devious paths we have to<lb/> tread in this nether life&#44; and help us to gain the heights<lb/> where repose and joy will be the lot of those that have<lb/> adhered to truth&#44; and endeavoured to perform their duty.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
