<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF7_19</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff7_19_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff7_19_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff7_19_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff7_19_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff7_19_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff7_19_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff7_19_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff7_19_4v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>6 pages on 2 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For a funeral<lb/></p>
            <p>The officiating Rabbi of the congregation to which Mr David<lb/> Kohn is attached&#44; laboring under an indisposition&#44; which<lb/> prevents his speaking&#44; commissioned me to act in his stead<lb/> on the present melancholy occasion.  I readily assumed the<lb/> task&#44; because I am taught by the religion we revere&#44; O fellow<lb/> Israelites&#33; that to comfort the mourners&#44; and purposely seek<lb/> them that we may give expression to our sympathies&#44; is a<lb/> duty&#44; while we will acquire by it a merit in the sight of<lb/> our God.  I come not to eulogise the dead.  Human<lb/> praise cannot add to the bliss&#44; which a just God reserves<lb/> for the upright among his creatures.  I come not to<lb/> pronounce a panegyric&#44; which might sound like flattery<lb/> to the living&#59; I come to lament for and with my bereaved<lb/> fellow&#45;creatures.  I come as the interpreter of sentiments&#44;<lb/> which an event so sorrowful as that which we now wit&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness must awaken in every breast.  Many of us have<lb/> felt the void&#44; which a lasting separation from those we<lb/> loved well&#44; creates. in our midst Many of us have been<lb/> wrenched with agony at the thought that the voice&#44; that which<lb/> spoke to us words of endearment&#44; has been for ever hushed<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>in the silent grave.  And when the object whose loss we<lb/> bewail is a mother&#44; then the delightful reminiscences of<lb/> the days that have gone&#44; crowd our memory&#44; and we cannot<lb/> contemplate the absence of that being from amidst our<lb/> family circle&#44; without experiencing a sense of utter<lb/> desolation.  We remember the pleasures of childhood&#44;<lb/> fostered and heightened by the cares of a mother&#44; now<lb/> lying lifeless in a coffin.  The delight experienced occasioned<lb/> at our restoration to health&#44; through the ceaseless attention&#44;<lb/> the sleepless nights&#44; the breathless watching of our tutelary<lb/> angel on earth.  The  gratification pictured on her countenance<lb/> at the effect in our character of her good training. in our characters  The<lb/> pride she evinced at our promotion in the community.<lb/>  All that which binds us with the silvery chords of ever&#45;<lb/>&#45;lasting gratitude to the preserver of our early years&#44; flashes<lb/> before our minds&#44; and we are all but crushed with grief&#44;<lb/> at the death of our mother.  The Royal Psalmist&#44; whose<lb/> life was exposed to many vicissitudes&#44; could not find a<lb/> stronger expression to his human sorrow&#44; than by comparing it<lb/> with that of one that mourneth for his a mother.<lb/>  Such feelings&#44; more than ordinarily experienced under a cir&#45;<lb/>&#45;cumstance similar to this&#44; pervade the soul of the only<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>surviving child of Mistress Janette Wolf.  At the hour<lb/> that she bid the world a last farewell&#44; her daughters remem&#45;<lb/>&#45;bered that she owed this lamented Jewess a twofold tribute<lb/> of respect and thankfulness.  For the same hand which<lb/> had directed her first steps&#44; became also the guide of the<lb/> children to whom Mistress Emma Kohn has given birth.<lb/>  Our friend was not conspicuous for talents&#44; but her industrious<lb/> habits&#44; her thriftiness&#44; her attachment to the principles and<lb/> observances of the ancestral faith&#44; and that spotless character<lb/> she possessed as a wife and a mother in Israel&#44; were<lb/> lessons infinitely superior to those in worldly knowledge.<lb/>  The qualities of the mind and of the heart&#44; which formed<lb/> her bright adornment&#44; the virtues&#44; which&#44; as I have learnt<lb/> from those who knew her intimately&#44; she could exhibit before<lb/> her household&#44; were indeed a bright model&#44; which her<lb/> daughter&#39;s descendants may well endeavour to copy.<lb/>  Like one of the women&#44; depicted by the pen of inspiration&#44;<lb/> she built her own house&#44; and the house of her daughter.<lb/>  Not by raising marble pillars&#44; and carved balusters&#44;<lb/> but by indefatigable labor to promote the welfare of those<lb/> among whom she enjoyed comfort and peace.<lb/>  And her efforts were rewarded.  They found a compensation&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>in the devotion of &#91;&#63;&#93; her daughter &#44;and in the dutiful<lb/> consideration&#44; and deference of the daughter&#39;s husband.<lb/>  Our sister in faith&#44; while treading the path of life&#44; did<lb/> not always eschew the ills and woes to which we all are<lb/> heir.  At one period of our existence&#44; the way became<lb/> exceedingly narrow&#44; so that she and her life&#45;copartner<lb/> had to walk in <sic>straitness</sic> yet&#44; she bore it all resignedly.  But And through the hep help<lb/> of God&#44; the path gradually widened&#44; and hardships<lb/> fled away.  And if the untimely decease of a son<lb/> and daughter&#44; has threatened to bring her also to an<lb/> early grave&#44; the teachings of that blessed religion to which<lb/> she adhered&#44; and the solicitude of her surviving relatives<lb/> soothed her pains&#44; and infused within her fresh courage.<lb/>  This thought should afford my bereaved friends real<lb/> comfort.  They performed one of the most sacred<lb/> ordinances of our faith&#59; that which has divine promises<lb/> in the hi right&#45;hand&#44; joyous fo the joys of self&#45;ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;proval in the left.  Janette Wolf&#44; has paid<lb/> her debt to nature&#59; for dust must return to dust.<lb/>  Having reached the end of her pilgrimage&#44; she landed on the<lb/> regions above.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>But the spirit of the honored mother&#44; is even now<lb/> beatified by the veneration in which her memory is<lb/> held.  She casts a look on this solemn gathering.<lb/>  She sees those who moan and weep because of her de&#45;<lb/>&#45;parture&#44; and she bids them wipe those their tearful eyes<lb/> and be comforted.  Bending at the footstool of the<lb/> throne of God&#44; she prays that the reward of filial respect<lb/> and filial support be continuance of health&#44; competence<lb/> and peace.<lb/></p>  
            <p>And you aged Sire&#33;  You who in the snowy winter of your<lb/> existence have been left destitute of the sweet companion&#45;<lb/>ship of a wife.  You that&#44; above all&#44; must feel utterly<lb/> desolate&#44; lean upon God.  Let that divine trust be the<lb/> staff with which you will ascend the fortress of your<lb/> refuge.  Like in the trials of the past&#44; seek shelter<lb/> under the shadow of the Most High&#44; and you will<lb/> be celestially protected.  Abide yet awhile here below&#44;<lb/> in the contemplation of surroundings&#44; which must afford<lb/> you comfort&#44; and when the last hour shall have struck&#44;<lb/> and when that part of yours which is mortal&#44; shall change<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>for the immortal&#44; you shall will meet a<lb/> spirit greeting you coming to the fields of<lb/> eternity&#44; where you will gather pleasures<lb/> that have no alloy&#44; delights which hourly<lb/> increase.  So may it be&#44; O consoler of<lb/> the afflicted&#33;  Shower down an abundance of<lb/> comfort on those that grieve.  Uphold their steps&#44; that they may not sink through the oppression of<lb/> sorrow.  And <sic>fulfil</sic> in each of them&#44; the sentence<lb/> of Thy inspired David servant.  &#34;Let him call<lb/> upon me&#44; and I will answer him&#59; I shall be with<lb/> him in trouble&#44; I will deliver him and make him<lb/> honorable.  I will satisfy him with length of days&#44;<lb/> and show him my salvation.&#34;  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
