<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF19_11</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_11_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_11_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_11_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_11_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_11_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_11_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_11_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_11_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_11_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_11_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_11_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_11_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For the Sabbath after the<lb/>
                fall holidays&#44; about the reopening<lb/>
                of the various Schools.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  The prophecy foretelling that handsome vir&#45;<lb/>&#45;gins and young men shall faint away from a thirst&#44;<lb/> which they will not be able to quench&#44; is the picture of<lb/> a tardy revival among the elders of the nation.  We&#44; the<lb/> descendants of those whom Amos addressed&#44; should pray that<lb/> the hunger which is not for bread and the thirst which is<lb/> not for water&#44; but only for hearing the word of the Lord&#44; may<lb/> always find in our midst ample means of satisfaction.  But more than<lb/> pray for it&#44; we must act towards it.  To gratify a wish for<lb/> the knowledge of our doctrines&#44; our history and literature should be<lb/> the joint endeavours of Israelites&#44; who honestly desire seek the perpetuity of<lb/> the Sinaic religion.  It would be idle to state what every<lb/> one of my hearers understands&#44; and perhaps has at times felt&#58;<lb/> I mean&#44; that as we form a very small minority in the popu&#45;<lb/>&#45;lation of Philadelphia&#44; our sons and daughters are exposed to<lb/> influences apt to prejudice their minds against all that ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;clusively belongs to Judaism.  But just because it<lb/> is unquestionably so&#44; it behooves us to avail ourselves of the<lb/> agencies by which we may counteract the tendency of baleful<lb/> surroundings.  Those agencies are three&#44; and it rests with<lb/> us to make each of them effective.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Home precept is the first in rank&#44; the readiest at hand and<lb/> the very best.  Like noiseless but steady rain which sinks into<lb/> the soil and practifies it&#44; is the instruction drawn at the family&#45;<lb/>hearth.  It may not always have great breadth&#44; but it has<lb/> depth and the element of indestructiveness&#44; that is&#44; if the parents<lb/> show an intelligent appreciation of the Law and traditions&#44;<lb/> and their characters vitalize the lessons imparted.  This truth<lb/> is self&#45;evident and needs not be illustrated or enlarged upon.<lb/></p>
            <p>The second agency is school&#45;teaching.  Not that communicated<lb/> under the auspices of a non&#45;religious commonwealth&#44; and which<lb/> ought to be perfectly free of a non&#45;religious commonwealth&#44; and which<lb/> ought to be perfectly free from whatever partakes of the dogmatic<lb/> or the denominational&#44; but the learning of the Cheder&#45;&#45;as our<lb/> German fellow&#45;believers call the Hebrew school room&#44; or the learning<lb/> taught in our vernacular tongue in kindred institutions.  It is<lb/> there that our children&#44; specially those who cannot afford to<lb/> engage a private tutors&#44; must gain a familiar acquaintance<lb/> with the tenets of their faith and the events and writings<lb/> of the past which that explain the vicissitudes which that faith<lb/> has undergone.  Now that no holiday will call<lb/> us away from the undertaking&#44; let us direct our attention to<lb/> that important agency of Jewish preservation&#59; make the greatest<lb/> number possible benefit therefromby&#44; and introduce improvements<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>to satisfy the young who hunger and thirst after the<lb/> words of the Lord.  Our four schools in which the<lb/> sacred tongue language is cultivated in its rudiments&#44; can add to their<lb/> utility by training the attending pupils also in the main prayers<lb/> common to our people&#44; and in the meaning and origin of<lb/> outward observances.  That knowledge will prove of double<lb/> advantage.  It will render Synagogue worship in reality public<lb/> worship&#44; and interest the rising generation in the proceedings<lb/> of our religious convocations.  But the two Sunday<lb/> Schools North and South&#44; to which I have lately alluded and<lb/> which will open their sessions to&#45;morrow morning&#44; owe it to<lb/> the future of Judaism in Philadelphia&#44; they owe it to the memory<lb/> of their founder&#44; and to their own honor to silence a captious opposition<lb/> by showing palpably demonstrating that they are perform more than a negative good.  They<lb/> must prove show that they are a positive agency of progress.  Let the work<lb/> be amplified&#44; and a larger corps of capable laborers to accom&#45;<lb/>&#45;plish it well set themselves to the task.  Every one<lb/> of my hearers can assure his or her neighbor that Jewish child&#45;<lb/>&#45;ren will be trained in the history of the Bible&#44; not simply<lb/> by memorizing the wording thereof&#44; but by being told the causes<lb/> and effects of events&#44; regardless of persons&#44; and always in obedience<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>to truth.  Every one can give the assurance of an eagerness<lb/> felt for initiating hundreds of our little ones in their ancestral<lb/> belief&#44; and in the exercises of devotion by joint hymns and<lb/> psalmody.  There would be ample scope for another<lb/> school of the same character in a locality thickly inhabited by<lb/> b our coreligionists&#44; but let&#44; at all events&#44; the two now existing<lb/> be diligently and unremittingly cared for from this time to the summer of next<lb/> year.  I&#44; on my part&#44; shall try to contribute in ren&#45;<lb/>&#45;dering that agency an element of lasting advantage.  I<lb/> invite all my little brothers and sisters in faith to form a<lb/> much larger class than that I taught during the last term&#44;<lb/> from 9 o&#39;clock to half past 10 on Sunday&#45;morning.  The only<lb/> requisite for admission is a passable knowledge of reading Hebrew.<lb/>  After the hour just mentioned&#44; I shall aid the superintendent<lb/> of the Northern School in explaining the Scriptures.<lb/></p>
            <p>But it is my wish&#44; as it is my duty&#44; to impart more than the<lb/> rudiments of a language which possesses a rich and varied<lb/> literature.  Formerly&#44; I taught several lads every afternoon day&#44;<lb/> after day public school hours&#44; in the prophets and the hagiographa.<lb/>  Subsequently&#44; I agreed to let my reverend colleagues share in<lb/> the undertaking.  This plan&#44; however&#44; proved a failure&#44; and I<lb/> could not succeed in bringing together again those who had studied<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>under my exclusive tuition.  To day I announce my readi&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness to resume what was discontinued for no fault of mine&#44;<lb/> and tell so that this publicly in order that it may be repeated abroad&#44; that&#44; as heretofore&#44;<lb/> boys or young men of any congregation or of no congregation in our<lb/> city will have my time and my books at their disposal each afternoon from<lb/> 4 &#189; to 6 &#189; o clock. p m  In the evenings I shall<lb/> instruct twice a week in higher branches branches two intelligent<lb/> youths <sic>worshipping</sic> in this synagogue. It would afford me<lb/> real satisfaction to extend the time and the number of attendants&#44;<lb/> but evidently Talmudical and philosophical works have no<lb/> attraction for the rising generation of Israelites in Philadelphia.<lb/>  Very exceptional are the instances in which a disposition to<lb/> acquire some ideas of the contents from the original itself is<lb/> manifested.  But that absence of hunger and thirst<lb/> to hear the words of our Sages acts as is to me an incentive in me to<lb/> utilize the pulpit as the third agency&#44; which ought to be made<lb/> effective in counteracting evil influences.  Admonitory<lb/> sermons may recall the hearers to a sense of duty&#44; and<lb/> prevent further trespassing&#44; but Israelites must know more<lb/> than their religious obligations.  They must know how to ele&#45;<lb/>&#45;vate the name they bear by a culture broad enough to<lb/> serve as a shield against the attacks of ridicule.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>when odious comparisons hel are drawn between the fathers of<lb/> church and the Rabbins&#44; when the books of which we may<lb/> boast are decried as an accumulation of rubbish&#44; and their<lb/> heads with shame for want of information.  They should<lb/> raise them aloft&#44; through the light they can throw on sub&#45;<lb/>&#45;jects that prejudice misrepresents.  In the hope<lb/> of partly furnishing that useful information&#44; I purpose delivering<lb/> a course of historical lectures&#44; short and easy&#44; in which the<lb/> lives and deeds of our ancient preceptors may receive obtain the<lb/> grateful approval of my hearers.  I shall&#44; however&#44; thank&#45;<lb/>&#45;full follow any suggestion in that line or in any other deemed<lb/> better calculated to instruct and interest.  For I have not<lb/> had the time lately at my command to mature a plan which may commends it&#45;<lb/>&#45;self to my every understanding&#45;&#45;the last holidays having entirely absorbed<lb/> my thoughts&#44; and since their expiration a correspondence unavoidably<lb/> neglected having engaged my attention.  I desire therefore to<lb/> be helped in the great object of delivering our children from an<lb/> ignorance which may cost us the loos of their hearts.  They will<lb/> be won by gentilism or incredulity&#44; unless we excite and gratify hun&#45;<lb/>&#45;ger and thirst for hearing the words of the Lord and of the Sages.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Parents at their fire&#45;sides&#44; directors and directresses in Hebrew<lb/> and in Sunday Schools&#44; teachers at their desks&#44; and ministers in<lb/> their pulpits&#44; though working in different ways&#44; are all con&#45;<lb/>&#45;verging towards one single point.  Let them vie with one<lb/> another in the effort to draw the nearest to it&#44; and the<lb/> preservation of Judaism in Philadelphia will become an<lb/> accomplished fact.  No more will it be said that<lb/> a child born in Israel is a stranger in the house of his<lb/> God&#44; or that he was entrapped in the meshes spread out<lb/> by our religious opponents because of a training defective education weak<lb/> and impotent.  For his heart shall issue from a Jewish<lb/> mould&#44; and his understanding will be shapen in a<lb/> Judaic form.  The prophecy of Amos that handsome<lb/> virgins and young men shall faint away for a thirst&#44; which<lb/> they shall be unable to quench&#44; will receive no confirmation<lb/> here.  On the contrary&#44; the glorious prediction of Isaiah<lb/> will find a realization in our midst through our united<lb/> endeavours and the help of God.  &#34;They shall not hunger<lb/> nor thirst&#44; neither shall the heat nor the sea smite them&#44;<lb/> for He that has mercy on them shall be their Leader&#44;<lb/> even by the springs of water shall he guide them&#34;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
