<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF3_16</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_16_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_16_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_16_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_16_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_16_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_16_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_16_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_16_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_16_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_16_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_16_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_16_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Post&#45;Biblical lecture<lb/>
                16th<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  The historian would have a delightful task&#44;<lb/> if he could always relate that families who rose to eminence&#44;<lb/> in a community&#44; through their own praiseworthy demeanour&#44;<lb/> succeeded in maintaining&#44; for ages&#44; their standing and re&#45;<lb/>&#45;putation.  But instances of that kind are more than<lb/> rare.  Often&#44; too often&#44; pride&#44; ambition&#44; avarice&#44; many unruly<lb/> passions supplant destroy the seeds of ancestral virtues&#44; so that the second or<lb/> third generation will witnesses a sad decline. in the  They will see the descendants of<lb/> those&#44; whose greatness seemed destined to continue without end sadly chan deteriorated changed.<lb/>  A melancholy illustration of this fact&#44; are is offered by the offspring<lb/> of John Hyrcanus.  The rule of that son of Simon&#44; the As&#45;<lb/>&#45;monean&#44; had brought redounded to his glory to himself and to that of Israel.<lb/>  With the exception of his having allowed the error he committed&#44; in his latter<lb/> days&#44; in having allowed a fit of anger&#44; to estrange him from the popular<lb/> Pharisees&#44; and make &#91;&#63;&#93; draw him favor among towards the aristocratic Saducees&#44;<lb/> his life was an uninterrupted series of triumphs to<lb/> the national cause.  Not so the life of his<lb/> successors.  Hyrcanus had left five sons&#44; but his<lb/> last will and testament declared demanded directed that his wife was to should<lb/> act as regent&#44; till his second son Antigonus had<lb/> grown older.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Possibly&#44; the remembrance of that banquet&#44; which had was<lb/> attended with unfortunate consequences&#45;&#45;as I explained in my last lecture<lb/> of the course&#45;&#45;had taught the Prince wisdom.  He may have determined the dying ruler to make provisions<lb/> for a separation of church and state.  He may have wished<lb/> finally to entrust Aristobulus&#44; the his eldest&#44; with the government&#44;<lb/> and to invest Antigonus with the priesthood.  But Aris&#45;<lb/>&#45;tobulus goaded on by an uncontrollable greed of for power&#44;<lb/> seized the supreme command before his mother could had the time to set forth and enforce her<lb/> claims.  With horror I tell it.  He cast into a<lb/> prison her that had given him birth into a prison and having put laid<lb/> his three in fetters three of his brothers&#44; who might have opposed his audacity&#44;<lb/> in fetters&#44; assumed the a title never worn by his pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;decessors&#44; that of King of the Jews.  But Destitute<lb/> as that unrighteous king was of the moral qualities which had adorned exalted characterized his family&#44; he<lb/> possessed nevertheless the military prowess of the Mac&#45;<lb/>&#45;cabean race.  He had fought side by side with<lb/> his father in the campaign against the Samaritans&#44; Samaria&#44;<lb/> and his younger brother had been his brave companion<lb/> on the field of battle.  Aristobulus was therefore<lb/> partial to Antigonus&#59; and had even shown a disposition<lb/> to make him share the kingdom.  But the prophet has<lb/> written&#59; that the wicked are like a troubled sea&#44; which cannot<lb/> rest.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Such was the precise state of Aristobulus&#45;&#45;rolling and tossing upon a sea of fears.  His wife Salome&#44;<lb/> or Alexandra&#44; who disliked her young brother in law&#44; had poisoned<lb/> the mind of her husband.  She insinuated that Anti&#45;<lb/>&#45;gonus was plotting to make himself absolute ruler the sole king.  And<lb/> he who had cause to fear dread Divine vengeance punishment&#44; believed.<lb/></p>
            <p>Antigonus had just won a brilliant victory over the<lb/></p> <p>Itureans&#45;&#45;an Arab tribe&#44; whom he&#44; wrongfully&#44; compelled to<lb/> accept Judaism&#45;&#45;and come back had returned home covered with glory.<lb/>  Aristobulus who was lying sick at the time&#44; heard of his<lb/> brother&#39;s return arrival&#44; of his having gone to the Temple followed by<lb/> his conquering victorious soldiers&#44; and dressed in a magnificent armour&#44;<lb/> of his having stood forth and offered a prayer for the recovery<lb/> of the king&#44; and of the deep impression his appearance had<lb/> made.  Queen Salome and her favorites&#44; playing on<lb/> the excitable temperament of Aristobulus&#44; interpreted that<lb/> incident with malice aforethought.  They alleged that Anti&#45;<lb/>&#45;gonus was trying false&#59; that he tried to ingratiate himself with the people&#44;<lb/> and that he was so as to preapreing the way to get rid of for supplanting his brother&#44;<lb/> at the first opportunity.  Aristobulus was loth to credit<lb/> it&#44; for in reality he loved the valiant Antigonus.  Accordingly&#44; he sought<lb/> an interview with the latter&#44; and sent a message that he should<lb/> immediately present himself immediately at the palace.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>But he gave secret orders that if his brother came <lb/>in his military garments&#44; he should be killed before<lb/> he reached the king&#39;s chamber.  The treacherous queen<lb/> won the messengers over to her side&#44; and induced them<lb/> to say to the unsuspecting youth&#44; that the king desired<lb/> to see how splendidly he looked in the new armour he<lb/> had lately worn.  Antigonus was crossing a dark<lb/> passage leading from the Temple to the royal castle<lb/> of Baris&#44; when the dagger of an assassin slew struck him dead.<lb/>  The news of that unnatural death tragedy&#44; brought on the unnatural<lb/> son and brother a paraxism of grief which culminated<lb/> into a severe hemorrhage.  The servant who carried<lb/> away the basin fell on the spot in which Antigonus had<lb/> been murdered&#44; and the blood of the wicked met that of<lb/> the innocent which cried for vengeance.  Artistobulus slew the hand of a Righteous<lb/> Judge sle stretched to strike him&#44; and he soon expired<lb/> in the agonies of remorse.<lb/></p>
            <p>His demise was the deliverance release of his imprisoned brothers.<lb/>  The mother had died&#45;&#45;I prefer to believe from her having denied<lb/> herself food in her anguish of mind&#44; than to credit the report<lb/> that Aristobulus had starved her to death.  By the influence<lb/> of Salome&#44; Alexander Janneus was crowned king.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Of all the sons of John Hyrcamus&#44; Janneus&#44; or Yanna&#239;<lb/> as he is called in the Talmud&#44; ought to have been the excluded<lb/> last to raise from power holding sway.  For his father had entertained shown an open<lb/> dislike to for against him.  Josephus attributes it to a certain dream<lb/> at the time of the child&#39;s birth&#44; but it may be that other<lb/> motives influenced the parent.  If this had entertained fore&#45;<lb/>&#45;bodings about the future of that son&#44; his presentiments were fearfully too well founded.<lb/>  realized.  For Alexander Janneus marked stained his first<lb/> step to the throne with the blood of one of his surviving brothers&#44;<lb/> allowing while he let the other&#44; who was of a peaceful temperament&#44; to live<lb/> in honored comfortable obscurity.  To tell the history of that<lb/> Asmonean ruler&#44; would be to relate the history of foreign<lb/> and civil wars&#44; of defeat and discontent&#44; of infidelity and<lb/> immorality.  It would be to show a stormy life&#44; which began<lb/> in blood shed and ended in debauchery.  For the warlike<lb/> disposition of Janneus led him to constant fighting&#44; in which<lb/> he was seldom victorious and frequently vanquished.  He<lb/> fought the Syrians and lost&#59; he fought the Arabs and lost&#44;<lb/> and as a mutual hatred existed between the King and the<lb/> bulk of his people&#44; he surrounded himself with foreign troops.<lb/>  Like the Popes of Rome before the unification of Italy that Jewish Pontiff called upon his<lb/> Swiss soldiers to slaughter away&#44; whenever he found his temporal<lb/> or sacerdotal dominion in jeopardy.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>The Judeans were belonged mostly to the sect of the Pharisees.  They looked with dissatis&#45;<lb/>&#45;faction upon a descendant of Mattathias&#44; who openly provokingly defied<lb/> the ancestral traditions.  One day&#44; on the feast of Taber&#45;<lb/>&#45;nacles&#44; when Janneus was about to offer the libations in<lb/> a manner contrary to rule&#44; a Pharisee threw at the King<lb/> the citron he was carrying in his hand&#44;&#45;&#45;an indignity&#44; which<lb/> others soon imitated.  That scandalous scene in the Temple&#44;<lb/> cost the lives of six thousand persons&#44; who had assembled for<lb/> the worship.  During a number of years&#44; Alexander<lb/> Janneus contended against struggled in vain to over crush the revolutionary party&#44; which<lb/> constituted the largest majority of the Jewish people.<lb/>  Over fifty thousand perished through that unhappy<lb/> struggle contest.  Weary of the contest&#44; i&#91;&#63;&#93; quarrels&#44; the king took occasion advantage<lb/> of a signal victory he had gained&#44; to send for the national representatives&#44;<lb/> of the nation&#44; and ask what he could do to bring about<lb/> a reconciliation.  &#34;To die&#44;&#34; was the instantaneous reply.<lb/>  The answer widened the rapture&#44; but Janneus knew how<lb/> to take revenge for public insults.  His cruelties were gained<lb/> for him the horrid epithet of &#34;Doker&#34; Assassin.<lb/>  Some of are of opinion that the name given him&#44; by reason<lb/> of his ferocity&#44; was &#34;Thracida&#44;&#34; meaning barbarous&#44; as the<lb/> Thracians were reputed to have been.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>But I dislike am loth to dwell on a subject which brings to<lb/> view the degeneracy shocking depravity of a scion of the illustrious Asmonean<lb/> family.  English speaking Jews will find an elaborate ac&#45;<lb/>&#45;count of the reign of Alexander Janneus&#44; written in choice<lb/> language and with much erudition&#44; in the second volume<lb/> of the Post Biblical History of Dr Morris J. Raphall&#44; late<lb/> Rabbi Preacher of in the Ben&#233; Yeshurun congregation of New York.<lb/>  With that Jewish divine&#44; I admit that the authority<lb/> we have&#44; may&#44; in a measure&#44; be prejudiced one sided.  Janneus may<lb/> not have been altogether the monster&#44; which Josephus&#44; who<lb/> was a pronounced sure decided Pharisee&#44; makes him.  That some of<lb/> the Talmudists call him Yanna&#239; &#34;Rashang&#34; wicked&#44; it cannot<lb/> excite surprise&#44; for the Talmud&#44; which is jealous for<lb/> the preservation of ritual laws&#44; could not have transmitted handed down<lb/> a good report of a king&#44; who not alone disobeyed those<lb/> laws&#44; but defied despised and persecuted the guardians thereof.<lb/>  We are told&#44; that when a slave belonging to Janneus had<lb/> been guilty of man&#39;s slaughter&#44; the Sanhedrin&#44; summoned<lb/> also the King.  He came and sat seated himself. down  The<lb/> President&#44; Simon Ben Shattach&#44; said &#34;Rise&#44; for now thou art<lb/> not now in the presence of mortal beings&#44; but before<lb/> the Supreme Judge&#44; whom we represent.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>The King haughtily replied&#58; &#34;Not as thou sayest&#44; but as<lb/> they say.&#34;  Simon Ben Shattach turned to his colleagues&#44; but<lb/> they&#44; intimidated by the looks of the arbitrary ruler&#44; hang<lb/> their down their heads.  The President sternly rebuked their administered a scathing rebuke.<lb/>  At another time&#44; to spite the Pharisees&#44; whose detestation<lb/> of their king was so intense&#44; and as frequently to &#91;&#63;&#93; break out into insur&#45;<lb/>&#45;rections&#44; he slew some and forced others into exile.<lb/></p>
            <p>Simon Ben Shattach&#44; who was the queen&#39;s brother&#44; secreted<lb/> himself&#44; till his sister&#39;s influence restored him to liberty.<lb/>  Yet&#44; notwithstanding his the numerous crimes of Alexander Janneus&#44; it may be that<lb/> prejudice omitted the description of redeeming qualities&#44; and<lb/> painted in darker blacker colours what was sufficiently repulsive.<lb/>  Certain it is&#44; that his was he ever evinced a turbulent spirit.  While<lb/> suffering acutely with a fever&#44; he resolved to lay <sic>seige</sic><lb/> against Ragaba&#45;&#45;a fortress on the eastern side of Palestine.<lb/>  The queen accompanied him in that expedition&#44; from which<lb/> he hoped to issue forth gather a harvest of glory.<lb/>  But the hour had struck&#44; when the degenerate Asmo&#45;<lb/>&#45;nean&#44; would be summoned to the highest tribunal.<lb/>  Terror seized his royal consort&#44; at the thought of what<lb/> might befall herself and her offspring.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>She wept and lamented and begged that he would make<lb/> some disposition for her safety and that of her children.  She<lb/> knew too well how unpopular her family had become.<lb/>  Janneus recommended that she would conceal his death<lb/> from the army&#44; till the fortress had been taken.  She<lb/> should&#44; meanwhile&#44; hasten to Jerusalem and place leading<lb/> Pharisees in important offices.  Then bring some prominent<lb/> members of that sect to view his dead body&#44; and ask<lb/> that they might do with it as they deemed best&#59;<lb/> give it a burial&#44; or expose it to public disgrace.  And<lb/> he added. &#34;If thou wilt follow my advice thou wilt be<lb/> queen&#44; in accordance with my testamentary request&#44; and the<lb/> Pharisees will accord to grant me a funeral more splendid than<lb/> thou couldst ever give.&#34;  Alexandra obeyed the parting<lb/> injunction&#44; and thus she secured for her husband a<lb/> magnificent obsequies&#44; and for herself the throne.<lb/>  In my next lecture I shall speak of her character and<lb/> of the stirring events&#44; during her reign.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
