<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF10_8</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1895-01" source="" attested="yes">1895</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_9_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_9_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_9_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_9_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_9_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_9_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_9_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_9_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_9_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_9_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_9_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_9_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>33<lb/></p>
            <p>95<lb/></p>
            <p>Judaism is not asceticism<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>About a month ago&#44; a solemn ceremony was held performed<lb/> within the borders of Philadelphia.  The description of it&#44;<lb/> touched me deeply. Stirring in its simplicity&#44; suggestive<lb/> in its final purpose&#44; I felt instinctively drawn towards the<lb/> central character in that affecting ceremony.  It was a<lb/> woman whose total negation denial of self laid strong hold of my<lb/> feelings.  Possessed of riches ever abundant&#59; connected by<lb/> family ties with a social circle conspicuous in this city of<lb/> her birth&#44; she renounced the world and all the pleasures it<lb/> affords&#44; in obedience to a religious aspiration.  The brightest<lb/> vision&#44; which wealth and high station set to view&#44;<lb/> paled into a faint shadow before the thought which<lb/> had the full mastery of her soul.  Poverty&#44; chastity and<lb/> lowliness she pledged to the service of sufferers from<lb/> racial prejudices.  That devotee to a cause&#44; which<lb/> she deemed most holy&#44; had founded a sisterhood for<lb/> the evangelization of Indians and colored people in the<lb/> United States.  Kneeling in a secluded spot of the<lb/> chapel&#44; which her gold had built&#44; she entered into a bond&#44;<lb/> that death alone could tear asunder.  I was carried<lb/> away by the idea of so great a sacrifice&#44; and if the con&#45;<lb/>secration of that life to a sentiment inspired by faith&#44; had<lb/> ended in the ceremony&#44; whose description I had read&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>had ended in the ceremony the impression left upon my<lb/> mind&#44; might have lasted a time&#44; though calm reason<lb/> and Judaism would combine to erase it.  But the<lb/> address which followed the ceremony&#44; soon dispelled the<lb/> charm.  He who spoke to command the act&#44; taught<lb/> that to deny oneself all the delights of this existence&#44;<lb/> is to supremely glorify God.  And in order the more strongly to<lb/> emphasize that teaching&#44; he authoritatively assigned as a<lb/> reward for the deed&#44; the privilege of sitting hereafter upon<lb/> twelve celestial thrones and judging the twelve tribes of<lb/> Israel.  I quote the Christian prelate&#44; not by<lb/> way of satire or derision.  My nature and my religion de&#45;<lb/>&#45;mand that I respect sincerity wherever met.  It is<lb/> when under the guise of sincerity&#44; fanaticism rises up uncontrolled<lb/> and overleaps all bounds&#59; when it dares assume a dict&#45;<lb/>&#45;atorship&#44; that what some term sincerity forfeits my<lb/> regard and that of all who think aright.  Admit&#44;<lb/> Catholicism can point to votaries&#44; who honor their<lb/> church by practical benevolence.  I always look<lb/> with reverence upon women who are entitled to the name<lb/> they bear&#45;&#45;&#34;sisters of charity.&#34;  Voluntarily&#44; eagerly&#44; they<lb/> expose their lives to diseases that they may assuage<lb/> in others bodily ailments.  They shrink at nothing&#44;<lb/> however loathsome or revolting&#44; urged on by the power<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>of a sincere belief that in so doing they serve the dei&#45;<lb/>&#45;fied being&#44; whom they adore on earth and whose loving smiling ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;proval love they hope to secure in heaven.  Admirable<lb/> unselfishness&#33;  But having conceded that much without any<lb/> equivocation&#44; I may ask whether the conception which we<lb/> should form of a merciful Creator&#44; warrants a course like<lb/> that which Miss Drexel adopted and an instruction like<lb/> that which Father Scully&#44; who preached the sermon&#44; im&#45;<lb/>&#45;parted.  I know that my negative answer&#44; clashes<lb/> with views that some sensitive Jewesses&#45;&#45;I trust<lb/> they are exceedingly few in number&#45;&#45;some morbidly constituted Jewesses&#44; do entertain.  One<lb/> who had been sorely tried in her affections&#44; lamented in<lb/> my presence&#44; the absence in Judaism of an inspiring strength<lb/> which in Judaism leading to a complete <sic>withdrawl</sic> from a seductive<lb/> world.  Christianity&#45;&#45;she asserted&#45;&#45;is supremely<lb/> spiritual.  It provides a balm for all ills.  Well&#58;<lb/> the Rabbis recommended to make allowances for those a<lb/> whose language is dictated by suffering &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> But I read my Bible without dark spectacles and<lb/> discover a shining brightness.  I discover that God<lb/> rejoiced in contemplating His handiwork&#44; that He and pronounced it<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;very good&#34; to effect the sublime object for<lb/> which it was brought forth&#45;&#45;namely to promote the happiness of His all sentient creatures.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>I do not need search far to learn that our Maker<lb/> wished us to enjoy the fruits of our labor&#44; in a glad&#45;<lb/>some intercourse with others for whose sake also He<lb/> ordered land&#44; sea and sky to <sic>yeilds</sic> blessings profusely.<lb/>  Isaiah&#44; a giant of intellect&#44; contemplating viewing surveying the world<lb/> we live in that we live in&#44; preached this lesson &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Not in vain did God create it.  He formed it for hu&#45;<lb/>&#45;man habitation.  The idea that to shun the world<lb/> we live in and the pleasures with which it teems&#44; is to reach the<lb/> climax of righteousness&#44; opposes the idea underlying the<lb/> object purpose of the creation and&#44; from a Jewish standpoint&#44;<lb/> it offends the Almighty&#44; for it impugns His so&#45;<lb/>&#45;vereign wisdom.  We daily say in our ritual &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Not in the solitariness of a cloister&#44;<lb/> but in the wide world seeking our own happiness<lb/> and the welfare of our companions through the journey<lb/> of life&#44; there is a restorative.  The whole history<lb/> of Israel protests against a gloomy construction of<lb/> religion.  Never were there among us nunneries&#44;<lb/> monasteries&#44; convents.  They would have been in<lb/> open antagonism with to the teaching that the Lord<lb/> is glorified by our gathering His celestial favors<lb/> unitedly&#44; that we must worship Him &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> with joyfulness and gladness of heart &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Serve the Lord with Joy&#44;&#34; exclaims the Psalmist.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>To imbue instill into us with sentiments of gratitude&#44; Moses<lb/> says&#58; &#34;Thou shalt rejoice over all the good that<lb/> the Lord thy God has bestowed on thee and thy house&#45;<lb/>&#45;hold&#44; even on thee and the Levite and the stranger<lb/> that is in the midst of thee&#34;.  Judaism is not<lb/> asceticism.  The Nazarite who&#44; abstained of his<lb/> own accord abstained from what is permissible with moderation&#44;<lb/> was obliged to bring a sin offering &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> when the term of his vow expired.  The Sages tell<lb/> us&#44; that he should not have burdened himself<lb/> with additional prohibitions &#91;Hebrew&#93;  There has been<lb/> a period in our history&#44; when a notion similar to<lb/> that which the Catholic Church encourages&#44; was<lb/> seized upon by a few born in the faith of Abra&#45;<lb/>&#45;ham.  National calamities must have given that notion<lb/> its origin.  The Essenes severed themselves from the<lb/> community of their brethren.  They accepted a mode<lb/> of living totally foreign to the principles that ever<lb/> guided Israelites.  Because Syro&#45;Grecian op&#45;<lb/>&#45;pression weighed us down&#44; and again later on because in&#45;<lb/>&#45;vincible Rome knocked at the gates of Judea&#44; the<lb/> Essenes&#44; despairing to regain the liberty yearned after which their brethren fought for&#44;<lb/> delivered themselves to austere practices and devotions&#45;&#45;some<lb/> even adopting celibacy&#44; against the letter and spirit<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>of Mosaism and traditionalism.  But the small<lb/> sect of the Essenes was an unnatural growth in<lb/> the soil of Judaism.  We let it go.  Nascent<lb/> Christianity&#44; preaching a kingdom of heaven and not hu&#45;<lb/>man freedom on earth&#59; nascent Christianity that asked<lb/> to give <sic>Ceaser</sic> what is <sic>Ceaser&#39;s</sic>&#44; and to care nothing for<lb/> the morrow&#44; nascent Christianity&#44; affecting contempt<lb/> for things temporal&#44; may have transplanted into its soil&#44;<lb/> that exotic plant in the field of Judaism.<lb/></p>
                <p>With us activity in the world which was moulded by the supremest<lb/> wisdom for our happiness &#91;Hebrew&#93; has ever been the leading thought<lb/> of a consistent Jew&#59; aye&#44; of a Jewess too.  Since the day<lb/> that Sarah quickly made ready three measures of<lb/> fine meal and kneaded them to hospitably entertain strange&#45;<lb/>&#45;rs&#44; women of Israel have considered real righteousness<lb/> to busy themselves in doing good widely in their<lb/> various relations of life as wives&#44; mothers&#44; sisters&#44; and<lb/> socially not less than domestically.  Hence our Haldah&#44;<lb/> our Beruria&#44; and in modern times our Deborah Ascarelli&#44; our Rachel Bandag&#45;<lb/>&#45;ger&#44; the Florence Mtinghale Nightingale of Italy.  It has<lb/> been my fortune in this city of my preference and<lb/> among the people whom I still serve&#44; to have<lb/> come in contact with Jewesses&#44; whose pleasure<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>it was and is to promote further whatever benefits man&#45;<lb/>&#45;kind in body and mind&#44; &#38; yet neglecting none of<lb/> the occupations necessary for the government of well<lb/> regulated households.  And I acknowledge with<lb/> sincere unfeigned satisfaction&#44; that as far as I can judge&#44; no<lb/> country has <sic>equalled</sic> America in the facilities offered<lb/> to women to work in numerous fields of usefulness.<lb/>  My satisfaction increases&#44; when I contemplate the ef&#45;<lb/>&#45;fects of such a recognition of woman&#39;s powers for<lb/> good&#44; or American women who are born and reared in my<lb/> ancestral creed.  To the Congregation Mickv&#233; Is&#45;<lb/>&#45;rael is due the merit of having been the first<lb/> to emancipate its women&#44; in accordance with the rule<lb/>&#45;&#45;which ought ever to be&#45;&#45;that taxation means repre&#45;<lb/>&#45;sentation.  Our women are members of enjoy the right of suffrage in this religious<lb/> body&#44; to whose maintenance they contribute.  And<lb/> whenever any of them&#44; or of their sisters in faith&#44;<lb/> through the length and breadth of this land&#44; fearlessly lift up<lb/> a penetrating voice to rebuke wrong &#38; commend right&#44; to arouse<lb/> the slumberers in religion&#44; to infuse new spirit the warmth of zeal into<lb/> the lukewarm&#44; to put falsehood to the blush&#44; and cham&#45;<lb/>&#45;pion truth&#44; I am reminded of the impersonation of<lb/> wisdom in woman&#39;s garb&#44; in that book &#91;&#63;&#93;<lb/> as a teacher and cultivator of ethics&#58;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>So&#33; wisdom cries out&#44; and as understanding gives forth<lb/> her voice.  ON the top of high places&#44; by the way side<lb/>.....she stands....and thus she speaks.  To you O men&#44; I call&#44;<lb/> my speech is for the sons of man.  O ye simple&#44; understand<lb/> discretion&#44; and ye fools acquire mind.  Listen&#44; for I<lb/> speak noble words&#44; and the utterance of my lips is for<lb/> righteousness....Receive my instruction and not silver&#44; know&#45;<lb/>&#45;ledge preferable to choice gold.....To fear the Lord<lb/> is to hate evil&#44; pride and arrogance&#44; and the way of<lb/> perversity.  Wise women capable so to address<lb/> the unwary can yet be found.  Come forth and teach us&#44;<lb/> men&#44; to shake off lethargy&#44; to rise to the defence of a Judaism<lb/> pure and simple&#44; such as prophetism&#44; at the head of which<lb/> Moses stands&#44; has inculcated.  The blessings of gene&#45;<lb/>&#45;rations yet unborn will rest upon your heads.  You<lb/> will be called the restorers of the house of Israel to<lb/> unity&#44; to fidelity&#44; to religious ancestral virtues.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
