<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF9_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff9_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff9_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff9_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff9_1_2v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 1 sheet<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For a funeral<lb/></p>
            
            <p>Brethren&#33;  Do not consider me an interloper.  To encroach<lb/> on another man&#39;s rights&#45;&#45;always an unpardonable offence&#45;&#45;<lb/> would indeed be a heinous sin at such an hour&#44; and upon<lb/> an occasion so indescribably sad.  But I conceive that<lb/> the family from whom this lovely Jewess sprung&#44; and that<lb/> with to whom she became allied&#44; have claims on every token<lb/> of sympathy&#44; which a fellow&#45;believer in the religion they have<lb/> ever honored&#44; may desire to offer express.  And to signify thus openly<lb/> a friend&#39;s sincere condolence&#44; is the sole object of my speaking.<lb/>  Leah Asch grown mid our community&#44; beloved by all&#44; who<lb/> knew her&#44; for that gentleness of spirit&#44; which her comely face<lb/> mirrored forth&#59; Leah Asch&#44; before she had assumed new<lb/> duties towards this&#44; now disconsolate&#44; Israelite&#44; gave pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;mise of a life tending ceaselessly to noble ends.<lb/>  Ready to fly the needle&#44; that the children of the indigent<lb/> might be suitably clad&#44; willing to impart gratuitously<lb/> to our sons and daughters the knowledge she possessed had acquired<lb/> of the good old book&#59; prompted instinctively to lend<lb/> her countenance and institutions of beneficence&#44; she elicited<lb/> respect&#44; and evoked prayful wishes for her happiness.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Many hearts beat in unison with that of the devoted father&#44; and<lb/> the mother of affection as well as adoption&#44; when she the deceased<lb/> had entered a new sphere of actions.  Her correct education<lb/> drawn from the unfallible unfailing source of Truth&#44; heightened the<lb/> hope&#44; that as a wife and a future mother in Israel&#44; her<lb/> demeanour would prove a spring of perennial blessings.<lb/>  She possessed all the qualifications&#44; whereby to secure<lb/> her husband&#39;s felicity&#44; and withal the capacity to in&#45;<lb/>&#45;fluence him righteously.  What a household might she<lb/> not have raised to shed lustre on the congregation of<lb/> the Lord&#33;  How lasting might have been the effects of a<lb/> woman&#39;s pious endeavours and godly example&#33;....<lb/> Alas&#33; with this coffin are this will to day to be buried the glowing<lb/> anticipations of parents&#44; husband&#44; brother&#44; even the well&#45;<lb/>founded expectations of a Hebrew community.  Was<lb/> the loveable being enshrined therein too pure for the corrupt<lb/> world&#63;  Were we undeserving of her association&#63;  Or&#44; was<lb/> an angelic creature wanted above to fulfil some celest&#45;<lb/>&#45;ial mission&#63;  Oh&#33; that we could tear asunder the impenetrable<lb/> veil cast over our vision&#33;  Perhaps the tears&#44; which now<lb/> copiously flow would dry at the rising in our horizon<lb/> of a sun of joy.  We would see that the heavens have claimed<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>their own to crown it with immortal glory.  But because<lb/> we are earthy and earth&#45;bound&#59; because we cannot fathom<lb/> the ways of Him who is all&#45;just&#59; &#34;the God of truth&#44; in whom there is<lb/> no inequity&#44;&#34; therefore grief bends us beneath its weight&#44; and we<lb/> bewail our lot as melancholy in the extreme.<lb/></p>
            <p>My bereaved friends&#33;  Could the power of human speech uplift you<lb/> from the sorrow into which you have been plunged&#44; I would call<lb/> to my aid the language most fitting to compass that object.<lb/>  But I can only mourn with you.  I can but express feelings<lb/> of deep sympathy&#59; feelings representing what a vast number<lb/> of your coreligionists experience&#44; because of this irreparable loss.<lb/>  May the Compassionate Lord look down towards you benig&#45;<lb/>&#45;gnantly&#44; and <sic>dispell</sic> the gloom&#44; which mortals cannot<lb/> fling away.  He&#45;&#45;the author of all things&#44; has dispossessed<lb/> you of a treasure&#44; but at His bidding a stow of abundant<lb/> gladness may yet open&#44; and spiritually enrich your ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;istence.  Family of Isaac M. Asch&#59;&#45;&#45;Sinas<lb/> Zellner&#44; man of sorrow&#33;  It is my vocation to preach fortitude&#59;<lb/> but in this instance I cannot add a tittle to the teaching<lb/> you have early imbibed.  Recall it at a time you<lb/> are so sorely tried&#44; and let it be your stay&#44; your<lb/> staunch support.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>That parental instruction will speak now of the ineffable<lb/> satisfaction derived from having arisen superior to worldly<lb/> vicissitudes.  It will speak also of the fleetness of life&#44; and <lb/>the folly of depending on the morrow.  It will say to<lb/> you that they have lived the longest&#44; who devoted their fina years<lb/> to the performance of good.  It That instruction will impress still more<lb/> indelibly on your minds the sentence of the Sages&#44; that our<lb/> abode here below is but a lingering at the porch of a great the Kings&#39;<lb/> palace&#59; that we must be ever prepared for the royal summons<lb/> by making ourselves ready while in the entrance&#45;way.<lb/>  And when the <sic>keeness</sic> of the present affliction shall have lessened&#44;<lb/> you will raise the eyes of faith upon high&#44; and see the dear<lb/> object you now bemoan in the enjoyment of the reward<lb/> reserved to filial reverence&#44; connubial fidelity&#44; and the pursuit of<lb/> Jewish practices ever acceptable to Israel&#39;s God.  You will then acknow&#45;<lb/>&#45;ledge in the words of the book which the faithful were reading on<lb/> the mournful day Leah departed hence&#44; that &#34;the Lord is good unto<lb/> those what hope in Him&#44; to the soul that seeketh Him&#59;&#34; and like<lb/> Jeremiah each of you will also exclaim.  &#34;The Lord is my portion&#44; saith my<lb/> soul&#44; therefore will I want for Him&#44;&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
