<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF4_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_1_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>Some remarks suggested<lb/> by Haftorah Vayer&#225;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>The first verse and the last of this day&#39;s Haftorah&#44; call to<lb/> mind a period of Jewish history which ought to revive.  I<lb/> mean that epoch in our annals&#44; when a great reformer effected<lb/> a change radical and inestimable most important.  Rise Samuel&#44; and tell<lb/> thy people again that obedience to duty is better than sacrifices&#33;<lb/>  Samuel the inflexible judge&#44; Samuel who loved the tribes&#44; but<lb/> was <sic>unyeildingly</sic> opposed to their corrupt or weak minded<lb/> rulers&#44; Samuel would&#44; if he were in our midst&#44; reproach<lb/> our ignorance and our heedlessness&#59; that lack of knowledge<lb/> which blights the growth of piety&#44; that indifference which<lb/> fosters infidelity.  In his days&#44; the altar reeked with the<lb/> blood of burnt&#45;offerings&#58; God&#39;s anger favor was not appeased propitiated.<lb/>  Men and women assembled around it in crowds&#58; the Deity was<lb/> not honored.  Why&#63;  Because the ministering officiating priests were<lb/> cormorants&#44; intent solely upon gain&#59; because the <sic>worshippers</sic><lb/> brought fat rams to the Temple sanctuary&#44; but not their hearts. into the temple<lb/> Unhappy Eli&#33;  He feared sin&#44; but more than it he dreaded<lb/> his children&#39;s public exposure&#44; and their dispossession of<lb/> sacerdotal perquisites.  And the deluded Hebrews&#33;  They<lb/> held in the right hand a gift for the sanctuary holy Tabernacle&#59; with their<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>left they pressed idols to their bosoms.  At that juncture the son<lb/> of Hannah&#44; the poetess and ardent believer&#44; arose.  In him<lb/> sparkled the glowing fire of her soul&#44; the brilliant gems of<lb/> her intellect.  That noble illustrious descendant and follower of Moses<lb/> the Levite&#44; plucked up weeds&#44; but he planted roses.  He<lb/> destroyed ministerial pretensions&#44; but constructed a service<lb/> truly Divine.  To him tradition attributes the establishing of<lb/> a worship&#44; in which daily oblations were presented at the<lb/> sound of voices <sic>harmonising</sic> with sacred instruments.  But the<lb/> sagacious republican understood well that outward external devotions<lb/> &#38; void destitute of knowledge are leaves without the stem&#44; when the<lb/> mind <sic>worshipper</sic> is destitute of knowledge.  And he opened the a field of produ&#45;<lb/> righteousness &#45;cing choice and deeply rooted plants&#59; such as in whose possession a nation may<lb/> justly glory.  He opened a school of learning.  This was not&#44;<lb/> as vulgarly considered a resort exclusively for men of an<lb/> ascetic disposition&#44; where they lived apart from the outward<lb/> world&#44; and studied cultivated hidden sciences.  It was an academy&#44;<lb/> in which poetry and music moulded the feelings&#59; the<lb/> study of nature&#44; history and jurisprudence disciplined the<lb/> mind.  Its attendants were called &#34;prophets&#44;&#34; in the<lb/> sense that Abraham&#44; the first preacher of truth&#44; and<lb/> Miriam the first songstress to a redeeming God&#44; were styled.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Samuel presided and taught.  On him a twofold position<lb/> of heavenly spirit had rested.  A Seer&#44; peering with a<lb/> broad look into foreshadowed events&#44; and impassioned<lb/> orator carrying conviction&#44; he ca challenged the admiration and affection of<lb/> his disciples.  And these became in turn the enthusiastic messengers of<lb/> his patriotic will.  Riches they spurned&#44; to political<lb/> preferments they did not aspire.  Like their master&#44; one thought<lb/> nerved them to the arduous task&#59; to rescue their coreligionists<lb/> from <sic>brutalising</sic> heathenism&#44; and inspire them&#44; through<lb/> knowledge&#44; with love for their laws and institutions.  Our<lb/> Haftorah introduces us into the humble dwelling of the widow of<lb/> one of Samuel&#39;s disciples raised in the stern school of Samuel.  The man&#39;s legacy to his<lb/> wife was poverty&#44; and the support of two children.  He<lb/> may have striven&#44; during his life&#45;time to promote virtue.  She<lb/> who knew him most intimately declared that he did fear<lb/> the Lord.  But now that his lips were sealed in the grave death<lb/> people forgot the merits of the apostle of truth.  Heartless creditors increased the<lb/> burden of affliction weighing down his &#91;&#63;&#93;&#44; by demanding<lb/> her son&#39;s servitude in payment of a debt.  In her dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;tress she cried to a personage&#44; who would not turn away listlessly.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Elisha represented at that time the class of individuals of<lb/> whom I have spoken.  More than in any other we discover in him<lb/> a close intercourse with the disciples of the prophets whom designated in the<lb/> Bible terms by the name of &#34;Ben&#233; Launebeem&#59;&#34; and more than of any other has<lb/> the history of his life been handed down under the veil of the<lb/> miraculous.  Fondly attached The mantle of Elijah<lb/> falling upon his shoulders&#44; appeared to have uplifted him above<lb/> the terrestrials.  His appear looks spread reverential awe&#59; yet&#44;<lb/> he moved with a gentle spirit among the tribes&#44; and identified<lb/> himself with their interests and their wants.  Austere to&#45;<lb/>&#45;wards the wicked&#44; he nevertheless embraced in his humanity&#44; the gentile<lb/> as well as his brother the Hebrew.  Singularly attached he<lb/> was the all&#45;souled religious chief to those&#44; who worked with him in the national cause&#44;<lb/> and the lament of the widow of a deceased colaborer&#44; struck<lb/> on his breast a sympathetic chord.  &#34;What shall I do for<lb/> thee&#63;&#34; full&#44; of &#91;&#63;&#93; he inquired at her wailings.......You<lb/> know my hearers&#33; how by a celestial interposition he became the means<lb/> of delivering her from destitution&#44; and her dearest from the rigour<lb/> of bondage.  For by drawing your attention to the first verse<lb/> of our Haftorah&#44; I did not purpose repeating what each of you all<lb/> can read&#44; but to explain incidents in our annals&#44; which are<lb/> fraught with lessons&#44; we should take to heart.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>If I have shown that by knowledge&#44; Samuel and his successors<lb/> endeavored thu by knowledge to elevate the standing of our people&#44; how discre&#45;<lb/>&#45;ditable must be would they have considered the conduct of such Jews who are <sic>envelopped</sic><lb/> in a thick cloud in ignorance&#44; and care not that it should scatter<lb/> away&#33;  The great universal cry is for reform&#44; but that which a mighty<lb/> reformer introduced&#44; they Israelites reject.  &#91;&#63;&#93; Shame upon us&#58; For it is just from this motive cause<lb/> that have sprung the unscrupulous changes that which made Judaism<lb/> in America a patch&#45;work.  We are Incapable of judging<lb/> for ourselves&#44; we let others do our thinking.  We are literally<lb/> a flock of sheep under the shepherd&#39;s crook.  Men like the sons of Eli&#44;<lb/> pretending to lead us to a rich pasture ground&#44; may cause ingood us on<lb/> to tread under foot precious plants in the garden of the Lord.<lb/>  We know it not.  But worse than the sin of ignororf <sic>wilful</sic><lb/> ignorance is that of <sic>wilful</sic> indifference&#44; a shrugging of the<lb/> shoulders at our dearest interests&#44; a belief that religion is an<lb/> empty name&#44; learning a useless acquisition&#44; money is all.<lb/>  Can such pertinacity be corrected&#63;  Not while the place<lb/> in which it might be softened&#44; is shunned.  I feel convinced<lb/> that&#44; in many instances&#44; calm reasoning emanating from the pulpit may convert hearts<lb/> which seem callous.  I shall never prostitute my calling by<lb/> saying that provided you attend this Synagogue&#44; and listen<lb/> to my speaking&#44; you may spend the balance of the Sabbath&#45;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>day in the counting&#45;house or in the shop.  But this I will<lb/> say&#44; without without a particle of self conceit&#44; or egotism&#44;<lb/> that if you&#44; who nominally constitute a conservative congregation body of Hebrews&#44; took<lb/> heeded of the direction of Samuel&#44; as told in the last verse of<lb/> our Haftorah&#44; we might not have occasion to complain of a<lb/> prevailing ignorance or chilling apathy in our immedaite congregation.  When the Shunam&#45;<lb/>mite requested her husband to let her go as far as the pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;phet&#39;s house&#44; he spoke so.  &#34;Wherefore art thou going to him to<lb/> day&#63;  It is neither new moon&#44; nor Sabbath.&#34;  Mark the effect<lb/> of a wise reform&#33;  Sabbath and festivals The days of the Lord had been sanctified<lb/> to the noblest purpose.  To public instruction.  Men and women<lb/> were then to listened then to the instr imparting of religion.  It is So that did<lb/> the immortal son of Hannah sharpened the weapon with<lb/> which to slay the hydra of apostacy.  What is the duty&#44;<lb/> he would now demand of you O Jews of this century &#38; of this land to perform&#63;  To come and draw<lb/> along after you with by example&#44; a crowd to the remaining spot where the word<lb/> of God is rehearsed and expounded.  In the absence of that<lb/> academy of learning he instituted&#44; he would that the pious<lb/> be confirmed in their belief&#44; the waverers be argued with&#44; and<lb/> the reckless be gently re&#91;&#63;&#93; against at the only place of public<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>assemblage&#58; this minor sanctuary.  Believe experience&#44;<lb/> my Brethren&#33; if you will discredit my assertion.  The longer<lb/> will parents keep aloof from this dwelling of prayer and preaching&#44;<lb/> the greater will be the estrangement of their families from<lb/> the fold&#44; &#38; the surer will be the disaffection of their posterity.<lb/>  To represent this evil&#44; which I&#45;&#45;being no prophet can &#91;&#63;&#93; predict&#44;<lb/> to rekindle in Jewish breasts a sense of religious obligations I<lb/> have alluded to a lesson derived form the section read this day.<lb/>  We owe it to the great and good men&#44; who endeavoured to uphold<lb/> our faith by knowledge&#44; we owe it to our national character &#44;we<lb/> owe it to our immortal souls to gain an insight into the<lb/> history&#44; tenets&#44; and traditional rules of Judaism.  And here an<lb/> effort is made to force us give it to all attendants.  Should you<lb/> henceforth feel incited to honor God by an early and constant<lb/> attendance at His hallowed courts&#44; I shall rejoice.  Should<lb/> you determine otherwise&#44; I shall&#44; at all events&#44; have rolled<lb/> away from me the reproach of inertness or unfaithfulness in promo&#45;<lb/>&#45;ting your interest.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
