<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF11_4</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_4_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_4_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_4_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_4_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_4_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_4_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_4_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_4_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_4_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_4_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_4_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_4_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 3 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>For Parashat B&#243;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;It shall be as to thee for a sign upon thy hand&#44; and as for a me&#45;<lb/>morial between thy eyes&#44; in order that the Law of the Lord<lb/> may be in thy mouth&#44;&#34; namely&#44; always before thy mind ever present.<lb/>  Brethren.  This sentence in our Parasha&#44; recalls to my<lb/> memory two writings&#44; which have lately given me<lb/> some pleasure&#44; mingled with much pain.  The first I men&#45;<lb/>&#45;tioned already in one of my recent lectures.  It came<lb/> from the pen of a clever English Jew&#44; who is young in<lb/> years&#44; but seems to be ripe in scholarship.  Mr<lb/> Claude Montefiore has set forth ideas entirely opposed contrary<lb/> to those which I hold&#59; but that does not prevent<lb/> my giving him credit for sincerity.  The more ready<lb/> I am to do him that justice&#44; because I have heard<lb/> that&#44; being rich&#44; he still purposes entering the mi&#45;<lb/>&#45;nistry&#44; to enjoy ample opportunities for instilling<lb/> his views into the minds of the rising generation.<lb/>  AS he will bring to the task&#44; earnestness and a<lb/> general acquaintance with the works of modern<lb/> authors&#44; specially of the German school&#44; now a days most<lb/> popular&#44; the his chances of his success are fair.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>I do not wish that his teachings may gain<lb/> followers&#44; because I consider them destructive.  Yet&#44;<lb/> better the agitation of skepticism than the stagnation of the Agnostics.<lb/>  I am felt pleased that amidst such prevailing indif&#45;<lb/>&#45;ference&#44; a youth&#44; in affluence&#44; who might find abundant scope<lb/> for the indulgence of a worldly disposition&#44; and vulgar propen&#45;<lb/>&#45;sities&#44; should devotes his thoughts to the serious subject<lb/> of his people&#39;s religion.  He meets in it two<lb/> extremes&#44; a blind attachment to forms among some&#44;<lb/> and a withering apathy towards even the underlying pervading<lb/> spirit among others&#44; and he thinks imagines that by banishing<lb/> away most of the forms&#44; the spirit will rise step forward and<lb/> assert its supremacy.<lb/></p>
            <p>A strong warm advocate of Mr Montefiore&#39;s opinions&#44; is<lb/> a liberal Christian lady&#44; whose writing presents an flowing attractive flowing<lb/> style and calm reasoning.  Miss Frances Power<lb/> Cobbe agrees with the praises her Jewish young countryman&#44; who<lb/> aims to change the traditional aspect of Judaism&#44;<lb/> but she contends that he stopped short in the middle<lb/> of a progressive way&#44; and did not summon courage<lb/> to go as far as it is actually needed.  According to her<lb/> judgment&#44; Judaism&#44; to have a future&#44; must turn<lb/> its back altogether upon the past.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>It must proclaim to the world&#44; that it discards<lb/> all doctrines&#44; except the belief in One God&#44; and the im&#45;<lb/>&#45;mortality of the soul.  It must declare that it rejects<lb/> all ordinances&#44; except those moral rules of the Pen&#45;<lb/>&#45;tateuch&#44; which Christianity has accepted and&#44; as she thinks&#44; improved upon.  She asserts<lb/> that to change Judenheze&#45;&#45;Jew baiting&#45;&#45;which she deplores&#44;<lb/> into Judenliebe&#45;&#45;Jew loving&#45;&#45;which she longs for&#44; her<lb/> suggestions must be adopted&#59; for&#44; the enlightened<lb/> of mankind are unwilling to weary of tolerating any more the<lb/> existence of a nation within other nations.  On reading<lb/> that excellently attractively written essay&#44; I exclaimed&#58; God save us from our friends.<lb/>  What future will Judaism possibly have&#44; once that it is<lb/> no longer Judaism&#63;  If every distinctive characteristic<lb/> is removed&#44; how could can it perform a distinctive mission&#63;<lb/>  Let me use plain&#44; very plain language.  Suppose<lb/> that a father designs one of his children&#44; as his commercial<lb/> representative abroad.  He will furnish him with<lb/> some object as a credential&#44; and at the same time&#44; as a reminder of<lb/> the charge given.  Let it be a ring&#44; a staff&#44; or a<lb/> paper.  So long as that object exists&#44; the commission will<lb/> be credited and duly performed.  Destroy it&#44; and the end it was<lb/> intended to reach&#44; will be defeated.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Moses has said it &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;It shall be to thee&#44; as for a sign<lb/> upon thy hand&#44; and as for a memorial&#44; between thy eyes&#44;<lb/> in order that the Law of the Lord may be in thy month&#44;&#34;<lb/> namely always ever present.  Miss Cobbe&#44;<lb/> notwithstanding her evidently bright intellect mis&#45;<lb/>&#45;takes human nature&#44; if she believes that the Monothe&#45;<lb/>&#45;ism of the Jew&#44; will remain pure and purify Christ&#45;<lb/>&#45;ianity of its dogmatic dross&#44; after the Jew shall<lb/> have ceased to be a Jew.  On the contrary&#44; having<lb/> nothing for its support&#59; the Abrahamic covenant being<lb/> abolished&#59; the Sabbath transformed transferred to a more convenient another day for convenience sake&#44; the historical holi&#45;<lb/>&#45;days repealed&#59; the dietary prescriptions abrogated&#44;<lb/> and intermarriages encouraged&#44; Monotheism will must per force lose<lb/> its identity through the irresistible force concurrence of circum&#45;<lb/>&#45;stances.  The idea of the Unity which<lb/> has made Israel the martyr people for the final<lb/> humanising of all races&#44; will be wiped away<lb/> from the memory of its few appointed guardians&#44;<lb/> without having effected any perceptible change<lb/> for the better in the belief dogma of the trinity among the many&#44; who<lb/> still adhere to it.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>You ask&#58; How will it then end&#63;  Can we<lb/> ever stand for ever the opposition of communities&#44; that reckon<lb/> tens of thousands to our ones&#63;  This question&#44; often<lb/> occurs to my mind&#44; and it<lb/> troubles and saddens me.  If Jews where were what<lb/> Moses and the prophets desired them to be&#44; the<lb/> answer would come readily and afford delight.  If<lb/> Jews&#44; with scarcely an exception&#44; were upright in<lb/> their dealings&#44; moral in their behaviour&#44; conscientious<lb/> in their religious practices&#59; in one word&#44; if they were<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;A holy people&#34;; we could say to our adversaries mankind&#58;<lb/> &#34;Look and learn.  Our common Parent has placed a small<lb/> family in the midst of a large family as a model&#44;<lb/> that you all may benefit.  See how the idea of<lb/> that the Lord is One all&#45;creating&#44; all&#45;watching<lb/> and all&#45;saving keeps that small family up in<lb/> virtue.&#34;  Could we say so&#44; we would not alone disarm op&#45;<lb/>&#45;position&#44; command but challenge universal respect&#44; and win followers to<lb/> our glorious belief.  But could we honestly speak<lb/> now thus&#44; without the and fear of not a rebuke&#63;  Willing<lb/> as I am to admit that in the aggregate we<lb/> are not worse&#44; but on many points better than our<lb/> neighbors of other creeds&#44; I would not venture upon that address<lb/> to the gentiles.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Yet&#44; I do not waver in my faith.  does not waver.  Israel Israel will abide everlastingly&#44; despite persecution from without and dereliction from within.  He has been<lb/> chosen &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;as a liht to nations&#44;&#34; and the<lb/> sufferings it bears at different intervals are so<lb/> many messages from above recalling the selection&#44;<lb/> and demanding obedience to the ancient covenant.  For<lb/> by a strict observance to the latter&#44; and not by more<lb/> abstractions can we hope to attract the world&#39;s attention<lb/> to redeeming truths&#44; and unite mankind the human race in the belief of<lb/> the absolute almightiness of God&#33;  It is not for<lb/> us&#44; finite beings&#44; to search when that promised uni&#45;<lb/>&#45;fication will be brought about&#44; but it is our bounden<lb/> duty&#44; as appointed workers&#44; to labor for the Lord&#44;<lb/> in sincerity and singleness of heart.  Blessed<lb/> Judenheze&#44; if it should stir up Hebrews to mighty<lb/> exertions&#44; so that the sar shame of materialism on<lb/> one side&#44; and of bigotry on the other be rolled<lb/> away&#44; so that we present mankind the aspect<lb/> which Moses and the prophets would give their<lb/> people&#44; so that we be acknowledged our deeds prove us the witnesses<lb/> of the Eternal Lord&#44; who is alone the Lord Eternal&#44; and besides whom<lb/> there is no saviour &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>High&#45;spirited youths now smarting under the<lb/> strokes of racial prejudices&#44; seek a remedy in<lb/> breaking down all ritual distinctions.  I do will not im&#45;<lb/>&#45;pugn their motives.  They may be honest.  But their earnestness in<lb/> destroying&#44; must be antagonized by the enthusiasm<lb/> of conservatism.  The ministry of a Claude Mon&#45;<lb/>&#45;tefiore that would save monotheism by chaining Judaism to the chariot<lb/> wheel of Christianity&#44; must meet a ministry that<lb/> will vindicate the right of the mother religion to<lb/> remain free and do her assigned mission.  The firmness of<lb/> convictions in enlightened orthodoxy must be pitted against the boldness<lb/> of self&#45;dependence a delusive reform.  But then no uncertain<lb/> sounds should proceed from the defenders.  Judaism shall<lb/> be preserved unentangled by dangerous compromises&#44; but let its principles be clearly defined&#44; that the young<lb/> generation rightly understand it.  The archprophet has shown<lb/> us to day the way &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;It shall be to thee&#44; as for a sign upon<lb/> thy hand&#44; and as for a memorial between thy eyes&#44; in order<lb/> that the Law of the Lord be in thy mouth&#44;&#34; namely&#44; ever present.  Forms are<lb/> means to an end.  They are invaluable as reminders and<lb/> as certificates of our credentials from on high.  Let us however&#44; take heed that<lb/> they do not usurp the place of the Torah&#45;&#45;which means<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>a heavenly instruction&#44; the imparting designed<lb/> to make us exemplary in all the our various relations. of life<lb/>  For then if they do&#44; we would then lose our life&#45;giving<lb/> subsistence&#44; and depend on unrealities.  We would<lb/> part with the kernel&#44; to hold on to the shell.  Let<lb/> the young hear it and their elders enforce the lesson by<lb/> example.  A Jew&#44; because he is a Jew&#44; has assumed<lb/> special directions&#44; in addition to the rules of integrity&#44;<lb/> of justice and beneficence&#44; which ought to govern society.<lb/>  Those directions are the emanations of inspired wisdom.<lb/>  Our legislator enacted them as warnings against evil<lb/> doing&#44; as checks upon unruly propensities.  So long<lb/> as they subserve that sacred purpose&#44; they are worthy<lb/> of all veneration.  When they represent nothing any<lb/> more&#44; or&#44; what is worse&#44; when they are construed into<lb/> an exemption for the fulfilment of social obliga&#45;<lb/>&#45;tions&#44; then their character changes from holiness<lb/> into profanity.  May it never be so with us.<lb/></p>
            
            <p>&#40;Here followed an address to a Bart Mitzvah&#41;<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
