<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF2_4</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_4_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_4_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_4_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_4_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_4_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_4_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_4_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_4_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_4_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_4_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_4_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_4_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Against the idea held forth<lb/>
                that Moses copied from Egypt.<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>A commentator&#44; whose sentiments I lately read in a<lb/> legendary book&#44; compiled more than eight&#45;hundred<lb/> years ago&#44; must have lived among skeptics&#44; or must<lb/> have foreseen the cavillers abounding in modern times.<lb/>  Referring to the three initial words of the Decalogue&#44;<lb/> he reasoned thus&#58; to harbor the idea that any inter&#45;<lb/>&#45;mediate being from earth or from heaven was the a&#45;<lb/>&#45;gency&#44; through which &#34;Anochi Adonai Elohecha&#34;&#44;<lb/> resounded at Sinai&#44; is to hold destructive errors.<lb/>  It is the height of arrogance in puny mortals to<lb/> argue that &#34;I am&#34; implies per force a bodily exist&#45;<lb/>&#45;ence&#44; and its utterance demands the organs of<lb/> speech.  For if we reflect that the limited ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;tent of human knowledge is not the criterion to<lb/> Judge of God&#39;s illimitable wisdom&#44; nor is God&#39;s<lb/> potency to be gauged by human powers&#44; we<lb/> will not refuse to admit what seems irrencon&#45;<lb/>&#45;cilable with our finite understanding&#44; since that<lb/> which we cannot grasp&#44; is absolutely within<lb/> the range of possibilities respecting the Almighty.<lb/>  Then&#44; the writer&#44; after having reminded his readers<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>of the incorporality of God&#44; as taught<lb/> in Deuteronomy in connection with the delivery of<lb/> the ten commandments&#44; gives us the wholesome<lb/> advice&#44; that we love the God of Sinai in simplicity<lb/> of heart&#44; banishing form our minds whatever is<lb/> derogatory to His glory&#44; never venturing to lower<lb/> it&#44; by applying to the Spirit of the Universe<lb/> corporeal senses&#44; but to remember that the world&#45;<lb/>humanising revelation in its outward enunciation&#44;<lb/> is not the only thing beyond our comprehension&#44;<lb/> that we neither can understand a vast deal of<lb/> <lb/>what passes under our immediate vision&#44; so that&#44;<lb/> like in the days of Job who exclaimed &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; the phenomenon of the far reverberating<lb/> thunder clap&#44; so often heard&#44; remains still un&#45;<lb/>&#45;explained.  But that ancient com&#45;<lb/>&#45;mentator might have doubled his own sight&#44; had<lb/> he beheld what is set to view in our days.  The<lb/> heirs of the covenant at Horeb&#44; nay the teachers<lb/> of the Law&#44; they who sit in the place of Moses&#44;<lb/> standing forth boldly to make an open denial<lb/> of that revelation&#44; not so much because it is<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>above their reach and ken&#44; but because their pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;tentious sagacity has detected therein plagiarism&#44;<lb/> and they will impartially give every one his due&#59;<lb/> they wish &#34;to mete out justice unto Egypt.&#34;<lb/>  Civilization summarized in the Decalogue&#44; is an Egy&#45;<lb/>&#45;ptian outgrowth.  The man who had been cradled<lb/> in an Egyptian court&#44; studied&#44; pondered and by<lb/> a <sic>marvellous</sic> power of combination&#44; succeeded in for&#45;<lb/>&#45;mulating a code which comprises the excellencies<lb/> of all past experiences.  The land of the<lb/> Pharaohs was exceptionally great.  It had ga&#45;<lb/>&#45;thered in those experiences&#44; but&#44; unaccountably&#44; it<lb/> did not make a practical use of them.  The<lb/> genius of Moses breathed them into actuality&#44; and<lb/> in that masterly ability of the son of Amram<lb/> lies his inspiration.  Such is the theory<lb/> by which the rising generation are to be kept<lb/> loyal to the Torah&#45;&#45;to hearken and obey.  Egypt<lb/> is the mould in which our religion was worked<lb/> into shape.  But that theory&#44; which has not<lb/> the merit of originality&#44; is as groundless as it is unjewish.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>I will not prove my assertion by the Bible<lb/> and Talmud&#44; nor by Herodotus or Josephus.  They<lb/> do assure us in one accord of sentiments&#44; that Egypt<lb/> was brutally heathenish&#44; degraded in morals&#44; body<lb/> and mind enslaving.  He who of all men knew<lb/> that fact best&#44; felt that the God who hates immora&#45;<lb/>&#45;lity and falsehood&#44; bid him warn Israel against<lb/> the detestable deeds of the country that boasted of its<lb/> learning &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;After the doings<lb/> of the land of Mizraim wherein ye dwelt&#44; do ye not.&#34;  And<lb/> again before the immortal leader departed from earth&#44;<lb/> he so addressed his people &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Ye know how we dwelt in the land of Egypt.&#34;<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Ye have seen their abominations and their revolting<lb/> idols of wood and stone&#44; of silver and gold that were<lb/> with them.&#34;  But say&#58; what else have Egypt&#45;<lb/>&#45;ologists discovered by their indefatigable researches&#63;<lb/>  They put their skill to the severest test.  Scientific<lb/> appliances by which the Age we live in has deser&#45;<lb/>&#45;vedly attained the pinnacle of fame&#44; have been resorted<lb/> to in order to make the pyramids disclose the past&#59;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>but nothing have the hieroglyphics told&#44; which belies<lb/> the declaration of God&#39;s faithful messenger.  No<lb/> great nation of antiquity had statutes and ordinances<lb/> so righteous as our Torah &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;  Even to this day the country from<lb/> which presumption assumes that those statutes and<lb/> ordinances were copied or modified&#44; or improved upon&#44;<lb/> has not unfolded a single document disproving<lb/> what the Hebrew archprophet asserted.<lb/></p>
                <p>It would be&#44; of course&#44; unreasonable and against all<lb/> historical analogy to suppose that along stay<lb/> of our ancestors in a foreign land&#44; had left no im&#45;<lb/>&#45;pression whatever upon their minds.  Persons<lb/> who read thoughtfully&#44; will not gainsay that<lb/> arts in their various branches were learnt in<lb/> Egypt by the posterity of the seventy persons who<lb/> went there with Jacob&#59; that in some instances<lb/> the domestic habits of our forefathers bore a likeness<lb/> to those of their former masters&#44; that even in the<lb/> priestly apparel of spotless white linen&#44; and in laws<lb/> recommending cleanliness and frequent ablations&#44; a strong<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>resemblance may be traced.  But in theo&#45;<lb/>&#45;logical truths&#44; in ethical truths&#44; in the rules that<lb/> guide society aright&#44; that protect the stranger&#44; di&#45;<lb/>&#45;gnify the citizen&#44; in those principles which mark<lb/> out a real state of civilization&#44; the sharpest line<lb/> of demarcation should be drawn &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;what<lb/> is chaff to choice wheat&#34;&#63;  I exclaim in the language<lb/> of Jeremiah.  Monuments crowded with the<lb/> deification of the dead and of the living&#44; of fulsome<lb/> animals&#44; and loathsome reptiles&#44; monuments veri&#45;<lb/>&#45;fying the saying of the Talmudists that Egypt was<lb/> the widest entrance into the temple of impunity<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; were <sic>levelled</sic> against by a Divine<lb/> arrow&#44; when the voice thundered forth the Decalogue.<lb/>  Idolatry and slavery&#44; vice and crime received the<lb/> execration of heaven by the ten words&#44; which made<lb/> religion and morality for ever one and an indivi&#45;<lb/>&#45;sible Unity.  I am not ignorant of the<lb/> fact that in some schools of the Greeks&#44; it was<lb/> taught that under the guise of idols&#44; hidden<lb/> verities were contained&#44; but neither the pyramids<lb/> nor the carefully preserved mummies&#44; have revealed<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>those verities.  To me the attempt of<lb/> a Jewish preacher to take a Diogenes&#39; lantern<lb/> and cast about looking for some remains of<lb/> what was theologically and morally great in<lb/> ancient Egypt&#44; so as to disprove the originality<lb/> of the Mosaic code&#44; is impious&#59; it justly condemns<lb/> the perpetrator to forfeit the name of &#34;Rabbi.&#34;<lb/>  But such has been for the last decade the precept<lb/> and example of the only Hebrew college in America&#44; that<lb/> its graduates have issued forth full fledged skeptics.<lb/>  And now one who was considered the least affected<lb/> by an unwholesome Western atmosphere&#44; has men&#45;<lb/>&#45;tally turned Eastward&#44; to rummage among the<lb/> relics of antiquity&#59; perhaps he will be able<lb/> yet &#34;to mete out justice unto Egypt.&#34;  No<lb/> matter&#44; if he does Israel&#39;s religion great injustice&#44;<lb/> and still continues to be its preacher.  The people<lb/> like it.  A liberal Rabbi&#44; who casts off notions<lb/> to which his fathers held&#44; and refuses to subscribe<lb/> to the doctrine of inspiration&#44; ought to gain the<lb/> plaudits of his congregation.  Did I agree to that&#44;<lb/> I would not have dared to read the Decalogue on<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>the anniversary of its glorious birth&#45;day.<lb/></p>  
            <p>Each letter would have seemed to me a fiery tongue&#44;<lb/> branding my soul as false.  It is because I<lb/> long to deliver Judaism from lying interpreters&#44;<lb/> that I have set my heart upon a holy under&#45;<lb/>&#45;taking.  The institution that costs me an&#45;<lb/>&#45;xious thoughts and ardent prayers will&#44; by the help<lb/> of God&#44; fight back successfully the disciples of<lb/> a school that tear the Torah into shreds&#44; and<lb/> then laying it together piecemeal&#44; present it in<lb/> the shape of a coat of many colours beyond<lb/> recognition.  The &#34;Jewish Theological Seminary&#44;&#34;<lb/> which I trust will soon rise in New York&#44; will<lb/> preserve intact what our ancestors deemed too sacred<lb/> to be tampered with.  The fealty of its students<lb/> will keep pace with their learning.  They will<lb/> not mentally travel to Egypt or to India&#44; search<lb/> into the ruins of Nineveh and Persepolis&#44; to finally<lb/> exclaim&#58; &#34;Eureka&#44; we have detected adulteration in the crown<lb/> of the Law &#91;Hebrew&#93;; precious stones that Moses stole<lb/> from countries lying on the Nile or the Niger&#44; the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Tigris or the Ganges and passed them off as the Lord&#39;s heavenly.  No&#58; the scholars<lb/> will look for support to that code upon which<lb/> human civilization rests&#44; in internal evidences&#44; in the<lb/> teachings of the Sages&#44; in the consent of mankind&#44;<lb/> in the <sic>marvellous</sic> existence of the people commis&#45;<lb/>&#45;sioned from on high to spread and treasure it.<lb/>  I had fondly anticipated a general appreciation<lb/> of a project to which I gave the initiative.<lb/>  Notably I desired encouragement from my Phila&#45;<lb/>&#45;delphia coreligionists&#44; and those to whom I minister.<lb/>  The lack of interest by the vast majority reflects<lb/> on my inability to arouse enthusiasm.  Yet&#44; I<lb/> refer again this Sabbath to the scheme on the success<lb/> of which conservative Judaism hinges&#44; before personal<lb/> appeals be made in its behalf.  I may cease<lb/> for a while to speak on this pulpit&#44; unless other&#45;<lb/>&#45;wise prompted by special occasions.  Hence<lb/> I beg once more of my brothers and sisters in<lb/> faith to give the subject the deep consideration<lb/> it merits&#44; to evince religions sympathy there&#45;<lb/>with&#44; and fraternal willingness to forward its<lb/> interest with unstinted liberality.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
