<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF9_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_1_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>A moral lecture to youths<lb/> on the 2d passage of the<lb/> Haftorah for Vayehi.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#34;Be strong&#44; and show thyself a man.&#34;  So did spoke a father on<lb/> the eve of his death speak to his a beloved son.  And the youth he<lb/> addressed&#44; needed in very deed superior strength.  Enemies<lb/> fierce and formidable unrelenting lay in wait to hurl at him poisonous<lb/> arrows.  To repel them the youth must have mustered all his powers.<lb/>  A sign of weakness would have caused him to fall mortally wounded.<lb/></p>
            <p>But is it not Solomon to whom that paternal charge<lb/> was given&#63;  What vigour was he required&#63; to exhibit&#63;  He<lb/> whose very name &#40;Shelomoh from Shalom&#41; had prophetically been made to foreshadow<lb/> a glorious reign of peace&#63;  Scarcely a ripple disturbed<lb/> the regal sea on which David&#39;s favored son launched the ship<lb/> of state.  Crowned heads journeyed from foreign lands to survey<lb/> what the poet&#45;king had almost created by his military prowess.<lb/>  They came from afar distant regions to visit the realms domains he had bequeathed<lb/> unimpaired to his successor.  He came not with a challenge<lb/> to battle&#44; but with tributes of allegiance&#44; and munificent gifts bespeaking<lb/> friendship.  Where did then the foes that the King&#45;elect must resist with manly<lb/> strength&#44; lie concealed&#63;  They lurked within his heart.  There&#44;<lb/> they met and designed plotted for an attack.  There&#44; they conspired to effect<lb/> his rein.  You have already understood it&#44; my dear hearers&#33;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Solomons&#39; deadliest enemies were the very riches and dominions<lb/> which his father had secured by his outstretched far&#45;reaching<lb/> arm.  The teachers of old have wisely said that&#44; &#91;Hebrew&#93; the higher is<lb/> a man&#39;s temporal position&#44; the greater are the inducements held out to him<lb/> to do wrong.  For&#44; the facility to gratify passions&#44; begets the<lb/> wish&#44; and this is intensified by the impunity which nobility<lb/> of birth and wealth often accord.  With the bulk of mankind&#44;<lb/> unruly cravings are tempered down by a multiplicity of feelings&#44;<lb/> which stir in the breast.  By a desire to earn a competence&#44;<lb/> to gain a reputation&#59; by a thirst for worldly honors&#44; by a fear<lb/> of public disgrace.  But individuals who possess all things&#44; and<lb/> dread nothing&#44; will be apt to bend the mind solely upon<lb/> the reaching attaining of one object&#44; the indulgence of immoderate<lb/> passions.  To those us who move among their our equals or supe&#45;<lb/>&#45;riors&#44; it may seem as if a thousand eyes scrutinized their our<lb/> conduct&#44; but they whom chance has placed above all others&#44;<lb/> will consider that no human looks can reach as far high as where<lb/> they have been elevated.  Unchecked by censure&#44; goaded on<lb/> by flattery&#44; the heirs of rank and opulence frequently enjoy<lb/> that to which the unremitting labor of their fathers gives them<lb/> a title&#44; adding not a little thereto by their own efforts.<lb/>  They eat to the full of the sweet fruits of parental planting&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>and&#44; tasting none of the bitterness experienced while gathering them<lb/> for the future&#44; waste in idleness and debauch what should have been<lb/> preserved by industry and purity.  Aye&#58; sloth and its inseparable<lb/> companion profligacy&#44; plot together to hasten on destruction.<lb/>  Such were the enemies which an anxious parent depreciated&#59;<lb/> and at the hour of a lasting separation from him that he would<lb/> have sustained by his counsel&#44; the faltering quivering lips uttered these<lb/> words.  &#34;I go the way of all the earth&#44; be thou therefore strong&#44; and<lb/> show thyself a man&#34;  I shall not now explain now how<lb/> far the parting monition was heeded.  The evidences of Solomon&#39;s<lb/> vigor in first grappling with evil&#44; and of his fatal weakness which<lb/> made him finally succumb&#44; can be distinctly traced in the<lb/> pages of an impartial history.   But as I believe that&#44; without being<lb/> surrounded by the same temptations which beset royalty&#44; many<lb/> a youth needs the advice which stands at the head of to&#45;day&#39;s<lb/> prophetic section&#44; of the prophets&#44; I will repeat it to each.  &#34;Be strong<lb/> and show thyself a man&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93; You lose a claim to that name&#44;<lb/> when you become wedded to animals cravings appetites.  Fo When you<lb/> chain reason to the ever&#45;rolling wheel of low passions.<lb/>  Weaker than a powerless infant&#44; is that rational being proves<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>himself&#44; who he allows the fleeting present to so<lb/> overrule his actions&#44; that he cannot retrace his steps on being<lb/> slavishly dragged into a pit of corruption.  A youth that<lb/> is wise&#44; considers the immense advantages which will flow<lb/> from controlling the wanton the impulses of the moment&#44; and the<lb/> <sic>the</sic> fearful consequences attending their gratification.  Or&#44; as the<lb/> Rabbins have said it&#44; &#91;Hebrew&#93;  he will place on the scales of his judgment<lb/> the slight privations he may suffer in performing a high<lb/> duty&#44; together with the vast reward forthcoming&#44; and the temporary<lb/> pleasures offered by sin with the severity of the punishment<lb/> which will surely follow it.  For&#44; that is virtue&#44; which in<lb/> its primitive sense signifies&#44; manly strength&#59; to pause before<lb/> doing a wrong and shake off temptation&#59; to force immoderate<lb/> wishes under the yoke of chastening morality.  It is a virtue<lb/> not less powerful than beautiful&#59; overspreading the soul of youths<lb/> with a brightness reflected in the countenance.  For&#44; hideous in looks<lb/> is the most stately form stooping to vice&#44; and fairest among the<lb/> fair&#44; the homely face radiant with purity.  Only idlers Wisdom<lb/> turns away with abhorrence from the former&#44; while she folds the<lb/> latter in a sweet embrace.  Only idlers&#44; or vile schemers who<lb/> seek to feather their own nest with the falling plumage of<lb/> richer birds&#45;&#45;if I may use the simile&#45;&#45;are the friends of the unchaste<lb/> and dissolute.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>They will applaud&#44; when the noble&#45;minded would frown&#44;<lb/> make merry over that which will excite the wroth of the upright&#59;<lb/> but let the penalty which dissipation is bound to pay be laid<lb/> upon the guilty&#44; and soon will those smiling associates depart&#44;<lb/> leaving but shame and remorse&#44; as shattered body and a broken<lb/> spirit&#44; as companions to the inconsiderate transgressor.<lb/>  Then will he be heard to exclaim.  &#34;How could I have thus hated in&#45;<lb/>&#45;struction&#44; and let my heart despise admonition&#63;  How could<lb/> I have rejoiced to do evil&#44; and delighted in the forwardness of the<lb/> wicked&#63;  How could I have suffered passing moments to strip<lb/> me of the nobility of manhood&#63;&#34;  But writes the moralist&#44;<lb/> &#34;wisdom will mock you in the day of your calamity&#44; deride<lb/> you when fear cometh at the last.  For you would receive none<lb/> of her counsels&#44; you set at naught her reproofs.&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>Be strong therefore O youths&#44; and show yourselves men.  In pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;portion to your social condition&#44; so must must be the vigour you<lb/> shall call to your assistance.  The child of poverty doubt&#45;<lb/>&#45;less sees enticements rise and beckon to him to follow where<lb/> they direct.  He that is covered with rags and eats the bread<lb/> of toil&#44; may be sorely tempted by at the sight of gold.  But the<lb/> youth who rolls in gold&#44; stands confronted by seductions more<lb/> tyrannical and &#91;&#63;&#93; appalling.  The intoxicating bowl&#44; and the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>gaming board&#44; and libertinism&#44; cast inviting looks towards him.<lb/>  &#34;Come child of fortune&#44; for you have kind parents <sic>ammassed</sic> wealth.<lb/>  Do not deny yourself pleasures.  Time will hang on your hands&#44;<lb/> if you refuse to spend it agreeably.&#34;  So does the enemy of human<lb/> virtue speak to the heirs of opulence.  Woe unto them that<lb/> listen.  Better had they never been born.  For they dig a grave wide<lb/> and deep where will be buried the paternal heritage with their own<lb/> name.  Pity such&#44; my young friends&#33;  Pity the unfortunate<lb/> possessor of corruptive riches.  He that surrenders his manliness<lb/> to worldly seductions.  Like a feeble bark&#44; <sic>buffetted</sic> by<lb/> every wind&#44; he must be overthrown&#59; for&#44; the power of resistance<lb/> was taken from him&#44; when he disdained to lend his hands to soul&#45;<lb/>saving labor.  Work&#44; work&#44; that is the ordinance of nature&#44; which<lb/> we cannot disobey without incurring the severest danger&#44; the loss<lb/> of character &#38; of health.  That idler all perfumed and<lb/> gloved&#44; who eats by the sweat of his father&#39;s brow&#44; cannot repel<lb/> the evils which will face him on all sides.  Lassitude has laid<lb/> hold of his frame.  His hardy fellow&#45;man&#44; he who rises early<lb/> to his daily task will war mighty and withstand temptations.  For&#44;<lb/> a shield and a buckler against vice is manual or mental occupation.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>and They who scorn it are an impure excrescence on<lb/> the body politic.  Happily I address a people who&#44; above all<lb/> others&#44; have imparted dignity to labor&#59; who count among the<lb/> highest in the land&#44; men who that arose from penury to affluence<lb/> and from obscurity to influence&#44; only through diligent work.<lb/>  But to their children&#45;&#45;and I wish I could address thousands in&#45;<lb/>&#45;stead of a few&#45;&#45;to their children I will say with the words of my<lb/> text.  &#34;Be strong and show yourselves men&#34;  Do not become enervated<lb/> by ease and hence by a sport to debasing passions.  Those glowing qualities<lb/> which distinguish youth were not intended to be sunk in the mire<lb/> of corruption.  They are not wholly yours.  They belong also to com&#45;<lb/>&#45;munity of your brethren&#44; the offspring of Adam.  You dare<lb/> not waste them in profligacy.  Stand in awe&#44; therefore for nature will<lb/> avenge itself.  Have you perchance inherited extensive means&#63;<lb/>  Cast them into the treasury of humanity.  They should not turn into wea&#45;<lb/>&#45;pons of destruction&#44; but they should minister to the comfort of the<lb/> joyless&#44; to the furtherance of social progress.  Were you even a<lb/> Cresus&#44; in riches you must still work for a high purpose.  To<lb/> leave your country an exemplar worthy to be copied.  I need not point<lb/> out the pure channels&#44; which you may cause to swell by the<lb/> exertions of patriotism and philanthropy.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Are you not in affluence&#44; but aim to gain it by dent of industry&#63;<lb/>  The elements of greatness lie in your sinewy arms.  With them<lb/> you may strike the mines which will bring forth treasures.<lb/>  Envy not the owners of a large &#91;&#63;&#93; estate.  Your lot is happier than<lb/> theirs.  &#34;Sweet is the sleep of the labour&#44; whether he eats much2 or little1&#44; but the abundance of the rich will not suffer him to sleep&#34;  Carry just balances and just weights on going in<lb/> quest of gold.  Dread temptation more than the prison and the<lb/> gibbet&#44; gather strength to crush it&#44; and you will soar high<lb/> and win fame by manly work.  But to Israelites I must<lb/> say more than I have said hitherto.  The dying father who<lb/> thus advised his son &#34;Be strong and show thyself a man&#34; fol&#45;<lb/>&#45;lowed that counsel by a sentence of deep significance.  I will<lb/> repeat it rehearse it again.  &#34;Keep the charge of the Lord thy God&#44; to walk in<lb/> His ways&#44; to observe His statutes&#44; His commandments&#44; His ordinances&#44;<lb/> and His testimony&#44; as written in the law of Moses&#44; that thou<lb/> mayest prosper in all that thou doest&#44; and withersoever thou<lb/> turnest thyself.&#34;  Jewish youths&#33;  Rally round that standard&#44;<lb/> and you will be safe.  It will cover you from the attack of<lb/> lurking enemies.  They The latter will behold you so well protested&#44; that and<lb/> despairing of success&#44; they will flee away.  Yes&#58; allurements will<lb/> move far from those&#44; whose spirit is imbued with the moral<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>and religious precepts of the Divine legislation.<lb/>  This should be the basis of your strength&#44; as it is the direction of<lb/> life &#91;Hebrew&#93; the future reserved for your labor will then<lb/> be lengthened in a path redolent of chaste delights&#44;<lb/> and when the whole course has been run&#44; looking back&#44;<lb/> you will not discover traces of <sic>ineffeccable</sic> wrongs per&#45;<lb/>&#45;petrated&#44; but only the memorials of a youth beautified<lb/> by chastity deeds of piety and virtue.  Be strong therefore and<lb/> show yourselves men.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
