<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF4_8</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_8_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_8_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_8_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_8_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_8_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_8_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_8_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_8_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_8_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_8_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_8_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_8_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_8_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_8_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_8_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_8_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Post Biblical history<lb/>
                28<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>The An effective means by which to remain humble minded<lb/> after having gained a high station in life&#44;<lb/> is to frequently look at objects remaining of bringing back to mind past<lb/> sufferings and privations.  Agrippa&#44; who by<lb/> a stroke of turn in the wheel of good fortune was raised to the throne upon which<lb/> his grand father Herod had sat upon&#44; acted according<lb/> to that sensible plan.  Arriving at Jerusa&#45;<lb/>&#45;lem&#44; where he was greeted King&#44; he hung in a<lb/> conspicuous place of the Temple&#44; the golden chain<lb/> given him by Caligula&#44; and having the same<lb/> weight as that of the iron chain which he had dragged<lb/> in a Roman prison.  That chain object served as<lb/> a monitor&#44; recalling to mind the lesson&#44; which<lb/> Moses had written to teach a Hebrew ruler wisdom&#44;<lb/> namely &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Let him not lift up his heart above his<lb/> brethren.&#34;  Both Josephus and the Tal&#45;<lb/>&#45;mudists lavish praises on Agrippa&#39;s conduct character.<lb/>  He is described as pious for attending public wor&#45;<lb/>&#45;ship and conforming with all the precepts of<lb/> the Law&#59; as zealous for watching over the in&#45;<lb/>&#45;terest of the religion&#44; never suffering allowing its<lb/> heathen enemies to do it injury&#59; as considerate<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>for relieving the people from the payment<lb/> of house taxes&#44; and for granting Israelites assistance<lb/> from the public funds&#44; like the poor of his own<lb/> faith.  Among instances illus&#45;<lb/>&#45;trating his humblety Agrippa&#39;s meek disposition&#44; the following ones are related.<lb/>  A certain influential man speaker&#44; called Simon&#44; took advan&#45;<lb/>&#45;tage of Agrippa&#39;s absence from Jerusalem to charge<lb/> him with double dealing and insincerity.  The king having heard<lb/> of it the attack on his character&#44; sent for the person accuser&#44; and asked that he would<lb/> show evidences of the faults he had said to have detected.  As none was point&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed out&#44; Agrippa forgave the man and dismissed<lb/> him with a gift&#44; as a token of his pardon.  On<lb/> one occasion&#44; Agrippa was walking out with a<lb/> number of his high officers&#44; when he saw a bridal party<lb/> coming on.  Fearing that his presence might dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;trub the procession&#44; then usual at weddings&#44; he re&#45;<lb/>&#45;tired&#44; saying&#58; &#34;I receive royal honors every day&#44; let<lb/> the Jewish bride be co crowned queen once in her life.&#34;<lb/>  Another time&#44; it being the seventh year&#44; upon the<lb/> feast of Tabernacles&#44; when the book of Deuteronomy<lb/> was to be read&#44; according to tradition&#44; by the chief of the<lb/> nation in the court of the Temple&#44; Agrippa was seen to shed<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>tears.  He had reached that sentence&#44; in which<lb/> Moses commanded thus&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;From among thy own brethren<lb/> thou mayest set a king over thee&#44; thou mayest not set<lb/> over thee a stranger&#44; who is not thy brother.&#34;  Agrippa<lb/> must have thought at that moment of his Idumean<lb/> extraction&#44; and his of the wickedness of his grand parent Herod&#44;<lb/> that had caused <sic>woful</sic> suffering.  But his hearers reassured<lb/> him the reader exalted reader by exclaiming&#44; &#34;be not troubled Agrippa&#44; thou art<lb/> our brother&#44; indeed thout art our brother.&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>Unfortunately Unhappily&#44; the reign which might have afforded Judea<lb/> some rest from external and internal agitations&#44; was of very short duration.  The reason<lb/> which&#44; according to Josephus&#44; brought it to an end&#44;<lb/> within four years cannot be credited.  We may<lb/> believe what that historian tells us about Agrippa&#39;s<lb/> ambition to which was not confined to a laudable endeavour to enlarge and beautify the country&#44; but displayed itself in building magnificent theatres and circuses&#44; in<lb/> the Roman fashion.  Human nature is such besides his laudable endeavouring besides to enlarging and beatifying the<lb/> country  Human nature is such that it needs<lb/> real heroism&#44; to resist temptations&#44; when the means are<lb/> within reach to gratify our cravings.  We may<lb/> believe also that Agrippa did not always remain<lb/> of the same meek temperament and that to satisfy vanity he invited neighboring<lb/> kings to witness observe his luxurious surroundings&#44; but that<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>he should&#44; even for an instant&#44; have<lb/> felt pleased at being called a god&#44; and he should<lb/> have been wonderfully punished in a most fearful manner by reason of it&#44; is in&#45;<lb/>&#45;credible&#44; though the story be substantially repeated receive a confirmation<lb/> in the New Testament.  Josephus says that<lb/> Agrippa went to Cesarea to celebrate some<lb/> festivities in honor of the Roman emperor.  On<lb/> the second day of the public games&#44; he came to<lb/> the theatre dressed in a garment robe of pure silver&#44; so dazzling<lb/> that the rays of the sun striking upon it made the<lb/> face of the wearer shine.  At that&#44; voices were<lb/> heard on all sides crying out &#34;a god&#44; a god.&#34;  Immediately<lb/> an owl perched over Agrippa&#39;s head&#45;&#45;an evil omen<lb/> which had been predicted to him by a fellow prisoner<lb/> at Rome.  Agrippa saw the owl ill&#45;foreboding bird and said &#34;your<lb/> god will soon become dust.&#34;  He was forthwith taken seized<lb/> with excruciating pains torments&#44; and after five days of intense<lb/> suffering agonies he died.  Now&#58; can it be admitted<lb/> that Jews who would have laid down their lives<lb/> rather than allow the mere emblems of idolatry<lb/> in their cities&#44; should become all at once so corrupt of a sudden so depraved<lb/> as to call him a god&#44; who had risked much three years before to prevent<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Caligula from setting up his image in the<lb/> Temple&#63;  It may be possible that Romans&#44;<lb/> present at the entertainments had shouted out the<lb/> impious cry.  They were accustomed to deify mortals&#44;<lb/> but that Hebrews should have become guilty of that<lb/> profanity&#44; or that Arippa should have winked<lb/> at the blasphemy&#44; is beyond credibility credibility.<lb/></p>
            <p>The premature death of King Agrippa died in his fifty fourth year.<lb/>  That premature demise which plunged the Jews into deep mourning&#44; was <lb/>the sign of most for horridly shameful scenes on that part of<lb/> the Greek population of Samaria and Cesarea.<lb/>  Many of the Romans who hated the Jews joined<lb/> in abominable acts&#44; and thus intensified the ani&#45;<lb/>&#45;mosities which inflamed made inflamed the passions in the last national struggle&#44;<lb/> so terrible and rendered it so terrible.<lb/></p>
            <p>Agrippa had left three daughters&#44; and one son named<lb/> after him&#44; and pursuing then a course of studies in Rome.<lb/>  As the youth was only seventeen years of age&#44; the<lb/> Roman emperor&#44; sent Fadus to govern Judea.  It<lb/> was during his the administration of that latter proconsul&#44; that a severe famine<lb/> broke out in the land.  In that sad emergency<lb/> assistance arrived providentially from a source unlooked for.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>In a country called Adiabene situated in<lb/> Western Asia&#44; where Kurdistan now lies&#44; a king<lb/> named Monobaz had married Helena his own sister&#45;&#45;<lb/> a circumstance not at all uncommon among heathens.<lb/>  He had by her a number of several sons&#44; two of whom have<lb/> a commendable record in Jewish history&#45;&#45;Monobaz and<lb/> Isates.  The latter&#44; however&#44; became the his parents&#39;<lb/> favorite.  Such a predilection naturally created jea&#45;<lb/>&#45;lousy&#44; and to ward off troubles&#44; the father sent Isates<lb/> to live with a friendly ruler in another a distant land.  When<lb/> King Monobaz was old&#44; wishing to secure the throne<lb/> for Isates called him nearer home.  Helena as soon<lb/>as her husband died&#44; assembled the nobility and prevailed upon her people them to<lb/> place the crown on the head of Isates.  Monobaz<lb/> his elder brother&#44; generously agreed&#44; and the other<lb/> brothers&#44; being provided for were made to settle abroad&#44; some<lb/> in Italy&#44; others in Parthia.  Now&#44; it happened<lb/> that in the country to which Isates had been sent<lb/> by his father&#44; as a safeguard against domestic quarrels&#44; a Jewish merchant<lb/> named Hananiah became the bosom friend of<lb/> the young prince from Adiabene.  In the course of frequent con&#45;<lb/>&#45;versations&#44; Hananiah explained to Isates the principles<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>and ordinances of the Law of Moses.; and they  The<lb/> youth was so profoundly impressed&#44; that he deter&#45;<lb/>&#45;mined the to embrace the Jewish religion.  When he Isates<lb/> was proclaimed a king&#44; he disclosed his sentiments to<lb/> his mother&#44; who had also without his previous knowledge shared his feelings.  For she also had been secretly instructed in<lb/> Judaism&#44; and had privately followed its rules.<lb/>  Helena&#44; however&#44; moved by political reasons&#44;<lb/> was unwilling that her son should venture openly<lb/> to declare himself a convert to the Hebrew faith.<lb/>  But a Galilean Jew&#44; called Eleazar&#44; having sur&#45;<lb/>&#45;prised him in the act of reading the Pentateuch&#44; said that un&#45;<lb/>&#45;less he carried out outwardly the belief which he had<lb/> accepted inwardly&#44; his conversion was of no account.<lb/>  Both his mother and Hananiah tried to dissuade<lb/> him from heeding the dangerous an advice&#44; attended with<lb/> great dangers&#44; but Isates resolved concluded to act boldly&#44;<lb/> and let his nation know the creed he professed.<lb/>  As a result a sedition broke out&#44; and some of the principal men<lb/> in the kingdom country invited the king of the Arabs to fight<lb/> Isates as he being in their estimation an enemy of the dominant religion.  Fortunately<lb/> the army stood by Isates&#44; so that he defeated the Arabs&#44;<lb/> punished the aristocracy opposed to him&#44; and order was restored.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Helena thankful for her son&#39;s success&#44;<lb/> resolved to go and worship the God she adored&#44;<lb/> in His sacred temple at Jerusalem.  She arrived in<lb/> the capital of Judea&#44; just as the famine was<lb/> raging.  Imbued with the maxims of the religion<lb/> which extol mercy and compassion as high most ennobling virtues&#44;<lb/> Helena of Adiabene scattered blessings broadcast.<lb/>  She ordered ship loads of grain from Alexandria&#44;<lb/> abundance of fruits from Cyprus&#44; and having filled<lb/> the hungry&#44; she distributed large means gold which her son Isates<lb/> had placed at his disposal&#44; to supply other wants.<lb/>  The Talmud makes laudable mention of Helena<lb/> as a generous donor also to the Temple Sanctuary.  She present&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed to it a chandelier and a plate of massive<lb/> gold.  But perhaps the most illustrious<lb/> of that family of righteous proselytes is Monobaz<lb/> II&#44; who succeeded his brother Isates in the govern&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment of the kingdom of Adiabene.  It is nar&#45;<lb/>&#45;rated that his open handed liberality had become<lb/> distasteful to some of his relatives.  They said<lb/> to him&#58; &#34;your ancestors <sic>ammassed</sic> untold fortunes&#44;<lb/> but you are giving away what they well guarded.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>To these compliments he was often subjected&#44; but he<lb/> would would reason thus&#58; &#34;My ancestors gathered<lb/> riches and laid them by on earth&#44; I am gathering riches<lb/> which will do me service in heaven.  My ancestors put<lb/> money where thieves can steal it&#44; I store it where<lb/> no robber can deprive me of it&#59; they took pains<lb/> about things which are fleeting&#44; I take good care<lb/> of human life&#44; and by doing that so acting I commission<lb/> a herald to pave the way to my lasting hap&#45;<lb/>&#45;piness&#44; for it is said written&#44; &#34;thy righteousness shall<lb/> walk before thee.&#34;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  The piety of the royal<lb/> house of Adiabene&#44; was equal to the munificent<lb/> charity that gained it a well deserved notoriety<lb/> in post Biblical history.  Three graves were<lb/> seen not far from Jerusalem long after the days<lb/> of Josephus.  They contained the remains of Helena&#44;<lb/> and her two sons Isates and Monobaz&#44; whose would last wish<lb/> was to be buried in the ground hallowed by the prophets<lb/> and sages of Israel.  whose teachings had been dear to their hearts.<lb/>  The descendants of that worthy triad&#44; attached to &#45;&#45;loving the<lb/> people&#44; whose religion they had adopted&#44; fought<lb/> side by side with the patriots who that resisted tyrannic Rome.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>Some bled for Judea and fell upon the battle field&#44;<lb/> others were taken captives and carried to the seven<lb/> hilled city&#44; when Titus burned the Temple&#44; and<lb/> scattered away like chaff the <sic>worshippers</sic> of the One Eternal God.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
