<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF2_13a</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1896" source="" attested="yes">1896</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_13_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_13_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_13_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_13_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_13_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_13_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_13_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_13_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_13_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_13_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_13_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_13_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_13_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_13_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_13_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_13_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>13 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>On the character<lb/>
                of Joseph<lb/>
                96<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Last year at this time&#44; I delivered two lectures&#44; which&#44; ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;parently&#44; met with general approbation.  I judge so&#44;<lb/> because several persons asked that they might peruse<lb/> the manuscripts.  The request was readily acquiesced in&#59;<lb/> but that circumstance neither rare nor remarkable&#44; was<lb/> attended with a result&#44; I had not anticipated.  It induced<lb/> me to discard altogether the written discourse&#44; and preach<lb/> simply from some brief notes.  For&#44; what I had lent&#44;<lb/> came never to hand.  My compositions&#44; of which I<lb/> possessed no other copy&#44; were lost&#44; and all endeavours to<lb/> recover them&#44; proved fruitless.  I consequently&#44; adopted<lb/> a plan&#44; which would preclude the recurrence of that<lb/> vexatious incident&#44; by preventing a repetition of the request<lb/> which had occasioned it.  But I have long regretted&#44;<lb/> my inability to make from memory even an abstract<lb/> of what I had then said.  For&#44; the subject I had treated&#44;<lb/> interested me greatly&#44; and for its sake alone I set<lb/> some value on my writing.  Now&#44; the same<lb/> topic presents itself to our consideration&#44; and I purpose<lb/> to dwell thereupon.  You will not&#44; I imagine&#44; refuse<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>me attention&#44; because ideas and probably expressions<lb/> I have uttered in your presence&#44; may be repeated.<lb/>  The character of Joseph cannot lose aught of its<lb/> attractiveness&#44; though our eyes be directed to it with<lb/> frequency.  Nay&#44; each time we contemplate it&#44; a<lb/> new feature may be revealed&#44; whose radiant beauty&#44;<lb/> had not yet struck our vision.  As a portrait from<lb/> the pencil of a great master&#44; will unfold all the<lb/> loveliness of its lineaments&#44; after minute observation&#59;<lb/> so will Joseph&#39;s excellencies virtues&#44; disclose their<lb/> full excellency&#44; the nearer we draw to them our minds.<lb/>  An ancient translator has rendered so a passage occur&#45;<lb/>&#45;ring at the commencement of the history of Jacob&#39;s favorite<lb/> son.  &#34;Israel loved Joseph more than all his children&#44;<lb/> for&#44; a wise son was he to him&#34;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> I will not discuss&#44; at present&#44; the correctness or in&#45;<lb/>&#45;correctness of that version.  It may not be borne out<lb/> by the text in the original.  But that the god&#45;like<lb/> quality attributed to the youth&#44; was stamped upon<lb/> his soul&#44; a checkered existence incontestably proves.<lb/>  Wisdom&#45;&#45;which is the employing of righteous means&#44;<lb/> to accomplish a righteous end&#45;&#45;&#44; governed his conduct&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>in all the relations of life.<lb/></p>
            <p>Joseph loved his father dearly.  Filial obedience had<lb/> prompted him to meet&#44; in a spot&#44; dangerous because<lb/> unfrequented&#44; those brothers who had not disguised the<lb/> rancour they harbored.  His heart which had<lb/> swelled with filial attachment under the garment&#44;<lb/> indicative of paternal preference&#44; throbbed with the same<lb/> sentiment&#44; under the insignia of power &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;I am Joseph&#44; is my father yet alive&#63;&#34; was the first utter&#45;<lb/>&#45;of the Egyptian ruler at the hour of recognition.<lb/>  Still&#44; twenty years glided by&#44; and no search had been<lb/> made of that father so cherished&#44; so reverenced&#44; Joseph<lb/> whence as a bondman&#44; Joseph an the inmate of a prison<lb/> cell&#44; might have found it impossible to apprize<lb/> his afflicted parent of his condition&#44; and of his land of<lb/> exile.  But all of us instinctively feel&#44; that when<lb/> seated next to the mighty Sovereign of Mizraim&#44;<lb/> he should not have suffered one instant to elapse&#44;<lb/> ere he sent that important communication.<lb/>  Whence then the apparent neglect&#63;....<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Seek it&#44; my beloved hearers&#33; in that quality which distin&#45;<lb/>guished him from his earliest years &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> such tidings directly from the individuall foully dealt<lb/> with&#44; must needs have <sic>criminated</sic> his brothers.  The<lb/> <sic>unravelling</sic> of that plot&#44; whose consummation<lb/> had plunged a fond parent with inconsolable grief&#44;<lb/> might have brought down a curse upon the<lb/> heads of eleven ten sons.  It might have created a<lb/> fatal estrangement between a father and his<lb/> numerous descendants&#44; <sic>rewakened</sic> and intensified<lb/> the ill will once entertained against the favorite<lb/> offspring of Rachel&#44; and prevented the realization<lb/> of those dreams&#44; which a voice within declared to<lb/> be prophetic.  Not so&#44; when the culprits crimi&#45;<lb/>&#45;nals themselves with tokens of fraternal reconciliation&#44;<lb/> with glowing countenances&#44; tell&#44; in accents not to be<lb/> mistaken &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Joseph lives<lb/> yet&#59; he is the governor of all the land of Egypt.&#34;<lb/>  That news&#44; so related&#44; is the dove with the olive branch<lb/> which betokensing the <sic>abeting</sic> of stormy passions.  the<lb/> It is the rain&#45;bow of family peace and reunion.<lb/>  In fact&#44; not a word denoting anger followed that disclosure.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>The heart&#44; suddenly opened to emotions long unfelt&#44;<lb/> cannot find reproaches and accusations.  Love&#44;<lb/> the purest&#44; the deepest love for a virtuous son&#44; thrilled<lb/> at that moment the aged patriarch &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;It is enough&#44; my son Joseph is lives yet alive I will go<lb/> and see him before I die.&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>Let us ponder again&#44; my dear hearers&#33; and we shall see<lb/> wisdom.  The viceroy of Egypt might have prepared<lb/> in the kingly court&#44; sumptuous apartments for the reception of his own<lb/> kinsmen. in the kingly court.  What a satisfaction<lb/> for the loving Joseph to set a habitation for his father&#44;<lb/> where he dwelt&#33;  Yet&#44; Jacob&#39;s household were far<lb/> removed from the metropolis.  Their benefactor desired<lb/> that the ancestral profession might not be exchanged<lb/> for others of greater dignity&#44; but of less simplicity.<lb/>  Shepherds were looked upon with abhorrence by the Egyptians&#44;<lb/> who paid divine honors to cattle and herd dumb animals.  But that<lb/> did not alter his purposes.  He had not aimed at<lb/> gaining for his brothers favor among the magnates<lb/> of the land&#59; but at obtaining a place of security&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>where they might abide together&#44; and&#44; pursuing<lb/> the ancient calling&#59; preserve in their midst the<lb/> precious knowledge entrusted by their progenitors to<lb/> their safe&#45;keeping.  The people&#44; whom Providence<lb/> had called Joseph to govern&#44; ranked foremost among<lb/> the enlightened nations of that time historical period&#59; but he prized<lb/> the knowledge of God&#39;s Unity treasured up as within<lb/> his own kinsmen family&#44; was above all the learning of<lb/> Egyptian sages.  To lose that knowledge&#44; would<lb/> have been to destroy the hope of Abraham&#44; and of<lb/> all generations to the end of time.  A constant intercourse<lb/> with high officials might have engendered that evil.<lb/>  It was therefore to strengthen the blessed belief in One God among<lb/> its chosen propagators&#44; that they were stationed away<lb/> from the capital&#44; where idolatry and idolators pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;ponderated.  But to show the world that the<lb/> most distinguished of all men in the kingdom&#44; gloried<lb/> in his lowly parent&#44; Joseph himself conducted Jacob into the<lb/> presence of Pharaoh.  The unpretending shepherd<lb/> of Canaan was introduced by his illustrious son to<lb/> the still greater potentate a still higher personage to the Monarch of a<lb/> renowned country.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Oh&#33; that we would so reverence our aged fathers&#44; and<lb/> our hoary&#45;headed mothers&#33;  We would not then witness<lb/> what many a house exhibits.  The sons and<lb/> daughters entertaining visitors&#44; from whose company&#44; the old parents have designedly been excluded.  Perhaps&#44;<lb/> they are not as polished as we ourselves.  They may not<lb/> speak with the same fluency on the topics of the<lb/> day.  But neither was Jacob acquainted with the<lb/> customs of the Egyptians&#44; nor had he been trained<lb/> in their schools.  It mattered not to the dutiful<lb/> son&#44; whether his father&#39;s manner of salutation agreed<lb/> with that which then prevailed&#44; or whether his expressions<lb/> betrayed his foreign birth.  Under all circumstances&#59;<lb/> in all every event&#44; publicly as well as privately he<lb/> would do the author of his life honor.  He would not<lb/> raise a shadow of suspicion that he esteemed the<lb/> guardians of his early days less&#44; because he himself was<lb/> respected more.  From the happy moment that father<lb/> and son were again clasped into <sic>each other&#39;s</sic> arms&#44;<lb/> every action betokened filial affection&#44; filial<lb/> devotion.  The patriarch felt the influence of<lb/> Joseph&#39;s wisdom in the direction of his household He felt that he was still &#91;Hebrew&#93; and with<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>overflowing love&#44; bestowed&#44; on his death bed&#44; a<lb/> blessing rich and infinite upon that child&#44; who<lb/> had become &#34;the shepherd&#44; the &#40;corner&#41; stone of Israel.&#34;<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            <p>But the character we have contemplated&#44;<lb/> displays features still brighter than those we have<lb/> hitherto beheld.  No effort is required to act gene&#45;<lb/>&#45;rously towards those who have even proved our staun&#45;<lb/>&#45;chest friends.  We are impelled by instinct to return<lb/> good to our benefactors&#59; and he does violence to his<lb/> nature&#44; who shuts out gratitude from his breast.<lb/>  But to seek the welfare of those who sought our<lb/> destruction.  To crush resentment&#44; and let kindliness<lb/> alone be the plummet of our deportment&#44; is a heroism&#44; which<lb/> but few possess.  &#34;Revenge is sweet&#59;&#34; so &#91;&#63;&#93; the<lb/> immoral adage.  And who could have wreaked it more<lb/> fully than Joseph upon his brothers&#63;  They had come<lb/> unawares&#44; under his <sic>his</sic> absolute power.  Those who had<lb/> plotted his ruin were in his grasp.  Why not thrust<lb/> into their sides the thorns by which he had been<lb/> pricked&#63;  They had ruthlessly torn him away from<lb/> a joyous home.  They had exposed his life to abject<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>servitude.  His wailing and entreaties had not softened<lb/> their hearts.  Now the time had arrived&#44; when the to force<lb/> up to their lips the bitter cup he had been made to<lb/> swallow.  But&#44;.... &#34;no.  Vengeance belongs only<lb/> to God.  What art thou O mortal&#44; that darest to<lb/> arrogate to thyself powers not thine own&#63;  The evil<lb/> devised against thee&#44; cannot do thee harm&#44; if thou be<lb/> righteous&#44; for&#44; Providence directs human events.  Guile<lb/> cannot succeed.&#34;  So thought Joseph.  The comforting<lb/> belief in a just God&#44; which had upheld him amidst<lb/> the severest trials&#44; infused into his soul a spirit<lb/> of forgiveness&#44; of pity for the sinners&#59; and an<lb/> irresistible wish to cancel even from their minds even<lb/> the remembrance of their guilt.  Joseph&#39;s austere<lb/> demeanour towards his brothers&#44; at the outset&#44; was<lb/> another wise means whereby which to reach a noble end.  It<lb/> was assumed to discover&#44; whether time had wrought a<lb/> salutary change in their feelings&#44; whether they had<lb/> become sensible of the enormity of their crime&#44; and they<lb/> would at all hazards&#44; shield Benjamin&#44; the favorite child of<lb/> the Rachel from the dangers&#44; whereby which he pa&#44; appa&#45;<lb/>rently&#44; he was beset.  But when that was ascert&#45;<lb/>&#45;ained<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>to his satisfaction&#59; then tears and kisses&#44; munificent<lb/> gifts&#44; and suasive words drew heart to heart in<lb/> fraternal reconciliation &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;It was not you that sent me hither&#44; but God.&#34;  He<lb/> has willed it.  You have only been the instruments of<lb/> his salvation.  You have&#44; unknowingly&#44; caused my<lb/> exaltation.  You have effected the preservation keeping of<lb/> your family from famine&#44; and the delivery of a<lb/> vast population.  Do not regret the past&#44; for it<lb/> has been fraught with happiness.  Such&#44; my dear hearers&#44;<lb/> is human forgiveness.  Not a pang should they suffer<lb/> who had been the deadliest enemies shown &#91;&#63;&#93; deep rooted enmity.  And when after<lb/> the death of their father&#44; Joseph&#39;s brothers dreading retributive justice resorted to<lb/> a stratagem&#44; in order to avert its strokes &#34;the rigtheous man the &#91;&#63;&#93; son &#91;Hebrew&#93; nay&#44; the &#91;Hebrew&#93; the merciful son he calmed<lb/> their fears.  How could he punish&#44; he exclaimed&#44; what had<lb/> <sic>yeilded</sic> so much good&#63;  Their thoughts had been the<lb/> seeds of a joyful harvest.  They should reap it&#44; they<lb/> should dwell together in the fruition of plenty in harmony in the<lb/> absence of all misgivings and terror&#44; in that revenge<lb/> is sweet.  But the other&#44; so styled by a corrupt world&#44;<lb/> is gall and wormwood.  It injures him that harbors<lb/> it&#59; more than the individual against whom it is cherished.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>For&#44; passions corrode our vitals&#44; and none is so virulent&#44;<lb/> as a spirit of vindictiveness.  There is a psalm&#44; which<lb/> I earnestly recommend those to read&#44; who are so un&#45;<lb/>&#45;fortunate as to be swayed by that evil spirit.  It is<lb/> the 37th.  In it&#44; the righteous are assured that<lb/> they will never be overpowered by the wicked &#91;Hebrew&#93; the<lb/> latter may&#44; at times&#44; seem to succeed in their devices&#44;<lb/> but the faithful will ever be saved up in the mountain<lb/> of the Lord.  Though they fall&#44; they will shall<lb/> rise.  For&#44; at their right&#45;hand stands the Director<lb/> of sublunary events&#44; at the left they are sup&#45;<lb/>&#45;ported by the purity of their conscience.  Joseph<lb/> in a dungeon&#44; was a happier being&#44; than his guilty<lb/> brothers at large.  And when the evnied and the hated&#44;<lb/> heaped upon the envious and the haters&#44; favors and<lb/> benefactions&#44; he&#44; against his will&#44; awakened a<lb/> feeling of gnawing remorse.  Glorious vengeance&#44;<lb/> and more glorious recompense.  We read &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Moses took the bones of Joseph with him.&#34;  The most<lb/> exalted of of all men&#44; assumed to convey those<lb/> precious relics to the promised land.  When the heathens&#44;<lb/> asked in astonishment &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p>&#34;Why does the ark in which a dead m creature is<lb/> deposited&#44; travel with that wherein the word of<lb/> a living God is enshrined.&#34;  The answer was<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;He that is enshrouded<lb/> in this ark&#44; fulfilled what the commandments pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;served in that ark.&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>Dear hearers&#33;  Moses Joseph had not been irra&#45;<lb/>&#45;diated by the light of revelation.  He intuitively<lb/> learnt what was is pleasing in the sight of the<lb/> Beneficent Lord&#44; and followed it to the letter.  We<lb/> were taught at Sinai not &#34;to revenge&#44; or bear<lb/> grudge&#44;&#34; &#34;not to hate our brother in our heart.&#34;<lb/>  That golden rule was given us by our Common<lb/> Parent&#44; that we may not fall out with our brethren<lb/> by the way.  Oh&#33; let us dwelt together as<lb/> children of the same God. &#91;Hebrew&#93;  In this transitory path<lb/> which we tread&#44; many are the prickly thorns which<lb/> impede our course.  Let us unite in our efforts and to remove<lb/> them.  Let us strew with flowers our neighbor&#39;s way&#44;<lb/> that the mercy shown unto others&#44; may be shown unto<lb/> us&#44; and we reach the end of our journey&#44; in peace<lb/> with our fellow&#45;mortals&#44; in peace with our conscience&#44;<lb/> in peace with our Creator and saviour.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
