<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF3_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_2_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>2d Historical lecture.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  In my last lecture I remarked&#44; that all which<lb/> I might say about respecting the condition of the exiles in Babylon<lb/> previous to the restoration&#44; was an inferential and not a positive<lb/> statement drawn from historical sources.  I also argued<lb/> that the admonitions of Ezekiel addressed to his coreligionists<lb/> who had been carried with him as captives&#44; not less than<lb/> to those who still remained in Palestine&#44; would seem to show<lb/> the want of a general return to the religion of Moses.<lb/></p>
            <p>What had happened since the death of the prophet&#44; to bring about a change for the better in<lb/> the feelings of our people&#44; after the death of their prophet&#44;<lb/> is no more certain than other events of that period.  It<lb/> has been supposed by some&#45;&#45;and it may not be improbable&#45;&#45;that political agitations in the<lb/> country of the dispersion&#44; exposed our ancestors to perse&#45;<lb/>&#45;cutions&#44; and&#44; as reverses are mostly a wholesome schooling&#44;<lb/> the half&#45;hearted Judeans were transformed by misfortunes<lb/> into rigid adherents of the Law.  Greek historians<lb/> have not deemed it worth their while to speak at any length of our<lb/> people in connection with the fall or rise of nations&#44; among<lb/> whom we dwelt and whose annals they handed down.<lb/>  A rare allusion scattered among their writings&#44; is not even a glimmer of light&#44; when we need clear<lb/> facts.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Modern discoveries&#44; specially in the art of deciphering<lb/> inscriptions on Assyrian and Chaldean monuments&#44; or what<lb/> is now called cuneiform writings&#44; will&#44; when further ad&#45;<lb/>&#45;vanced&#44; help us very considerably.  But for the present&#44;<lb/> we must rest satisfied with the slight information in&#45;<lb/>&#45;directly afforded by the Bible.<lb/></p>
            <p>In the lo book of Daniel King Darius is styled &#34;the Median.&#34;<lb/>  We learn therefore that the dreaded Babylon&#44; which had<lb/> conquered the once mighty Assyrian was in turn blotted out crushed by<lb/> another great power.  Media allied to Persia gained the mastery<lb/> over the band to which our fathers had been banished.  When<lb/> Cyrus&#44; who is described by sacred and profane historians as<lb/> brave and generous&#44; mounted the throne&#44; a bright era of pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;mise opened for the Judeans.  &#34;The ransomed of the Lord shall<lb/> return&#44; and come to Zion with songs and everlasting joy upon their<lb/> heads&#58; they shall obtain gladness and joy&#44; and sorrow and siging <sic>sighying</sic><lb/> shall flee away.&#34;  This olden prophecy must have then<lb/> inspirited the dejected.  For thou a new generation<lb/> has been born since the blinded and shackled Zedekiah had<lb/> ended his life in a Chaldean prison&#44; the memories of the past<lb/> still lingered with the aged&#44; and in those painful memories the<lb/> young were reared.  Love for the desolate home was kept alive in many<lb/> a breast.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Psalm CII is unquestionably an outburst of patriotic<lb/> sentiments.  The writer feels distressed&#59; for his life is drawing<lb/> to a close and the spot whose stones are held dear&#59; whose very<lb/> dust is cherished&#44; lies yet in ruin.  &#34;Thou wilt rise O Lord&#33; and<lb/> have pity on Zion&#44;&#34; the exile exclaims.  Men burning with<lb/> such zeal must have could not have been rare.  They must have enkindled hope when recalling the declaration of Jeremiah<lb/> uttered within their own hearing.  &#34;Thus says the Lord&#44; when seven&#45;<lb/>&#45;ty years shall have been completed by Babylon I will visit<lb/> you.&#34;  Should it also likewise also be true&#45;&#45;as a legend tells&#45;&#45;that Synagogues<lb/> existed at that period&#44; the prayers and the preaching of<lb/> the enthusiastic must have contributed incalculably to<lb/> inspire a longing for a reconstruction of the Hebrew<lb/> nationality.  Cyrus may have been consulted<lb/> on the subject by some of the most influential of our an&#45;<lb/>&#45;cestors&#44; who in various capacities had free access to the<lb/> royal courts.<lb/></p>
            <p>I myself had formerly always shared the opinion prevalent among<lb/> scholars that a similarity of religious doctrine had actuated<lb/> Cyrus our deliverer in his proclamation.  Not alone its wording<lb/> as reported in our Bible led me to think so&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>but also the general impression that the illustrious<lb/> Chief&#44; whose valor and sagacity made him the sole<lb/> monarch of Asia&#44; had been the folly of idolatry and dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;carded it.  Zoroaster had founded a new belief which<lb/> admitted no more than one god.  His was represented in<lb/> a twofold character by the element which preserves life<lb/> and destroys it&#45;&#45;by fire.  The sun&#44; as its symbol&#44; was<lb/> paid homage to.  You perceive the remarkable im&#45;<lb/>&#45;provement which that worship was over the polytheism multiform varied and demoralising idolatry<lb/> of the ancients.  Cyrus who had adopted it&#44; may<lb/> have felt deep sympathy the for an enslaved race that<lb/> lamented the loss of a country&#44; where an all&#45;sustaining spirit<lb/> had a sanctuary.  Recently&#44; however&#44; my opi&#45;<lb/>&#45;nion has been somewhat shaken&#44; though not upset&#44; by<lb/> the writing of a learned critic.  He asserts that old cu&#45;<lb/>&#45;neiform inscriptions&#44; now legible&#44; prove Cyrus a confirmed<lb/> polytheist.  He farther contends that the edict of the Medo&#45;<lb/>Persian ruler was a mere stroke of policy.  By delivering the<lb/> Judeans from bondage&#44; Cyrus the liberator would secure to himself an open<lb/> road to his contemplated conquests.  Aiming severe blows at<lb/> Egypt&#44; he would set a friendly and grateful people in ter&#45;<lb/>&#45;ritories&#44; which gave him an unimpeded passage from Asia to Africa.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>I am not ready to accept those views&#44; knowing how<lb/> deceptive have been the hopes of having gained obtaining the key<lb/> for the a perfect deciphering of those inscriptions.  But what&#45;<lb/>&#45;ever the real motive of our liberator the great Cyrus was&#44; none will deny<lb/> that he displayed great great magnanimity towards our ancestors.<lb/>  Besides his having returned the sacred vessels of the Temple&#44;<lb/> which Nebuchadnezzar had carried as trophies to Baby&#45;<lb/>&#45;lon&#59; besides his having ordered that those disposed to go<lb/> back to Palestine should receive substantial aid from all his<lb/> subjects&#44; he appointed over the Judeans&#44; as Pasha&#44; or Governor&#44;<lb/> a man of their own religion&#44; enjoying the highest repu&#45;<lb/>&#45;tation.  Zerubabel&#44; great grand&#45;child son of King Jeho&#45;<lb/>&#45;jachin became the leader of his zealous brethren&#44; and he&#44;<lb/> with praise worthy modesty&#44; associated to himself a man<lb/> equally venerated&#45;&#45;Joshua the priest of the family of Zadok.<lb/></p>
            <p>What follows what that which the statements I have hitherto narrated related presented is chro&#45;<lb/>&#45;nicled in the Scriptures&#44; and each of my hearers can read it in<lb/> the books of Ezra and Nehemiah.  Still Nevertheless&#44; it may not<lb/> be amiss before we proceed with post&#45;biblical narratives&#44;<lb/> to cast a cursory glance at events which occurred im&#45;<lb/>&#45;mediately after the restoration.<lb/></p>
            <p>The number of our people who voluntarily chose to make<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>their home again in the patriarchal land&#44; was com&#45;<lb/>&#45;paratively small.  The largest majority of the Israelites<lb/> whom Assyria had transported to the dominions she then<lb/> possessed&#44; but which now belonged to Cyrus&#44; stayed<lb/> back.  Nor did the tribes of Judah and Benjamin<lb/> fully return.  All told&#44; comprising including priests&#44; levites<lb/> and Nethunim&#44; or servants&#44; did not amount to fifty<lb/> thousands.  Still those who revisited Zion wee sterling patriots&#44; men truly actuated<lb/> by righteous intentions.  Puritans they have been inaptly called&#58; no&#44; they were the avant&#45;guard or God&#39;s army.  Their inspired contemporary might<lb/> well apply to them his sentence &#34;Not by might and<lb/> not by power&#44; but only by My Spirit says the Lord of<lb/> hosts.&#34;  Those who had The newly arrived would not have con&#45;<lb/>&#45;sidered any sacrifice too great to accomplish their sacred object.<lb/>  They erected a temporary altar and held there the daily service.<lb/>  They engaged Phoenicians&#44; who were proverbially skilled<lb/> in cutting down trees and preparing timber&#44; and made<lb/> every arrangement for reconstructing the Temple.  The<lb/> corner stone was laid with deep solemnity amidst devo&#45;<lb/>&#45;tional songs with which the sobbing of the aged&#44; who remem&#45;<lb/>&#45;bered Solomon&#39;s temple became loudly mingled.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>&#34;Oh give thanks unto the Lord who is good&#44; for His<lb/> mercy endureth for ever.&#34;  This national anthem resounded again upon the soil&#44; where<lb/> it had first burst forth from the hearts of happy thousands&#44;<lb/> on the day that David carried the Ark of the testimony to the ca&#45;<lb/>&#45;pital of his kingdom realm.  A speedy issue to the auspicious<lb/> beginning was anticipated&#44; but unfortunately it was not reali&#45;<lb/>&#45;zed.  The jealousy of neighboring tribes&#44; that who had<lb/> peopled the portion of the country forming &#91;&#63;&#93; the Kingdom<lb/> of Israel&#45;&#45;specially the ill&#45;will of the Catheans or Samaritans&#44;<lb/> harassed the workers and maliciously caused the suspension of the work.<lb/>  After the death of Cyrus&#44; those who could not bear to see<lb/> the new colony so greatly signally favored by the Persian govern&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment&#44; grew very daring.  By preferring direct<lb/> charges before the authorities&#44; they succeeded in arising arousing dark<lb/> suspicions against our people&#44; and stopping altogether the sacred holy<lb/> undertaking.  Fifteen years passed away in<lb/> inactivity.  Private dwellings were being slowly set up&#44; but<lb/> the Temple remained unbuilt.  Then prophets arose and<lb/> spoke.  Hagga&#239; addressed stirredly up words to Zerubabel&#44; the governor&#59;<lb/> Zachariah with pointed figures and allegories&#44; and figures with glowing de&#45;2<lb/>&#45;clarations and predictions1&#44; reanimated revivified the public spirit.<lb/>  The labor was proceeding well when and the laborers rejoiced suddenly the right to do it was again<lb/> challenged.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>But Providence had raised a mighty protector&#59; a worthy<lb/> Happily successor of Cyrus.  Carius Hystaspis&#44; the ruling sovereign&#44; when<lb/> appealed to&#44; confirmed the edict of Cyrus his predecessor.  In language<lb/> which reveals in him sentiments of generosity like those not at all suf&#45;<lb/>of his illustrious predecessors &#45;fering at all in comparison with those of the first and most illustrious king of who had sat on the throne of Medio and Persian throne&#44;<lb/> he ordered that that every facility be lent for the completion<lb/> of the house of God&#44; for promoting its service worship&#44; and for making<lb/> the settlement of the Judeans in their ancient home&#44; a re&#45;<lb/>&#45;sidence of security and ease.  Under his auspices&#44; the Temple<lb/> on mount Moriah arose lifted up its turrets a second time in its glory heavenward.  The<lb/> dedication was was an occasion of national triumph.  Our Hebrew<lb/> sources reckon the hundred of animals slaughtered at its cele&#45;<lb/>&#45;bration.  In my next lecture I shall describe a service more ac&#45;<lb/>&#45;ceptable to the Deity than the blood of rams&#44; and present shall introduce to your<lb/> to you acquaintance some of the men who gave our people eternity on earth by means<lb/> of that service soul&#45;exalting service&#45;&#45;prayers and the study<lb/> of the holy Torah.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
