<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF6_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1896" source="" attested="yes">1896</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff6_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff6_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff6_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff6_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff6_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff6_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff6_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff6_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff6_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff6_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff6_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff6_1_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>96<lb/>
                On the Haftorah of Vayishlach<lb/>
                on Idumea.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Your distinguished personages&#44; bearing the<lb/> same name are mentioned in the Hebrew scriptures<lb/> concerning the first in historical order&#44; we read some&#45;<lb/>&#45;thing in the book of Kings &#91;Hebrew&#93; chapter Eighteenth.<lb/>  All that are familiar with the Bible&#44; will re&#45;<lb/>&#45;member how Jezebel&#44; the <sic>Phenician</sic> idolatress&#44;<lb/> who had become the wife of the easily to be corrupted<lb/> Ahab&#44; determined to make the debauching worship<lb/> of her non native land&#44; set aside every law of<lb/> Sinai.  She could not think of a quicker me&#45;<lb/>&#45;thod by which by which to gain her point&#44; than by<lb/> forcing into silence men&#44; who in the school of<lb/> the prophets had learned to go about preaching<lb/> the Torah.  In her wickedness&#44; she ordered<lb/> some of those true ministers of the Lord&#44; to be<lb/> killed&#44; others she compelled to hide away from the<lb/> public notice community.  But within the walls<lb/> of the palace at Samariah&#44; from whence Jezebel<lb/> <sic>tyrranized</sic> over the Kingdom of Israel&#44; there was a<lb/> <sic>a</sic> servant of God&#44; unknown as such to the idolatry steeped queen queen&#44; steeped in idolatry.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Obadiah was he called.  Entrusted with the<lb/> stewardship of the royal house unsuspected by the inmates thereof he secretly<lb/> endeavoured to thwart defeat the plans of the iniquitous<lb/> Jezebel.  He delivered a number of those whom<lb/> she would have consigned to the grave slaughter thus<lb/> personally facing dreadful dangers in his love obedience to the<lb/> of dictates of religion and humanity.<lb/></p>
            <p>The second bearing the name of Obadiah&#44;<lb/> we meet in the days of Jehoshaphat&#44; the<lb/> righteous Jew who ruled over the kingdom<lb/> of Judah.  In Chronicles iz chapter<lb/> seventeenth&#44; it is recorded taht the good<lb/> king sovereign&#44; bent upon awakening again a senti&#45;<lb/>ment of devotion to the national belief&#44; brought<lb/> close to himself a number of faithful subjects.<lb/>  He supplied them with a written copy of the<lb/> five holy books&#44; and bade them travel through<lb/> the country to teach the whole people the ordi&#45;<lb/>nances of Horeb the Pentateuch.  Among those subjects an Oba&#45;<lb/>&#45;diah ranked high&#44; and he&#44; together with his<lb/> associates&#44; carried out the royal injunc&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion with fidelity.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>The third known by the same appellation&#44;<lb/> was a Levite&#44; whom the pious Josiah&#44; King<lb/> of Judah&#44; appointed to officiate as a<lb/> chorister among others of his tribe&#45;&#45;the tribe<lb/> which alone was entitled to sing and make instrumental<lb/> music resound within the courts of the Temple.  But<lb/> none of those three just mentioned&#44; appears to<lb/> have been d endowed with the gift of prophecy.<lb/>  The Haftorah of this Sabbath&#44; has special re&#45;<lb/>ference to the inspiration vouchsafed to Oba&#45;<lb/>&#45;diah&#44; for&#44; it opens with the words &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;The vision of Obadiah.&#34;  It may now fittingly<lb/> be asked&#58; do we possess any reliable information<lb/> touching that personage&#63;  Well&#58; from the<lb/> Talmudical treatise of Sanhedrin&#44; we might infer<lb/> that he was identical with Obadiah of the<lb/> days of Ahab.  I notice moreover that a<lb/> certain Ephraim&#44; a scholar of Rabbi Meir&#44; tries<lb/> to give us&#44; in the name of his teacher&#44; some intimation<lb/> regarding the birth place and nationality of the author of our<lb/> Haftorah.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>But in reality what the Talmud tells<lb/> us is a mere surmise&#44; entirely too vague.<lb/>  Neither the subject treated&#44; nor the stage of Jewish<lb/> history supports that surmise conjecture.  The select&#45;<lb/>&#45;ion of the chapter which we have read&#44; to cor&#45;<lb/>&#45;respond&#44; in a measure&#44; with the contents of the<lb/> Parashah is acceptable&#44; for because Esau spoken of<lb/> there&#44; was the founder of the Edomite or Idu&#45;<lb/>&#45;mean people&#44; reproached with deserved severity<lb/> in our Haftorah.  On one point my<lb/> mind wavers respecting as to the topic under discussion.<lb/>  It is whether Obadaiah could not be credited with<lb/> having left us more than a single chapter.<lb/>  I do not entertain any suspicion about the ho&#45;<lb/>&#45;nesty of the redactors or compilers of the Hebrew<lb/> Scriptures.  I firmly believe that they would<lb/> neither add to nor diminish from what they<lb/> actually found.  But we positively know<lb/> that not a few of the writings of our scribes and<lb/> <sic>and</sic> seers are now &#91;&#63;&#93; missing.  Thus&#44; the chronicles<lb/> of events which transpired in the two divided king&#45;<lb/>&#45;doms&#44; and which are often alluded to in our Bible&#44; exist no more.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>The prophecies of Jehu son of Hanani&#44; a<lb/> contemporary of Jehoshaphat&#44; we do not pos&#45;<lb/>sess.  The Midrash of Iddo failed to<lb/> reach posterity.  So likewise the instructions<lb/> of Shemujah&#44; of Adhijah the Shilomite&#44; of<lb/> Nathan and of others in various ages of our<lb/> annals&#44; are sought after for in vain.  Conse&#45;<lb/>&#45;quently&#44; the supposition that Obadiah may<lb/> originally have contained more than one chapter&#44;<lb/> should not be considered a sheer invention the offspring of the imagination.<lb/>  But let that be as it may&#44; we will&#44; at all events&#44;<lb/> devote a thought to the subject dwelt upon in<lb/> our Haftorah.  The burden of complaint<lb/> by the writer&#44; is the cruelty which the descendants<lb/> of Esau practiced towards the progeny of Jacob.<lb/>  The cup of national sorrow seemed to have over&#45; run<lb/>flowed over&#44; when Nebuchadnezzar transported the remain&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing tribes of Judah and Benjamin to Babylon.<lb/>  We have several psalms testifying to that fact.<lb/>  While it is very venturesome to decide which of those<lb/> stirring outpourings issued at that period&#44; we can scarcely<lb/> doubt that the 102nd&#44; the 137th and possibly the 126th&#44; had their<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>origin&#44; when nationality and country were brought<lb/> to the verge of ruin by the our banishment into Chaldea.<lb/>  The author of our Haftorah&#44; must have lived<lb/> at that time.  I hear in his words&#44; the sound<lb/> the sound of a righteous indignation&#44; because of<lb/> inhumanity.  The people of Edom&#44; forgetful<lb/> of the ties of relationship&#59; oblivious of the cir&#45;<lb/>&#45;cumstance that Moses had ordered not to wage war<lb/> against Edom&#59; forgetful of the sought availed itself of every oc&#45;<lb/>&#45;casion to vex and distress our people.  Obadiah&#44;<lb/> who probably saw that the same potent army which<lb/> humbled Judah&#44; lowered down beyond recovery &#91;&#63;&#93; sought with similar blows the pride<lb/> of Edom&#44; points out the cause of that Divine punish&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment.  Edom felt secure in the rocky mountains<lb/> of its dwelling place.  Who would will attempt to cast<lb/> me down from here&#63; triumphantly exclaimed&#44; the boast&#45;<lb/>&#45;ful descendant of Esau &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;If<lb/> thou couldst fly aloft&#44; like an eagle&#44; or make<lb/> thy home in the starry sky&#44; the hand of the heavenly<lb/> avenger of wrong&#44; would drag thee down&#44;&#34; cries the prophet Obadiah.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>We learn from him that Edom had rejoiced&#44; when the<lb/> inimical sword decimated the progeny of Jacob&#59;<lb/> that Edom helped strangers to cut into pieces the<lb/> the fugitives who looked for safety&#44; beyond the borders<lb/> of unhappy Judea&#59; that Edom had linked in<lb/> ambush to seize them and with brutal pleasure<lb/> should hand them over to the foe.  But<lb/> Nebuchadnezzar whom Edom aided in the hope of<lb/> escaping our fate&#44; or of being given the ownership<lb/> of Jerusalem and of our depopulated country&#44;<lb/> turned the unsparing weapon also against the<lb/> children of Esau.  Obadiah&#44; raised above<lb/> his surroundings by the vision vouchsafed to him&#44;<lb/> predicts the restoration of our exiles and the final<lb/> overthrow of Edom.  Soaring high on the wings<lb/> of prophecy&#44; he may also have seen the conquest of the<lb/> Idumeans by John Hyreanns of the Asmonean race.<lb/>  That Obadiah must have lived at the stage of history<lb/> when the destruction of the first Temple occurred&#44; I argue<lb/> from the circumstances that Jeremiah in the book of<lb/> lamentations&#44; speaks in bitter irony of Edom&#39;s<lb/> inhumanity &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>&#34;Rejoice &#38; be glad thou daughter of Edom&#44; who<lb/> dwellest in the land of &#91;&#63;&#93;.  To thee also<lb/> the intoxicating cup will be reached&#44; drunk<lb/> and denuded thou shall thou remain.&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>Had I the time&#44; and my hearers the patience&#44; I<lb/> would set forth the opinion of some of our accredited<lb/> commentators&#44; who believe that in the sentence pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;ceding the closing of our Haftorah&#44; events that hap<lb/>&#45;pened in later ages to Jews of France and Spain are<lb/> foretold.  To be brief&#44; this day&#44; I may reserve to say another occasion<lb/> my views upon that subject.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
