<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF9_12</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff9_12_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff9_12_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff9_12_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff9_12_2v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 1 sheet<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For a funeral<lb/></p>
            <p>&#34;From a man&#39;s funeral&#44; one may judge of his merits&#44;&#34; that is&#44; of the high stand<lb/>&#45;ing which the departed had enjoyed occupied in society and<lb/> which entitles him to a reward hereafter.<lb/>  This maxim of the Rabbis&#44; which may have had<lb/> a right application in ancient days&#44; cannot be<lb/> declared entirely correct in modern times.  It is<lb/> not true&#44; at all events&#44; as far as it concerns our&#45;<lb/>&#45;selves&#44; the Hebrews of America.  Our people once<lb/> so guileless so unsophisticated in their habits practices&#44; so plain and unosten&#45;<lb/>&#45;tatious in their habits have learnt to ire with each of their in the art of varnishing their sentiments<lb/> disguising their feelings weaknesses.  Even at a funerals which<lb/> ought to be the simplest and most expressive of<lb/> Jewish rites&#45;&#45;they display what is supposed to be<lb/> tokens of respect to the dead&#44; but which in reality<lb/> means serves only to ratify the vanity of the living.  The<lb/> spontaneously flowing tears&#44; and the sincere lament honest just tribute<lb/> of the speaker&#44; have made room for floral offerings&#44;<lb/> silver mountings&#44; studied elegies&#44; and the rounds and marching around<lb/> circuits and bows of of associations and orders.  It has become with their badges The Rabbis would find it difficult<lb/> to distinguish the virtuous from the vicious&#44; the con&#45;<lb/>sistently religious from the impious by the outward demonstrations<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>at the obsequies.  according to the sentence of the unsophisticated<lb/> Rabbis But though it is so among us in most too many instances&#44;<lb/> on the present melancholy occasions&#44; the signs of<lb/> grief shown represent reveal in reality what is truth the sentiments felt in<lb/> the deep recesses of the heart.  It is Now a community<lb/> conscious aware of a loss almost irreparable that sorrows laments<lb/> over the death of Dr Phillip De Young.  Very<lb/> much larger than the number of sincere mourners<lb/> gathered round the coffin&#44; is that of men&#44; women<lb/> and children who mentally accompany<lb/> this Israelite to his grave final home with a blessing.<lb/>  For notwithstanding feelings&#44; which I may call<lb/> constitutional&#44; despite a new observance of precepts<lb/> partly caused by training and vocation&#44; my<lb/> brother in faith possessed rare excellencies which<lb/> have deservedly endeared him to the people among<lb/> whom he was born&#44; and ot the inhabitants of<lb/> Philadelphia of every denomination.  How my greatly will the<lb/> poor will miss their medical adviser&#44; who<lb/> was withal their personal&#44; ever sympathising and helping<lb/> friend.  The eccentric manners of the physician<lb/> will be forgotten&#44; when the familiar voice of<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>the good man in the hovel of distress and<lb/> anguish&#44; soothing calming the agitated mind and relieving the<lb/> quivering body will linger in the memory of this generation.<lb/>  I speak of the services which Dr De Young rendered<lb/> the community in the merciful and disinterested<lb/> exercise of his profession&#44; because my own calling<lb/> has enabled me to witness and appreciate his actions<lb/> I speak of his sterling worth as a benefactor to<lb/> suffering humanity because I believe I stand un&#45;<lb/>&#45;contradicted in what I have learnt from personal<lb/> experience&#44; and from the testimony of individuals<lb/> belonging to all classes of society.  But I<lb/> cannot so speak as knowingly of the services also dwell with a full knowledge of the subject on the benefits<lb/> which the rendered lamented Israelite bestowed upon his immediate family.<lb/>  Though it has been my painful duty to bury his<lb/> father and his sisters&#44; to officiate and offer prayers at the loss demise of his wife&#44;<lb/> of and his children&#44; and sisters&#44; I never enjoyed that<lb/> degree of intimacy qualifying me to say that<lb/> he was in his intimate domestic circle what he proved<lb/> himself in a wider sphere.  You his surviving sons can<lb/> tell what your father parent was in his own home&#44;<lb/> and towards his own offspring.  If it is<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>a fact&#44; as reported&#44; that the tender&#45;hearted and<lb/> most considerate physician to the needy&#44; was<lb/> likewise indulgent and devotedly attached to<lb/> his children&#44; you ought to evidence it in your<lb/> conduct&#44; not by mere sighs and tears which poignant<lb/> sorrow may drown while at the trying hour&#44; when the body so active is about<lb/> to be laid in the silent grave&#44; but by reverencing the memory<lb/> of your benefactor&#44; with deeds of charity truthfulness and good&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness.  Each of you pursuing a career of honor&#44;<lb/> that may <sic>yeild</sic> an honest livelihood&#44; will honor hallow<lb/> the memory of the departed and show forth his excellencies by copying the<lb/> principles of broad humanity which guided his steps.  It will be a<lb/> consolation to the immortal spirit of my friend deceased coreligionist to feel that the<lb/> good name he has left&#44; was perpetuated by his dear<lb/> ones&#44; through a life of industry usefulness&#44; free from<lb/> weakness and foibles foibles to which he at times yeilded succumbed&#44; and rich in social and<lb/> domestic virtues which he abundantly possessed.  Thou O forgiving God&#44; who<lb/> hast called to the bar of Thy justice Phillip De Young<lb/> at this solemn season of the Jewish year&#44; forgive wipe away his<lb/> sins&#44; and let his excellencies high merits win for him his soul joys unalloyed<lb/> and everlasting.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
