<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF9_12</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1891-04" source="" attested="yes">April 1891</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_12_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_12_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_12_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_12_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_12_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_12_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_12_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_12_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_12_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_12_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_12_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_12_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. Fifth St.<lb/></p>
            <p>Philadelphia&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>157<lb/></p>
            
            <p>April 91<lb/></p>
            <p>Judaism stands on the defensive<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Last Sabbath we read an additional portion from the<lb/> Pentateuch&#44; indicative of the approaching Hebrew<lb/> month&#44; on the fifteenth of which Israelites celebrate<lb/> the Passover.  That historic holiday&#44; occurred last<lb/> year almost three weeks sooner than the forthcoming<lb/> one&#59; that is&#44; on the fifth of April.  For&#44; I scarcely need<lb/> say that it can happen as early as the 26<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of March&#44;<lb/> although not later than the 24th of April.<lb/>  But as generally Passover and Easter come together&#44;<lb/> or very close to each other&#44;&#45;&#45;for the latter was origin&#45;<lb/>&#45;ally intended to copy figuratively symbolically reproduce the former&#44; substituting church sym&#45; sym<lb/> &#45;bols bols for the <sic>synagogual</sic> rites and rules of the Synagogue. practices&#45;&#45;I have<lb/> taken occasion&#44; perhaps more than once&#44; to contrast the<lb/> two festivals.  I remember distinctly&#44; at all events&#44;<lb/> that a year ago on the first day of Pesach&#44; I sub&#45;<lb/>&#45;mitted to my hearers the thoughts which the Matzah&#45;&#45;or un&#45;<lb/>&#45;leavened bread&#45;&#45;inspires&#44; and those which the<lb/> belief in a man&#45;god&#39;s resurrection awakens.  I<lb/> did not mean by the words I spoke uttered to offer my Christian neighbor an<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>offence affront&#44; for the religion which we profess teaches<lb/> toleration.  Our patriarchs reckoned gentiles among<lb/> their allies&#59; Aner&#44; Eshcol &#38; Mamre were the confederates of Abram &#91;Hebrew&#93; our prophets declared even our national<lb/> enemies the objects of God&#39;s care hence entitled to our personal consideration&#44; &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Assyria is the work of my hands&#34;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; while some of our renowned Rabbis asso&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciated with heathen Sages&#44; Trained in such schools&#44;<lb/> I have learned to respect my fellow man of every<lb/> creed&#44; so long as he does not make his own religious<lb/> notions publicly aggressive.  Still&#44; some who<lb/> heard me speak&#44; objected to my discourse.  They<lb/> considered deemed it inadvisable to exhibit to view the<lb/> mystic dogmas confessed by a majority&#44; in order<lb/> to bring out in bold relief the reasonable doctrines<lb/> of the minority.  But with due deference to<lb/> the objectors&#44; I hold that I did not overstep<lb/> the bounds of propriety&#44; for it is usual to hear<lb/> 2at this season with1 ministers in the Church to invite<lb/> Jews to seek salvation by forsaking the ancient faith.<lb/>  Why should I not then&#44; in honor and defense of<lb/> my religion&#44; show that &#91;Hebrew&#93;.<lb/>  &#34;Israel is saved by the Eternal Lord with an everlasting<lb/> salvation&#34;&#63;  Why should I refrain from giving my brethren<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>the scriptural assurance that &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;The Lord is our Judge&#44; the Lord is our lawgiver&#44; the Lord<lb/> is our King&#44; that He will save us&#34;&#63;  Now&#44; to prove<lb/> that I am not drawing on the imagination&#44; when<lb/> attributing to Christian preachers an offensively <sic>proselytising</sic><lb/> spirit&#44; I will tell how this very week I casually<lb/> met a coreligionist&#44; who is ordinarily brought in<lb/> contact with church goers.  He stated that on the<lb/> Friday preceding Easter&#44; one of his acquaintances related<lb/> that upon the same day prayers had been offered for the benighted Jews&#44; that they might see the light of the<lb/> gospel.  It is not&#44; as some allege&#44; only men<lb/> bound within a narrow compass of knowledge<lb/> that indulge in such cant&#44; but persons distinguish&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed for their vast learning will urge us to exchange<lb/> Judaism for Christianity.  No less a scholar<lb/> than the late Franz Delitzsch&#44; familiar with the<lb/> whole range of our Hebrew literature&#44; was caught by death<lb/> when almost in the act of finishing an essay&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>which tried to explain the motives&#44; that ought to<lb/> induce Jews to accept the doctrine of the messiah&#45;<lb/>&#45;ship of the man of Nazareth.  I do not<lb/> for a moment doubt the sincerity of the author&#44; and<lb/> I must award to him the merit of moderation<lb/> in his efforts.  I am even grateful to the German<lb/> savant&#44; for having exposed the falsities of the man<lb/> Rohling&#44; a hater of our race&#44; who dared assert that<lb/> according to Talmudical or Kabbalistical teachings&#44;<lb/> Christian blood must be mixed in the dough of<lb/> the Passover bread.  Nevertheless&#44; the dogma<lb/> of a predestined mediator between man and his<lb/> Maker as the sole means of forgiveness&#44; is the idea running<lb/> through some of the multifarious Delitzsch&#39;s&#43; writings of Delitzsch the <sic>Leipzick</sic> professor.  All in this<lb/> country may not have read the works of that erudite<lb/> scholar&#44; but many must have listened to a high prelate<lb/> of the Presbyterian church&#44; whose recent demise<lb/> called forth wide spread regrets.  For great was<lb/> his reputation for varied learning&#44; and as head of the<lb/> University of New York&#44; as President and very<lb/> active member of the Society for the prevention of<lb/> crime&#44; as Pastor of a large and influential congregation<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>and as an author&#44; Dr Howard Crosby&#39;s opinions<lb/> carried a heavy an immense weight.  Evidently&#44; however&#44; they<lb/> lacked broadness in one respect.  For the reverend preacher made<lb/> himself conspicuous shortly before his demise decease by<lb/> defending an apostate form our religion&#44; whose obtru&#45;<lb/>&#45;siveness became obnoxious to our people.  The re&#45;<lb/>&#45;creant found in Dr. Crosby a strong advocate&#44; not&#45;<lb/>&#45;withstanding most damaging charges&#44; simply because<lb/> the unscrupulous renegade has hired himself to the<lb/> service of the church.  The trade which he still plies<lb/> is to lure the unwary into the abandonment<lb/> of the ancestral belief.  Consistent in his con&#45;<lb/>&#45;victions&#44; that the Jew is beyond the pale of sal&#45;<lb/>&#45;vation&#44; the learned Presbyterian minister would<lb/> encourage proselytism and annually preach dwell on the necessity of our conversion&#45;&#45;I mean<lb/> <sic>pervesion</sic>&#45;&#45;in order that we may be delivered from<lb/> perdition.  But why do I have reference<lb/> to the minister of a denomination&#44; whose articles<lb/> of faith have remained unchanged&#63;  He held firm<lb/> to the idea that a denial of the atoning power of<lb/> the one whom the Romans executed at at Calvary&#44; is like<lb/> cutting off from the soul every hope of immortality.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>The surprise is that the exponent of another deno&#45;<lb/>mination&#44; which prides itself on its enlarged liberalism&#44;<lb/> intimated on Easter Sunday nearly the identical<lb/> idea.  The venerable nonagenarian clergyman of the first<lb/> Unitarian church in Philadelphia&#44; set forth the<lb/> theory of a that an actual bodily reappearance on earth of the crucified one&#44; to Nazarene hap&#45;<lb/>&#45;pened&#44; as a proof that faith can conquer physical death.  The sym&#45;<lb/>&#45;bolic cross&#44; the music&#44; the oratory formed a trinity&#44; ill&#45;<lb/>according with the Unity&#44; on which the sect which that<lb/> Dr Furness represents&#44; is credited to have its founda&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion stone.  A feature which I noticed with pain<lb/> is that a Philadelphia synagogue&#44; employs the<lb/> same singers and songstresses who figured prominently<lb/> at the Easter ceremonies services in that church.  Thus are<lb/> our religious opponents given just cause to charge us with<lb/> hollow professions&#59; as postponing principles to outward<lb/> appearances&#44; the integrity of the a Jewish worship<lb/> to expediency.  Well&#58; that compromise also doubtless enters<lb/> into the plan now boldly advocated by radicalism.<lb/>  For in a late Sunday lecture its champion in our<lb/> city&#44; advised the amalgamation of Judaism<lb/> with Christianity.  The former must cast off<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>whatever savors of Orientalism&#44; namely&#44; as I inter&#45;<lb/>&#45;pret it&#44; break down every vestige of the bridge con&#45;<lb/>&#45;necting the past with the present&#44; and the latter<lb/> must make a public denial disavowal of the divinity of<lb/> the Galilean Jew.  What species of religion such an im&#45;<lb/>&#45;possible fusion will create&#44; I am at a loss to im&#45;<lb/>&#45;agine&#44; unless it be a step in advance to the<lb/> Ethical culture non descript which&#44; I am assured&#44; is now moving<lb/> slowly backward in search of some outward aids for<lb/> its support.  No&#58; abstractions cannot guide the<lb/> bulk of mankind.  We must per force employ ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;ternal forms to recall the inner requisites of the spirit&#44;<lb/> and those forms are the wisest which retain a people<lb/> within the line of morality&#44; without sacrificing the<lb/> demands claims of reason.  How the ceremonies of the<lb/> Hebrew church have answered that purpose&#44; let<lb/> the approaching Passover so enlivening in its surroundings&#44; fastening domestic ties&#44;<lb/> tell.  The day on which its abolition&#44; together<lb/> with all that has come down from the East&#44; will<lb/> be abrogated&#44; we shall retrograde in the path of practical goodness.  We may set up on a lofty pedestal<lb/> Philosophy as a deity&#44; but it will be a deity incapable of holding<lb/> humanity at large in integrity&#44; incapable to save.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Not by destroying&#44; but by purifying cleansing our rites and<lb/> usages&#44; we shall verify the words of the archpro&#45;<lb/>&#45;phet of the East &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;All the people of the earth shall<lb/> see that the name of the Lord is resting upon thee&#44; and<lb/> they shall do thee reverence.&#34;  I admit with<lb/> Maimonides that Christianity is a wide step forward<lb/> towards the reception of the Unity&#44; when compared with<lb/> the gross polytheism of polished Greek and all&#45;con&#45;<lb/>&#45;quering Rome.  Yet&#44; what strides it must take&#44; in<lb/> order to reach the pure knowledge of God&#39;s absolute<lb/> Oneness.  For very slow it is from the to acceptation of our<lb/> daily declaration of faith &#91;Hebrew&#93; and which the unknown author of the<lb/> hymn where with which the Sephardic ritual closes its Sabbath<lb/> service so expresses &#34;Sole God&#44; unequal and beyond compare&#44; without<lb/> division or associate&#34;.  The hand that shapes human events&#44;<lb/> will guide lead intelligent creatures to unroll the volume on which<lb/> to inscribe their names to the Eternal Lord.  So have they predicted whose vision was uncircumscribed.  As to ourselves&#44; O disciples of Moses&#44; it It is by<lb/> holding fast to our creed&#44; by defending it&#44; by showing its<lb/> saving powers through active virtues&#44; that we may hope<lb/> for to promote the final suppression of all species of idolatry&#44; and for<lb/> the sanctification of the One incorporeal&#44; all creating and all&#45;<lb/>loving God.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
