<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF8_6</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1888-01" source="" attested="yes">1888</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_6_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_6_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_6_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_6_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_6_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_6_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_6_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_6_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_6_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_6_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_6_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_6_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>On the Sabbath &#38; on the Seminary &#47;88<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  As&#44; very probably&#44; with the advan&#45;<lb/>&#45;cing of the summer&#44; season&#44; I shall suspend<lb/> sermons&#44; simply addressing lads when they become<lb/> Bar Mitzvah&#44; and generally confining my services to the<lb/> recital of the accepted ritual&#44; I will not close my<lb/> English discoursing English preaching in English for the season&#44; without referring again to a<lb/> subject which has been uppermost in my mind&#44;<lb/> during the past six months.  It is<lb/> lamentably true that the Sabbath has lost the sweet<lb/> fragrance which it formerly imparted to our homes.<lb/>  I recognize the tyranny of circumstances&#44; which<lb/> pitilessly delivers it to general desecration&#44; and<lb/> I cannot think of that and not feel a sense<lb/> of personal grief and self abasement&#44; conjointly with added to<lb/> communal shame.  But the idea of legalizing<lb/> the profanation of the day&#44; and investing with<lb/> its God&#45;given sanctity that which represents a belief&#44;<lb/> subversive of Monotheism&#44; is a cause of terror to<lb/> my heart.  Are we not all alive to the<lb/> fact that a custom&#44; having once struck deep root&#44;<lb/> will supplant each a clearly defined law&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>No one who reflects will need illustrations to<lb/> be shown how actions which&#44; at one stage of his<lb/> life&#44; he would have considered incompatible with<lb/> the ordinances of Holy Writ&#44; were made permissible<lb/> to his mind in his ordinary ways only through the force of a prevalent<lb/> custom.  Suppose now that for ten<lb/> consecutive years Sunday services remain the set&#45;<lb/>&#45;tled usage among American Israelites&#44; depend upon<lb/> it&#44; our children will have grown&#44; through a long<lb/> habit&#44; to look on consider regard the first day of the week as having<lb/> set aside the holiness of the seventh&#44; just as other te&#45;<lb/>&#45;nets&#44; emanating from a Biblical source&#44; were were overridden from being al&#45;<lb/>&#45;lowed to go into <sic>desuatude</sic>.  The consequence<lb/> is very clear to my understanding.  I look on the obser&#45;<lb/>&#45;vance of Sunday&#44; by a special worship&#44; as the<lb/> closest approximation to trinitarianism&#45;&#45;what ever may<lb/> be said to the contrary&#45;&#45;for pure Unitarians are an<lb/> insignificant minority in Christendom&#44; and that<lb/> rapprochement will bring in its train mixed services&#44;<lb/> the downfall of the synagogue&#59; mixed marriages&#44;<lb/> the death blow knell of Mosaism.  Let those who are<lb/> prepared for such an issue&#44; advocate the novel abominable scheme.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>But I hear many say&#58; &#34;This man prophesies<lb/> to us only evil.  He ought to know that a remn&#45; residue<lb/> &#45;ant of the faithful will always be found&#44; for we have<lb/> a Divine promise&#44; declaring our eternity as a distinct<lb/> people on earth&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93; Yes&#59; but if our ancestors had<lb/> folded their arms and adopted a &#34;go as you please&#34;<lb/> policy&#45;&#45;excuse the vulgar phrase&#45;&#45;the heavenly assur&#45;<lb/>&#45;ance would have gone remained unfulfilled.  History testifies<lb/> to the truth&#44; that by the spirit which is the almighty &#91;&#63;&#93; into<lb/> man&#44; and which stirred up heroes in the defense<lb/> of our belief&#44; Judaism was saved.  Imagine&#44; for<lb/> example&#44; that a Johanan Ben Zaccha&#239; had not arisen<lb/> to breast the swelling tide which threatened to<lb/> carry before it all our sacred learning&#44; would not<lb/> the Torah have perished&#63;  Or&#44; to cite an instance of<lb/> later times&#58; imagine that Isaac Abarbanel had<lb/> been unwilling to sacrifice wealth&#44; &#38; civic and politi&#45;<lb/>&#45;cal honors&#44; and talk up the pilgrim&#39;s staff and<lb/> roam abroad in search of a land home of refuge and share<lb/> suffering with hundreds of thousand of his brother exiles&#59;<lb/> imagine&#44; I say&#44; that he had urged by his own example submissiveness<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>a voluntary yeilding to the demands of the inqui&#45;<lb/>&#45;sition&#44; the accepting of trinitarianism&#44; would not<lb/> the sephardic branch of our race have become largely in a great measure<lb/> lost&#33;  Folly it is to hold that without our<lb/> personal efforts&#44; Judaism will have permanence<lb/> among American Israelites&#44; in the face of a widespread<lb/> defection&#44; and the combined forces of the would be li&#45;<lb/>&#45;beral aiming at its overthrow.  If we are<lb/> in earnest&#44; we must work for its preservation.<lb/></p>
            <p>Pardon a sentiment which may savor of selfishness&#44;<lb/> but I am impelled by circumstances to give it ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;pression.  In order to counteract the effects of teachings<lb/> that have produced destroyers&#45;&#45;men whose object<lb/> clearly is to modernize our ancient code by having<lb/> it tucked on the skirts of genitlism&#45;&#45;I threw<lb/> myself with all the ardor of my soul into the<lb/> project of establishing a Rabbinical School<lb/> in New York.  Its founders accepted the pe&#45;<lb/>&#45;cuniary assistance of all Hebrews&#44; who&#44; knowing the ten&#45;<lb/>&#45;dency of the Jewish Theological Seminary&#44; gave<lb/> it support&#44; notwithstanding their individual or congre&#45;<lb/>&#45;gational departure from strict conservatism.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>I never promised a sure realization of<lb/> all my aspirations.  The future is open only to<lb/> God&#44; but as far as it lies in my power&#44; I have<lb/> provided for the raising of disciples sworn to keep<lb/> holy what Moses and the prophets called holy&#44;<lb/> by the choice of confessedly reliable instructors&#44; acting under<lb/> my supervision.  The pulpits which those disci&#45;<lb/>&#45;ples shall ascend&#44; the desks from which they<lb/> will read the Law&#44; or at which they shall sit<lb/> to communicate religious knowledge&#44; will not be polluted<lb/> by new fangled doctrines concocted to convict the<lb/> Sabbath of bastardy.  They will be able to con&#45;<lb/>&#45;trovert the absurd theory of that a moon worship having<lb/> given birth to our Sabbath&#45;&#45;which is in itself a theory based on an<lb/> astronomical miscalculation&#44; for the changes in the lunar phases do<lb/> not occur each seventh day&#44; since the moon returns every performs its revolution round the earth in<lb/> twenty nine days and a half and about forty five<lb/> minutes and not in twenty eight days.  The disciples of the Jewish Theological<lb/> Seminary will show prove the fallacy of arguments by<lb/> which our Sabbath is fathered now on the Acadians&#44;<lb/> anon on the Egyptians&#44; again on the Assyrians<lb/> or the Chaldeans&#44; nations whose documents&#44; if found any of an &#91;&#63;&#93; date when found may show a division of weeks&#44; but not the celebration of a Sabbath.  In a word&#44; our disciples&#44; will&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>I fervently hope&#44; redeem the name of the glorious immortal son<lb/> of Amram from the aspersions foul accusation of deception cast upon it him by<lb/> faithless preachers.  Yet&#44; who would credit<lb/> it&#63;  On the plea that persons with whom I take<lb/> counsel&#44; regarding the scholastic government arrangement of the<lb/> Seminary&#44; are not precisely of my religious mode<lb/> of thinking&#44; a <sic>wofully</sic> mistaken orthodoxy&#44; wages<lb/> war against me.  It strives to wound cut me to<lb/> the quick&#44; by drawing away from me all turning into foes Israelites that lent me help.<lb/>  It seeks to root out my good planting&#44; regardless<lb/> of the ruin that must follow&#44; in poisonous seed that will be imbedded there&#44; by leaving the<lb/> whole field&#44; clear of opposition&#44; to unscrupulous &#34;reform.&#34;<lb/>  It must certainly see how the strength of the faith is wa&#45;<lb/>&#45;ning away&#59; how mangled are her limbs&#44; how implo&#45;<lb/>&#45;ringly she asks of those who love her to hasten to the<lb/> deliverance&#59; but no&#44; let all go to wreck and ruin rather<lb/> than favor what is not ruled over governed absolutely by men of the most rigorous orthodoxy.  does<lb/> not rule over absolutely  But the institution<lb/> to which I have given existence will live&#44; despite<lb/> wicked hostility on one side&#44; and a senseless&#44;<lb/> and not less sinful antagonism&#44; on the other.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Nothing can cause its death&#44; except the<lb/> withdrawing of the sustenance afforded to it by my brethren<lb/> brothers and sisters who have responded to my appeals.<lb/>  They inspirited me with their encouragement&#44; because they<lb/> felt convinced of my eagerness to prop what is<lb/> declining.  to lend They trusted me&#44; when I said that to impart fresh vigor to the seminary&#44; to enlarge<lb/> its scope sphere&#44; is&#44; under God&#44; to supply Judaism in Ameri&#45;<lb/>&#45;ca with Readers2&#44; and Teachers3 and Preachers1 kindled with<lb/> zeal for the Torah&#44; and endowed with the capacity<lb/> to uplift it to glory.  And that alone is is my aim and scope&#59; my sole am&#45;<lb/>&#45;btion.  What other object can I have in view at<lb/> my age&#44; with little simple habits that have grown on me as<lb/> a second nature&#44; and with a decided preference for Phila&#45;<lb/>&#45;delphia&#44; and her people than to devote my remaining ener&#45;<lb/>&#45;gies&#44;&#45;&#45;as far as I can by a frequent inspection&#45;&#45;to the development of an organization in the ser&#45;<lb/>&#45;vice of the written and oral Law&#63;  I felt happy<lb/> therefore in obtaining a gift for the promotion furtherance of my<lb/> object from at the hands of a pious coreligionist congregant of mine&#59; a bequest from another&#44;<lb/> who has departed me&#44; and glad I am to have succeeded in<lb/> founding a branch of the association in our city.<lb/>  The number of its members is yet small&#44; but I<lb/> look forward to the circulation of a forthcoming<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>report of our two years&#39; working in New York&#44;<lb/> for its increase.  That document may recall the Semi&#45;<lb/>&#45;nary and its needs to the memory of my fellow<lb/> believers&#44; better than my speech to day could do have done <sic>have</sic> recalled.  For<lb/> we all stand in want of tangible objects as reminders of the performance<lb/> of duty.  so we are forcibly told in the concluding<lb/> sentences of our section from the Pentateuch.  It is note&#45;<lb/>&#45;worthy that in bidding us to wear Hebrew men to array themselves with in a four&#45;fringed gar&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment&#44; the Divine legislator says&#58; &#34;You will look upon it<lb/> and remember all the commandments of the Lord.&#34;  and again&#58;<lb/> &#34;In order that you may remember and do all my<lb/> commandments and be holy to your God.&#34;  That is<lb/> the secret of the Eternal aids of are then essential to religion.  They must Whatever be their<lb/> character&#44; so long as they keep alive the memorial of the mission entrusted to us<lb/> from on high they are sacred&#59; They indeed and those Israelites appreciate it welld that mission best&#44; who&#44;<lb/> in accordance with their means&#44; promote undertakings<lb/> that tend to eternize Judaism and glorify the<lb/> God of Sinai.  May I always count among<lb/> such all my congregants brothers &#38; sisters in faith to whom I have ministered and point to them<lb/> with the satisfaction of having labored in their midst among them to a holy<lb/> purpose.  So may it be.  May the Lord grant it.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
