<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF21_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet></placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1891" source="" attested="yes">1891</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff21_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff21_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff21_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff21_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff21_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff21_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff21_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff21_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff21_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff21_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff21_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff21_2_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>37</p>
            
            <p>The virtues of modesty &#38; moderation<lb/>
                predicated in the death of Nodab &#38; Abihoo<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#91;inserted by author&#58; <lb/>&#93;91<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Modesty and moderation are virtues that become<lb/> us human beings well&#44; in our every stage or condition of life.  Their<lb/> possession lends the aged a more venerable appearance.<lb/>  By the exercise of those virtues the learned gain in influence.<lb/>  Modesty and moderation add dignity to the judge<lb/> upon the bench.  Better than war trophies&#44; they<lb/> win for a conqueror universal applause.  And<lb/> in the young&#59; how strikingly they set off the<lb/> comeliness of the person&#59; the endowments of the<lb/> mind.  Modesty and moderation&#45;&#45;twin virtues&#45;&#45;<lb/> born of wisdom and humility&#44; watch over<lb/> our physical and moral health&#59; they awe back<lb/> threatening dangers and beckon near abiding<lb/> <sic>tranquillity</sic>.  But when we look for those<lb/> virtues&#44; where are we apt to find them&#63;  In places<lb/> which wealth tread upon with haughty steps&#63;<lb/>  Too often riches beget vainglory and dissipation.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  The man in affluence&#44; say the<lb/> scriptures&#44; boasts of his large means&#44; as of a fortress<lb/> built for his own defence security&#44;and because he cares not<lb/> for public censure&#44; he will defy public opinion and let his appetites go unbridled.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Will those virtues be met with frequency where<lb/> the sceptre bears sway is weilded&#63;  Human frailty&#63;  Nothing<lb/> seems so calculated to engender pride and extrava&#45;<lb/>&#45;gance more than as the exercise of temporal authority.<lb/>  Are we not constantly shown how instances of persons who ought<lb/> to have been models of meekness and sobriety&#44; but who grew<lb/> to be overbearing and intemperate&#44; when clothed even simply &#34;dressed in a<lb/> in small little brief authority&#34;&#63;  With the preacher of old&#44;<lb/> each of us&#44; calling experience as a proof&#44; may exclaim<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; in the hall of justice&#44; injustice<lb/> daringly stands forth.  No&#44; modesty&#44; which is low&#45;<lb/>&#45;liness of mind&#59; moderation&#44; which is a victory over<lb/> self&#45;indulgence&#44; are not the characteristics of opu&#45;<lb/>&#45;lence and power.  The hovel rather than the mansion<lb/> exhibits them.  The man in coarse garments rather<lb/> than he who wears the insignia of high offices.<lb/>  Individuals credited with the possession of knowledge&#44;<lb/> ought always to illustrate exemplify in their conduct those<lb/> essential qualities&#44; for&#44; to learn is to discover our igno&#45;<lb/>&#45;rance&#44; and the necessity of guarding against what&#45;<lb/>ever may injure our intellect and our character.<lb/>  But so much of human knowledge is impractical&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>&#91;&#63;&#93; that not rarely&#44; we will see find mental acquirements<lb/> destitute of social requirements&#44; erudtion stalking<lb/> abroad in company with ostentation.  To youths<lb/> especially will that airy knowledge proves become a<lb/> slippery path&#44; on which they slide down fast<lb/> into shame and misery.  Filled with an over&#45;<lb/>&#45;weening opinion of their capacities&#44; they will<lb/> scorn the idea of holding a subordinate position.<lb/>  They wish to begin their career&#44; where their pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;decessors ended it&#44; forgetting the how very<lb/> slow was their parents&#39; ascent up to the step<lb/> of the ladder which they finally reached.  Modesty&#44;<lb/> which would dictate to the children a similar<lb/> course&#59; moderation&#44; which would afford satisfaction<lb/> with a lowly station&#44; as the sure means to a gradual elevation&#44;<lb/> are cast aside&#44; and contrary evil counsels are listened to with<lb/> complacence.<lb/></p>
            <p>I do not think&#44; that Holy Writ has offered any&#45;<lb/>&#45;where a more forcible exemplification illustration of God&#39;s dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;pleasure with the conduct demeanour of such youths&#44; as in<lb/> a stirring event recorded in this week&#39;s section of<lb/> the Pentateuch.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Nadab and Abl Abihoo&#44; whose fearful doom turned<lb/> a people&#39;s joy into sorrow&#44; may be taken as types<lb/> of a large number&#44; <sic>developping</sic> now into man&#45;<lb/>&#45;hood.  With an average of knowledge&#44; suffi&#45;<lb/>&#45;cient to create ambition&#44; but insufficient to check<lb/> vanity&#44; they hug delusive hopes.  They dream<lb/> of bright success&#44; but keep it at a distance by<lb/> their lack of modesty and moderation.<lb/></p>
            <p>The day had arrived on which the high priest<lb/> was consecrated to the service of the newly erected<lb/> Tabernacle.  Gladness sparkled on every coun&#45;<lb/>&#45;tenance&#44; when Aaron&#44; crowned with the golden<lb/> mitre&#44; accompanied by in unison of sentiments with his prophetic brother&#44; and&#44;<lb/> faced the Congregation of Israel&#44; bestowed upon them pronounced<lb/> &#38; with uplifting his hands pronounced the threefold blessing.  Thril&#45;<lb/>&#45;ling was the shout that rent the sky.  A whole<lb/> nation triumphed in their Lord.  But who are<lb/> they that rush towards the holy of holies&#63;  The<lb/> two elder sons of the installed High priest disdained<lb/> to be mere attendants at the altar&#59; aids to the<lb/> Chief minister.  They must Why not show that they also<lb/> are entitled to a share of public veneration&#59;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>that they also enjoy privileges of a first rate order&#63;<lb/>  Now stirred Goaded on by vanity&#44; &#34;Nadab and Abihoo took<lb/> each his censer&#44; put fire therein&#44; set incense thereon&#44;<lb/> and brought before the Lord a strange fire&#44; which<lb/> He had commanded them not.&#34;  But why what<lb/> does motive had the Bible to in designating the sinners&#44; in the present<lb/> instance&#44; as &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;the sons of Aaron&#34;&#63;  Because&#44;<lb/> intended by nature and religion as assistants to their<lb/> father in his sacerdotal functions&#44; they dared act as<lb/> his coequals.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; write the<lb/> Talmudists.  But another reason have<lb/> the Rabbis alleged for having the guilty men<lb/> being to particularly named.  Because their self&#45;<lb/>sufficiency prevented their consulting the advice<lb/> of their superiors &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  As &#34;sons<lb/> of Aaron&#44;&#34; they should have been guided by pater&#45;<lb/>&#45;nal example.  Their father recognized in Moses<lb/> his spiritual guide&#44; and meekly was he directed<lb/> by the inspired word of the arch prophet.  They&#44;<lb/> on the contrary&#44; considered it useless to ask whe&#45;<lb/>&#45;ther a voluntary oblation at that time and under<lb/> those circumstances would be reckoned an honor to the Lord.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>&#34;Surely there can exist no difference between our<lb/> offering and that which our father presented.<lb/>  We are fully as capable of officiating in the<lb/> Sanctuary.  For&#44; have we not also been clothed<lb/> with distinguishing garments&#63;&#34;  So may those<lb/> arrogant youths &#43; have argued&#44; and so do others<lb/> contend&#44; who look on modesty as a womanish<lb/> virtue.  They cannot see why persons of<lb/> their <sic>calibre</sic> should be subservient and submissive<lb/> to others&#59; why they should acknowledge their superiors&#44;<lb/> when they possess all the qualifications for rising<lb/> and gaining at once the greatest height.  And<lb/> because the world will not give them credit for<lb/> that which they have discovered in their own selves&#44;<lb/> therefore they waste their energies in indolence baseless projects&#44; and<lb/> not infrequently in wanton follies.<lb/></p>
            <p>I am not prepared&#44; to accept altogether the opinion views<lb/> of some of the Talmudists&#44; in connection with the<lb/> event just narrated&#44; and yet it may have some<lb/> foundation in its close proximity to a divine command&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment which follows it immediately.<lb/></p>
            <p>&#43; The word &#34;youths&#44;&#34; is here used only relatively.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Those Sages assert that the sin of Nadab and Abi&#45;<lb/>&#45;hoo was the offspring of intemperance.  &#91;Inserted above&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#93;  The absence<lb/> of modesty in their character made room for insa&#45;<lb/>&#45;tiable ambition&#44; but immoderation led to an act<lb/> of unblushing impiety.  They  The Sages illustrate their views idea<lb/> by a parable.  A king had a servant&#44; on whom he<lb/> relied for the faithful performance of a certain<lb/> work.  But one day the royal master saw him stand<lb/> in a particular locality.  To the general surprise and<lb/> consternation the king had his servant executed.<lb/>  Appointing another in his stead&#44; the monarch cautioned the man<lb/> not to visit the spot which his predecessor frequented.<lb/>  None&#44; none knew in what manner the former officer<lb/> had offended the Ruler.  But when they heard that<lb/> order&#44; they learned the cause of his displeasure.  It is so<lb/> likewise in this case.  As we perceive that after the<lb/> fatal occurrence which caused Aaron the poignant grief of berea&#45;<lb/>&#45;vement&#44; the injunction was given that his surviving sons&#44;<lb/> as himself&#44; must abstain from wine or strong drink<lb/> before entering the sanctuary&#44; lest they die&#44; we may<lb/> infer that the two&#44; suddenly cut off&#44; had been guilty<lb/> of an offence of that nature.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Now&#44; it is optional with one any one to agree or<lb/> disagree with that Rabbinical reasoning&#44; but the<lb/> lesson which our ancient teachers endeavoured to im&#45;<lb/>&#45;part commands itself to our serious consideration.<lb/>  It points out an error which is on the increase&#44; be&#45;<lb/>&#45;cause our children misconstrue the privileges granted<lb/> by this Republic.  As In the same manner as the sons of Aaron regarded<lb/> their father&#39;s superior rank as their own by divine<lb/> right&#44; and were led to sin&#44; so young Americans deem<lb/> their country&#39;s liberty an inherent right&#44; freeing from<lb/> hard toil and humble endeavours exertions.  Is not each of them an<lb/> independent sovereign&#63;  Does it become a king to<lb/> stoop and work under another&#39;s direction&#63;  I need<lb/> not say even to those who boast of being American<lb/> born&#44; what is the issue which idleness allied to vanity<lb/> will bring forth  But as surely as Nadab and Abihoo fell<lb/> while attempting to mount high on their father&#39;s shoul&#45;<lb/>&#45;ders&#44; so will they be dragged down from the lofty<lb/> pedestal&#44; which their overweening brains have raised<lb/> in their conception.  Early&#44; a young&#44; early in life<lb/> choose modesty and moderation as <sic>counsellors</sic>.  They<lb/> are not noisy.  They do not stalk abroad with pomposity.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>They delight in retiredness&#44; but follow their gentle lead&#44; and you<lb/> will avoid many a stumbling block against which<lb/> pretentious youths constantly strike.  Those twin<lb/> virtues will preserve the soundness of your bodies&#59; the<lb/> freshness of your intellects&#59; nay&#44; they will spread<lb/> round your existence a mantle hiding faults&#44; which<lb/> all mortals are liable to commit.  For&#44; whereas vanity<lb/> provokes jealousy and insobriety excites stirs up strife&#44; modesty<lb/> and moderation silence censure and disarm envy.  Hatred<lb/> cannot level its shafts at them&#44; for they seek only peace&#44;<lb/> and walk humbly to secure love.  Understand their<lb/> so sterling worth&#44; O youths&#44; and be never tempted to<lb/> prefer to it the tinsel wherewith bewitching vice is<lb/> presented.  Before God who reckons presumption among<lb/> the seven abominations of His heart&#44; bend to the earth&#59;<lb/> before God who has gifted you with an intelligent soul&#44;<lb/> worship with a mind undimmed by the fumes of<lb/> a brutalizing passion.  Before man&#44; whom you must<lb/> join to promote happiness&#44; before the community of<lb/> your brethren&#44; whom you must benefit by example&#44; be<lb/> distinguished for the possession of the two ennobling<lb/> virtues&#58; modesty and moderation.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
