<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF3_10</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_10_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_10_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_10_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_10_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_10_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_10_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_10_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_10_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_10_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_10_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_10_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_10_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 3 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Sabbath Before Purim<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>B.  The days of youth are a receptacle of for quick<lb/> impressions&#59; no a riper age often removes banishes away what<lb/> the d susceptible mind has hastily accepted.  I<lb/> remember to have read in my school days a Hebrew<lb/> book which prejudiced my mind greatly against the character<lb/> of Mordecai.  The author denies the historic Jew<lb/> of Shushan any quality worthy of the esteem of<lb/> posterity.  In his opinion&#44; a refusal to show<lb/> Haman the same mark of respect&#44; as other court officials<lb/> paid to the favorite minister&#44; proceeded from an ill&#45;founded<lb/> piety&#44; while to insist in refusing obeisance to withholding homage from a<lb/> superior officer&#44; after having discovered the harm which<lb/> such a conduct refusal had occasioned&#44; was an inexcusable wrong.<lb/>  I was somewhat surprised a few years ago on hear&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing a minister from a neighboring city&#44; incidentally<lb/> present&#44; in the course of a well prepared lecture before a<lb/> Philadelphia literary association&#44; similar arguments views.<lb/>  in They were very disparagingent of Mordecai as a Jew and a man.<lb/>  A female member of this congregation rebuked the lec&#45;<lb/>&#45;turer at that time&#44; in a weekly paper&#44; and pleaded on<lb/> behalf of a Biblical character endeared to the house of Israel&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>who for upwards of twenty two centuries have<lb/> celebrated the joyful festivity of Purim.  I cannot<lb/> recall just now the arguments that my sister in faith<lb/> brought forth in <sic>defence</sic> of our illustrious ancestor&#44;<lb/> but to me it seems clear that Mordecai was governed<lb/> by sentiments deserving my of all praise.  I admit<lb/> without any hesitation that no prohibition exists<lb/> in the scriptures against prostrating oneself in de&#45;<lb/>&#45;ference to persons we wish to honor.  I have learned on the contrary that<lb/> some of the worthiest among our people followed that<lb/> eastern custom in their social intercourse&#44; but I must<lb/> be greatly at fault&#44; if Holy Writ contradicts disproves my assert&#45;<lb/>&#45;ion&#44; that to kneel down&#44; except in <sic>worshipping</sic> the Deity&#44;<lb/> was never allowed in Biblical times.  And that<lb/> was precisely&#44; according to the Hebrew wording of the text&#44;<lb/> what Haman demanded of Mordecai &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  He must<lb/> offer to a mortal a sign of adoration due only to Al&#45;<lb/>mighty God.  Had the recipient been an individual<lb/> ever so preeminent in virtue&#44; the act would even then find<lb/> no extenuation&#44; but how much less when proposed evinced<lb/> to an ungodly scion of Amalek the Agagite upstart swelling with ambition&#63;<lb/>  Such hypocrisy was repelling to the nature of a high minded<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Jew.  That his incapacity to cringe and play<lb/> false to religion&#44; should have exposed his people to<lb/> the vindictiveness of a minion in the Persian court&#44;<lb/> Mordecai lamented in sack cloth and ashes&#44; but could<lb/> he&#44; without becoming despicable in his own eyes&#44; have<lb/> fawned and flattered&#44; so that the arch enemy of his<lb/> race might resent&#63;  Never.  Now&#58; on reading<lb/> the legendary tales of the Talmud&#44; upon this incident episode<lb/> in the book of Esther&#44; I realized how true it is<lb/> that history does repeats itself.  There will always<lb/> be in a community&#44; a large number who cannot rise<lb/> to a very high standard.  Good enough men are they when<lb/> the course current of life runs smooth&#44; but if severe drawbacks<lb/> loom up&#59; if a choice is to be made between principles<lb/> and sufferings trials&#44; they will readily sacrifice ideas to enjoy avoid<lb/> ease troubles.  As early as in the days of Moses regrets were<lb/> expressed by certain Hebrews that the endeavour of our inspired<lb/> leader to gain freedom for the slaves&#44; had brought on additional<lb/> sufferings.  They bondmen would have preferred the chains which they<lb/> were used to drag&#44; to the hard struggle necessary to break<lb/> them asunder.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>So likewise in much later times&#44; say the Rabbis&#44; Jews<lb/> remonstrate with Mordecai&#44; because his rigid adherence to<lb/> what he considered right&#44; had intensified the hatred of gentiles<lb/> against the Hebrews.  Better <sic>yeild</sic> to the overbearing than<lb/> be exposed to endure persecution&#59; so thought a vast multitude in Shushan.<lb/>  But I was not prepared to hear a like complaint and a like argu&#45; reasoning<lb/> &#45;ment from certain Hebrews Eurpean brethren of ours&#44; when other brethren<lb/> with the kindest intention sought to benefit.  There fell<lb/> into my hands last week&#44; a copy of a Hebrew periodical pu&#45;<lb/>&#45;blished in Prussia.  In it an article appeared which was headed<lb/> thus &#34;sorrows and lamentations&#34;.  It The paper had been written in Roumania&#44;<lb/> and for obvious reasons no signature had been appended to it&#44;<lb/> but that the gloomy picture was not overdrawn&#44; I can vouch for.<lb/>  I have compared it with an authoritative one&#44; and have seen<lb/> that it is unfortunately too correct.  But is it fair&#44; is it<lb/> sensible to lay the origin of the evil at the door of the<lb/> Isr Universal Israelitish Alliance&#63;  This far&#45;reaching organization had<lb/> its spokesmen at the international Berlin congress in 1878.  Sup&#45;<lb/>&#45;ported by the late Benjamin Disraeli&#44; the Alliance forcibly<lb/> pleased for the recognition of Roumanian Jews as citizens of<lb/> the new Kingdom about to be established.  Prince Charles<lb/> who laid claims to the title of independent sovereign of the principalities&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>which he formerly ruled at the sufferance of European<lb/> potentates&#44; promised all&#44; and performed nothing.  His<lb/> Jewish subjects&#44; who are very numerous&#44; find every<lb/> avenue to progress tight shut against them.  No ad&#45;<lb/>&#45;mission to public schools of learning&#44; none to industrial<lb/> schools&#44; not even to higher superior ranks in military departments.<lb/>  Eight hundred and eighty three Jewish soldiers who distin&#45;<lb/>&#45;guished themselves in the Turks&#45;Russia war &#40;1877&#41; in which<lb/> Roumania fought as an ally to Russia&#45;&#45;&#44; and who where<lb/> assured of obtaining the right of citizenship&#44; never received it.<lb/>  The Jew has a right to be killed for his country&#44; but not that to<lb/> of being be deemed a son of that unmotherly land.  No matter<lb/> how may many centuries the Jews may have lived in Roumania&#44;<lb/> he that is not a christian&#44; is a stranger&#44; the birth of<lb/> his children is not registered in public municipal records&#44; and yet<lb/> to procure a passport and flee away from that new<lb/> Egypt&#44; is almost as difficult as to cross the Red Sea on<lb/> foot.  Last year&#44; whether to spite the Alliance in its<lb/> incessant remonstrances&#44; or by reason of the inveterate hatred<lb/> of the Greek march against Jews&#44; a new Pharaonic law<lb/> was enacted.  It reduces to beggary 20&#44;000 persons of<lb/> our faith&#44; who&#44; debarred from following higher callings&#44; earned<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>a livelihood by peddling and hawking goods merchandise of various<lb/> kinds.  It is realted that a father of a large family&#44;<lb/> being forbid to offer ply his trade&#44; hired himself as a daily journey<lb/> laborer man&#44; and for the privilege of not being molested in his<lb/> work&#44; he had to pay a fellow&#45;laborer of the Christian<lb/> faith a part of his scanty wages.  Four hundred Israelites<lb/> among those affected by the cruel ordinance&#44; petitioned the<lb/> Senate in the hopes of bringing about some modification&#44;<lb/> but &#91;&#63;&#93;&#44; the prime minister of King Charles&#44; a<lb/> veritable counterpart of Haman&#44; set aside the me&#45;<lb/>&#45;morial.  Said he&#58; &#34;Strangers have no right to address public<lb/> bodies constituting the Roumanian government.&#34;  The<lb/> Hebrew article to which I have referred&#44; dictated by<lb/> despair&#44; pours forth its a vial of wrath on the Alliance&#44; just as<lb/> the Hebrew officers of the Hebrew slaves&#44; inveigled against<lb/> <sic>against</sic> Moses and Aaron by telling them &#34;May the Lord<lb/> look upon you and judge that you have made us<lb/> odious in the sight of Pharaoh and his servants&#44; and<lb/> put a sword into their hands to kill us&#34;&#44; and just<lb/> as the Hebrew contemporaries of Mordecai&#44; according<lb/> to the Talmudists&#44; reproached him for having<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>delivered them to slaughter&#44; &#34;If the alliance<lb/> did not give publicity to our grievances&#44; if it did expose<lb/> the tyranny of our masters&#44; the latter might be more<lb/> lenient&#34;.  So&#44; no doubt&#44; the sufferers exclaim.  Poor slaves&#44; kiss the hand that strikes you.  We<lb/> may pity&#44; we must forgive a people weighed down<lb/> by intolerable vexations for that outburst of bitter<lb/> feelings.  But we Americans rather than censure<lb/> the Alliance&#44; will extol is championship of the cause<lb/> of Right against Might.  True&#44; the Alliance forces<lb/> Roumania before the bar of civilization&#44; it shows that discloses the<lb/> land hollowness of that land&#44; its her perjury&#44; and thus thrusts<lb/> thorns into her sides.  But that is its mission&#44; unspeakably<lb/> difficult sorrowful painful as it indeed it is.  It dares not &#91;&#63;&#93; silent in<lb/> the face of medieval barbarity&#59; only by agitating questions of vital&#45;<lb/> importance to our race&#44; by insisting upon the recognition<lb/> of our brethren to an equality which will afford accord to us<lb/> everywhere freedom of instruction&#44; of commerce&#44; of property<lb/> and of religion&#44; can Jews in benighted regions climes hope to<lb/> rise from their torpor and abject humiliation.  Using its<lb/> own language&#58; To promote the emancipation and moral pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;gress of the Jewish people is the object of the Alliance<lb/> Israelite Universelle.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Brethren.  I have so often explained how well founded<lb/> are the claims of the most comprehensive of our insti&#45;<lb/>&#45;tutions to the cooperation of the whole Jewish world&#44;<lb/> that I could not&#44; without wearisomely respecting my&#45;<lb/>self&#44; rehearse now its praises.  Still I cannot deny<lb/> &#91;&#63;&#93; estimable and public spirited.  The Central committee<lb/> at Paris&#44; desires me to ask that you will signalize this<lb/> Purim&#45;&#45;the twenty fifth anniversary of the founding<lb/> of the Alliance&#45;&#45;by exceptional tokens of sympathy.<lb/>  As I do not anticipate to address many to morrow<lb/> morning&#44; when I shall speak a few words to act in&#45;<lb/>&#45;<sic>formaly</sic> with sister&#45;congregations&#44; I seize this opportu&#45;<lb/>&#45;nity to thank my coreligionists who acceded to my<lb/> written request.  In anticipation of being able to pride<lb/> myself on a universal response&#44; either by donations<lb/> or by a yearly subscription&#44; I invoke Divine blessings.<lb/>  May they rest on those who have already evinced<lb/> fraternal sentiments&#44; and on those others who will copy<lb/> the example.  May the joyous festivity bring to<lb/> all&#44; domestic happiness&#44; and the delightful sa&#45;<lb/>&#45;tisfaction of having done their duty even as recommended by Esther and Mordecai and Esther the Jew.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
