<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF16_3</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_3_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_3_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_3_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_3_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_3_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_3_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_3_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_3_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_3_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_3_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_3_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_3_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_3_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_3_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_3_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_3_8v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_3_9r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_3_9v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_3_10r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_3_10v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>118</p>
            <p>An admonitory lecture.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  There exists in our communities a fondness<lb/> for the sensational&#44; which some journals are pleased to<lb/> to graf gratify against all rules of propriety&#44; and often<lb/> to the perversion of truth.  Civility would demand that<lb/> the religious feelings of any denomination be not unnecessa&#45;<lb/>&#45;rily wounded&#44; but when absolute falsehood is made to<lb/> breed popular prejudice&#44; the offence becomes still more<lb/> grievous.  Of this offence the secular press in a neigh&#45;<lb/>&#45;boring city is guilty at all times.  Now&#58; I can readily<lb/> understand why some obscure sheets which depend for<lb/> their continuance upon the patronage of individualism the lowest grade<lb/> of society&#45;&#45;whom they think it unwise to elevate&#45;&#45;have<lb/> a fling at the Jew.  It is their pabalism&#59; their daily<lb/> subsistence.  But I cannot fis allege a reason for the<lb/> perpetuation of that wrong by Da papers which circulate<lb/> among a better class of society the community&#44; and which<lb/> possess ample means enabling them to assume a<lb/> high&#45;toned independence.  Yet&#44; inexplicable as we<lb/> may consider it&#44; a journal which has acquired an en&#45;<lb/>&#45;viable notoriety for having materially aided scientific<lb/> researches and discoveries by with its princely wealth&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>caters for a depraved taste by frequently filling its<lb/> columns with writings exposing to ridicule either our<lb/> people or our practices.  We must and can stand<lb/> bantering.  Perhaps we may finally live it down<lb/> in this country.  But we are too jealous of our reputation<lb/> as steadfast adherents to a Monotheistic belief not<lb/> to feel aggrieved when an impression to the contrary<lb/> is recklessly created.  My attention was lately<lb/> called by an intelligent and observant Jewess to an<lb/> invitation which a worthless being born of our race sent<lb/> to all &#34;Christian Israelites&#44;&#34; and which&#44; surprisingly&#44; he<lb/> succeeded in having published in a New York popular<lb/> journal.  Reading that invitation&#44; the Community<lb/> have a ground for thinking that a large body of<lb/> men of the seed of Jacob&#44; though <sic>worshipping</sic> a triune<lb/> god&#44; is can really to be met in the United States&#59; for&#44;<lb/> it is to such that the apostate addresses himself&#44; urging<lb/> for an early convention&#44; to facilitate an alliance with all<lb/> Hebrews of the same stamp.  I shall not follow<lb/> the renegade in his vagaries.  What he writes about<lb/> Shilo&#44; the promised Messiah&#44; and touching the necessity<lb/> we stand in to make a national confession of the sin of deicide&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>is too <sic>hackeneyed</sic> and trite not to provoke a derisive<lb/> smile.  His plan for petitioning all governments in the<lb/> world to restore to us Palestine&#44; so that the principles of<lb/> the new testament may form there the basis of our recon&#45;<lb/>&#45;structed existence would prove him demented.  But whe&#45;<lb/>&#45;ther a craving for notoriety or sheer madness dictated<lb/> the summons&#44; the paper which gave it publicity has of&#45;<lb/>&#45;fended greatly.  It has engendered the opinion that<lb/> many are in America eager are deserting our ranks&#44; eager to<lb/> make common cause with our religious opponents&#44; and that<lb/> the number of Hebrews abroad who have exchanged the<lb/> Synagogue for the Church is such as to warrant the possi&#45;<lb/>&#45;bility of an imposing assemblage of them in some principal<lb/> city.  This aspersion ought not to go unresented&#44; and<lb/> there should have been left enough spirit in th our<lb/> brothers of a sister city to force the wretched scribbler into<lb/> a hiding place of disgrace&#44; through the very same pu&#45;<lb/> journal which has pushed him on into note......<lb/> But speaking to you&#44; my Brethren&#44; with all friendly<lb/> candor&#44; I acknowledge that the conduct of many<lb/> Israelites in this land does justify the suspicion of a<lb/></p> 
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>general defection.  Witness&#44; the festivities of the<lb/> present week&#44; which&#44; originating with ancient hea&#45;<lb/>&#45;thenism&#44; and having been transferred for as a political<lb/> measure&#44; to Christianity&#44; find so vast a quantity of<lb/> Abraham&#39;s descendants to join in most heartily.<lb/>  I am not a cynic by nature.  I am by disposition<lb/> fond of all my fellow&#45;beings&#44; irrespective of creed&#44; or<lb/> nationality and I would have my neighbors to choose such diversions as best promote home reunions and social good&#45;will&#44; but where is consistency&#44; where self&#45;respect<lb/> in us as Jews to showing that while we allow the our grand&#45;historic<lb/> memories to lie in the pit of oblivion&#44; we help in to keep<lb/> alive inauthentic stories entirely foreign&#44; if not pan<lb/> painfully hostile to the Jewish ancestral religion&#63;......God forbid&#44;<lb/> that I should agree with that apostate Jew who would<lb/> fain represent us as inclined to accept for our ever&#45;<lb/>lasting Redeemer the son of man whose induction into<lb/> the world&#44; the bulk of the inhabitants of this country<lb/> celebrated at this season&#44; but the example we set<lb/> before our children is <sic>frought</sic> with ill&#45;omens.  It is<lb/> a coffin nail in the coffin in the coffin of our<lb/> venerable mother&#45;&#45;the Hebrew faith.  She will be<lb/> dead for our offspring&#44; who will remember her only as<lb/> a think in a state of decrepitude&#44; treated by their parents<lb/> irreverently.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Ah&#33; my Brethren&#33;  Would that my eyes saw not&#44; nor<lb/> that my hear ears heard the shame of the house of Israel.<lb/>  In our streets the testimonies are cast aside&#44; through a<lb/> culpable indifferentism&#59; in a hall of a neighboring<lb/> city a new teacher commands their abolition&#44; and advo&#45;<lb/>&#45;cates the usages and practices of the Nazarenes as more<lb/> useful and sensible.  He rewins People are charmed.<lb/>  He wins the applause plaudits of Hebrews whom to conci&#45;<lb/>&#45;liate and draw to the Synagogue from which they had<lb/> been estranged&#44; not long ago a time&#45;honored liturgy and<lb/> the ritual service were <sic>remodelled</sic> and modernized.<lb/>  When that teacher dogmatically asserts that Passover<lb/> and the paschal&#45;lamb are a substitute for the human<lb/> sacrifice of the first&#45;born into which our fathers were<lb/> wont to indulge&#59; when he declares that Monotheism<lb/> is no more the property of Mosaism&#44; than of Buddhism&#44;<lb/> all look up admiringly&#59; a smile of complacence and<lb/> approval rests on every countenance&#44; at what is deemed<lb/> so broad&#44; so liberal&#44; so free from any secta&#45;<lb/>rianism.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Dear Brethren&#33;  I will unbosom myself to you&#44; this morn&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing.  There has been a time in which I felt disposed to judged favorably<lb/> of that son of &#91;&#63;&#93; superannuated Rabbi of a New<lb/> York temple.  Believing him learned&#44; I fancied<lb/> that he was eager to employ his talents for bringing<lb/> about a reformation&#44; which&#44; proscribing all external<lb/> signs of religion&#44; might draw closer together in amity&#44;<lb/> different denominations now hostile to each other.<lb/>  I could not naturally symapthise with the would&#45;be apostle<lb/> nor with his principles.  I considered him an<lb/> unpractical enthusiast&#44; but honest withal.  Now&#44;<lb/> I register his name in the book where the sycophants<lb/> and time&#45;serving whose sole aim in life is to win public<lb/> popularity figure conspicuously.  For it be true&#44;<lb/> as reported&#44; that he recommends the festivities of the<lb/> present season&#44; and bids all his hearers to participate<lb/> thus therein because the majority observe them&#44; then<lb/> expediency and not the right is taught in his school<lb/> to be the standard that man should follow&#59; then to<lb/> run after the multitude is to seek wisdom&#44; and the<lb/> minority must always sacrifice convictions upon<lb/> the altar of convenience............<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Here&#44; it is Christianity&#44; or members of the Christian<lb/> creed that reckon the largest number.  They have their<lb/> days of rest&#44; and seasons of recreation.  Jews must readily<lb/> make the exchange&#44; and wiped away the whole of<lb/> the twenty third chapter of Leviticus.  Where Islam<lb/> rules&#44; other periods of the week &#38; of the year are set<lb/> apart as holy.  Jews must see there also in discretion<lb/> in forming an amalgamation.  And inasmuch as<lb/> the <sic>Hindoos</sic> also have a knowledge of Almighty<lb/> God&#44; whom they serve under some material form&#44; Jews<lb/> should there likewise bend the knee to the idol&#44; and<lb/> part with the Decalogue............<lb/> Why so much suffering&#63;  Why the martyrdom of<lb/> twenty centuries&#63;  Why have rivers run with the blood<lb/> of our fathers&#63;  Folly it was in Akibah of<lb/> yore to expose his hoary head to the engines of the<lb/> torture.  The ordinance of Adrian was supreme&#44; all<lb/> bowed to it.  To no purpose that old Rabbi suffered<lb/> his flesh to be torn from off his body....Away&#44; &#91;&#63;&#93; im&#45;<lb/>pious thought&#33;  No&#58; with the blood of such<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>we purchased eternity upon earth&#44; to verify the revealed word<lb/> of our that &#34;God is not a man who lies&#44; nor the son of<lb/> man who repents.&#34;  Hear the prediction.  The<lb/> Eagle &#40;Adler&#41; that fain would carry us in one of its<lb/> flights to the way of destruction&#44; will be left wingless&#59;<lb/> and Israel and his law will remain indestructible.  May the<lb/> Israel Lord of our fathers grant that when the day of reckoning arrives&#44;<lb/> we be found among the remnant of the faithful few&#44;<lb/> who have stood faced the fiery battle.  One one side the<lb/> darts of the church whizzing in through the air to exterminate<lb/> us&#59; on the other the arrows of apostates trying to pierce<lb/> our hearts&#59; here&#44; the destructive baneful example of Radicalism&#44;<lb/> there the taunts of the unprogressive&#59; exposed everywhere<lb/> to danger but standing our ground resolutely&#59; turning<lb/> neither to the right to gratify the changelings&#44; nor to the<lb/> left to avoid ridicule&#44; but walking straitforwardly<lb/> to serve God with singleness of heart&#44; with honesty and<lb/> truth......<lb/></p>
            <p>Oh&#33; be Thou with us&#44; Almighty King in our <sic>straitness</sic>.<lb/>  For verily fearful is are the difficulties with which we must<lb/> grapple not to be unfaithful unto Thee.  Strengthen us<lb/> for the victory&#44; and when we shall have come forth unscathed&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>illumine still our understanding that we may follow<lb/> what Thou willest&#44; and seek neither the whimsical&#44;<lb/> the fickle approval of the populace&#44; nor any perishable<lb/> advantage&#44; but only the unspeakable pleasure of having<lb/> loved Thee&#44; O our Father&#44; and adhered to Thy word&#44; O<lb/> our Legislator&#44; our Protector&#44; our Saviour.  Amen<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
