<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF16_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_2_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>An admonitory lecture &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  It was just thirty years ago&#44; in the<lb/> month of June&#44; that on my way to Italy&#44; to<lb/> visit my father and relatives&#44; before I settled for life in this<lb/> country&#44; I stopped in England&#44; where I had<lb/> personal friends.  In the course of conversation<lb/> with one&#44; I was asked about the manner of conduct&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing religious services in America.  I gave an<lb/> account of it&#44; and said that here sermons are<lb/> not delivered&#44; as at that time in London among<lb/> Portuguese Jews&#44; on special occasions&#44; but oftener&#44;<lb/> and not before the afternoon service as there&#44; but<lb/> at the closing of the morning prayers.  The<lb/> man to whom I told that&#44; remarked that the plan<lb/> was sensible.  It would enable all to at&#45;<lb/>&#45;tend the worship&#44; and leave the Synagogue&#44; if<lb/> they did not understand or enjoy a discourse.<lb/>  His words made an impression on me&#44; and I<lb/> resolved to act accordingly.  To be sure&#59;<lb/> it is not flattering to one&#39;s self&#45;love to see a<lb/> thinning off of the congregation&#44; when the lecture<lb/> is about to be delivered&#44; but better witness that&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>than be a cause of dissatisfaction.  So<lb/> thinking I have repeatedly stated in public&#44;<lb/> and mentioned it also in private&#44; that I shall<lb/> not feel offends&#44; however humiliated I may feel inwardly&#44; if<lb/> those who do not believe they can learn by listening<lb/> will quietly retire before the sermon begins.  And<lb/> most assuredly I cannot deem it an affront&#44; when<lb/> those who are unfamiliar with the vernacular&#44;<lb/> will leave.  With me the recommendation of<lb/> the Sages not to fatigue the attendants at the<lb/> sanctuary &#91;Hebrew&#93; has great weight.  So careful<lb/> I am not to occasion the slightest inconvenience&#44;<lb/> that&#44; when I happen to offer an English<lb/> prayer&#44; I do not require my audience&#44; as usual<lb/> everywhere else&#44; to rise.  What pains me<lb/> is to see some in a posture indicating weariness&#44;<lb/> and a wish to divert the mind from the preaching.<lb/>  That sight does more than hurt me&#44; it distracts<lb/> my thoughts&#59; and for a moment&#44; at lest&#44; it<lb/> scares me&#44; lest I lose the thread of my discourse<lb/> and blunder over it.  I have now and<lb/> then hinted at this&#44; but now that I am<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>about to suspend for a season my weekly<lb/> speaking&#44; I deem it fit to say so plainly&#44;<lb/> to give my hearers time to reflect and act<lb/> as hereafter as propriety suggests.  I would<lb/> rather address a few&#45;&#45;and I am not too vain when<lb/> I believe to have their attention&#45;&#45;a few willing<lb/> to receive my humble counsel or some inform&#45;<lb/>&#45;ation than many who consider it an infliction<lb/> to be sermonized.  Truly&#44; were it not for<lb/> the hope I cherish that those few may occasion&#45;<lb/>&#45;ally benefit&#44; so great are the heartburnings I<lb/> have endured&#44; that I would never turn this sacred<lb/> desk into a pulpit.  For with many the<lb/> topic is seldom fittingly chosen.  If it is doctri&#45;<lb/>&#45;nal&#44; it reflects on persons who are not so particular<lb/> in Jewish observances&#59; if it is literary&#44; it rises<lb/> above general comprehension and it becomes waste<lb/> of tim e.  Then references to defections are inappro&#45;<lb/>&#45;priate.  They injure the interests of the Congre&#45;<lb/>&#45;gation.  Allusions to current events&#44; give room<lb/> to invidious comparisons.  Oh&#33; happy<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>they of old who earned their livelihood<lb/> by handicraft.  Their teaching was sought after<lb/> and was gained gratuitously.  They were Rabbis<lb/> in the true sense of the word.  Masters were<lb/> they and not salaried servants&#44; subject to the<lb/> crotchets of those who profess means.  To be<lb/> like them is the height of my ambition&#44; to be<lb/> needed for the promotion of my people&#39;s spi&#45;<lb/>&#45;ritual welfare and never to pecuniarily require<lb/> them.  But the expectation is a delusion.<lb/>  Still there are some who command influence&#44; even<lb/> if they are highly remunerated for their mental ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;ertions&#44; some whose words are heeded&#44; and obedience<lb/> to them is not forced but voluntary.  As to<lb/> myself I was given cause of late to perceiving<lb/> the decline of my powers for good congregationally.  I might cite<lb/> several instances&#44; but to spare my neighbor&#39;s<lb/> feelings&#44; I shall mention only one more imme&#45;<lb/>&#45;diately concerning me&#44; and will say that after<lb/> three full weeks of ineffectual trial to hold service<lb/> during Omer time&#44; I was compelled to forego<lb/> it.  Not once could I draw together the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>requisite Minian.  Other years I may have<lb/> been short occasionally&#44; but this year&#44; except when<lb/> a congregant kept the anniversary of the death of<lb/> a relative&#44; and brought the full number along&#44;<lb/> the historical services between Passover and Pentecost<lb/> had to be relinquished.  But our retrogression<lb/> was not noticeable only at that period&#44; it is to<lb/> me painfully perceptible at other times.  Saturday<lb/> evening&#44; which in winter brought more than legally re&#45;<lb/>&#45;quired&#44; but always enough at other seasons to hold<lb/> congregational prayers&#44; now finds the synagogue<lb/> deserted.  Perhaps one or two may visit it be&#45;<lb/>&#45;sides the sexton and myself&#44; but the anticipation<lb/> of raising the full number would be groundless.<lb/>  I even fear that as the season advances&#44; and some<lb/> who attend Friday evening will leave the city&#44; we<lb/> shall look in vain for the ten who will assem&#45;<lb/>&#45;ble here to greet the coming of the Sabbath.<lb/>  It was once my pride that this congregation<lb/> did not unfasten the gates of its Synagogue<lb/> only on the Sabbath morning&#44; when some would<lb/> drop in at convenient hours&#44; but that it kept<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>them open frequently&#44; with greater frequency<lb/> than larger bodies of Jews in our city&#44; but now<lb/> the seeds of decay have set in taken root among us also.<lb/>  Many have we lost who habitually attended&#59; some<lb/> have been called to their lasting home&#44; some have<lb/> removed to other cities&#44; or to distant localities&#44; and<lb/> the young are raised in ignorance of our practices.<lb/>  They take no pleasure&#44; very naturally&#44; for what<lb/> they have received no training in.  This is a<lb/> source of unspeakable grief to me.  For I hear<lb/> complaints that the Sabbath morning service is<lb/> unimposing.  Could we secure bu ta score<lb/> or even loss of our boys who might understandingly<lb/> chant the ritual&#44; and lead in the responses&#44; the<lb/> worship would clearly gain in impressiveness.<lb/>  But when I alone bear the burden of control&#45;<lb/>&#45;ling some inharmonious voices&#44; and use efforts&#44;<lb/> which I do not regret but which are too often<lb/> of no avail to prevent discordance&#44; none should<lb/> wonder that our beautiful hymns and psalms<lb/> fail to create the devotional feelings which they<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>ought to arouse.  I acknowledge<lb/> that another hindrance to solemnity is the<lb/> demeanour of some whom I cannot impress<lb/> with the idea of reverence for the house of God&#44; but<lb/> who act there with a freedom scarcely al&#45;<lb/>&#45;lowable in one&#39;s own parlor&#44; conversing noisily<lb/> and entering and quitting the place of worship<lb/> indecorously.  But it would be a stretch of authority&#44;<lb/> on my part&#44; to approach such individuals with<lb/> a reprimand.  Innumerable are the occasions<lb/> on which I called attention to the imperative ne&#45;<lb/>&#45;cessity of correcting an evil which is damaging us<lb/> materially as well as spiritually.  I lament<lb/> again my lack of influence which has prevented<lb/> success.  But let me close a chapter of<lb/> criminations and &#91;&#63;&#93; self humiliating confessions.  It is long<lb/> and I started with the intention of reading it fully&#44;<lb/> but I grow weary over it.  Let those who<lb/> are at fault try to remedy what they can&#44; and<lb/> that which is beyond mending&#44; will have to<lb/> be borne without refining.  We are<lb/> wedded together for life&#44; and I judge we shall<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>remain so.  It would not redound to the<lb/> honor of the household&#44; to let stranger know of<lb/> domestic disagreements&#44; differences of taste&#44; or vexations&#44;<lb/> and after all since we are bound in one&#44; existence is<lb/> too short to spend days in charges and accusations.<lb/>  I would wish&#44; of course&#44; a respectful appreciation<lb/> of services rendered not for the sake of filthy lucre&#45;<lb/>&#45;which to my sorrow I cannot dispense with&#45;&#45;but<lb/> but proceeding from higher motives&#44; from deep set principles.<lb/>  You perhaps would desire an officer more pliant&#44;<lb/> more on a level with the men of the age&#44; shaping<lb/> things after the approved models of the time.<lb/>  We must therefore exercise mutual forbearance.<lb/>  In the book of books has been written that they who<lb/> can check their dispositions to live influence&#44; are mightier<lb/> than <sic>heros</sic>&#44; and the Talmud&#44; which is our guide ritual&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly ends thus&#58; God looked but found no vessel capable<lb/> of holding bette happiness better than that which is<lb/> called &#34;Peace&#59;&#34; therefore David after having extolled<lb/> the goodness of the Lord&#44; says&#58; &#34;the Lord will give His<lb/> people strength&#44; the Lord will bless His people with peace.&#34;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
