<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF10_3</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_3_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_3_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_3_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_3_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_3_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_3_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_3_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_3_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_3_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_3_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_3_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_3_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>On Shemoth<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>In the palace of Rameses II&#44; a princely reception<lb/> was held.  Foreign rulers came from afar to own al&#45;<lb/>&#45;legiance to their sovereign lord.  They laid golden wreaths<lb/> at the foot of his throne&#44; in token of submission.  Upon<lb/> that festive occasion&#44; high officials admitted the dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;tinguished visitors into the presence of the mighty dreaded king.<lb/>  For&#44; the monarch of Egypt celebrated his birth&#45;day<lb/> surrounded by courtiers and vassals with barbaric pomp.  He received their<lb/> homage and&#44; in return&#44; graciously dispensed favors. of his courtiers&#44; and vassals&#44; and granted in return&#44; approving smiles.<lb/>  Among the train of swelling a crowding nobility&#44; two plebians<lb/> opened their way to the royal gates.  They are an&#45;<lb/>&#45;nounced.  What is their errand&#63;  Have they also<lb/> brought costly chaplets to crown bedeck adorn Pharaoh&#45;&#45;the<lb/> ruler of a thousand rulers&#63;..  The strangers have no<lb/> gift to offer.  They must stand back and tarry&#44;<lb/> till the illustrious assemblage has departed.  They<lb/> cannot hope to be granted an audience amidst the<lb/> grandees of the kingdom.  The lowly shall not mingle<lb/> with the lofty.  So have the Sages portrayed the first<lb/> scene of the grandest episode in human history&#45;&#45;a scene<lb/> of which the fifth chapter of the book that the Synagogue<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>began this Sabbath&#44; gives an outline.  We read&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew &#34;Afterward&#44; Moses and Aaron went in&#34;.<lb/>  Pharaoh asked the strangers a reason for what he considered an<lb/> intrusion.  &#34;A message form the Supreme Lord&#44; has<lb/> led our steps hither.  He demands that thou shalt let<lb/> thy slaves hold a celebration beyond the limits of thy<lb/> land&#44; in honor of Himself&#45;&#45;Adonai&#44; the Everlasting<lb/> One&#45;&#45;their God of Israel fathers&#39; God&#34;  At these words&#44; uttered<lb/> by the strangers with manly composure&#44; Pharaoh<lb/> commands that a role of papyrus be unfolded.<lb/>  In it the names and famous deeds of deified <sic>heros</sic><lb/> are recorded.  He will see if Adona&#239;&#44; called the Ever&#45;<lb/>&#45;lasting&#44; has a place&#44; where national deities have received received<lb/> an reverential honorable mention.  He will seek for Israel&#39;s<lb/> God where Isis and Osiris Milcom and Dagon are<lb/> depicted.  He &#91;&#63;&#93; turns over the examines through that scroll&#44; he finds what the Edomites worship&#44; and<lb/> that which the Ammonites supplicate entreat in their temples&#59; what the<lb/> Sidonians adore trust in&#44; and that which the Philistines Moabites bow<lb/> to.  Adona&#239; is not in the superior nor in the inferior<lb/> ranks of ancient gods.  &#34;Oh king&#44; thou searchest<lb/> for the living on a ground which is strewn with the<lb/> dead.  The Hebrews whom thou keepest in bondage&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>descend from a father parent&#44; who taught them to bend adore<lb/> before the incorporeal Author of the Universe.  That all&#45;<lb/>pervading spirit never put on flesh&#44; that thou mayest<lb/> write out his description.  The witnesses of His existence<lb/> are not memorials traced upon papyrus&#44; but the hea&#45;<lb/>&#45;vens in their measureless extent&#59; the earth in its count&#45;<lb/>&#45;less productions.  They attest His power and eternity &#34;and His power&#34;.<lb/> Thus calmly spoke the two messengers&#44; and Pharaoh<lb/> curtly replied&#44; &#34;I know not Adona&#239;&#44; neither will I let<lb/> Israel go.&#34;  Brethren.  The story which<lb/> I have just related is told in a book&#44; where the<lb/> legends of the Rabbis are collected.  I fancied that<lb/> its recital might be suggestive&#44; while it entertained.<lb/>  For&#44; Moses and Aaron forced into the rear of the nobility&#44;<lb/> as they went in to face a tyrant&#44; become the central<lb/> figures in the drama which&#44; for some time&#44; will be weekly<lb/> represented.  not a debasing stage&#44; where a Unlike a late representation on a debasing stage&#44; where a prurient<lb/> curiosity for evanescent beauty is was to be gratified&#44; this drama will be set to view but before<lb/> the holy will&#44; wherein they purifying word of the on a spot in which the word of the Eternal is expounded&#44; to elevate<lb/> Eternal&#44; its enshrined and purify man.  You&#44; O seed of Jacob&#44;<lb/> should gaze upon those figures. in the drama&#44; where so<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>A proud monarch&#44; is brought led by them prostrate to the foot&#45;<lb/>&#45;stool of the Lord he had denied&#44; and freedom for<lb/> his slaves is wrested from his iron grasp.  Who<lb/> more than you should rivet their looks upon those<lb/> apostles of the Omnipotent&#63; Your deliverers&#63;..  History is si&#45;<lb/>&#45;lent about the origin of privileges&#44; which&#44; to all ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;pearances&#44; a few of the Hebrews singularly enjoyed.<lb/>  I cannot explain the causes which exonerated the<lb/> champions of our liberty from the crushing burdens un&#45;<lb/>&#45;der which their people groaned.  Our teachers assert&#44;<lb/> that the exemption was not peculiarly theirs.  It extended to the whole tribe of<lb/> Levy.  But be it so or not&#59; this is certain&#59; and this you should<lb/> weigh consider well at these times&#44; which by try men&#39;s souls&#33;  The immunity was not the price of<lb/> faithlessness disloyalty&#59; of treason against the belief of Abra&#45;<lb/>&#45;ham and of his suffering progeny.  It might<lb/> have been easy for either brother to rise magnificently&#44;<lb/> by disowning affinity with the oppressed.  The learn&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing of Moses would have gained for him access among<lb/> the priests of Mezraim&#44; of whom none exercised greater<lb/> influence.  The eloquence of Aaron would have secured<lb/> him a seat in the high&#45;toned society of Tanis and<lb/> Memphis&#44; whose chief inhabitants Isaiah pictured as the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>mainstay of Egypt &#91;Hebrew&#93;...&#91;Hebrew&#93;...&#91;Hebrew&#93;.  But what would<lb/> Israel&#44; the armor bearer of eternal Truths&#44; be&#44; if the sons of Amram<lb/> had craved for self <sic>aggrandisement</sic> and refused to cast their lots with the lowly&#63;  If they Or if<lb/> had shrunk back in dismay when thrust aside&#44;<lb/> and frowned upon and rebuked by a dreaded mighty ruler&#44; they<lb/> had taken counsel with worldly prudence&#44; and desisted&#63;<lb/>  What would society&#44; that has stretched forth her hand<lb/> to call choice fruits of Jewish planting&#44; what would<lb/> she now be&#44; if those Levites&#44; the determined avengers of our wrongs&#44; had<lb/> been terrified into inaction&#63;  How many ages would Our section<lb/> civilization havve been retarded subjects brings Moses them to our close examination.  I observe him<lb/> Moses Moses&#45;&#45;a humble shepherd&#44; whilst he might have sat a king&#45;&#45;<lb/> as he seeks to read the future of Israel in the bright flame<lb/> of the typical burning bush&#44; and he grows gigantic before<lb/> my mind.  I behold Aaron giving a fraternal<lb/> kiss and setting forth girding up his loins to work out salvation&#44; and<lb/> his aspect assumes a grandeur superior even to that<lb/> described in the glowing language of the Psalmist.  I let<lb/> my vision rest upon both&#44; as they confront the enemy<lb/> of justice&#44; and&#44; remembering how unflinchingly at their<lb/> pleading for right&#44; I recognize two characters preemi&#45;<lb/>&#45;nent in sacred history&#44; preeminent because of their<lb/> sublimest devotion to a national desperate most righteous cause.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Oh the pigmies of our days&#44; who skulk behind<lb/> the subterfuge of fictitious names&#44; to hide their com&#45;<lb/>&#45;mon extraction with the persecuted&#63;  Come forward<lb/> ye knights of self&#45;assertion&#33;  Come and measure your<lb/> moral height stature with that of your people&#39;s lawgiver&#44;<lb/> and his coadjutor.  You will sink into nonentity.<lb/>  Yet Still&#44; you imagine that you will gain in moral height by exchan&#45;<lb/>&#45;ging your parent&#39;s heritage for a smile of the pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;judiced.  Samaritan&#45;like you belong to Israel<lb/> when the scale of our prosperity turns up rises.  You are<lb/> not of us&#44; when modern Hamans make conjure up anti&#45;Semi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tism popular to vex and harass us.  But the icy cold wave of in&#45;<lb/>&#45;humanity which surged up in Germany&#44; and rolled<lb/> on farther into distant lands&#44; and stopped the warm throbbings<lb/> beatings of the heart for of fraternal kindness&#44; and compassion will<lb/>sometime have spent itself.  The Stoeckers and the<lb/> Treitchkes may yet be made to feel ashamed of their offences<lb/> against civilization&#44; and the Munisens and Firckows&#91;&#63;&#93;<lb/> may rejoice over the vindication of liberality.  Then<lb/> those among the Hebrews&#44; who did not change sides&#44;<lb/> when the finger of scorn was pointed at us&#44; will<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>be acknowledged worthy disciples of the two<lb/> self&#45;denying champions of our race.  Then shall<lb/> the time&#45;serving and disloyal&#44; who courted the acquaint&#45;<lb/>&#45;ance of the prejudiced illiberal&#44; shall wear as their badge&#44;<lb/> public contempt.  Not in the sroll scroll&#44; which<lb/> set in array Pharaoh&#39;s dead gods&#44; but in the volume<lb/> which trained mankind in the knowledge of one ever<lb/> living and Universal Father&#44; is written that finally<lb/> righteousness shall wax strong&#44; and iniquity melt<lb/> away.  And history&#45;&#45;the real reliable chronicler&#45;&#45;<lb/> verifies that divine imparting...But it is never&#45;<lb/>&#45;theless the duty of incumbent upon every Israelite&#44; to stand by<lb/> his brethren&#44; and make the hand that now throttles<lb/> them&#44; palsied.  According to a recent ordinance<lb/> Jews dare not practice as chemists in Russia&#59;<lb/> according to another they dare not act as physi&#45;<lb/>&#45;cians&#44; and but yesterday the wires across the ocean&#44;<lb/> announced to the world&#44; &#34;that railway companies<lb/> have ordered the discharge of their Jewish <sic>employis</sic>&#59;<lb/> that the no indulgence shall be shown to Jews resi&#45;<lb/>&#45;ding in the capital without official leave&#59; that no<lb/> court can authorize the transfer of land to a Jew&#34;.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>In these trying times&#44; I who&#44; in my eagerness anxiety for<lb/> a reign of tranquillity peace &#38; good will when my sorefooted brethren may enjoy rest&#44; study current events&#44; note<lb/> the faithful and the faithless among my people.<lb/>  True to the cause of the oppressed are those who&#44; with<lb/> the intense earnestness of the miser&#44; watch over their<lb/> wealth affluence&#44; that it may not help not a coin drop may fall to help on the wheel of grinding tyranny.<lb/>  All honor to the Jewish firm Efrussi&#44; which&#44; after the<lb/> carnival of butchery in the doomed realms of the Czar&#44;<lb/> closed up its banking house&#44; of fifty years standing in<lb/> Odessa&#44; and&#44; regardless of losses&#44; removed to the capitals of<lb/> Austria and France.  Would that I could bestow the<lb/> same meed of praise on the princes kings of the money&#45;<lb/>market&#33;  But their last transaction forbids it.  The<lb/> negotiation of a loan on behalf of the Pharaoh of the<lb/> nineteenth century&#44; is a treason.  To you&#44; my brethren&#44;<lb/> whom a beneficent Providence has lifted placed beyond the<lb/> reach of kingly hatred&#59; to you American Hebrews&#44; I say&#58;<lb/> Hold constantly in view the two central characters in<lb/> the drama&#44; which opened this sabbath.  Gaze intently<lb/> on their unselfishness on their love for the sufferers.  You will then bear with your<lb/> fellow&#45;believers&#44; when if despotism has put them on below your<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>standard.  As God lifted up you up&#44; so must you<lb/> raise the lowly and fit them for civilization.  It is<lb/> your bounden duty before mankind&#44; and before Him who declared what was has been<lb/> registered in the Haftorah prophetic chieftan portion we have read.  &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Holy Israel<lb/> is holiness unto the Lord&#44; the first fruits of His <sic>yeilding</sic>&#44;<lb/> whosoever shall all that devour him will offend.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
