<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF2_18</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1890-09" source="" attested="yes">7 September 1890</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_18_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_18_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_18_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_18_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_18_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_18_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_18_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_18_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_18_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_18_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_18_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_18_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_18_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_18_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_18_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_18_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>A dedicatory sermon<lb/>
                for<lb/>
                the Congregation &#34;Adath Israel.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <p>It was rewritten &#38; delivered at the consecration<lb/>
                of Zechron Ephraim Syn in N.Y. Sep 7.&#47;90<lb/>
                The copy is in here<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Most fitting is the time you have chosen for the<lb/> dedication of a sanctuary&#44; my fellow believers&#33;  For&#44;<lb/> at this season&#44; Israel of yore&#44; saw the glory of the Deity<lb/> rest upon the hallowed shrine they had built.  A year<lb/> had elapsed since the shackles of a cruel bondage had<lb/> been cut asunder.  The redeemed of Mizraim&#44; now<lb/> reverently bent in the mansion devoted to the Almighty<lb/> Deliverer.  With uplifted hands&#44; Aaron&#44; their <sic>annointed</sic><lb/> priest&#44; pronounced the three&#45;fold blessing.  Moses&#45;&#45;<lb/>his countenance illumined with rays divine&#45;&#45;invoked<lb/> the all&#45;gracious God&#44; that the work of His people be<lb/> celestially established.  Every breast swells with gra&#45;<lb/>&#45;titude.  Every mind is impressed with awe.  Suddenly<lb/> a shout burst forth&#59; that rent the sky.  The heavenly<lb/> fire&#44; symbol of God&#39;s unfathomable essence&#44; has descended<lb/> upon the consecrated altar.  A whole nation behold<lb/> the entrance of the Sovereign Lord into His sumptuous<lb/> palace.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  &#34;Rejoice ye righteous<lb/> in the Lord.&#34;  Observe&#44; my friends&#33;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  The Psalmist<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>did not simply write &#34;Sing to the Lord&#34; but&#44; rejoice<lb/> in the Lord&#44;&#34; namely&#44; when His divine presence is<lb/> visibly shown in your midst.  When His manifestation<lb/> is reflected in the imposing solemnity of your assemblies.<lb/>  That sentence so parabolically explained by our Rabbins&#44;<lb/> will I employ in addressing you&#44; my Brethren on so pecu&#45;<lb/>&#45;liar an occasion.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  The satisfaction ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;perienced at having dedicated in this memorable month&#44;<lb/> a dwelling for a Synagogue&#44; must proceed from the same<lb/> cause&#44; which influenced our ancestors at the rearing of<lb/> their Tabernacle.  It must emanates from motives un&#45;<lb/>&#45;mixed with human alloy.  The thought of extolling<lb/> Israel&#39;s God&#44; by watching over the preservation of His<lb/> Law&#44; should alone pervade your mind.  Nothing savoring<lb/> of self&#45;glorification or ambition&#44; nothing which par&#45;<lb/>&#45;takes of unfriendly feelings towards any of the existing<lb/> congregations of your brethren&#44; should blend with your pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;sent rejoicing.  You have lighted upon<lb/> a spot where prayers will be offered agreeably to your<lb/> religious convictions.  That event you rightly consider<lb/> a source of gratulation.  For&#44; sincerity is the soul<lb/> of the worship.  When our in inmost sentiments<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>fail to be identified therewith&#45;&#45;let it be never so grand&#45;&#45;<lb/>it becomes sheer pageantry&#44; an offence&#44; not an honor<lb/> to the Most High.  If you truly believe&#44;<lb/> that the interests of Judaism demand the retaining un&#45;<lb/>&#45;alterably of its prescribed rules.  If you believe that<lb/> the removing of the land&#45;mark set by the ancients<lb/> would engender baneful evils&#44; that it would gradually<lb/> estrange our children from our fold&#44; and lure them<lb/> into the ranks of gentilism.  If you share the<lb/> opinion I have humbly ever held&#44; that the outpouring<lb/> of the heart of a whole people&#45;&#45;though less harmo&#45;<lb/>&#45;nious and euphoric than choral songs on instru&#45;<lb/>&#45;mental music&#45;&#45;is still most acceptable to our<lb/> Maker.  That it furthermore behooves every son<lb/> of Israel to acknowledge the unity of God&#44; and openly<lb/> avow his utter dependence upon the Omnipotent for<lb/> support&#44; for guidance and defense&#44; and in order<lb/> the better to promote these views you have hallowed<lb/> a spacious edifice&#44; then I will say&#44; in the language<lb/> of the inspired shepherd&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Rejoice ye righteous<lb/> in the Lord.&#34;  He who irradiated<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>with His Divinity our father&#39;s tabernacle&#44; will fill with<lb/> His glory this minor sanctuary devoted to His name.<lb/>  When its walls shall resound with your united praise&#44;<lb/> a superhuman voice will cry forth.  &#34;Thou&#44; art my<lb/> servant&#44; O Israel&#44; by whom I am glorified.&#34;  That<lb/> voice&#45;&#45;a reverberation of the spirit that abides in your<lb/> midst&#45;&#45;you will hear in the consciousness of having<lb/> acted consistently with your principles&#59; in the conviction<lb/> of having tendered to the Lord a homage&#44; which you deem<lb/> pleasing in His sight&#44; and conducive to the end of for<lb/> which worship was instituted.<lb/></p>
            <p>Need I explain to any of you&#44; what is that noble goal&#63;<lb/>  None among my audience&#44; I hope&#44; imagine that the<lb/> bare rehearsing of a ritual entitles to the appellation<lb/> of righteous &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Only when God is present before<lb/> our mental vision&#44; when the soul&#45;stirring idea of holding<lb/> communion with our heavenly Father&#44; elevates the<lb/> mind and softens the heart&#44; we can aspire to that<lb/> epithet.  And to render the worship thus<lb/> spiritually beneficial&#44; we must guard it against<lb/> all disturbing elements.  Our Rabbis have offered<lb/> valuable instruction upon this subject.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>It were well that we followed it with precision.<lb/>  We might then dispense with the appointing of<lb/> individuals to preserve order&#44; as practised in various<lb/> congregations.  Every being ere he bows to the oracle<lb/> of the Law&#44; would prepare himself becomingly&#59; so<lb/> that his posture&#44; his gravity of manners&#59; his whole<lb/> demeanour denote the seniments by which he is influen&#45;<lb/>&#45;ced.  Without admitting the necessity of altering<lb/> our time&#45;honored rites&#44; to lend the service an im&#45;<lb/>&#45;posing aspect&#44; we must be mindful of this irre&#45;<lb/>&#45;futable fact.  We are naturally affected by our<lb/> surroundings.  If while engaged in devotional<lb/> exercises&#44; our attention is diverted by untimely speaking&#44;<lb/> or the indulgence in levity on the part of some of our<lb/> brethren&#44; the impression we should have received will<lb/> be lost&#44; and another will supplant it&#44; not at all<lb/> calculated to benefit our soul.  Our Teachers<lb/> of old&#44; anxious to improve us by means of these holy<lb/> convocations&#44; condemn the slightest deviation from the<lb/> rules of decorum in the house of prayer.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Quoting the prophet Amos&#44; they say&#44; that Israelites<lb/> should prove by every disposition of the body and of the<lb/> mind&#44; that they look upon this spot as on the seat<lb/> of Divine glory.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            <p>But powerful as that consideration assuredly is&#44;<lb/> to restrain us from any action derogatory to the sanctity<lb/> of the Synagogue&#44; another not less cogent exists.<lb/>  We should be extremely jealous for the honor of our<lb/> people&#44; lest we be guilty of &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Whatsoever might<lb/> reflect in the least&#44; discredit upon our character&#44; must<lb/> be studiously avoided.  Now&#44; my fellow&#45;believers.<lb/>  Through the mercy of Him who guides nations with wis&#45;<lb/>&#45;dom&#44; we&#45;&#45;long constrained to dwell in solitariness&#45;&#45;<lb/>are being brought forth to enjoy social intercourse with<lb/> the world at large.  In this blessed land especially<lb/> we meet our gentile neighbor in every walk of<lb/> life&#44; and exchange with him civilities and favors.<lb/>  Hence&#44; he is not unfrequently a visitor in our sanc&#45;<lb/>&#45;tuaries&#44; carefully noting the ceremonies of our ancient<lb/> creed.  Let him not&#44; I pray you&#44; for the sake<lb/> of our common cause&#44; depart hence prejudiced by reason<lb/> of a conduct ill&#45;comforting with the dignity of the worship.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>The Synagogue should not suffer in comparison<lb/> with the church.  Far be it from me to offer<lb/> a treacherous counsel&#45;&#45;the <sic>yeilding</sic> of our observances<lb/> to expediency&#45;&#45;.  No fear of derision should incite<lb/> us impiously to sever the connexion of the present<lb/> with the eventful past.  And you&#44; my Brethren&#33;<lb/>  Who have assumed the significant title of &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;the assembly<lb/> of Israel&#34; you will never be instrumental in dissolving<lb/> the bond of union among the scattered members of our<lb/> race.  Faithfully you will promise to strengthen it<lb/> by your adherence to ancestral practices.  You will<lb/> continue to address the Deity in the language of<lb/> inspiration.  You will appear before Him arrayed in<lb/> that robe&#44;  signif typical of your allegiance to the<lb/> kingdom of heaven.  You will read from the traditionally<lb/> written scroll of the law&#44; the duties binding upon the descendants<lb/> of the enfranchised slaves of Mr Egypt.  But all<lb/> this and whatever appertains to our sacred communions&#44;<lb/> let it be performed with impressiveness&#59; with striking<lb/> proper solemnity.  The stranger unacquainted with<lb/> our faith&#44; may perchance betray some astonishment.<lb/>  But he will not scoff at a worship&#44; which betokens<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>the sincerity of the suppliants.  Struck by the<lb/> deportment you exhibit&#44; he will exclaim &#34;Sublime<lb/> must be that religion&#44; whose votaries after the<lb/> lapse of many ages&#44; and despite untold vicissitudes&#44;<lb/> still bow to the same shrine&#44; and unswerveinglyedly follow<lb/> the sane rites.  You will have thus sanctified<lb/> your living saviour in the sight of all people&#44; and<lb/> you will have merited the title of &#34;righteous&#44;&#34; because<lb/> you rejoiced in the Lord&#44; and not in the gorgeousness<lb/> of a novel service &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            <p>Be not then at all concerned about the comparative<lb/> lowliness of this habitation.  The spirit of God descends&#44;<lb/> where the heart is turned heavenward.  No structure<lb/> can be likened in stateliness to that which adorned the capital of<lb/> Judea&#44; but it was delivered to the flames&#44; when it<lb/> ceased to represent the eternal principles of Sinai.<lb/>  These&#44; you should principally chiefly engross your attention.<lb/>  These you should cherish&#44; and be taught in by men<lb/> filled with ardent zeal for the Torah.  Know&#45;<lb/>&#45;ledge must be the staff of your religious support.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>You will then proceed cautiously.  You will learn<lb/> that to tear down the fence raised by our Sages&#44;<lb/> is to trample under foot the rarest flowers in<lb/> the garden entrusted to our guardianship.<lb/>  Aye&#58; my friends&#33;  The Synagogue should be the agency<lb/> alike of our edification and purification.  To that<lb/> high purpose it was destined from its origin&#44; and there&#45;<lb/>&#45;fore it has proved the mightiest link in the chain<lb/> that joins our nation indissolubly.  Keep it un&#45;<lb/>defiled.  Let not supineness&#44; nor negligence foist in<lb/> corruption.  No strange fire should be laid upon<lb/> the altar of our God.  Remember&#58; the joy which<lb/> reigned supreme at the dedication of the Tabernacle&#44;<lb/> turned to universal lamentation&#44; when the unwary<lb/> sons of Aaron presented an incense that God had not<lb/> commanded.  Oh&#33; may you ever rejoice in the Lord&#44; by<lb/> holding fast to that which He has enjoined.  Let<lb/> this spot you now consecrate&#44; attest hereafter the<lb/> sincerity of your professions.  Enter its portals<lb/> with thanksgivings&#59; its courts with praise.  Let<lb/> your own lips bless the name of God&#44; and ack&#45;<lb/>&#45;nowledge amid multitudes&#44; that He is good to Israel&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>and His faithfulness endureth from generation to<lb/> generation.  Let your youths find here wholesome<lb/> instruction to guide them through life&#44; the aged a<lb/> foretaste to the rest awaiting them above.  Let the<lb/> afflicted cast the burden of their sorrow at the foot<lb/> of this altar and be relieved.  Let all its attendants<lb/> be inspired by it with awe for the Creator&#44; with love for<lb/> His creatures&#44; with forbearance for the foibles inherent<lb/> in our nature&#44;&#45;&#45;frail and mortal beings as we are&#45;&#45;<lb/> so that they may learn to forgive&#44; as they hope to be<lb/> forgiven in the great day of judgment at the bar of the<lb/> Almighty Lord.<lb/></p>
            <p>And Thou spirit uncreated that pervadest the universe cast<lb/> a flood of light around this place&#44; and let the congregation &#34;Adath<lb/> Israel&#34; be illumined.  As this month was to our fathers<lb/> memorable for the descending of Thy glory on their Tabernacle&#44;<lb/> so may it be joyous unto those who now devote this<lb/> sanctuary in honor of Thee&#44; and as a testimony of their<lb/> enduring attachment to the revealed Law.  May<lb/> such be Thy gracious will.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
