<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF8_6</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff8_6_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff8_6_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff8_6_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff8_6_2v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 1 sheet<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For a funeral<lb/></p>
            <p>He is not dead.  The heart has ceased to beat throb&#44; but the senti&#45;<lb/>&#45;ments which quickened it&#44; vitalize&#44; eternize&#44; imparadise the<lb/> soul.  He is not dead&#44; who has cleaved to God.  Steadily he ad&#45;<lb/>&#45;vanced&#44; and soon reached the palace of the great King.  &#34;Lift up<lb/> your heads O ye gates&#44; and be raised up ye everlasting doors&#59; let the<lb/> righteous man enter.  Who is that righteous man&#63; a descendant and<lb/> disciple of Moses&#44; even Jacob Isaacs the Levite&#44; who &#34;loved his neighbor<lb/> like himself.&#34;  But does he in all truth deserve so eminent a title&#63;  Say<lb/> ye that have gathered round his decaying body.  Was the spirit which<lb/> animated it god&#45;like and purified&#63;  My sad feelings cannot so<lb/> darken my vision&#44; that I see not methinks.  I read in your countenances<lb/> the reflections of your a consonance of thoughts.  Aye&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;From the obsequies of the departed&#44; we may judge whether<lb/> he be the heir of heavenly bliss.&#34;  Those tears flowing from a multitude<lb/> are a tribute of respect paid to sterling goodness.  Because at the hour<lb/> that the soul of my friend left its tenement of clay&#44; charity was<lb/> bereft of a noble representation&#44; because you recognize in the<lb/> demise of this Israelite a loss to the community of his brethren&#44;<lb/> and to human society&#44; therefore you echo my lamentations.<lb/>  Command that a just God must needs have set apart a<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>vast reward for his deeds of kindness&#44; you still bewail<lb/> the departure of one who could ill be spared.  For the number of&#45;<lb/> of those who yearn for the unfortunate&#44; and lend a generous support<lb/> to every undertaking aiming at the alleviation of misery&#44; is not so<lb/> abundant.  Jacob Isaacs the Levite identified himself with the institutions<lb/> of beneficence established in our midst&#44; but to obey a divine instinct&#44;<lb/> ennobling his character&#44; he sought distress that he might relieve it.<lb/>  To speak to him of suffering&#44; was to engage his sympathies&#44; his<lb/> zealous cooperation in the cause of humanity.  To allude before him to<lb/> a plans by which want or shame might be averted from the mortals was to secure<lb/> his strong advocacy.  This leading feature in his demeanour&#44; won<lb/> for him our brother the love affectionate regard of his fellow men&#44; irrespective of race or creed.  He<lb/> loved his neighbor like himself&#44; and a reciprocity of feelings sprung up&#44;<lb/> as &#91;&#63;&#93; on the present melancholy occasion.  For this is not the<lb/> pageantry attending the funeral of an individual allied by chance to<lb/> some popular organizations.  The large concourse of people who<lb/> accompanied these mortal remains to their eternal resting place is a volun&#45;<lb/>&#45;tary a spontaneous declaration of the worth of the man&#44; whose untimely decease<lb/> deprives the needy and the afflicted of a friend indeed.<lb/></p>
            <p>But at the side of charity bemoaning by this coffin the loss of<lb/> her votary&#44; there stands also practical Judaism.  Jacob Isaacs the Levite<lb/> had not always proved himself its staunch adherent.  Like many<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>others&#44; he had&#44; inconsistently&#44; neglected to perform the tenets he<lb/> believed in.  But new ties and consequently new claims to his example<lb/> of a religious life&#44; wrought within his mind a change&#44; a happy change&#44;<lb/> for&#44; piety sustained and uplifted him mid trials of a severe nature.<lb/>  And Prayer assuaged his pains.  As his agonies grew in intensity&#44; his<lb/> devotions increased.  He A confiding trust in the Lord&#44; &#34;who doth not<lb/> afflict willingly&#34; became his soothing balm.  And if&#44; as we have<lb/> been taught by the Sages &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; &#34;bodily sufferings atone<lb/> for the sins of the flesh&#34; our much lamented brother can present before<lb/> the judgment&#45;seat of the Most High&#44; a spirit tenfold cleansed and<lb/> purified.  Relieved of the burden of human trespasses&#44; he can fly upon<lb/> the wings of righteousness to the heavenly Mansion.  He possesses<lb/> the mystic keys which will open its portals.  Faith and charity.<lb/>  &#34;Let him come in peace&#34; cry a host of archangels.  &#34;The limbs which<lb/> once moved by the direction of the will&#44; repose in their resting place earthly terrestrial abode.&#34;  But<lb/> the will itself&#44; the agent of the soul&#44; that led them on to uprightness<lb/> shall live and enjoy delights everlasting.&#34;  My departed<lb/> friend&#33;  Short was thy stay upon earth&#44; but more profitable<lb/> to thee&#44; than the long abiding here of the impious.  For thou<lb/> hast earned the means of securing an eternity of glory&#59;<lb/> they have been gathering fagots wherewith to consume their<lb/> future existence.  Soar then on high&#44; sainted being&#33;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>and when thou reachest the throne of the great king bend at its footstool to offer<lb/> at its footstool supplications for those who have been left in<lb/> this valley of tears.  Pray for the wife of thy youth&#44; she needs<lb/> a superhuman support in her bereavement&#59; she needs it to <sic>fulfil</sic> her task well&#58; to train the children<lb/> she bore unto thee&#44; as thou woulds that they be reared.<lb/>  Pray for thy disconsolate parents.  The absence of thy companionship<lb/> hands weighs them down with sorrow.  They submit to but they grieve exceedingly<lb/> over the divine decree that so soon summoned thee hence.  Pray for the<lb/> relatives&#44; whose unwearied and careful tending calmed thy agi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tation&#44; and eased thy pangs.  Pray for all thy friend&#44; who la&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment this separation&#44; that assisted from above&#44; they may<lb/> like thyself lay hold of faith and charity&#44; and essay to mount<lb/> the hill that leads to Beth&#45;El&#44; where righteousness is<lb/> crowned with never&#45;fading laurels.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
