<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Finzi, Ab.</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF2_10</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Finzi, Ab.</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_10_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_10_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_10_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_10_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_10_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_10_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_10_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_10_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_10_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_10_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_10_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_10_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_10_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_10_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_10_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_10_8v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_10_9r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_10_9v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>13 pages on 6 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>The prophetic blessing of Jacob<lb/></p>
            
            <p>Written by my friend<lb/>
                Ab Finzi<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            <p>&#34;So they read in the Book&#44; in the Law of God distinctly&#44; and they gave<lb/> the sense and caused them to understand the reading&#34;&#45;&#45;&#40;Nehemiah Chap. 8th. V. 8th.&#41;<lb/></p>
            <p>Dear Brethren.<lb/></p>
            <p>The veneration in which we hold the sacred writings&#44;<lb/> would greatly diminish in its value&#44; were it only passive&#44; or the mere effect<lb/> of an habitual example&#59; for to use a comparison&#59; whom do you believe<lb/> will be better impressed with awe and admiration for the work of God&#63;<lb/>  he&#44; who raising his eyes to the firmament&#44; sees in the stars so many spark&#45;<lb/>ling spots&#44; suspended above to illumine his nightly path&#44; or he who has<lb/> learnt their nature&#44; their system&#44; their various course through the space&#44; and<lb/> who beholds in them myriads of worlds ready to perform the task imposed on<lb/> them by their mighty Creator.&#45;&#45;  Will not the knowledge of the latter give him<lb/> a more sublime idea of the Deity and his boundless power&#44; than that which<lb/> the former possesses&#63;  Now we will arrive at the same conclusion with respect<lb/> to Holy Writ&#44; He who peruses it and admires the purity and loftiness of its<lb/> diction&#44; without diving into its meaning&#44; cannot certainly be on a par with<lb/> him who not content with the surface will search into its inward beauty.<lb/></p>
            <p>To these reflections which now strike our mind&#44; our ancestors must have also<lb/> been awake&#44; when they requested their generous leader Ezra to expound to them<lb/> the Law of God.&#45;&#45;Seventy years of Babylonian servitude had erased from<lb/> the mind of the majority the knowledge of the Hebrew language&#59; that of<lb/> Chaldea had superseded it&#59; They assembled within the walls of the Sanctuary<lb/> on their Sabbaths and Festivals to hear a portion of the Pentateuch&#44; but few<lb/> were those who could comprehend it in its original text.&#45;&#45;It then became<lb/> indispensable to resort to some means in order that the people might be<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>taught the duties contained in the Mosaic code&#44; hence we find that beside<lb/> Ezra the priest&#44; who was acknowledged as supreme chief of Israel&#44; and best<lb/> expositor of their Laws&#44; other eminent Jews&#44; like Joshua&#44; Shabbethai&#44; Iszabad&#44;<lb/> and their colleagues&#44; joined in elucidating the sacred pages to their brethren who<lb/> had returned from the captivity&#59; and so far they succeeded in their noble<lb/> vocation&#44; as to excise in many of them respect for their ancient institutions&#44;<lb/> and love for their Divine Author.&#45;&#45;  But this state of things&#44; which under<lb/> different circumstances would have been but temporary&#44; for a few years settle&#45;<lb/>ment in the Holy Land might have sufficed to revive the Hebrew tongue<lb/> among our predecessors&#44; was not the case with them.<lb/></p>
            <p>It would be unjust however to assert that this evil could be easily<lb/> obviated&#44; for many impediments militated against it.  Companies of a<lb/> large number of Israelites whose interest or connexions had induced them<lb/> to remain in Babylon&#44; even after the edict of Cyrus had been promulgated&#44;<lb/> occasionally returned to the countries of Judea&#59; They were totally ignorant<lb/> of the vernacular speech&#44; and lest their intercourse with the rest of their<lb/> Brethren should be impeded by that difficulty&#44; the Chaldaic language was necessarily<lb/> kept alive amidst our Nation.  Again&#59; you all know how eventful was the<lb/> history of our Fathers during the second Temple&#58; debarred at first by jealousy<lb/> from rebuilding that structure&#44; they had scarcely begun to re&#45;visit its sacred<lb/> Halls&#44; when hordes of foreign people invaded their cities&#44; their languages of<lb/> an entirely different nature&#44; when blended with the hebrews&#39;&#44; produced a<lb/> barbaric jargon which marred the purity of the latter.  But another<lb/> and a stronger obstacle unfortunately intervened against the diffusion of<lb/> the Holy tongue among our progenitors&#59; I mean their intermarriages with<lb/> idolatrous women&#59;  In vain did their leaders protest&#59; to no purpose they<lb/> excommunicated the perpetrators&#44; because they foresaw the baneful consequences<lb/> which would have accrued from that crime&#59; They disobeyed&#59; and their children<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>under the Tuition of their mothers&#44; were every day more estranged from the lan&#45;<lb/>guage of their forefathers&#44; Even as early as the time of Nehemiah&#44; we perceive<lb/> this awful sin predominating among our people&#44; Thus that man of God complains&#44;<lb/> &#34;In those days also saw I Jews that had married wives of Ashdot&#44; of<lb/> Amman and of Moab&#59; and their children spakehalf in the speech of Ashdot&#44; &#38;<lb/> the Jewish language they knew not&#44; but could speak according to the language<lb/> of each people.&#34;  Consequently to preserve against so many obstructions&#44; the<lb/> law of Sinai amidst Israel&#44; a clear exposition of the same was of paramount<lb/> necessity.  We have no written record of any version of the Bible previous<lb/> to the last dispersion&#44; but&#44; that there existed several we deduce from sundry<lb/> passages in the Talmud&#59; It is probable however as a modern Author of great<lb/> celebrity observes&#44; that these translations ranked under the same law relative to the<lb/> oral traditions&#44; which were to be learnt only by rote.&#45;&#45;But although the exposi&#45;<lb/>tors of the law had all adopted in their versions the Chaldaic&#44; on account of its<lb/> popularity&#44; yet it appears that they varied much in their translations&#44; each render&#45;<lb/>ing the sense of the text&#44; in the manner which he deemed the most explicit&#44; or<lb/> couching his language in a style that he esteemed the most elegant&#59; That these<lb/> discrepancies should have existed does not at all surprise us&#44; but that in process of<lb/> time they might have given rise to confusion as to the right understanding of the<lb/> Scriptures&#44; we can easily conceive&#59; To prevent it&#44; as well as to supply every teacher<lb/> with a standard whereby to facilitate the comprehension of the Five Books of<lb/> Moses.  The illustrious proselyte &#34;Onkelos&#44;&#34; who flourished some years after the<lb/> second dispersion&#44; submitted to the judgment of his preceptors R. Joshua &#38; R.<lb/> Eliezer&#44; a well digested interpretation of those sacred volumes&#44; which they lauded<lb/> and approved.  I do not assume to say that I have scanned the work of this<lb/> ancient teacher&#44; so as to be able to pronounce an impartial opinion&#44; nor do I feel<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>myself competent to do so&#44; but this much I can assert that it is so highly reputed<lb/> by the Israelites in general&#44; that in my native land&#44; each section of it is read<lb/> every week&#44; together with the original Hebrew.&#45;&#45;Thanks to this translation<lb/> of &#34;Onkelos&#34; our brethren who lacked knowledge in their primitive language&#44;<lb/> received through it&#39;s organ religious instruction touching their line of conduct as<lb/> Jews.  But a still greater advantage they derived from the same work&#58; it&#39;s<lb/> author did not&#44; like the major part of our modern translators&#44; adhere servilely<lb/> to the Text&#44; he hesitated not to deviate from it&#44; when he with his sagacious mind<lb/> perceived&#44; that to convey a right sense such a freedom was requisite.<lb/></p>
            <p>He for instance understood that in the lesson we have been perusing this<lb/> morning&#44; the forty ninth chapter if rendered according to the letter would be almost<lb/> incomprehensible&#44; for it is so concise&#44; so full of allegories&#44; and so very peculiar in<lb/> its expressions&#44; that no one unless deeply versed with our national vicissitudes&#44; could<lb/> dive into its real signification&#44; wherefore casting off the shackles of servility&#44;<lb/> he ranged through it without restraint&#44; and thereby shed light on many obscure<lb/> passages&#59;&#45;&#45;This example I have chosen to day to imitate&#44; and humbly will<lb/> I also submit to your judgment&#44; a paraphrase of the above named chapter&#44;<lb/> which I trust will facilitate its understanding&#59; It is not original&#44; for who can<lb/> boast of originality after the gigantic minds of hundreds of authors have been<lb/> employed in elucidating the Scriptures&#63; yet I can sincerely affirm that I have<lb/> laboured to select from the best commentaries the sentiments that I <sic>conscienciously</sic><lb/> believe to be the right&#44; and if while I recite it your will compare it with the<lb/> Hebrew text&#44; and will recall to your mind at the same time the events in which<lb/> subsequently our nation was involved&#44; and ot which I judge our Father Jacob<lb/> alluded&#44; I doubt not but many of you will coincide with my opinion.<lb/></p>
            <p>Beloved Brethren&#44; favor me with your attention.&#45;&#45;  The last<lb/> hour of Jacob&#39;s life having come near&#44; he sent for his Sons and thus addressed<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>them.&#45;&#45;  &#34;Gather your household together that I may relate what will happen<lb/> to you in future times&#59; Be assembled and listen ye children of Jacob and hear&#45;<lb/>ken to Israel your father.&#34;&#45;&#45;<lb/></p>
            <p>Reuben&#44; thou art my first son&#44; to whom the first produce of my labor&#44;<lb/> and the choice of my wealth appertained&#44; thine would also have been the supremacy<lb/> in sacerdotal dignity&#44; and thine the pre&#45;eminence in regal power&#44; but when wan&#45;<lb/>tonness stirred like as foaming waters&#44; impelled thee to an act which my soul<lb/> abhorreth &#40;Genesis Chap. 35. V. 22nd.&#41; honour &#38; dominion departed from thee&#44; thy right of<lb/> primogeniture devolved on Joseph&#44; to whom I have given a portion above his Brethren&#44;<lb/> and Judah the fourth of my Sons shall be invested with sovereign authority &#40;1st Chroni&#45;<lb/>cles Chap. 5th V. 1st &#38; 2nd&#41;</p>  
            <p>Simeon and Levi are allied in work of cruelty&#44; their weapons<lb/> are the ministers of their vengeance.  Wherefore I pray O God&#33; let not my Soul<lb/> be defiled by joining in their subtle devices&#44; nor my glory be lowered by uniting<lb/> with them&#44; when they design to perpetrate iniquities&#59; for it was in their irrepress&#45;<lb/>&#45;ible fury that they spilt the blood of men whom they enticed to enter the cove&#45;<lb/>nant&#58; and to gratify their selfwill they devastated a populous city &#40;Genesis Chap. 35th<lb/> V. 25th 28th &#38; 29th&#41;  May they never speed in their evil schemes&#44; may their violent im&#45;<lb/>pulses fail their directions&#44; and when the time shall be arrived for them to<lb/> share inheritance in the land of promise&#44; may their lot be totally <sic>seperated</sic>;<lb/> Let the territories of Simeon be intersected by Judah&#39;s possessions &#40;Joshua Chap. 19th<lb/> V. 1st.&#41; and let Levi dwell in forty eight cities interspersed among the tribes of<lb/> Israel.&#45;&#45;&#40;Joshua Chap. 21st V. 8th &#38; 41st&#41;&#45;&#45;<lb/></p>
            <p>But as for Judah&#44; his Brothers shall pay him a tribute of honour&#44; the<lb/> first to follow the Ark of the testimony&#44; his standard shall rank foremost<lb/> amongst the Banners of Israel&#44; &#40;Numbers Chap. 2nd V. 9th&#41; Him also shall the Almighty<lb/> choose to humiliate the arrogance of the Cananitish tribes&#44; in the day that his<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>sword shall mow down ten thousand of the enemies of the Lord in the city of<lb/> Bezek &#40;Judges Chap. 1st V. 2nd &#38; 4th&#41; and when the Royal Diadem shall be placed on the head<lb/> of the 1st king of his lineage &#40;2nd Samuel Chap. 5th V. 3rd&#41; and with the Lord at his right<lb/> hand he shall soar aloft.&#45;&#45;and when after repeated victories he shall sheath his<lb/> weapon and lie at rest&#44; like a lion returning from prey&#44; who shall rouse<lb/> him up&#63;  No human power will deprive him of the sceptre which he wields&#44;<lb/> he shall bequeath it to Shiloh &#40;from the root &#91;Hebrew&#93; to be tranquil&#41; the king of peace&#44; whom the<lb/> Lord will vouchsafe to call Shelomok&#44; for Shalom will reign in his days &#40;1st Chronicles<lb/> Chap. 22nd V. 9th&#41; and to him people from remote regions shall come to bow &#40;1st Kings Chap. 10th V. 21st&#41; and<lb/> Judah shall happily abide under his vine and under his fig&#45;tree all the days of<lb/> Solomon &#40;1st Kings Chap. 4th V. 25th&#41;.&#45;&#45;<lb/></p>
            <p>The inheritance of Zebulun shall fall unto Jared&#44; at the uttermost<lb/> border of the land of Judea &#40;Joshua Chap. 19th V. 10th V 11th&#41; bounded by the great Sea&#44; he shall<lb/> enrich himself by commercial intercourse with the Syrians and Phoenicians&#44; who<lb/> dwell at the foot of Lebanon in Sidon&#44; and whose laden ships shall convey to<lb/> him the treasures hid in the sand &#40;Deuteronomy Chap. 33rd V. 18th V. 19th&#41;.&#45;&#45;<lb/></p>
            <p>Not so with Issachar&#58; averse to mercantile pursuits&#44; for his soil will<lb/> bring forth abundance of good&#58; unskilful in battle&#44; for the knowledge of the Law<lb/> alone is his desire &#40;1st Chronicles Chap. 12th V. 32nd&#41; willingly will he pay a tribute to remain at<lb/> his fire&#45;side&#59; and even at the glorious epoch of the coronation of David&#44; when<lb/> thousands of his brethren arrayed in armour&#44; shall flock to Hebron to salute their<lb/> Sovereign and offer their aid&#44; two hundred only&#44; of his tribe will repair thither<lb/> unarmed &#40;1st Chronicles Chap 12th. V. 32nd.&#41;.&#45;&#45;<lb/></p>
            <p>Dan&#44; though he be the Son of a handmaid will be charged with a highly<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>important mission&#44; placed as the <sic>rereward</sic> of the whole Army of Israel&#44; he is to<lb/> avenge their cause on those who would fain impede their progress &#40;Numbers Chap 2nd. V. 31st&#41;<lb/> he will not allow the enemies to pursue their route&#44; but as the serpent twirls round<lb/> the body of his victim till vitality ceases&#44; and as the sting of the adder envenoms<lb/> man&#39;s channels of life&#44; in like manner will Dan twist his scourge round the<lb/> hoof of the courser&#44; that the rider may fall transfixed by his sword.&#45;&#45;  In so<lb/> perilous a task for the aid of his brethren&#44; may Heavenly help be at his side&#58;<lb/> It is in God that I trust for the salvation of Dan.  &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#40;is to be understood as an<lb/></p> <p>apostrophe&#41;.&#45;&#45;  Gad&#39;s location will be in the east beyond the Jordan &#40;Numbers<lb/> Chap. 32nd. V. 33rd.&#41; but from thence will he come with numerous troops to place himself at<lb/> the head of the tribes who shall divide heritage on the other side of the River&#44;<lb/> &#40;Joshua Chap. 4th. V. 12th.&#41;  He will not abandon them but faithful in his love for his brethren&#44;<lb/> he shall be the last to re&#45;visit his homestead after the entire conquest of Palestine<lb/> shall be accomplished &#40;Joshua Chap. 22nd V. 9th.&#41;<lb/></p>
            <p>Luxuriantly will the olive&#45;trees grow in the country of Asher&#44; distant<lb/> people shall wend their way to that fertile land in quest of its sweet product&#44; On<lb/> the delicacies of his soil Kings and princes will fare&#44; and they shall pour their<lb/> gold into his Treasuries &#40;Talmud&#44; Treatise Menahot Solis 85&#41;.<lb/></p>
            <p>I behold Naphtali like a speedy hind&#44; ready to fly to battle at the first<lb/> summons of the Prophetess&#44; and on the summit of Mount Tabor he jeopardises<lb/> his life to dart his shafts against the redoubtable host of Jabin &#40;Judges Chap. 4th. V. 14.&#41;<lb/>  He has routed it&#33; freedom is restored to Israel&#33; and joyfully he joins Deborah<lb/> in the language of the Poets to celebrate the wondrous deeds of the Lord &#40;Judges Chap.<lb/> 5th. V. 1st.&#41;.&#45;&#45;  How beautiful is Joseph&#44; my beloved Son&#33; like<lb/> the branch of a fruit&#45;bearing tree incessantly watered&#59; like the shoot of a Tree<lb/> widely spread&#44; whose boughs extend along the wall.&#45;  And though Slavery em&#45;<lb/>&#45;bittered his life&#44; though perfidious calumny pierced his heart like Arrows&#44; though<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>the unjust hatred of his brethren aimed at his destruction&#44; yet he desponded not&#44;<lb/> assured of God&#39;s protection&#44; his moral courage remained unflagged &#91;inserted above&#58; unshaken&#93;; and by this<lb/> faith in the Divine mercy he acquired new power&#44; for the hands of the mighty<lb/> one of Jacob were Mended to him&#44; they raised him high in the land of his<lb/> bondage&#44; where he became the nourisher&#44; the corner&#45;stone of the House of Israel&#44;<lb/> &#40;Genesis Chap 45th v. 7th&#41;  O may the same God of thy Father never withdraw his help<lb/> from thee O my Joseph&#33; may the Almighty bless thee with propitious rains&#44; and<lb/> fertile irrigations&#59; May thou never shed tears over the unripe death of thy<lb/> children&#44; nor lament the premature birth of thy offspring.  Grant O God&#33;<lb/> that the blessings which thou didst vouchsafe to confer on me&#44; when I was made<lb/> confident of thy perpetual aid&#44; when it was declared to me that I should spread<lb/> abroad to the west and to the East&#44; to the North and to the South&#44; which promise<lb/> exceeded all those conferred on my progenitors &#40;Genesis Chap. 28th. V. 14th&#41; Grant O God&#33; that<lb/> these valuable blessings may be realized on Joseph&#44; and rest on the crown of the<lb/> head of him whom his Brothers recognized as their superior.<lb/></p>
            <p>The morning dawn of independence from foreign yoke shall break<lb/> forth over the hills of Benjamin&#44; for out of his tribe the first monarch of Israel<lb/> shall spring&#59; &#40;1st. Samuel Chap. 9th. V. 1st. &#38; 2nd&#41; he like a ravenous wolf shall spread terror<lb/> abroad&#44; he will also share the booty of the inveterate foes of the Hebrews&#44; and with<lb/> his might will consolidate his people into a compact Nation &#40;1st Saml. Chap. 14th V. 46th<lb/> 47th &#38; 48th&#41; But even when the Sun shall set in the horizon of Israel&#44; and on the<lb/> willows of Babylon the exiles of Judea shall hang their harps&#59; a man out<lb/> of Benjamin shall rise to their help&#58; he will rescue them from the foul<lb/> machinations of a wily minister&#44; whose property he shall inherit&#59; then tran&#45;<lb/>quility shall ensue&#44; for Mordecai the Benjamite when elevated to power will seek<lb/> the welfare of his people and promote the peace of all his seed &#40;Esther Chap. 10th V. 3rd&#41;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>The following 6 verses which complete the Chapter&#44; are too obvious to require<lb/> any further comment.<lb/></p>
            <p>But ere I dismiss this subject&#44; from which&#44; though inadequately<lb/> treated&#44; you may have derived some useful information&#44; I will even at the risk<lb/> of being taxed with presumption&#44; boldly put to you a question.  Brethren&#33; do<lb/> you believe that the perusal of the English or any other modern version of the<lb/> Bible&#44; could have enlightened you on this obscure chapter of Genesis&#44; or that<lb/> they are able to unfold to you the recondite sense of many other pages of the<lb/> inspired writings&#63;  You will answer that it is not your province to employ<lb/> your time to that effect&#59; Let them you will say whose mind is entirely devoted<lb/> to literary researches&#44; pursue that study&#44; enough for us if we can recite and<lb/> comprehend our habitual prayers.&#45;&#45;  But&#44; dear friends will it be through a<lb/> knowledge so scanty that you shall learn the truths of God&#39;s holy word as<lb/> revealed to his Servants the Prophets&#63; will it be through so poor a knowledge<lb/> that your faith shall become enlightened&#63;  You know&#44; and it would be<lb/> useless to conceal it&#44; that the very predictions on which we base our future<lb/> destination&#44; have become weapons in the hands of our opponents&#44; they strive to<lb/> convince us that all those consoling promises that have cheered the heart of<lb/> Israel amidst a gloomy thraldom&#44; have long since been fulfilled&#44; that we<lb/> can hope for redemption by only flinging aside &#40;to use their language&#41; the<lb/> veil which dims our sight.  And how shall we be able to produce arguments<lb/> against arguments&#44; how can we prove the fallacy of their reasonings&#44; unless<lb/> endowed with a deeper knowledge than that which they possess&#63;  And<lb/> whence shall we draw this knowledge&#44; if we have not recourse to those vene&#45;<lb/>rated volumes of our pious predecessors&#44; whose profound learning has thrown<lb/> a new and lovelier brilliancy upon the sacred pages&#63;  The productions of<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>Abarbanel&#44; of Kimhi&#44; of Maimonides&#44; who have emphatically and suc&#45;<lb/>cessfully defended the cause of Judaism&#44; are unknown to us&#44; and yet<lb/> although a blush will mount to our face when we have to acknowledge it<lb/> to our Brethren of different creeds&#44; nevertheless we cannot summon energy<lb/> to amend our past heedless course&#44; to remove this ignorance from among<lb/> us by providing betimes for the religious instruction of a future generation.<lb/></p>
            <p>Our hearts did glow with joy when we heard that a hebrew<lb/> school was about to be established&#44; and when we saw at its directions men<lb/> of indefatigable zeal&#44; we with sanguine hope watched its progress&#44; antici&#45;<lb/>pating a continual concourse of scholars&#44; and a liberal pecuniary aid from<lb/> our public.&#45;&#45;  But alas&#33; that our expectations have hitherto been frustrated&#33;<lb/> the efforts of few are crippled by the inertness of many&#59; and whereas a compa&#45;<lb/>ratively small contribution by the whole community&#44; would have enabled<lb/> this school in a short period to keep pace with other institutions of this en&#45;<lb/>lightened metropolis&#44; and encouraged its directors to take measures for a superior<lb/> education in the hebrew department&#59;&#45;&#45;we now apprehend quite a contrary<lb/> result&#44; yes we fear our children will have also to reproach their parents<lb/> for their want of knowledge in the language of their ancestors&#59; Let it not<lb/> be so beloved hearers&#59; It is&#44; believe me for a very sacred cause that I wish to<lb/> enlist your sympathies&#59; nay&#44; this dwelling of God where we worship&#44; these<lb/> scrolls of the Law which we revere&#44; are held by our Sages in a minor degree of<lb/> sanctity than religious schools erected for the promotion of the word of God<lb/> among the faithful.&#45;&#45;Let me then entreat you with all the power of my<lb/> soul&#44; give us heartily a helping&#45;hand tow&#39;rds the attainment of so great&#44; so<lb/> holy an end&#44; skew to our fellow&#45;men of different belief that we alive to this<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>essential object of rearing our children as it <sic>behoves</sic> the descendants of our<lb/> pious Father Jacob&#58; Let our united labour prove to our brethren in distant<lb/> lands that we also like them cherish the memorial of our Prophets and<lb/> of our Teachers&#59; not only by adhesion to their directions&#44; but by disseminating<lb/> their learning among all classes of our people&#44; then&#44; and then alone&#44; we may<lb/> consider ourselves the true <sic>worshippers</sic> of God&#44; for we shall have learnt to<lb/> obey his immutable word in spirit as well as in outward form&#59; then we<lb/> shall be Israelites without guile for we shall have taught our offspring<lb/> to glorify the blessed name name of the Lord&#59; we shall have kindled in their<lb/> soul the inextinguishable light of truth&#59; it will guide their path&#44; it will<lb/> save them from external temptations&#59; it will render them dutiful children&#44;<lb/> loving husbands&#44; faithful citizens &#38; zealous Jews&#59; then the Almighty God<lb/> will pour his spirit upon our seed&#44; and his blessing upon our offspring&#59;<lb/> &#34;And they shall spring up as among grass&#44; and as willows by the water<lb/> courses.&#34;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            <p>Almighty God&#33;  Blessed be thou when thou <sic>benefitted</sic> us&#44;<lb/> blessed be thou when thou inflictest punishment&#59; Teach us only our<lb/> Father to appreciate the former&#44; and receive the latter as a condign<lb/> retribution of our deeds&#58;&#45;&#45;but when we have humbled our spirit and<lb/> come to thee for mercy&#45;&#45;do not O Lord&#33; withhold it from us.&#45;&#45;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p>Truly distressed are we now heavenly Creator&#33; for the cry of many<lb/> has rent our hearts&#44; we have beheld Sons mourning for their cherished mothers&#44;<lb/> Parents bewailing over the loss of their dear children&#44; beloved wives that of<lb/> their loving husbands&#58; we have viewed the fruit of honest labor suddenly<lb/> devoured&#44; and the work of industry blighted by calamities.<lb/></p>
            <p>Gracious God&#33; let this our fervent prayer reach thy Throne&#44; and<lb/> accept Thou it according to thy endless goodness.  Bid the messenger<lb/> of thy wrath slay his hand&#44; bind up the wounds which death has opened&#44;<lb/> and they shall speedily heal&#45;&#45;Remove from us sadness and sorrow&#58;<lb/> guard us from pestilence&#44; from indigence&#44; and from fatal occurrences.<lb/>  Let the light of thy countenance shine on the mourners and on the sick&#44;<lb/> and grief will disappear.  O grant us our petition thou fountain of<lb/> blessing&#44; and we shall sing thy praises in the land of the living for a<lb/> length of days.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
