<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF19_9</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_9_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_9_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_9_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_9_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_9_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_9_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_9_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_9_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_9_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_9_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_9_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_9_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_9_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_9_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_9_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_9_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>On cooperative work<lb/>
                in educational institutions<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  If even all Jewish parents habitually<lb/> engaged private teachers to instruct their children<lb/> in the Hebrew language&#44; in the reading and meaning<lb/> of the accepted prayers&#44; and the history of Holy Writ&#44;<lb/> I still would still advocate the establishment of religious<lb/> schools.  The emulation which those are apt to create&#44;<lb/> sufficiently warrants their existence.  The Sages of our people<lb/> showed evinced a right appreciation of such institutions&#44; for&#44;<lb/> while admitting that from a Biblical point of view it<lb/> behooves parents themselves to train their offspring into<lb/> a knowledge of the Torah&#44; as we read &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Ye shall teach them unto your children&#44;&#34; nevertheless they<lb/> entered into details about the system that should be<lb/> followed at schools&#44; the arranging of the classes and<lb/> the promotion of pupils.  The Talmudists recognized<lb/> the fact that not every father has the capacity or<lb/> leisure to perform his tuitionary obligation.  To guard<lb/> therefore against the possibility of raising a generation<lb/> in ignorance of religion&#44; the Rabbis ordered that no city<lb/> where Jews live dwell should be destitute in want of school houses.<lb/>  I need not add that they And all have heard that our Sages claim a higher degree of sanctity<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>for the humble rooms where the hearts and minds of<lb/> our successors are fashioned in a Jewish mould&#44; than for<lb/> the most gorgeously built synagogues.  Very interesting<lb/> it is to read the history and of the gradual spreading<lb/> of scholastic educational institutions in Judea&#44; and of the dif&#45;<lb/>&#45;ficulties and prejudices overcome before they grew into<lb/> popular favor.  For&#44; like in our own days so in the days of antiquity&#44; new ideas&#44; however sound made a slow progress in the days of antiquity. A wise provision howeve of the Talmud was that which<lb/> required of parents ordinarily to send their children to<lb/> religious schools ordinarily not later than when their little<lb/> ones had reached their seventh year&#59; for at that<lb/> age the teacher can enforce gently command discipline&#44; and the<lb/> pupils will receive such impression as are likely<lb/> to be lasting.  Now&#44; Brethren&#44; if in<lb/> times when many a father considered it binding<lb/> upon himself to teach his own children&#44; and many<lb/> a family hired a private instructor&#44; religious schools were<lb/> earnestly recommended and extensively established&#44;<lb/> how stronger the reason for their existence is in our<lb/> days times&#44; when most fathers voluntarily&#44; or unavoidably<lb/> perhaps&#44; have shaken off a god&#45;given responsibility&#44;<lb/> and exceptional are the instances in which a salaried teacher at home supplies their neglect&#63;<lb/>  is supplied by a salaried teacher at home&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>I may be told that the want is filled by Congregational<lb/> schools&#59; that these keep up a knowledge of what I<lb/> have described as deem essential for the preservation of pu&#45;<lb/>&#45;blic worship and of for a correct understanding of<lb/> Judaism.  But personal observation has forced on<lb/> my mind the unbiased conviction that the central object in<lb/> the majority of those schools is a drilling of the<lb/> young for the confirmation&#45;&#45;a meaningless word&#44; foreign<lb/> to our belief.  Few are the attendants who issue<lb/> from them such these schools fully prepared to resist the materialism<lb/> of our age by the spirit of our faith&#59; exceedingly few<lb/> these the attendants whose acquaintance with Hebrew&#44; qualifies them<lb/> to resist the become live participants in the Divine<lb/> Services.  So evident are the defects of which<lb/> I speak&#44; that a minister prominent in the school<lb/> of &#34;Reform&#34; has been loud in his complaints&#44; and has<lb/> proposed to defer the confirmation to the sixteenth<lb/> or seventeenth year of the confirmants in the hopes that previous teaching culture<lb/> will give then the ceremony will have then some reality and spiritual<lb/> efficacy.  But inasmuch as to combine the culti&#45;<lb/>&#45;vation of the Bible language with the study learning of the Bible<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>history and doctrines is a task growing every day<lb/> more difficult by reason of a multiplicity of secular studies&#44; and a striving after accomplishments&#44; a strong tendency&#44; is exhibited to<lb/> substitute English for Hebrew in the worship.  Already<lb/> one Congregation at Rochester has introduced the change<lb/> &#38; at Cincinnati&#44; where the Union college was avowedly<lb/> established in the interest of Hebrew lore&#44; and where its<lb/> president has compiled his &#34;Minhag America&#34; mainly in<lb/> Hebrew&#44; a pressure is being brought about to the same<lb/> end effect.  A late announcement informs the public that<lb/> all Hebrew will be eliminated&#44; leaving in their primitive<lb/> language only the Shemang and a few more familiar<lb/> passages in the liturgy.  Thus at a fell swoop is the work of Ezra<lb/> is carried away. at a fell swoop For that new<lb/> Moses and his colaborers&#44; with a singleness of thought<lb/> directed to the unification of our people&#44; formulated<lb/> prayers in Hebrew&#44; when the Aramaic or Chaldaic<lb/> was the vernacular tongue&#44; and ordered the reading of<lb/> the Torah at Synagogues in the original text&#44; allowing<lb/> an interpreter verbally to explain its meaning in the<lb/> absence of printing&#44; which was then unknown.  They Our wise hearted<lb/> guides of old would that the Hebrew might continue to remain the national<lb/> language&#44; the &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; the sacred tongue of&#44; the medium<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>of communion with Israel&#39;s God&#44; and of intercom&#45;<lb/>&#45;munion among Israel&#39;s preceptors.  In it wrote Jeshua<lb/> Ben Sira his excellent admirable books of morals after the close of the Scriptural canon&#59; in it were written other<lb/> books volumes of the Apocrypha&#44; written&#44; according to the testimony<lb/> of Origen and Jerome&#44; early fathers of the Christian church.<lb/>  In it has the Mishna or oral law been handed down<lb/> to posterity&#59; in it the Jewish poets of Moorish Spain<lb/> gave us their matchless supplicatory effusions&#44; and in it parents&#44;<lb/> or their tuitionary substitutes trained the young&#44; till even within the first<lb/> quarter of the present century.  But now it Hebrew has<lb/> been relegated to into the possession of Christians.  They cherish it&#44; and diffuse<lb/> its knowledge&#44; they unearth a wealth of learning which<lb/> we despise&#44; but which is ours treasure&#44; deposited lying hidden in ancient<lb/> libraries.  Not long ago&#44; a very scholarly<lb/> colleague of mine who was in Philadelphia on a visit&#44;<lb/> deprecated in my presence the ignorance of Hebrew among<lb/> our youths&#44; and declared it a loss danger to our solidarity and a shame&#44; but I was<lb/> reluctantly impelled to charge the Reform school&#44;<lb/> to which that minister belongs&#44; with the prevailing<lb/> evil&#44; for that school has made the study of the Bible<lb/> language unnecessary&#44; since the worship it variously formulated has been virtually<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>reduced to various polyglot hymnal service sung by a mixed choir of paid<lb/> Jews and gentiles&#44; and to a sermon more or less Jewish<lb/> in its aim and character.<lb/></p>
            <p>But do we ourselves the pretentious miscalled conservatives contribute to the preservation of<lb/> the language which possessed so merited a value<lb/> in the eyes of our fathers&#44; and invisibly an but po&#45;<lb/> &#45;tently knit marvelously welded our scattered race together&#63;  I must have<lb/> shocked a member of my congregation whom I accidentally<lb/> net last week.  I urged was urging him to see to the education of<lb/> his children&#44; and I begged that he would let them&#44; while<lb/> young&#44; associated with their coevals of the Jewish faith&#44; and<lb/> be taught the language of our public prayers.  He inter&#45;<lb/>&#45;rupted me by saying&#44; that his oldest would before long<lb/> become Bar Mitzvah&#44; and therefore it might be advisable<lb/> to have him prepared for the occasion.  at that Whereupon I simply remarked&#58;<lb/> &#34;that is the least&#34; &#34;Why&#44;&#34; he answered&#44; as if surprised &#34;Do you mean to say<lb/> that the ceremony is of no account&#63;&#34;  &#34;No&#44;&#34; I rejoined&#58;<lb/> &#34;No&#44; whenever a preliminary education&#44; which ought to begin<lb/> as early as the child&#39;s power of observation mental development begins&#44; to develop&#44; has fitted<lb/> the lad for an intelligent rendering of a chapter of the Torah&#44;<lb/> and an appreciation of the words addressed to him<lb/> from the pulpit.  But when nothing Jewish in its<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>letter form and in its spirit has been previously shown<lb/> imparted&#44; then the Bar Mitzvah ceremony is indeed<lb/> a misapplication of the Rabbinical ordinance.  It misleads<lb/> &#45;ing to the lad&#59; and allusive it is a delusion to his parents.&#34;  My Brethren.<lb/>  It is to An eager wish to help in the dissemination<lb/> of Hebrew knowledge and Hebrew doctrines that gave origin to our<lb/> free schools.  owe their origin Yet&#44; the number of<lb/> pupils who avail themselves of thereof endeavours of public spirited Philadelphians does by no means<lb/> represent the large Jewish population&#44; unattached to<lb/> any congregation&#44; and for whose benefit these institutions<lb/> were chiefly established.  Our Sunday schools do<lb/> draw an attendance to which we might point with<lb/> a hearty satisfaction&#44; if the instruction inclination of the<lb/> young ones to enter the classes&#44; was encouraged by the<lb/> gratuitous teaching of their elders.  I did not disguise<lb/> upon on Sunday last the painful sensation I experienced<lb/> on entering the Southern school.  The new superin&#45;<lb/>&#45;tendent&#44; who&#44; kindly responding to a sense of duty&#44; her her own laudable promptings&#44; assumed an onerous office on<lb/> trial&#44; was trying doing her utmost to overcome <sic>insuferable</sic><lb/> difficulties&#45;&#45;to supply instruction for classes without<lb/> instructors&#44; to maintain order among scores of boys&#44;<lb/> disorderly by the reason of the lack of teachers&#44; to supervise<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>the infant school in an upper room&#44; while her<lb/> presence was needed in the lower rooms&#44; and to<lb/> make the usual weekly record of matters connected<lb/> with the institution.  It is not my<lb/> purpose&#44; nor would it be sensible to chide and to<lb/> censure.  But for the sake of this cause&#44; and as I<lb/> sincerely think that Sunday schools prevent a<lb/> stagnation of the Jewish sentiment&#59; as I believe<lb/> that&#44; though not of immediate advantage to Hebrew<lb/> learning culture&#44; Sunday Schools by bringing our little ones together&#44; foster mutual attachment<lb/> among all classes of Israelites&#44; by the act of bringing<lb/> our little ones to gather&#44; and that by imparting Bible<lb/> lessons in the vernacular&#44; they furnish our rising gene&#45;<lb/>&#45;ration with arms of defense against apostasy or<lb/> atheism&#44; therefore I again appeal to my hearers<lb/> in all earnestness.  Brothers and sisters in faith.<lb/>  Do not suffer the Southern Sunday School to go fall<lb/> into decay.  Within a short distance from thence&#44;<lb/> the Bedford a mission school is in active operation full<lb/> of vim and vigour.  Those who lend it time&#44; mind<lb/> and means&#44; do not stop to inquire into the character<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>of the locality.  On the contrary&#44; the lowlier<lb/> the surroundings&#44; the stronger is the incentive to<lb/> labor zealously in order to lift them up to social purification.<lb/>  We may profit by the example of men and women<lb/> who&#44; mistakenly but honestly&#44; seek to attract our child&#45;<lb/>&#45;ren into their folds&#44; and who would rejoice at the closing<lb/> of our Southern Sunday School.  At one time we raised<lb/> a double wall against our religious opponents&#45;&#45;our<lb/> Sunday Schools in the morning&#44; and our Sewing schools<lb/> in the afternoon.  Must I lament the extinction<lb/> of the latter&#63;  The fall season is nearly at end <sic>end</sic>&#44;<lb/> and no indication of an effort to resume has been<lb/> yet shown.  If the children whom I lately saw<lb/> waiting in anxious expectation at the doors of the Hebrew<lb/> Education society school for the reopening of a sewing<lb/> school&#44; are lured into away&#45;&#45;If they enter christian institutions of the same<lb/> nature&#44; and learn to sing praises to a man&#45;god<lb/> in the hopes of receiving gifts at his supposed natal day&#44;<lb/> our culpable negligence will be accountable for the<lb/> offense against the One uncreated God of Israel.<lb/>  I grieve&#44; my Brethren&#44; when I reflect that the love<lb/> of ease is so much stronger in us than the love of religion.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>In moments of noble enthusiasm we undertake<lb/> what will further a sacred object&#44; but soon is our<lb/> ardor dampened.  Obstacles which we meet&#44; and which<lb/> we magnify&#44; personal likes and dislikes&#44; the idea<lb/> that others may be found more able&#44; or who are abler than we&#44; or can commanding<lb/> more leisure&#44; are the ill&#45;advisers that hinder the<lb/> inscribing of our names in the book of the righteous.<lb/>  Oh&#33; that we would realize our capacities&#33;  Singly we may<lb/> accomplish nothing&#44; but if we join our forces&#44; the<lb/> weak fl feeblest in our midst may do Judaism blessed<lb/> services.  Let me tell it in the Bible language&#58;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;the weak must say&#44; &#34;I am strong&#34;&#33;  &#34; I will<lb/> let a sense of obligation to the Lord I worship infuse<lb/> into me an irresistible will to take part in whatever<lb/> promotes the welfare of Israel&#44; educationally&#44; charitably<lb/> congregationally.  What I was wont to call &#34;inconvenience&#34;<lb/> I shall deem a pleasure&#44; stumbling blocks in my way&#44; shall will<lb/> be removed by a united power&#44; and I shall enjoy the<lb/> delight of having labored contemplating the solid foundations of my people&#39;s<lb/> progress.&#34;  Brothers and sisters in faith.  Let the coming winter<lb/> &#38; spring see us all engaged in that holy undertaking.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
