<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF2_7</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1867" source="" attested="yes">1867</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_7_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_7_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_7_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_7_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_7_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_7_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_7_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_7_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_7_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_7_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_7_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_7_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_7_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_7_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_7_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_7_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>7</p>
            
            <p>Messrs<lb/>
                For the 7th anniversary<lb/>
                of the Synagogue<lb/>
                in 7th st<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  I have an announcement to make&#44; and yet I hesi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tate to deliver it.  My feelings are at variance.  Duty says&#58;<lb/> speak fearlessly&#44; for&#44; your intentions are good.  Prudence&#44; or&#44;<lb/> to call it by its own name&#44; expediency&#44; advices silence.  I have been<lb/> therefore debating in my mind what course to follow.  Knowing<lb/> how apt we all are to misjudge&#44; I would spare myself the<lb/> mortification of having given occasion to a wrong construction of<lb/> my motives.  On the other hand&#44; as I have been entrusted with<lb/> a religious mission&#44; I conceive that I would be guilty of inexcusable<lb/> selfishness&#44; if to avoid vexation&#44; I neglected its <sic>fulfilment</sic>.<lb/>  As you see&#44; I am truly &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;halting between two opinions&#34;<lb/> between that formed by cool reflection&#44; and that which conscience<lb/> tacitly expresses.  But the latter has a much greater weight than the former<lb/> It I must heed&#44; regardless of consequence.  Well then&#44;<lb/> my hearers&#33;  Let it be known unto all of you&#44; that this<lb/> Synagogue has just completed its seventh year&#44; and it<lb/> has not yet become the house of God.  I do not aim at<lb/> creating a sensation.  I state actual facts.  This Synagogue<lb/> is not yet the house of our God.  And I will prove it.<lb/>  I turn to the page sin the book of Exodus&#44; which record<lb/> the dedication of the Tabernacle&#44; and there I read that<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>men vied with each other in endowing that edifice with<lb/> their bountiful gifts.  Nay&#44; women gladly parted with the<lb/> polished steel&#44; which&#44; in those ancient days&#44; served them as a<lb/> mirror&#44; in order that it might be used for a holy purpose.<lb/>  Spontaneously and with boundless generosity the people<lb/> offered&#44; with the view that the building in which the Lord<lb/> was to be <sic>worshipped</sic>&#44; might lack neither beauty nor support.<lb/>  Therefore was the Tabernacle properly called &#34;the house of<lb/> the Eternal God&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  I search further<lb/> into historical events&#44; and I find that the renowned Temple<lb/> set up on mount Moriah&#44; was the witness of a spirit of<lb/> unequalled liberality&#59; that king David in his utterance of<lb/> thanksgivings&#44; acknowledges&#44; that he was not alone in laying<lb/> aside treasures for the rearing of that long&#45;contemplated struc&#45;<lb/>&#45;ture and its maintenance&#44; but that many&#44; though need&#45;<lb/>&#45;lessly&#44; brought the choicest objects they possessed&#44; as tokens<lb/> of their devotional sentiments.  Therefore was the Temple<lb/> rightly called &#34;the house of God&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  And even<lb/> at a still later period&#44; when a remnant of Judah&#44; frew<lb/> and poor&#44; hailed again the ancestral land&#44; they could gather<lb/> means to raise the Sanctuary from its ruins&#44; and enrich it<lb/> with voluntary contributions.  Therefore was also the second<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Temple fitly called &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;the house of God&#44; that<lb/> is&#44; the God of Israel.&#34;  Contrast now&#44; my Brethren&#33; the condi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion of this devoted spot with those&#44; in which our ancestors<lb/> poured forth their entreaties&#44; and say whether it is likewise<lb/> entitled to the name they bore.  I may be ridiculed&#44;<lb/> according to prevailing ideas&#44; but I contend that the dwelling in<lb/> which I reside&#44; is not exclusively my own&#44; so long as any<lb/> one can exact of me a sum yet left unpaid&#44; or compel<lb/> the disposing of the premises to meet the demand.<lb/>  Is it then an honor to our God&#44; that such should precisely be<lb/> the state of this habitation&#44; avowedly hallowed to His service&#63;<lb/>  Is it an honor to you&#44; I will ask&#44; who having the ability&#44; refuse<lb/> to place this Synagogue above all contingencies&#63;  I know<lb/> your answer&#44; and can anticipate it.  &#34;The circumstance you<lb/> apprehend cannot possibly happen&#44; for the pledge into which<lb/> the congregation have entered&#44; will ever be faithfully redeemed&#44;<lb/> and no one shall dislodge us hence.  You may therefore dismiss<lb/> at once those sombre thoughts form your mind.&#34;  Now&#44; Brethren.<lb/>  I insist that even if the case were&#45;&#45;beyond all unforseen and<lb/> unthought of casualties&#45;&#45;&#44; as you have described it still it would<lb/> be an insult to the Almighty&#44; to allow any human being<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>to own a portion&#44; however small&#44; of his sacred abode.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93; says the Sage of the Mishn&#225;h.<lb/>  All we claim as ours&#44; even our own existence&#44; is a gift at<lb/> His divine hands.  Shouldwe then let strangers to our faith&#44;<lb/> boast of having a title to a mansion&#44; of which we&#44; pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;fessedly&#44; made the Donor of all good a present&#44; because we<lb/> in all reality will not give Him a little of our superfluities&#63;  But in&#45;<lb/>&#45;dependent of this serious consideration&#58; can we be so certain<lb/> that our moral obligation will always be discharged&#63;  It must<lb/> be in the recollection of all my hearers&#44; that at one time&#44;&#45;&#45;and<lb/> that not many years ago&#45;&#45;&#44; the treasury of this congregation was<lb/> very night exhausted&#44; and great difficulty was experienced<lb/> in preventing the unfortunate event&#44; which that fact threatened<lb/> to bring on.  What has once come to pass&#44; may occur a second time with a more discreditable issue&#44; and you will have doubly sinned against God&#44; because<lb/> warned by experience&#44; you scorned its lessons.  Indeed&#44; my<lb/> Brethren&#33;  Averse as I am to communicate to you the misgi&#45;<lb/>&#45;vings I entertain&#44; I cannot forbear pointing out some of<lb/> the causes which depress my spirits.  I see a gradual<lb/> waning of our numerical strength.  The void created by<lb/> the decease of some of our members or by their non&#45;attendance through age&#44; has not been filled of by<lb/> their offspring.  They who weekly <sic>worshipped</sic> at this shrine<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>when young&#44; are&#45;&#45;with few honorable exceptions&#44; absent at all<lb/> times&#44; now that they have reached manhood.  Some&#44; again&#44;<lb/> have left our city&#44; and some have&#44; for reasons of their own&#44;<lb/> become attached to other Synagogues.  All this&#44; I acknowledge&#44;<lb/> may happen elsewhere&#44; as well as among us&#44; but not with the<lb/> same results.  If a hundred quit a community of Ashkena&#45;<lb/>&#45;zim Israelites&#44; a thousand among those who emigrate to this<lb/> country&#44; will swell up the its ranks.  Not so with us.  Our<lb/> ritual and pronunciation of the Hebrew language will<lb/> not attract many of our fellow&#45;believers&#44; who are unac&#45;<lb/>&#45;customed to the same.  They will naturally join those who adhere<lb/> to a form with which they are most familiar&#44; while scar&#45;<lb/>&#45;cely any&#44; educated in ours&#44; take up their residence in our midst.<lb/>  We cannot therefore depend upon a large accession of<lb/> number&#44; and through it on our ability to liquidate a debt&#44; offensive<lb/> to the Lord&#44; by the accumulated surplus of our annual<lb/> revenue.  For my part&#44; I would feel truly happy&#44;<lb/> if we could but retain those who have long followed the Sephardic<lb/> Minhag&#58; if we could but induce them to watch at these<lb/> portals&#44; and evince a lively interest in the welfare of<lb/> their Synagogue&#33;&#44; now alas&#33; so neglected.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>I was much pained when during last winter every Sabbath<lb/> exhibited new vacant seats.  But the air of genial spring<lb/> did not breathe into my brothers in faith&#44; a wish to revisit<lb/> these courts of the Lord&#59; while the summer&#45;&#45;I know&#45;&#45;will find them<lb/> far away from a place where the word of God is listened to<lb/> and obeyed.  The autumnal season will see them return&#44;<lb/> but the days in which they will seek the face of the King<lb/> who delights in the gathering of His prayful servants &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> will not equal in number those which they spent in sp seeking pleasure.<lb/>  I was not aware&#44; however&#44; that what I so lament&#44; was<lb/> aggravated by my own actions.  Some attribute it to the<lb/> absence of a weekly address that stirs up the heart and<lb/> edifies the mind.  Others&#44; to the want of harmonious singing&#44;<lb/> and there are many also who consider that I unnecessarily<lb/> prolong the service.  Nevertheless&#44; I aver that I am entirely<lb/> guiltless.  The first charge cannot be brought against<lb/> me&#44; for as I no sooner was I made to feel that my preaching was distaste&#45;<lb/>&#45;ful than I signified my willingness to <sic>yeild</sic> the position to<lb/> abler and more acceptable men.  Of the second&#44; I stand<lb/> clear&#44; for&#44; repeatedly I have requested the temporal leaders<lb/> of this Synagogue to exercise their authority in preventing<lb/> ill&#45;timed and discordant responses.  The third accusation&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>can only emanate from persons who perform their devotions<lb/> as an habitual task &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; who prefer haste to beco&#45;<lb/>&#45;ming emphasis.  I have not the right&#45;&#45;and nor will I ever<lb/> assume it&#45;&#45;&#44; to alter the ritual&#59; wherefore until it is abridged<lb/> by universal consent&#44; and under proper authorities&#44; I must needs<lb/> detain the attendants at this minor sanctuary&#44; with the recital<lb/> of its entire form.  Still&#44; I am earnestly anxious<lb/> to draw hither a multitude of worshippers&#44; not for any<lb/> personal advantage&#44; I solemnly declare before this oracle of our<lb/> Lord&#44; but for the glory of this house and of the Divine spirit<lb/> hovering around and above it.  Will a choir of male singers&#44;<lb/> among those&#44; who can read at least our sacred tongue accom&#45;<lb/>&#45;plish it&#63;  I offer my gratuitous tuition to qualify<lb/> them&#44; prior to the ensuing new year&#44; for the discharge of their duty.<lb/>  Will more frequent exhortations&#44; a more frequent expounding of<lb/> our laws and practices&#44; effect it&#63;  I will bring to it unabated<lb/> zeal&#44; and if I fail&#44; then you will be enabled to engage the<lb/> services of my superiors in knowledge.  The name which this<lb/> congregation shall have obtained for piety and high&#45;standing&#44;<lb/> will attract to it ripe scholars and finished orators.<lb/>  But you also&#44; O my Brethren you must show a disposition<lb/> to second my endeavours.  The most glowing enthusiasm<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>will gradually die away&#44; when instead of favor&#44; it meets with<lb/> scorn and apathy.  It is unreasonable to expect<lb/> from men&#44; because clothed in a ministerial garment&#44; a<lb/> complete self&#45;denial.  You have a right to demand from<lb/> them an irreproachable character&#44; learning accompanied<lb/> with devout habits&#59; but you cannot ask and scarcely anti&#45;<lb/>&#45;cipate that they shall see their labor unappreciated&#44; and<lb/> wax more active and energetic.  They are&#44; like yourselves&#44; but<lb/> flesh and blood.  Heirs to human infirmities&#44; liable to the<lb/> same weaknesses and the same frailty of nature.  Like yourselves&#44;<lb/> they are sensible of neglect&#44; and exultant at the approval<lb/> of their fellow&#45;creatures.  Brothers&#33;  Friends&#33;  Let us work together.<lb/>  You plan and I will execute&#59; or&#44; I will devise and you bring<lb/> it to pass.  Only let us continue steadfast to the principles<lb/> of our religion&#44; and our holy traditions.  Let us strive by<lb/> concerted actions to improve the temporal and spiritual<lb/> condition of our congregation&#44; but without entrenching on<lb/> &#34;the ancient land&#45;&#45;mark set by the ancient &#91;Hebrew&#93; fathers of our nation &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> We need a larger assemblage at all occasions&#44; when divine<lb/> worship is held in this sacred fane.  We need a more<lb/> decorous demeanour when gathered therein.  We need<lb/> a more punctual attendance.  We need a more<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>impressive manner of chaunting the beautiful psalms<lb/> and hymns of our ritual liturgy.  We need&#44; seemingly&#44;<lb/> pulpit instruction of a higher order.  We need more liberal<lb/> donations&#44; that this holy house be established on im&#45;<lb/>&#45;moveable basis&#44; that the shame resting upon us be<lb/> rolled away&#44; and our Lord be sanctified among the gentiles.<lb/>  I have already this day&#44; and at other times&#44; presented<lb/> my views as to the method by which we can compass<lb/> much of what is needed&#59; and now I will add&#44; that in order<lb/> to accomplish&#44; that which I last mentioned&#44; free&#45;will of&#45;<lb/>&#45;ferings&#44; of a generous character&#44; should be made or sent<lb/> on each return of the glorious season of the feast of weeks&#44;<lb/> until the extinction of a claim on this hallowed edifice<lb/> is consummated.  Let it be a fund specially devoted to that righteous object.  This is not&#44; indeed&#44; the most<lb/> expeditious and noblest way leading to the goal of my desires&#44;<lb/> but as my efforts towards the adoption of a better course<lb/> have been unsuccessful&#44; I now resort to this&#44; and bid it<lb/> God&#45;speed.  Brethren&#33;  Let the morrow prove<lb/> that of the abundance wherewith your Maker has blessed<lb/> you&#44; a slight portion is&#44; with a joyful heart&#44; laid upon His<lb/> altar.  Let the morrow be a vindication of the character<lb/> of the Mikv&#233; Israel Congregation&#44; showing to the Jewish<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>world that you are equal to many&#44; but inferior to none<lb/> of your fellow&#45;believers in acts of devotion&#44; in deeds of<lb/> liberality&#44; and in ardency of love for your religion and your<lb/> God.<lb/></p>
            <p>And Thou who abidest on high&#44; but deignest to look down<lb/> below&#44; accept the offering that Thy children will bring<lb/> in honor to thy name.  May it be counted to them for<lb/> righteousness&#44; and may it propitiate Thy fatherly<lb/> grace.  Grant that the merit thus acquired&#44; shall<lb/> stand as their advocate at the judgment&#45;seat&#44;<lb/> and obtain for their forgiveness&#44; prosperity and<lb/> endless bliss.  And now O Lord&#44; let the prayer<lb/> of Thy servant ascend Thy throne&#44; and return not<lb/> unfulfilled.  I beseech Thee to exalt this congregation&#44;<lb/> to bless it with material and spiritual wealth&#59; to<lb/> render it the instrument of religious enlightenment<lb/> and of salvation to many.  May it be<lb/> Thy gracious will that the youths thereof&#44; ever remain<lb/> attached to it&#59; that they become zealous colaborers in<lb/> the promotion of its welfare&#44; and faithful adherents<lb/> of the sublime laws&#44; whose promulgation&#44; we shall&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>on the morrow jointly celebrate in this consecrated<lb/> spot.  And upon those&#44; who with hearts flut&#45;<lb/>&#45;tering between hope and fear&#44; have lately stood before<lb/> Thy holy ark&#44; to vow obedience to Thy will&#44; let Thine<lb/> eyes be open&#44; O beneficent Creator&#33;  Lead them securely<lb/> through the devious paths of life&#44; uphold their steps<lb/> that they may not be entangled in the meshes<lb/> of vice.  Grant that they may walk at large on the<lb/> way that opens to their views a heaven of social and<lb/> domestic delights.  Grant that the lad&#44; who from<lb/> this day will be numbered among the <sic>worshippers</sic> of Thy<lb/> Unity&#44; may&#44; like Samuel at the Sanctuary&#44; be ever awakened<lb/> by a voice which calls him to Thy service&#44; and be<lb/> ready to answer &#34;speak O Lord&#33; for thy servant heareth.&#34;<lb/>  So may it be&#59; and say ye all.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
