<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF1_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_2_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>16</p>
            
            <p>An address on Parashat &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>
                for<lb/>
                Two Bar Mitzvah.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;The rich and the poor have met together&#44; the Lord hath made them<lb/> all.&#34;  Brethren&#33;  It is my wish and my prayer&#44; that<lb/> the occurrence of this day&#44; may be intended as an acknowledgment<lb/> of that Biblical truth.  Two youths have presented them&#45;<lb/>&#45;selves in this holy house&#44; and have in the same language<lb/> offered thanks to God.  But their station in life is not alike.<lb/>  He who first blessed the name of the Lord&#44; is lowly&#44; deficient<lb/> in earthly goods&#44; and bereft of a fathers&#39; tender care and<lb/> love.  The one who followed him is&#44; on the contrary&#44;<lb/> the inmate of a luxurious home&#44; the child of wealth&#44; and the<lb/> object of parental endearments.  Yet both asserted that they<lb/> are the joint&#45;heirs of an inestimable treasure.  Both<lb/> declared that to possess the means which will secure equally<lb/> to each of them endurable happiness.  Is it really so&#63;<lb/>  Have the rich and the poor in Israel a common heritage&#63;<lb/>  A par patrimony&#44; which supplies all with an unfeeling<lb/> support&#63;  What say ye&#44; my young hearers&#63;<lb/>  I fully agree with the two Bar Mitzvah in their open<lb/> declaration.  Do you also assent to it&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Is the law which Moses commanded us&#44; valued as an inheri&#45;<lb/>&#45;tance by you&#44; who will soon form a congregation in Jacob&#63;<lb/>  Let me rejoice in the assurance that your warm hearts beat<lb/> high still for your religion and your people.  Not many<lb/> years have elapsed&#44; since you first ascended this pulpit&#44; and<lb/> publicly avowed that the word of God is the sole guide to<lb/> human felicity.  Is that your present conviction&#63;<lb/>  You must pardon me&#44; if my expression betrays any mistrust<lb/> in your firmness of purpose.  Sad experience has taught me<lb/> caution.  Too often have I seen the professions of youth&#44;<lb/> be lied ere manhood had even been reached.  Some whom I imagine<lb/> would have grown to do Judaism honor&#44; evince by their daily actions&#44;<lb/> utter contempt for its ordinances.  While others that I prepared<lb/> for the day on which they attained religious majority&#44; now disdain<lb/> to be reckoned as members of the Synagogue.<lb/></p>
            <p>This is indeed a gloomy picture&#44; but not one which has been<lb/> designedly a overdrawn.  I have simply delineated what<lb/> every one that has eyes to see&#44; can testify to be a palpable<lb/> fact.  Yes&#44; I am deeply grieved at so great a defection<lb/> among the rising generation&#44; but thank God I have not lost<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>all faith in my Brethren.  The cause of religion will triumph&#44;<lb/> though&#44; like among the army of Gideon&#44; only three hundred<lb/> could be found that did not bend the knee to Baal.<lb/>  To you&#44; my young friends&#33; do I look&#45;&#45;if not with the san&#45;<lb/>&#45;guine expectation of former years&#45;&#45;with anxious hope at least.<lb/>  To you I look for the success of that holy cause.  Your<lb/> minds are open to healthful impression.  <sic>You</sic> feelings strike<lb/> a sympathetic chord at the appeals of the forsaken religion<lb/> of Sinai.  Let not&#44; I pray you&#44; let not the dictates of<lb/> self&#45;interest change your noble enthusiasm into chilling<lb/> indifference.  Keep its flame vivid and bright.  Suffer not<lb/> ambition or avarice to extinguish it from within your breasts.<lb/>  I &#91;&#63;&#93;&#44; my beloved friends&#33; the day on which I see the increase of<lb/> your number&#44; for despite many disappointments&#44; I delight<lb/> in thinking&#44; that the disaffection of some&#44; will be counteracted<lb/> by your staunch adherence to the belief of our fathers.<lb/>  This sabbath especially&#44; has inspired me with fresh hope&#44; for&#44;<lb/> as I said&#44; on it a biblical truth has been clearly illustrated.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;. &#34;The rich and the poor have met<lb/> together &#40;to acknowledge that&#41; the Lord hath made all of them.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>The religion of Israel does not&#45;&#45;like that of heathens&#44; admit of<lb/> different castes entrusted with a partial knowledge of human<lb/> duties.  No&#44; universal enlightenment is its ruling<lb/> principle.  Hence it is that the humblest among our brethren&#44; not<lb/> less than the highest&#44; is expected to perform the commandments of<lb/> the Lord.  None needs plead ignorance&#44; for the light that<lb/> shone or the summit of Horeb&#45;&#45;illumined all&#44; ab and by all<lb/> can Judaism be faithfully and intelligently f represented.<lb/>  Raise then your head with manly dignity&#44; my young<lb/> Brother&#44; who are humbly situated.  The religion you have acknowledged<lb/> this day has exalted your existence.  It has conferred upon<lb/> you the right of equality.  Morally and spiritually you<lb/> are inferior to none.  Your future exertions&#44; and not the worldly<lb/> good your parents have gathered&#44; will enhance your position<lb/> on earth.  They will glorify your Creator&#44; and give your soul<lb/> immortality.  Only be sincere and steadfast in your declarations.<lb/>  You should consider the event you have celebrated&#44; as the<lb/> first step to a career of usefulness and honor.  You are<lb/> now lacking what others possess in abundance&#44; but the<lb/> Father of the fatherless did not forsake you.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>He did prepare for you the requisite comforts of life.<lb/>  A home where you met sympathy&#44; consideration and timely<lb/> aid was open to receive you.  I can appreciate<lb/> the loss you have early sustained.  It was severe and<lb/> irreparable.  But friends and relatives most affectionate<lb/> and kind are still with you.  Their arms are stretched forth<lb/> to help&#59; and they they will&#44; under Providence&#44; lead you to<lb/> a path&#44; where industry obtains its reward.  Let this<lb/> thought animate you&#59; let it inspire you with gratitude<lb/> to God&#44; and with a powerful desire to mount high up<lb/> on the social ladder.  You may yet acquire influence<lb/> and wealth&#44; for&#44; it has been authoritatively written &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;The hand of the diligent shall bear rule&#44;&#34; and<lb/> in the same volume &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;The hand of the diligent<lb/> maketh rich.&#34;  But remember this day&#44; forget<lb/> not&#44; nor be ever ashamed of your lowly extraction.  The portion<lb/> you have read&#44; affords you instruction.  We find recorded<lb/> therein a circumstance worthy of your notice.  It is the<lb/> following&#58; Eliezer saw that his undertaking was about<lb/> to be crowned with success.  The family of Rebecca<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>had offered him a generous hospitality.  Their demeanour<lb/> towards him denoted respect.  He might then have repre&#45;<lb/>&#45;sented himself as a great personage.  He might have said&#44; that<lb/> he was the confidential friend&#44; the messenger charged by Abraham<lb/> with an errand which he would entrust to no inferior man.  He<lb/> might have exhibited a pardonable pride at his being deemed<lb/> of so much consequence.  But what were the words with<lb/> which Eliezer opened his speech&#63;  &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;I am the<lb/> servant of Abraham.  His humility <sic>equalled</sic> his fidelity.<lb/>  In all the walks of life&#44; let it be your endeavours&#44; to exem&#45;<lb/>&#45;plify those noble trials of human character&#59; humility<lb/> and fidelity to God and man.<lb/></p>
            <p>And you&#44; my young brother&#33; you whom the Almighty has<lb/> so greatly blessed.  You the only surviving son of fond parents.<lb/>  You who are being reared with the tenderest care&#44; and surrounded<lb/> with joys&#59; what sentiments&#44; but those of gratitude ought<lb/> now to fill your breast&#63;  The exertion you made to overcome<lb/> you made a natural timidity&#44; in order to perform a religious<lb/> practice is laudable.  You have gratified thereby those you owe<lb/> a debt that can never be paid&#44; and shown some disposition to<lb/> righteousness.  But much greater exertions than<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>that will be necessary&#44; to <sic>fulfil</sic> what the law of our God commands.<lb/>  The best manner in which you can express gratitude for the favors<lb/> enjoyed&#44; will be by your future efforts to conquer sin.<lb/>  Your happy condition of life exposes you to enticements&#44; which<lb/> are not held out to youths in needy circumstances.  The love<lb/> of pleasure may lead you astray.  The facility you will have<lb/> to overreach others in the pursuit of gaiety and fashion&#44; may<lb/> lay a snare to your feet.  Be on your guard.  Beware<lb/> of false friends.  Avoid those that advise a departure from<lb/> the religion you have openly avowed this day&#44; in order to satisfy<lb/> the cravings of the flesh.  Restrain your appetites and the lust<lb/> of gain.  Give to God what is God&#39;s&#44; even&#44; the days He has set apart<lb/> for His worship.  You may by so doing discover perhaps that the<lb/> heap of gold which will so much gratify your eye&#45;sight&#44; has<lb/> grown a little lower&#44; but you will then stand higher before<lb/> your heavenly Creator&#44; before your fellow&#45;men&#44; and in your estima&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion.  Thus you will show a thankful heart for the<lb/> benefits enjoyed in early years.  Thus you will prove the sincerity<lb/> of your utterance before the G Lord&#44; and before this Congregation<lb/> of your Brethren.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>And now I conclude with a prayer that your future may be as<lb/> joyous as your past&#44; but also with an exhortation to follow the<lb/> example pointed out to you in the section you have rehearsed.<lb/>  The relatives of Rebecca were loth to part with her so<lb/> unexpectedly&#44; and they asked of Eliezer that she might remain<lb/> with them a short space of time.  But the faithful<lb/> servant could not consent&#44; lest he break the promise made<lb/> to his mother.  &#34;Do not delay me.&#34;  &#91;Hebrew he exclaimed.<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;  Since the Lord hath prospered my way.&#34;  The<lb/> Lord&#44; and not his well&#45;matured plans&#44; or his sagacity.  The<lb/> Lord&#44; and not his foresight or wisdom.  Him alone he recognized<lb/> as the Author of his success&#44; and in Him he confided for the<lb/> speedy realization of Abraham&#39;s dearest wish.  My young brother&#33;<lb/> Keep this scriptural incident fresh in your memory&#44; and let<lb/> it be the standard of your conduct.  When prosperous in your<lb/> undertakings&#44; see always the hand of the Lord that showers down blessings<lb/> upon you.  Attribute to the Director of human events the affluence<lb/> you may enjoy&#44; and the honors which may be in store for you.<lb/>  Then humility will beautify your existence.  You will be religious<lb/> and virtuous.  You will be charitable and kind to all.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>You will obviously illustrate by your actions&#44; what you<lb/> have tacitly avowed this day namely &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;The Rich and the poor have met together&#44; the Lord hath<lb/> made them all.&#34;.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
