<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF2_17</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1894" source="" attested="yes">1894</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_17_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_17_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_17_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_17_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_17_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_17_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_17_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_17_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_17_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_17_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_17_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_17_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 3 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English, Hebrew</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
           <p> S. MORAIS,<lb/>
            546 N. FIFTH STREET,<lb/>
            PHILADELPHIA, PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <p>65
            Penitential Sabbath 55 - 94<lb/>
            [Hebrew]<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"></pb>
            <p>[Hebrew]  "I shall sprinkle you with clear<lb/> water and you shall be cleansed"  So promised God to <del>sinning</del> backsliding<lb/> Israel by means of the priestly Seer on <del>the</del> the river Cheba.  To<lb/> that prophetic declaration, our martyred Sage, Akiba ben Joseph, added,<lb/> the following utterance as an incentive to a full confession of <del>our backslidings</del> one's shortcomings<lb/> or [Hebrew]<lb/> [Hebrew]<lb/> "Happy you, O Israel, who is He that cleanses you, and before<lb/> whom ye cleanse yourselves?  Your Father in heaven."  Brethren.<lb/>  Waters of <del>regenerative</del> purification are now streaming from the fountain<lb/> of Divine Goodness.  Let all who are conscious of being<lb/> diseased with <del>sin unrighteousness</del> human sinfulness, draw night that they may be tho-<lb/>-roughly healed.  We all have read, how a famous<lb/> general of antiquity <sic>travelled</sic> in search of a cure to his<lb/> sad illness.  A suffering leper was Noaman. <del>was</del>.  The confidence<lb/> of his King, the respect of his army, the esteem of nations<lb/> he valued as nothing, so long as a loathsome malady clung<lb/> to his <del>skin</del> body.  Can there be no remedy for <del>it</del>? the foul <del>disp</del> distemper?  A young Jew-<lb/>-ess whom he had captured in battle and had <del>kept</del> retained<lb/> as his wife's waiting maid, told her mistress that<lb/> Israel's God, who wounds but also heals, can do impos-<lb/>-sible things by means of his prophets.  Quickly Noaman<lb/> makes ready, to go in <del>search</del> quest of what he yearned after-<lb/>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            a restoration to bodily health.  He journeys from Syria<lb/> to <del>Judea</del> the land of the Hebrews and stands a petitioner at the door of Elisha's<lb/> dwelling.  If the relinquishing of his lofty position, of<lb/> his great wealth had been demanded to obtain a cure,<lb/> he would have parted with all.  To what end?  To enjoy a<lb/> few years of this fleeting existence in the companionship of<lb/> mortals, who shunned the leprous.  Is the association of the<lb/> good and the saints in the realm of eternity, the commu-<lb/>nion of our soul with the Most High, an object of less con-<lb/>-cern?  What efforts can be too great that will secure<lb/> those glorious ends!  Yet, the conditions upon which they<lb/> depend are not at all severe.  I have not learned that<lb/> my religion requires the discipline of the scourge like<lb/> that of monks and capuchins who flog themselves to please a<lb/> supposed mediator <del>that</del> believed to intercede<del>s</del> for sinners.  The man<lb/> of Nazareth said to the youth who prayed for a share in<lb/> the world to come, that to gain it he must dispossess<lb/> himself of all his substance, <del>saying</del> and turning to his disciple<lb/> he asserted that "it is easier for a camel to go into the eye of<lb/> a needle than for a rich man to enter the King-<lb/>-dom of heaven."  Judaism, the religion of reason, does<lb/> not demand our voluntary self-castigation, nor the<lb/> surrendering of our wealth.  It wishes of those who are morally<lb/> diseased, to make a clear breast of it to the heavenly Physician and trust <del>the heavenly</del><lb/>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <del>Physician</del> Him for a perfect cure.  In other words: they<lb/> must confess that they have lived a life which ill-<lb/>accords with the dictates of <del>religion and morality  Not </del>righteousness and<lb/> <del>to confess</del> admit that not to fallible man as in the Catholic confessional, but to Him the One who<lb/> understands our most secret thoughts, who wants our<lb/> every heart's beating, to know if it throbs nobly or ignobly.<lb/>  </p>
           <p> A [Hebrew], says our Rabbis is what the Lord waits for.<lb/>  "I have sinned.  Forgive me, O compassionate Father!" God<lb/> pleaded with the daughter of Zion, because she refused<lb/> that admission [Hebrew] "Thou dist say: I am in-<lb/>-nocent" Therefore I enter into judgment with thee, <del>because</del> for thou<lb/> <del>thou</del> dost say<del>est</del> 'I have not sinned'" [Hebrew] Brethren.  If any<lb/> Israelite <del>enters</del> comes to the synagogue on the most solemn day<lb/> fast approaching with a proud heart, tacitly declaring<lb/> that he needs not confess.  [Hebrew], because his actions<lb/> have <del>been</del> always been measured by the square and compass<lb/> of undeviating justice; that he has never offended<lb/> the Universal Parent by wronging His creatures in acts,<lb/> in words or thoughts, let him depart.  Yom Kippur<lb/> will avail him nothing.  The waters of purification <del>are</del> flow for<lb/> those who acknowledge themselves <del>religiously spiritually</del> spiritually diseased.<lb/>  And "who, exclaims the moralist, "who can <del>say</del> boast thus: [Hebrew]<lb/>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            my heart is clean [Hebrew] I am free from sin."  If<lb/> any Israelite imagines <del>wh</del> that when he laid aside the Law,<lb/> which Moses gave as a heritage to the congregation of Jacob,<lb/> he walked in the light of progress; that he liberalized<lb/> the world and made the Jew popular, when he endeavoured<lb/> to prove his identity with this gentile neighbor, his ab-<lb/>-stinence on Yom Kippur is will be profitless, for he contradicts <del>it is written in</del><lb/> the five holiest books, where it is written: [Hebrew] "I have set you apart<lb/> from other people to be my own."  If any one feels no<lb/> compunction that his children are reared in ignorance of<lb/> the religion entrusted to our safe keeping, considering it right &amp; proper<lb/> to leave its adoption or rejection by his sons and daughters,<lb/> at a maturer age, he cannot be included among those<lb/> whom Kippur will restore to spiritual health, for <del>it is</del><lb/> repeatedly <del>enjoined</del> it is commanded in the Pentateuch [Hebrew]<lb/> "Thou shalt make (the precepts) known to thy children and<lb/> thy children's children.  Nay, <del>sha</del> thou shall teach them<lb/> diligently unto thy children, at all times" with no cessation, a fatal error is<lb/> that of some easy going fathers, who leave the choice of<lb/> Judaism to the option of their progeny, <del>an</del> a rueful error which<lb/> has robbed the synagogue of many votaries, and enriched the<lb/> church, or filled the ranks of skeptics and agnostics.  Brethren.<lb/>  Kippur was instituted for such as are aware of their<lb/> <del>shortcomings</del> weaknesses and failings, not for those who justify in their minds all their deeds.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>A sense of our imperfections must lead us humbly to God<lb/> with a [Hebrew] on Yom Kippur, relying on the compassionate<lb/> Father for a cleansing away of what is impure in our actions<lb/> or conceptions.  Each of us in his respective sphere must<lb/> be conscious of his shortcomings, and to confess that before<lb/> the Lord, to implore His assistance that we may hence-<lb/>forth shape our course in a manner acceptable in His<lb/> sight, is the object of the day which the house of Israel<lb/> is about to solemnize.  We may have fallen short in the performance of our<lb/> duty as social beings.  We may not have heeded the ex-<lb/>-cellent proverb [Hebrew] "A wholesome tongue<lb/> is a tree of life, but perverseness therein is a breaking<lb/> of the spirit."  We may not have been always guarded<lb/> so as not to wound our neighbor's feelings, disparage<del>ing</del><lb/> his worth, tarnish<del>ing</del> his <del>character</del> reputation.  As<lb/> parents we may not have bestowed equal attention on<lb/> the moral as on the physical development of our offspring,<lb/> forgetting that the soundest foundations of one's character,<lb/> are love of industry and religious probity.  [Hebrew] "By what will a youth keep his way pure? by observing God's word."  As children<lb/> we may not have exhibited so high a degree of<lb/> respectful consideration for the earthly authors of our exist-<lb/>ance as due them, unmindful of the injunction [Hebrew]<lb/> [Hebrew] "Listen to thy father who has begotten thee,<lb/> and slight not thy mother, when she has grown old."<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
           <p> As partakers of the same paternal and maternal<lb/> care we may have been wanting in that spirit<lb/> of mutual forbearance, which harmonizes dif-<lb/>-ferences and sweetens the home, where we still are, or have been<lb/> gladly provided for and kindly sheltered; ignoring<lb/> perhaps that [Hebrew] "A brother is born to<lb/> help his brother in time of distress".  As Israelites, we<lb/> may not have cooperated with the good, to elevate the<lb/> condition of the lowly and needy, to further their education,<lb/> or we may have misled the unsophisticated and unwary<lb/> by an open disregard of Mosaic ordinances, thus substan-<lb/>-tially transgressing the behest that we should not lay<lb/> a stumbling block in the way of the blind [Hebrew]<lb/> But though every one of us--God forbid--were guilty of all<lb/> those sins, he would be cleansed and become as white as<lb/> snow, as pure as a newly born babe, if he will say in<lb/> his heart of hearts [Hebrew] "I have sinned," and regret-<lb/>-ting that it is so,--mistrusting his own powers, will lean<lb/> upon God for support to become regenerated in virtue.<lb/>  For these are two of the essentials to the cleansing of the<lb/> soul [Hebrew] An unreserved acknowledgment of<lb/> our backslidings and a sense of compunction for their existence.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
           <p> By [Hebrew] we shall have declared that to follow<lb/> our own devices, is to meet a moral death; to be guided by<lb/> the dictates of religion, is to cling to everlasting life.<lb/>  We shall have proved that frailty is inherent in our<lb/> nature, perfection belongs solely to God.  And our humiliation,<lb/> our contrition, our penance and supplications will stand<lb/> at the bar of judgment on the dreaded day of Kippur,<lb/> and earn for us pardon and durable blessings [Hebrew]<lb/> [Hebrew] "Happy you O Israel,<lb/> who is He that cleanses you and before whom ye cleanse yourselves!  Your<lb/> Father in heaven".  But a third essential must also be<lb/> fulfilled.  <del>We w</del> Would we clasp again in our embrace a way-<lb/>ward child, who after a long absence, while in the pursuit of<lb/> vice, returns home admitting his frowardness but refusing<lb/> to forsake his low habits and vicious companions?  Would<lb/> we not exact especially, <del>that</del> a total change of conduct, as a pledge<lb/> of his repentance?  Unless a determination to alter what is<lb/> wrong in our habits <del>accompanies</del> attends our [Hebrew] we<lb/> may cry aloud a thousand times.  [Hebrew], it will avail us<lb/> nothing.  We must vow to repudiate faults to which<lb/> we have been [?]; to hold fast to righteous resolves,<lb/> to become upright in our social relations, pure in our<lb/> domestic affections, charitable to man, pious towards<lb/> God, and  continue thus not a day or a month, but always.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>[Hebrew] "Confession, contrition and a rejection<lb/> of sin," that is the threefold cord, will which will bind<lb/> us indissolubly with our forgiving God.  Let our own<lb/> hands weave it.  To day we possess strength and<lb/> knowledge and will to accomplish the task,<lb/> to morrow we may have been left only the power<lb/> to lament our powerlessness.  With this reflection,<lb/> I commit myself and you &amp; all, with the sincerity of a prayer,<lb/> to the infinite goodness of Israel's God.  May<lb/> He be <del>y</del>our <sic>counsellor</sic>, breathing into your souls sen-<lb/>-timents of the deepest righteousness, the sublimest<lb/> virtue and an abiding love for whatever ennobles<lb/> human nature.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
