<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF5_21</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1897-01" source="" attested="yes">January 1897</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_21_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_21_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_21_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_21_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_21_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_21_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_21_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_21_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_21_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_21_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_21_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_21_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA.</p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Jan. 97<lb/>
                A Post Biblical Lecture<lb/>
                64<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Very many have been the lectures&#44; which I delivered&#44;<lb/> here form time to time&#44; upon post&#45;biblical history.<lb/>  Beginning with the account of the epoch&#45;making sy&#45;<lb/>&#45;nod under the presidency of Ezra&#44; the priest&#44; after the<lb/> restoration of Babylonian captives to Palestine&#44; I reached<lb/> the period of the total expulsion of Jews from Spain and Portugal.<lb/></p>
            <p>My reason for allowing long intervals to elapse be&#45;<lb/>&#45;fore resuming those narratives was twofold.  Firstly&#44;<lb/> because I feared that the subjects treated&#44; might prove<lb/> too dry&#45;&#45;so to say&#45;&#45;to command general attention.  Se&#45;<lb/>&#45;condly&#44; because an accurate presentation of those sub&#45;<lb/>&#45;jects involves the necessity of abundant reading and<lb/> research&#44; not always within reach of the lecturer.<lb/></p>  
            <p>This morning&#44; however&#44; I shall come back to a topic of<lb/> the same character&#44; by briefly referring to that stage<lb/> of our history&#44; which&#45;&#45;though sad&#45;&#45;is always invariably of deep in&#45;<lb/>&#45;terest to me.  The Spanish family of Duran&#44;<lb/> has furnished us with authors of wide learning<lb/> in several branches of our literature.  Prolific in<lb/> their writings&#44; they enriched sacred lore us with commentaries&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>with treatises on Jewish doctrines and philosophy&#44;<lb/> on Talmudical decisions &#38; on the origin and development<lb/> of the Hebrew Grammar.  and&#44; because they Moreover&#44; some members of that family who succeeded to<lb/> escape being burnt alive in the seething caldron of the Inqui&#45;<lb/>&#45;sition&#44; some members of that family&#44; undertook&#44; as<lb/> soon as they would throw off the mask which made<lb/> them appear devoted Catholics&#44; undertook to take up the<lb/> cudgel in the defense of the religion that they fondly loved.<lb/></p>
            <p>Interesting is to read in a volume of response &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; called Tashbetz&#44; by Simeon Ben Zenach Duran&#44;<lb/> an apologetic discussion regarding his own person and<lb/> others situated alike.<lb/>  That erudite Jew from of Spain had fled form the thumb<lb/> screws and consuming flames of the autos da fe of<lb/> wicked Iberia&#44; to the more humane dominions of Otto&#45;<lb/>&#45;man rulers.  He settled in Algier.  Chosen there<lb/> as ecclesiastical Chief or Chacham&#44; he argued with keen reasoning<lb/> powers&#44; in favor of the practice just introduced<lb/> to receive a stipulated sum&#44; as compensation for<lb/> religious services rendered.  All know that<lb/> in early history&#44; our preceptors and preachers derived<lb/> their earnings from manual labor&#44; as tillers of<lb/> the soil&#44; or by from their ability to handleing mechanical tools skilfully.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Their controlling idea principle was that as Israel had ob&#45;<lb/>&#45;tained the knowledge of the rules of life gratuitously<lb/> from God and His inspired servants&#44; so likewise it<lb/> behooved them to impart for nothing no remuneration whatever the knowledge<lb/> of the Torah&#44; which they possessed.  But times<lb/> had radically changed.  In the Spain and Portugal<lb/> of the Middle ages&#44; our men of learning could not<lb/> imitate their Palestinian predecessors.  Agriculture<lb/> and handicraft were not universal pursuits&#44; still<lb/> our Rabbis who dwelt there did not go then invariably as now invariably regularly in quest<lb/> of material rewards for their endeavours to familiarize<lb/> their contemporaries with the Torah.  In a letter<lb/> by Maimonides&#44; preserved yet among his multifarious writings&#44;<lb/> the celebrated sage of Cordova states that&#44; notwith&#45;<lb/>standing his exhaustive work as a court Physician<lb/> at Cairo&#44; where he had settled&#44; he robbed himself<lb/> of daily rest and of Sabbath rest for a single purpose.  He aimed to spread abroad the<lb/> knowledge of ordinances of the Torah&#44; among querists&#44;<lb/> anxious to acquire it.  Probably others in Spain and<lb/> and elsewhere&#44; followed the same commendable practice.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>But Simeon Ben Zemach Duran had lost his<lb/> all.  In his native land&#44; as a doctor of medicine&#45;&#45;<lb/> a profession almost exclusively under the control<lb/> of Jews&#45;&#45;he could&#44; with ease&#44; gain a respectable<lb/> livelihood&#44; but he had reached a foreign country<lb/> in a state of destitution&#59; nor was his former calling<lb/> available in the Barbary states&#44; as in Spain.<lb/>  All he had possessed&#44; had gone partly to bribe spies&#44;<lb/> who lay in ambush to catch him&#44; and consign his body<lb/> to an unmerciful church&#44; and partly to satisfy<lb/> the greed of covert enemies&#44; who hungered after the property of suspected<lb/> Marranos.  In the same plight&#44; as Simeon Ben<lb/> Zemach Duran&#44; were&#44; doubtless&#44; many of his brother<lb/> refugees&#44; who had sought an asylum abroad&#44; there&#45;<lb/>&#45;fore he decided that their acting as ministers of<lb/> religion for pay&#44; could not be condemned as a<lb/> venal offence&#44; and therefore he himself had accepted a situation for in self support.<lb/>  But the most attractive personality of the Duran family was&#44; in my<lb/> judgment&#44; Prifort Duran&#44; who used to signed his name<lb/> &#34;Ephod&#34;&#44; &#91;Hebrew&#93; three initial Hebrew letters words which stand in Hebrew<lb/> for &#34;I am Prifort Duran.&#34;  Very Recently&#44; I came<lb/> in possession of a valuable grammar&#44; which he that exegete wrote<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>in the fourteenth year century of the vulgar era&#44;<lb/> but which remained <sic>inedited</sic> till late years.  Now&#58;<lb/> it happened that about a century before the final<lb/> expulsion of 1492&#44; Prifort Duran&#44; who lived in Catolonia&#44;<lb/> had long <sic>prentended</sic> for some time to bow to the cross&#44; in order to<lb/> save his body from terrible tortures&#44; and his substance<lb/> from depredation.  Weary and disgusted with his en&#45;<lb/>&#45;forced duplicity&#44; he watched with lynx eyes for<lb/> any opportunity&#44; when he might facilitating his fleeing to a spot<lb/> in which he could declare himself a believing Jew.<lb/>  The occasion arrived at length&#44; and he ran fled to a<lb/> seaport town in France&#44; with the intention of<lb/> emigrating from thence to Palestine.  But<lb/> Prifort Duran had a friend&#44; who also had<lb/> feigned attachment to the Catholic faith.<lb/>  The two agreed to meet in a safe place&#44;<lb/> and to journey together to the Holy Land.<lb/>  In fain did Duran wait for his friend&#39;s<lb/> arrival.  He could not account for the disap&#45;<lb/>&#45;pointment&#44; since that friend had seemed likewise<lb/> very anxious to throw off the mask long<lb/> worn.  Later on&#44; however he received a letter &#91;&#63;&#93; sent from Avignon.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>It had been written by Bonet or Benedict Ben Gudan&#44;<lb/> the expected <sic>travelling</sic> companion.  In that epistle<lb/> the last mentioned Marrano&#44; related that while<lb/> in Avigńon&#44; he had made the acquaintance of a cer&#45;<lb/>tain Master Paul&#44; a baptised Jew&#44; whose former<lb/> name was Solomon Levi.  He has held serious very earnest con&#45;<lb/>&#45;versations with the convert&#44; and through them he had become convinced<lb/> that Catholicism is right and Judaism wrong.<lb/>  Prifort Duran felt greatly surprised amazed&#44; but he was not tardy in acknowledging<lb/> receipt of that strange unexpected surprising letter.  With a biting sarcasm<lb/> and <sic>and</sic> the keenest irony which the Catholic<lb/> church misunderstood at first as the confession<lb/> of an earnest sincere Christian&#44; Duran pretended to fully<lb/> concur in the new ideas by imbibed by Bonet Ben<lb/> Gudan.  He also would advised commended the principle theory of discarding the Unity and<lb/> embracing the Trinity&#44; he also would was ready to admit the<lb/> wonderful immaculate conception that brought forth a man<lb/> god&#44; also the dogma of a blood&#39;s redemption through<lb/> the crucifixion of the Creator&#39;s own begotten son&#59; in short&#44; every thing<lb/> taught by that Saul of Tarsus&#44; who became St Paul&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>had taught&#44; and all which Solomon Levi&#44; who had become<lb/> Maestro Paul of Santa Maria&#44; swore to.<lb/>  But I shall reserve for another lecture&#44; a<lb/> fuller delineation of the character of that famous<lb/> letter&#44; purposely crushed in a obscure peculiar style.  This Sabbath I will close my nar&#45;<lb/>&#45;rative with words of thanksgiving.  For the<lb/> Almighty&#44; who neither slumbers nor sleeps&#44; has<lb/> watched over the preservation of this dear city of<lb/> ours.  When on the third day of this week&#44;<lb/> an angry wind&#44; &#91;&#63;&#93; in the face of a frozen<lb/> atmosphere&#44; threatened a far&#45;extended confla&#45;<lb/>&#45;gration&#44; the Creator of nature&#44; commanded the<lb/> element of water to force back the element of fire.<lb/>  Thus were its strides&#44; towards a conquest of destruct&#45;<lb/>&#45;ion&#44; cut short.  I thank God also for the<lb/> feelings of instinctive humanity exhibited on that<lb/> trying occasion&#59; how even because the herculean efforts of those<lb/> engaged in the work of deliverance&#44; were recognized and<lb/> rewarded and fraternally praised.  Oh&#33; may He who<lb/> directs sublunary events&#44; and causes good often to rise spring<lb/> up from apparent evil&#44; make this week&#39;s event occurrence&#44; to unite<lb/> more closely the hearts of capitalists to the hearts of the laborers.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>May the latter be <sic>benefitted</sic> in their domestic<lb/> and social interests&#44; and the fear of mischievous<lb/> discord between the employer and the employed&#44; be<lb/> chased away.  Oh&#33; may the day also speedily<lb/> arrive&#44; when the noblest of propositions just<lb/> emanated from the capital of this land of liberty&#44;<lb/> be eagerly accepted by all the nations of the potentates.<lb/> earth.  For&#44; then the aspirations of our Isaiah<lb/> and Micah will receive universal <sic>fulfilment</sic>.<lb/>  &#34;A nation shall not raise a sword against another<lb/> nation&#44; and the art of war will be learnt no more.&#34;<lb/>  So may it be.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
