<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF9_20</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff9_20_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff9_20_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff9_20_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff9_20_2v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 1 sheet<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Funeral oration<lb/></p>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  The wish to hear the praises of our departed relatives&#44; rises spon&#45;<lb/>&#45;taneously in the human breast.  Death seems to possess a twofold<lb/> power.  That invisible hand&#44; which cuts the thread of life&#44; erases<lb/> also from the tablet of memory the foibles of those we have held dear.<lb/>  The causes of discordance on momentary irritation&#44; sink from our mental<lb/> vision&#44; to bring out into bold relief the thousands of occasions&#44; which fastened<lb/> the chords of our affection round the hearts that have ceased to throb.<lb/>  Sweet are therefore the words which recall the excellencies of our beloved ones.<lb/>  A public acknowledgment of their worth&#44; relieves soothes the poignancy of our grief.<lb/>  But feelings so natural to the bereaved&#44; are not always sympathised<lb/> with by strangers.  The world may perhaps be harsh in its judg&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment.  It do no doubt is so in many instances&#59; but unless the<lb/> qualities of those who have died obviously showed some claim to commend&#45;<lb/>&#45;ation&#44; the world which cannot investigate all our deeds&#44; will look<lb/> upon the obsequies performed as an unbecoming exhibition.  The<lb/> officiating minister may well specially expect to meet with censure&#44; when<lb/> the unenviable epithets of time&#45;sowing and obsequies will be<lb/> unsparingly applied.  I rejoice&#44; my Brethren&#33; to know<lb/> that you will not so consider me this day.  Whatever I shall say<lb/> of Judah Levy&#44; reechoes your sentiments&#44; and represents as true<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>in all its bearings that which a desolate wife and sorrow&#45;<lb/>stricken relatives believe.  He was a good man&#59; that is&#58; he<lb/> endeavoured to follow right&#44; as God had given him a mind to under&#45;<lb/>&#45;stand the right.  He conceived that time was a creation of the<lb/> Most High&#44; and that to appropriate to oneself that portion thereof which<lb/> belongs not unto man&#44; is a sacrilege.  Hence&#44; he determined to employ<lb/> the seventh day&#44; as his Bible dictated &#91;Hebrew&#93; a Sabbath unto the Lord.  Few have become as zealous<lb/> in personally supporting the religious worship.  None more hearty in upraising<lb/> a voice&#45;&#45;ever melodious&#45;&#45;to enhance the service tendered to the<lb/> Almighty.  And our lamented friend could boast that the richest did<lb/> not&#44; comparatively&#44; exceed his liberal offerings.<lb/></p>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  As often as the old adage that &#34;the voice of the people is the voice<lb/> of God&#34; is misapprehended&#44; I think that in the present instance<lb/> it cannot be regarded as wrongly applied&#59; when an entirely impartial community<lb/> of Israelites attests to the merits of Judah Levy&#39;s conduct in life.  Had our<lb/> deceased friend proved them simply in the Synagogue&#44; I myself and our my<lb/> coreligionists attached thereto&#44; might possibly be anxious impelled to accord to him a<lb/> meed of praise.  Had his fidelity&#44; fond attachment&#44; and<lb/> yielding temperament towards his wife of his bosom been his principal<lb/> characteristic.  Or had he merely as a son behaved dutifully and reverently&#44;<lb/> and as a brother affectionately and considerately&#44; those alone<lb/> of his household would be now wail and weep.  But when<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>we hear on all sides an expression of sorrow at his untimely<lb/> death&#44; we are led forcibly to conclude that our brother possessed<lb/> more than ordinary qualities.  Yes&#58; in his social as well as in his<lb/> domestic and denominational relations he Judah Levy manifested a disposition<lb/> which won for him great respect.  He strove to be just&#44; while being<lb/> generous.  I shall never agree with the maxim set forth<lb/> in the books of our gentiles neighbors&#44; that &#34;charity will cover the<lb/> multitude of sins.&#34;  A virtue it is indeed&#44; and of the highest order&#59;<lb/> but when I am told that an Israelite faithless to his God&#44; dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;honest with his fellow&#45;man&#44; must elicit general esteem&#44; be&#45;<lb/>&#45;cause he gives freely to the poor&#44; I bl blush and hung down my<lb/> head.  Such is not the Jewish code&#44; and such nor was that not the<lb/> moral standard of our deceased brother friend.  To vast commercial<lb/> schemes he preferred small undertakings&#44; that he might not<lb/> overstep trespass the bounds of probity.  Yet&#44; he found always more<lb/> than a sufficiency to attend to the demands of humanity.<lb/>  He did stretched forth a helping hand to that his brother the needy fall<lb/> not by the rugged road he must cross&#59; but he remembered also likewise<lb/> that justice is runs the shining&#45;light which would guide his own steps<lb/> upwards.  &#34;The2 path of the just is brilliancy itself&#44; brightening<lb/> on unto the perfect day&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;1<lb/> and that he steadily endeavoured to follow.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Restrain then your grief&#44; my bereaved friends.  Let your agitation be<lb/> calmed.  He whom you loved is nearing the goal&#44; when<lb/> that perfect day dawns.  He proceeds unobstructed by<lb/> the impediments that unrighteousness interposes.  He speeds<lb/> on with gigantic strides&#44; for his spiritual stature has heightened&#44;<lb/> since he became purified by patient suffering.  Acts of<lb/> devotion&#44; kindness&#44; justice and charity have atoned for<lb/> the trespasses of his youth.  The angels of peace greet his approach&#44;<lb/> and a voice above the Cherubim calls forth &#34;Judah shall ascend&#34;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
