<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF3_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_2_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_2_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_2_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_2_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_2_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>14 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Explanatory lecture for<lb/>
                Sabbath Sheakhin.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>A virtuous life&#44;&#45;&#45;always praise&#45;worthy&#45;&#45;&#44; has greater<lb/> claims to respect&#44; when exhibited amidst prevailing vice.<lb/>  For as in the physical world&#44; we may with comparative ease<lb/> keep our health&#44; when breathing a pure atmosphere&#59; but we<lb/> are forced to use every precaution not to endanger it&#44; when<lb/> compassed around by foul air&#44; so in the moral world&#44;<lb/> we may&#44; with facility&#44; hold on to righteousness&#44; when we<lb/> see it universally <sic>practised</sic>&#44; but it is only by exceeding self&#45;<lb/>control that we can avoid wickedness&#44; when precept and example<lb/> lead directly to it.  This truth is applicable both to the<lb/> character of nations and individuals.  A youth&#44; whose<lb/> parents and teachers jointly labor to imbue his mind with a<lb/> proper sense of duty&#44; will&#44; in all likelihood&#44; grow upright&#44;<lb/> while&#44; on the other hand&#44; if home influence and the habits<lb/> of the instructors&#44; encourage evil&#45;doing&#44; he will be unable<lb/> to eschew corruption&#44; unless he struggles mightily to<lb/> overcome besetting obstacles.  Again&#58; history will show that<lb/> the conduct of those noted for wealth or political power will<lb/> invariably be reflected in the demeanour of the com&#45;<lb/>&#45;munity at large.  If exemplary&#44; it will find many to<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>imitate it&#44; but if tainted with sin&#44; a large<lb/> number among the humbler classes will rival the so&#45;called<lb/> high&#45;toned.  We do not need travel far&#44; nor ransack an&#45;<lb/>&#45;cient libraries&#44; to find illustrations.  Our immediate circles&#44;<lb/> and the book of every day&#39;s experience will furnish them<lb/> plentifully.  What we constantly see and read will<lb/> present to view individuals kept under salutary restraints<lb/> by domestic and social influences&#44; and others running<lb/> headlong in the way of extravagance and depravity through<lb/> pernicious surroundings.  Still the idea I have set forth&#44;<lb/> is not based upon any incident feature in our personal or national<lb/> character.  It was suggested by an event of ancient date connected with<lb/> the Haftorah of this Sabbath&#44; to which I desire to draw<lb/> your attention.  We will cast a glance over the internal<lb/> condition of the Hebrew people&#44; at the time in which<lb/> that occurrence took place.<lb/></p>
            <p>The union of the twelve tribes&#44; that David had consolidated&#44;<lb/> and Solomon maintained&#44; had been broken asunder.  A<lb/> schism fostered by the incompetency of Rehoboam&#44; and<lb/> consumated perpetuated by the prefidious policy of Jeroboam son<lb/> of Nebat&#44; gave rise to civil wars that devastated the<lb/> land&#44; and to immorality that defiled it.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Virtue and patriotism could not exist&#44; where a wanton<lb/> court was supported by burthensome taxes laid upon the<lb/> populace multitude.  The law of Moses&#44; demanding the severest guard most vigilant watch<lb/> over our passions&#44; could not hold its ground&#44; where altars<lb/> to a debauching idolatry burnt in the palaces of Kings.<lb/>  Even the voice of a fearless Elijah&#44; thundering against<lb/> crimes committed by the great&#44; and copied by the multitude populace<lb/> was drowned in the din of heathen carousals.  If at one<lb/> time&#44; the efforts of zealous men seemed to succeed&#44; injurious<lb/> surroundings soon neutralized them.  We may admit&#44; that<lb/> though since the division of the tribes&#44; the example of the<lb/> high&#45;stationed had contaminated every grade of society&#44; still<lb/> some of the Rulers of Judah&#44; had striven to reform their sub&#45;<lb/>&#45;jects&#44; and by rekindling a love for religion and country&#44;<lb/> had put an end to foreign dictation&#44; and reasserted the right<lb/> of the law of God to govern supreme.  And Very possibly&#44; if<lb/> they who sat on the throne of David&#44; had ever kept aloof<lb/> from those who held dominion over the Kingdom of Israel&#44;<lb/> they might have given permanence to the wholesome<lb/> changes effected.  But in an evil hour&#44; a marriage<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>was contracted between the son of the righteous<lb/> Jehoshaphat and the daughter of the wicked Ahab.<lb/>  A branch of a root stock so corrupt could but pollute at the<lb/> very touch.  So it happened that the sceptre&#44; which<lb/> in the hand of the former sovereigns of Judah had represented<lb/> piety and military glory&#44; became in the hand of their suc&#45;<lb/>&#45;cessor&#44; the instrument of ungodliness and humiliation.<lb/>  Jehoram allied in matrimony with Athalia&#44; stained his<lb/> throne with the blood of six brothers&#59; and to remove every<lb/> object that might recall his iniquity&#44; slew several of the most<lb/> distinguished personages in the realms.  The eight years<lb/> he held the sway&#44; may be fittingly called the reign of<lb/> degeneracy.  His example stirred up in others low<lb/> cravings&#44; and sanctioned all the abominable rites of<lb/> idolatry.  Enfeebled by vice&#44; the people and their mo&#45;<lb/>&#45;narch could not cope with the stranger that invaded their<lb/> territories&#44; and pillaged what had been secured before in a<lb/> many a hard fought battle.  The impotent King of Judah&#44;<lb/> who had slain butchered his own father&#39;s children&#44; saw all his sons&#44;<lb/> but the youngest&#44; pierced by the sword of the enemy&#44;<lb/> and himself stricken with an incurable disease.<lb/>  His suffering in which his successor&#44; Ahaziah&#44; ought to have<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>recognized the finger of God&#44; pointing out to him the<lb/> path he ought to tread&#44; in order that peace and prosperity<lb/> might be restored to the house of David&#44; created no impression.<lb/>  But that child was born of Athalia&#59; of a mother who<lb/> nurtured him with a soul&#45;poisoning milk&#44; of a mother<lb/> whose first lessons had been irreconcilable hatred against the<lb/> law of Moses.  She had chosen as his preceptors men of<lb/> her own mind&#59; idolaters&#44; steeped in corruption.  She had<lb/> joined forced him into &#91;&#63;&#93; the closest association with those<lb/> of her kindred&#44; and made her influence felt in all he<lb/> undertook.  One year was the extent of his reign&#44; and<lb/> when the avenging sword of Jehu cut him off&#44; the un&#45;<lb/>&#45;natural mother&#44; thirsting for power&#44; killed her offspring<lb/> that none might be left of the root of Jesse.<lb/>  Upon the head which had devised that atrocious deed&#44; the<lb/> monster placed a royal diadem&#44; and defying all rules&#44;<lb/> proclaimed herself queen.  We may judge of the state<lb/> of degradation into which the country&#44; once governed by<lb/> the valiant David and wise Solomon&#44; had sunk&#44; when<lb/> Athalia the murderess of her progeny could thus with<lb/> impunity insult a nation.  But example had accomplished<lb/> its work too thoroughly.  Every feeling of self&#45;respect was deadened.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>The man of Judah grown effeminate suffered a woman<lb/> to lay reduce them to the lowest ebb of disgrace debasement.  Still&#44; the<lb/> ends of Providence could not be defeated by human subtlety.<lb/>  God had promised His <sic>annointed</sic>&#44; that his seed would<lb/> live for ever&#44; and now&#44; as at all periods of history&#44; when<lb/> it appeared to be on the very eve of destruction&#44; an unforeseen<lb/> power drew it out of the impending danger.<lb/></p>
            <p>Within the walls of Athalia&#39;s detestable palace&#44; a maiden<lb/> was brought up&#44; who did not become infected with the moral<lb/> pestilence&#44; of prevailing the surrounding atmosphere.  It may be<lb/> that the blood of Ahab did not course through her veins.<lb/>  Perhaps the bosom that had given her nourishment&#44; had beat<lb/> with purer tenderer sentiments than those which stirred the breast<lb/> of the wife of Jehoram.  Certain it is that Jehosheba was<lb/> a noble heroine&#44; for she clothed herself with the armour of<lb/> purity&#44; and struggled to remain undefiled&#44; despite all<lb/> the pollution with which she came in constant contact.<lb/>  Happily for herself and the nation&#44; she was wedded to<lb/> a man&#44; who loved virtue for its own sake&#59; a rare character<lb/> over which selfishness exercised no power&#44; one who<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>considered that to promote the welfare of our<lb/> fellow&#45;beings is the highest reward to which we should<lb/> aspire.  He doubtless lamented the degeneracy of his<lb/> brethren&#44; and looked for a mighty arm hand that should tear<lb/> the meshes of sin in which Judah was entangled.  But<lb/> though the heart of his wife throbbed in unison with his heart he poured forth his complaints before her&#44; whose hear panted with for a national regeneration&#44;<lb/> though she his wife shared the eager wish of witnessing a change<lb/> in the condition of their humiliated country yet she neither could<lb/> not with any greater faint hope of success have under&#45;<lb/>&#45;taken aught&#44; had not the Almighty chosen him Jehosheba as the<lb/> means of salvation.  She must have been at court&#44;<lb/> when the perfidious scheme of Athalia was consummated.<lb/>  Entering the chamber of horror&#44; where the children of<lb/> the late King had been slaughtered&#44; she knelt over them<lb/> to see whether the last spark of life&#44; was extinguished<lb/> in all&#44; when to her unspeakable joy the infant Joash<lb/> was yet breathing.  She calls restores him to a new existence&#44; consciousness&#44;<lb/> and with a motherly care&#44; that braves all perils she steals<lb/> away&#44; and conceals the precious boy in a sudden secluded room<lb/> of the Temple.  Jehoiada&#44; the noble&#45;minded husband<lb/> of that heroine Jehosheba&#44; becomes party to her secret&#45;plan&#44;<lb/> and by his assistance&#44; her brother&#39;s child is saved.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>But while the infant prince was imbibing pure sublime lessons under<lb/> the tuition of Jehocada&#44; the high point&#59; the latter did not<lb/> remain inactive.  From the moment that the scion of<lb/> the house of David had been miraculously wrested form the<lb/> tight grasp of death&#44; his whole soul was bent upon the<lb/> accomplishing of one object&#44;&#45;&#45;the reformation of Judah&#44;<lb/> through the revival of the law of Moses&#44; and the overthrow<lb/> of idolatry.  He felt that so long as the corruptive<lb/> rites of heathenism&#44; supplanted the worship of the One<lb/> God&#44; and the populace were goaded on to sin by the<lb/> conduct of their Chief rulers&#44; a happy change could not<lb/> be realized.  But he knew well that to prevent his design<lb/> being miscarried&#44; the extremest caution was necessary.<lb/>  For had it been divulged too early&#44; the saved child and<lb/> many interested in his future elevation&#44; would have become<lb/> involved in a common ruin.  He therefore worked covertly and with prudence&#44; abiding his time<lb/> for six years.  In the seventh he confided with five trust&#45;<lb/>worthy personages&#44; to whom he showed the Prince.  He<lb/> charged them to journey through the land&#44; and seek among<lb/> the principal men of the nation Judah staunch adherents to the<lb/> national cause.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Having thus far matured his project&#44; and brought<lb/> over to it many of the Levites&#44; and prominent heads of<lb/> families&#44; he assembled the multitude in the courts of the<lb/> Sanctuary&#44; divided them into three companies&#44; furnished<lb/> them with arms&#44; and made them solemnly swear that<lb/> they would defend the claims of their legitimate king<lb/> against the usurpation of Ahab&#39;s murderous daughter.<lb/>  He then proceeded to <sic>annoint</sic> the yet infant Joash&#44; and<lb/> adorning his brow with the crown of his ancestors&#44; proclaimed<lb/> him ruler of Judah.  Like an electric shock&#44; the<lb/> impetus given by the patriotic priest was experienced among<lb/> all classes.  They rallied round the standard&#44; typical of<lb/> order&#44; virtue and sincerity.  At the loud burst of voices&#44;<lb/> which exclaimed &#34;long live the King&#34; Athalia hastened to the<lb/> Temple.  She breathed threats and as she entered&#44; but and looking on the imposing scene<lb/> presented offered to view&#44; cried &#34;treason&#44; treason&#34;.  But the measure of her<lb/> iniquities was full.  She who had trampled under foot<lb/> the commands of the Most High&#44; was ignominiously forcibly<lb/> thrust out of his holy house.  She who had ruthlessly inhumanly<lb/> massacred the innocent was delivered to the pitiless sword.<lb/>  Yet&#44; the work of Johoiada was incorup but commenced.<lb/>  His aim had not been merely to vindicate right&#44; but<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>to correct wrongs.  Since the decease of Jehoshaphat&#44;<lb/> the people had <sic>revelled</sic> in licentiousness paganism.  The<lb/> gates of Jerusalem once thronged with sincere <sic>worshippers</sic><lb/> had been deserted.  The daily sacrifices&#44; were either neglected&#44;<lb/> or immolated by impure hands.  No respect was paid<lb/> to the moral ordinances enjoined in the heavenly volumes&#44;<lb/> a pandering to the vices of the great was the predominant<lb/> wish.  Jehoiada appealed to the minds and feelings<lb/> of his brethren&#44; and by the mighty influence exercised&#44;<lb/> gradually weaned them from vicious and irreligious habits.<lb/>  He created enthusiasm&#44; where apathy had chilled all senti&#45;<lb/>&#45;ments of goodness rectitude.  He reconstructed a declining race upon<lb/> the foundations of righteousness.  He drew a voluntary<lb/> declaration that they would obey the ordinances of the Al&#45;<lb/>&#45;mighty&#44; while they owned allegiance to the Sovereign<lb/> who was to be the exponent of the ancient Law.  Defection<lb/> ceased&#44; <sic>apostacy</sic> became an unmeaning word through the<lb/> teaching and example of that saintly priest.  The internal<lb/> arrangement was reestablished as in the days of Solomon.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>And during the minority of Joash&#44; the wise go&#45;<lb/>&#45;vernment of the regent erased the vestiges of a long misrule.<lb/>  But how beneficial to the youthful king was that school<lb/> of human perfection&#33;  When the hour arrived that he could<lb/> hold unaided the royal sceptre&#44; he had learnt fittingly<lb/> to wield it.  The first illustration which the monarch of Judah illustrated gave of his early<lb/> training in religion was by reforming abuses crept among the officials at<lb/> the Sanctuary&#44; by his devoted attention to the interests of the dwel&#45;<lb/>&#45;ling of the Lord&#44; and by awakening a new spirit in his subjects<lb/> to annually bring in the half&#45;shekel intended by Moses<lb/> as a national contribution for the maintenance of public<lb/> worship.  It is&#44; my Brethren&#33; the last&#45;named<lb/> direction given by that monarch king of Judah&#44; which suggested to our<lb/> sages the portion of the prophets we have read&#44; as the <sic>ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;priate</sic> Haftorah of this Sabbath.  For presented in the month<lb/> of Adar&#44; our ancestors were accustomed to offer that coin<lb/> by which the expenditure of the ensuing civil year&#44; begin&#45;<lb/>&#45;ning in Nissan&#44; might be defrayed.  At present&#44; we<lb/> cannot use our half&#45;shekel for the purpose described.<lb/>  Still&#44; in other lands where our brethren are scattered&#44; the<lb/> practice continues as a memorial of the past&#44; and the<lb/> amount is either employed to keep the Synagogue in repair<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p>or it is distributed among the poor.  I leave with you<lb/> to decide whether their example needs&#44; in this instance<lb/> be copied&#59; but what I desire that you will closely<lb/> imitate is the model which the characters of the pious<lb/> Johoiada and his virtuous wife have set before our vision.<lb/>  Praise to be to God&#58; notwithstanding the dereliction of many<lb/> Hebrews from duty&#44; none of us&#44; however exalted&#44; is called<lb/> upon to work for such changes&#44; as were needful in<lb/> that stage of Jewish history to which I have alluded.<lb/>  Exile and the wise prescriptions of the Rabbis have<lb/> corrected many grave errors into which our fathers were<lb/> apt to fall.  Nevertheless as parents and as instructors&#44;<lb/> our responsibility is very great&#44; and we ought to be fully<lb/> alive to that truth&#44; so as to shape our conduct in a<lb/> manner that they who see it constantly may not<lb/> be tainted with blemishes copied from ourselves.<lb/>  But also as social beings&#44; irrespective of our obligations<lb/> as fathers and teachers&#44; it is incumbent upon us to guard<lb/> against moral imperfections.  Communities&#44; are but an<lb/> aggregate body of beings&#44; and heedlessness regarding<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="14"/>
            <p>the rules of probity and religion&#44; extending from one<lb/> circle to another&#44; may by degrees mischievously affect<lb/> the whole society.  Let us then&#44; my Brethren&#44; each<lb/> in his own sphere&#44; exhibit a conduct&#44; which may stand<lb/> the severest scrutiny&#44; a life above reproach&#44; and<lb/> habits exemplary for piety&#44; and wide&#45;spread beneficence.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
