<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF13_4</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_12_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_12_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_12_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_12_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_12_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_12_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_12_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_12_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_12_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_12_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_12_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_12_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_12_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_12_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_12_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_12_8v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_12_9r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_12_9v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_12_10r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_12_10v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>15 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Morton Mc Michael p. 12<lb/></p>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>
                About Doctors&#39; pride and dissensions<lb/>
                with a few words in memoriam<lb/>
                M Mc M.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  Among the many lessons&#44; which the<lb/> history of Joseph&#45;&#45;just brought to a close&#45;&#45;imparts&#44;<lb/> one is so forcible&#44; that its weight ought to be felt by<lb/> all human beings&#44; but specially by such as have been<lb/> called upon to tend congregations.  The magnanimous<lb/> son of Jacob had tied to remove very gently to remove the thorn&#44;<lb/> which pricked his brothers with remorse.  Super&#45;<lb/>&#45;humanly generous&#44; he would inspire the belief&#44; that<lb/> the ill&#45;will they had once harbored&#44; was the working of<lb/> a higher Power&#44; for the realization of a blessed end.<lb/>  But the softening words of the viceroy of Egypt&#44;<lb/> could not silence altogether the voice of conscience.<lb/>  His discerning eye&#44; could read the reproaches of the in&#45;<lb/>&#45;ternal monitor upon the countenances of the men he<lb/> affectionately addressed.  Joseph had reasons to<lb/> fear that as soon as his absence relieved his brothers<lb/> from restraint&#44; they would jointly turn to the past.<lb/>  Reuben would then proclaim himself innocent&#44; and<lb/> accuse the others of crime.  Judah would palliate<lb/> his sin by a declaration that he did not know Reuben&#39;s<lb/> intention&#59; that he only aimed to save the lad from an<lb/></p> 
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>unnatural death determined upon by the rest.<lb/>  The anxiety of each to appear less guilty than in<lb/> reality before the hoary&#45;headed father&#44; might have led<lb/>to a quarrel&#44; in which all would have been involved.<lb/>  Hence the fitting advice &#34;Do not fall out by the<lb/> way&#44;&#34; that is&#44; avoid entirely criminations and re&#45;<lb/>&#45;criminations&#44; so that the slightest cause for dispute<lb/> be not raised.  Would to God it were<lb/> in our power always to act up to that excellent<lb/> counsel&#33;  Paradise might be enjoyed on<lb/> earth&#44; if <sic>uggly</sic> passions&#45;&#45;the offspring of heedlessly<lb/> spoken words&#45;&#45;could be put under absolute check.<lb/>  But then&#44; again&#44; all around should feel bound to<lb/> exercise that control&#44; and what is more to the<lb/> point&#44; but almost impossible to be anticipated&#45;&#45;&#44; all<lb/> should have a proper appreciation of what justice and<lb/> truth demand.  With the possession of that sentiment<lb/> contentions would surely cease.  But to hear wrong<lb/> defended&#44; to see falsehood prevail&#44; and remain pas&#45;<lb/>&#45;sionless&#44; is to surrender one&#39;s manhood.  For my part&#44;<lb/> as I sometime do find that my nature is about to<lb/> rebel against the direction of the good Joseph&#44; I<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>eagerly wish I could follow that of King David.<lb/>  Aye&#58; keep my mouth muzzled&#44; not to utter<lb/> a single word when that at which my soul revolts&#44;<lb/> is boldly set out.  Nor otherwise&#44; can I behold<lb/> treason in the Jewish camp&#44; without rebuking it.<lb/>  Not otherwise can I listen to the plots of the faith&#45;<lb/>&#45;less and continue silent.  Oh&#44; my Brethren<lb/> to you I may pour out my complaints.<lb/></p>
            <p>A youth surcharged with the fire of enthusiasm about<lb/> his utopian schemes&#44; but icy cold touching the grand history<lb/> tents and tendencies of his fathers&#39; belief&#44; preaches a<lb/> crusade against revelation.  but his more aged oppo&#45;<lb/>&#45;nents&#44; pretending to cross his designs&#44; stir him afresh&#44;<lb/> help him on in the work of destruction.  The<lb/> daring prophet who fortells the dissolution of Ju&#45;<lb/>daism&#44; must needs feel encourage&#44; when they<lb/> who were sworn to keep it alive and vigorous&#44; with&#45;<lb/>&#45;hold their hands&#44; when they say to the daughter of heaven&#44;<lb/> imploring their help &#34;bygone&#44; we know thee not.&#34;<lb/>  Yes&#44; the adjured priests forget the day in which they<lb/> accepted the offer of a ministerial relic&#44; implying<lb/></p> 
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>fidelity to the Sinaic constitution&#44; else they would<lb/> not brand with reproach the very same brethren who<lb/> chose them with confiding trust as guardians of the<lb/> Law.  They would not insult the suffering of<lb/> creatures&#45;&#45;their own flesh and blood&#45;&#45;who will<lb/> not part at any cost with the sacred books&#44; though<lb/> these bear the marks of times long bygone.  For&#44;<lb/> what means the assurance of Rabbis to their &#34;dear<lb/> Christian brethren&#44; that old Judaism is on the point<lb/> of death&#63;&#34; and a modern Judaism has already ad&#45;<lb/>&#45;ministered the extreme unction&#63;  Must the<lb/> writings of Moses&#44; the prophets&#44; and the Rabbis to<lb/> boot&#44; be blotted out and their lovers be hooted at&#63;<lb/>  Must a humanitarian constitution&#44; which the world<lb/> is yet ill prepared to receive take the place of the<lb/> inspired volumes&#63;  Must that which the Psalmist<lb/> describes as supremely wise and righteous and which<lb/> has been to us&#44; like unto him&#44; a support&#44; standard<lb/> and comfort&#59; be read for curiosity sake&#44; never to draw<lb/> therefrom wholesome instruction&#44; and carry the same<lb/> into practice&#63;  Ah&#33; that I could guard my<lb/> mouth with a muzzle&#44; not to speak evil of men<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>I wish always to treat with consideration&#44; since<lb/> unless so restrained&#44; I can scarce resist the tempt&#45;<lb/>&#45;ation to full out by the way.  Surely&#44; individuals<lb/> who ought to be looked upon as representatives of the<lb/> golden rule &#34;seek peace and promote it&#44;&#34; should not<lb/> scandalize the community with their wranglings.<lb/>  Too well I know the harm which ministerial squab&#45;<lb/>&#45;bles create.  It is the experience of many&#45;&#45;not at all<lb/> fault finders&#44; not <sic>cavillers</sic>&#44; aiming to damage the<lb/> cause of Israel&#39;s religion&#44;&#45;&#45;but of conscientious and sober<lb/> minded individuals&#59; it is their experience&#44; I say&#44;<lb/> that the incompatibility of temperaments among such<lb/> as ought to labor harmoniously for a good cause has brought our faith<lb/> into disrepute&#44; and contributed largely to estrange<lb/> therefrom the rising generation.  Proofs are not<lb/> wanting.  I can unfortunately&#44; supply them myself&#44;<lb/> and I will cite one even at the risk of being egotisti&#45;<lb/>&#45;cal.  When I last summer <sic>travelled</sic> as far as<lb/> Ohio&#44; I had but a single object in view&#44; To ascertain<lb/> by personal inspection whether a school for training<lb/> our future teachers was a reality&#44; or whether we in<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>the East had been deceived by the ambition of one<lb/> man&#44; and the ignorance of his dupes throughout the<lb/> West.  Only to respond understandingly to<lb/> inquiries about a subject of national value&#44;<lb/> I accepted with extreme reluctance and after re&#45;<lb/>&#45;peated solicitations the charge of examining the<lb/> pupils of that high school.  But I was not alone&#44;<lb/> others took part in the proceedings&#44; and to them I sub&#45;<lb/>&#45;mitted my daily observations.  Finally&#44; the time<lb/> arrived for drawing the report&#44; and as the chairman<lb/> of the committee had been called away&#44; I was requested<lb/> to prepare the document.  With that commission<lb/> my trials began.  For one of my colleagues&#45;&#45;a clergy&#45;<lb/>&#45;man&#45;&#45;determined I should not accomplish my<lb/> task.  Hindrances were put in the way to em&#45;<lb/>barass and perplex all my doings&#44; regardless of the<lb/> baneful impressions&#44; resulting from such a demeanour.<lb/>  Was it petty jealousy&#44; temper&#44; or an overweening<lb/> opinion of one&#39;s superiority&#63;  I did not stop to ask<lb/> for the motive&#44; I succeeded&#44; to my satisfaction&#44; in<lb/> that instance at least&#44; to hold before my eyes the<lb/> directions of both Joseph and David.  I hastened<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>home to perform the duty I had been assigned&#44; with&#45;<lb/>&#45;out being harassed&#44; and to prevent a general experience<lb/> from receiving confirmation by any incautious act on<lb/> my part.  For it was it intimated&#44; there and then<lb/> and in my own presence&#44; that ministers meet but<lb/> to disagree.<lb/></p>
            <p>Now&#44; I had greatly hoped that the occasion which<lb/> recently brought various Doctors together in this city<lb/> of love&#44; would have proved a signal exception.  It concerned<lb/> the establishing of a course of studies&#44; most fit to<lb/> give the minds of Hebrew students a healthful<lb/> bent&#59; a course best qualified to make the future<lb/> teachers in Israel the right interpreters of the Law<lb/> and traditions.  You will then realize the im&#45;<lb/>&#45;portance of the undertaking.  A place had been<lb/> prepared and submitted by a Rabbi who had a<lb/> prior claim to being heard&#44; because he labored indefa&#45;<lb/>&#45;tigably to create a spirit which did not exist&#44;<lb/> to propagate it&#44; to raise means&#44; to procure pupils&#44;<lb/> and to gratuitously impart knowledge in the new institution<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>That the plan was defective&#44; it may be confessed&#44;<lb/> that others were capable of improving upon it may<lb/> be admitted.  No one disputes the advisability of<lb/> letting two or three or more documents be written and<lb/> discussed&#44; so that perfection might be reached or<lb/> approached.  But how wrong&#44; how culpable for<lb/> any to insist that his scheme shall be accepted in<lb/> preference to all others&#44; that the propositions he<lb/> makes shall receive unanimous compliance&#44; that<lb/> what he suggests become a controlling rule hereafter&#33;<lb/>  Yet&#44; that act of arbitrariness was attempted.<lb/>  A Rabbi&#45;&#45;for they are all Rabbis&#44; though violating<lb/> the very fundamental principles of Rabbinism&#44;<lb/> a Rabbi voted for his radical opposition to the laws<lb/> not alone of the Talmud&#44; but of the Bible&#44; tried to<lb/> challenge obedience to his rationalistic notions.<lb/>  How far he carried his point I am unable to tell.<lb/>  Possibly&#44; the desire of the meeting not to prolong<lb/> an unpleasant contest&#44; may have gained the dispu&#45;<lb/>&#45;tant some advantage.  But I trust&#44; and I have<lb/> reason to think&#45;&#45;he did not come off altogether victorious.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Still&#44; my feelings impell me to declare&#44; that if his<lb/> views destructive of historical and traditional Judaism<lb/> should at any time become the standard of the West&#45;<lb/>&#45;ern college&#44; I will ever lament the fusion with the<lb/> East&#44; over which on the first day of our New Year<lb/> I publicly rejoiced.  For what is now a mere<lb/> doubt&#44; will assume the form of a fearful re&#45;<lb/>&#45;ality.  Judasim transformed into free religionism&#44;<lb/> will be preached on the pulpits which our future<lb/> guides shall ascend.  The intolerant liberals will<lb/> gain a supremacy fatal to conservatism.  To<lb/> remain an adherent of ceremonial injunctions will be<lb/> to elicit the derision of the Hebrew community.<lb/>  If I am then alive on this side of the grave&#44; I<lb/> shall brave that contempt&#44; though were I to be<lb/> spitted upon&#44; but I shall weep&#44; because like Esther&#44;<lb/> I cannot look unconcerned on the evil befalling my<lb/> people.  Our college&#45;graduates will have studied<lb/> the Scriptures&#44; not to elieve with Malachi that<lb/> Moses was appointed in Horeb to lay down statutes<lb/> and ordinances for all Israel&#44; but to assure our<lb/> children that some unknown has palmed upon them off<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>Assyrians&#44; Egyptian and Persian rules for<lb/> inspired behests.  Our college&#45;graduates will<lb/> have learnt Talmud&#44; not to seek the lessons which<lb/> the noblest among our progenitors gathered&#44; but to<lb/> imitate the recreant Pfeffercorn and Eisenmenger<lb/> who accused an encyclopedia of wonderful knowledge<lb/> of being an agency of demoralization effects spirit.  Our college students<lb/> graduates will have fathomed Jewish philosophy&#44; not<lb/> to bring about a reconciliation between the theosophy<lb/> of the son of Amram and that of Socrates and Plato&#44;<lb/> but to dethrone the wisdom of our seers and set up fal&#45;<lb/>&#45;lible Reason.  Our college&#45;graduates will exchange<lb/> pulpits with Christian divines&#44; in the hopes of effect<lb/>ing a change among trinitarians&#44; but the adherents<lb/> of the Unity destitute of the support which a &#91;&#63;&#93;<lb/> Jewish life affords&#44; will be drawn after the largest<lb/> majority&#44; to be lost amidst their number.  No&#58;<lb/> the Messianic era has not arrived.  All creatures<lb/> are not ready to make common cause with us&#44; to<lb/> bend the knee before the One uncreated God.  The mis&#45;<lb/>&#45;sion of Israel cannot be fulfilled by currying favor<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>with gentilism&#44; but by an earnest and dignified at&#45;<lb/>&#45;tachment to the practices of old Judaism.<lb/></p>
                <p>Upon my youthful brethren who unfold the pages<lb/> of our holy books&#44; upon them I call who aspire to<lb/> the honorable but onerous office of spiritual guides.  In<lb/> them I trust for the salvation of a small residue.  Be<lb/> not inveigled by the seductive teachings of modern<lb/> Doctors.  Rabbi Meir had sat at the feet of a Master&#44;<lb/> whose erudition did not save him from defection&#44;<lb/> but the scholar&#39;s own discernment found the right<lb/> among the false&#44; or&#44; to say it with the Talmudists&#44; of<lb/> the pomegranate offered to his acceptance&#44; he sucked<lb/> the sweet juice&#44; but cast off the acid skin and the<lb/> outer rind.  Hebrew students need now a<lb/> days that discernment&#44; to take an independent stand<lb/> and fearlessly proclaim the sanctity of a religion which<lb/> has survived the wreck of Kingdoms&#44; because it<lb/> contains the strongest elements for self&#45;preservation&#44;<lb/> Truth&#44; allied with Peace and goodwill to man.<lb/>  Rigorous towards its adherents&#44; it is eminently tolerant<lb/> towards non&#45;Israelites&#44; social in its tendencies<lb/> to a very high degree.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p>The religion of Israel that breathes a spirit of<lb/> brotherhood towards all the creatures of the univer&#45;<lb/>&#45;sal Parent&#44; teaches us to recognize goodness where&#45;<lb/>ever it exists&#44; and to be thankful <sic>therefor</sic>.<lb/></p>
            <p>I avail myself of this broadness of principles enun&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciated on the wilderness of Sinai&#44; and exemplified<lb/> by the prophets and Sages of the Hebrew race to per&#45;<lb/>&#45;form an act of justice&#44; which ministerial duty<lb/> has often before demanded at my hands.  I wish<lb/> to pay a last tribute of respect to a Philadephian&#44;<lb/> not born in our faith&#44; but whose memory ought to<lb/> be enshrined among those who cling to the belief in<lb/> the Unity.  Morton McMichael in his private<lb/> and public capacity&#44; showed unmistakably the enlarged<lb/> views that guided his well spent existence.<lb/></p>
            <p>It was my fortune to have met him at the house of<lb/> representative Israelites Jews and the pressure of his hand&#44;<lb/> that general converse&#44; unrestrained and familiar&#44; betokened<lb/> the real friend.  It was my pleasure to have<lb/> heard him plead the cause of charity and education<lb/> on repeated occasions&#44; in behalf of his Jewish fellow&#45;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="14"/>
            <p>citizens&#44; and his language surpassingly eloquent&#44;<lb/> but exceedingly chaste&#44; stamped his words with the<lb/> seal of sincerity.  The Nestor of journalism<lb/> in the city of his pride&#45;&#45;a city which his pen and<lb/> personal influence beautified and exalted&#45;&#45;&#44; never<lb/> allowed the name we bear to be aspersed.  If a<lb/> report injuring our reputation crept in the &#34;North<lb/> American&#34; without his knowledge&#44; the editor would<lb/> <sic>fortwith</sic> open its columns that a reparation might<lb/> be amply made.  The civic virtues&#59; the men&#45;<lb/>tal wealth which gave the son of Pennsylvania high<lb/> distinction&#44; have been and will doubtless be further<lb/> dilated upon&#45;&#45;by those who enjoyed his intimacy<lb/> with all the pathos and favor of diction the sub&#45;<lb/>&#45;ject dictates.  It is not my intention to pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;nounce a panegyric.  My insufficient acquaintance<lb/> with the deceased&#44; and my practice to be sparing of<lb/> posthumous commendations&#44; unfit me for the task.<lb/>  But gratitude to the Almighty Being&#44; from whom<lb/> whatever is noble in man emanates&#44; has impelled<lb/> me to mention with praise a public servant&#44; who<lb/> worked steadily and unobtrusively&#59; a minister<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="15"/>
            <p>of God&#39;s will&#44; who employed his rare gifts to<lb/> sow the seeds of goodness and peace.<lb/>  My the illustrious dead find a recompense<lb/> among the righteous of all nations and creeds&#44;<lb/> and may his spiritual joys be enhanced at<lb/> the contemplation of that increasing prosperity<lb/> which he sought and labored for to procure<lb/> for the Keystone state of our union.  To the re&#45;<lb/>&#45;newal of that prosperity we all anxiously look&#44; for<lb/> we feel that our interests&#44; the <sic>tranquillity</sic> of our<lb/> friends&#44; the continuance of our civil and religious<lb/> liberties as Israelites&#44; greatly depend on the welfare<lb/> of the place in which our lot was Providentially<lb/> cast.  May God&#39;s choice blessings rest there&#45;<lb/>&#45;upon and give it perpetuity and glory<lb/>  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
