<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF2_14</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_14_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_14_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_14_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_14_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_14_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_14_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_14_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_14_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_14_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_14_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_14_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_14_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_14_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_14_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_14_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_14_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For Penitential Sabbath &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;I raised over you watchmen&#44; &#40;saying&#41; &#34;Listen to the sound<lb/> of the cornet&#44; but  they said &#34;We will not listen.&#34;<lb/>  In this language&#44; Jeremiah expressed the recklessness<lb/> shown by the Hebrews of his time.  The divine light&#44;<lb/> which illumined his mind&#44; made him see in the com&#45;<lb/>&#45;mission of barefaced crimes&#44; a sure downfall&#44; and to<lb/> avert it&#44; he exercised all the powers of his soul&#44; and<lb/> that touching eloquence&#44; by for which he was so distinguished.<lb/>  But when those he urged to hearken to exhortations&#44;<lb/> answered without any sense of shame &#34;will We will not<lb/> listen&#34;&#44; then&#44; he thundered forth&#44; and declared such<lb/> beyond the reach of heavenly grace.<lb/></p>
            <p>Dear Brethren&#33;  The sound of prophetic warning has<lb/> last long ceased to be heard.  The righteous men&#44; to whom<lb/> God imparted His will&#44; instruct us no more&#44; im&#45;<lb/>&#45;mediately&#44; with the lessons of their inspired wisdom.<lb/>  But let no one imagine that because the celestial<lb/> direction has been withdrawn&#44; we have therefore<lb/> been left without a guide.  An angel now<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>accompanies Israel throughout their earthly<lb/> journey write the Rabbis in their figures of speech.  It is conscience.  When after having<lb/> neglected duty&#44; or after having become guilty of<lb/> some misdeeds&#44; we experience an inward agitation&#44;<lb/> the &#34;still small voice&#34; which reproves us&#44; is that of<lb/> the angel conscience.  And if awakened by it to<lb/> the necessity of regulating our lives after the rules<lb/> laid down by sainted men&#44; we may properly assert<lb/> that conscience has held us up&#44; and prevented our<lb/> ruin.  That accompanying angel assures therefore<lb/> a twofold character.  It is admonitory and corrective.<lb/>  To a the once wicked Menasseh&#44; humbled to the dust&#44;<lb/> and of broken spirit&#44; it promises a renewal of strength.<lb/>  But how does it happen&#44; that we&#44; having at our side&#44;<lb/> one an object mentor that gives constant good counsel&#44; proceed never&#45;<lb/>&#45;theless disordelry&#44; like a ship without rudder&#44; tossed<lb/> about by contrary winds&#63;  Attend&#44; and hear my<lb/> explanation.<lb/></p>
            <p>Among the strange rites <sic>practised</sic> by olden nations&#44;<lb/> one exceeded all in brutality.  It was the homage<lb/> paid to Molock.  That horrid idol&#44; shaped<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>in human form &#40;except his head&#41; was set up highly.<lb/>  It extended its brazen arms&#44; as if inviting its followers<lb/> to receive a lasting ent embrace.  But a blazing fire<lb/> hidden underneath&#44; heated its hollow breast.  Shocking<lb/> sight&#33;  Tender mothers&#44; deposited in it&#44; as a token<lb/> of reverence&#44; their darling babes.  Meanwhile all the<lb/> neighborhood&#44; echoed with the sound of a thousand instru&#45;<lb/>&#45;ments.  They drowned the shrieks of the agonizing<lb/> victims&#44; and rendered the offering less harrowing to<lb/> maternal feelings.  Now&#44; I fear that the con&#45;<lb/>&#45;duct of many of us&#44; professing Judaism&#44; may bear<lb/> some cop comparison with that heathen worship.<lb/>  Self&#45;interest uncontrolled&#44; is the idol to which we<lb/> sacrifice much which is dear and lovely.  I have said<lb/> &#34;uncontrolled&#34;&#44; because self&#45;interest&#44; like self&#45;love&#44;<lb/> when within correct bounds&#44; is a blessing feeling stirring us<lb/> up to activity&#44; and capable of working out our happiness.<lb/>  It is only when it overpowers all other sentiments&#44; that<lb/> it turns a blessing into a curse.  Then it proves the Moloch<lb/> at whose unholy altar we worship.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>The spirit within&#44; which is God&#39;s most precious<lb/> gift&#44; cries aloud piercingly&#44; but we say &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;We will not listen&#44;&#34; and to make those cries inaudible&#44;<lb/> we raise a deafening noise around us.  Business and<lb/> pleasure create that tumult.  Incessant affairs&#44; the<lb/> devising of new schemes&#44; the excitement of attending the<lb/> prospect of success&#59; then&#44; the indulging in diversions&#44;<lb/> which vary with each season&#44; and each circle of<lb/> acquaintances&#44; all this din which we raise set up&#44; drowns the<lb/> lamentations of our conscience.  To listen to them&#44; might<lb/> be to lose in the opinion of our associates&#44; to lessen<lb/> the number of our admirers&#59; that gorgeous parlor<lb/> might be shut against us&#44; that carriage and four<lb/> might no longer be placed at our disposal.  Aye&#58;<lb/> self&#45;interest uncontrolled is the Molock to which many<lb/> sacrifice the offspring of their intellects of and of their<lb/> hearts.  Its open arms seduce us&#44; and we lay in its<lb/> hollow breast&#44; what is good and ennobling to our<lb/> nature.  That sentiment of kindly consideration we<lb/> should cherish for one another&#44; the wish that all may<lb/> labor&#44; like ourselves&#44; for their future welfare&#44; that every human<lb/> beings may receive from us help to rise and shine in the community&#44; all our<lb/> best instincts are consumed in that idol&#39;s hidden fire.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Even the affection esteem we had conceived for a fellow&#45;creature<lb/> is at times withered therein.  Let an undertaking from<lb/> which we anticipated to derive the exclusive advantage&#44;<lb/> be bring another also some profit&#44; and not unfrequently<lb/> the hearts which mutual affections love regard had knit together<lb/> will be sundered apart.  Peaceably dwelt Isaac among<lb/> the people of Gerar.  The amicable feelings&#44; which<lb/> circumstances appeared to have cemented between himself<lb/> and the ruler of that country&#44; promised him the unmo&#45;<lb/>&#45;lested enjoyment of his hard&#45;earned possessions.  But<lb/> the sight of those riches&#44; converted amity into enmity.<lb/>  The same king who had singled out the patriarch&#44; as an<lb/> object of his peculiar regard&#44; bid him leave his territories&#44;<lb/> when he fancied that to allow him to sojourn there&#44;<lb/> would injure his interest.  But that which<lb/> above all&#44; cannot be sufficiently deplored&#44; is the<lb/> discord which a sentiment so baneful sows among<lb/> the members of the same household.  Uncontrolled<lb/> self&#45;interest will tear asunder the holiest family ties.<lb/>  Brothers have been heard reviling brothers&#44; fathers and<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>sons have been seen most unnaturally set against<lb/> each other.  Yes&#58; the revolting manner in which self&#45;<lb/>interest can dry up the sources of inborn affection&#44;<lb/> has been witnessed&#44; as an illustration of the gloomy<lb/> picture left by the prophet&#44; in which &#34;a son vilifies<lb/> his father&#44; a daughter rises against her own mother&#44;<lb/>...and a man&#39;s enemies are the inmates of his dwelling&#45;place.&#34;<lb/>  Conscience outraged&#44; will would occasionally lift up its voice<lb/> and utter reproaches&#44; but we will try to suppress it by<lb/> the commotion which worldly objects raise about us was set up.<lb/>  But can we always succeed in hushing our internal monster&#63;  Will that undaunted its upbraidings<lb/> monster remain ab for ever unheard&#63;  Ask it&#44; my<lb/> friends&#33; of those brothers whom jo jealousy stirred up<lb/> to commit an unnatural crime.  See them&#44; who knew<lb/> not fear&#44; quake at the recollection recalling recollection of an<lb/> even perhaps long&#45;forgotten &#34;We are guilty&#44; because<lb/> of our brother&#44;&#34; they exclaim&#59; &#34;for we saw the distress<lb/> of his soul when he entreated us&#44; and we would not<lb/> listen&#44; therefore has this trouble come upon us&#34;.<lb/>  Aye&#58; when some startling event happens&#44; then every<lb/> attempt to keep hush the upbraiding silence conscience is useless.<lb/>  Then our misdoings are arrayed pictured brought back to us in their naked hideousness.<lb/>  The fall faults which we would ordinarily gloss over<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>or look upon with indifference&#44; assume their<lb/> true character&#44; and we would fain recall the past&#44;<lb/> so that instead of having said to the remonstrances of<lb/> our inward angel &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;We will not listen&#44;&#34; we<lb/> might say &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;We will do and obey&#34;.<lb/>  It cannot be denied&#44; however&#44; that men are very inventive<lb/> in finding extenuating circumstances for their transgressions&#44;<lb/> specially so&#44; if these related to the neglect of duty as<lb/> children of the covenant made with Israel&#39;s God.<lb/>  Self&#45;interest will&#44; again&#44; hasten to their assistance.<lb/>  The extensiveness of their commercial enterprises&#44; the<lb/> constant desire and on their time&#44; the great  large number<lb/> of their dependents&#44; all these and more pretexts besides&#44;<lb/> will be brought forth&#44; as precluding altogether the<lb/> discharge of religious observances.  Frequently<lb/> also they have recourse to a still speedier method&#44; to<lb/> justify their disregard for the commands.  They have<lb/> discovered&#44; so they presume&#44; the true objects origin of Mosaic<lb/> prescriptions.  This&#44; was ordained for a to promote a<lb/> certain end&#44; which is no longer attainable.  Another<lb/> had its origin in emanation from circumstances&#44; which have ceased to<lb/> exist.  A third&#44; was a sanitary regulation suitable to<lb/> different other climates and countries.  A fourth&#44; agreed only<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>with a different state of society&#44; and so thus is every ordinance<lb/> of a book&#44; whose acceptance gives us the name we bear&#44;<lb/> explained away.  So true is the maxim&#44; that the way<lb/> which a man chooses&#44; is right in his own eyes&#44;&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> but the u conclusion of that sentence is not less true<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; &#34;but the Lord searches the hearts.&#34;  To men&#44;<lb/> like ourselves&#44; we may offer so such reasons in defence of<lb/> our conduct&#59; to men who look with carnal eyes&#44; but we<lb/> cannot so deceive Him who penetrates every recondite<lb/> thought.  He will detect that it is not because of<lb/> our legitimate callings that we spurn the Torah&#59; it is not because<lb/> we are so exceedingly wise&#44; that we give each precept<lb/> and statutes an aim and a purport&#59; but because self&#45;<lb/>interest&#44; which promises material gain&#44; or wanton pleasures&#44;<lb/> has a higher value in our estimation than all the rec<lb/> ordinances of religion.  God will detect also the insincerity<lb/> of many of us in appearing before Him at this season&#44;<lb/> burdened with all the imperfections&#44; from which we do<lb/> not intend to be relieved.  He will detect that if we<lb/> could not summon courage a few days ago to<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>answer to the demands of conscience &#34;We will not<lb/> hearken listen&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; we were ready to let them go un&#45;<lb/>&#45;heeded very soon after&#44; without compunction.<lb/>  But&#44; dear Israelites&#33; to join in holy communion on Rosh<lb/> Hashanah and voluntary plunge in sin the following<lb/> Sabbath is false repentance.  It will not be accepted.<lb/>  To abstain from any food on the day of Atonement&#44; and<lb/> pollute ourselves immediately after with things called<lb/> by the Divine Legislator loathsome to a child of Israel is false<lb/> repentance.  It will not be accepted.  To listen with seeming<lb/> reverence to the word of God at the most solemn time of our year and incite our children by our<lb/> example to reject it&#44; is false repentance.  It will not be<lb/> accepted.  No&#44; let me say it.  So long as the day of<lb/> the Lord is profaned&#44; the dietary laws are trespassed against&#44;<lb/> and our offspring cast away Holy Writ &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> as a valueless object&#44; we cannot stand purified in the<lb/> presence of our forgiving Parent.  Hebrews&#33;  Brethren&#33;<lb/>  Let the voice of the internal monitor given for our<lb/> escort&#44; be heard.  It will point t out how by seeking an<lb/> imaginary interest we lost that which our im&#45;<lb/>&#45;mortal souls long after.  The How by looking for the<lb/> gratification of the senses&#44; we let the spirit hunger<lb/> for that demanded by its high nature<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>This duty we owe to ourselves&#44; to our sons and daughters&#59;<lb/> we owe it to our brethren at large more than any com&#45;<lb/>&#45;munity among the outcasts of Judah.  See&#91;&#63;&#93; the enemies<lb/> of freedom&#44; boastingly cite us as an exemplification of<lb/> their erroneous belief.  They assert that liberty and piety<lb/> are incompatible.  That to keep Israel within the bounds<lb/> of the law&#44; they must be weighed down with oppression.<lb/>  It rests with us&#44; to refute that fallacious reasoning.<lb/>  To prove that the religion of Sinai is a religion of light&#44;<lb/> that when it inhales the exhilarating air of freedom<lb/> it thrives&#44; it expands&#59; that its banner is raised aloft&#44;<lb/> when the hands that carry it are unfettered.<lb/></p>
            <p>What glory you will then shed upon our sacred faith&#33;<lb/>  The gentile world that now marvels at our &#91;&#63;&#93;<lb/> will acknowledge surely this is a wise and understanding<lb/> people&#34;.  But how beneficial to ourselves the result flowing<lb/> from that righteous determination.  We will be at peace<lb/> with our own conscience.  We will experience the unnut&#45;<lb/>&#45;terable delight of having bequeathed to our children<lb/> what is more valuable&#44; than the corn&#44; or the love of<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>pleasure&#45;&#45;even a pious example that will lead them<lb/> securely through the devious paths of life.  We will&#44;<lb/> above all&#44; dispel the mist which our sins have raised<lb/> between ourselves and the sin that vivifies our existence.<lb/>  His refulgent light will again irradiate our souls&#44; and<lb/> we shall enjoy a foretaste of the unalloyed happiness<lb/> reserved for those who love the Lord and observe His<lb/> precepts &#91;Hebrew&#93; Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
