<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF8_5</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1888-01" source="" attested="yes">1888</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_5_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_5_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_5_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_5_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_5_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_5_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_5_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_5_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_5_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_5_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_5_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_5_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>About Phila Jewish schools 88<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>What brought a <del>large</del> vast number of Jewish men<lb/> and women together in the afternoon of last Sunday&#63;<lb/>  The building in where they those very many met of their own accord&#44;<lb/> did not exhibit architectural beauties&#44; on which the<lb/> lovers of the Aesthetic might look with pleasure delight&#44; nor<lb/> were there carved works&#44; chiselled by masters&#44; and paint&#45;<lb/>&#45;ings that delight to gratify the taste of the judges of the fine arts.  An plain&#44;<lb/> unadorned and humble dwelling had attracted a throng.  Preachers too had<lb/> gone there wended their way thither&#44; but not they were the cause of a crowded at&#45;<lb/>&#45;tendance.  For once ordained &#91;&#63;&#93; ministers held back<lb/> their set speeches and carefully rounded sentences&#44; and<lb/> allowed the eloquence of facts&#44; rather than that of<lb/> fancy&#44; to flow unimpeded.  Scores of infants of<lb/> both sexes&#44; and somewhat older girls among the Hebrews&#44; of a somewhat older growth<lb/> made use of their deft well trained deft little hands&#44; in exercises that<lb/> quicken the senses and widen the regions of the intellect.<lb/>  Those young creatures of our race had been furnished<lb/> with fitter rooms than were they occupied heretofore&#44; and<lb/> for the first time they entered a house rented for<lb/> their <sic>accomodation</sic>&#44; and for other purposes religiously<lb/> important and temporally useful.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>The Kindergarten system which justly sensibly plays<lb/> an important prominent part in our now a days in elementary teachings&#44;<lb/> and together with plentiful household training tender management training&#44; which&#45;&#45;we must hope&#45;&#45;may<lb/> finally dispel ill&#45;founded prejudices and elevate the<lb/> position of a domestic in respectable families&#44;<lb/> are pursued in that hired building under the<lb/> direction of unmarried daughters in Israel.  One<lb/> cannot sufficiently praise the zeal of those Jewesses&#44; and because<lb/> devotion to a harmonizing an ennobling object must arouse<lb/> public sympathy&#44; therefore last Sundays&#39; recept&#45;<lb/>&#45;ion in the new premises&#44; rewarded the unselfish<lb/> labor of the persons who gave it.  The President<lb/> and all her coworkers saw in the vast large assemblage<lb/> interested in the children&#39;s exercises a merited recognition&#44; and the encou&#45;<lb/>&#45;raging promise of support.  This will be<lb/> granted&#44; and they really rightly understand what is greatly much<lb/> needed&#44; who offer of their means to institutions of<lb/> that kind and of a kindred nature in the Southern<lb/> portion of our city.  A casual visit through<lb/> its surroundings will substantiate what I plainly state&#44;<lb/> without the least tint of prejudice a perfect freedom from bias&#44; and simply<lb/> out of love for an equal wish for the welfare of my religion and people.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>A melancholy occasion took me to that<lb/> neighborhood last Sabbath morning&#44; and I felt pained at<lb/> heart&#44; while I walked and observed.  Aside<lb/> from the open and almost universal desperation<lb/> of the day of the Decalogue among brethren<lb/> who but a very short time ago bore a galling<lb/> oppression by reason of their race and belief&#44;<lb/> I contemplated the condition of small man children the very young offspring small children<lb/> of those same foreign coreligionists&#44; following menial<lb/> occupations&#44; hollowing as they <sic>hauked</sic>&#44; in ignorance<lb/> of a correct language and an elevating trade.  I<lb/> thought earnestly&#44; and asked myself whether the<lb/> honor of our faith does not imperatively demand<lb/> that we shall endeavour to raise that fast growing<lb/> element from its lowliness&#44; by infusing into it a sense of<lb/> self&#45;esteem.  I reasoned thus&#59; if we could but broaden<lb/> the sphere of the Kindergarten&#44; continuing to educate<lb/> the eye and the hand of the male offspring of our<lb/> fellow&#45;believers&#44; we might rear a generation of<lb/> men that would redeem the name of Israel<lb/> in America from many an aspersion cast upon it.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>My hearers know by that mainly by<lb/> the determined steadfast will of a member of this congregation&#59;<lb/> industrial schools were established in two different localities.<lb/>  The success has not altogether <sic>equalled</sic> the ef&#45;<lb/>&#45;forts&#44; but what of that&#63;  Are we to become<lb/> dispirited&#59; lose courage&#44; because we have been foold foiled<lb/> in some of our anticipations&#63;  To persevere in what is good&#44;<lb/> despite obstacles&#44; is manliness&#44; to conquer in<lb/> the face of impediments&#44; is true heroism.  In this<lb/> Northern locality&#44; the teaching of person training of lads into callings which<lb/> some of our most renowned sages historically pursued and highly<lb/> recommended&#44; may have gone remained unappreciated&#44; but<lb/> where thousands of Israelites&#44; born in benighted countries&#44;<lb/> now congregate&#44; that tuition may reawaken the<lb/> ancient spirit&#59; excite a love for what the Rabbis call term<lb/> honorable&#45;&#45;handicraft &#91;Hebrew&#93; and the absence of which they deprecate in the strongest terms &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  At all events&#44; I hold<lb/> it as our bounden duty to leave nothing untried<lb/> towards the accomplishment of that object.  In the<lb/> language of the Talmudists I say&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93; Thou art not ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;pected to complete the undertaking singly&#44; but neither<lb/> art thou exempt from the obligation of busying<lb/> thyself concerning it.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>And those Philadelphia Israelites who have dispensed liberally of<lb/> their wealth to mitigate the suffering of bodily<lb/> ailments&#44; will deny they refuse to act generously in order to<lb/> lessen a moral disease&#44; on which is upon the increase&#63;  I mean&#44; the evil<lb/> of a generation of peddlers uncultured and unameri&#45;<lb/>&#45;canized&#63;  Never should the charge of a Jewish in&#45;<lb/>&#45;capacity to conceive the existence of moral and spi&#45; intellectual<lb/> &#61;ritual wants&#44; be brought against us.  I long to<lb/> disprove it by through the cooperation of the rich and the intelligent philanthropic&#44; that will drawing out of its environments that<lb/> generation and aft uplift it to a higher plane&#44; still within<lb/> the pale of Judaism.  For that purpose&#44; alike<lb/> religious and mechanical industrial teachings instruction must<lb/> be imparted.  Nothing daunted by the war con&#45;<lb/>&#45;stantly waged on certain Hebrew pulpits against<lb/> the Hebrew language&#44; as effete&#44; dead exploded&#44; of no efficacy<lb/> and advantage&#44; we must preserve it.  The holiest me&#45;<lb/>&#45;mories of the past&#44; and the dearest interest of the<lb/> future to those who believe in the solidarity of our<lb/> race &#91;Hebrew&#93; bid us preserve it cherish it Therefore keep it alive among our progeny.  Hence a building<lb/> might consequently be purchased&#44; and divided arranged in<lb/> many compartments suitably agreeably to our comprehensive<lb/> plan.  It should be a veritable &#91;&#63;&#93; constitute present a well combined division of work.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>For there also besides the cultivation of the sacred language and that of mechanical trades&#44; there should exist also in that spot&#44; those premises&#44; our Sewing and Sunday schools<lb/> should offer there also spacious and well ventilated rooms<lb/> for its their ever crowding attendants.  Philadelphia<lb/> Israelites.  On the night of the third of March<lb/> of this year&#44; a celebration not to be forgotten<lb/> was held in our magnificent Academy of music.<lb/>  The assemblage was of men and women of our peo&#45;<lb/>&#45;ple was <sic>unprecedently</sic> large vast.  The orators arose<lb/> equal to the memorable Jubilee.  Enthusiasm<lb/> prevailed&#44; and I anticipated&#44; as an immediate<lb/> result of the festivity which recalled the founding of<lb/> an educational institution in our midst&#44; I anticipated the speedy realization<lb/> of the aim in view.  I shall not venture<lb/> an opinion as to the failure in raising upon the<lb/> very spot an adequate sum to effect a high<lb/> purpose.  Perhaps it was wise not to go in<lb/> quest thereof at that meeting&#44; lest strangers<lb/> to our faith deemed the action undignified.  But<lb/> this it behooves me now to say unequivocally plainly to tell.  The Southern Sunday<lb/> School&#44; where an ever swelling number of our young<lb/> sons and daughters have been wont to gather for instruction&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>has long been condemned is as unqualifiedly<lb/> unsuitable.  It has now been sold&#44; and we<lb/> need not lament the circumstance&#44; though we<lb/> may regret that the sacred purpose object for which<lb/> it was procured&#44; will suffer by reason of that<lb/> purchase.  A synagogue in such a place and<lb/> under such auspices as its services will be per&#45;<lb/>&#45;formed&#44; cannot be calculated to glorify Israel<lb/> and Israel&#39;s God.  At all events&#44; we must now<lb/> forthwith seek be active and make provision to secure ano&#45;<lb/>&#45;other building&#44; prior to the autumnal season.<lb/>  Negligence on our part&#44; would be visited as a sin<lb/> because of the deplorable issue it might bring on.<lb/>  I hold in my hand a card upon which are written<lb/> the names of six children born in our faith that were hired<lb/> into buildings where missionaries play all means<lb/> and opportunities in search of souls.  None can possibly<lb/> object to their christian ministers seeking to deliver save from destruction the<lb/> progeny of the inebriate and the wanton&#45;&#45;and they are not a<lb/> few&#45;&#45;among trinitarians.  Such exertions we will always commend&#44; as social beings and inhabitants of a noble land&#44; but the offspring of monotheists<lb/> we must care for.  We must guard them against the wiles apostasy&#44;<lb/> of propagandists and hold them intelligently in our own fold.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>In former years I rescued some form the meshes of<lb/> apostasy propagandists&#44; and I shall look to the deliverance of<lb/> others&#44; but all who love the Jewish faith must act promptly not to<lb/> encourage recreancy by an &#91;&#63;&#93; delay or neglect.<lb/>  I repeat it.  Let it never be said that Philadelphia Israelites<lb/> have thousands for the physical requirements of<lb/> their poor&#44; but not even hundreds for their mental&#44; moral<lb/> and spiritual needs.  In the scene which met<lb/> my vision last Sunday afternoon&#44; is to me I interpret as recognize a rain&#45;<lb/>&#45;bow of promise.  An appeal to the sentiment of<lb/> my brothers and sisters in faith&#44; when the Almighty<lb/> has blessed with wealth&#44; will elicit a hearty response.<lb/>  Ere a the summer shall have elapsed&#44; a<lb/> commodious structure will be seen in the Southern<lb/> portion of Philadelphia our city.  It will bear this<lb/> inscription.  Schools devoted to the dearest in&#45;<lb/>&#45;terests of the Jewish people in Philadelphia.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
