<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF2_9</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_9_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_9_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_9_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_9_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_9_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_9_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_9_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_9_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_9_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_9_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_9_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_9_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_9_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_9_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_9_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_9_8v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_9_9r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_9_9v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>15 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>A sermon on penitence<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  Have you heard the voice&#44; which from<lb/> heaven addressed us all&#63;  It cried thus &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Return O Israel&#33; unto the Lord Thy God&#33;&#34;  But....will<lb/> He receive us whom we have long forsaken&#63;  Are we<lb/> not those who yearly make to Him professions of love&#44; but<lb/> soon to relapse into our habitual inconstancy&#63;  Can we<lb/> hope that the friend&#44; whose word we have laughed to scorn&#44;<lb/> will again admit us into his favor&#63;  Aye&#58; He yearns after<lb/> our return.  He beckons us to come nigh&#44; and that we may cast ourselves<lb/> into the boundless arms of His mercy.  Hark&#33;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;I will heal their backslidings&#44; I will love them dearly.<lb/>  And what does that best of friends ask as an atonement for<lb/> our desertion&#63;  Does He demand that we tear away the<lb/> heart which has led us astray&#63; that we put out the eyes<lb/> which have lured us to dereliction&#63;  Oh&#33; Divine beneficence&#33;<lb/>  A word can effect the reconciliation.  To regain man&#39;s<lb/> estranged affection&#44; the utterance of the lips may be of no avail&#44;<lb/> but we can simply by that means appease the wrath<lb/> of God.  A &#91;Hebrew&#93; as pronounced by the adulterous King&#44;<lb/> will avert from us also the sentence of eternal death.<lb/>  Brother&#45;sinners&#33;  We need but take words with us this day&#59;<lb/> for&#44; so has the heavenly voice proclaimed &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Let those words be the breathing of a contrite spirit&#44; let<lb/> them betoken a mind that humbles itself before the wisdom<lb/> of the Supreme Legislator&#59; let them be the true expression of<lb/> sorrow for irremediable offenses&#44; and the Almighty will<lb/> gladden us with the assurance &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; &#34;that his<lb/> anger hath turned away from us&#34;.<lb/></p>
            <p>But you still doubt. You cannot believe that He who<lb/> is clothed in purity&#44; will draw us to His bosom&#44; whose gar&#45;<lb/>&#45;ments are steeped in pollution.  You remember that despite<lb/> His warning&#44; we sunk into the mire of sin&#44; and you na&#45;<lb/>&#45;turally dread his rebuke.  Follow me then and be inspired<lb/> with courage.  A murder and a robbery have<lb/> been committed.  The victim is an humble individual&#59; the<lb/> culprit a crowned head.  Prompted by avarice&#44;<lb/> Ahab would seize upon a vineyard adjoining his palace.<lb/>  It belonged to one of his subjects&#59; but the royal offer<lb/> of a compensation for its relinquishment was refused.<lb/>  Wounded pride mingled with ill&#45;suppressed anger&#44; and<lb/> Ahab could not disguise from his wife the cause of his<lb/> humiliation.  You know the sequel.  Two ungodly men<lb/> were procured&#44; and Naboth&#44; charged by them with treasonable<lb/> and blasphemous language&#44; suffered death.  What<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>could not be attained by legitimate means&#44; was<lb/> gained by confiscation.  &#34;Go and enjoy thy vineyard&#44; it<lb/> is thine own&#59; its former possessor can no more dispute thy<lb/> right to it&#34;; so spoke the wicked Jezebel.  But that<lb/> <sic>covetted</sic> vineyard&#44; became all thorns and briers and thistles.<lb/>  Shame&#44; remorse&#44; horror of the blood that cried for vengeance&#44;<lb/> laid hold of Ahab.  The words of the dauntless Elijah thrilled<lb/> his whole being.  He saw but destruction&#59; an unquenchable<lb/> fire blazed before his eyes&#44; and his brazen countenance was at<lb/> length bedewed with tears of repentance.  The all&#45;for&#45;<lb/>&#45;giving God received as an atonement his acts of contrition.<lb/>  We have not sinned so greatly.  None of us has reenacted<lb/> the atrocious deeds of that ancient Ruler&#59; nor those of which<lb/> Menasseh Sovereign of Judah became guilty.  For&#44; he<lb/> set up altars to his debauching idols in the house of<lb/> God.  He reddened the highways of Jerusalem with the<lb/> blood of the innocent&#59; he burnt his own children at the<lb/> shrine of the abominable Molock&#59; yet sacred history<lb/> records that because he finally humbled to the earth his proud spirit to<lb/> the earth&#59; because he prayed with intensity of fervour<lb/> that he might not carry beyond the grave the burden of his<lb/> inequities&#44; God heard his voice&#44; and accepted his repentance.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>And the people of Nineveh did they not purchase redem&#45;<lb/>&#45;ption by pentience&#63;  Tradition reale relates&#44; that they<lb/> were given to stealing&#44; to lying&#44; to oppressing the needy&#59;<lb/> that they outraged nature by their crimes&#44; still of them<lb/> also we read &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;God saw their deeds&#44; that<lb/> they turned from their evil way&#44; and he repented of the<lb/> evil that he had said&#44; He would do unto them&#44; and He did it not.&#34;<lb/>  But why multiply examples to show that a broken and<lb/> contrite heart God will not reject&#63;  Does the declaration<lb/> of the Most High need be corroborated&#63;  Lo&#33; He has<lb/> said it&#44; and imprinted it on the volumes of heavens inspiration.<lb/></p>
            <p>&#34;The wicked man who turneth from all his sins&#44; and keepeth<lb/> all my statutes&#44; and doeth justice and charity&#44; shall<lb/> surely live&#44; he shall not die&#59; none of his transgressions that<lb/> he hath committed shall be remembered against him&#34;.<lb/>  Oh consoling words&#33;  Oh&#33; joyous thoughts&#33;  No&#44; my Brethren&#44; be not dismayed.<lb/>  Despond not.  We have lived in sin&#44; but we shall not be cast off<lb/> from the presence of our God.  Let us say to Him &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Take away all inequity&#44; and receive us favorably&#34;<lb/> and He will answer from heaven.  Yes&#44; &#34;my &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> anger is turned away from you&#34;.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>True&#44; we have hitherto returned evil for good.  We<lb/> have used divine gifts as weapons of war against the<lb/> Lord.  The faculty of speech&#44; we should have employed<lb/> to thank its Donor for every breath we draw&#44; has been a<lb/> source of contamination.  For mere trifles we have<lb/> taken the name of the Lord our God in vain.  And how<lb/> frequently&#44; how very frequently Alas&#33; in our eagerness to<lb/> dispose of an object advantageously to ourselves&#44; we have<lb/> had recourse to an oath&#45;&#45;would it were not false&#45;&#45;ima&#45;<lb/>&#45;gining that we might thus more easily secure success.<lb/>  I am indeed painfully affected when in my daily walks<lb/> I hear striplings utter profanities with an air of<lb/> self&#45;importance&#44; and I have cause to think that<lb/> that sin lies at our door.  We are too apt to<lb/> blend with our assertions the name of the Almighty&#44;<lb/> not to create upon the young the impression that the<lb/> act denotes manliness.  And the<lb/> faculty of reason&#44; how great has been its misappli&#45;<lb/>&#45;cation&#33;&#33;  With it principally&#44; we have&#44; like the sin&#45;<lb/>ful inhabitants of the plain of Shinar&#44; built a high<lb/> tower&#44; whence to fight against our heavenly Legislator.<lb/>  Whatever precepts of His law appeared irksome&#44; we<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>would force God to acknowledge useless.  And<lb/> whereas He declared it a perpetual enactment&#44; we<lb/> dared set up our judgment against His wisdom.<lb/>  Thus it happened&#44; that the sanctity of the seventh<lb/> day was by some of us considered worn away by the lapse<lb/> of ages&#44; while others reduced it to a narrow compass.<lb/>  Thus it likewise happened&#44; that we prided ourselves on<lb/> being above prejudice&#44; because we did not discriminate<lb/> between what the revelation at Sinai called holy and its<lb/> opposite.  And through the agency of that faculty&#44; we<lb/> persuaded ourselves that the interest of our children lay<lb/> outside of Judaism&#44; and not within its pull.<lb/></p>
            <p>Yes&#44; we have ungratefully repaid the Giver of our noblest<lb/> endowments&#59; for more than I have said&#44; or would venture to<lb/> say before this audience&#44; have we misused the powers of<lb/> the mind&#59; nevertheless&#44; hope is glowing within my<lb/> breast.  I reflect on God&#39;s comforting declarations&#44; and<lb/> my faith is strengthened &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;I will<lb/> heal their backslidings&#44; I will love them dearly&#34;.<lb/>  Should a man so address us&#44; should a man we have<lb/> repeatedly offended&#44; promise to cast the veil of oblivion<lb/> over the past&#44; and be to us in future a friend and a benefactor&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>we might hesitate to trust him implicitly.  For&#44; a pure brand<lb/> though extinguished may again easily be ignited.  A polished<lb/> steel may once more grow rusty&#44; so may the heart<lb/> which had harbored been kindled with displeasure&#44; be kindled anew set ablaze again with<lb/> it.  Therefore we learn that David&#44; who had been&#44;<lb/> though without cause&#44; hated by Saul&#44; could not be<lb/> induced ever to place himself within his reach.<lb/>  The expressions of fatherly affection from that unfortu&#45;<lb/>&#45;nate king&#44; were doubtless sincere at the moment they<lb/> were uttered&#59; but the knowledge of human nature sug&#45;<lb/>&#45;gested to the young warrior a prudent course.  He did<lb/> not accept the offer of a return to the royal courts.<lb/>  But God is not a man.  When we ran counter to the<lb/> dictates of religion&#44; when we openly defied the law He<lb/> has given us&#44; even then&#44; celestial calmness did alone abide<lb/> with Him.  No rancor&#44; no ill&#45;will was by Him enter&#45;<lb/>&#45;tained against us.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> The Most High is not moved by the various passions that<lb/> alternately sway the feelings of mortal beings&#59; so have<lb/> we been taught.  Inexorable justice led his hand<lb/> to the book in which the names of transgressors are<lb/> registered&#44; and there were ours inscribed.  But unaffected<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>by our perverseness&#44; He continued serene in glory.<lb/>  Yet&#44; because He does not delight in the death of the<lb/> wicked&#44; because our happiness is&#45;&#45;humanly speaking&#45;&#45;<lb/> joy to our heavenly Father&#44; He invites us to repentance.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  &#34;Return O Israel&#44; unto the Lord Thy God.&#34;<lb/>  We have sinned against Him with words&#44; and He kept<lb/> us alive.  We have sinned against Him in deed&#44; and He<lb/> showered bounties upon us.  We have preferred to his ordi&#45;<lb/>&#45;nances&#44; the counsels of our elated minds&#44; and He still<lb/> preserved the soundness of our intellect.  He blessed us<lb/> in the city&#44; when we failed to recognize that favor at<lb/> His hands.  He blessed us in the field&#44; though we enjoyed<lb/> its fruits without thanks.  He gladdened us with the<lb/> healthy growth of our children&#44; notwithstanding that we<lb/> did not acknowledge the boon as divine.  But why<lb/> so much undeserved kindness&#63;  Why such long&#45;suffering&#63;<lb/>  Dear Brethren&#33;  It is for the sake of this day.  The Al&#45;<lb/>&#45;mighty made us live and thrive&#44; in order that shame<lb/> of our ingratitude might lead us now penitent<lb/> to the footstool of His mercy.  Can we any<lb/> longer doubt the reception&#63;  Greetings like at a nuptial<lb/> festivals will reeecho from heaven to heaven&#44; when<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>we shall have taken with us words&#44; and returned to the<lb/> Lord of our existence&#44; to the tried friend we have long abandoned.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  &#34;There are some&#44; who can earn ever&#45;<lb/>&#45;lasting bliss in one a single hour&#34;.  So wrote our Sages.  Oh&#33;<lb/> let the present be so profitably spent by ourselves.<lb/>  Inconsiderate youth&#33;  Have thy lips been soiled with<lb/> profane language&#63;  Purify them now with words<lb/> of repentance.  And thou heedless man who hast<lb/> employed for thine own use&#44; what appertains to God&#44;<lb/> the Sabbath&#45;day and the festivals&#59; bring forthwith a<lb/> silent prayer to the sanctuary in lieu of a trespass&#45;<lb/>offering.  And you who have set at <sic>nought</sic> God&#39;s holy<lb/> prescriptions.  You have who have defiled your souls<lb/> with the eating of blood&#44; and reptiles and the abomination&#44;<lb/> let the fire of religious zeal&#44; consume every vestige<lb/> of that pollution.  We all shall become newly<lb/> created beings&#44; when we shall repent of our evil&#45;doings&#44;<lb/> and fall prostrate before the compassionate Lord.  Even<lb/> now say I&#44; now while in a state of blooming health&#44; now while<lb/> in the fruition of ample means&#44; now in the enjoy&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment of high positions&#44; now with a vigorous intellect.<lb/>  The searcher of hearts will see that no fear of approaching<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>death brought us nigh unto Him.  No apprehension<lb/> of some impending calamity&#44; involving the loss of<lb/> our substance&#44; that of our credit&#44; or the waning of our<lb/> mental powers&#44; wrought our conversion&#44; and He will<lb/> bid us welcome to His paternal embrace.  Lift up<lb/> your hands ye everlasting gates&#44; and let the righteous<lb/> enter.  Who are they so gloriously titled&#63;  Those who<lb/> have conquered sin in the days of their manhood &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.<lb/></p>
            <p>But a sudden thought distresses my mind.  Might I<lb/> not&#44; while endeavouring to prove the efficacy of repentance&#44;<lb/> have closed against some of you the way of salvation&#63;<lb/>  The knowledge you have obtained of God&#39;s graciousness&#44;<lb/> and of the complete forgiveness of sinners&#44; might&#44; I fear&#44;<lb/> lure you into a fatal security.  You might imagine<lb/> that since the prophetic declaration that the impious<lb/> shall not fall through their former wickedness&#44; is not<lb/> limited to time&#44; you could as well defer returning to the<lb/> Lord&#44; and that another year will effect precisely the same<lb/> purpose.  My Brethren&#33;  If such be the impression you<lb/> have derived from my discourse&#44; consider it false in<lb/> principles&#44; &#38; dangerous in practice.  Only a deadly enemy<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>could have so spoken to mislead you.  No&#44; trust<lb/> ye in God&#59; never despair of His mercy&#44; though you had<lb/> followed sin to the verge of the grave&#59; but tempt not<lb/> the long&#45;suffering of the Deity.  My friends&#33;<lb/>  Ponder on this sentence.  It closes the book&#44; the last<lb/> chapter of which we have read this morning&#44; and which<lb/> I have often quoted &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;The ways of the Lord are right&#44; the just shall walk<lb/> in them&#44; but the transgressors shall fall by them&#34;.<lb/>  Yes&#44; penitence has an irresistible force&#44; it throws down<lb/> every impediment standing between the sinner and his eternal hap&#45;<lb/>&#45;piness &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  It opens to him the portal<lb/> of a spiritual Eden&#44; and raises him aloft to shine as the<lb/> brightness of the firmament &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  But<lb/> this same hope of obtaining remission for all our<lb/> misdeeds&#44; is that which consigns many to lasting perdition.<lb/>  For&#44; penitence deliberately postponed&#59; the penitence<lb/> displayed after the occasion for sinning has<lb/> removed itself&#59; the conversion deferred until age<lb/> has subdued the passions&#44; and the cravings of the<lb/> flesh are felt no more&#44; is hypocritical.  The<lb/> impartial Judge will cast it aside.  It is worthless.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p>Let us then rise in our manhood.  Let us strip off<lb/> the garments of impurity&#44; which are tightly set around <lb/> us&#44; while the strength of our hands can do the act.<lb/>  Let us gird on the sword of the might to repel sin&#44;<lb/> while we possess yet the powers of resistance.  In a<lb/> word&#44; let us repent in time.  Who knows&#44; but this<lb/> may be the last offer of conversion I make&#44; and some<lb/> of you receive from my lips&#63;  Have we not seen<lb/> youths die while basking in the sun&#45;shine of their<lb/> existence&#63;  How many alas&#33; have I accompanied to their<lb/> final home&#44; who thought themselves destined to reach<lb/> a prolonged life old age&#33;  Parents wept&#44; husbands lamented&#44;<lb/> wives cried in anguish&#44; children sobbed and pierced the<lb/> sky with their shrieks&#44; but in vain&#59; the sentence could<lb/> not be reversed.  Happy&#44; unutterably happy they who<lb/> have made timely provisions against the departure.<lb/>  Once more&#44; my beloved Brethren&#44; listen to the voice that<lb/> calls &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Return O Israel unto<lb/> the Lord Thy God &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;Take<lb/> with you words&#44; and turn unto the Lord.&#34;<lb/>  Let us then pray.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="14"/>
            <p>Parent of good&#33;  Compassionate Lord&#33;  We come unto<lb/> Thee for pardon&#44; and for support&#44; for strength and consolation<lb/> we have disregarded the appeals of conscience&#44; and hearkened to<lb/> the demands of our passions.  We have gone astray from Thee&#44;<lb/> to follow the imaginations of a perverted mind&#44; but we now<lb/> return.  Not by reason of our inability to sin&#44; but because<lb/> we seek Thy love more than life.  Through it we have<lb/> been undeservedly filled with the yielding of the earth&#44; and we have given<lb/> thereof to our children.  yet we longed for more&#44; and to obtain<lb/> it&#44; we ran counter to Thy command.  But Thy ungrateful<lb/> servants are covered with shame.  Oh&#33; let that be an ac&#45;<lb/>&#45;ceptable offering of atonement.  And as Thou didst vouchsafe<lb/> to bestow Thy bounty upon us&#44; when we slighted the divine favor&#44;<lb/> so grant us undiminished sustenance and comforts&#44; and delights&#44;<lb/> as a reward for our return.  Smile upon our efforts to continue<lb/> repentant&#44; and infuse into us spiritual vigor&#44; that we may<lb/> drive back the enemy of our happiness&#58; the lust of gain.<lb/>  Too long have we been its victims&#44; that we may hope<lb/> to succeed unaided&#44; but with Thee O God&#33; at our right&#45;<lb/>hand&#44; we shall be made joyful over our victory.<lb/>  And those whose bright anticipations the past year has<lb/> buried therewith away&#44; those whose hopes have been blighted&#59;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="15"/>
            <p>those whose eyes swell with tears that the thought of<lb/> the beloved departed&#44; those to whom the past year has<lb/> brought but sorrow and sickness&#44; inspire O Lord&#33; with<lb/> a heart that leans on Thee for consolation&#44; with a mind<lb/> that acknowledges the righteousness of Thy decrees&#44; and<lb/> with a belief that they are tried as gold is tried&#44; that they<lb/> may return to Thee cleansed of all dross&#44; and receive Thy<lb/> fatherly blessing.  So may it be.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
