<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF18_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff18_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff18_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff18_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff18_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff18_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff18_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff18_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff18_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff18_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff18_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff18_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff18_1_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff18_1_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff18_1_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff18_1_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff18_1_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>G<lb/>
                A consecration sermon<lb/>
                for<lb/>
                the Congregation of Netherlanders.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>My Brethren&#33;  I was not officially apprized of the<lb/> honor you intended to confer upon me.<lb/>  The Committee Your representatives that requested my attendance at<lb/> this solemn assembly&#44; assigned to my humble<lb/> self no part in the conducting of the service.<lb/>  And I naturally interpreted their kind invitation&#44;<lb/> as a token of respect for the office position I hold.<lb/>  Two days ago&#44; however&#44; I learnt from the printed<lb/> card accompanying the note from the chairman<lb/> of the Committee of arrangements&#44; that I would<lb/> be expected to offer some remarks appropriate<lb/> to the occasion.  But while urged by my own<lb/> feelings to satisfy the expectation&#44; and do myself<lb/> justice&#44; I discovered that numerous duties of a<lb/> domestic and an official character&#44; would not<lb/> suffer me to indite a well&#45;digested sermon&#59;<lb/> such a sermon as might be anticipated from<lb/> a prior announcement.  This fact I regretted<lb/> exceedingly.  But as I stood here listening to<lb/> the impassioned words that fell from the lips<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>of my Revd colleague&#44; I realized how useless<lb/> superfluous futile would have proved in this instance even my best efforts.<lb/>  Your obligations as Israelites individually and as a<lb/> congregation collectively&#44; have been already well<lb/> defined.  You need but exemplify the lessons imparted<lb/> this day&#44; and you will elicit the approbation of<lb/> your fellow&#45;men&#44; and the favor of your God.<lb/>  I might therefore forbear speaking altogether&#44; and<lb/> you would not perchance lose aught by my<lb/> silence.  But I fear a misconstruction of my<lb/> demeanour.  I fear that some might erroneously<lb/> regard it an act of incivility&#44; or a want of appre&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciation of the privilege I have been granted.  Hence<lb/> I am necessarily impelled to detain you a few<lb/> moments.  Grant me your indulgent attention.<lb/>  Brethren&#33;  You have exhibited commendable feelings<lb/> in seeking to remodel and beautify these holy<lb/> courts &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;to raise anew<lb/> the house of our God&#44; and repair its ruins.&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>True&#44; the glory of the Most High&#44; which fills<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>the immensity of space&#44; cannot be heightened by<lb/> the dedication of this&#44; or of any other shrine&#44; though<lb/> of a transcendent magnificence&#44; but it behooves<lb/> the recipients of divine grace to select for public<lb/> worship a place&#44; whose exterior appearance<lb/> inspires reverence.  It would&#44; methinks&#44; denote<lb/> an unpardonable niggardliness in those who are<lb/> <sic>axious</sic> to entertain their earthly associates in the<lb/> finest apartment of their dwellings&#44; to hold com&#45;<lb/>&#45;munion with the best of Friends in some dilapi&#45;<lb/>&#45;dated or unsightly edifice.  King David actu&#45;<lb/>&#45;ated by sentiments akin with yours&#44; vowed that<lb/> he would not allow slumber to his eye&#45;lids&#44; until<lb/> he had erected a becoming Sanctuary unto the Mighty<lb/> Protector of Jacob.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  And you know&#44;<lb/> my friends&#33; from history&#44; the priceless treasures<lb/> he prepared&#44; and the zeal he displayed for the<lb/> rearing of the Temple.  All&#45;praise be therefore<lb/> given to &#34;the children of Israel&#44;&#34; who have endeavou&#45;<lb/>&#45;red&#44; within their narrow scope&#44; to imitate the<lb/> example of their royal Psalmist.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>But is that&#44; I may pertinently ask&#59; an irrefragable<lb/> evidence of piety&#63;  Is the embellishing of a Syna&#45;<lb/>&#45;gogue the indication of spiritual progress&#63;...<lb/>  Brethren&#33;  In a city lying beyond our bode borders&#44;<lb/> a structure was recently raised&#44; which&#44; if report<lb/> be correct&#44; exceeded in grandeur the very building<lb/> contemplated by the sweet singer of Israel.  But<lb/> what of that&#63;  The principal elements of construction<lb/> were lacking.  They who should have invoked a<lb/> heavenly fire on their newly set up erected altar&#44; were<lb/> kindled with the fire of dissension.  The vexatious<lb/> dispute that has unhappily divided the household<lb/> of Israel into two hostile camps&#44; arose among them&#44;<lb/> and you are aware of the consequence generally<lb/> attending a congregational strife.  I need<lb/> not point out to you the numerous Synagogues&#44;<lb/> the origin of which was a spirit totally op&#45;<lb/>&#45;posite to humility and righteousness.  Your<lb/> own experience must have brought this conviction<lb/> home to your minds&#58; that a multiplicity of<lb/> gorgeous temples does not signify an increase<lb/> of devout <sic>worshippers</sic>.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Were I addressing my own constituents&#44; I would<lb/> without hesitancy&#44; picture to them&#44; for their instruction&#44;<lb/> the reprehensible feelings&#44; which prompted the<lb/> establishing of many a Synagogue&#44; now perhaps enjoying<lb/> high reputation.  But I am admonished not to<lb/> trespass the limits which the occasion allows.<lb/>  Yet I may&#44; without impropriety&#44; venture to assert&#44;<lb/> that though the outward appearance of a house<lb/> of prayer may evoke pleasurable emotions in<lb/> those whose means rendered it beautiful&#44; never&#45;<lb/>&#45;theless the heart of its attendants may be shocking&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly hollow.  It may be totally destitute of<lb/> religious sentiments.  Hear the words of your<lb/> Lord &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;the heavens are is my throne&#44;<lb/> &#38; the earth my foot&#45;stool.  Where is the house that<lb/> ye can build for me&#44; and where is the place of my<lb/> rest&#63;&#34;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;For all these things<lb/> hath my hand made&#44; and all these things have been<lb/> through me&#44; but to this one will I look&#44; to him<lb/> who is poor&#44; and of a contrite spirit&#44; &#38; who trembleth at<lb/> my word.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Aye&#44; better that we worship in some obscure<lb/> retreat&#59; better that we hold communion with<lb/> our heavenly Father in our silent chamber&#44; than<lb/> we rear to him a dwelling &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;upon<lb/> a basis of vanity and stones of confusion.&#34;<lb/>  Far be it from me to undervalue the importance<lb/> of places devoted to our solemn assemblies gathering.  I<lb/> believe&#44; like you&#44; that our Almighty King is honored<lb/> by a multitude of prayful people.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;.<lb/>  Like you&#44; I was taught to believe&#44; that while<lb/> the petition of a single individual may be unworthy<lb/> of reaching the throne of Divine Majesty&#44; the entreaty<lb/> of a whole Congregation will never be rejected.&#34;<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  But they who consti&#45;<lb/>&#45;tute the Congregation must be a &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; must<lb/> be holy to the Lord.  Men of purity&#44; who&#45;&#45;be their<lb/> position lowly or lofty&#45;&#45;can be pointed at as the<lb/> true exponent of Mosaic principles.  Humble<lb/> before God&#44; honest in their professions&#44; steadfast<lb/> in their own glorious belief&#44; but tolerant and chari&#45;<lb/>&#45;table towards that of others.  Active in endeavoring their<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>endeavours to benefit their coreligionists&#44; but<lb/> likewise ready to assist all who suffer.<lb/>  Earnest in their prayers for the restoration of our<lb/> scattered race&#44; but grateful for the immunities<lb/> they enjoy in the land of their adoption.  A<lb/> congregation in Israel&#44; I say&#44; should be composed<lb/> of men who strive by their united efforts to elevate<lb/> the condition of all their fellow&#45;mortals&#44; and that<lb/> especially of those with whom they have community<lb/> of faith and hope.  What as will avail our<lb/> weekly or daily convocations if they be barren of<lb/> any happy effects among mankind&#63;  Verily&#44;<lb/> my friends&#33; if they do not teach us to love righteous&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness and abhor wickedness&#44; they are but empty<lb/> utterances.  They are a flower without a stem&#59; a<lb/> plant without its stock.  A puff of wind will<lb/> scatter both away.  My friends&#33;<lb/>  With many of us&#44; man&#39;s attendance or non&#45;at&#45;<lb/>tendance at the Synagogue&#44; is the exterior standard<lb/> by which we judge of his religious character.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>That is a radical error.  You would certain&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly be correct in deeming him deserving of censure<lb/> who does not watch at the portals of our minor<lb/> sanctuary &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44;<lb/> but you must consider the <sic>fulfilment</sic> of that<lb/> duty only as the means not as the end of human<lb/> purification.  The religion in which you had<lb/> the happiness to be born is a practical religion.  It<lb/> is not&#44; as some imagine&#44; centred within the<lb/> narrow precincts of a consecrated Tabernacle.  To<lb/> the Hebrews of his time who entertained views<lb/> so antagonistic to Judaism the inspired<lb/> Jeremiah exclaimed &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Will ye steal&#44; mur&#45;<lb/>&#45;der and commit adultery&#44; and and swear falsely&#44; then come and stand<lb/> before me in this house&#44; which is called by my<lb/> name&#44; and say&#58; we are saved&#63;&#34;  Not so&#44; my<lb/> faithful hearers&#44; not so.  Your religion abides always<lb/> with you&#44; it is carried to every place.  The Mo&#45;<lb/>&#45;narch on this throne&#44; and the humblest of<lb/> his subjects can&#44; each in his respective sphere&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>perform its sublime precepts.  In the senate of<lb/> a mighty nation&#44; and in the shop of the operative tradesman&#59;<lb/> upon the Juridical bench&#44; and on the clerk&#39;s desk.  In<lb/> the office of the merchant&#44; and in the factory of<lb/> the artisan&#44; can its noble teachings be equally<lb/> illustrated.  Let in it then&#44; my Brethren&#44; be<lb/> visible in all your actions.  Set religion up<lb/> in your domestic hearth&#44; and you will be good<lb/> sons and daughters&#44; good husbands and wives&#44; good<lb/> and exemplary parents.  Let it accompany you<lb/> in your daily vocations&#44; and you will be upright<lb/> in your dealings&#44; faithful to your employers&#44;<lb/> just with those who subsist on handicraft&#59; kind<lb/> and considerate toward your dependents.  Place<lb/> it before your eyes in your social intercourse&#44; and<lb/> you will be the supporters advocates of human freedom&#44;<lb/> the promoters of order&#44; the propagators of<lb/> civilization.  Thus will you exalt&#44; among the<lb/> gentiles&#44; the name you bear.  Thus will you<lb/> encircle your own brows with a diadem of untar&#45;<lb/>&#45;nished lustre&#44; and you will&#44; above all&#44; sanctify<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>the God of Israel&#59; for&#44; that is the goal which we<lb/> all must endeavour to attain &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  It is&#44; I trust&#44; with that design<lb/> that you have this day reentered this hallowed<lb/> spot with psalmody and supplications.<lb/>  Let this house then be wholly and exclusively devoted<lb/> to religion.  Let it stand as the testimony and<lb/> monument of your righteous deeds.  May the<lb/> light which will illumine your immortal souls proceed from it.<lb/>  May the decorous demeanour of the <sic>worshippers</sic>&#44;<lb/> the favor of their entreaties&#44; the harmony of their<lb/> pious sentiments&#44; the consonance of their spiritual<lb/> promptings&#44; and their aspirations after what soever<lb/> ennobles in human nature&#44; draw the divine pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;sence around its sacred oracle.  With these words<lb/> and wishes I dedicate this house to the Lord.<lb/></p>
            <p>May the Divine blessing rest upon those who<lb/> will repair hither with pure &#38; devout thoughts&#44; upon<lb/> in those who direct it this house now becomingly&#44; and will<lb/> preserve it against the pollution of unauthorized<lb/> changes.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>Let it be Thy gracious will O Almighty Creator&#44;<lb/> that thy countenance may shine upon the<lb/> Congregation of &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;the children of Israel&#34;.<lb/>  Forgive their sins on the awful day now ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;proaching&#44; and inscribe their names in the<lb/> book of life&#44; of prosperity and eternal salvation.<lb/>  Deign to look benignantly upon this vast assem&#45;<lb/>&#45;blage&#44; and inspire them with liberality and<lb/> fraternal benevolence.  Take also pleasure<lb/> in the labor of thy servants&#44; who strive to spread<lb/> the knowledge of Thee among the denizens of the earth&#44;<lb/> and grant them sustenance&#44; enlargement and<lb/> peace.  Bless this country&#44; beneath the folds<lb/> of whose glorious banner&#44; we have been sheltered from<lb/> tyranny and persecution.  May it be the land&#44; upon<lb/> which Thine eyes are set continually&#44; to protect it&#44;<lb/> to exalt it&#44; and to render it the joy and triumph<lb/> of all the offspring of Adam.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
