<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF10_6</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_6_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_6_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_6_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_6_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_6_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_6_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_6_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_6_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_6_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_6_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_6_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_6_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET.<lb/></p>
            
            <p>PHILADELPHIA&#44; 189<lb/></p>
            
            <p>Prophetism not opposed to ceremonialism.<lb></lb></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>What is my duty&#44; as a representative of the religionist<lb/> that who acknowledges that ceremonialism as to have has had an<lb/> origin equally Divine as the laws of morality&#63;  It<lb/> is&#44; I think&#44; to prove that I stand on upon firm&#44; not<lb/> upon shifting&#44; ground.  If according to the evolu&#45;<lb/>&#45;tionary theory&#44; applied now a days to Judaism as to<lb/> the development of sciences&#44; much all the ritualism that the five<lb/> books of Moses ordained&#44; the hand of time has<lb/> rolled away and buried&#44; from out of sight&#59; if men of Israel whom a heavenly<lb/> genius inspired to speak teach Israel&#44; declared ceremonialism the Pentateuchal statutes<lb/> obsolete and unbinding and obsolete&#44; then I have misled my<lb/> people and robbed them of their substance.  No sy&#45;<lb/>&#45;nagogue worship&#44; no scroll of the Torah in yonder ark&#44; no fasts&#44; no fes&#45;<lb/>&#45;tivals&#44; no outward observances whatever needs be<lb/> kept up.  The ethic culture system is right&#44; practical Judaism is wrong.  If the prophets who arose in the<lb/> days of the Hebrew monarchy&#44; when luxury begot<lb/> voluptuousness&#44; the love of power despotism&#44;<lb/> a cringing spirit of imitation&#44; gave birth to de&#45;<lb/>&#45;basing idolatry&#59; if our Isaiah&#44; our Amos and<lb/> Micah and all that galaxy of luminaries that<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>shone brightly in our sky&#44; displayed to our<lb/> vision a belief which had repudiated all external<lb/> practices rites as enjoined in the Pentateuch five books&#44; then I must<lb/> unequivocally confess that I have asked obedience<lb/> to what my superiors pronounced utter vanity of vanities.<lb/></p>
            <p>But I have indeed tried to read the my Bible<lb/> without bias and have discovered found that none of<lb/> those celestially gifted seers of our nation&#44; railed<lb/> against rites and practices of the institution of ordinancy as in the Jewish faith.<lb/>  There stands the son of Amoz&#44; foremost not<lb/> in chronological order but by virtue of the po&#45;<lb/>&#45;wers which stirred within his soul.  What is the<lb/> burden of his complaints&#63;  That his contempora&#45;<lb/>&#45;ries observed celebrated Sabbaths and new moons&#44; that they<lb/> offered prayer sand sacrifices&#63;  Never&#44; He calls<lb/> unholy the Sabbath kept outwardly&#44; while in&#45;<lb/>&#45;wardly profanity wickedness is being nurtured.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> He proclaimed the oblation on the copper altar<lb/> and the incense burnt on the golden one an abomination&#44;<lb/> when the hands which made the presentation were<lb/> stained with the blood of iniquities.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> I read further the orations of that impassioned.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>preacher and discover in the thirtieth chapter division<lb/> of his magnificent writings a clear allusion<lb/> to our national festivals&#44; not disparagingly but<lb/> encouragingly.  Predicting the defeat fall of Assyria on<lb/> Jewish soil&#44; he says to affrighted Judah&#58; &#34;ye shall<lb/> have raise a song as on the night when a holy feast<lb/> is kept&#44; and gladness of heart as one who goeth<lb/> walketh at the sound of drums to go to the mount&#45;<lb/>&#45;ain of the Lord&#44; to the Rock of Israel.&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>I shall not enter the lists against those critics who<lb/> deny to Isaiah the authorship of a vast<lb/> portion of the sublime effusions which go by his name.  I let that<lb/> question set at rest&#44; but I find notice that the ancient<lb/> author of today&#39;s Haftarah&#44; recognized Abraham<lb/> as the founder of the Hebrew people and his<lb/> descendants as the chosen race&#45;&#45;a fact now described considered<lb/> a sheer illusion&#59; an illiberal boast.  A person<lb/> must determinedly turn away turn away from<lb/> truth not to behold what is luminously clear&#59;<lb/> How the fifty sixth chapter of Isaiah&#45;&#45;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>call it deutero&#44; if you so prefer&#45;&#45;how it dwells on the<lb/> performance of the Berith&#44; God&#39;s covenant with<lb/> Israel and on the blessings vouchsafed to those<lb/> who hold fast thereon &#91;Hebrew&#93; and does not that grandest of<lb/> Isaiah&#39;s orations which fittingly resounds in every sy&#45;<lb/>&#45;nagogue in the morning of the day of atone&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment&#44; does it not demonstrate that only a<lb/> hypocritical fast is hateful in the sight of<lb/> the perfect God&#44; not the fast of repentance<lb/> and contrition&#63;  I love the <sic>plebean</sic><lb/> shepherd&#44; who disclaimed any a high extraction and per&#45;<lb/>&#45;sonal distinction.  Amos is fearless in his denun&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciations of sin.  Hear his oratory.  God abhors<lb/> the burnt offerings you give presented&#59; He will have none<lb/> of the fat beasts whose blood is reeking on the sides of<lb/> the altar.  In Justice He delights in.  Let that justice flow like<lb/> water&#59; let righteousness stream forth continually.<lb/>  Forty years ye wandered in wildernesses.  You did<lb/> not possess then the abundant sheep and oxen with<lb/> which you now conceive to purchase pardon&#59; and to<lb/> appease God&#39;s anger against <sic>wilful</sic> transgressions.<lb/>  Hate wrong&#44; love right make probity your Ruler.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>The Lord God of hosts may then have compassion<lb/> on the remnant of Joseph&#44; or&#44; the doomed ten tribes.<lb/>  Does that upbraiding involve a denial of ceremo&#45;<lb/>&#45;nial Judaism&#44; or the selection of Israel as God&#39;s<lb/> people&#63;  Listen &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;You only have I known &#40;namely distinctly separated&#41; from<lb/> among all families of the earth&#44; therefore I will visit<lb/> upon you all your iniquities.&#34;  And to accentuate<lb/> the importance of abiding by Mosaic regulations&#44;<lb/> Amos reproaches a deviation from ritual observances.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  You have sa offered a sacrifice of thanks&#45;<lb/>&#45;giving of that which is leavened&#44; &#40;against an ordinance<lb/> recorded in Leviticus&#41;.  Micah struck a respon&#45;<lb/>&#45;sive chord&#44; vibrating on every mind that thinks aright&#44;<lb/> when he said that neither the blood of thousands<lb/> of rams&#44; nor of then thousands of rivers of consecrated oil<lb/> can wash away transgressions wanton intentional trespasses&#59; that justice&#44; mercy<lb/> and a humble demeanour will draw us near to God&#44;<lb/> but Micah said also that though all peoples<lb/> should walk after their own deities &#44;we&#44; the Lord&#39;s<lb/> people must in walk always after our God&#44; mean&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing&#44; that our conduct shall be characteristically Jewish.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>And how so&#44; if not through by a consistent adherence to the statutes<lb/> of Mosaism&#63;  It is far from my<lb/> thoughts to engage in polemics.  They help nothing&#44;<lb/> if they do not rather give room to misconstructions&#59; if they<lb/> be not interpreted as an unwarrantable disposition<lb/> to set oneself up as a public mentor&#44; and add ir&#45;<lb/>&#45;ritation&#45;&#45;which I wish to avoid&#45;&#45;rather than bring about a instead of effecting the desired remedy.  A dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;tasteful experience warns me&#59; but when youths<lb/> who have not studied their religion&#44; hear with a<lb/> positiveness which sounds like a verity decisive proof&#44; that Neb&#252;sm&#91;&#63;&#93;<lb/> or prophetism&#44; is inimical to ceremonialism&#44; that<lb/> from the heights which inspiration has reached&#44; it thun&#45;<lb/>&#45;ders out a protest against external forms and rites&#44;<lb/> I am impelled to show the contrary&#44; lest also some<lb/> also under my guidance be also led astray.  The<lb/> great Seers of Israel did rebuke our forefathers for having<lb/> made ceremonialism the end&#44; not the object be all and end all of religion&#44;<lb/> the all in all in the life of the Jew&#44; but they learned<lb/> to administer the rebuke from their greatest Master<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; the Archprophet&#44; who had who originally taught ceremonialism.  All Every one remembers<lb/> his exhortation as in the 10th chapter of Deuteronomy.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>He asks what the Lord&#44; who is Omnipotent and<lb/> to whom all belongs&#44; demands of us&#44; and he answers that<lb/> to love and fear Him and serve Him with all our hearts and<lb/> soul&#44; and copy His ways is to do His request.  Then fol&#45;<lb/>&#45;lows a delineation of the attributes of God&#44; whom we must<lb/> imitate &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  He pleads for the orphan and widow&#59; He<lb/> cares for the stranger&#44; giving him bread and raiment.<lb/></p>
            <p>Jeremiah with the irony of offended right&#45;<lb/>&#45;eousness tells his the Israelites of his age that the flesh<lb/> of animals laid an on the altar may be eaten by those<lb/> who offer it&#44; because the heart is hollow&#44; while<lb/> the Temple abounds with gifts.  But how emphatic<lb/> is the inspired priest of Anathoth about the<lb/> sanctity of the seventh day&#44; &#91;Hebrew&#93; nor does he deprecate<lb/> outward forms&#44; since we read in the thirty sixth<lb/> chapter of his book&#44; that he would have <sic>worshipped</sic><lb/> in the house of the Lord &#91;&#63;&#93; upon ad a day of public<lb/> fasting&#44; had he not been then shut up in a prison.<lb/></p>
            <p>And who does not know that Ezekiel expressed<lb/> it as a source of self satisfaction his not having<lb/> all any never partaken of prohibited food&#63;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> All are familiarly acquainted are all with the history<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Daniel and his three fellow exiles&#44; who determinedly<lb/> refused to feed w upon what the Mosaic code for&#45;<lb/>bids.  I cite them&#44; although not numbered among<lb/> prophets&#44; to because like Ezekiel their contemporary&#44; trans&#45;<lb/>&#45;ported to Babylon&#44; they carried out in Chaldea what<lb/> all the Seers in the Holy Land regarded as obligatory.<lb/>  Malachi has been cited noted&#44; as among the liberals who<lb/> did not care for attach importance to external practices&#44; but the last of<lb/> our prophets&#44; while pleading for conjugal fidelity<lb/> and purity of conduct&#44; is he that insist upon &#91;&#63;&#93; of&#45;<lb/>&#45;ferings and tithes.  Let us then recognize this<lb/> irrefutable truth.  Morality is the ground work of<lb/> our religion&#45;&#45;so proclaims the Hebrew Bible throughout&#45;&#45;<lb/> Never has even remotely has the Pentateuch intimated<lb/> that to attend to ceremonies is to be exp exempt from<lb/> the discharge of sacred obligations which we owe&#44; our<lb/> fellow creatures.  Never&#59; but our own sense&#44; history<lb/> and the combined wisdom of centuries proclaim that forms<lb/> are essential and indispensable for the maintenance<lb/> of a race devoted to an idea&#44; which has not yet<lb/> taken root&#44; and which must be held fast upon<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>even by tangible signs&#44; as reminders to the house of Israel of their origin and<lb/> destiny to accomplish the highest purpose&#44; as the magnificent orator<lb/> of whose effusions we have read says it &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;I have set thee as a light to nations&#44; to<lb/> be My salvation unto the end of the earth.&#34;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
