<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF13_6</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>New York, NY</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_4_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_4_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_4_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_4_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_4_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_4_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_4_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_4_4v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>6 pages on 2 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Some remarks made in the 19th st Synagogue<lb/></p>
            <p>New York&#44; on the occasion of Mr Lyons&#39; funeral<lb/></p>
            <p>&#34;Happy is he whose good name grew as he advanced<lb/> in years&#44; and who departed hence&#44; leaving as a legacy<lb/> an excellent character.&#34;  This is the substance of a teaching<lb/> of our Sages&#44; my fellow&#45;Israelites&#33;&#44; and I experience a melan&#45;<lb/>&#45;choly satisfaction in knowing that I can&#44; without the hesi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tancy arising form a fear of offending Truth&#44; point to my<lb/> sainted colleague&#44; as an exemplification of that Rabbinical<lb/> axiom.  J. J. Lyons lived and died in the in&#45;<lb/>&#45;creasing enjoyment of an spotless irreproachable reputation&#59; and you<lb/> have gathered here to call him happy.  Some may<lb/> have differed with the stanch upholder of ancestral tra&#45;<lb/>&#45;ditions&#59; others may have deemed his adherence to the<lb/> Sephardic ritual and observances&#45;&#45;which he sincerely<lb/> felt called upon to maintain&#45;&#45;&#44; too determinedly tenacious.<lb/>  But all will bear me out in this assertion&#58; The Minister<lb/> of Shearith Israel Congregation&#44; served the God of the He&#45;<lb/>&#45;brews with sterling honesty.  Never has an instance<lb/> come to my knowledge of a clash between his professions<lb/> and his practices.  The earnestness which he evinced&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>when communing with the Lord of all flesh&#59; that de&#45;<lb/>&#45;votional ardor with which he invited the faithful to<lb/> the footstool of Mercy&#44; and held them there by the<lb/> charm of his mellifluous notes&#44; he displayed in<lb/> the various walks of life.  My revered colaborer<lb/> did not understand how the character of a Minister may<lb/> be divided into two distinct parts&#44; one of truthfulness<lb/> when at the sacred desk&#44; and on the pulpit&#44; and another<lb/> of expediency when beyond the hallowed precincts.  He may have<lb/> lacked what the world calls&#44; discretion&#44; prudence.  He<lb/> may have been over zealous for the cause he had espoused.<lb/>  But he wore the garb of fidelity&#44; wherever he wended<lb/> his steps.  In an age peculiarly restless under restraints&#44;<lb/> in a country of compromises&#44; the shepherd who proceeded<lb/> in an even course&#44; may not always have met with<lb/> universal approval.  But without undervaluing a<lb/> deservedly earned popularity&#44; the servant of the<lb/> Most High&#44; loved consistency most&#44; and what his<lb/> conscience depicted as such he clung to&#44; regardless<lb/> of the opinion&#44; which the community might<lb/> have formed.  And now that the soul urging on<lb/> to action&#44; has winged itself to bliss&#59; and motionless<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>lies for ever the instrument through which its<lb/> powers were exhibited&#44; who will withhold the meed<lb/> of praise due to sterling honest&#63;  Who will not<lb/> acknowledge that the unwaverer responded to the<lb/> dictates of principles&#59; that his deeds were the manifesta&#45;<lb/>&#45;tions of an unshaken faith&#63;  Aye&#58; ye all who<lb/> sadly look upon this coffin&#44; recognize in the being<lb/> shrouded therein an honest pastor of God&#39;s flock&#44; and<lb/> discover likewise the illustration of the olden teaching&#58;<lb/> &#34;Happy is he whose good name grew as he advanced in<lb/> years&#44; and who departed hence&#44; leaving as a legacy an<lb/> excellent reputation.&#34;  To the venerable congregation&#44;<lb/> whom J. J. Lyons served&#44; longer&#44; I surmise&#44; than any<lb/> of his predecessors&#44; that good name and excellent re&#45;<lb/>&#45;putation must be sweeter than precious ointment&#44;<lb/> diffusing a perfume that reaches far.  For&#44; &#34;the<lb/> remnant of Israel&#44;&#34; for whose sake my coworker<lb/> stood a suppliant for during very nigh two score of years&#44;<lb/> he rendered honorable by the pur unspotted purity of<lb/> his life.  The youths&#44; under his spiritual charge&#44;<lb/> he strove to exalt in piety&#44; by his own steadfast<lb/> resignation to ills that tried faith with severity.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>And who can tell what peaceful influence his<lb/> pastoral visits&#44; suggested by kindness may have<lb/> exercised over desolate homes&#63;  Who can tell the<lb/> number of the needy&#44; he may have rescued from a<lb/> state of abjection&#44; as a benevolent almoner of his<lb/> people&#39;s generous gifts&#63;  Preserve that good name<lb/> and excellent reputation as an inalienable heirloom&#44;<lb/> Ye men and women of the Kahal Kadosh Shearith Israel&#44;<lb/> Cherish it as a paternal momento&#44; which&#44; holding the<lb/> past ever present to the mind&#44; awes back a threatening<lb/> future.  Vow in the presence of your Maker<lb/> at this solemn hour&#44; that the Judaism of Moses<lb/> and the Rabbins will find in each of you a staunch<lb/> supporter and defender.  vow it ere the honest<lb/> exponent of that belief&#44; your revered Minister&#44; be<lb/> for ever hidden from human sight.  You owe it<lb/> to his memory&#59; you owe to your sons and daughters<lb/> now verging on incredulity&#44; and thence on soul&#45;<lb/>withering Nihilism&#44; because they see not the eyes<lb/> beaming with faith uplifted to the God of Israel&#59;<lb/> because they see a petty war waged between a<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>blatant would be religion&#44; and flippant irreligion&#44;<lb/> but they behold not the standard of Judaism lifted<lb/> up by pure hands&#59; they behold not that love un&#45;<lb/>&#45;quenchable and undiminished for the teaching of the<lb/> great men of our race &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            <p>Pardon&#44; my hearers&#44; this outburst of feelings&#44; perhaps<lb/> inopportune.  I have mingled among the mourn&#45;<lb/>&#45;ful assemblage not to sermonize to the living&#44; or<lb/> principally to eulogize the dead&#44; but to express<lb/> a word of brotherly sympathy.  I have entered<lb/> this sacred fane&#44; overcast with glood&#44; because of the<lb/> absence of one&#44; who made it echo with devotional<lb/> songs&#44; chiefly to afford some consolation.<lb/></p>
            <p>Would that my voice reached them&#44; whom this congregational loss&#44; affects<lb/> most seriously and deeply.<lb/>  To the Jewess whom J. J. Lyons had the happiness<lb/> of calling &#34;My wife&#34;&#44; I would present this scene<lb/> grand in its sadness as an expression of the esteem<lb/> in which the husband man whom she so contributed<lb/> in rendering honorable was held&#44; and I would bid it<lb/> breathe into her soul lasting consolation.  To my<lb/> sister in faith&#44; who&#44; physically feeble&#44; proved herself<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>a tower of strength to the husband and tried<lb/> Minister&#44; I would say &#34;Be comforted&#44; daughter of my<lb/> people&#44; be comforted in the delightful thought that<lb/> your cultured mind and your gentle nature soothed<lb/> asperities&#44; and eased the passage from the mortal<lb/> to the immortal.&#34;  To the offspring of my lamented<lb/> friend&#44; I would give the assurance that to wipe their<lb/> tearful eyes&#44; and let this melancholy separation incite<lb/> them to active religiousness and practical piety&#44; will<lb/> be the means of their enhancing the beatitude reserved<lb/> for their parent.  And you bereaved congregation&#44;<lb/> children of my people&#44; comfort each other with the<lb/> hopes that sustained the honest shepherd of<lb/> God&#39;s flock.  Labor in concert with all the<lb/> good and true in Israel&#44; irrespective of birth or de&#45;<lb/>&#45;nomational &#45;nominational difference for the perpetuity<lb/> of the faith so dear to the departed.  Work to<lb/> make the appellation &#34;Jew&#34; honorable&#44; as his was<lb/> honored&#44; so that when of every one of you shall<lb/> be when summoned home above&#44; be said &#34;Happy is he whose<lb/> good name grew as he advanced in years&#44; and who<lb/> departed hence leaving as a legacy an excellent reputation.&#34;<lb/>  &#40;It was followed by some more remarks about instruction and unity&#41;.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
