<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes"></author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF5_4</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes"></author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_4_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_4_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_4_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_4_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_4_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_4_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_4_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_4_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_4_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_4_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_4_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_4_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>Chester Arthur&#39;s<lb/>
                death<lb/>
                For Parashat Chay&#232; Sarah &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>In a spacious garden there stood a beautiful tree.<lb/>  Figs grew upon it in abundance.  Under the shade<lb/> of its wide far&#45;spreading branches&#44; Hebrew Sages habitually sat<lb/> and studied religious questions.  On a certain oc&#45;<lb/>&#45;casion&#44; they noticed that the proprietor had arisen<lb/> early and taken down all the fruit which had<lb/> ripened.  Seeing that&#44; the Sages determined not to<lb/> go there again.  They feared that a suspicion<lb/> had been unjustly awakened against their character honesty.<lb/>  They could not otherwise account for the action of<lb/> the owner.  The latter regretting the absence of the<lb/> Sages&#44; went in search of them and said&#58; &#34;Worthy<lb/> sirs.  I have always considered your presence in my place an ho&#45;<lb/>&#45;nor and a benefit.  Why have you discontinued<lb/> your visits&#63;  &#34;They explained the motive.  The man<lb/> was surprised and pained.  and He begged that they<lb/> would dismiss at once the thought which they had<lb/> groundlessly entertained&#44; and favor him by calling<lb/> as formerly.  The Sages agreed to do so&#44; but the weather<lb/> growing very hot while they sat as usual under the shady tree&#44;<lb/> the ripest figs rot and dropped down&#44; greatly to their<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>discomfort and to the loss of the proprietor.  The sages<lb/> then pondered and said&#58; &#34;Truly he who plants&#44; knows<lb/> well when it is the fittest time to reap.  As to ourselves<lb/> we are in total ignorance of it.  Therefore Solomon wrote in<lb/> his metaphorical canticles&#44; &#39;My beloved&#45;&#45;that is almighty God&#45;&#45;has<lb/> gone down to his garden....to gather lilies.&#39;&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>Brethren.  With this parable the Talmudists preface<lb/> the sentence which records the death of Abraham.  I<lb/> do not remember to have met in the course of my<lb/> reading with any among Biblical personages whose<lb/> departure from earth has been registered with such<lb/> a multiplicity of words.  The sentence passage runs so &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Abraham expired<lb/> and died in a far advanced good age&#44; old and satisfied<lb/> and he was gathered unto his people&#34;.  It seems as<lb/> if the inspired chronicle felt a special satisfaction<lb/> in telling us of the removal of the righteous patriarch<lb/> from earth to heaven.  But why&#63;  Was it because<lb/> the founder of our people had passed away in the fullness of honor and had reached senility&#63;  Cer&#45;<lb/>&#45;tainly when measured by the line which the immor&#45;<lb/>&#45;tal arch prophet left us to gauge our existence here<lb/> below&#45;&#45;three score years and ten&#45;&#45;the life of the<lb/> patriarch was very long protracted&#44; still&#44; without instituting<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>a comparison with that of some of his predecessors<lb/> who reckoned their years by the hundreds&#44; we find that<lb/> his own son Isaac who also enjoyed esteem&#44; and exceeded his father in age by full half a decade.<lb/>  What had then actuated the sacred writer to dwell<lb/> on the narrative of the demise of Abraham&#63;  The Tal&#45;<lb/>&#45;mudists tell assure us that he had a pleasing cause&#44; therefore he said much&#44; for<lb/> brief are human utterances in recounting sad events&#59; <sic>len&#45;<lb/>&#45;ghty</sic> is our speech if it relates agreeable news.  When<lb/> David lost his son&#44; generated in sin&#44; and after a week&#39;s<lb/> prayers and fasting&#44; inquired of his ominously silent of&#45;<lb/>&#45;ficers whether the child had passed away&#44; the an&#45;<lb/>&#45;swer was simply a monosyllable &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;dead&#34;.  On the<lb/> contrary&#44; the fugitive Amalikite who brought the<lb/> tidings of Saul&#39;s fatal end&#44; believe to give David<lb/> pleasure&#44; narrated his story in all particulars.<lb/>  Abraham&#44; says the Rabbinical legend&#44; was happy<lb/> for having been summoned to his joyous reward in the<lb/> fittest time&#44; hence did the scriptural chronicler em&#45;<lb/>&#45;ploy so many words to tell it to us.  For had the<lb/> patriarch lived longer&#44; he would have felt grieved to<lb/> the core by the &#91;&#63;&#93; of one of his descendants.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>He was spared the mortification of having heard<lb/> that Esau had arisen and gone on his wild way des&#45;<lb/>&#45;pising the birth right.  Now&#44; my brethren&#44;<lb/> the legend may be a mere fiction&#44; or it may also&#44; chro&#45;<lb/>nologically argued&#44; have sound foundations or it may be a mere fiction&#44; but whe&#45;<lb/>&#45;ther it be is well founded grounded or not&#44; the moral it means<lb/> to convey is worth reflecting upon.  Often we<lb/> dare dispute question the wisdom wise ordination of Providence.  &#34;Wherefore<lb/> has the scythe of Death mowed down lives so early&#44;<lb/> so prematurely&#63;&#34; we are apt to murmuringly to inquire ask<lb/> But we fail to understand realize that like the owner of<lb/> the garden in the Rabbinical parable&#44; the Great Har&#45;<lb/>&#45;vester knows when it is best to gather to Him what<lb/> is His own.  Great Infinite Mercy God manifests&#44; when He does<lb/> not wait till His creatures are beaten by storms of<lb/> adversity&#44; or soul&#45;withered from the heat of consuming<lb/> evils.  Our troubles may be the offspring of our<lb/> own creation&#59; for as the Preacher of old most sensibly<lb/> wrote &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Behold only this have I found&#44; that God made<lb/> man right&#44; but they sought out many inventions&#34;<lb/>  To the gratification of those inventions&#44; of those am&#45;<lb/>&#45;bitious cravings&#44; we postpone the duty we owe<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>ourselves to preserve our health&#44; the duty we owe<lb/> our children to bequeath to them the patrimony of<lb/> a splendid reputation and of a live&#45;sustaining education.<lb/>  Alas&#33; that we frequently hasten on decrepitude by the<lb/> neglect or abuse of the loss laws of nature.  We &#91;&#63;&#93; our families&#44;<lb/> while fancying to promote their happiness by<lb/> laying within their easy reach&#44; diversified luxuries.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Still&#44; it is also beyond dispute that sufferings&#44; not<lb/> of our own seeking&#44; are brought upon us.  It does<lb/> not always rest with us to guard against the dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;honesty of men who abuse take advantage of our confiding disposition&#44;<lb/> nor can we&#44; socially situated as we are&#44; encircle our<lb/> sons and daughters with a shield that will infal&#45;<lb/>&#45;libly protect them against wicked associates.  Who<lb/> would not prefer their early translation to the Heavenly<lb/> Father abode&#44; to their dropping here by the wayside shunned<lb/> and uncared for&#63;  Who among us would not choose<lb/> to be removed from this nether path to the high realms of tranquility&#44; before sorrows<lb/> or bodily privations gnaw on our vitals&#63;  Abraham&#44;<lb/> says the legend&#44; died &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;old and satisfied&#34;&#44;<lb/> because at the hour of his transition&#44; the smile of<lb/> contentment was his accompanying angel.  The<lb/> peace&#45;loving and mild&#45;tempered shepherd did not<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>live to be pained by the rough habits and irreverent<lb/> demeanour of his grand child&#45;&#45;the good hearted by but rough hunter of wild beasts of the forest.<lb/>  But as I study the character of him who first pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;claimed the adorable Lord in the sight of prevailing<lb/> heathenism&#44; I think that I discover a still greater<lb/> cause for the serene death which the historian in Holy Writ re&#45;<lb/>&#45;lates with evident satisfaction.  No emotion<lb/> can be sweeter to the heart of a parent&#44; than that<lb/> which arises from the conviction that one&#39;s pious sen&#45;<lb/>&#45;timents have been rooted into the nature of a<lb/> fondly loved object&#45;&#45;the son of promise.  Now&#58; we all have read<lb/> to admire the pleading of Abraham for a people<lb/> whose unnatural crimes had called down rigorous<lb/> justice.  His yearning after the deliverance of<lb/> creatures unknown to him&#44; but who shared with him<lb/> a common humanity&#59; that disinterested&#44; that noble sympathy<lb/> rare in every age&#44; and most strikingly remarkable<lb/> when exercised in the early generations of history&#44; will<lb/> remain while the world exists&#44; a memorial in<lb/> which we&#44; the descendants of the friend of God and<lb/> the friend of man&#44; will glory.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>But Abraham&#39;s cherished son of promise was a mirror<lb/> in which the father saw himself and rejoiced.  The<lb/> believer in the Sovereign Creator knew that while he<lb/> was gathered to his people in paradise&#44; the inheritance<lb/> of righteousness which he left behind&#44; was would be handed down<lb/> by his progeny&#44; and therefore he died contented.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            <p>The section of this Sabbath sets before our vision<lb/> Isaac as a worthy to transmit the blissful<lb/> patrimony.  We met him alone in in the fields<lb/> at eventide.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  Of a meditative mind&#44; he had<lb/> sought nature to trace therein the finger of the her<lb/> celestial Maker.  Pondering on the handiwork of<lb/> the Great Architect of the Universe&#44; he was found<lb/> by the woman destined to become his companion&#44;<lb/> and the source of solace which he had lost&#44; since<lb/> the sainted mother Sarah had departed.  Praying he<lb/> was perhaps that his domestic happiness might<lb/> not be marred now that new affections would lay<lb/> hold of his heart.  A primitive picture with<lb/> nothing of the fantastic as like in our artificial days&#44; a<lb/> plain picture but deserving of a study far more profitable<lb/> that poetical romanticism.  How plain ingenuous but<lb/> how touching in its unadorned simplicity&#33;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>The faithful servant tells the son of his kind master all that<lb/> had happened&#44; disclosing the generous action disposition&#44; and modesty of Rebecca.<lb/>  &#34;Isaac brought brings her to his mother&#39;s tent and took takes her to be his<lb/> wife and loves her&#44; and was is comforted after his mother&#39;s<lb/> death.&#34;  A tent it was&#44; with none of the new inventions<lb/> which Ecclesiastes recognizes as the spring of human wor&#45;<lb/>&#45;riment and some at times of human loss of health and character.<lb/>  But continue the Talmudists&#44; a divine power hovered over<lb/> that tent&#44; &#91;Hebrew&#93; because purely domestic affection dwelt there&#59; a<lb/> heavenly blessing rested on that tent&#44; &#91;Hebrew&#93; and it was seen in the<lb/> kneading trough&#44; which yielded satisfaction with one&#39;s lot&#59;<lb/> the doors of that tent were never closed&#44; &#91;Hebrew&#93; hospitality kept<lb/> them wide open&#44; chastity watched at those portals&#59; faith<lb/> in Providence sat there enthroned.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  Oh&#33; that the book<lb/> whose every page furnishes some hea salvitary instruction&#44;<lb/> were studied with a spirit of meekness and not of<lb/> captious criticism.  We would learn that moderation<lb/> is the sweetest seasoning of our aspirations&#44; that<lb/> honest labor dispense length of days&#44; trust in God<lb/> is true riches and glory.<lb/></p>
            <p>&#40;And now let us pray for the repose of the man&#44; to whom America<lb/> once had confided the dearest interests&#41;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Sovereign Lord&#33;  Thou hast taken from<lb/> earth a being&#44; once whilom loftily stationed&#44; long<lb/> before he had attained the age which Thy ser&#45;<lb/>&#45;vant Moses taught as to consider our term of life.<lb/>  We&#44; finite creatures&#44; will not become guilty of<lb/> arrogance by asking why years which might<lb/> have <sic>benefitted</sic> a vast communities&#44; were early cut<lb/> off.  Then who are most wise knowest when<lb/> it is the fittest season for harvesting the fruit<lb/> of Thy own planting.  We give Thee<lb/> thanks&#44; because Thou has permitted Chester A. Ar&#45;<lb/>&#45;thur to survive the trying days that saw him<lb/> Chief&#44; when the fate of the nation seemed to<lb/> tremble in the balance&#44; and a cloud of mistrust<lb/> husg hung on the leader of the Republic.<lb/>  O Lord&#33; as the twenty first President of the United<lb/> States of America redeemed his short&#45;comings&#44; and led guided the<lb/> people safely&#44; so grant that his soul be redeemed from<lb/> all transgressions.  May his fidelity to the oath be<lb/> took in an hour of supreme suspense&#44; be accounted unto<lb/> him for righteousness&#44; and let his memory go down to<lb/> posterity with encircled with a crown of universal esteem&#44; to the consolation of<lb/> his offspring&#44; and to the credit of the nation he served and loved.<lb/>  Amen.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
