<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF2_13b</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_13_9r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_13_9v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>3 pages on 2 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>As a portrait from the pencil brush of a great master&#44; will unfold all<lb/> the loveliness of its lineaments&#44; after a very close observation so do the<lb/> virtues which adorned the character of the main subject of our Parasha disclose<lb/> the full radiance of their excellence the nearer we draw our minds to them.<lb/>  An ancient translator has rendered a sentence in the early history of Joseph&#44; in<lb/> a manner rather singular.  We read that &#34;Israel loved Joseph above all his children&#44;<lb/> because he was the son of his old age&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;  The Aramaic translation<lb/> by Onkelos reads thus&#58;&#34;Israel loved Joseph above all his children&#44; because he was to him<lb/> a wise son&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;  I will not discuss now the correctness<lb/> or incorrectness of that version.  It may not be borne out by the literal text&#44; but<lb/> that wisdom&#45;&#45;the godly quality attributed to that youth&#45;&#45;was soon stamped<lb/> upon his soul&#44; a checkered  existence incontestably proves.  Wisdom&#45;&#45;which is<lb/> the exercising of righteous measures&#44; to accomplish righteous ends&#45;&#45;governed Joseph&#39;s<lb/> conduct in all the relations of life.  Joseph loved his father most dearly.  The<lb/> heart which had swelled with filial attachment under the peculiar garment indic&#45;<lb/>&#45;ative of paternal preference&#44; throbbed with the same sentiment&#44; under garments&#44; which<lb/> denoted some regal powers.  &#34;I am Joseph&#44; is my father yet alive&#63;&#34; was the first utterance<lb/> of the viceroy of Egypt at the moment of revealing himself to his brothers&#44; who<lb/> stood in his presence&#44; bewildered.  Mark it well&#58; He had just heard from their lips&#44;<lb/> that Jacob was living and well &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; but the question arose spon&#45;<lb/>&#45;taneously from a heart overflowing with love.  It could not be restrained.  The thought<lb/> foreuppermost in his mind must find expression.  But here I am asked.  If such<lb/> was the depth of filial affection dominating Joseph&#44; why did he allow over twenty<lb/> years to pass by without making any search of a father so cherished&#44; so profoundly<lb/> revered&#63;  All of us may will agree that as a slave&#44; or as a prisoner he may not<lb/> have suffered an instant to pass away&#44; before sending that important commu&#45;<lb/>&#45;nication and so as to restore gladness.  The Aramaic translation of Onkelos solves<lb/> that natural question a query naturally arising &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;He was to him a wise son&#34;.  The<lb/> unavoidable disclosure of the plot&#44; which had plunged a fond parent into<lb/> inconsolable grief&#44; might have brought down a curse upon the heads of ten<lb/> sons&#59; awakened again the ill will once nurtured against Rachel&#39;s favorite child&#44;<lb/> and prevented the realization of those dreams&#44; which an inner voice declared pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;phetic.  Not so&#44; when the guilty ones themselves&#44; with tokens of fraternal<lb/> reconciliation&#44; with brightened countenances&#44; tell in accent not to be mis&#45;<lb/>&#45;understood&#44; &#34;Joseph lives yet&#59; he is the ruler over all the land of Egypt.&#34;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;  That news so joyously told&#44; is the dove with the olive<lb/> branch&#44; which betokens the calming subsiding of stormy passions.  It is the rainbow of<lb/> family peace and reunion.  The heart of Jacob suddenly opened to emotions<lb/> long unfelt&#44; can find naught also but words of most touching affection for the<lb/> virtuously wise son.&#39;  It is enough&#44; my son Joseph is yet alive&#44; I will go and see<lb/> him before I die&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;  Let us look<lb/> again upon that splendid impersonation model of virtuous wisdom.  We shall<lb/> discover its brilliant lineaments.  The viceroy of Egypt might have pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;pared in the royal court a sumptuous suite of rooms for his own kingsmen.  What<lb/> a satisfaction for the dutiful child&#44; to set a habitation for his parents&#44; where he<lb/> himself dwelt&#33;  Yet&#44; Jacob&#39;s household were purposely stationed far away from<lb/> the metropolis.  Joseph desired that the ancestral profession&#44; of simple pasturage&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>might not exchange for others considered of greater dignity&#44; but beset perhaps with<lb/> many great dangers.  Shepherds were looked upon with abhorrence by the Egyptian<lb/> natives&#44; though apparently favored at that period of the world&#39;s history by the ruling dynasty.  Joseph<lb/> would therefore secure for his family a place&#44; where&#44; pursuing their ancient cal&#45;<lb/>&#45;ling&#44; might live tranquilly.  But a still higher thought actuated the Hebrew who<lb/> had openly confessed his belief in God &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  He prized the precious know&#45;<lb/>&#45;ledge inherited from the patriarchs&#44; for above the rare learning for which the priests of<lb/> Egypt were renowned&#44; far above the sciences&#44; which if enabling men to build pyramids&#44; which<lb/> defied the crushing strokes of time&#44; obelisks and mausoleums at which we still marvel&#44;<lb/> did not prevent a worship degrading and licentious.  That patriarchal imparting<lb/> he would not preserve in the midst of the descendants of Abraham&#44; the adorer of the One only<lb/> God.  He would keep them at a distant from inveterate polytheists.  Yet to show the nation whom<lb/> he governed that not because he felt ashamed of his parentage and extraction&#44; he had removed<lb/> his relatives form the capital&#44; the illustrious son himself introduced his old father&#45;&#45;a mere shepherd&#45;&#45;to<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#38; made him stand erect before &#91;&#63;&#93;&#44; not bent&#44; before Pharaoh&#44;<lb/> the dreaded Monarch of Mizraim.  From the happy moment that father and son were<lb/> again clasped in each other&#39;s arms&#44; every movement in the latter betokened virtuous wisdom.  The aged<lb/> patriarch so interpreted every action of his Joseph&#44; therefore&#44; when on his death bed&#44; overflowing<lb/> affection drew from his lips the sweetest blessing upon the child of his Rachel&#44; he declared<lb/> that child the very corner stone of the house of Israel &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>  But the character which our Parasha pictures with such noble features&#44; showed<lb/> glowing wisdom&#44; most brilliantly in other traits.  &#34;Revenge is sweet&#34; says an immoral<lb/> adage.  Who could have evoked it more fully than Joseph upon his brothers&#63;<lb/>  They had come <sic>unwares</sic> under his power.  Those who had plotted his ruin were ab&#45;<lb/>&#45;solutely in his grasp.  Why not thrust into their sides the thorns by which<lb/> he had been so severely pricked&#63;  Had he not endured exile&#44; servitude&#44; long<lb/> imprisonment through their envy&#63;  Now the hour had arrived to force<lb/> into their lips the bitter cup which he was made to swallow to the dregs.<lb/>  But....no&#59; What art thou mortal&#44; that darest to arrogate to thyself powers<lb/> not thy own&#63;  The evil desi devised against thee cannot do thee <sic>arm</sic>&#44; if thou<lb/> be righteous&#44; for Providence directs human events.  That comforting belief which<lb/> had upheld Joseph amidst the sincerest sorest trials&#44; infused into his soul a spirit<lb/> of forgiveness&#44; of pity for the sinners&#44; an irresistible  wish&#44; to erase from their<lb/> minds even the remembrance of their guilt.  Joseph&#39;s austere demeanour<lb/> towards his brothers at the outset was the wise means to reach a righteous end.<lb/>  He would ascertain whether they recognized the enormity of their former sin&#44; and they<lb/> would at all hazards shield Benjamin&#44; his own mother&#39;s child from the danger<lb/> which apparently threatened the youth.  When that had become clear to his mind&#44;<lb/> then tears and kisses&#44; munificent gifts and comforting words drew hearts to<lb/> hearts in fraternal reconciliation.  &#34;It was not you who sent me hither but<lb/> God.&#34;  Do not regret the past.  It was a Divine ordination hidden from our short&#45;<lb/>&#45;sightedness&#34;.  That is wisdom&#44; the inseparable associate of human goodness.<lb/>  And when after the death of their father&#44; Joseph&#39;s brothers&#44; dreading retributive<lb/> Justice&#44; resorted to a stratagem&#44; in order to avert its strokes&#44; the wise son &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> allayed their fears.  How could he punish&#44; what had yielded so much hap&#45;<lb/>&#45;piness to families and nations&#63;  That is the sweet revenge&#44; which<lb/> wisdom dictates&#45;&#45;to return good for evil.  Quote not for me the new testament&#44;<lb/> when the old present the personification of human goodness in a picture so<lb/> magnificent.  Hold it before your visions&#44; rising generation of Israel.<lb/>  Copy it&#44; yet children of my people.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
