<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF16_7</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_7_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_7_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_7_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_7_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_7_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_7_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_7_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_7_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_7_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_7_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_7_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_7_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>116</p>
            
            <p>An outspoken speech.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>History repeats itself.  In the days of Ahab&#44; a<lb/> Micah dared refuse to let his voice swell the chorus<lb/> of mean fawning parasites and mean flatterers.  He soon found a Zedekiah who struck<lb/> the seer proclaimer of distasteful truths upon the cheek.<lb/>  When Isaiah tried essayed to convince Israel&#44; who looked for<lb/> help to a foreign nation&#44; that they could not expect hope for<lb/> deliverance so long as they were proved disloyal to the Sinaic con&#45;<lb/>&#45;stitution&#44; of Sinai&#44; he raised a storm of opposition.  That<lb/> is no the kind of oratory suiting multitudes.  &#34;Speak<lb/> to us smooth things&#34; voices cried&#44; and a tradition tells<lb/> that Menasseh made an end of the bold preacher.<lb/>  Jeremiah became unbearable.  Knowing that his<lb/> admonitions reflected on the conduct demeanour of the rich and the<lb/> powerful&#44; he still continued breathing out denunciations.<lb/>  Rebuffs and buffettings were the price of his such daringness.<lb/>  Hezekiel might have fared no better.  As he cut<lb/> to the quick the Shepherds who at took in the fattest of among the<lb/> flocks&#44; who put on the wool shorn from off their backs&#44;<lb/> and suffered the charges over which they should have<lb/> watched to run at random without guidance or<lb/> restraint&#44; he also might have been sorely scourged&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>did had not the distance separating Kebar from the<lb/> Jordan screened him from the lash.  The history circumstances<lb/> connected with the predictions of the plebeian prophet seer&#45;&#45;the herdman of Tekoah&#45;&#45;<lb/> clearly obviously shows the danger to which he is exposed who<lb/> rebukes sin.  Yes&#58; history repeats itself.  Those<lb/> whose inspiration or vocation demands an unreserved<lb/> utterances&#44; will be put set unto the pillory of public<lb/> abuse.  Now&#58; I am not so arrogant as to claim the<lb/> office of a prophet&#44; the mantle of of the murdered Zechariah has not fallen upon upon my shoulders&#59; but I neither aspire to the glory<lb/> of martyrdom.  I am a plain teacher in Israel&#44; and as such I have<lb/> already borne my share of contumely.  while in the pur&#45;<lb/> &#45;suit of my calling.  I have borne while in the pursuit of my calling more than I could<lb/> like to acknowledge without a feeling sense of self&#45;debase&#45; wounded<lb/> &#45;ment dignity.  But after twenty seven year&#39;s service&#44;<lb/> I have conceived a decided aversion against rough&#45;handling.<lb/>  Willing&#44; nay&#44; anxious to do my duty to the utmost<lb/> extent of my humble capacities&#44; I will listen to<lb/> any suggestion respectfully made but dictation&#44;<lb/> or chiding as to a school&#45;boy&#44; I do not wish any shrink from&#44; and I will<lb/> more to decline not to receive nay more.  The vanity of believing that<lb/> my reading and <sic>Lecturing</sic>&#44; my deportment and<lb/> general carnage must command universal approval&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>does not enter into the category of my natural failings.<lb/>  But I possess own to this weakness&#45;&#45;if people will so call please so to term<lb/> it&#45;&#45;I think that during the short sa stay naturally al&#45;<lb/>&#45;lowed to me upon earth&#44; I ought to seek to enjoy some<lb/> mental rest&#44; of mind&#44; and not be harassed by the browbeating<lb/> of any of my Hebrew constituents or hearers.  For if it is true that the no greater punishment could be inflicted<lb/> on me than the withdrawing of their goodwill of my brethren&#44; would be to me a great<lb/> punishment&#44; I nevertheless do not still never solicited it as a per&#45;<lb/>&#45;sonal favor&#44; regardless of services rendered to the cause<lb/> I must steadily promote with steadiness.  I have always aimed to secure the favorably kind opinion of men it<lb/> by fitting exertions as servant a steward of Israel&#39;s God&#39;s holy house.<lb/>  Eternally grateful for the slightest recognition of my<lb/> labors&#44; I still nevertheless yet crave for no temporal reward&#44; material compensation&#44; further<lb/> than what was voluntarily assigned to me as a due<lb/> recompense remuneration for the performance of clerical obligations duties.<lb/>  In short&#58; I claim nothing&#44; save the right to act<lb/> independently&#44; and be addressed not as a Hazan<lb/> of olden times days in the old world&#44; but as the spi&#45;<lb/>&#45;ritual leader of a Congregation&#44; whose dignity ancient honor I have<lb/> ever endeavoured to uphold&#44; and whose real interest<lb/> I have mightily at heart.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>We Hebrews are prohibited to follow imitate the practices of gen&#45;<lb/>&#45;tiles&#44; but we may in several instances learn from<lb/> them our neighbors what will improve our standing.  The<lb/> priestly bard of Chaldea taught imparted that truth when<lb/> he so upbraided his contemporaries.  &#34;You have not<lb/> done even like the ordinances of the nations that are<lb/> roused a bout you&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93; explain the Rabbis.<lb/>  Those right proper usages they which non&#45;Israelites follow in carrying out their auto&#45;<lb/>&#45;nomy you have not striven to copy.  Our neighbors Christians<lb/> may exceed the bounds of wisdom by sacrificing in the homage and<lb/> self regard respect to pay homage to the views of in the degrees of reverence paid to their<lb/> officiating ministers&#44; but we&#44; specially the Hebrews<lb/> of the Sephardic ritual&#44; fall far below the mark<lb/> by letting the Sheliach Zebbur&#44; or minister representative of<lb/> the community&#44; be at the mercy of any who chooses<lb/> to treat him as a menial.  I do not express<lb/> myself so pointedly&#44; because I would prefer to<lb/> offer my time and efforts to other bodies of Jews.<lb/>  This Minhag is endeared to me by the earliest and<lb/> holiest associations.  I love its style diction&#44; its <sic>chauntings</sic>&#44;<lb/> its general g character&#59; nor would I&#44; so I now think&#44;<lb/> now&#44; at the time&#44; exchange Philadelphia and the Mikve<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Israel Congregation for the handsomest spot<lb/> in the globe&#44; or for the most lucrative station.  But<lb/> I hold that he from whose mouth instruction is sought&#44;<lb/> should be left <sic>untramelled</sic>; and if he is found wanting<lb/> in honesty&#44; he neither ought to be suffered to implore the<lb/> throne of Grace on behalf of his people&#44; nor obtrude his<lb/> remarks on an assemblage of Hebrews faithful Jews.  In a word&#58; a<lb/> dismissal ought to take place of an unfaithful rid the faithful of a faithless guide.<lb/>  It must Unhappily&#44; however&#44; be  unhappily acknowledged it must be confessed that the<lb/> situation of a Rabbi&#44; or preacher in America is very peculiar. presents exceptional difficulties.<lb/>  To satisfy his conscience and not to hurt the feelings<lb/> of his hearers has nearly become an impossibility.  For&#44;<lb/> the sphere of religious observances has by common consent been<lb/> so narrowed down&#44; that few will relish any allusion<lb/> to the wide circumference it originally legitimately occupied&#44; and<lb/> which has was unlawfully been trenched upon.  Eating Partaking of<lb/> the Passover bread&#44; attending the worship upon the New<lb/> Year&#44; and fasting on the day of atonement constitute<lb/> the characteristics by which most Israelites in these United States claim<lb/> the title of adherents to Judaism.  Any intimation<lb/> of depriving them of that title because they value<lb/> the earnings of the Sabbath&#44; more than God&#39;s ordinance would&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>give prove very offensive.  The breaking of the fourth com&#45;<lb/>&#45;mandment of the Decalogue is justified by commercial<lb/> necessity.  and To speak of it deprecatingly is a very to say the least<lb/> an unpopular act.  The observance keeping of the three annual festivals<lb/> by abstaining from servile work has ceased to<lb/> be deemed important.  Why shall the pulpit annoy<lb/> the men and women who at all events remember the<lb/> holidays by spending an our at in the Synagogue&#44;<lb/> with Jeremiads on the declining of the ancestral<lb/> faith belief&#63;  Dietary laws can scarcely count a few laws count nowhere a smaller number of<lb/> votaries.  So very rife is the violation of that part of our code that at<lb/> solemn ceremonies the Hebrew Jewish Minister is may be placed at<lb/> the head of the a table laden with food j <sic>unjewisly</sic><lb/> prepared&#44; and be expected to invoke a blessing on the repast and the guests from<lb/> the God who has instituted dietary special directions for that Jews must<lb/> obey in the choice of their viands.  How galling then to the ears of<lb/> such as eat strangled fowls and larded pastry to be told that<lb/> they have forfeited the names of disciples of Moses.<lb/>  And nothing more apt to make the preacher insufferable<lb/> than to by condemning the absence of those outward signs of our<lb/> creed recommended in the portion of the Shemang&#44; supposed<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>to be recited by every son of Israel when he lies<lb/> down and when he rises up.<lb/></p>
            <p>History repeats itself&#59; and here&#44; to our confusion&#44; with too<lb/> much exactness.  Like in the days when the son of Amoz<lb/> addressed the tribe of Judah&#44; my brethren this voices sound<lb/> echoes forth.  &#34;Speak to us smooth things.&#34;  My brethren<lb/> want to be pleased&#44; and not remonstrate with&#59; to be<lb/> gratified and not rather than edified.  But then they do not need<lb/> an ecclesiastic born within their fold.  Individuals<lb/> superior to him in the art of rhetorics may be met<lb/> beyond the precincts of a Rabbinical seminary.<lb/>  Individuals of a pleas with a fluent tongue and ready wit hare<lb/> not unattainable&#44; but a Darshan with us means<lb/> more than an easy speaker&#44; an agreeable lecturer.<lb/>  It means a person who searches to find discover how he can best carry<lb/> out the object of his vocation.  It means a poison<lb/> thoroughly imbued with the sanctity of his calling.<lb/>  It means a person sincerely convinced of the truths<lb/> of Judaism&#44; and fearless in proclaiming them.<lb/>  It means a person who loves the spiritual well&#45;<lb/>being of his people more than their gifts flattering resolutions and rich<lb/> testimonials gifts.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Now&#58; I have the boldness to declare that in me<lb/> You have such a one.  My mind&#44; not fraught<lb/> with wisdom&#44; may often err.  My heart&#44; impressi&#45;<lb/> &#45;ble and our sensitive&#44; may mislead my judgment&#59;<lb/> but honest are my intentions&#44; steadfast is my<lb/> devotion to the cause I have espoused.  &#182; Self&#45;pause<lb/> is loathsome.  I know it full well&#44; and were I making<lb/> my maiden speech in your presence&#44; I would blush<lb/> thus to describe my qualities&#44; but after having given<lb/> to your service my youthful years and the energy of the days<lb/> of glowing enthusiasm for the religion of Sinai which I desired<lb/> to perpetuate through your offspring&#44; I may be<lb/> pardoned for saying that my long abiding in your midst country<lb/> in this capacity should win&#44; if not a general appro&#45;<lb/>&#45;bation&#44; a respectful consideration.  As I&#44; in the<lb/> prosecution of my duty&#44; have ever shown the same regard for<lb/> that while I live with the congregation in whose midst I<lb/> hope to die&#44; I may receive a treatment which will sweeten<lb/> the rest of my existence and infuse into me unabated vi&#45;<lb/>&#45;gor even unto the last&#44; when I shall be summoned by the<lb/> great Master to give to Him an strict account of my work.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
