<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF29_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff29_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff29_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff29_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff29_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff29_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff29_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff29_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff29_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff29_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff29_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff29_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff29_2_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 3 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>For Haazinu<lb/>
                bet. Kippur &#38; Succot<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.<lb/></p>
            <p>Some time ago&#44; I paid an estimable Jewess a visit on a<lb/> Sabbath afternoon.  The conversation drifted into a religious<lb/> topic&#44; when the lady candidly said that she objected to<lb/> the discourse I had delivered in the morning.  I agreed<lb/> with her&#44; as far it regarded the language and the tone&#44;<lb/> but as to the cause which had suggested the discourse&#44; I<lb/> proved that it was calculated to provoke.  You may perhaps<lb/> recall the occasion.  My remarks had purposed to show<lb/> that parents are accountable for their children&#39;s indiffer&#45;<lb/>&#45;ence to the Synagogue and the worship.  I cited then in<lb/> my support of my assertion&#44; the case of lads who were<lb/> to go through the ceremony of being called for the first<lb/> time to the Law&#44; or being publicly acknowledge Bar Mitzvah&#44;<lb/> but who failed to put in an appearance&#44; when expected.<lb/>  I admitted that not always ought fathers and mothers to<lb/> be censured for their children&#39;s religious apathy&#44; but contended that at so<lb/> tender an age&#44; parental control ought to be visibly felt.  If at in<lb/> his thirteenth years of age&#44; a lad is heedless about the faith<lb/> in which he was born&#44; some radical fault must<lb/> exist in home education.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>That point the lady conceded&#44; but she made this sen&#45;<lb/>&#45;sible observation&#58; &#34;Scolding lectures do no good&#34;.<lb/>  I have kept her lesson in mind&#44;&#45;&#45;though I dare say<lb/> I may forget it again under the pressure of exciting<lb/> circumstances.  Accordingly&#44; more than once on being<lb/> displeased with the conduct of the boys who attend<lb/> our divine service on the Sabbath morning&#44; I tried to<lb/> express my disapproval by a look or by a slight mo&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion of the head.  But I have had reason to re&#45;<lb/>&#45;gret that the plan did not answer&#44; and seldom did<lb/> I lament its insufficiency&#44; in my mind&#44; more than on<lb/> a very late occasion.<lb/></p>
            <p>I do not allude to the behavior on the day of atone&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment&#45;&#45;though simply offensive to God and man&#45;&#45;because<lb/> the evil appears incurable.  Not until all my people<lb/> shall have learnt &#40;when will that be&#63;&#41; the spirit<lb/> of their religion&#44; and have become more reverential toward<lb/> it&#44; will the going out and coming in&#44; the exchanging<lb/> of signs and the familiar conversation cease among<lb/> adults as well as minors&#44; during the services of that<lb/> sacred day.  I do not allude to that which is beyond our<lb/> control&#44; since strangers  crowd then on Kippur our place of worship&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>as curious lookers on&#44; and we have made it a rule not<lb/> to close these doors against any person at any time.<lb/>  I have special reference now to what happened last Saturday.<lb/>  A minister of the gentile faith had just entered and seated himself<lb/> nearly opposite me&#44; while I was reading the prayer for<lb/> the government.  But just at that moment a number<lb/> of our lads&#44; some large and intelligent enough to under&#45;<lb/>&#45;stand what is due to propriety&#45;&#45;if not to religion&#45;&#45;passed<lb/> that minister in their way to the usual recess they take<lb/> in the synagogue yard.  Oh how I wished I could have<lb/> eyed them back.  How I wished when I saw them go&#44; that to spare me the shame<lb/> of their passing again before that clergyman&#44; they would<lb/> remain away the rest of the service&#33;  Fortunately&#44;<lb/> the gentleman did not ask for an introduction&#44; for had<lb/> he inquired of me&#44; whether it is the practice in our ser&#45;<lb/>&#45;vice to let our children absent themselves at a certain<lb/> stage thereof&#44; I would have felt unutterably confused.<lb/>  I know that the stranger visitor must have thought the sight peculiar&#44;<lb/> for in churches all remain within&#59; public opinion would<lb/> not tolerate a contrary deportment.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>With us Israelites&#44; public opinion is in a floating<lb/> condition.  It has not assumed any particular shape<lb/> or form.  We are certainly the most independent of<lb/> all people&#59; holding to our personal notions&#44; each<lb/> individual is left to his own option.  I deprecate<lb/> this state of affairs in religious questions&#44; and I believe<lb/> it is high time we should create a healthy public<lb/> opinion.  We must begin with to work on the hearts<lb/> and minds of the children of this generation&#44; else it will never grow<lb/> with their growth.  I thought therefore that I would<lb/> this morning mildly address the boys on a subject with<lb/> which the decorum and imposingness of our worship<lb/> are strictly connected.<lb/></p>
            <p>Dear young brethren.  I have noticed with pain that<lb/> you don&#39;t understand the holiness of this place&#44; in which<lb/> we come together to pray&#44; and ask we choose one among our number<lb/> to bless us and instruct us in the name of God.  Now&#58;<lb/> suppose you went to a friend&#39;s house&#44; and you were asked<lb/> into the parlor&#44; and you found there a great many persons&#44;<lb/> and you saw among them one&#44; who was reading a book<lb/> to the whole company&#44; and all listened&#44; or kept quiet&#44;<lb/> would you get up&#44; after a little while&#44; and with noisy steps&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>leave the room&#44; and come back again banging the<lb/> parlor door&#44; not caring a bit for the reader or for<lb/> the company&#63;  I am sure you wouldn&#39;t.  I am sure<lb/> that you would be among the first to call whoever did<lb/> so a very rude boy.  Now&#58; suppose that instead<lb/> of being in your friend&#39;s house&#44; you were in the house<lb/> of the President of the United States&#44; how much more<lb/> careful you would then be.  You would be afraid almost<lb/> to move turn on your seat&#44; not to cause the least disturb&#45;<lb/>&#45;ance.  Now consider&#44; my boys&#58; in a friend&#39;s house<lb/> you would not rise to go&#44; before all are ready to leave&#44;<lb/> so as not to be called <sic>unmmanerly</sic>&#59; in the house of the<lb/> a chief magistrate of your country you would not even move&#44; our of deep<lb/> respect.  This is the house of your greatest Friend&#44; who<lb/> gives you life and health and intelligence&#44; but it is also<lb/> the house of the2 King of Kings&#44; the1 Ruler of all rulers.<lb/>  We have dedicated it to God&#44; and not to our amusement&#44;<lb/> to God and not to our ambition.  We hoped that the<lb/> Almighty who sees and is not seen&#44; would let His<lb/> spirit be with us&#44; and receive our supetitions with favor.<lb/>  For we were told that wherever we assemble to call upon<lb/> His name&#44; He would come to us and bless us.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>I know that if some of you feel pleased when they<lb/> are given an honor in this sacred place&#44; that is a pleasure<lb/> which I approved of.  Some of you are proud to be called<lb/> to the Law&#44; soon after having become Bar Mitzvah&#44;<lb/> that is a pride to be which deserves praised.  But not one of you<lb/> ought to think that he is a man because he can strut<lb/> about in the middle of the service&#44; going in and out<lb/> with an air which seems to say&#58; &#34;I don&#39;t care&#44; this<lb/> place is like my own yard&#44; I can do as I like.&#34;<lb/>  No&#44; my boys&#44; that is not a sign of manliness&#44; but<lb/> of want of good&#45;breeding&#44; and&#44; what is still worse&#44; of<lb/> the want of proper feelings for religion and for the divine<lb/> worship.  I trust that you understand why I have addressed<lb/> you this morning&#44; and you will form now behave respect&#45;<lb/>&#45;fully&#44; not only when a Christian happens to drop<lb/> in&#44; but at all times.<lb/></p>
            <p>While I am speaking on this subject&#44; I remember that our<lb/> next holiday will be the festival of Tabernacles.  I noticed<lb/> with much pain great mortification that children run<lb/> out of the synagogue wildly&#44; both evenings and mornings&#44; expecting to<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>be among the first in the Succah.  It is time that<lb/> the fault is not always our boy&#39;s fault&#44; that strange<lb/> children flock in and conduct themselves very badly.<lb/>  But I believe that if our own children kept in till old&#45;<lb/>&#45;er persons had moved on&#44; they would shame the strangers<lb/> into a good behaviour.  There was a time when kind&#45;hearted ladies<lb/> and gentlemen used to send fine eatables in honor of<lb/> the day and of the Succah&#44; which reminds us of the<lb/> mercy of God to our forefathers&#44; who <sic>travelled</sic> through<lb/> wildernesses&#44; and had no houses&#44; but tents to save them&#45; and still they were sheltered<lb/> &#45;selves from heat and frost.  With much regret I was<lb/> obliged to advise that we should put a stop to that&#44;<lb/> on account of the children&#39;s misconduct.  Now&#44; my boys&#44;<lb/> let me ask that you will set a good example to others&#44;<lb/> who don&#39;t belong to our congregation&#44; and that during<lb/> the coming holiday you will leave the Synagogue in a very<lb/> orderly manner&#44; wait till your turn comes for going in<lb/> into the Succah&#44; and when there&#44; listen to the prayers&#44;<lb/> and behave receive &#34;what is given you with a polite<lb/> bow&#44; and always make room for those who are older<lb/> than yourselves.  I have said all I wished to say to you&#44;<lb/> and which I trust it will be enough for my purpose.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>From you parents I beg a favor.  Exercise all<lb/> the influence you possess to check the young&#59; sup&#45;<lb/>&#45;plement my few words with intelligent explana&#45;<lb/>&#45;tions on the origin&#44; the object&#44; and the sanctity of<lb/> the Synagogue.  Give your sons and daughters the<lb/> benefit of example as well as that of precept.<lb/>  The season for admonitory sermons&#44; has&#44; thank Pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;vidence&#44; passed away.  May it not have come and<lb/> gone without leaving a healthful impression.   But<lb/> I cannot sufficiently recommending guarding against a tran&#45;<lb/>&#45;sitory effect.  Let us improve the feelings aroused by<lb/> New Year and the Day of Atonement&#59; use our authority<lb/> while our dear ones are still small&#44; and under our<lb/> absolute control.  &#34;Scolding lectures&#44;&#34; as my lady<lb/> friend&#44; called one of mine&#44; will not be needed&#44;<lb/> when fathers and mothers&#44; aware of what they owe<lb/> their offspring and Judaism&#44; will attend personally<lb/> attend the worship&#44; and supervise in the Syna&#45;<lb/>gogue the conduct of their children.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
