<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF2_5</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_5_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_5_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_5_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_5_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_5_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_5_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_5_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_5_4v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>5 pages on 2 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>An unfinished lecture<lb/> on Noah.<lb/></p>
            
            <p>This lecture was finished by heart<lb/> and considerably altered and embellished<lb/> in the course of its delivery<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>The name of Rabbi Joshua Ben Levi is not<lb/> new to American Israelites.  A poet&#44; whom<lb/> the world admires&#44; but this country claims and fondly<lb/> loves&#44; has embalmed that name in sweet verses.<lb/>  Henry Wadsworth Longfellow told English speaking<lb/> peoples in flowing rhymes&#44; the Talmudic legend<lb/> of the Hebrew sage who outstripped Death&#44; and&#44;<lb/> having seized the sword of the Destroyer entered paradise<lb/> while clothed in flesh.  Nor&#44; adds the legend&#44; did he<lb/> return the bereaving weapon till after having exacted<lb/> a promise that the looks of that sword would not<lb/> terrify its victims any more.  Brethren.  It is very<lb/> natural that a Rabbi whose holy live won for him<lb/> the reputation of a saint&#44; should find disciples who<lb/> enlarged upon his every doing and every expression&#44; and<lb/> trained them up as worthy of a special record.  In<lb/> fact&#44; a volume containing prodigious acts and sayings<lb/> of a remarkable character attributed to Joshua Ben Levi<lb/> exists for the gratification of such as take pleasure<lb/> in stories and tales of the days of old.<lb/>
                I was reflecting upon a passage in to&#45;day&#39;s lesson of<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>the Pentateuch&#44; when an idea advanced by the<lb/> same famous Rabbi occurred to my mind.  Joshua<lb/> Ben Levi held that whoever sees the rainbow&#44; must<lb/> bow to the ground in humble adoration.  For so did<lb/> Ezekiel or the shores of the river Chebar&#44; when<lb/> the vision that passed before him assumed the aspect<lb/> of a rainbow.  Let us search into the meaning<lb/> of the Rabbi&#39;s thought.  We short sighted beings<lb/> are stuck with amazement at what we call a<lb/> phenomenon&#44; or an extraordinary appearance which<lb/> we cannot explain&#44; but we will fail to pause and<lb/> ponder on meeting with what is just as inexplicable&#44;<lb/> but which from the habit of seeing it often&#44; we<lb/> fancy that all can easily understand.<lb/></p>
            <p>Last spring every evening after sun set our sky con&#45;<lb/>&#45;tinued to be tinged with the deepest red&#44; and even after<lb/> night had studded the heavens with its shining stars&#44;<lb/> that appearance lingered in the West&#44; showing itself<lb/> again before dawn in the East.  Science was put<lb/> to the test&#44; but the men devoted to its study could<lb/> not agree.  Some beheld in the phenomenon the ef&#45;<lb/>&#45;fects of a volcanic eruption in far off lands&#59; others<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>attributed it to the melting of mountains of snow<lb/> assuming in the milder season that colour from the<lb/> rays of the departing and returning sun.  But whatever<lb/> may have been the cause which produced that splendid<lb/> scenery at which we <sic>marvelled</sic>&#44; because of its unusual<lb/> manifestation&#44; certain it is that its secret lies back<lb/> behind the veil which we dare not fling aside&#45;&#45;the la&#45;<lb/>&#45;boratory of Almighty God&#44; His creation of nature&#44; the<lb/> first and greatest of wonders.  When creation was<lb/> completed&#44; God made an agreement with it&#44; that<lb/> whenever so requested by its Maker&#44; it should perform<lb/> stupendous things&#44; so wrote the Talmudists&#44; and to say<lb/> it again in their language &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> the works of God at the beginning were perfect in their<lb/> formation&#44; perfect in their character&#44; that is capable<lb/> of developing the inherent forces which the Omnipotent<lb/> had set into them.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  We have visited the<lb/> last exhibition which has added honors to the city<lb/> in which we live&#44; and to the unpretending but great<lb/> man buried in yonder cemetery&#45;&#45;Benjamin Franklin&#44; who<lb/> disarmed the lightning with his rod.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>In that exposition we were shown the workings<lb/> of master minds.  Galram&#91;&#63;&#93;&#44; and Volta and Fabbroni<lb/> the Italians&#44; and Edison the American stood out in<lb/> bold relief&#44; as factors in a science&#44; supremely practical<lb/> &#45;&#45;electricity&#45;&#45;which seems destined to revolutionize arts&#44;<lb/> professions and trades.  But those celebrities created<lb/> nothing new&#44; they simply unfolded and usefully ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;plied the powers which the Almighty has given nature&#44;<lb/> by the powers of the intellect which the Almighty has<lb/> granted them.  Recognizing this truth&#44; the Jewish re&#45;<lb/>&#45;ligion asks that when standing before such persons&#44;<lb/> we should <sic>pronounced</sic> this benediction.  &#34;Blessed be Thou<lb/> O Lord our God&#44; King of the universe who hast imparted<lb/> some of Thy wisdom to human creatures&#34;.<lb/></p>
            <p>Now it does not require a scientist to produce a rain<lb/>&#45;bow.  Without being Newton one may exhibit it<lb/> in a basin of water placed in a suitable direction towards<lb/> the rays of the sun.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  But can any of us&#44;<lb/> can the highest in mind&#44; the most gifted in skill<lb/> create a single ray of the sun&#44; which breaking through<lb/> the drops of water forms the splendid colours which<lb/> it reflects&#63;<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
