<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF32_2b</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_2_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_2_7v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>2 pages on 1 sheet<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <p>When I found it necessary to gain some knowledge of English style&#44; which I might<lb/> apply acceptably in the description of Biblical characters&#44; I read attentively Miss O&#39;<lb/>Keef&#39;s &#34;Patriarchal Times.&#34;  The sketches are attractive in their language&#44; and also in&#45;<lb/>structive by reason of the moral lessons drawn from them. The authoress was not a<lb/> Jewess&#44; yet&#44; many a Jewish minister&#44; might learn from her to let som address the audience on sub&#45;<lb/>&#45;jects like those which she advanced&#44; praising in Biblical characters what deserves com&#45;<lb/>&#45;mendation and pointing out weaknesses and defects&#44; which detracted from their merits&#44; and<lb/> which we ought in consequence to avoid.  More fitting and more useful might that<lb/> plan be in general&#44; than the choosing of topics altogether foreign to the Synagogue&#44; such as<lb/> the debt which Christianity owes our people for books which&#44; after all&#44; it discards and for having given it the putative redeem&#45;<lb/>&#45;er&#44; alleged to having been born and named at this season of the year&#59; topics which are<lb/> repeated at nausem and which are at least to me&#44; very distasteful.  I myself have lately dwelt<lb/> somewhat upon the shining glorious deeds of two personages&#44; truly eminent&#44; namely&#44; Joseph the<lb/> vice roy of Egypt&#44; and Moses the leader of the tribes freed from the bondage of Egypt.<lb/>  History can produce exceedingly few&#44; if any&#44; so <sic>surpassingly</sic> good.  To day&#44; I shall try<lb/> to outline the character of a man&#44; not quite equal to the two just mentioned&#44; but<lb/> nevertheless deserving of our study and admiration.  I see him adorned with a golden<lb/> mitre&#44; upon which are read the most significant Hebrew words &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Holiness<lb/> unto the Lord.&#34;  That man was the first priest who worshipped in a Tabernacle&#44; set up in<lb/> honor of the One Almighty Lord&#59; our sages who have considered Aaron Peace the summary of<lb/> God&#39;s blessings&#44; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> appreciated Aaron&#39;s brightest virtue&#44; when they called him &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;a lover<lb/> of peace and the follower of peace.&#34;  They claim to have discovered in Malachai&#39;s gra&#45;<lb/>&#45;phic delineation of a real servant of God&#44; a counterpart of the elder son of Amram&#44;<lb/> the Levite.  Are the Talmudists correct&#63;  Can they support the ideas held forth&#44; or<lb/> have they largely drawn on the imagination&#63;  Let us judge impartially.  We first<lb/> meet Aaron&#44; when giving his long absent brother a paternal kiss.  You&#44; doubtless&#44;<lb/> remember the occasion.  Moses with that extreme humility which even for him<lb/> the title of &#34;the meekest of all men&#44; upon the face of the earth&#44;&#34; had been<lb/> unable to overcome his self&#45;distrust.  He had petitioned God to send<lb/> another on the fearful errand imposed.  The vision in the burning bush closes<lb/> with this announcement&#58; &#34;Behold Aaron&#44; thy brother&#44; the Levite&#44; will speak.<lb/>  I surely know it.  He is even coming towards thee&#44; and seeing thee&#44; he will be<lb/> glad in his heart.&#34;  Upon that a legendary volume&#44; or Midrash&#44; remarks.  Great in<lb/> deed was the joy which the older brother felt when clasping in his arms the<lb/> younger&#44; but the pleasure experienced at that hour would have been tenfold&#44; if he had<lb/> heard the all&#45;seeing God&#44; who searches our inmost soul&#44; declare him a very affection&#45;<lb/>&#45;ate brother.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  He might then have made the sound of instruments<lb/> and of songs precede his steps to the place of the fraternal meeting.  From that mo&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment&#44; the two became inseparable companions on a mission of the extremest difficulty.<lb/>  Closely associated in the momentous undertaking of working out redemption&#44; the older&#44;<lb/> unobtrusively held a subordinate position.  Envious feelings did not mar<lb/> brotherly harmony.  What mattered if the last born wielded a superior power&#44; when<lb/> the endeavours of both tended to create a nation free from galling bondage and<lb/> divinely taught&#63;  Such were the sentiments which knit two beings in one&#59; such<lb/> was the noble example&#44; that the conduct of the peace loving Aaron exhibited.  Follow<lb/>&#45;ing only straightly a line of peace&#44; his lofty figure disappears almost completely behind<lb/> that of Moses.  Yet&#44; it was Aaron who spoke and acted in the land of Egypt.  It was<lb/> mainly he who warned and punished the tyrant&#44; he who <sic>counselled</sic> and comforted the enslaved.<lb/>  &#34;He shall speak for thee to the people&#59; he shall be thy mouth piece&#44; and thou shalt be to him a <sic>a</sic><lb/> Divinity.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>So had God said in the vision vouchsafed to Moses.  The trusty interpreter of his<lb/> brother&#39;s inspired command possessed that nobility of spirit&#44; which recognizes in<lb/> another a longer gift of intellect&#59; a deeper insight into the knowledge of God&#39;s will<lb/> and the right government of men.  Mark Aaron at the battle of Rephidim.<lb/>  A youth&#45;&#45;a hitherto comparative stronger&#44; Joshua&#45;&#45;is entrusted with the generalship<lb/> at the battle of the combatants that were to repel the attack of ferocious Amalek.<lb/>  But not to aver himself with military glory did the elder brother of Moses crave&#59;<lb/> not to enter the lists and carry off trophies was his ambition.  On the top of the<lb/> hill where the archprophet raised his hands heavenward&#44; Aaron stood with him to<lb/> uphold the arms which might not drop down wearily&#44; before the sound of victory echoed<lb/> forth in the camp of Israel.  Notice again Aaron&#44; when the jealously of an ill&#45;<lb/>&#45;natured relative&#44; that of his cousin Horah&#44; stirred up a conspiracy which was intended<lb/> to strip him of sacerdotal authority.  He was pointed at as the usurper &#91;&#63;&#93; of an office<lb/> given him by partiality.  Yet&#44; he&#45;&#45;the object of Horah&#39;s wicked plot&#44; did not show<lb/> any resentment&#59; no remonstrance passed his lips.  Moses in his brother&#39;s defense<lb/> arose majestically on the occasion&#44; and asked the conspirators &#34;Aaron of what is he<lb/> guilty&#44; that ye murmur against him&#63;&#34;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  I admit&#44; the<lb/> older son of Amram fell short in the possession of such quality as constitute a brave<lb/> leader of communities.  He loved peace dearly&#44; but he lacked the energy&#44; which is<lb/> quick in appliances to meet rising emergencies successfully.  The moral weakness dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;played at upon the humiliating circumstance of his melting the women&#39;s golden rings into<lb/> the shape of a molten calf&#44; whether through a wish to temporize&#44; in the hope of<lb/> a speedy return of Moses&#44; as some commentators have alleged&#44; or whether under the threat<lb/> of being mercilessly killed&#44; as others have surmised&#44; proves at all events incapacity to face<lb/> extreme difficulties and overcome them.  But if Aaron&#39;s intellectual moral strength was<lb/> not equal to that which distinguished the archprophet&#44; his spiritual strength<lb/> would have not suffered by a comparison.  It is in the honor of severe trials that<lb/> our virtues are put to the test.  Then we can discover of what mold our mettle<lb/> be.  Joy was unusual upon the day that the first priest was installed<lb/> into office.  The hands devoted to bless God&#39;s people had been uplifted in prayerful<lb/> attitude.  The threefold benediction had been pronounced.  Suddenly a shriek of<lb/> horror thrills every heart.  Two sons of the Pontiff have met with a sudden<lb/> death.  Their presumption to enter the Holy of Holies without summons&#44; had dug<lb/> their graves.  Plunged in sorrow is the unhappy father.  Willingly would<lb/> he withdraw from that distressful scene and solitarily go to lament the sad loss.  But he<lb/> is the minister of Israel&#39;s religion&#59; he must refrain from mourning and weeping.<lb/>  Sad Moses to the bereaved parent&#58; &#34;The Lord hath spoken it.  By those who come<lb/> nigh unto Thee&#44; I must be hallowed&#34; Tears are then forced back.  The silence of pious re&#45;<lb/>&#45;signation followed &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Sublime fortitude&#33;  Now brethren reared as I have been<lb/> in the lap of Rabbinism&#44; which abounds in praises for Aaron&#44; as a model of Peace<lb/> maker&#44; admiring many trials in Aaron&#39;s character&#44; illustrated in the Scriptures and in<lb/> traditional legendary&#44; I wish that I could explain in his favor an event which<lb/> seems to contradict the sages and my impressions.  Nevertheless I may remark that<lb/> the incident which seems to have misled Aaron once into an act of unbrotherliness conduct&#44; is so<lb/> obscurely set forth in Holy Writ&#44; that it becomes almost impossible to judge of the<lb/> motive which occasioned it.  Miriam who certainly had loved Moses&#44; over whom<lb/> she had intently anxiously watched when a babe exposed to the waters of the Nile&#59; Miriam who<lb/> had invited her sisters in faith to sing in the same gladsome strains as Moses&#44; after the passage of the red<lb/> sea&#44; could not have wished to belittle his greatness.  Yet&#44; she is mentioned first as guilty<lb/> culpable of rash words.  She must have been the principal offender&#44; because she bore was made to bear<lb/> the penalty.  Who the Episthian woman was&#44; who that indirectly provoked the offence<lb/> Holy Writ does not tell.  Ancient chronicles in Midrashim and Josephus also&#44; would<lb/> have us believe that Moses&#44; after fleeing from Egypt&#44; emigrated to at one time before settling in &#91;&#63;&#93; fought in Ethiopia<lb/> and the king&#39;s daughter pe captivated by his manly looks and valor&#44; had pledged to him<lb/> her love&#44; and finally had joined the camp of Israel in the wilderness.  To pronounce a Jud&#45;<lb/>&#45;gment would be rash.  I leave the question open.  But if in that instance Aaron be&#45;<lb/>&#45;came involved in a wrong act&#44; how humble the his apology&#33;  &#34;Oh&#33; my lord say not&#44; I pray<lb/> thee&#44; a sin against us&#44; in that which we have done foolishly and sinfully.&#34;  &#91;Hebrew&#93; Barring an inde<lb/>&#45;fensible <sic>mistep</sic>&#44; proceeding from the <sic>yeilding</sic> a temperament&#44; Aaron remains a pattern<lb/> of righteousness&#44; of forbearance&#44; of piety and peace&#44; so considered him the immortal Psalmist<lb/> who couples hide with &#91;&#63;&#93; that of Moses and Samuel&#44; saying&#58; &#34;They invoked the Lord if He responded to<lb/> their petitions&#44; for they kept His testimonies and the ordinances which He had given them&#34; &#38; because he was gentle&#44; kind &#38; forbearing&#44; it is recorded that at his death all the house of Israel wept for his loss.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
