<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF2_5</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_5_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_5_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_5_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_5_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_5_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_5_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_5_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_5_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_5_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_5_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_5_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_5_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_5_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_5_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_5_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_5_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>13 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For Sabbath of penitence<lb/></p>
            
            <p>Altered&#44; abridged and corrected from an old lecture<lb/>
                delivered twenty years before.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#34;Return ye backsliding children&#44; I will heal your<lb/> backslidings.&#34;  &#34;Behold we come unto Thee&#44; for Thou art<lb/> the Lord our God.&#34;  Brethren&#33;  Is there a man&#44;<lb/> who having long been separated from a companion&#44; most<lb/> beloved&#44; does not yearn for the pressure of his friendly<lb/> hand&#63;  Is there a child who having long departed from<lb/> the parental home&#44; does not move with rapidity towards<lb/> the hearth&#44; where a father in open arms&#44; awaits for his<lb/> return&#63;  You answer there can be none.  Why are<lb/> then Israelites so tardy in returning to Him&#44; whose com&#45;<lb/>panionship is their safest guide&#44; through the devious<lb/> paths of life&#44; to Him who is the best of friends&#44; the most<lb/> loving of fathers&#63;  How does it happen that they will<lb/> so often follow their own course&#44; heeding not the land&#45;<lb/>marks set up by Providence&#63;  But hark&#33;......<lb/> The voice of warning is being heard.  &#34;Traveller&#44; thou<lb/> who treadest the path of thine own choice.  Thine eyes<lb/> have deceived thy mind.  Thou hast mistaken a meteor<lb/> for a beacon light.  Retrace thy steps&#44; ere thou be en&#45;<lb/>&#45;shrouded in darkness&#34;.  So speaks the thrilling<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>sound of the Shofar&#44; and so addresses every man<lb/> and woman in Israel&#44; this Sabbath of penitence&#44; a<lb/> season the most solemn in our year.  Suffer me<lb/> to become the interpreter of those celestial messengers.<lb/>  We are asked to submit our spiritual infirmities<lb/> to the Almighty Physician&#44; that we may be tho&#45;<lb/>&#45;roughly healed.  I shall stand before you in the<lb/> capacity of that spice&#45;merchant&#44; mentioned in the<lb/> Talmud&#44; who walked abroad&#44; offering a restorative<lb/> and crying thus &#34;Who is it that wishes for life&#44; who lives<lb/> many days&#44; that he may see good&#63;&#34;  Crowds gathered<lb/> around&#44; anxious to secure so invaluable a recipe.<lb/>  He wrote &#34;Keep thy tongue from evil&#44; and thy lips<lb/> from speaking guile.  Depart from evil&#44; and do good&#44;<lb/> seek peace and pursue it.&#34;  Whosoever has impaired<lb/> his moral health&#44; let him accept a prescription&#44; which<lb/> affords a complete cure.  Let him swallow the potion<lb/> that he may be fully restored.  Then will he have<lb/> lengthened his days.  Nay&#58; he will have renewed<lb/> his youth like the eagle&#39;s&#44; and returning to his<lb/> Father purified&#44; he will have purchased an exist&#45;<lb/>&#45;ence never ending.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>We are offered a medicine&#44; which must act in two<lb/> different manners.  I judge it to be an astringent&#44;<lb/> and a stimulant.  You understand&#44; my Brethren&#33;<lb/>  The sentence of the Psalmist&#44; demands not alone our<lb/> refraining from doing wrong&#44; but our performing what<lb/> is right.  A universal adage tells us that<lb/> habit becomes a second nature.  The maxim applies&#44;<lb/> of course&#44; both to good as well and to evil habits.  But<lb/> desiring now to refer particularly to the latter&#44; I would say&#58;<lb/> We are often loth to do at first&#44; what we do afterward constantly&#44; with&#45;<lb/>&#45;out the slightest hesitation&#44; because we overcame learnt to slight set aside the good<lb/> advice of our conscience.  Thus&#44; the practice of disparaging<lb/> the character of our neighbour&#44; or an indulgence into it imperceptibly grows upon us till it clings<lb/> to us with great the utmost tenacity.  It may be but originally a breezy<lb/> air whisper&#44; or the Rabbis would call it &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; &#34;the fine<lb/> dust of aspersion&#44;&#34; soon swelling however into a hurricane carry&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing all things before it.  The Thus the evil tongue&#44; grows shop gradually gains in its<lb/> sharper power to with it cuts right and left &#91;&#63;&#93; piercing pierce through and cut unsparingly&#44; heeding neither people&#39;s<lb/> feelings nor people&#39;s reputation.  Against a practice so<lb/> reprehensible yet so rife&#59; we are forcibly cautioned.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>A striking command occurs in the book of Leviticus.<lb/>  It forbid us to curse the deaf.  Does it mean to imply<lb/> that we may curse those whose sense of hearing is<lb/> not impaired&#63;  Most assuredly not.  It purposes to<lb/> admonish us not to blacken the character of the absent.<lb/>  To do so thoughtlessly&#44; it betrays a want degree of inconsideration&#44;<lb/> reflecting upon unbecoming a being gifted with intellect and feelings.<lb/>  To brand the name of our fellow&#45;creatures with the stigma<lb/> of reproach designedly is cowardly and unjust.  Cowardly&#44;<lb/> because if they were present&#44; we would&#44; most likely&#44; measure<lb/> our words&#44; lest we commit a personal offence.  Unjust&#44; be&#45;<lb/>&#45;cause we can never dive into the motives which occasioned<lb/> what we censure&#44; we cannot be made acquainted with<lb/> all the surroundings&#44; with the circumstances that led to error.<lb/>  But if the faults which others exhibit so scandalize our<lb/> piety&#44; why do we not conform with the precept &#34;Thou<lb/> shalt surely reprove thy neighbour&#44; and not bear any<lb/> sin against him.&#34;  Why do we not confront him&#44; as<lb/> Elijah faced Ahab&#44; as Nathan sought David&#63;  You<lb/> say to do that&#44; one must be like those inspired men&#44;<lb/> who did not court Royal favor&#44; who cared not for<lb/> popular applause&#59; but whom a scanty meal sufficed.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>But because we are unable to rise to the standard of<lb/> our superiors&#44; we2 should1 come down to the level of our<lb/> inferiors&#44; of the beings in the brute creation&#44; that shrunk<lb/> within themselves inflict sting us ar unawares&#63;  One<lb/> may put on his armor himself to repel the attack of an open enemy&#44;<lb/> but he will be unprepared to ward off the onslaught of<lb/> a concealed foe&#63;  How shall he compel the detractors<lb/> of his character&#44; to return to him the fair name of<lb/> which he has been robbed&#44; if he does not know who and<lb/> where they are&#63;  Nay&#58; the offenders themselves may be<lb/> incapacitated from repairing the mischief they have done.<lb/>  For it is easy to create an unfavorable impression about<lb/> an individual&#44; but very difficult to erase it.  You<lb/> remember that Pharaoh&#39;s magicians could turn the rods<lb/> into serpents&#44; but a power from above could alone restore<lb/> them to their primitive condition.  Therefore says our<lb/> sentence &#34;Keep thy tongue from evil&#58; If thou canst not<lb/> make favorable mention of thy neighbor&#39;s doings&#44; forbear<lb/> injuring his reputation by innuendos or defamation.<lb/>  Remember that we all are frail mortals&#44; and like reeds apt to bend under<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>the stormy passions rising within us.  The faults with<lb/> which we unscrupulously charge others&#44; may be imputed<lb/> to ourselves&#44; for&#44; the Sages have reasonably &#91;inserted above&#58; wisely&#93; asserted&#44; that<lb/> we should not trust our virtue&#44; till the day of our death.<lb/>  We ought therefore to keep close to Him whose compa&#45;<lb/>&#45;nionship will guard us from becoming entangled in the<lb/> meshes of sin&#59; heed the advice of the loving Father&#44; who<lb/> will guide us aright&#44; and keep our tongue from evil withhold our speech when it may do evil.<lb/>  But if to use a foul tongue is to be guilty of theft against<lb/> our fellow mortals&#44; to speak with guile&#44; is to steal man&#39;s<lb/> precious possession&#44; his mind &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Many will<lb/> contend that to banish deception altogether from society&#44;<lb/> is an utter impossibility.  Constituted as society the world is&#44; we<lb/> must blend a little guile with our dealings&#44; in order to<lb/> proceed smoothly.  The promotion of our temporal welfare<lb/> may imperatively demand it.  And we may do so&#44; inflicting<lb/> no pain on others&#44; nor acting to their detriment&#44; while<lb/> <sic>benefitting</sic> ourselves.  Bu the sentence I have quoted<lb/> admits of no qualification.  Not because a fault is pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;valent&#44; is its commission is less offensive to the Deity.<lb/>  According to our expositors&#44; to proffer services&#44; which<lb/> we know in advance they will be declined&#44; is a deception&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>debasing of our nature.  To be pressing in invitations&#44; which<lb/> we are certain will not be accepted&#44; to lead persons to believe<lb/> that their presence affords much pleasure&#44; that to see<lb/> it again will be happiness to us&#44; and similar expressions&#44;<lb/> rarely meant in earnest&#44; is to violate the injunction<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Keep away from false matter.&#34;  The Talmud il&#45;<lb/>&#45;lustrates its teaching by the narrative of the following in&#45;<lb/>&#45;cident.  A Rabbi renowned for his learning was taking<lb/> a walk for his recreation with his pupils.  While proceeding<lb/> in his way&#44; he was met by a certain personage returning<lb/> from a long journey.  That individual mistaking the<lb/> object of the Rabbi&#44; said&#58; &#34;It pains me to think that<lb/> you should have taken the trouble to walk our purposely<lb/> to welcome me home.&#34;  &#34;Not so&#34; interrupted the honest teacher<lb/> of old.  &#34;Such had not really been my intention.  I simply<lb/> desired to find some diversion in strolling about for a while.&#34;<lb/>  Others might have confirmed a mistake&#44; which would<lb/> possibly prove advantageous&#44; or at all events&#44; have remained<lb/> silent&#44; allowing him who was deceived laboring under a mistake&#44; to make his own<lb/> construction.  The Rabbi would have deemed that an unpardonable<lb/> prevarication&#44; and quickly he disabused the mind unwittingly de&#45;<lb/>&#45;ceived.  In like manner as he would keep his tongue from evil&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>so did he restrain his lips from speaking guile.<lb/>  But however essential it is to the restoration of our  moral<lb/> health that we abstain from the two sins of which I<lb/> have hitherto referred&#44; we cannot hope to remain sound<lb/> and well&#44; unless our negative goodness is accompanied by<lb/> positive righteousness.  As with regard to our bodily pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;servation we may be obliged to have recourse alike to stimulants<lb/> as well as to astringents&#44; so touching our spiritual recovery<lb/> we must feel incited to active virtues&#44; in the same manner as we<lb/> are checked from &#91;&#63;&#93; vice.  Our sentence tells us that<lb/> Judaism is not a negative but a positive religion&#44; that<lb/> is&#44; it demands of its votaries&#44; To &#34;depart from evil&#44; and<lb/> do good&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93; To &#34;seek peace and pursue it&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>  But what is good&#63;  What is the good&#44; so important to<lb/> our health&#44; and which the Psalmist urgently recommends&#63;<lb/>  I open the pages of profane history&#44; and discover that it has<lb/> not always conveyed the one meaning.  There was a time<lb/> when it was men considered it good to sacrifice our nearest and dearest<lb/> to the shrine of implacable gods.  There was a time&#44; when<lb/> it was children deemed it good to cut the threads of their parents&#39; life&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>to lessen the pain of protracted diseases.  There was<lb/> a time when it was people judged it good to wash out the stain<lb/> imagined to have been cast on our honor&#44; with the blood of<lb/> the offender.  There was a time when it was so called &#91;&#63;&#93;polished nations reckoned it<lb/> good that the many should labor for the few&#59; and that<lb/> the bulk of mankind be a footstool to those whom chance<lb/> has lifted high.  Even in our own days&#44; the signification<lb/> of that word varies according to climes&#44; and to the degree of<lb/> civilization men of different lands have attained.  Thus a<lb/> Brahmin will not understand it like a Turkish Mufty.<lb/>  Nor either of them as a minister of the Nazarene church<lb/> interprets it.  What is then to us Hebrews the supreme<lb/> good we must choose&#44; as essential to our salvation&#63;<lb/>  Our Bible&#44; my Brethren&#33;  The word of God breathed into<lb/> holy men&#44; that is the good to which we must cling.<lb/>  I have given you a good instruction&#44; forsake not my<lb/> Law.&#34;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  To others the term good may<lb/> have a relative meaning&#44; to us Israelites it has had<lb/> a positive signification for the last thirty five centuries&#44;<lb/> adherence to the moral and ceremonial behests is good&#59;<lb/> it is working for our deliverance&#59; through the restoration<lb/> of our moral and spiritual health.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>I shall not ask whether we act as if we adhered<lb/> with fidelity to that good.  The walks of this Sy&#45;<lb/>&#45;nagogue with a triumphant tongue speak of our heedless&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness.  They tell us to compare the throng which assembled<lb/> here on the last Rosh Hashan&#225;&#44; with the slender number<lb/> who came to sanctify the Sabbath of penitence&#59; and to<lb/> Judge for ourselves draw the conclusion.  Aye&#58; the Sabbath&#44; the sign of<lb/> the covenant between the heavenly Legislator and his people&#44;<lb/> is wantonly desecrated.  Not exclusively by those&#44; whose<lb/> famished children look for a morsel doled out to them by<lb/> their indigent parents&#44; but specially by such&#44; who could<lb/> well spare of their superfluities&#44; the earnings of the<lb/> holiest day.  The Sabbath is set at <sic>nought</sic>&#44; and<lb/> as a legitimate issue&#44; we contemplate the chilling apathy<lb/> of the rising generation for the ancestral faith&#59; the<lb/> undisguised aversion evinced by our children for what concerns<lb/> the ordinances of Holy Writ the Decalogue.  Parents have said<lb/> within my hearing&#44; that they will not bias the minds<lb/> of their minds of their sons and daughters.  When<lb/> arrived at the age of maturity&#44; the truths enunciated by<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>Moses and the prophets will assert themselves&#44; and strike<lb/> a deep root into the minds of intellectual Israelites.<lb/>  But are we so certain that they will discern between sublime<lb/> verities&#44; and that which bears the semblance thereof&#63;  Is it<lb/> not more probable that in the continual din&#44; in the tur&#45;<lb/>&#45;moil of a busy life&#44; our offspring will not bestow their<lb/> thoughts upon a subject all&#45;important to their hereafter&#63;<lb/>  Our law&#45;giver who knows human nature because He framed it&#44;<lb/> would not that we trust to future circumstances the education<lb/> of our children.  He recommended &#34;Thou shalt teach the commands dili&#45;<lb/>&#45;gently.&#34;  &#34;You shall teach them to your children&#44; speaking of<lb/> them.&#34;  Between each maternal kiss&#44; and paternal embrace&#44;<lb/> we ought to instill into them the principles of the Mosaic<lb/> code.  Explain that life is not a ceaseless grappling<lb/> with fortune.  That higher duties than gathering pelf<lb/> have been imposed upon creatures destined for immortality.<lb/>  That such alone&#44; who have learnt how to combine the<lb/> gathering of their own daily bread&#44; with the accomplishing of<lb/> their obligations to God and their fellow creatures beings are the<lb/> chosen representatives of Judaism.  Then will we have<lb/> &#34;departed from evil&#34;&#44; &#34;and done good&#44;&#34; while we will also have<lb/> &#34;sought peace and pursued it.&#34;  The peace of our<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p>mind&#44; feeling that we have used our best endeavours<lb/> in discharging the task required at our hands as fathers<lb/> and mothers in Israel.  The peace of our progeny&#44; whom<lb/> we will have supplied with a support&#44; through the ever&#45;<lb/>&#45;changing incidents of this terrestrial existence.  The peace<lb/> of the community&#44; we will have furnished with members&#44;<lb/> whose integrity rests upon the immoveable basis of a<lb/> belief in a Judge&#44; at exacting an account of our deeds.<lb/>  Do that good&#44; parents&#59; follow that prescription&#44; which<lb/> proves a complete restorative.  Let our spiritual health be ever de&#45;<lb/>&#45;clining&#44; we may recuperate the necessary strength.  And<lb/> provided we follow the companionship of our heavenly friend&#44;<lb/> and heed the counsel of our beneficent Father&#44; the voice invitingly<lb/> exclaiming.  &#34;Return ye backsliding children&#44; I will heal your<lb/> backslidings&#34; will joyfully proclaim &#34;I have forgotten<lb/> your sins&#44; and your trespasses shall not remembered any more&#34;<lb/> Oh let us all return&#44; with throbbing hearts to our forgiving<lb/> Lord &#34;Behold we come unto Thee&#44; for Thou art in very<lb/> deed the Lord our God&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
