<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF14_3</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_3_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_3_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_3_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_3_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_3_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_3_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_3_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_3_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_3_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_3_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_3_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_3_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>3d lecture on Revelation.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.<lb/></p>
            <p>Ideas cannot spread abroad miraculously.  A single<lb/> individual&#44; gifted with keen understanding and a philanthropic<lb/> heart&#44; may find out an invaluable truth.  Deeming it pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;motive of social progress&#44; he may feel eager to propagate<lb/> it.  But to accomplish his object he must needs unavoidably employ<lb/> human agencies&#44; else the verity he discovered will remain<lb/> an abstraction&#44; of no practical utility.<lb/></p>
            <p>Now&#58; I will not be charged with heresy&#44; when I assert that<lb/> Providence acts in the same principle&#44; for our continued exist&#45;<lb/>&#45;ence&#44; as a distinct people&#44; proves me indisputably correct.<lb/>  Israel is God&#39;s devised medium&#44; as revealed in the visions to the soul of<lb/> vouchsafed to the great believer&#45;&#45;Abraham in the visions vouchsafed unto him&#59; and as foreshadowed&#44;<lb/> in the never consuming bush&#44; to the mind of the heaven&#45;soaring<lb/> thinker&#45;&#45;Moses.  &#34;My first&#45;born son is Israel&#44;&#34; was the<lb/> message sent to the King of Egypt.  The Father of all beings<lb/> has taken took under his immediate tuition the oldest child first&#44; in the<lb/> household so that from him the younger branches of that same household identical family<lb/> might learn the rules of life.  The teaching began early with a prepared<lb/> and &#91;&#63;&#93;.  It but and proceeded slowly&#44; almost imperceptibly in every instance&#59; yet&#44; each but every lesson stage in the historical develop&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment of the first born son of God&#44; imparted a lesson of universal advantage.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>A hard  bondage and a glorious redemption&#44; in territorial<lb/> conquest&#44; and a sore captivity&#44; a partial limited restoration and a<lb/> wide&#45;spread exile&#44; dire sufferings and a phenomenal survival&#59;<lb/> all these pase phases in the annals of a our nation may be termed the interweaving of so many threads which<lb/> will finally produce a texture&#44; as beautifully designed by the Master&#45;Mind.<lb/>  Let me be plain.  The destiny of Israel concerns mankind&#44; Mankind is concerned in the destiny of Israel&#44;<lb/> because Israel and mankind are knit together&#45;&#45;for a high purpose&#45;&#45;by the hand of<lb/> One Omnipotent Father There does not exist a break&#44; holding has bound Israel to mankind&#44; for a high<lb/> apart the instructors from the instructed. purpose.<lb/></p>
            <p>I must emphasize this idea which to me&#44; as the pivot round I look upon as the sole cause<lb/> which Judaism hinges for the origin&#44; and indestructible existence maintenance of my people.  Israel is the people chosen of God&#44; but<lb/> not the favorite of a partial Deity.  His God is a shield<lb/> of protection to the appointed messengers of a Divine will&#44; but He is not a<lb/> tribal God.  At no price&#44; not even to raise a band of<lb/> sworn defenders of to orthodoxy&#44; would I instill encourage a sentiment<lb/> which may estrange our youths from the rest of the human<lb/> race&#44; which may cramp their views&#44; and warp check their gene&#45;<lb/>&#45;rous instincts.  No&#58; I say it&#44; and every fibre of my being heart being<lb/> re&#45;echoes the words&#58; Israel is has a special title&#44; has a has a title to a &#91;&#63;&#93; to a deathless life as the servant ministering priest of humanity&#59; and has whose<lb/> God is &#34;the God of the spirit of all flesh.&#34;  Supremely important<lb/> it is that this idea strike deep root into the hearts of my young<lb/> coreligionists.  Their remaining believers depends on it.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>For if the accusation f execrable mendacious charge of prejudiced men be true that the receives finds credence among the ri&#45;<lb/>&#45;sing generation of our children&#59; if they are poisoned by the thought that the Jew&#44; to continue a Jew&#44; must be a fungus in the social body&#44;<lb/> an alien everywhere&#59; with no that he must disown any community of interests feelings and<lb/> interests binding him to with the bulk of the population among<lb/> whom he lives&#59; or if some Rabbinical Talmudical utterances extorted by bitter<lb/> persecutions be correct&#44; and&#44; accordingly&#44; accepted authoritatively&#44; and our children become impressed with the notion that a Jew must shun the<lb/> world at large as pollution&#44; and prefer a state of isolation&#44; then the children<lb/> of Hebrews in this generation will grow either infidels or bigots. not intelligent believers but infidels or bigots scoffing infidels or insufferable bigots will<lb/> misrepresent grow in our midst to dishonor their faith and their ancestry.<lb/>  To avert either evil&#44; they our sons and daughters should be made to weigh well the<lb/> imparting of Revelation.  They will learn with a positive&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness which leaves no room for doubts chases away casts away out all misgivings and suspicions&#44; that the Lord of the<lb/> patriarchs is the beneficent Creator beneficent Maker of heaven and earth all nations &#91;Hebrew&#93; the author of heaven &#38; earth&#59; He who has no regard<lb/> for class or caste&#44; but who rewards righteousness and justice<lb/> in all sentient creatures wherever found.<lb/></p>
            <p>Our prophets did us a language apt&#44; at first sight&#44; to mislead&#44;<lb/> capable of giving a color to the erroneous notion opinion of a racial<lb/> God&#44; but let it be remembered that they spoke in a world<lb/> altogether polytheistic.  Thus when Pharaoh claimed<lb/> ignorance of the Eternal Lord&#44; the Adona&#239; in whose name<lb/> he was asked to allow his slaves an intermission of three days from their labor&#44;<lb/> Moses said that &#34;the God of the Hebrews&#34; demanded it.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>That expression he repeated throughout his the warnings&#44; which<lb/> foretolding the coming chastisements&#59; yet those &#91;&#63;&#93; Hebrews&#44;<lb/> accustomed to a popular phraseology&#44; which seems to admit<lb/> a plurality of gods&#44; knew form ancestral traditions that the<lb/> adorable Lord is the Absolute One&#44; all&#45;sustaining and all&#45;<lb/>loving.<lb/></p>
            <p>Reflect an instance on the announcement of Israel&#39;s selection&#44;<lb/> before that a voluntary acceptance of the Decalogue openly invested clothed the pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;geny of Abraham the faithful with a spiritual mission power.  &#34;Now&#44; if you<lb/> will indeed hearken to obey my voice indeed&#44; and keep my covenant&#44;<lb/> you shall be a peculiar treasure to me from among all peoples&#44;<lb/> for all the earth is mine.  You shall be to me a kingdom of priests<lb/> and a holy nation.&#34;  Here the relation between God and humanity&#44;<lb/> and the position of Israel towards mankind are clearly defined.<lb/>  The world and its inhabitants the dwellers therein are dear to the Almighty&#44; but<lb/> He set apart as a medium of divine instruction&#44; such as were among the inhabitants as were then willing<lb/> and capable of fitted to carrying out and perpetrating the law.  and what was this in very<lb/> truth&#44; but the embodiment of the principles which the Parent<lb/> of good had originally implanted into the human breast&#44;<lb/> for human happiness but which the fumes of the passions stifled&#63;<lb/>  Righteousness and justice&#44; the twin regenerating virtues&#44; which the life of<lb/> Abraham was to mirror forth&#44; and which Moses understood in their<lb/> perfection&#44; received a heavenly sanction&#44; in a manner manifestation terrifically grand.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>No unfathomable dogmas was were imparted&#44; but rules for guidance here below&#44; conducive<lb/> to the wef welfare of nations and individuals.  I have<lb/> shown&#44; in a former lecture&#44; why and how idolatry was is destructive<lb/> of man&#39;s felicity.  You comprehend then the reason that the Decalogue<lb/> inserts upon the rejection of polytheism.  Well Now&#58; the recognition<lb/> of One Sovereign God King&#44; implies the duty of showing Him alone<lb/> reverence&#44; of guarding against a light treatment of His majestic august<lb/> name&#44; not to endanger the social order.  The acknowledgment<lb/> of One universal Creator&#44; brings with it the obligation of giving all<lb/> creatures who labor for or with us a time for rest and relaxation.  I shall not make any<lb/> reference to the six commandments which follow the ordinance of<lb/> the Sabbath.  Their essentialness to the stability of families and<lb/> peoples is obvious to all who have a reflecting thinking mind.  But I<lb/> will say again more plainly what my study of the important subject in which we<lb/> are engaged has disclosed to me.  The Decalogue was not in the declaration promulgation of<lb/> new religion never known&#44; nor practised observed.  No&#58; it It presented a sublime codification of laws severally<lb/> practised by the virtuous among men previous to the days of Moses&#44;<lb/> but and in a manner most splendid the nearest to completion and most admirable by Joseph the son of<lb/> Jacob.  The author of that codification is Almighty God&#44; and the<lb/> recipient is priestly sacerdotal Israel.  But the gift was a trust&#44; and so<lb/> it has&#44; measurably&#44; proved&#44; since a considerable portion of the dwellers<lb/> of the earth has eagerly sought its possession&#44; and treasured it partly at least it up.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>The sanctification of the seventh day of the week Sabbath would<lb/> appear an exception&#59; for&#44; the Decalogue simply confirmed what<lb/> the miracle descent of the manna had specially particularly enjoined upon<lb/> the Hebrews.  But though the observance of the seventh day may be exclusively be Jewish&#44;<lb/> the humanitarian principle it which the institution involves&#44; is all&#45;comprehensive<lb/> in its application.  &#182;Now I imagine I have explained have clearly demonstrated set forth the necessity for<lb/> a revelation&#44; and the object to be accomplished by its chosen pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;pagators.  Still&#44; I have cause to think believe that the my intel&#45;<lb/>&#45;ligent hearers who have so far followed the thread train of my<lb/> thoughts&#44; demur at one of the agencies of revelation&#44; that<lb/> is&#44; the performance of miracles.  Specially are Notably does their judgments<lb/> in suspense in waver regarding the superhuman voice that spoke<lb/> from the top of Sinai.  And I&#44; fearing myself distrusting my own self&#59; dreading<lb/> unintentional utterances of impiety would prefer silence.<lb/>  Yet I dare not follow please my inclination when a great issue<lb/> is at stake&#45;&#45;Our youths&#39; favorable or unfavorable impression<lb/> of the religion in which they were born which will have a bearing upon their future conduct through life.  Well&#58; Ju&#45;<lb/>&#45;daism does not depend upon miracles.  The teachings it<lb/> communicates are not worthy of our obedience because not for their being con&#45;<lb/>&#45;nected with events occurrences which we cannot naturally explain&#44; but be&#45;<lb/>&#45;cause they are inherently sublime&#44; and as seen by the light<lb/> of reason and experience.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Still&#44; Judaism Jewish books relates wonders which effected great<lb/> or beneficial ends.  Were the laws of nature then suspended<lb/> for a time&#63;  If so&#58; would might not the disruption or derangement<lb/> of the whole structure of the universe follow&#63;  So Thus we ask ourselves&#44; because<lb/> we&#44; unavoidably&#44; base form our criterions from seeming analogues. which are<lb/> not analogies.  We compare the work of finite beings with<lb/> the work of infinite wisdom&#44; and draw our imperfect inferences.  For<lb/> instance example.  We know that if a machine made for a certain<lb/> purpose is tampered with in any of its parts&#44; the entire motion<lb/> will be hindered&#59; bu this happens because the mechanic<lb/> can only act according to the laws of nature&#44; and of each the properties<lb/> of the different materials of which he makes use&#44; at his command&#44; but God&#44; who<lb/> is the author of nature&#44; and of each of its laws&#59; of all substances<lb/> and their properties&#59; God who has built up worlds not through<lb/> means already prepared by by his own absolute volition&#44; can produce a<lb/> miracle&#44; without sensibly affecting the whole structure&#44; and nor the<lb/> laws of which generally guide govern it.  In a word&#44; He can do<lb/> what we consider physically impossible&#44; as we would<lb/> likewise consider likewise impossible many a phenomenon of magnetism<lb/> and elecrt elecrti electricity&#44; but at which w we have ceased wondering stand against to be struck with<lb/> amazement&#44; because our ey senses have become accustomed to<lb/> it.  Thus little I have ventured to say&#44; on general terms.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Referring&#44; however&#44; to the audible utterances of the<lb/> Deity on the summit of Horeb&#44; I will reproduce the thought<lb/> of our believing whole&#45;souled philosopher and poet&#44; Judah Hallevi.<lb/>  For Far be it that our religion should admit what reason<lb/> rejects as false.  The very opening of the Decalogue aims<lb/> to repel the idea of a God with bodily organs&#44; but He who<lb/> created the air may have caused certain vibrations to pass<lb/> through it&#44; and strike the ears of the listeners&#44; and make that they might<lb/> hear distantly what He desired them to learn.  Urge me<lb/> no further&#44; my intelligent youths&#59; but halt and ponder on the ema&#45; mani&#45;<lb/>&#45;nation &#45;festation of the Omnipotent Spirit.  Read in the history of the<lb/> human race&#44; in whose development you have singularly<lb/> participated&#44; read the results of the revelation of the Everlast&#45;<lb/>ing Adona&#239; to your fathers&#44; and you will issue from your con&#45;<lb/>&#45;templation nobler&#44; higher&#44; stronger in faith&#44; more thank&#45;<lb/>&#45;ful for your origin&#59; more hopeful of the future.<lb/></p>
            <p>&#40;The subject of my next lecture will be the Pentateuch and<lb/> its authenticity&#41;.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
