<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF3_9</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1897" source="" attested="yes">1897</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_9_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_9_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_9_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_9_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_9_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_9_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_9_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_9_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_9_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_9_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_9_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_9_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_9_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_9_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_9_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_9_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>14 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>97<lb/></p>
            <p>On the 46th anniversary<lb/>
                of my ministry<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>I have been weighing quite long in my mind the propriety&#45;&#45;<lb/> or may be the impropriety&#45;&#45;of making my own self<lb/> the subject of a discourse upon this Sabbath.<lb/>  I venture it&#59; for because it seldom happens that the<lb/> same person fills a situation of a threefold character&#44;<lb/> and less seldom more rarely does it happen that he remains in<lb/> it forty six consecutive years.  That uninter&#45;<lb/>&#45;rupted period I complete just now in the ser&#45;<lb/>&#45;vice of this Congregation.  The very few<lb/> yet remaining among my brethren&#44; who saw<lb/> me enter a career so continuously followed&#44; may&#44;<lb/> I hope&#44; testify to my having all along avoided<lb/> egotism in my speeches and in my deeds.<lb/>  However&#44; as I am very far from claiming in&#45;<lb/>&#45;fallibility&#44; I admit that occasions may have arisen<lb/> when natural impulses overpowered the counsels<lb/> of precedence.  Still&#44; I feel certain that<lb/> neither my talks nor my actions ever inflicted per&#45;<lb/>&#45;manent injury&#44; surely they did not reflect dishonor<lb/></p> 
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>upon the religious body to which I minister.<lb/>  The preservation of its respectability and its<lb/> welfare had been invariably the end that I have<lb/> wished to attain.  Firmly holding that<lb/> conviciton&#44; I feel emboldened to apply to my&#45;<lb/>&#45;self the language of the latest&#44; but greatest of the<lb/> Judges of Israel.  Before Samuel withdrew from the station which he had filled with unswerving<lb/> integrity&#44; he asked his people whether they<lb/> could remember that he had ever winked at<lb/> wrong for the sake of gain&#59; whether the had<lb/> ever allowed bribe to corrupt his morals&#59; whether<lb/> he had ever stealthily hidden away that by which<lb/> human influences sought to get the mastery<lb/> over his sense of self&#45;respect.  Like Samuel<lb/> I have grown old in ministering to my people&#44;<lb/> older&#44; according to historical traditions&#44; than the son<lb/> of Hannah was at his death.  I ask then<lb/> whether nay one has discovered that the sight<lb/> of gold so dazzled me that I mistook the path<lb/> of unrighteousness for the way of integrity&#59; that<lb/> I interpreted self&#45;interest as a Divine Call.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Pertinent is the query&#44; for age and ailments give are<lb/> me the premonitions announcing at that my continuance on earth may<lb/> be of short duration.  Surely&#44; not to be reckoned<lb/> by a return of years.  Before I am sum&#45;<lb/>&#45;moned away&#44; let such as have detected in me<lb/> evidences of a reprehensible conduct&#44; condemn now<lb/> in public what I might have sought in vain<lb/> to commit in secret.  But looking back<lb/> with unsparing impartiality&#44; I am given reasons<lb/> to believe that there are some in this very assem&#45;<lb/>&#45;blage who might rise and say&#58; &#34;The man who<lb/> addresses us this Sabbath did not only decline<lb/> what might have temporally <sic>benefitted</sic> him&#44;<lb/> but he has repeatedly parted with his own<lb/> to hinder the decay of the religious body&#44; whose<lb/> perpetuity he has had always at heart.&#34;  Aye&#58;<lb/> more than that they could say&#44; and I rejoice<lb/> because of it.  They could attest that the poorest<lb/> have met in me a sympathetic friend&#44; a ready<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>help in sorrow and in want&#44; that the untutored<lb/> have had a gratuitous and anxious teacher<lb/> in the merest rudiments of learning&#44; not less<lb/> than in higher branches of sacred literature.<lb/></p>
            <p>But to shun flattery&#44; distasteful to the<lb/> upright when spoken by laymen&#59; disgusting<lb/> when indulged in by clergymen&#44; I must&#44; on<lb/> my part make an acknowledgment on this&#44; to me&#44;<lb/> a day of memorial.  My efforts have not<lb/> been seconded by those in whose behalf I tried<lb/> faithfully to labor.  While other congre&#45;<lb/>&#45;gational schools count the attendance by<lb/> the hundreds&#44; ours can scarcely count it by<lb/> the tens.  Some of us pride themselves on<lb/> the retention of the old land&#45;mark&#59; I mean&#44;<lb/> the preservation of the Hebrew language in our<lb/> ritual&#44; and provisions to that effect have<lb/> been made in our constitution and by&#45;laws&#44;<lb/> while the preamble thereof declares that our<lb/> aim is to improve and extend religious in&#45;<lb/>&#45;fluences.  Yet&#44; we have allowed our child&#45;<lb/>&#45;ren to grow in ignorance of the language of<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>the Bible and of the contents and spirit of<lb/> Holy Writ.  Does it surprise that Jewish youths<lb/> turn their backs on this minor sanctuary and<lb/> prefer to it &#34;temples&#34; where a close approxima&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion to the governing rules of the Church is the con&#45;<lb/>&#45;trolling object&#59; where the man of Nazareth is held<lb/> up as a paragon of sanctity&#44; superior to Moses<lb/> in his lessons of a religion of love&#63;  Say&#44; my<lb/> brother&#45;Israelites.  Can orthodoxy and a voluntary<lb/> unacquaintance with the import of the written and<lb/> oral Law be synonymous&#63;  Kind friends&#44; who<lb/> know my sentiments&#44; tell me to cease worrying<lb/> concerning matters beyond my control&#59; relatives<lb/> remonstrate against my agreeing to every propo&#45;<lb/>&#45;sition&#44; requiring exertions on my part in the line of<lb/> Jewish instruction.  They fear that my health<lb/> might suffer.  But what value has a pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;tracted life of ease for an earnest Jew&#44; who feels<lb/> that duty demands restless energy&#44; unabated exertions&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Those exertions are still&#44; as they always were&#44;<lb/> at the disposal of my people.  But I can&#45;<lb/>&#45;not conceal that had they been practically re&#45;<lb/>&#45;warded&#44; this congregation would have taken the<lb/> lead in the triumphal march of loyalty to<lb/> the Torah.  It would never have suffered back&#45;<lb/>&#45;sliders to jeer at our apathy&#44; at our lack<lb/> of consistency&#44; evinced in empty schools&#59; in a<lb/> liturgy left determinedly beyond comprehension.<lb/>  Believe&#44; my brethren&#44; that if I have insisted<lb/> upon associating lectures with our accepted prayers&#44;<lb/> it has not been for the sake of earning popu&#45;<lb/>&#45;larity&#44; for very rarely&#44; I <sic>yeild</sic> to the request<lb/> to let my speeches here occupy the columns of<lb/> religious or secular papers.  My sole object<lb/> was to interest the young in our history&#44; and enhance<lb/> thereby the respect due to the Hebrew ritual.<lb/>  But where are the young on Sabbaths and Festivals&#63;<lb/>  Not here&#59; not here.  My Maker alone<lb/> knows the anguish of my soul at the recollection<lb/> of the large number&#44; who have grown only to<lb/> forget the synagogue&#44; in which they were raised&#59;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>to become indifferent&#44; if not inimical to<lb/> their extraction from patriarchs and prophets&#59;<lb/> the many&#44; I say&#44; who recognize me not as<lb/> the one who tried his best to offer some instruct&#45;<lb/>&#45;ion.  The only shade of comfort to my<lb/> burning feelings is the knowledge that in<lb/> no instance did my personal neglect or indif<lb/>&#45;ference occasion the sundering of any Jew from<lb/> a connection with our fold.  On the contrary&#44;<lb/> looking back with the severest scrutiny at<lb/> the forty six years of my ministration&#44; I can<lb/> do myself justice by recalling circumstances&#44; when<lb/> I bore insults&#44; slights and rough denials in<lb/> my endeavouring to prevent the humblest attend&#45;<lb/>&#45;ants in this house of God to withdraw from it.<lb/>  My regret at the absence of such is aggravated by<lb/> the fact that on every revolving Sabbath&#44; it<lb/> becomes more difficult to select Israelites who may<lb/> share the honors connected with the performance of<lb/> our rites and ceremonies&#44; without having recourse nearly<lb/> always to the same identical persons.  To that morti&#45;<lb/>&#45;fication is added the pain produced by the want of<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>respect&#45;&#45;not to me that I claims none but<lb/> to our Sanctuary&#44; by the young who imitate<lb/> their elders in quitting these sacred courts&#44;<lb/> before the service is concluded.<lb/></p>
            <p>Now&#44; brethren&#44; I am fully aware that such<lb/> remarks as have fallen this morning from my lips&#44; because<lb/> chilled by a deep sense of my accountability<lb/> before God&#44; may be deemed by some an impolite<lb/> speech.  Censure&#44; however built on sound found&#45;<lb/>&#45;ations&#44; is always distasteful.  But the she&#45;<lb/>&#45;pherds who paint their flock as spotlessly<lb/> white to win favor&#44; cannot care for the<lb/> real progress of their charges&#44; as I care for the<lb/> spiritual advancement of mine.  Hear me&#58;<lb/> In the days of Isaiah&#44; the prophets were approach&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed by their contemporaries in the following language.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Speak ye to us smooth<lb/> things&#44; preach Ye pleasant things&#59;&#34; but too dear<lb/> was truth in the minds of the olden Seers&#44; that they<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>should dare to prevaricate.  I&#44; the least of<lb/> God&#39;s servants&#44; impressed with the holidays<lb/> of the mission assumed&#44; will not prove<lb/> false to it.  I read almost daily of<lb/> festivities held to celebrate anniversaries of having<lb/> first entered the ministry&#44; or having officiated<lb/> half a decade&#44; or a decade&#44; or a score of years.<lb/>  Fancy that I were to invite Philadelphia Jews<lb/> with whom I am closely identified&#44; to come this<lb/> Sabbath and rejoice with me&#44; over the visibly<lb/> permanent good accomplished among nearly<lb/> three generations&#44; would not history rise and<lb/> strike the meretricious mouth that speaks<lb/> smooth things&#44; self adulatory things&#63;..........<lb/> Once more will I say it.  The short time naturally<lb/> left to me upon earth&#44; shall still belong to the<lb/> brethren who whilom entrusted a youth of fo&#45;<lb/>&#45;reign birth with solemn obligations.  What I<lb/> know of Judaism shall continue to be theirs on de&#45;<lb/>&#45;mand.  My feelings for Jews shall&#44; to the very <lb/>last&#44; be disclosed to them&#44; so that their own feelings<lb/> be enkindled with love for all the coheirs of the Sinaic<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>covenant.  I will keep at the post that I have<lb/> been assigned&#44; until the body which now stands at<lb/> this desk shall have ceased to move&#44; but never<lb/> will I remain by promising to thrust verity aside<lb/> and set up flattery and falsehood in its place.<lb/>  The same candor&#44; which is my inseparable com&#45;<lb/>panion&#44; I shall ask now to become the inter&#45;<lb/>&#45;preter of one of my thoughts&#44; before we part to<lb/> day.  I crave for a manifestation of confidence.<lb/>  What is bidden of a novice&#44; or a tyro&#44; let not<lb/> be enforced on a Hazan&#44; teacher and preacher<lb/> of forty six years&#39; standing.  When his<lb/> services are sought after by Israelites not imme&#45;<lb/>&#45;diately affiliated to this congregation&#44; let ac&#45;<lb/>&#45;ceptance or declination be left to his judgment<lb/> and discretion.  Let printed rules remain in<lb/> abeyance when to carry them out is to wound a<lb/> minister&#39;s feelings and lower him in the estimation<lb/> of a whole community.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p>I may be permitted to add&#44; that if I had<lb/> heeded words in types rather than have consult<lb/>&#45;ed my sentiments&#44; even some of the Sabbath<lb/> services might have been omitted.  Really&#44; an<lb/> the evil result would have followed my adhering<lb/> to the letter of the original contract which I was de&#45;<lb/>&#45;manded to sign.  I would have been then a drone&#44;<lb/> not a working bee&#44; striving to extract from the<lb/> flowery garden of our literature some of its sweet&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness for the benefit of my people.<lb/>Well&#44; brethren.  Assured of the token of regard&#44; which<lb/> I have just requested&#44; I urge upon the temporal<lb/> directors of this religious body to make a strong<lb/> effort for the broadening of our schools&#59; a power&#45;<lb/>&#45;ful endeavour to increase the attendance in the<lb/> Synagogue at all times.  Of my usual hearers<lb/> now present or absent&#44; I fraternally beg that an<lb/> attitude solemn and decorous may be maintained<lb/> in these holy courts&#44; in order that the services become<lb/> notable&#44; through an accord of modulated voices and<lb/> a harmonious chanting which will enhance the<lb/> imposingness of our assemblies.  These I consider<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="14"/>
            <p>most acceptable to our Lord&#44; because conform&#45;<lb/>&#45;able to the command of His inspired Psalmist<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Bless my God in congregations&#59; even the Lord&#44; ye<lb/> that are of the fountain of Israel.&#34;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
