<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF8_10</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1889-05" source="" attested="yes">May 1889</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_10_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_10_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_10_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_10_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_10_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_10_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_10_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_10_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_10_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_10_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_10_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_10_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>69</p>
            
            <p>For Kedoshim on the rescuing of the<lb/>
                Dannmark by Captain Murrel of the Missouri<lb/>
                &#47;89<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Whoever denies Moses originality&#44; and insists that he<lb/> palmed off as Divine what was a mere reproduct&#45;<lb/>&#45;ion of older legislations&#44; ought to read with criti&#45;<lb/>&#45;cal analysis the 19th chapter of Leviticus&#44; whichx<lb/> forms part of the Pentateuchal section of this Sabbath.<lb/>  Let him compare the rules statutes it contains from begin&#45;<lb/>&#45;ning to end&#44; with the record which Herodotus&#45;&#45;the<lb/> reputed father of of history&#45;&#45;has left concerning Egypt.<lb/>  Aside from the account of a senseless and often lasci&#45;<lb/>&#45;vious worship paid to innumerable and ludicrous<lb/> and hideous objects&#44;&#45;&#45;exclaimed against by our inspired<lb/> lawgiver&#44;&#45;&#45;let the critic show what resemblance was<lb/> there between a religion which calls filial dutiful&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness a soul&#45;sanctification&#44; and the one day of physical and mental rest<lb/> holy&#44; and the religion which according to which sons were<lb/> not obliged to support their parents&#44; <del>and</del> the religion which&#44; through a<lb/> fictitious division of casts&#44; whole classes of men were<lb/> doomed to incessant toil.  If the pyramids&#44; which<lb/> Napoleon invoked&#44; that&#44; from their lofty heads&#44; hoary<lb/> with the age of forty centuries&#44; they might tell his sol&#45;<lb/>&#45;diers the daringness they needed to conquer the famous<lb/></p>
            
            <p>x is a sparkling gem of unfading lustre among the moral<lb/> beauties of the Pentateuch.<lb/></p>
            
            <p>x but daughters must support both their father and mother<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>land of antiquity&#44; could have spoken&#44; they would<lb/> have related tales of blood&#45;&#45;the blood which streamed<lb/> from their builders.  The story of the hundreds who<lb/> died in the <sic>quaries</sic>&#44; and of the thousands who perished<lb/> in the transportation of the huge stones from whence<lb/> they arose skyward&#44; would have thrilled the invading French invaders.<lb/>  But the incredulous or skeptical critic should read in Hero&#45;<lb/>&#45;dotus of the irreconcilable antipathies of ancient peoples against<lb/> foreigners&#44; and draw a contrast with what we have re&#45;<lb/>&#45;cited this morning&#58; &#34;As one born in the land among you&#44;<lb/> shall be to you the stranger.&#34;  And then reviewing closely all<lb/> the ordinances regarding honesty of dealing and of<lb/> thought&#44; of charity bestowed upon the needy necessitous as if<lb/> it were their legitimate claim&#44; of respect to age and<lb/> virtue&#44; of compassion to the infirm and the afflicted.<lb/>  In fine&#44; he should let his mind dwell upon that golden<lb/> rule&#44; which is ours&#44; and say whether in the codes of the<lb/> renowned nations of old&#44; he finds&#58; &#34;love thy neighbor as<lb/> thyself&#34;.  And yet&#44; I agree with an ancient writer<lb/> that even this glorious principle&#44; so broad and compre&#45;<lb/>&#45;hensive&#44; has had precedence nad a more emphatic expres&#45;<lb/>&#45;sion in the earliest pages of our Bible.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>To my mind Ben Azza&#239; is has discovered in the Scriptures the brightest example manifestation of hu&#45;<lb/>&#45;man brotherhood.  Many are the valuable maxims enun&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciated by that young Sage&#44; who did prematurely from<lb/> too intense an application to metaphysics&#44; or&#44; to ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;press it in Talmudical langaue&#44; who passed away because he entered the Pardes&#44;<lb/> in search of the unknowable.  But of the many<lb/> aphorisms attributed to Ben Azza&#239;&#44; the following re&#45;<lb/>&#45;veals the whole depth of his religious soul&#44; most<lb/> clearly.  Unfolding the book of Genesis&#44; and pointing<lb/> to the passage&#44; which tells that God&#39;s creation<lb/> of mankind in His own image&#44; comprises male and<lb/> female&#44; whom He equally blessed&#44; the youthful SAge<lb/> regarded that&#44; a teaching of even a superior character above superior even to<lb/> that of the golden rule &#34;love they neighbor as thyself&#34;.<lb/>  He argued that Holy Writ lays down by it thus great grandest<lb/> of principles&#59; that to serve our fellow&#45;creatures is to serve<lb/> their Sovereign Creature whose spiritual celestial impress this immortally bear.  Noble sentiment&#44; enhan&#45;<lb/>&#45;cing in sublimity when we remember that at<lb/> the historical period it was uttered&#44; imperial Rome<lb/> mercilessly crushed the learned in Judea under the<lb/> wheel of refined engines of refined torture.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>National sorrows penetrating piercing the heart&#44; could not never&#45;<lb/>&#45;less obliterate what the finger of God has ineffaceably<lb/> imprinted thereon.  All reasoning beings have a common<lb/> origin&#44; they are the offspring of the pair&#44; male and<lb/> female&#44; upon whom&#44; the Author of every thing that<lb/> exists&#44; bestowed a portion of His undying spirit and His<lb/> benediction.  It is because we have an identical descent<lb/> and intellectual inheritance&#44; that &#34;one touch of nature<lb/> makes the whole world kin.&#34;  We feel that touch<lb/> at the sight of misery&#44; and never pause to <sic>enquire</sic><lb/> who the sufferer is&#44; what is his the place of his birth&#44;<lb/> what language he speaks&#44; what creed he swears by.<lb/>  How magnificent the illustration of this soul&#45;ennobling<lb/> truth&#44; which Philadelphia has just given&#33;  From<lb/> the hour it became known that a ship had been<lb/> lost&#44; in the midst of the sea&#44; universally eager was<lb/> the wish to learn that her passengers and crew had<lb/> survived the wreck.  The painful suspense did<lb/> not abate when days&#44; rolling into weeks&#44; brought<lb/> no tidings of the precious burden carried by the Dan&#45;<lb/>&#45;mark&#44; the floating wreckage of which was seen discovered<lb/> by another vessel on the trackless ocean.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>The sad fate of the President&#44; the Schiller and others vessels that ruled<lb/> and staggered like a drunken man upon stormy waves<lb/> and sunk into the depths&#44; was already feared and la&#45;<lb/>&#45;mented&#59; but how joyful that spontaneous outburst<lb/> of a people&#39;s greeting as the rescuer and his recsu&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing vessel arrived at our shores&#33;  The 365 human<lb/> beings whom the Missouri carried brought alive to this dear<lb/> city of ours&#44; after their soul had very nigh melted be&#45;<lb/>&#45;cause of the danger&#44; and the 369 whom she safely<lb/> landed at Lisbon&#44; were not related to me&#44; nor to you&#44;<lb/> I surmise.  They spoke a language conversed in a manner which possibly<lb/> none of us understand&#59; most probably not a single<lb/> Israelite could be found among their number&#44; yet&#44;<lb/> that &#34;one touch&#34;&#44; of which the peerless interpreter<lb/> of nature in the English tongue&#44; speaks&#44; stirred us<lb/> all and made us &#34;kin&#34; to creatures who share us with us the<lb/> heritage of the spirit of which God He breathed in the pri&#45;<lb/>&#45;meval days of the world into the parents of the human<lb/> family.  Thanks to that touch of nature 734 of<lb/> our brothers and sisters in humanity&#44; were delivered by<lb/> the man&#44; whose name is now a praise and a blessing<lb/> and his deed an exemplar in both the Western and Eastern hemisphere.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>He declares that he is not entitled to an ovations<lb/> and to a rewards for having simply done his duty&#44;<lb/> but to have done it under such tremendous diffi&#45;<lb/>&#45;culties as met faced him&#59; to have done it so tenderly&#44;<lb/> so readily in his care for mainly poor immigrants&#44; valuing<lb/> as nothing the tens of thousands of property&#44; in com&#45;<lb/>&#45;parison with the life of the humblest among those he<lb/> snatched from death&#59; to have done it regardless of<lb/> the risk of having to face stand reproof for the distinction<lb/> of a rich cargo&#44; and perhaps of losing his position&#44; is<lb/> indeed a just claim to popular acclamation and<lb/> gratitude.  And I confess that I read with un&#45;<lb/>&#45;feigned satisfaction of the gift of a gold watch<lb/> studded with the a diamond&#44; set in it by a Philadelphia Hebrew.<lb/>  To the brave captain&#44; Hamilton Murrel of the Missouri&#44;<lb/> that time&#45;piece will be a memorial of that which what<lb/> we delight in.  The book which Jews have treasured<lb/> up as an inalienable heirloom&#44; first taught the bro&#45;<lb/>&#45;therhood of man&#44; and the descendants of Abraham&#44; the<lb/> friend of God&#44; loyal to that principle&#44; have been recog&#45;<lb/>&#45;nized as eminently humane &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;merciful children of merciful parents.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>But while I am glad rejoice that our city and one of our<lb/> people gave luminous proofs of harboring the sen&#45;<lb/>&#45;timent inculcated by Ben Azza&#239;&#44; and exquisitely ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;pressed by Shakespeare&#44; I am glad that hte reci&#45;<lb/>&#45;pient of encomiums and of presents in America is an<lb/> Englishman.  The incident which does so much credit<lb/> to him and to us&#44; may be the olive branch indicative<lb/> of the complete allaying of waters in Meribah&#44; which swelled up<lb/> not long ago through an episode reflecting honor upon<lb/> neither side of the Atlantic.  The Sackville&#45;Murchi&#45;<lb/>&#45;son affair revealed a laxity of morals&#44; and a breach of<lb/> propriety highly reprehensible.  Incident is the maxim<lb/> that all is allowed in politics&#44; as it is very foul when<lb/> applied in the transaction of business.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Righteousness&#44; only righteousness shalt thou follow&#59;&#34; we<lb/> have read to&#45;day.  He who entrapped an indiscreet re&#45;<lb/>&#45;presentative of a foreign government by subterfuge&#44;<lb/> and then made him odious by divulging what was<lb/> intended as private correspondence&#44; is contemptible in<lb/> the extreme&#44; but the prime minister who&#44; led by na&#45;<lb/>&#45;tional dislike&#44; jeopardized the state of amity between two<lb/> great powers&#44; might have occasioned severe injury.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>That is what might have been the issue of Salis&#45;<lb/>&#45;bury&#39;s favoring or conniving at an indefensible intru&#45;<lb/>&#45;sion in upon the internal division of political parties in<lb/> the United States.  That mischief was averted&#44; we may<lb/> attribute to the our change of administration soon following<lb/> the complicated plot&#44; still&#44; should any remains of<lb/> the grudge exist in the minds of those over the other<lb/> side of the ocean&#44; who have with us Americans unity of language<lb/> and of literature&#59; the public acknowledgment and subst&#45;<lb/>&#45;antial recognition of the hero of humanity&#44; will remove<lb/> all disturbing elements.  Perchance&#44; it was that thought<lb/> which induced Captain Murrel to emphasize the phrase&#44;<lb/> that he did what any Englishman would have done<lb/> under the same circumstance.  For there is no desire<lb/> among true patriots &#34;to twist the tail of the British<lb/> lion&#44;&#34; as recently thrown out by the unscrupulous.  To<lb/> grow stronger&#44; and more respected by pursuing the way of<lb/> equity must be the endeavour and prayer of the Republic<lb/> of Washington.  With Isaiah I ask for peace&#44; peace<lb/> to those that are far and those that are near &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
