<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF2_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_2_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>An exegetical lecture<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Dear Brethren&#33;  Wherever civilization has spread its benign<lb/> influence&#44; men acknowledge that the ten divine commands<lb/> we have rehearsed this morning&#44; are the basis and pillars<lb/> of the social edifice.  That fact would lead to suppose<lb/> that their authenticity is likewise unexceptionably admitted&#44;<lb/> but the annals of time&#44; and those of our own especially&#44;<lb/> prove that criticism has not spared even the most<lb/> important and most authoritative of all documents.<lb/>  From the first hour that adverse circumstances brought<lb/> the inhabitants of Judea into closer contact with the gentile<lb/> world&#44; the attention of the learned among the conquerors&#44; was<lb/> drawn to the code which governed the conquered.  Thus we<lb/> read that weighty questions upon touching the promulgation<lb/> of from Sinai&#59; were often propounded to our Sages by the Rulers<lb/> of ancient Rome and her philosophers.  And as the<lb/> principles imbibed by the latter were antagonistical<lb/> to those professed  by our ancestors&#44; <sic>contraversies</sic> ensued<lb/> which evince a spirit of acrimony on one side&#44; and<lb/> acute reasoning upon the other.  But that which<lb/> could not justly be condemned&#44; because the effect of<lb/> a prevailing belief in false deities&#44; ought scarcely to<lb/> find justification when met with among communities<lb/> that have repudiated paganism&#44; and embraced a purer<lb/></p> 
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>creed.  Yet they who analyze the Scriptures in search<lb/> of defects are not alone countenanced in our enlightened<lb/> days&#44; but followed and consulted by multitudes.  Many<lb/> a youth&#44; who has applied his mind to every study&#44; but<lb/> to that of the sacred volumes&#44; will grow skeptical<lb/> and irreverent&#44; because he is shown therein passages&#44; which&#44;<lb/> to his over rated judgment&#44; appear contradictory.<lb/></p>
            <p>And how could it be otherwise&#44; my beloved friends&#63; when<lb/> the faith entertained by the civilized world&#44; the testimony<lb/> of historical facts universally admitted credited deter not the neologists of this<lb/> century to seize upon the very essence of revealed religion&#44;<lb/> and boldly impugn it.  Yes&#44; to convince us that the<lb/> decalogue lacks internal evidences of its divine origin&#44;<lb/> they institute a comparison between that which is recorded<lb/> as having been proclaimed by the Deity after the exodus&#44;<lb/> and its repetition by Moses at the expiration of forty<lb/> years&#39; vagrancy in the wilderness.  The slight discrepancy<lb/> which that holy document exhibits&#44; invalidates&#44; in their<lb/> prejudiced minds&#44; its accepted genuineness.  I deem it<lb/> superfluous to recall to your memory all the variations<lb/> contained in that important passage&#44; upon which the<lb/> critics dwell to sustain their position.  A glance<lb/> thereat will reveal&#44; here&#44; the omission of a conjunctive<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Vav&#44; there&#44; the addition of one&#44; as in one place the introduction<lb/> of a new phrase&#44; in another&#44; the substitution of a new <sic>synonimous</sic><lb/> word term.  And although I firmly believe that those changes<lb/> are not accidental&#59; notwithstanding I could quote the<lb/> writings of a profound Hebrew scholar&#44; who explains<lb/> all of them in a masterly manner&#44; I will not launch<lb/> into a lengthy disquisition&#44; lest I weary your attention<lb/> before I have concluded.  But as among all the varia&#45;<lb/>&#45;tions exposed to view those which occur in the fourth commandment&#44;<lb/> are the principal and the most numerous&#44; I will<lb/> content myself with elucidating their purport&#44; and it will<lb/> serve as a criterion to judge judge thereby of the others that<lb/> are of less moment.  In the section of this day&#44; it is written<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; in the fifth chapter of Deuteronomy&#44; we read<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  My Brethren&#33;  It<lb/> was the divine voice which spoke through Moses&#44; that dictated<lb/> the difference of phraseology because needful to times and circumstances.<lb/>  While the sense of the behest remained perfectly identical<lb/> in every respect&#44; its altered diction applied more directly to<lb/> the men&#44; whose existence was about to assume an entirely<lb/> new phrase aspect.  To those who had already been solemnly<lb/> charged at Sin with the observance of the Sabbath&#44;<lb/> the simple instruction&#44; to remember the day&#44; the sanctity<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>of which their supernatural nutriment weekly testified&#44;<lb/> was deemed sufficient&#59; but to a generation who had not<lb/> received immediately the same celestial imparting&#44; and<lb/> who moreover were soon2 destined1 to procure their suste&#45;<lb/>&#45;nance by their own labor&#44; it was necessary to enjoin<lb/> their keeping with much heed&#44; a command of God&#44;<lb/> which might clash with their future interests.  And such<lb/> was the design of the inspired legislator.  By sub&#45;<lb/>&#45;stituting the word &#91;Hebrew&#93; for &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; and by adding &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; &#34;as the Lord thy God hath commanded thee&#34; he bid the<lb/> children of the enfranchised boundmen of Egypt to allow<lb/> no human consideration to withhold their obedience from<lb/> the dictates of the Almighty.  Hitherto no obstacle<lb/> had arisen to prevent their devoting the seventh day<lb/> to the Author of their lives.  It was but a <sic>wilful</sic> impiety<lb/> that could incite them&#44; while dwelling in deserts&#44; to quit<lb/> their tents on the Sabbath&#44; and follow their pleasure&#44;<lb/> but now they would enter an inhabited country.<lb/>  There&#44; would they be engaged in building houses&#59; in plant&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing vineyards&#44; and be frequently lured to transgress by the<lb/> prospect of material advantage.  Therefore said the mes&#45;<lb/>&#45;senger of the Most High&#58; believe not that the execution<lb/> of this precept was intended solely for them&#44; whose<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>wants were extraordinarily supplied but also for those<lb/> who shall would use the harrow and wield the scythe.  And<lb/> in order to bring more vividly before the mind of his hearers&#44;<lb/> the truth of his tacit assertion&#44; he specified two animals&#44;<lb/> which are not named in the same verse of our section&#44; as entitled to rest like<lb/> with their master owners&#44; namely&#44; the ox and the ass &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> so essential heretofore in the pursuit of agriculture.<lb/>  But he to whom the Eternal communicated his will&#44;<lb/> foresaw that a change of habits in his nation would<lb/> create new necessities&#44; and that a desire to gratify<lb/> them&#44; might weaken the humane feelings which the<lb/> Scriptures had striven to inculcate.  He feared that<lb/> a Hebrew&#44; whose possessions had vastly increased&#44; might<lb/> argue&#44; that inasmuch as the gentiles had been excluded<lb/> from the law&#44; it would not be sinful to subject them<lb/> to unlimited labor&#59; he feared that by some process of fallacious<lb/> reasoning he the same Hebrew would persuade himself that the work<lb/> which was not to be imposed on them the bond&#45;men&#44; could only be<lb/> such as might be exacted demanded by nomadic tribes&#44; but that<lb/> when fields required tending&#44; when the harvest was<lb/> to be reaped&#44; and lives to be pressed&#44; their services<lb/> might be exacted at any period.  To prevent a wrong con&#45;<lb/>clusion so dictated by selfishness&#44; Moses appositely added<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>&#34;So that thy man&#45;servant and thy maid&#45;servant may<lb/> rest like thyself.&#34;  In like manner as thou&#44; who art<lb/> a recipient of the law must forego on the Sabbath all<lb/> thy customary vocations&#44; so must thy dependents be exempted<lb/> on that day from any species of labor.  Thou shalt not<lb/> sit at ease&#44; and suffer thy fellow&#45;mortal&#44; whom chance<lb/> has bound subjected to thy service&#44; to toil without intermission.<lb/>  Thou shalt not seek diversion for thy mind&#44; and<lb/> deny him the privilege of even recruiting the strength of<lb/> his wearied body.  Remember that thou also wast<lb/> a bondman in the land of Egypt&#44; and that the Supreme<lb/> Ruler of the Universe who abhors oppression&#44; beheld thy<lb/> affliction&#44; because of the hard thraldom&#44; and purchased thy<lb/> ransom by mighty and <sic>marvellous</sic> deeds.  Let then<lb/> the Sabbath&#45;&#45;which was instituted to commemorate<lb/> thy freedom from servile work&#45;&#45;&#44; soften thy heart<lb/> towards all beings&#44; that thou mayest exercise the com&#45;<lb/>&#45;passion which was greatly shown thee.<lb/></p>
                <p>
                    Now&#44; my dear Brethren&#33; my elucidation will explain<lb/> why in the repetition of the Decalogue&#44; to which my<lb/> remarks have mainly been confined&#44; the cause assigned<lb/> for the celebration of the seventh day differs from that<lb/> chronicled in the lesson of this morning.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>When God vouchsafed to appear at Sinai&#44; the recollection<lb/> of their hardships was still vivid in the mind of Israel.<lb/>  Scarcely any time had elapsed since their task&#45;masters<lb/> ruthlessly plied the lash&#44; so that the breasts Sabbath which pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;claimed general rest&#44; must needs have then awakened in the<lb/> breasts of our ancestors feelings of gratitude to their heavenly<lb/> Redeemer&#44; and of kindliness towards all his creatures&#59;<lb/> hence on that memorable occasion&#44; the motive for<lb/> the separation sanctification of that day from above all others was given &#216;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;For in six days the Lord made the heavens and the earth&#44;<lb/> therefore the Lord blessed the Sabbath&#45;day and hallowed it&#34;<lb/> &#216; while the reason significative of the liberation from the fetters<lb/> of Mizraim&#44; was withheld&#44; because unnecessary &#43; But a<lb/> period of forty years had effaced somewhat the memory of Egyptian<lb/> servitude&#44; and they who would shortly possess a land<lb/> flowing with milk and honey&#44;&#45;&#45;growing oblivious of their<lb/> former suffering&#45;&#45;might not attach the same importance<lb/> to the Sabbath&#44; as in the primordial stage of their national<lb/> existence&#44; consequently the arch&#45;prophet in his allusion<lb/> to the ten commandments&#44; attributed the institution<lb/> of the Sabbath to an historical event&#44; fraught with<lb/> the deepest meaning to the descendants of the patriarchs.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Thou shalt remember that thou was a servant in the<lb/> land of Egypt&#44; wherefore hath the Lord thy God commanded thee<lb/> to keep the Sabbath&#45;day.&#34;  It was not&#44; my friends&#33; as the<lb/> hyper&#45;critics represent it&#44; the fabrication of a novel motive&#44;<lb/> which betrays the spuriousness of the document&#44; but one<lb/> real and true&#44; like that which was uttered by the Omnipotent<lb/> on the summit of Horeb.  The reason registered in the book<lb/> of Exodus seems to conveys the idea&#44; that the Hebrews who<lb/> were selected as a kingdom of priests&#44; should elevate their<lb/> thoughts by contemplating the creative power of the Supre Eternal&#44;<lb/> and that the fittest time for their musing thereon&#44; is that<lb/> when the whole world issued forth perfect from the hand<lb/> of its Author.  The other&#44; recorded in Deuteronomy&#44; purposes<lb/> to fasten an impression&#44; upon the durability of which<lb/> depend Israel&#39;s love for devotion to God&#44; their affection love for Man&#44;<lb/> and the final consummation of their divine charge.<lb/>  For&#44; when we constantly reflect that the Father of the whole<lb/> human race stretched forth his arm to deliver a small number<lb/> of his oppressed children&#44; that to secure for them liberty of<lb/> action&#44; he invented the laws of nature&#44; that to improve<lb/> their morals&#44; he deigned to communicate his will unto<lb/> them&#44; the instruction with which the event is fraught<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>will not be lost upon us.  We&#44; that have been so divinely favored&#44;<lb/> will not only dedicate to our Almighty Saviour a portion of our<lb/> time&#44; but cheerfully let allow those whose endeavours promote our<lb/> advantage to enjoy a weekly repose&#44; that they may&#44; like us&#44;<lb/> restore their physical and invigorate their spiritual powers.<lb/>  Such a demeanour will best demonstrate that the law which<lb/> governs the Hebrews&#44; is a wise and humane law&#44; and the<lb/> heart of the gentiles shall open to the convictions of the eternal<lb/> truths it has proclaimed.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> It is then evident&#44; my beloved hearers&#33; that the allegation of<lb/> the captious cannot be sustained&#44; for what they style a contradict&#45;<lb/>&#45;ion in the fourth commandment&#44; reveals in a stronger light&#44;<lb/> to him that ponders thereon&#44; the goodness of our celestial Legislator&#44;<lb/> who sought to benefit all men by the enactments of Sinai.<lb/>  Be then exceedingly wary how you lend your ear to the arguing<lb/> of subtle critics&#44; who discover errors in the word of God.  Let<lb/> rather the knowledge you have acquired of its wisdom&#44; be a stand&#45;<lb/>&#45;ard by which you will judge of that which is not obvious to<lb/> your understanding&#44; for verily I tell you&#44; that like with respect to the<lb/> repetition of the Decalogue&#44; of which the variations will be found<lb/> to contain a weighty significance&#44; so will other apparent incon&#45;<lb/>gruities in the holy volumes&#44; disclose to you a treasure a valuable<lb/> learning&#44; which will profit you here and hereafter &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>&#34;Meditate incessantly thereon&#44; for it is all perfect&#34;  And may the Almighty grant<lb/> that my simple illustrations may heighten in your estimation the transcendent worth<lb/> of the book which is Israel&#39;s inheritance to the end of time.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
