<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF10</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_28v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_28r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_27v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_27r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_26v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_26r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_25v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_25r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_24v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_24r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_23v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_23r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_22v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_22r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_21v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_21r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_20v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_20r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_19v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_19r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_18v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_18r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_17v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_17r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_16v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_16r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_15v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_15r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_14v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_14r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_13v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_13r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_12v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_12r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_11v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_11r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_10v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_10r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_9v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_9r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_8v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff10_1_2r.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>26 pages on 26 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Moses&#44; Ezekiel&#44; &#38; Rabbenu Tam<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Ladies and Gentlemen.  My lecture will not be<lb/> consecutive&#44; but miscellaneous.  Perhaps it will prove<lb/> less fatiguing of a strain to the listeners&#44; and much easier to the<lb/> speaker.  I confess that were I to follow the whole<lb/> bent of my mind&#44; I would let my talk this evening<lb/> be altogether a sequel to another talk which I gave two win&#45;<lb/>&#45;ters ago.  I hold that the venerable books entrusted<lb/> to our safe&#45;keeping&#44; and the principally the Pentateuch&#44;<lb/> ought closely to engage the attention of a &#34;Young Men&#39;s<lb/> Hebrew Association.&#34;  Surely&#44; I do not offend by saying<lb/> that an indescribable perplexing bewildering confusion of ideas exists among Jews<lb/> in general&#44; about touching a subject which&#44; above all others&#44; should<lb/> be perfectly clear to the understanding.  The<lb/> notions entertained concerning the writings which<lb/> Christians have variously called by way of eminence<lb/> the &#34;Bible&#44;&#34; the &#34;Scriptures&#34; and &#34;Holy Writ&#44;&#34; and which<lb/> among our people Rabbis go under the generic name of<lb/> &#34;Mikr&#225;&#34; or reading par excellence&#44; are most<lb/> extravagant.  With some they are so through<lb/> an inconsiderate pietism with others by reason<lb/> of inveterate deep rooted misapprehensions.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Ask one and you will be told that the five books<lb/> of the Law&#44; the eight of the Prophets&#44; and the eleven<lb/> of the Hagiographa&#44; as the Mikra was singularly<lb/> divided by the Talmudists&#44; claim with equal right<lb/> the title of &#34;God&#39;s word&#34;.  Inquire of another&#44; and<lb/> you will hear that nothing in those twenty four<lb/> volumes&#45;&#45;the famous Arbang&#225; Vengesrim &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#45;&#45;was given<lb/> by superhuman agency.  A radical fault in<lb/> both&#59; but the fault did not originate with us&#44; Israel&#45;<lb/>ites.  It is largely due to surroundings&#44; which will un&#45;<lb/>&#45;avoidably affect even the most thoughtful independent thinkers.<lb/>  I can recall an informal meeting which I attended&#44; by<lb/> special request&#44; at the house of a clergyman not of<lb/> our faith.  That minister contended that the Bible<lb/> is a book whose authorship must wholly be ascribed to<lb/> a Supreme Power&#44; that which dictated it verbally.  The<lb/> good Christian appealed to me for a confirmation of<lb/> his position&#44; and he seemed greatly disconcerted<lb/> at my dissenting.  I argued however that my reason<lb/> and the knowledge I possess of the views entertained<lb/> by the Sages of my people&#44; forbid my acceptance<lb/> of the doctrine inculcated by the Nazarene Church.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>My reason could see nothing heavenly in the mere<lb/> narrative of events&#44; some of which are obviously of a revolting<lb/> character&#44; as the dethroning of kings by atrocious<lb/> means&#44; or the bloody schemes of crowned rulers against<lb/> their subjects.  Again&#58; my knowledge showed me<lb/> that the sentiments underlying the teachings of the Bible teachings disclose a<lb/> celestial inspiration to a degree incalculably vast&#44;<lb/> but that the language in which those sentiments<lb/> were couched&#44; proceeded from the author&#39;s impassioned<lb/> eloquence&#44; or from his moderate fluency of speech.<lb/>&#45;&#45;a verity imparted by the Rabbis who assert that<lb/> our prophets differed optionally in their phraseology&#44;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  In contrast<lb/> with the credulousness of my clerical friend in<lb/> Philadelphia&#44; are the utterances of a prominent mi&#45;<lb/>&#45;nister of the Anglican Church in New York.  He<lb/> lately scandalized all believers&#44; by placing the<lb/> Bible on parallel ground with works of human genius&#44;<lb/> and by delivering to each of us a pair of censor&#39;s shears<lb/> to cut away unsparingly whatever does not<lb/> rise up to the modern standard of social propriety.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>What is then the Orthodox&#45;&#45;I use the word in its<lb/> primitive sense&#44; namely the of right opinion&#45;&#45;what<lb/> is the orthodox belief in the premises&#63;  I answer&#59;<lb/> the Torah is an emanation divine.  Let me be<lb/> very explicit.  The legislative code of the five<lb/> books must be accepted as an oral imparting of<lb/> a Supreme Power.  I shall not attempt to ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;plain that spiritual phenomenon&#44; any more than<lb/> I would undertake to make clear to your under&#45;<lb/>&#45;standing the invisible force power within my mind by which I am enabled<lb/> now to shape my thoughts into intelligible words.<lb/>  Suffice to me that to me a denial of that doctrine is<lb/> heterodoxy&#44; because it nullifies the obligatoriness<lb/> of the commandments.  If Moses did not tran&#45;<lb/>&#45;smit the message with faithful precision&#44; his<lb/> delegation&#44; however healthful in its tendency&#44; cannot<lb/> possess a binding force.  The moral tenets and<lb/> those which regulate civilized society in marital relations&#44; not less than<lb/> ceremonial precepts lose their validity.  Experience<lb/> may have proved them valuable&#44; still&#44; they are simply<lb/> the offspring of a human intellect&#44; hence ine&#45;<lb/>&#45;vitably fallible and exposed to mutations in all their bearings.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>But the messenger repeatedly assured us gave us his assurance that<lb/> the rules he enjoined issued from the mind of an<lb/> all&#45;comprehending Being and that therefore obedience<lb/> thereto constituted the wisdom of would signally distinguish for their intelligence the people for whom on whose behalf<lb/> those behests were committed to writing &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> But what a mass of confusion surrounds that subject<lb/> of primary importance&#33;  How few they are who have<lb/> learned to distinguish that which is stamped with the<lb/> seal of the Divinity in the wonderful volumes of the<lb/> Scriptures&#44; from that which is man&#39;s profound meditation<lb/> has produced&#59; the sublime outpourings of hearts panting<lb/> after a kingdom of righteousness from mere historical<lb/> records&#33;  That this ignorance is fruitful of<lb/> mischief&#44; needs not be demonstrated.  However Yet&#44; I judge&#44;<lb/> however that an association as that which I<lb/> now address&#44; ought to endeavour to rise like a pillar of fire<lb/> illumining the way out of a wilderness<lb/> of erroneous notions.  It cannot be<lb/> gainsaid.  A spirit of discontent is manifested<lb/> among our Hebrew young men.  Not all are worldly<lb/> and irreverent&#44; as some of their elders appear to think.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Many wish to winnow the chaff from the<lb/> grain&#59; to separate the irrational ideas of gentilism from the<lb/> sensible teachings of Judaism.  They ask for<lb/> help and it should be heartily given&#44; lest their<lb/> intellects be warped by influences potent in<lb/> accomplishing evil.  For it is not flippant suf&#45;<lb/>&#45;fers and babbling <sic>cavillers</sic> that now breed disbelief.<lb/>  Those whose literary efforts in our days tend need to undermine Mosaism&#44; bring<lb/> to bear on their undertakings a skill which is<lb/> thorough.  They are masters of the subjects which<lb/> they place into the crucible of a relentless criticism&#44;<lb/> and they challenge respect for the depth and richness<lb/> of erudition that their works reveal.  Since<lb/> the time that the Westminster Review and Bishop<lb/> Colenso called the authenticity of the Scriptures into<lb/> question&#44; the danger incurred by our rising gene&#45;<lb/>&#45;ration has increased tenfold.  Thus&#44; to an English<lb/> speaking people&#44; a scholar and stylist like<lb/> Professor William Robertson Smith is a greater danger than<lb/> a thousand Thomas Paines.  But to forcible<lb/> arguments and an incisive diction&#44; a stronger array of<lb/> counter reasons should be invoked and set over against the deniers<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>of Pentateuchal authenticity.<lb/></p>
            <p>Had I resolved to request your attention this evening to<lb/> a single topic&#44; I would open in your presence the<lb/> five books of the Torah&#44; and compel internal evidences<lb/> to testify that the son of Amram is their inspired<lb/> author.  Historically&#44; I would show that<lb/> only one born and bred in Egypt could have so accurately<lb/> portrayed the manners and practices of her in&#45;<lb/>&#45;habitants&#44; as traced throughout Genesis and Exodus.<lb/>  Linguistically&#44; I could might cite Coptic words&#44; disclosing<lb/> a familiarity with terms used in the land of the<lb/> Pharaohs and adopted in the early portions of the Scriptures such as Yeor<lb/> for the Nile&#44; Shesh for fine linea&#44; Anoschi&#44; for<lb/> the personal pronoun I&#59; even the name of Phineas<lb/> from <sic>Phenix</sic>&#45;&#45;the famous bird that rises from its own ashes&#44; and that and of the great lawgiver himself Moses&#44;<lb/> which by the testimony of Philo Judea&#44; is derived<lb/> from Mus water&#59; in the Coptic tongue.  I could<lb/> also demonstrate that the minute description of<lb/> the Sinaic Tabernacle and a variety of ordinances connected<lb/> with it and with the journeys of the tribes&#44; would be<lb/> sheer absurdity after the conquest of Palestine&#44; and the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>building of Solomon&#39;s Temple.  I could force com&#45;<lb/>&#45;mon sense to acknowledge that the large space<lb/> devoted to the sacrificial ritual in three of the five<lb/> books&#44; would not have been given&#44; after our Seers<lb/> and psalmists uttered withering rebukes against a<lb/> multiplicity of burnt&#45;offerings&#44; supplanting the laws<lb/> of morality.  I could show that the parting<lb/> benediction which closes the Pentateuch&#45;&#45;that magni&#45;<lb/>&#45;ficent outburst of fervent love for all the tribes&#44; and chiefly that for the descendants<lb/> of Joseph&#44; would read like a ludicrous anomaly<lb/> after Jeroboam of the tribe of Ephraim had led<lb/> the schism which broke up our nation into<lb/> two hostile camps.  I should necessarily detain<lb/> you long&#44; but I would summon before your presence<lb/> annalists and prophets&#59; writers anterior to the Babylonian<lb/> exile and authors posterior to that event&#44; and they<lb/> all in one accord of voices would declare that the five<lb/> venerable volumes barring a few sentences&#44; proceeded from him whose name appellation<lb/> they bear.  In the small Bible which I hold<lb/> in my hand&#44; I have marked out for my instruction and<lb/> satisfaction every passage wherein expressions are inter&#45;<lb/>&#45;spersed through the nineteen books constituting the rest of<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>the Mikr&#225;&#44; &#38; which evince reveal in their form&#44; in their<lb/> language&#44; in their meaning&#44; the prior existence of the Penta&#45;<lb/>&#45;teuch&#44; as handed transmitted from high antiquity by<lb/> the faithful servant of his <sic>soul&#45;commaning</sic> Master.<lb/>  And when to an analysis of those expressions&#44; I should<lb/> add a demonstration of the gradual development of<lb/> the Monotheistic idea as disclosed in the phraseology<lb/> of the various writings of the Scriptures&#44; the conviction<lb/> would force itself into your minds that the Hebrews<lb/> whom Hez Ezra and Nehemiah exhorted&#44; were widely<lb/> different in their sentiments from those whom the<lb/> author of the Pentateuch addressed.  You would then<lb/> acknowledge clearly perceive that to date the Torah from the days<lb/> of the Chaldean captivity is an impossibility&#44; rebutted<lb/> by tangible facts&#44; antagonized <sic>combatted</sic> against by the laws of<lb/> causes and their effects&#44; declared proved false and heretical<lb/> beyond peradventure by our own criterion&#44; not less than by religion.<lb/>  But you would probably feel that my action imposes too<lb/> great a strain on your attention.  I therefore forbear&#44; and<lb/> beg have to direct your thoughts to another channel&#44; though it runs<lb/> through the same field which I fain would offer for your<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>special cultivation.<lb/></p>
            <p>Those of my hearers who have visited London&#44; must<lb/> have noticed two figures of a colossal dimension.  They<lb/> are seen at Guildhall&#45;famous as the spot for installing<lb/> municipal high officials&#44; and for the sumptuous civic<lb/> feasts given in it.  The extraordinarily large<lb/> sized statues&#44; claim a history which dates as far back<lb/> as three thousand years&#59; but the hoary age of which<lb/> they boast has spread over them a misty veil&#45;&#45;so<lb/> thick did rolling centuries render it&#44; that the skill<lb/> of the ablest are artificer would be baffled in trying<lb/> to fling that cover aside.  Nor would a successful<lb/> effort prove of any advantage to us.  Narratives<lb/> respecting fighting giants&#44; two of whom are ima&#45;<lb/>&#45;gined to have been captured alive and chained as<lb/> trophies by the inhabitants of Albion&#44; can have<lb/> no special interest to Jews.  Still&#44; there is a<lb/> something about the two colossal figures&#44; which must<lb/> excite the attention of a people&#44; that has taken<lb/> into its guardianship the holy books.  The<lb/> names which the statutes bear are notably attractive.<lb/>  I could not discover why they were christened by the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>old Britons&#44; Gog and Magog.  I must<lb/> believe that a thrilling vision of Ezekiel worked upon<lb/> the susceptible minds of the ancients&#44; and allowed<lb/> wide scope to the exaggerations of a heated fancy.<lb/></p>
            <p>Already in Mishnic times Gog and Magog received<lb/> a dishonored mention &#91;Hebrew&#93;; and in legends scattered throughout<lb/> Rabbinical writings&#44; those two were likewise pictured in hideous colors.<lb/>  Their prospective looks are said to have appalled prophets and<lb/> psalmists&#44; as the impersonation of what is sorely<lb/> trying to human endurance.  My hearers may<lb/> perhaps remember also that volumes held sacred by<lb/> Christians&#44; connect Gog and Magog with stirring events&#44;<lb/> supposed to happen before a last resurrection&#44; and<lb/> Mohammedans too in the Koran have their myths&#44;<lb/> concerning the same mystical objects&#44; under the<lb/> names of Jadjondi and Madjondi.<lb/></p>
            <p>When we turn to the Hebrew Scriptures for some<lb/> accurate information&#44; we find that in the famous<lb/> truth Chapter of Genesis Magog was reckoned<lb/> as the second son of Japheth&#44; but Gog has no<lb/> record in the genealogical table therein presented.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p>Ezekiel is the only authority for the use<lb/> of that name&#44; jointly with Magog.  In two<lb/> chapters which follow each other immediately&#44;<lb/> the prophet describes pictures a mighty nation&#44; whose<lb/> sceptre is <sic>weilded</sic> over a vast quantity of peoples.<lb/>  She arms them to fight aggressive wars&#44; and they<lb/> move swiftly on from a land in the extreme north.<lb/>  With the violence of a storm they seek to uproot<lb/> all as they proceed&#44; and leave in their train devasta&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion.  Those two descriptive chapters in Ezekiel are&#44; in my<lb/> humble opinion&#44; a sequel to the preceding.  In this&#44; latter<lb/> the inspired bard towers high on the wings of prophetic<lb/> genius.  He beholds Israel rise from abjection<lb/> and misery to elevation honor and happiness.  The dried<lb/> bones and withered flesh of the outcasts are reshapen<lb/> into sentient beings&#44; endowed with a spirit vigorous<lb/> and <sic>joyoyful</sic>.  Setting the wheel of time into rapid<lb/> motion&#44; Ezekiel beholds the end of his people&#39;s<lb/> suffering&#59; a complete fusion of all clashing ele&#45;<lb/>&#45;ments in Judaism&#44; and a reign of peace and pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;gress in a country of temporal prosperity.<lb/></p>
            <p>But the bright vision of Israel&#39;s restoration to liberty<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="14"/>
            <p>vanishes momentarily from the prophetic view&#44; to<lb/> give room to another thrillingly fearful.  Israel<lb/> is not allowed to abide undisturbed and to recuperate after<lb/> long centuries of soul&#45;deadening oppression.  A clo<lb/> colossal power&#44; grown terrifically strong by having<lb/> subjugated many and diverse nationalities&#44; stretches<lb/> its envious looks from a far reaching land in the<lb/> extreme North&#44; where its dominions lie&#44; to the narrow<lb/> strip of land in Western Asia.  That ferocious<lb/> power will not suffer Judea to store away the<lb/> wealth which may flow into her lap from the<lb/> Mediterranean sea and the Suez canal.  It will<lb/> gather an army composed of numerous peoples&#44; and<lb/> invade a country repopulated by a nation&#44;<lb/> that wishes to develop her resources in tran&#45;<lb/>&#45;quillity.  To bedeck itself with the richest<lb/> plunder&#44; it will plan extermination&#44; the wading<lb/> through rivers of human blood.  We read thus&#58; &#40;Ezek 38&#41;<lb/> &#34;In the latter years thou wilt come unto the land recovering<lb/> from the sword&#44; and which is gathered together out of<lb/> many peoples&#44; even against the mountains of Israel&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="15"/>
            <p>that have been continually destroyed........<lb/> Thou wilt come like a tempest&#44; like a cloud that<lb/> covers the whole earth&#44; thou and all thy armies<lb/> and the many peoples with thee....to match up<lb/> the spoil and to take away the prey.&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>I think that if Ezekiel had described portrayed only that<lb/> characteristic of the colossal power he saw march<lb/> on from the North&#44; we must have recognized it.<lb/>  For who has Slaves and Poles&#44; and Tartars and Cossacks<lb/> and Mongols and Turks and Germans and Fins to<lb/> fight her unrighteous battles&#63;  Who has such count&#45;<lb/>&#45;less diversity of nationalities and languages and<lb/> races&#44; forming the ninety millions of her luckless subjects&#63;<lb/>  And who has kept a covetous eye on the high<lb/> road to Syria&#44; since the days of her fiercest iron&#45;willed au&#45;<lb/>&#45;tocrat&#63;  And who would rejoice to tear Israel out<lb/> of existence&#63;  Who but Russia the perfidious&#44; that<lb/> has again and again raised the hopes of the free&#45;<lb/>&#45;dom loving&#44; and again and again in lieu of loosening<lb/> the bonds has tightened a galling yoke&#63;&#45;&#45;Russia<lb/> the pitiless that sends her own children to be blasted<lb/> by the deadly breath of Siberia.  Russia the mistress<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="16"/>
            <p>of the Greek Church&#44; holding the knout<lb/> over men and women who dare turn their backs upon<lb/> the creeds that she prescribes.  She stood before<lb/> the illumined vision of the Seer who prophesied<lb/> on the shores of Chebar&#44; and he called her by<lb/> name and predicted her final doom.  &#34;So says the<lb/> Lord God&#58; Behold I am against thee O Gog&#44; prince<lb/> of Rosh&#44; Meschech and Tubal.....Upon the mount&#45;<lb/>&#45;ains of Israel thou shalt fall&#44; even thou and all<lb/> thy armies and the peoples that are with thee.&#34;  &#40;Ez. 39.&#41;<lb/>  You cannot help&#44; to have noticed the close if affi&#45;<lb/>&#45;nity of sound.  Gog is the chief&#44; or Sovereign ruler<lb/> of Rosh.  Without any stretch of the imagination&#44;<lb/> or any straining of the text&#44; it will be obviously<lb/> perceived that by Rosh&#44; Russia is meant.  But<lb/> the prophet wishes to be explicit&#44; and he points<lb/> out a section and a leading city in Russia&#45;&#45;<lb/> Meshech&#44; Moscow&#44; the seat of a provincial<lb/> government of that name and a city of primary<lb/> importance&#59; a former capital of a world wide<lb/> renown&#44; and still famous for its vast area and<lb/> population&#59; for its fortified walls and lofty towers&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="17"/>
            <p>for its extensive manufacturing and commercial<lb/> industry.  Tubal is as country annexed to Rus&#45;<lb/>&#45;sia&#44; anciently known as Tibarene&#44; but now as<lb/> Georgia or Transcaucasia.  Observe it well.<lb/>  Ezekiel uses unequivocal language.  Magog of<lb/> the 10th chapter of Genesis gave the name<lb/> of to the country over which Gog has dominion&#44;<lb/> just as Javan mentioned in the same chapter&#44; gave<lb/> his name to the Ionian islands&#44; or Greece&#44; and Mada&#239;<lb/> to Media.  But Magog the country&#44; as Ezekiel<lb/> styles it &#34;Eretz ha&#45;Magog&#34; is not to be confounded<lb/> with Gog the king.  I have read that the<lb/> term Magog for some portions of Russia is<lb/> still retained among tribes under her sway&#44; but<lb/> the correctness of that statement I am unable<lb/> to ascertain.  Yet&#44; there is one point&#44; on which<lb/> I venture an opinion&#44; though&#44; as it lacking the sup&#45;<lb/>&#45;port for our authorities&#44; it may be controverted.<lb/>  I hold that Ezekiel designedly applied to the<lb/> Czars the generic name of Gog.  First&#44; because the<lb/> appellation agrees in sound with Magog&#44; secondly&#44; because both words in Hebrew are capable of<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="18"/>
            <p>conveying the idea uppermost in the mind of<lb/> the Seer in his soul&#45;stirring vision&#44; namely&#44; the<lb/> final overthrow of the crushing rule of Russia<lb/> on the hills of Palestine&#44; the melting away the<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; Hithmogeg&#44; as it were&#44; of that colossal<lb/> power relentlessly inimical to Judaism to and<lb/> to human liberty progress.  When will that longed<lb/> for consummation gladden the earth Freedom&#63;  When<lb/> will the clanking of the chains shock mankind<lb/> no more&#44; and the song of redeemed millions break<lb/> forth in joyous strains from land to land&#63;<lb/>  Narrow is man&#39;s horizon&#59; human our looks cannot<lb/> stretch beyond a span&#44; but what arose before<lb/> a mind celestially illumined will infallibly<lb/> come to pass.  How&#63;...By invisible turns<lb/> in the political wheels.  Many have been<lb/> the changes in this wonderful century&#44; and the<lb/> Eastern question stands up brea threatingly rises like a spectre at all<lb/> times pointing with a blood stained finger to the plains of the Jordan.  Russia is even now arming her motley<lb/> soldiery.  Jealous of France is her schemes upon<lb/> Asia&#44; fearful of the ascendency which England<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="19"/>
            <p>has gained in Africa&#44; suspicious of the<lb/> union of Germany and Spain and of her extente cordiale with Italy and Spain&#44; the Gog at<lb/> St. Petersburg is massing terrible forces in ad&#45;<lb/>&#45;vance of the <sic>irrespressible</sic> conflict.  Watch<lb/> and note the results.  I shall not under&#45;<lb/>&#45;take the impossible attempt of peering into the<lb/> future.  &#182; With your permission I will Permit me again to change<lb/> the scene.  As I have set before you Moses<lb/> tracing in ineffaceable lives the dictates of Eternal<lb/> Wisdom&#44; and a prophet of the captivity forecasting<lb/> the issues of the world&#39;s Divine rule&#44; I will<lb/> now present a Rabbi for your mental inspection.<lb/>  To study his character&#44; you it will be necessary<lb/> that you accompany me to France.  We shall<lb/> not tarry there long.<lb/></p>
            <p>Before the XV century when Jews had been driven away as a community&#44;<lb/> towards the end of the XIV century&#44; from the country<lb/> watered by the Seine and the Loire the Rhine and<lb/> the Garonne two sharply defined lines&#44; divided Rabbinical schools were divided there in that part of central Europe.<lb/>  into two sharply defined lines.  In the Southern<lb/> of France&#44; the influence of neighbouring Spain<lb/> was very sensibly felt.  Provence gave<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="20"/>
            <p>translators of Arabic works&#44; like as the brothers Aben<lb/> Tibbon of Lunel&#59; philosophers as the celebrated<lb/> Gersonides of Bagnoles&#59; poets as the far famed Be&#45;<lb/>&#45;drasi of Beziers&#59; Grammarians&#44; commentators and<lb/> lexicographers like as the Kimchi&#45;family of Narbonne.<lb/>  In those days and in most of the cities thus geogra&#45;<lb/>&#45;phically situated&#44; the standard of culture was<lb/> borrowed from the schools flourishing under the<lb/> civilization of the Kalifs.  For like the Moors&#44; the<lb/> Jews in the <sic>Ibernian</sic> peninsula mostly preferred linguistic<lb/> and speculative sciences to casuistical theology and casiustry.<lb/>  In the Northern of France&#44; the opposite system pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;vailed.  The Talmud and kindred writings found<lb/> formed a chief study&#44; and I scarcely need unfold<lb/> in your presence the roll of honor on which<lb/> the names of Israelites distinguished in such branches&#44;<lb/> are inscribed.  One name universally known&#45;&#45;that<lb/> of our Isaacides of Troyes&#44; or Rashi&#44; comprehends all<lb/> in those departments of our literature.  For truly no<lb/> man has surpassed him in the knowledge of Tradition&#45;<lb/>&#45;alism and in the capacity of facilitating and understanding<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="21"/>
            <p>thereof to students of every generation.<lb/>  That illustrious French Rabbi of the XI century&#44; whom<lb/> nature did not allow to perpetuate his learning<lb/> by means of male descendants&#44; bequeathed it to us&#44;<lb/> through his daughters&#39; sons.  Of the child of<lb/> his elder&#44; Miriam&#44; little has been left in writing&#44;<lb/> but the three children of Jochebed the younger have enriched<lb/> our literature with by their active steadfast exertions.  Samuel<lb/> and Jacob exceeded their oldest brother Isaac&#44; because<lb/> they joined to a most extensive Talmudical eru&#45;<lb/>&#45;dition a familiarity with the linguistic and poetical<lb/> abilities style of their countrymen and coreligionists of<lb/> Southern France.  What chiefly attracted my<lb/> attention most chiefly in the course of my reading is<lb/> not&#44; however&#44; the qualities of the mind I profoundly admired but the<lb/> traits of the heart of Rashi&#39;s grandsons.  Not<lb/> inappropriately has the name of the youngest come<lb/> down to posterity with the epithet of &#34;Rabbenu<lb/> Tam&#34; or&#44; Our teacher the upright&#59; for he inherited<lb/> in a superlative degree the modesty and piety which<lb/> signalized his gra maternal grand parent.  It is<lb/> of him that I purpose briefly to speak.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="22"/>
            <p>One of his contemporaries was Aben Ezra the<lb/> famous Abraham Aben Ezra.  All have heard of<lb/> that great man of Toledo. prolific author.  He had gone deeply<lb/> into all the sciences cultivated in his age.  He had<lb/> written learnedly and vastly uniquely in diction terseness of diction upon a variety of<lb/> subjects&#44; and his commentaries to on the Scriptures rank&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed preeminently among people who could appre&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciate the author&#39;s concise and deeply strikingly suggestive<lb/> language.  But versatile and superior as his the abi&#45;<lb/>&#45;lities of that Spanish Jew certainly were&#44; he appear&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed to have prided himself particularly on his poetical vein.<lb/>  Not however&#44; because wealth flowed from it&#44; for Aben Ezra illus&#45;<lb/>&#45;trated to the letter the sentence of Ecclesiastes &#34;I<lb/> have again seen that...not &#40;always&#41; have the wise<lb/> bread or the intelligent riches.&#34;  The life of that He&#45;<lb/>&#45;brew poet was an unenviable one.  Either through<lb/> a fondness for changes of scene&#44; or by reason of a<lb/> restless disposition&#44; he was continued unsettled to the end&#44; and in straight&#45;<lb/>&#45;end circumstances.  He has left us an elegy<lb/> upon his fate In a lengthy poem of flowing smooth<lb/> rhymes&#44; he has left us an elegy upon his fate.  He writes&#58;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="23"/>
            <p>&#34;I lost my vigour in my long wanderings.  Per&#45;<lb/>&#45;plexed are now my thoughts&#59; my mouth and my tongue<lb/> refuse their office.  I would once weave such<lb/> songs as would adorn the Hebrews like <sic>jewelled</sic> chains<lb/> upon fair necks.  Wheresoever I would wend my<lb/> steps my pen traced lines like a mirror brilliantly<lb/> transparent.  At my nod mountains bent&#44; and<lb/> on their heights&#44; my swift thoughts rushed with the<lb/> speed of lightnings.&#34;  And after having drawn a<lb/> glowing mournful contrast between the success which had<lb/> formerly attended his efforts&#44; and the humiliation debasement<lb/> which he then fancied to experienced&#44; the poet hurls his shafts<lb/> at countries whose inhabitants could not value<lb/> the learning of men reared in the schools that<lb/> flourished in Arabic Moorish Spain.  He so complains&#58;<lb/> &#34;In the domains of Christians no honor will he receive<lb/> who saw the light first in Moorish Arabic Spain.  People<lb/> hiss and hoot at us.  But&#44; if a pigmy from the Grecian Ionian Grecian<lb/> isles arrives in their midst with a muttering of Greece little learning he is lifted on men&#39;s should&#45;<lb/>&#45;ers and looked up to as if he were a giant.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="24"/>
            <p>It will not surprise any that a man hold&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing so exalted an opinion of his own confessedly sterling<lb/> merits&#59; that a man ascribing to his native land literary<lb/> supremacy&#44; should turn away with contempt from the<lb/> productions of a Rabbinist in Northern France.<lb/>  Abraham Aben Ezra heard that the grandson of Rashi&#45;<lb/>Jacob of Ramera in the province of Champagne&#45;&#45;tried his<lb/> hand at rhymes.  With more piquancy than<lb/> courtesy he sent the Rabbi a Hebrew note.  It read<lb/> so&#58; &#34;Who has allowed a Frenchman admission into<lb/> the temple of the Muses&#59; how dares a stranger tread<lb/> on ground consecrated unto Poesy&#63;  Were the song of<lb/> Jacob sweet as the manna to the taste&#44; I shall be<lb/> the sun at whose burning rays it will melt away.&#34;<lb/>  Haughty was the epistle&#59; beautiful was the answer in<lb/> its lowliness.  I very much regret the inadequacy<lb/> of an English translation to present the peculiar word&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing of the original.  It substantially said&#58; &#34;Let<lb/> Aben Ezra my superior dismiss the suspicion that I<lb/> dare presume to deem myself his equal.  I am but a submissive<lb/> servant to Abraham&#44; and bend the knee and<lb/> bow before his learning.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="25"/>
            <p>The great&#44; but haughty&#44; Spaniard was conquered by the<lb/> extreme humility of the Frenchman&#44; and he traced<lb/> these lines as an amende honoerable.  &#34;Ought one<lb/> so loftily high stationed&#59; a spiritual shepherd of God&#39;s flock&#44;<lb/> to lower himself to write to and address one so vulgar as myself&#63;<lb/>  Never should the angel of the Lord prostrate fall<lb/> before Balaam.&#34;  You easily perceive the<lb/> meaning drift of the epigram.  Aben Ezra repenting of an<lb/> act unworthy of a descendant of the father of our race&#44; whose name he bore&#44;<lb/> compared himself to the boastful soothsayer of<lb/> Mesopotamia.  He recalled the saying of Israel&#39;s<lb/> Sages that in the school of Abraham a generous<lb/> spirit&#44; chaste thoughts and meekness have their training&#44;<lb/> while in that of Balak&#39;s prophet the opposite<lb/> qualities are instilled. dispositions obtain a culture.  The former represents to Rabbinism profoundly the latter Grecianism&#44; <sic>For</sic> highly greatly esteemed as<lb/> learning is in the sight of our preceptors&#59; invaluable<lb/> as knowledge has been declared by in their impartings&#44; still<lb/> the maxims and apothegms that run through the<lb/> writings of the Rabbis are a golden crown diadem to<lb/> social virtues.  &#34;The pilth of wisdom is withdrawing<lb/> from evil and performing righteous deeds&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="26"/>
            <p>I shall not suffer my talk to degenerate into a<lb/> sermon&#44; but with the &#34;Young Men&#39;s Hebrew Association&#34;<lb/> that have patiently listened&#44; I may assume the place<lb/> of mentor.  Hitherto this organization has accomplish&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed little in its endeavours to illustrate its appellation by wise deeds.<lb/>  It must redouble its efforts.  It must aid the Sy&#45;<lb/>&#45;nagogue in the preservation of the traditions which<lb/> have prevented an approximation to gentilism.  It must<lb/> aid in the preservation perpetuation of the sacred language&#44; which<lb/> has knit together the dismembered limbs of our na&#45;<lb/>&#45;tional body.  It must aid educational establish&#45;<lb/>&#45;ments&#44; where our children obtain an understanding<lb/> of their duties as Israelites&#44; and as citizens of a country<lb/> which has recognized our manhood.  It must aid<lb/> the Alliance Israelite Universelle in its and kindred associations in their herculean<lb/> task to change our brethren in the Orient from ignorant<lb/> and grovelling clans into enlightened and self respecting<lb/> communities.  Those are the engines with which to<lb/> raise the standard of Judaism loftily.  May<lb/> you Ladies and Gentlemen lend those engines an impulse&#44; which will become<lb/> potent and lastingly effective.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
