<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF1_6</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_6_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_6_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_6_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_6_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_6_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_6_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_6_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_6_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_6_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_6_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_6_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_6_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For the Sabbath before Rosh Hashan&#225;<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;  Noble words&#33;<lb/>  Sublime example&#33;  A people have assembled to hear<lb/> what their godly leader will speak ere he departs<lb/> heavenward.  It may be the last charge of the beloved she&#45;<lb/>&#45;herd to the flock of his pasture.  Will he ask that<lb/> his name be sweetly embalmed in the memory of posterity&#63;<lb/>  That forty years of self&#45;denial may be rewarded with a<lb/> universal outburst of grateful feelings&#63;  Listen O descend&#45;<lb/>&#45;ants of the meek prophet.  Listen to the address he made.<lb/>  &#34;Ye stand this day all of you <hi rend="underline">before the Lord your God</hi>&#34;<lb/> The knowledge of <del>the</del> God&#39;s omnipresence must be kept<lb/> fresh in your minds.  That&#44; more than the parting<lb/> counsel of a perishable mortal will hold you in righteous&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness.  Along then with rhetorical figures&#45;&#45;the trappings<lb/> of oratory.  Shining truths&#44; reflecting the all&#45;seeing<lb/> God must be set before the congregation of Jacob.  That is<lb/> the mirror in which they shall behold themselves.  Ugly<lb/> features in their characters will be appear to the naked<lb/> eye.  They who view them&#44; will learn to loathe those moral<lb/> deformities&#44; and to exchange them for the beauties of holiness.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Dear fellow&#45;believers&#33;  We devoted some time together<lb/> in casting a look on our past conduct.  We did not<lb/> conceal from one another distasteful facts&#59; nor would we<lb/> practice the art of glossing wrongs to palm them off as<lb/> rights.  How we displeased the heavenly Legislator&#44; to<lb/> gratify worldly appetites&#59; how we swerved from upright&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness to follow directly our greed of gain&#44; formed the sub&#45;<lb/>&#45;ject of our consideration&#44; during the Sabbaths of Elul.<lb/>  And now that we have <del>reached</del> drawn night to the borders of a new month&#44;<lb/> opening to our vision the dawning of a new year&#44; let the<lb/> same degree of candor one be exhibited.<lb/>  In meeting at the season of solemnity no fast approaching&#44; let sincerity marshal our steps.<lb/>  If any Israelite exists&#44; who presumes that he can evade the<lb/> looks of ubiquitous Providence&#44; let him not enter these sacred<lb/> courts.  If any imagines that because the laws of the com&#45;<lb/>&#45;munity with whose interests he is identified are far&#45;reaching<lb/> and liberal&#44; he has attained a height inaccessible to Divine<lb/> Justice&#59; or because the land he chose to dwell in is rich<lb/> and prosperous&#44; he has therefore purchased for himself a<lb/> shield against which the arms of celestial judgment will<lb/> be blunted&#44; let him depart from our midst.  He is none<lb/> of us.  The blood of the patriarchs does not course<lb/> through his veins.  Not I but Moses tells it.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Who are they who that must believe in a Supervising Being&#44; holding<lb/> creation in the palm of his hand&#44; and directing it by His<lb/> omnipotent will to be a staff of life or a rod of chastise&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment&#63;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  &#34;Every man of Israel.&#34;  The wealthiest<lb/> and the humblest&#44; the master and he who hews wood by his<lb/> command&#44; and draws him water.  To gainsay that truth<lb/> would be to forswear the covenant made with us by the ever&#45;<lb/>living God.  Aye with us&#44; who count our national existence<lb/> by <sic>millenial</sic> centuries&#44; as well as those of Israel who lived<lb/> in the remotest ages &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Not with you alone do I establish this covenant&#44; but with him<lb/> us that is standeth here with us&#44; and also with him that is not here with<lb/> us this day&#34;.  Praised be the Lord&#59; we do recognize the<lb/> <del>unquestionable</del> all important verity often&#45;taught by the son of Amram&#44;<lb/> and dwell<del>eth</del> upon with all the energy of his righteous soul<lb/> prior to his death.  Deeds offensive to religion and morality<lb/> may be laid to our charge&#44; but the wilful perverseness<lb/> of having trained our minds to deny Providence&#44; and our<lb/> individual accountability will not be reckoned among our sins.<lb/>  Hence we all prepare to stand on the coming day before the God of mercy&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>high heavens&#39; King.  Close up your ranks&#44; my<lb/> Brethren&#33; and form a glorious phalanx to greet the<lb/> Monarch of the world.  You can yet present an imposing<lb/> sight.  Adverse circumstances have <del>militated</del> created many<lb/> a gap amid your files&#44; <del>but</del> still your strength is not consumed.<lb/>  Be true to the grand old past&#44; O my Congregation&#33; and<lb/> the future will vindicate your loyalty.  The spirit of the<lb/> time militates against your success.  From within&#44; an<lb/> uncontrollable rushing after an imitative worship&#44; hampers<lb/> your movements.  From without stamp&#45;oratory and<lb/> the press have leagued together to shame you into a total<lb/> relinquishing of your trust.  Only three days ago&#44; a<lb/> journal noted for its liberality&#44; demanded <del>you</del> a surrender&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing of your religious identity&#44; a fusion <del>with</del> into gentilism<lb/> as the completion of your destiny.  But let me quote<lb/> again the words of Moses as metaphorically commented on<lb/> by the Sages &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;you stand this day all of you&#34;&#44; you will ever stand&#44; so<lb/> long as you cluster together in one close&#44; compact body.<lb/>  But no sooner you divide&#44; than you will be lost<lb/> in the swelling tide&#59; than you will no longer be distinguished<lb/> as the harbingers of eternal truths.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  Did the narrative of the first night&#44; which<lb/> Jacob&#44; weary and disconsolate&#44; spent beyond the parental<lb/> home&#44; ever strike you as containing in the text an expression&#44;<lb/> unaccountably strange&#63;  We read that he took &#34;of the stones<lb/> of the place&#44; and put them for his fellows&#34;&#44; but in the morning<lb/> one huge stone was found whereon he had laid his <sic>acking</sic> head <del>upon</del><lb/> and that he set up as a monument of his trust in the<lb/> protecting Lord.  A fit type of the tribes on whom the<lb/> patriarch relied for the perpetuity of Abraham&#39;s faith.<lb/>  Yes&#58; our firm adherence to principles&#44; our unity of<lb/> thoughts and actions&#44; will render us immoveable.  It<lb/> will accomplish the will of the Omnipotent in selecting in<lb/> for his people&#44; and it will be the most acceptable thanks&#45;<lb/>&#45;giving offering to the altar of Israel&#39;s King.  With<lb/> that oblation let us enter these holy courts on our Rosh<lb/> Hashana.  Let the strength of belief&#44; supply the place<lb/> of member&#59; the fervency of devotion&#44; that of crowded<lb/> multitudes.  And here I must pause<lb/> to consider whether I ought to give utterance to distasteful<lb/> truths.  But I said that sincerity must be our fore&#45;<lb/>&#45;runner in meeting the solemn festivals of the present<lb/> season&#44; and I will speak.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  In none of the service rendered in this hal&#45;<lb/>&#45;lowed spot is the effect of prayer so neutralized by<lb/> disturbing causes as on those offered during the ensuing<lb/> holidays.  I will be silent concerning the indecorous<lb/> demeanour of some who arrive late at the synagogue&#44; and<lb/> leave soon after&#44; of some whose attention is engaged in<lb/> aught but the religious exercises&#59; though I ought to cry<lb/> aloud and spare not.  This Sabbath I will chiefly<lb/> allude to a circumstance&#44; which I deem very detrimental<lb/> to our interests.  Our irregular manner of chanting the<lb/> ancient airs of the Sephardic rite&#44; occasions complaints<lb/> prejudicial to conservatism I need not assure my hearers&#44;<lb/> that&#44; as far as God has given me the faculty of judging&#45;<lb/> I hold that service to be acceptable&#44; in which a whole<lb/> congregation join.  But must such a service be ne&#45;<lb/>&#45;cessarily inharmonious&#33;  Is it orthodoxy to vie with<lb/> one another in producing jarring sounds&#44; rather than sub&#45;<lb/>&#45;during our voices&#44; and evoking a sweet accord of tones&#44;<lb/> agreeable to the ear&#44; and soothing to the soul&#63;  For&#44;<lb/> after all&#44; my friends&#33; we <hi rend="underline">are</hi> forcibly affected<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>by the senses.  And as much as we should object<lb/> to a worship formal and restrained&#44; it would be<lb/> hypocrisy to deny that the dignity of our assemblies&#44; and<lb/> the beauties of our orisons are enhanced&#44; when human<lb/> voices swell in one grand and melodious strain.  Let<lb/> then the sons and daughters of our modern Asaphs attune<lb/> their vocal powers to our national hymns and psalmody.<lb/>  They will naturally benefit the cause we all have at heart&#44;<lb/> glorify our sanctuary&#44; and secure to themselves a heavenly<lb/> blessing.  I may hereafter aid those among my brethren&#44;<lb/> who are thus prompted to devote their natural gifts to<lb/> the honor of the beneficent Donor&#44; so that at the revolving of<lb/> another triennial cycle&#44; we may rejoice in our increase&#44; and<lb/> in the firm stability of our sacred institution.<lb/></p>
            <p>And Thou O Lord who wilt seat on the throne of judgment<lb/> to reward us according to our deeds&#44; cleanse our spirits&#44;<lb/> and befit us to stand before Thy presence becomingly<lb/> on the approaching solemn days.  And vouchsafe to<lb/> <sic>fulfil</sic> in us the Biblical sentence&#44; where it is written&#44;<lb/> &#34;Ye that have cleaved to the Lord your God&#44; ye are<lb/> alive all of you even this day.&#34;  <del>May</del> So may<lb/> it be.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
