<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF4_12</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_12_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_12_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_12_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_12_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_12_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_12_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_12_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_12_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_12_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_12_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_12_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_12_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_12_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_12_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_12_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_12_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Post&#45;Biblical<lb/>
                32<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>A French writer&#44; whose knowledge of military tactics<lb/> entitles him to a hearing&#44; referring to the defensive wars of<lb/> the Jews against the aggressive Romans&#44; says&#58; &#34;The <sic>seige</sic> of Jerusalem&#44;<lb/> so famous in history&#45;being one of the most remarkable memorable<lb/> in the annals of antiquity both for the severity violence of the<lb/> attack assault and the firmness of the resistance&#45;&#45;is neverthe&#45; yet<lb/> &#45;less&#44; in the opinion of those who understand and examine<lb/> matters closely still less remarkable than the <sic>seige</sic> of Jota&#45;<lb/>&#45;pata.  All which is vast and profound in the art of<lb/> war&#44; all which can be done to oppose a sagaciously<lb/> planned assault attack&#44; all which the human mind can<lb/> devise&#44; as shrewd&#44; dashing&#44; bold&#44; we meet in that <sic>seige</sic>.<lb/>  Bravery and a determined daringness are displayed<lb/> alike in Jerusalem and in Jotapata&#44; but at the latter a<lb/> <sic>marvellous</sic> conduct is seen which is lacking at the <sic>seige</sic> of<lb/> the former.  In Jerusalem fiery anger urged spurred on the com&#45;<lb/>&#45;battants&#44; but in Jotapata the abilities of the Chief<lb/> and the indomitable courage of his soldiers&#44; withstood<lb/> the well disciplined and well commanded Roman legions&#45;&#45;<lb/>a prudent intrepidity it was&#59; a valor most extraordinary&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>In the last lecture of my post&#45;biblical<lb/> series&#44; I laid some stress upon the thrilling scenes of at<lb/> Jotapata&#44; and gave Josephus who led on the fearless<lb/> Galileans to the desperate struggle&#44; due credit for a<lb/> masterly generalship worthy of the highest encomium.<lb/>  I could not praise him as a self&#45;denying patriot&#44;<lb/> and an earnest Jew&#44; because my mind discovered egotism<lb/> and insincerity in his character. but without Nevertheless I will not attempting<lb/> to forestall the opinions of others&#59; I will let the sequel<lb/> to the fall of Jotapata be the standard by which<lb/> our celebrated historian shall be judged.<lb/></p>
            <p>The silence of the grave reigned supreme.  The Roman<lb/> sword had turned the captured gallant city of Jotapata<lb/> into a charnel house&#44; still forty men evaded<lb/> its deadly strokes.  They had ventured from the height<lb/> of a rock into a hollow cavern below.  The country<lb/> of Judea opened a refuge to fugitives fugitives in its clefts<lb/> and grottos.  All will remember the flight of David<lb/> to the cave of Adulam&#44; and the staying of Elijah in<lb/> that of Carmel.  If enough provision could be gathered&#44;<lb/> those forty men might elude the vigilance of the enemy&#44;<lb/> and watch for the opportunity to go out at large.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Josephus was the moving spirit in their midst.  In vain<lb/> had the Romans sought him the fallen leader among the prisoners&#44; searched<lb/> for him among the slain&#44; so that Vespasian and Titus<lb/> might wreak their vengeance on his person&#44; or treat<lb/> his corpse with contempt.  Josephus had put<lb/> himself beyond their reach&#44; and now with a watchwakefulness<lb/> which knew no rest was designing an escape.  Once<lb/> One night he stole out of his hiding place&#44; hoping to<lb/> surprise the sentinels&#44; overcomepower them while if asleep at<lb/> their posts&#44; and flee away.  He tried it again without<lb/> success&#44; but at on the third time a woman recognized him the well&#45;known Hebrew&#44;<lb/> and the report of his having found a shelter in a cave<lb/> soon spread abroad like a wild fire.  The Roman general rejoiced&#59;<lb/> a <sic>redoutable</sic> chieftain would be in his power.  He dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;patched two officers with a demand that Josephus<lb/> should surrender on the promise of a full pardon.<lb/>  The demand struck terror.  The reputation of the Romans<lb/> for truthfulness was not above suspicion&#44; but when a<lb/> third official with whom Josephus knew was familiarly acquainted arrived&#44; and<lb/> made the same request&#44; the fugitive agreed to submit.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>What happened at that juncture in that<lb/> subterranean retreat&#44; none has ever told&#44; save the<lb/> writer whose interest it was to put on his narrative<lb/> the least repulsive features.  Let us hear him<lb/> that we may not prejudge.  Josephus was<lb/> seized with a spirit akin to prophecy at that<lb/> soul trying moment.  The dreams which he<lb/> had had dreamt&#44; flashed before his vision&#44; and he<lb/> learned that he must forsake the cause of his<lb/> brethren and go over&#44; as the messenger of a Divine or&#45; dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;dination &#45;position&#44; to the Romans&#44; whom the God of battles had<lb/> rendered victorious.  But the superhuman ge&#45;<lb/>&#45;nius of which he boasted&#44; was not appreciated  by<lb/> his companions.  With drawn swords they surrounded<lb/> him&#44; and disloyal&#44; craven&#44; cowardly were the epithets<lb/> by which he was addressed.  The thirty &#91;inserted above&#58; forty&#93; nine fugitives<lb/> offered him the choice to die by his own hand&#44; or pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;pared to be slain by theirs.  They would never suffer<lb/> the oppressors of Judea to glory that the defender<lb/> of Jotapata had accepted their terms of the sake<lb/> of dragging and enslaved existence.  But Josephus<lb/> had determined to live at all hazards.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>With a coolness scarcely credible&#44; he then delivered<lb/> a lengthy and learned discourse on the crime of suicide&#44;<lb/> using every argument to prove that no circumstance<lb/> can justify the act of putting an end to one&#39;s exist&#45;<lb/>&#45;ence.  His words fell upon unwilling ears.  They served only to kindle the wrath of patriots who would have died a hundred deaths rather than cringe before<lb/> a heathen foe.  They ran at him&#44; and would have<lb/> cut him down on the spot&#44; if his looks of utter distress&#44; his<lb/> pitiful tones&#44; the memory of his military services and of his great scho&#45;<lb/>&#45;larship had not softened the irritation and held his<lb/> armed companions back.  Finally&#44; perceiving that he<lb/> could not move them from the resolve they had taken&#44; Josephus<lb/> proposed a plan by which suicide might be avoided&#44;<lb/> except unavoidably in a single instance.  They should cast lots&#44;<lb/> and he whose name was drawn out first should be kil&#45;<lb/>&#45;led by him whose name came out second&#44; and the latter<lb/> by the third&#44; till the last was reached&#44; who surely would<lb/> not wish to live in the face of such self&#45;sacrificing.<lb/>  The proposition was readily accepted&#44; and all bared the neck<lb/> to receive the deadly thrust.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Was Josephus an adept in sleight of<lb/> hand performances&#63;  Among the many mental<lb/> qualifications he possessed&#44; did he reckon also<lb/> jugglery&#63;  He relates that by chance&#44; or by a<lb/> providential ordination&#44; his name was not drawn<lb/> out till thirty eight had died&#59; then his persuasive<lb/> tongue induced the thirty ninth one not to resort to<lb/> the lot and either kill or be killed&#44; but accept<lb/> the offer of the Roman general and live.  They<lb/> both surrendered and under the an escort were led to<lb/> the camp of the enemies.  The presence of Josephus<lb/> was the sign of a tumult.  Many would have<lb/> pierced him through with their javilns javelins&#44; many<lb/> pressed forward to look at the chief of the heroic<lb/> Galileans&#44; but all stood and marvelled for and amazed <sic>marvelled</sic>. at his &#91;&#63;&#93; He was<lb/> young in years&#44; and of a commanding appearance&#44;<lb/> and his he carried himself in just manner aloft as becoming it behooves one whose deeds had been gained for him a far&#45;reaching renown.<lb/>  Titus showed him courtesy&#44; and commended him the late Jewish general to his<lb/> fathers kindness kindly consideration.  Yet&#44; Vespasian&#44; notwithstanding the<lb/> promise that he would do the captive no harm&#44; intended<lb/> him as a trophy to be sent to gladden Rome.  Josephus knew<lb/> what that it meant and on hearing it that he was to appear to be sent to the city on the Tiber&#44; and<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>before Nero&#44; begged that he might be granted<lb/> a private interview with Vespasian.  He had a<lb/> communication of deep importance to impart.<lb/>  Brought before the Roman general the wily prisoner<lb/> spoke thus&#58; &#34;Thou Vespasian&#44; thinkest merely<lb/> that thou hast taken Josephus captive&#44; but I have come<lb/> to thee as a messenger of great tidings.  Had I not<lb/> been sent by God&#44; to thee&#44; I know what was would be the law<lb/> of the Jews in this case&#44; and how it becomes a general<lb/> to die.  Wilt thou send me to Nero&#63;  Why&#63;  Are<lb/> Nero&#39;s successors&#44; it l till it comes to thy turn&#44; to live&#63;<lb/>  Thou Vespasian art Ceasar and Emperor&#44; even thou<lb/> and thy son.&#34;  And having said that&#44; Josephus asked<lb/> to be kept in closer custody till his prediction was<lb/> fulfilled.  It is not impossible that Vespasian put<lb/> faith to in the prophecy.  The unnatural end of Tiberius&#44;<lb/> Caligula and Claudius warranted a belief that the<lb/> monster Nero would share their fate&#44; and the victor<lb/> of many battles in Europe African and Asia&#44; would be lifted up to the throne&#44; but&#44;<lb/> at all events&#44; it suited Vespasian to use the cunning<lb/> prophet as an easy instrument facilitating the over&#45;<lb/>&#45;throw of the tenaciously contested capital of Judea.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>For from that moment&#44; to the end of his servile<lb/> existence&#44; Josephus sold his heart and his pen to<lb/> the tyrannic power that destroyed his country<lb/> and dispersed his people.  The Talmud<lb/> attributes to Johanan Ben Zacka&#239; the prediction<lb/> which Josephus claims as his own.  The volumes<lb/> of our traditions tells that when the Rabbi&#44; who belonged<lb/> to the peace party&#44; was carried out by his friends&#44; as<lb/> if dead&#44; beyond the walls of Jerusalem&#44; and brought<lb/> before Vespasian&#44; he saluted the latter in these terms&#58;<lb/> &#34;Peace be with thee O King.&#34;  I shall not al discuss<lb/> the question as to whom the first prognostication must be<lb/> credited.  To me it is immaterial&#44; but a what assumes<lb/> great vast importance in my mind is the aim and issue<lb/> of the interview.  With Josephus selfishness was the<lb/> motive power&#59; with Johanan the preservation of<lb/> Judaism.  If our historian flattered Vaspasian with the<lb/> title of Emperor&#44; it was to prevent being delivered by<lb/> Nero to the executioner.  If our Mishnic Sage gratified<lb/> the vanity of Vaspasian it was to prevent the Torah<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>being cast into a pit of oblivion.  For Rab&#45;<lb/>&#45;bi Johanan Ben Zacka&#239; asked as a gift Jabne<lb/> or Jamaia&#44; that he might establish there a college&#45;&#45;<lb/> a college which in very deed supplied breathed into Israel with<lb/> an undying spiritual existence after his its political<lb/> life become extinct&#45;&#45;Josephus prayed that he<lb/> might bask in the sunshine of perfidious Rome&#59; for&#44;<lb/> according to his own statement&#44; he was receiving precious<lb/> gifts and being treated very obligingly&#44; while Galilea&#44; that<lb/> he had deserted&#44; was spilling her precious blood&#44; or was<lb/> obliged to drag the bonds shackles of thraldom.  Joppa or Jaffa&#44; famous in<lb/> Scriptural history as the starting point of the prophet Jonah in his<lb/> attempt to run away form a Divine office mission&#44; had made<lb/> a stubborn resistance.  Women helped the men to fight<lb/> the invaders&#44; but the elements also conjured against the<lb/> defenders.  For as they took to their ships&#44; a hurricane<lb/> dashed those vessels against rocks&#44; and they who ventured to<lb/> approach the shore&#44; were forced back into the raging sea<lb/> by the Romans&#44; or were mercilessly cut down.<lb/>  None was left to announce in the metropolis that<lb/> all Galilee was in the throes agonies of death.  At Jerusalem<lb/> even the news of the fall of Jotapata had not arrived.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>Gradually it was told rumored about in a subdued tone&#44; but when<lb/> the report spread everywhere&#44; the cries of lament<lb/> rent the sky.  Josephus who had commanded<lb/> the band of maryred <sic>heros</sic> was wept for as dead.<lb/>  Thirty days a general universal mourning lasted&#44; but just<lb/> as the sorrow at the supposed tragical fall of the<lb/> general at Jotapata had been profound&#44; so was the<lb/> destination intense&#44; when it was learned that Josephus<lb/> had not died sword in hand&#44; but had meanly surrendered<lb/> to enjoy the attentions of the common foe.  Curses<lb/> loud and deep were on every lip&#44; and a burning wish<lb/> to make him feel the weight of their indignation sei&#45;<lb/>&#45;zed all.  The desire&#44; natural in hearts so embittered&#44; was<lb/> not gratified&#44; and I&#44; with the sensible and good Solomon<lb/> Men Munk&#44; say&#44; that the historian student of history must thank<lb/> Providence for the miraculous preservation of that<lb/> illustrious writer.  For he left to poseterity has eternized the memory<lb/> of the gallant defender of Jotapata.  <sic>he</sic> delivered the was kept alive that he might<lb/> might compose the a funeral oration over to be the coffin delivered over the coffin of his unhappy people&#44; and surely he acquitted<lb/> himself with admirable exceptional talents&#59; admirably and with capacities surpassingly great.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
