<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF11_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1896-01" source="" attested="yes">1896</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_1_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>107<lb/></p>
            <p>96<lb/></p>
            <p>Continuation of the subject<lb/>
                on &#34;Jewish life in Middle ages.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>A Club quite different form many a one which<lb/> infests Philadelphia&#44; flourishes in the city of London.<lb/>  It bears an historic name&#44; but I think that I<lb/> may challenge contradiction when I say that its<lb/> appellation is not a blind to cover up deception.  That<lb/> club is not a gilded sink&#44; wherein man&#45;<lb/>&#45;hood is dragged and lost.  No gambling orgies<lb/> allure to that spot our unwary youths&#44; who<lb/> squander their father&#39;s hard earned money and<lb/> rob their mother of the joys of home.  An<lb/> pleasurable intercourse for mutual instruction&#44;<lb/> is held there.  I allude&#44; as easily under&#45;<lb/>&#45;stood&#44; to the Maccabean Club.  In it meet<lb/> the literary worthies of whom I spoke in a measure as they<lb/> deserve&#44; in my last lecture.<lb/></p>
            <p>A short time ago&#44; a German Israelite sought<lb/> an entrance into that Club.  Accorded the pri&#45;<lb/>&#45;vilege of addressing its members&#44; he delivered<lb/> a speech which created much surprise a commotion.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Some interpreted it as the dream of a<lb/> visionary&#59; others opposed it as calculated to<lb/> encourage the charge of the Goldwin Smiths&#44;<lb/> abounding every where&#44; who declare that Jewish hearts are dead to<lb/> patriotic sentiments.  But&#44; in truth&#44; Mr Dr.<lb/> Herz&#39;l is neither a utopian or a fanatic.<lb/>  Not to play the role of a messiah&#44; he pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;posed his scheme&#59; nor does he ignore the<lb/> luminous fact that voluntarily&#44; most heroically<lb/> and generously Jews have spilt their blood and<lb/> unfastened the locks of their treasuries for the honor<lb/> of the countries of their birth or adoption.<lb/></p>
            <p>But Dr Herz&#39;l keenly feels the gross injustice<lb/> of antisemitism throughout the habitable globe.<lb/>  He notices that it is not f confined to cities<lb/> on the Danube and the Vistula.  He knows that<lb/> an under current of inveterate prejudice can<lb/> be detected even in the freest of lands&#44; where<lb/> riches so called liberal ideas and social commercial standing count nothing for<lb/> the admission of millionaires&#39; sons into clubs&#44;<lb/> where the money aristocracy of Wall street the New York elite<lb/> band together.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Dr. Herz&#39;l burns with enthusiasm.  He would<lb/> rejoice to pave the way for the opening of a<lb/> corner of the earth&#44; in which the right of<lb/> confessing of Judaism is not a grinding stone to<lb/> sharpen the barbed arrows of malevolence.<lb/>  England is strong&#59; her Jews <sic>weild</sic> political influence.<lb/>  What might not from Great Britain a<lb/> stream of salvation open to well up for some of the millions<lb/> shut up in wildernesses of degradation&#63;  Love<lb/> for his suffering brethren dictated the speech he which our German coreligionist made.<lb/>  To some nevertheless it became the butt of ridicule&#44; to<lb/> others the target of reproach.  But not by reason of it did the<lb/> man&#44; who has the courage of his opinion bent flinch and<lb/> beat a retreat covered whelmed with shame.  He believes<lb/> that Palestine&#44; at which industry has begun to<lb/> take up her abode&#59; even the ancient heritage of<lb/> <sic>of</sic> our fathers&#44; encouraging inspiring now the hope of<lb/> restoring to its soil the smile of plenty&#44; may be induced to widen<lb/> her portals to secure a home of tranquility to myriads save among the tribes of the<lb/> wandering foot and weary breast.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>As I understand him the speaker before<lb/> the Maccabean club&#44; he waved all questions<lb/> involving a reconstruction of our nationality with on the plan<lb/> with of a return to sacrificial rites and the reha&#45;<lb/>&#45;bilitation of all Mosaic prescriptions.  Had he<lb/> adopted that project&#44; I would decidedly have<lb/> opposed it.  Once before I had occasion to set<lb/> myself squarely against ideas which we dare<lb/> not entertain&#44; but&#44; ventilate the consummation of which<lb/> partial or total his in the bosom of a future shrouded in impene&#45;<lb/>&#45;trable darkness.  That Israel is destined to oc&#45;<lb/>&#45;cupy an exalted rank among the family of nations<lb/> I firmly&#44; most profoundly believe&#59; else my<lb/> prayers would be a mockery&#44; and my defense<lb/> of the prophecies sheer hypocrisy.  But the Rabbis<lb/> in their wisdom have condemned the arrogance that<lb/> pretends to set forth the how and the when our<lb/> final restoration will occur.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> In treatise Sanhedrin they themselves&#44; indulging in<lb/> speculations upon that subject&#44; would that confusion<lb/> be the reward of those who imagine they can tell at<lb/> what stage of the world&#39;s history we shall hail the redemption.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Maimonides himself too&#44; who ventured a prediction addressing in<lb/> a letter to a certain Nathaniel Alfayumi of<lb/> South Arabia&#44; deprecates reckoning upon uncertain&#45;<lb/>&#45;tainties.  But to go in search of means<lb/> to facilitate the acquisition securing guaranteed recognized purchase of a spot where<lb/> the systematically degraded of Abraham&#39;s pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;geny may breathe freely&#44; is a noble philanthropic design.<lb/>  Such I consider Dr Herz&#39;l&#39;s plea before<lb/> the Maccabean Club.  Not so&#44; how&#45;<lb/>&#45;ever has Mr Israel Abrahams interpreted construed<lb/> it.  In the introduction to his otherwise excellent<lb/> work on &#34;Jewish life in the Middle ages&#34;&#44; he writes&#58;<lb/> &#34;The superficial appearance of a national entity&#44;<lb/> has&#44; I fear&#44; originated the movement now po&#45;<lb/>pular with some modern Jews in favor of creating<lb/> a Jewish State&#44; politically independent and<lb/> perhaps religiously homogeneous.  I speak<lb/> regretfully&#44; because one does not like to see<lb/> enthusiasm wasted over a conception&#44; which has<lb/> no roots in the past and no fruits to offer<lb/> in the future.&#34;  In this manner does the gifted En&#45;<lb/>&#45;glish Jew join the party that sees our ultimate redemption in a<lb/> total <sic>absorbtion</sic> into Christianity&#44; Islamism or Buddhism.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Even Mr Zangwill&#44; whom none will accuse of<lb/> staunch orthodoxy&#44; discovers an historical blunder in Mr<lb/> Abraham&#39;s unqualified assertion&#44; that the idea which inspired<lb/> a Judah Hallevi&#44; &#34;has no roots in the past and no fruits to offer<lb/> in the future.&#34;  To me that sweeping statement&#44; is offensive to<lb/> the millions who still pray&#58; &#34;Oh Look at our affliction&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> I moreover lament it&#44; for I fancy to behold a backward<lb/> step&#44; from that which the same author took when<lb/> preparing some of his admirable sermons on &#34;aspects<lb/> of Judaism.&#34;  I lament it&#44; for I fancy that<lb/> his immediate predecessors&#44; whom I personally<lb/> knew&#44; would have condemned a denial of our<lb/> people&#39;s return triumphal return to Zion&#44; whi&#45;<lb/>&#45;ther gentilism shall flock to learn the ways<lb/> of the Lord &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>  But sober minded as Israel Abrahams appears&#44; he<lb/> has become infected nevertheless with a spirit of<lb/> the time.  That has led him beyond the confines<lb/> of conservatism&#59; that has made him also the champion<lb/> of practices which for untold centuries&#44; the<lb/> synagogue has turned against.<lb/></p>
            <p>But on the Sabbath that I resumed lecturing after<lb/> a long enforced silence&#44; I promised that brevity would<lb/> characterize my speaking.  I shall therefore reserve<lb/> to another time the treatment of my second objection<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>to the latest production under the auspices<lb/> of the &#34;Jewish Publication Society of America&#34;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
