<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF3_15</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_15_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_15_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_15_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_15_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_15_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_15_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_15_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_15_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_15_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_15_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_15_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_15_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For Sabbath Parah<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>When the Romans ruled Judea&#44; our laws and practices became were<lb/> the subject butt of sharp criticism.  Heathen masters would add<lb/> insult to injury by casting ridicule on observances which a people<lb/> in subjection fondly cherished.  But if in the bloody and<lb/> persistent struggle against an all&#45;crushing power&#44; our strength<lb/> was became exhausted&#44; in religious contests the Rabbis know how<lb/> to cope with and conquer their opponents.  Among the teachers of old often captious&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly questioned&#44; Johanan son of Zacchai stood prominently at<lb/> that sad period of our history annals.  The prediction of Hillel&#44;<lb/> the Babylonian&#44; that of all his numerous pupils&#44; the<lb/> youngest would be the greatest&#44; was completely fulfilled.<lb/>  He seemed to have been born&#44; when cool judgment&#44; and keen fore&#45;<lb/>&#45;sight were most needed for the preservation of Judaism.<lb/>  Merciless wars turned away the public mind from that sacred object.<lb/>  Victorious paganism stormed the citadel of our faith.  Joha&#45; In the<lb/> &#45;nan had to meet in his endeavours prosecution of his righteous endeavours&#44; Johanan had to meet home adversaries as well as fo&#45;<lb/>&#45;reign foes.  The radicals or zealots&#44; as historians<lb/> call the uncompromising but misguided patriots of the time&#44;<lb/> looked on him with no partial eye.  He preached modera&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion.  Seeing the utter impossibility to throw off the yoke<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>of imperial Rome&#44; he strove to avert the total<lb/> destruction of his country by <sic>counselling</sic> the submission.  But<lb/> this word was treason with the men&#44; who had resolved to fight<lb/> the battle of independence to the bitter end.  High&#45;character<lb/> and rank extensive tenuring&#44; social ranks did not deter them from sacrificing to their revenge the adherents<lb/> of the moderate party&#44; whom they <sic>stigmatised</sic> as the arm<lb/> of tyrannical heathenism.  Still none could accuse Johanan&#44;<lb/> as they rightly accused Josephus&#44; of deserting the national<lb/> cause to ingratiate himself with the insolent foreigner.<lb/>  They His mild disposition and that far reaching mind sanctity with which he was endowed led him<lb/> to advocate peace&#44; as the only policy by which to avert untold miseries<lb/> and the final overthrow of our people.  And when neither<lb/> the usual caution usually exercised nor the reputation he bore&#44; could<lb/> make it safe for him to remain ensure his safety any longer ensure his safety in Jerusalem&#44; he<lb/> escaped from the capital to the Roman camp.  A bold<lb/> undertaking&#44; justified by an ardent wish to deliver the<lb/> law and the traditions from extinction&#44; while delivering protecting his<lb/> own life.  The manner in which he accomplished it&#44;<lb/> shows a fixed determination which the sight of danger could not<lb/> hold back.  Johanan confided with some of his<lb/> most attached disciples&#44; feigned sickness and caused the<lb/> news to be of his death to be spread abroad.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>He then had himself carried in a box outside of encased in a coffin&#44; and carried beyond the city&#45;<lb/>limits&#44; as towards a place of burial place.  The guards stationed<lb/> at the principal gates by the war party then in the ascendancy&#44;<lb/>&#45;&#45;ever suspicious&#45;&#45;&#44; would have tested the truth of the report<lb/> circulated by forcing the coffin open&#59; but their Chief&#44; related<lb/> to the Rabbi&#44; and conniving at his escape&#44; prevented the act<lb/> as an too great an indignity against the remains of an eminent teacher in<lb/> Israel.  The fame of the son of Zacchai had already reached<lb/> the tent of the general of the inimical army.  So that when<lb/> brought before his presence&#44; he met with a cordial reception.<lb/>  Encouraged to ask a favor&#44; the Rabbi petitioned for<lb/> that which had impelled his every movement&#44; and which was<lb/> next to hes heart. namely&#44; to be He expressed the wish that he might be allowed to establish a<lb/> school of learning in Jabai&#44; a southern town of Palestine.<lb/>  The request was granted as fully quite harmless&#59; and thus while a cruel hand<lb/> set on fire the Temple and its altar to consume therewith the Hebrew race&#44; a holy beneficent hand kindled a flame<lb/> was kindled and kept unquenchably quenchlessly ablaze to which to rescusci&#45;<lb/>&#45;tated paralyzed Judaism.  R. Johanan created formed a new epoch.  He became then<lb/> the central figure in the religious events of the time.<lb/>  To him were directed all minds in searching for of instruction&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>and his notoriety drew also to his academy many a<lb/> heathen who desired to have bent upon having a fling at Moses and<lb/> the prophets.  On one occasion a Roman who had<lb/> heard of the rites connected with the purification through the red&#45;heifer&#44;&#45;&#45;the<lb/> ordinance of which we have perused this sabbath in our<lb/> additional section&#45;&#45;&#44; spoke as follows.  &#34;I think that you<lb/> Jews practice witchcraft&#44; for I can see nothing but magic<lb/> in some of your observances.  For instance.  You take an<lb/> animal of a peculiar colour&#44; burn it to ashes&#44; mix with<lb/> them other matters substances&#44; put all in water&#44; sprinkle a few<lb/> drops on a person who has come in contact with a dead<lb/> body&#44; and profess that by such means he is made pure&#34;.<lb/>  Now&#44; to explain satisfactorily to a sneering unbeliever a<lb/> precept for which no reason has been assigned&#44; must have<lb/> been very perplexing.  But R. Johanan was never at a<lb/> loss for an <sic>ingenius</sic> answer.  He immediately said.  You<lb/> seem to forget your own doings.  Have you ever been af&#45; suffered<lb/> &#45;ected with contagious diseases&#63; by contagion&#63;  by infection&#63;  No replied the heathen.<lb/>  But you may have entered a room&#44; where one so affected lay.<lb/>  Tell me how do your people generally seek to drive away the foul air&#63;<lb/>  Do they not use as a disinfectant&#44; drugs dissolved into<lb/> vapor by a slow fire&#44; and water in which some odoriferous aromatic<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>substance is hung soaked&#63; plants are exhale their sweet odor&#63;  Well&#44; we Israelites have another adopted<lb/> a process not very dissimilar by which to remove impurities from one of us who touched<lb/> a corpse&#44; before he be allowed to come among a large concourse<lb/> of his brethren&#44; <sic>worshipping</sic> in the Sanctuary.  The disciples<lb/> of the Sage perceived at once that the explanation given was<lb/> a mere evasion&#44; to silence a captious pagan&#44; and as he<lb/> left they addressed their teachers so.  Rabbi&#33;  Thou hast<lb/> lightly made easily caused the stranger to cease to <sic>criticising</sic> our station tenets.<lb/>  But how wilt thou expound to us a command so singular in<lb/> its nature&#63;  To which Johanan answered.  Believe that neither<lb/> the dead make us unholy&#44; nor the sprinkling of any water<lb/> can cleanse our souls.  But that God who has separated us to<lb/> His service&#44; would keep us distinct by rites and usages extraor&#45;<lb/>&#45;dinary and above our comprehension&#44; but against which we dare not<lb/> set up our feeble judgment.  Dear Brethren&#33;<lb/>  Will the words of that illustrious preceptor of antiquity be heeded<lb/> by the present generation&#63;  The law to which I have referred&#44;<lb/> does not concern us now has become absolute been rendered imperative through our dispersion.  We have rehearsed it this Sabbath<lb/> simply as a memorial of what our fathers practised in the<lb/> patriarchal land&#44; when Passover approached.  Anxious<lb/> to offer the paschal&#45;lamb on the prescribed season day&#44; they<lb/> put in operation had recourse to the ordinance of the red&#45;heifer&#44; enabling<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>the ceremonies attending the executor of that statutes&#44;<lb/> all to participate in the national celebration.  The books of our traditions contain a minute account of and through In later times the<lb/> origin and object of that statute became in later times thereof have engaged the deep study the deep<lb/> study attention of our commentators&#44; and they endeavoured to explain<lb/> the same agreeably to human reason&#44; but we of this age being not bound to object exempt from its observance may<lb/> not feel sufficiently interested in listening to their learned elucidations.<lb/>  Therefore I forbear speaking on the subject exegetically.<lb/>  But there are statutes still in force&#44; which ought to exhibit arrest our<lb/> thoughts&#44; and to which the pulpit ought to allude&#44; to secure their<lb/> full attention that we perform them with exactness<lb/> exact performance.  Among our religious ceremonies&#44; we may reckon as very important those attending the great<lb/> I generally allude to the ordinance of unleaven that connected with<lb/> statutes not above but consonant with our reason&#44; statutes of the highest importance&#44; easily<lb/> stand confessedly in the front rank<lb/> the festival which we will soon solemnize comprehended because founded on irrefutably historical facts.  But noticing the<lb/> loose manner in which the commemorative bread of the season<lb/> is prepared&#44; and the heedlessness recklessness of some Israelites in fitting<lb/> their habitations for the rigid observance of our ensuing holiday&#44; one<lb/> might be led to think that the explicit words of Holy<lb/> Writ require a nevertheless recital and an explanation.  What I see<lb/> and hear must be the effect of an error which has taken hold<lb/> of the mind of my coreligionists.  Some of They appear to think labor<lb/> imagine under the misapprehension that provided we ourselves do not transgress&#44; we<lb/> may wince at the irregularities committed by those we<lb/> employ.  This unwelcome fact can be discovered in<lb/> visiting establishments&#44; where the bread for the Passover<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>is made and stored&#44; and it will be traceable<lb/> in dwellings where the domestics are allowed every lati&#45;<lb/>&#45;tude.  In both cases instances those upon whom it is incumbent<lb/> to direct and supervise set aside the plain ordinance<lb/> of the Bible&#59; incurring thus the severe penalty specified<lb/> in the text.  For time has not abrogated the injunction<lb/> of guarding against the admission of any leaven in our<lb/> borders&#44; and the admixture of any ferment in our food.  It is obligatory now as when first given by the<lb/> Deity.  And it would indeed be a lamentable circumstance&#44;<lb/> if even that which has hitherto survived the onslaught<lb/> of miscalled progressive ideas&#44; were also to <sic>yeild</sic> to the evil<lb/> spirit of innovation.  If the Matz&#225; around which so many<lb/> dear associations cluster&#44; were regarded as a thing of the<lb/> past&#44; and the slight privations of the Passover be replaced<lb/> by the prohibited dainties of a luxurious table.  But I address<lb/> consistent Israelites&#44; and trust that the bear mention of the<lb/> <sic>offence</sic>&#45;&#45;perhaps unintentional&#45;&#45;may bring will effect the correction&#59; so that<lb/> we all&#44; in the language of our Haftorah&#44; may walk in the<lb/> statutes of God&#44; and keep His behests.  Oh&#33; may He sprinkle<lb/> upon us pure waters that we may be cleansed of all our imperfections&#44;<lb/> and be imbued with a new heart and a new spirit binding us<lb/> to our Legislator gratefully&#44; and to our people fraternally.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>&#40;This lecture was considerably lengthened in delivering it&#44; and<lb/> it concluded with an appropriate prayer&#44; elicited by there being a<lb/> number of sick and dead in the Congregation&#41;.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
