<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF5_4</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_4_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_4_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_4_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_4_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_4_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_4_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_4_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_4_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_4_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_4_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_4_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_4_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For Sabbath Nahamin<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>It is not surprising&#45;&#45;though it may be painful&#45;&#45;<lb/> that those of our brethren who never fell the iron hand<lb/> of oppression&#44; look with indifference upon the anniversary<lb/> of our national dispersion.  But what must needs excite amaze&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment is to hear Israelites assert that the lamentations<lb/> uttered on the 9th of Ab&#44; represent the feelings experienced<lb/> only during ages long since buried in oblivion.  For&#44; then<lb/>&#45;&#45;as one of our poets writes&#45;&#45;the name of Jew was a turn<lb/> of opprobrium &#91;Hebrew&#93; but now that it commands universal<lb/> respect&#44; now that the sun of freedom has very nigh<lb/> reached its meridian&#44; and the exiles of Judea can bask<lb/> thereon&#44; those elegies have lost their significance.<lb/>  They should cease to be rehearsed in this century of<lb/> equality and fraternity.  A bright picture&#33;  How<lb/> beautiful all its lineaments&#59; how grateful to the<lb/> eye of the beholder is the genial smile resting on its visage&#33;<lb/>  But as I contemplate it&#44; a strange scene presents it&#45;<lb/>&#45;self to my views.  The habitable globe sinks shrinks into<lb/> a narrow compass.  What&#44; are all geographers&#44; his&#45;<lb/>torians and travelers mere visionaries&#63;  Does not the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>world comprehend the vast area they have described&#63;<lb/>  Is the space covered by the American republic of the North<lb/> America&#44; the spot apportioned by the Creator Deity for the habita&#45; dwelling<lb/>&#45;tion of all man&#63;  For in vain do I look further for a<lb/> clime where no line of separation was drawn between the trails are exhibited which truly distinguish the beings creatures made after the image<lb/> the children of the same God of God&#44; from irrational animals&#44; are exhibited where goodness and wisdom afford everyone ample scope for the pursuit of happiness&#59; where religion is not incestuously allied with state.  I discover not elsewhere<lb/> the beaming light which is said to have arisen&#44; and<lb/> scattered away the mist of prejudice.  No&#44; the murky<lb/> clouds are still lowering upon the heads of the children<lb/> of my people.  Scorn and persecution is yet the lot of<lb/> the dispersed of Judah&#44; throughout the largest portion of<lb/> the earth.  Have you&#44; my hearers&#33; ever<lb/> heard of a land afar off&#44;&#44; laying in the south western coast&#44;<lb/> of Asia&#63;  It has been called &#34;Arabia the happy&#44;&#34; but those<lb/> who sorrow for Israel will fittingly style it &#34;Arabia the<lb/> abode of wretchedness.&#34;  Shut up from the rest of<lb/> the inhabitants&#44; in almost prison cells&#44; compelled to<lb/> wear a badge of reproach&#44; robbed with impunity&#44; vexed<lb/> and tormented&#44; myriads of our brethren lead there an<lb/> existence which is alas&#33; literally <sic>fulfils</sic> of the woeful calamities<lb/> predicted to those whose sins would lead them to captivity.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Thy life shall hang<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>in doubt before thee&#44; thou shalt be in dread night<lb/> and day&#44; and have no assurance of thy life&#34;.<lb/></p>  
            <p>Does a Jew&#44; meeting a Mussulman&#44; omit to pay him obeisance&#63;<lb/>  Insults and stripes punish the offender.  Does he bow<lb/> before the son of Ishmael&#63;  He is haughtily asked&#44; how<lb/> dares &#40;a &#91;&#63;&#93;&#41; an infidel look upon a believer in Mohammed&#63;<lb/>  Is he industrious&#63;  He must have accumulated a substance&#44;<lb/> which will gratify the rapacity of irresponsible officials.<lb/>  The fearful consequences of being esteemed wealthy&#44; deny<lb/> the Hebrew of Arabia all every comforts.  To save himself<lb/> and those near and dear to his heart from dire more fierce persecution&#44;<lb/> he lets his wearing apparel&#59; his whole appearance<lb/> denote the in condition of lowliness. of his condition.  But no human<lb/> degradation can equal that which a recently book of<lb/> travels describes recently published&#44; describes.  To supply the Moslems<lb/> with the means of heating their bath&#45;houses&#44; each of the<lb/> existing congregations must forcibly appoint certain<lb/> men from their midst&#44; that may gather the necessary<lb/> fuel.  I will not offend your ears&#44; and desecrate this hal&#45;<lb/>&#45;lowed spot by naming the materials employed for that purpose.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Any slight acquaintance with Asiatic habits will<lb/> tell it.  He that who witnessed that state of crushing<lb/> abjection writes.  &#34;At the sight of the oppression practised<lb/> in this land&#44; my whole being thrilled with horror.<lb/>  I have often seen Hebrews suffer hardships and distress&#44; but<lb/> what they endure in other countries&#44; is the enjoyment<lb/> of privileges peace&#44; when compared to the tribulations borne<lb/> in these benighted regions.  For here only is a Jew the<lb/> butt of you universal contempt&#33;  Here only he is valued much less than esteemed below the grade of the beast of the field.  Among these Satanic<lb/> tribes&#44; is he the object of constant plunder and savage<lb/> violence.&#34;  Could you&#44; my hearers&#33; betake<lb/> yourselves &#91;&#63;&#93; once to the synagogues in2 the capital<lb/> of Yemen upon1 the 9th of Ab&#44; you would then realize<lb/> the axiom of our Rabbins that &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;The generation that has not seen<lb/> the rebuilding of the Temple&#44; may consider it was has seen its<lb/> destruction&#34;.  Your tears would then blend with those which<lb/> bedew the countenance of young and old.  The laments<lb/> which pierced the sky&#44; would issue even from the recesses of<lb/> your hearts.  Forgetful of self&#44; you would then yearn for<lb/> the millions of your afflicted brethren&#44; and a prayer for the restoration<lb/> of Israel to national freedom and independence would burst from your lips.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>The same object should be compassed by the observance<lb/> of the sad day just passed.  When we deny ourselves food&#44;<lb/> and&#44; sitting low&#44; recite the tale of horrors recorded delineated by our<lb/> poets&#44; we should be uplifted from our narrow surroundings&#44;<lb/> to look with pity on our distant fellow&#45;believers&#44; who<lb/> suffer constant martyrdom for the sake of their religious<lb/> convictions.  We should feel&#44; on the 9th of Ab feel that to<lb/> spend that night and that day as others are spent&#44; is unjewish<lb/> and unbrotherly&#44; that to refuse beseeching the Lord for a national<lb/> return to Palestine of the exiles to the patriarchal land&#44; is to wish for the continuance of the scourge <lb/>that weights our race down to the earth&#44; for the <sic>triump</sic> of<lb/> wickedness&#44; and the persecution of innocence.  God will<lb/> in His own time bring to pass the joyous predictions of His<lb/> inspired servants.  The people who have drunk to the<lb/> cup of bitterness to the dregs&#44; will yet raise the cup of salvation brimful within<lb/> the gates of Jerusalem but the fatal day on which the Roman eagle spread its<lb/> unholy wings&#44; over the holiest of holies&#44; should continue be remembered<lb/> by every Jew with fasting and lamentations&#44; until the Shekinah and<lb/> the Cherubim shall hover again above the mercy&#45;seat<lb/> in the Palestinian Temple &#38; the scattered flock are regathered anew to their fold.  We&#44; the happiest of all the<lb/> outcasts of Judea&#44; may not&#44; undividedly as a body&#44; wish to exchange our<lb/> present abode even for that&#44; which was celestially given as our peculiar heritage.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Nor are we demanded so to do.  But the community of<lb/> faith&#44; the community of spiritual interests we have that bind us with<lb/> with the rest of the Hebrew family&#44; should prompt us<lb/> ever to pray ardently for the dawning of the Messianic<lb/> era.  For then&#44; Israel shall see evil no more.<lb/>  Thus sayeth the Lord&#44; &#34;Behold at that time I will undo<lb/> all that afflict thee&#44; and I will save her that holleth&#44;<lb/> and gather her that was driven out&#44; and I will get them<lb/> praise and fame in every land&#44; where they have been put<lb/> to shame.&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  This hope resting on a<lb/> Divine promise&#44; steels the heart&#44; and mitigates the sufferings of<lb/> millions of our unhappy coreligionists.  So that the approaching<lb/> of the Sabbath which succeeds the fast of Ab&#44; and on which the consolatory<lb/> words of Isaiah are rehearsed&#44; is hailed by them with more than ordinary delight.<lb/>  They rejoice when they hear the message of the Lord from the herald of happy tidings &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> My young friend Bar Mitzvah.  By a coincidence which<lb/> I dare not call fortuitous&#44; your birth&#45;day corresponds with<lb/> that on which the remnant of the captivity of Zion weep bewail<lb/> over the destruction of the house of God.  Who more<lb/> than the descendants of Aaron&#44; ought to grieve over that<lb/> catastrophe&#63;  Theirs was the privilege to minister at the sanctuary and<lb/> to teach&#44; to propitiate the Deity and make atonement for sin&#59; and<lb/> you are numbered among the members of that household.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>The greater the loss sustained the stronger must be our the<lb/> endeavours to recover it.  Suffer Permit not therefore the spirit of apathy<lb/> now prevailing&#44; to obliterate from your memory the events which<lb/> deprived the priests of the exercise of their high functions.<lb/>  But the let each on the contrary&#44; each throbbings of your breast be a prayer for the welfare<lb/> of Jerusalem&#44; a supplication for the redemption of her enslaved<lb/> children.  Love with intensity of feelings this country of<lb/> our adoption.  A Jew should bless every stone thereof&#44; and<lb/> value prize her dust&#59; but forget not that country land where the father of<lb/> our race first raised an altar to the M universal everlasting God&#59;<lb/> and whence a pure religion was disseminated. throughout  Entreat the<lb/> the world Almighty that the time may soon arise not long be delayed&#44; when she will be<lb/> put off the garments of her mourning&#44; and array herself in<lb/> a glorious apparel.  Your petition may be answered with favor<lb/> as that of your sacerdotal predecessors before the sacred oracle&#59;<lb/> for&#44; if the hour of your nativity was that of our national dissolu&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion&#44; that upon which you f avowed your intention to remain<lb/> a faithful Israelite&#44; was the Sabbath of consolation&#44; the forerunner&#44; we trust&#44; of our deliverance.  Oh<lb/> may this act of your devotion to Judaism be accepted as a propitiatory<lb/> offering.  May it cancel trespasses&#44; and bring salvation.<lb/>  May we count from this auspicious Sabbath Nahamin&#44; the<lb/> beginning of a happier life to all who bear contumely and<lb/> oppression for the sake of <sic>of</sic> the &#91;&#63;&#93; Israel&#39;s God.  our O our Redeemer&#44; and our shield&#44;<lb/> &#34;save Thy people&#44; bless Thy inheritance&#44; feed them&#44; &#38; exalt them again &#38; thence forevermore.&#34;<lb/>  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
