<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF11_8</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1897-03" source="" attested="yes">March 1897</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_8_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_8_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_8_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_8_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_8_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_8_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_8_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_8_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_8_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_8_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_8_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_8_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. Fifth St.<lb/></p>
            <p>Philadelphia&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>76<lb/></p>
            <p>March 97<lb/></p>
            <p>On Suicides among Jews<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Whether the people who lived before the flood&#44; fed<lb/> on slaughtered animals&#44; is a question which historians<lb/> have left open.  Writers&#39; who incline to think that in<lb/> the primitive ages&#44; human beings derived their nourish&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment largely from cattle and fowl&#44; like in our own days&#44; point<lb/> to our organism as a proof.  They contend that the teeth<lb/> in their varied shape indicate a capacity to use flesh<lb/> as nutriment&#45;&#45;nature having created nothing without<lb/> a wise purpose.  Others&#44; who dispute the theory&#44; cite<lb/> in their support the words of the Bible&#44; for we read<lb/> that Noah was told&#44; &#34;As the green herb  I have given<lb/> you all&#34;&#45;&#45;which sentence some Talmudists explain so&#58;<lb/> In the same manner as Adam and his immediate<lb/> descendants were permitted vegetables and fruits&#44; do now&#44;<lb/>&#45;&#45;since the deluge has occasioned a change that enfeebled<lb/> human bodies nature&#44; you may partake of every thing.<lb/>  I shall not attempt to set the question at rest to the general satisfaction<lb/> nor does it concern us intimately.  I simply wish<lb/> to show that both in his silence and in his command&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>the inspired author of the book of Genesis&#44; gives<lb/> us reasons to infer that the wanton shedding of<lb/> blood&#44; even of irrational beasts&#44; did not meet with his<lb/> encouragement.  Let the Pentateuch be attentively<lb/> read&#44; and the thoughtful will have no difficulty in<lb/> discovering the almost aversion of Moses to an indul&#45;<lb/>&#45;gence in the flesh pot&#44; necessitating the spilling of blood.  So that the Rabbis correctly<lb/> quoting Deuteronomy call it &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; a craving which could no longer be<lb/> forbidden in later times&#44; but which did not agree with<lb/> the prophet&#39;s ideas.  Mark again how considerate was<lb/> he in his directions.  Having admitted that Noah<lb/> could feed on all things&#44; he says&#58; &#34;but flesh while<lb/> the blood&#44; which is its vitality&#44; remains in it&#44; you shall<lb/> not eat&#59;&#34; that is&#44; you shall not cruelly cut a limb<lb/> or a portion of a limb&#44; or the least part of a live animal<lb/> and gratify your appetites&#45;&#45;a practice not rare among<lb/> the Bedouins of the desert&#44; when on a distant journey&#44;<lb/> but abhorred by the Sages who have proclaimed<lb/> it a sing against religion&#44; to hurt irrational crea&#45;<lb/>&#45;tures.  &#91;Hebrew&#93; and the abused Rabbi who have moreover formula&#45;<lb/>&#45;ted admirable regulations to ease the death of beasts&#44;<lb/> and to draw therefrom all vital blood that we ourselves become<lb/> not animalised.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Now&#44; so far we have noticed the rules of humanity<lb/> towards beings inferior to our nature.  Was the Bible<lb/> silent about practising an act of cruelty against our&#45;<lb/>&#45;selves&#63;  I consult tradition&#44; and it tells me that what<lb/> we read in the same section of Genesis&#58; &#34;Surely your blood of your lives will I require&#44;&#34; is<lb/> an intimation of God&#39;s displeasure exhibited in the endless hereafter at self&#45;<lb/>murder.  What a contrast with the notions of<lb/> heathens&#44; who deemed it nobler in man to put an snap short<lb/> end to existence&#44; rather sooner than hear the ills that flesh is<lb/> heir to.  A Brutus A Cato demanding a sword to stab himself&#44; &#38; the exclaiming &#34;Now I am free&#44;&#34; or a Brutus falling upon his sword and crying&#58;<lb/> &#34;O virtue&#44; thou empty name&#59; I have <sic>worshipped</sic> thee as<lb/> as a god&#44; but thou art only a slave of fortune&#44;&#34; a Cato and a Brutus&#44;<lb/> would not have won the laurel and plaudits of posterity among<lb/> Hebrews.  Life is looked upon by us as a Divine trust to be surrendered solely at the will of the heavenly giver.  Through the whole range of Biblical<lb/> history&#44; covering a period of upwards of three thou&#45;<lb/>&#45;sand years&#44; only three instances of actual suicides are<lb/> recorded.  Saul could scarcely be held responsible<lb/> for his self&#45;destruction.  Crazed by fear&#44; long a<lb/> victim of to an unconquerable depression of spirits&#44; he<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>deserves our pity commiseration instead of our censure for having<lb/> pierced his body through.  The Talmudists&#44; so rigid<lb/> in their judgment against a &#91;Hebrew&#93; one<lb/> who deliberately does away with himself&#44; apologize<lb/> for the unfortunate king&#44; who dreaded to be taken<lb/> alive and made a mockery of by his inveterate enemies.<lb/>  Saul&#39;s &#91;&#63;&#93; hearer&#44; following his master&#39;s terrible<lb/> example&#44; I interpret as a pardonable token of devo&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion to an unfortunate military chief and king. Sovereign Ruler.<lb/>  The third case in our Bible&#44; is presented in the cha&#45;<lb/>&#45;racter of a recreant&#44; who sided with a rebellious son<lb/> against his royal parent.  Ahithophel had<lb/> enjoyed David&#39;s perfect confidence.  The Rabbis<lb/> assert that concerning him&#44; the shepherd psalmist<lb/> sang&#58; &#34;Thou wast a man my equal&#44; my guide and<lb/> my friend.  We took sweet counsel together and walked<lb/> to the house of God amidst a multitude.&#34;  But<lb/> Ahithophel treasonably espoused the cause of Absalom<lb/> in his resolve atrocious attempt to dethrone and kill his father.  When<lb/> the plan which the wicked counsellor had deeply laid was<lb/> set aside&#44; and the advise of one secretly favoring David<lb/> was accepted&#44; Ahithophel foreseeing the breaking up<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>of the conspiracy and his own ignominious end&#44; hast&#45;<lb/>&#45;ened home and hanged himself.  I cannot recall<lb/> any other instance of suicide among Hebrews in Holy Writ.  Was<lb/> it cowardice that prevented &#34;to take arms against a sea<lb/> of troubles&#44;&#34; or was it an overweening attachment to<lb/> worldly pleasures&#44; or incapacity to set a higher<lb/> value or virtue than on life&#63;  Ignorant of stirring<lb/> episodes in our history annals must he be&#44; who advances<lb/> those charges.  Let him read of men and women<lb/> of Israel girded with strength&#44; ready to rush into<lb/> the embrace of death rather than sacrifice principles.<lb/>  I have no reference now to religious martyrs or patrio&#45;<lb/>&#45;tic <sic>heros</sic> that every country and creed produced.  I allude<lb/> to a voluntary surrendering of existence&#44; when faced by<lb/> temptations inevitable.  Why did the fair wife of Moses<lb/> of Cordova&#44;&#45;&#45;captured by pirates&#45;&#45;&#44; plunge into the raging sea&#63;<lb/>  Because she chose to be a prey to the waves rather<lb/> than to the licentious cravings of her captor.  Why<lb/> did the scion of the famous stock of Ashin in<lb/> Toledo kill himself&#44; to set his f wife and family<lb/> a similar example&#63;  Because he preferred the grave<lb/> to disgrace and apostasy.  Aye&#58; honor<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>was prized above life by the true in Israel&#59; yet<lb/> they did not dare cut off asunder the threads of their earthly<lb/> existence in order to loosen let go the burden of human trials go off.<lb/></p>
            <p>How fearfully we have degenerated&#44; a glance at<lb/> the daily journals will show.  With shame<lb/> I acknowledge that suicides among Hebrews<lb/> are&#44; in proportion&#44; as frequent as among those<lb/> not born in our faith.  Congregational rules to<lb/> denying such the usual obsequies and burial are not<lb/> a the means to determent to from the rash deed&#44; and I myself&#44;<lb/> have in recent years set laid aside in regulation which<lb/> serves only to intensify grief&#44; without hinder&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing a sinful act.  Sometime ago a youth<lb/> who appeared anxious to learn&#44; and whose laud&#45;<lb/>&#45;able disposition I tried to encourage by procuring<lb/> for him free admission to the lectures at the rooms<lb/> of the Young Man&#39;s Hebrew Association&#44; and the<lb/> use of the library&#44; seized with morbid feelings&#44; occa&#45;<lb/>&#45;sioned perhaps by his humble parentage and sur&#45;<lb/>&#45;roundings&#44; instead of summoning his inner powers<lb/> and rising above his lowliness&#44; he allowed morose&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness to master his energies and lead him to self&#45;murder.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Very shortly after a man widely learned for his<lb/> age&#44; and who had filled the office of Rabbi preacher&#44;<lb/> and aspired to the same position in our city&#44; fired at his<lb/> head after leaving sought in vain a livelihood as a<lb/> deserter to his faith creed and a perjurer.  Since then in&#45;<lb/>&#45;stances have multiplied&#44; and none created so great a<lb/> stir as the latest&#44; for&#44; a voluntary suicide&#44; involved an<lb/> involuntary one.  Humiliating in the extreme we must<lb/> consider the circumstance&#44; when we bear in mind that the<lb/> main actor in the tragedy was ostensibly generally believed to be qualifying<lb/> himself as a leader in the path of righteousness&#44; for&#44; to<lb/> a college which claims to train youths to the Jewish<lb/> Rabbinate&#44; he was admitted on strong recommendations&#44; unconditionally if you wish as now apologetically alleged&#44; or on probation. as was claimed.  What supervision was kept over that student&#44; may<lb/> be clearly inferred form the fact that notwithstanding<lb/> certain of his irregular practices of his own&#44; ill&#45;agreeing with the Mosaic<lb/> injunctions which forbid seeking to dive into matters wi&#45;<lb/>&#45;sely hidden form human minds comprehension&#44; the Philadelphia<lb/> youth was held by the hand twice accepted as a scholar and permitted to freely<lb/> associate with the guileless over whom he exercised a fatal<lb/> influence.  None will ever be able to tell the<lb/> subtle working&#44; which resulted in a double self&#45;murder.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>My pity goes principally with the innocent victim<lb/> of a companion&#44; who confessedly preferred to the simple<lb/> but soul&#45;elevating literature of his people with which he<lb/> was in duty bound to become familiar&#44; a German<lb/> philosophy&#44; which sees in the government of the<lb/> world&#44; a blind Will.  The mind that should have<lb/> been lifted on high by the teachings of Holy Writ&#59;<lb/> widened by the maxims of our moralists&#44; drawn lovingly<lb/> towards all creatures as the objects of God&#39;s providential<lb/> care&#44; became engulphed in the theories of a Schopen&#45;<lb/>&#45;hauer breeding discontent and malevolence&#44; and in the<lb/> vagaries of a Mesmer and an awfully dangerous hypnotism.<lb/>  I will not be guilty of rash accusations.  I will not as&#45;<lb/>&#45;cribe to assign to the fault of the trustees of the Union College the cause<lb/> of the terrible appalling event.  but I am of opinion that They may have depended on the vigilance of<lb/> the President for should have guarded against it by<lb/> a close inspection of the habits of his misled and mis&#45;<lb/>&#45;leading pupil.  Rather than grow indignant be&#45;<lb/>&#45;cause the latter asked to be cremated&#44; and peremptorily com&#45;<lb/>&#45;mand that the body be removed from the school<lb/> room to which it had been taken&#44; the Dr main professor should<lb/> have early set about to enforce among those sitting at<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>his feet the golden rule of Ben Sera.  &#34;Search not<lb/> what is too high above thee&#44; neither what is too<lb/> deep for thee&#59; seek to understand what is allowed<lb/> unto thee.  Let not thy heart keep away from that<lb/> which is concealed&#44; do not look after events and<lb/> their causes too profound&#44; enough has been shown thee.&#34;<lb/>  If the studies and their imparting had carried out<lb/> that wholesome aphorism&#44; we would hear more of<lb/> Judaism in the pulpits occupied by the graduates of<lb/> the West and less of Darwinism&#44; more of man&#39;s amenableness to an Omnipotent Judge&#44; and less of evolutionary theories.  If the lessons were Jewish intended for Jews&#44; in we would be told more of our Joshua<lb/> son of Perachia&#44; than of Jesus son of Joseph&#44; more<lb/> of Rabbi Gamliel than of Paul of Tarsus.  Above all ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;ample better than the tuition would prove a fence<lb/> against subversive ideas&#44; and guard against such<lb/> appalling shocking misfortunes as the unhappy occurrence<lb/> which must have cast a gloom on the institution<lb/> and humiliated its professors.  Twice I find in<lb/> the book of Proverbs the following maxim&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;The prudent man foresees<lb/> the evil and hides himself&#44; but the simple passes<lb/> and they are punished.&#34;</p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
