<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Voorsanger, Jacob</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx4FF1_29</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Voorsanger, Jacob</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Morais, Sabato</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Houston, TX</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1886-04" source="" attested="yes">22 April 1886</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx4ff1_29_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx4ff1_29_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx4ff1_29_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx4ff1_29_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx4ff1_29_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx4ff1_29_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx4ff1_29_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx4ff1_29_4v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>The Sabbath Visitor&#44;<lb/>
                Cincinnati&#44; Ohio.<lb/>
                Jacob Voorsanger&#44; Editor.<lb/></p>
            <p>Houston&#44; Texas&#44; April 22&#91;&#44;&#93; 1886<lb/></p>
            <p>Rev S. Morais<lb/></p>
            <p>My dear Sir<lb/></p>
            <p>In accordance with the promise expressed in my<lb/> last letter I write you freely in reply to your valued favor of April 7.<lb/></p>
            <p>1.	 I must repeat the assertion I am not as black as I am painted. To be sure&#44;<lb/> it is the easiest thing&#44; especially on the part of the zealots of whom we have too many<lb/> to misrepresent both motives&#44; and the results flowing therefrom&#44; I am not disposed<lb/> to shield myself be &#91;y&#93; hind a hypocritical denial of the facts&#44; or some glittering mean<lb/>ingless sophistries. All I want of you&#44; if you have finished this letter is to judge<lb/> me upon the face of the statements therein contained and to still believe that a<lb/> fervent love of and for Judaism&#44; a keen anxiety to uphold the banner of the<lb/>Thora are still  the motives that guide my conduct. The first intimation you<lb/> received of my having &#34;made common cause with the radicals&#34; was doubt&#45;<lb/>lessly when I  publicly defended the action of my conference in endorsing the<lb/> Pittsburg platform. Am I right&#63; To explain my defense you must know<lb/> the minor&#91;&#63;&#93; history of the Southern endorsement. Believe me&#44; never have I be&#45;<lb/>held more earnestness than in our December conference. The day before the<lb/> meeting the Ex. Comm. heard Mr. Guttheim&#39;s &#94; Annual report&#44; in which there was<lb/> an unqualified endorsement of Pittsburg. A long and earnest discussion<lb/> took place. For my part&#44; I bitterly upbraided the organizers of the<del>is</del><lb/> Pittsburg movement&#44; and held&#44; as I did subsequently&#44; that the policy<lb/> of the gathering was unwise and inexpedient&#44; and that the platform<lb/> as a basis of religious belief was unavailable&#44; because too philosophically<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="2"/>
            <p>and ambiguously expressed. Still&#44; there were the three fundamental doctr&#45;<lb/>ines of Aebo&#91;&#63;&#93;&#44; &#91;Hebrew&#93; and &#91;Hebrew&#93; clearly expressed&#44; and in<lb/> so far I also subscribed. But I held that the wisest policy would be to ignore<lb/> the Pittsburg conference. Mr. Guttheim&#44; a man who&#44; next to you has  ever my<lb/> complete esteem and  veneration claimed&#44; I think justly&#44; that an ignoring of<lb/> the Pittsburg conference<lb/> would be a black insult&#44; and imply a want of policy<lb/> on our part<del>ly</del>. The country was just ringing with the affair&#44; the South looked<lb/> to their assembled ministers for guidance in the matter&#44; and we <hi rend="underline">must</hi> express<lb/> an opinion favorable or otherwise. The discussion lasted till deep in the<lb/> night&#44; Leucht&#44; Berkowitz &#40;of the college&#41; and myself&#44; holding the one opinion&#44;<lb/> Mr Guttheim and Hecht the other. We finally agreed that the President&#39;s<lb/> report should be so modified as to embody his consent to the proposition&#44;<lb/> that the Southern Conference allowed no one to control their action as<lb/> regards &#91;Hebrew&#93;  or &#91;Hebrew&#93;. If you will look at the report&#44; which I sent you<lb/> you will find it so expressed. Subsequently I was on the committee to report<lb/> upon the suggestions embodied in the president&#39;s report&#44; and if you will<lb/>look at the Committee report&#44; the past alluding to the Pittsburg con&#45;<lb/>ference I think you will discover my style. The task before us was either<lb/> to reject or <del>to</del> endorse the P. platform&#44; and conscientiously I could<lb/> not oppose the platform if my simples&#91;&#63;&#93;&#44; concerning &#91;Hebrew&#93; were satisfied.<lb/> The discussions in conference were long&#44; earnest but more heated&#44; and<lb/> there was a unanimity as regards the platform yet a tinge of<lb/> conservatism in the unanimous&#45;&#45;but 2&#34;adoption of the com&#45;<lb/>mittee&#39;s clause&#44; that &#91;Hebrew&#93; and &#91;Hebrew&#93; were as binding now as they ever<lb/> were. To show you how men may be misinterpreted&#58;When the two<lb/> who were against adopting this clause demanded an opinion on the<lb/> subject<del>ion</del> of Mr Guttheim &#40; the chair&#91;<lb/> insered by author&#93; my venerable friend said that<lb/> he could not express an opinion&#44; but were he on the floor he would<lb/> vote for the committees report&#33; Thus the Pittsburg platform found<lb/> its way in our conference&#44; with the reservation mentioned&#44; and having<lb/> committed  myself&#44; I felt obliged to defend our actions in the Be&#91;...&#93;<lb/> especially when the Record&#34;with that wonderful logic for which chu&#91;&#63;&#93;&#45;<lb/>ma&#91;&#63;&#93; is celebrated&#45;&#45;&#91;Hebrew&#93;&#45;&#45;proved that we had condemned the Pittsburgers&#33; So much for this.<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="3"/>
            <p>The Sabbath Visitor&#44;<lb/>
                Cincinnati&#44; Ohio.<lb/>
                Jacob Voorsanger&#44; Editor.<lb/></p>
            <p>2. But&#44; this is not all I have to say&#44; and since I accord you full authority<lb/> to be my judge&#44; you must know all. We have corresponded for years&#44; and<lb/> it has never been a secret to you that I am always struggling&#44; always<lb/> thinking&#44; always praying to find the right way. Had I remained at home I might<lb/> have been a good&#44; pious&#44; unquestioning semi&#45;Hasid&#44; or else a performing <lb/> sceptic as I have known many a Talmudist to be. But I came to cast my lot with<lb/> my brethren in America&#44; I began to move in an atmosphere strange to me<lb/> at first; and being a mere youth&#44; yet shrewd enough to take an occasional<lb/> peep&#91;&#63;&#93; in the future&#44; I perfected my German studies and auto&#45;didactically<lb/> began to read that immense&#44; wonderful &#91;&#63;&#93; of German&#45;Jewish literature&#44; that<lb/> fairly equals that of our Spanish sages. My dear friend&#44; need I tell you that<lb/> such reading must necessarily change youthful convictions&#63; Yet for<lb/> along time I could hardly tell wherein I had changed. The conservatism<lb/> of my native home was too strong an armor&#44; nor has it yet lost its force.<lb/> Come&#44; let us compare ideas&#44; and you shall judge whether I <del>too</del> am a<lb/> &#34;radical&#34; though I am in this congregation&#44; as you have been told. I have<lb/> read Kuenen&#91;&#63;&#93; and Willhausen&#91;&#63;&#93; and Noldeke&#91;&#63;&#93; and Robertson Smith&#44; and<lb/> a &#91;&#63;&#93; of other authors. If I tell you that my faith is strong in<lb/> these truths&#44; of which  Albo says correctly&#44; they are the pillars of Juda&#45;<lb/>ism&#44; and our religion stands or falls with them&#44; can I not allow<lb/> myself the latitude of a scholar&#63; You have never  met a scoffing<lb/> word in any of my writings. In my Sabbath School lessons I have ever<lb/> been conservative&#44; assuming the standpoint of revelation&#44; treating every<lb/> fact of history as traditionally received. But that my private opinions tend<lb/> in different directions I do not deny&#44; nor am I disposed to gloss over<lb/> my scepticism. Remember&#44; I am in no sceptic on the  cardinal points of<lb/> Judaism. These are as firm in my mind as the foundations of<lb/> mountains. But is a belief in the Thorah being of Moses a &#34;cardinal<lb/> doctrine of Judaism&#34;&#63;  Maimonides has indeed&#91;Hebrew&#93;  <lb/> and also &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; and do either of these doctrines either<lb/> prove that Moses wrote the whole Thora&#44; or that his having written<lb/> it is a continual point of Judaism&#63; I am somewhat surprised at <lb/> the tenacity with which you hold this one point as cardinal. Our Thora<lb/> in the Thorath Moshe&#44; but must it be in its entirety&#63; Noldeke&#91;&#63;&#93; gives<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="4"/>
            <p>proof positive&#44; that at keast two points of the  Zend&#45;Avesta&#91;&#63;&#93; is written<lb/> in a language&#44; with which Zorvaster&#91;&#63;&#93; was unacquainted. Yet it is the Zoro&#45;<lb/>astrian book I f I believe that Deuteronomy is older than Exodus&#44; and<lb/> that Genesis is of more recent origin than either&#44; can I not be firm<lb/> nevertheless in my belief that the divine wisdom is laid down in these<lb/> books&#63; And supposing I have serious doubts as to the &#94;veracity if supernatural&#45;<lb/>ism&#44; am I an isolated case&#63; Did or diid not Saadjah Ea&#91;&#63;&#93;<lb/> &#40;&#91;&#40;Hebrew&#93;&#41; endeavor to explain that Revelation<lb/> was the highest conception of reason&#63; Or if we speak of text critic&#45;<lb/> ism is there anything new in it&#63; What else is the greatest part<lb/> of Medrash but these text criticism&#63; To be sure&#44; it was different from<lb/>ours&#44; and I beg you to believe that I am not trying to hoodwink<lb/> you. Our criticism is destructive of the sacred character of the<lb/> scriptures&#34;but believe me again I never carry my opinions in the<lb/> Synagogue or the schools. I think of these matters largely as you think<lb/> of the Shulhan Aruka&#91;&#63;&#93;. Now&#44; in what do differ from you&#63; Possibly<lb/> in any belief that the Bible is not &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; that it is a book of<lb/> gradual developments&#44; in which  compilers have had a larger share<lb/> than Moses. But&#44; there are technical divergencies. The<lb/> main thing would be  whether we can agree upon the manner<lb/> and method of propagating our beloved religion. And these<lb/> I say boldly&#44; the conservatives do not believe a little more than<lb/> we do&#44; some of them possibly less. I do believe in God and His<lb/> revelation as embodied in and outside the Scriptures&#44; I believe<lb/> further that he rewards and punishes&#44; and that He will take<lb/> care of me when I am no more. I believe that He has<lb/> reserved a &#91;Hebrew&#93; and &#91;Hebrew&#93; for Israel  to be a &#91;Hebrew&#93;. Do you<lb/> believe more&#63; Shall we haggle over a &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#63; neither<lb/> of which doctrines  were accepted by Albo&#63; Shall we<lb/>split on the question of being &#91;Hebrew&#93; or &#91;Hebrew&#93; and lecture<lb/> one another as Ben Shesheth did the good pious Eali&#45;<lb/>papa&#63;  Now&#44; you know what kind of a radical I am&#44; I stand<lb/> squarely upon the rock of Judaism&#44; and think of the relative<lb/> doctrines as millions before me may have done. We are in<lb/> ths midst of a trife which has a good many amusing<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="5"/>
            <p>The Sabbath Visitor&#44;<lb/>
                Cincinnati&#44; Ohio.<lb/>
                Jacob Voorsanger&#44; Editor.<lb/></p>
            <p>features. If you had seem one day before yesterday &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; sitting<lb/> in mys study surrounded by these Russian peddler&#44; to whom I<lb/> read a few pages of the &#91;Hebrew&#93; in the &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; you would have thought<lb/> I was a good old Bachur&#91;&#63;&#93;. Yet&#44; because my ideas are more liberal<lb/> as regards unessentials&#44; and because my association as radical&#44;<lb/> must I need be one of those of whom it is said &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#63; I do<lb/> not say &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#33;<lb/></p>
            <p>3.You say that you hoped I would become an honor to intelligent conser&#45;<lb/>vativism. I beg you&#44; if you have still faith in me&#44; to hope so still&#44; and I will<lb/> not disappoint you. My  alliance is with the radical means that I am<lb/> seeking among them what the conservatives refuse me&#44; and that<lb/>is&#44;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; liberty of thought. You are too noble&#44; too honest to fully perceive<lb/> the plots of New York&#33; I pray you&#44; once more&#44; let me speak frankly<lb/> to you. You are my old friend&#44; and I would be unworthy of the name<lb/> if I were not to explain my standpoint to you. I am a journalist<lb/> by intuition &#44; that mean I have the leaven of this world about me. Yours are the &#91;crossed&#45;out&#91;Hebrew&#93;&#93; &#91;Hebrew&#93; and therefore you have been all<lb/> your life the &#91;Hebrew&#93;. Now&#44; what could I&#44; with my ideas for<lb/> the unification of all Jewish interests in this country&#44; do in this<lb/> singular alliance&#44; of which you are said to be the <hi rend="underline">principium</hi> <hi rend="underline">et</hi><lb/> <hi rend="underline">fons</hi>&#63; Cast about me&#44; and I find that this alliance has other<lb/> component parts. With the largest part&#44; of the Polish Hassidistic<lb/> element of New York you have as little sympathy as I have. They<lb/> will treat you&#44; upon intimate acquaintance as the German&#45;Ital&#45;<lb/>ian Rabbis Juda Menz and Joseph Kolon treated Messer Leon and<lb/> Del Medigo&#44; and as the named Rabbi of Paisa treated the<lb/> pious Capsali of Constantinople. Do you think I could conceive<lb/> of an alliance between my brave&#44; consistent old friend and the<lb/> scandal mongers of the Allen Street Beth Ham&#39;&#91;&#63;&#93; Medrash&#63; Never&#33; They are not of your kind. Their Judaism is not yours or mine. It is<lb/> Catholicism with Hebrew letters&#44; Parseeism brought over to New<lb/> York. Deduct that element. Would you train your Seminarians<lb/> to serve them&#63; And if you did&#44; do you suppose they would<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="6"/>
            <p>accept your scientifically trained Rabbis instead of their Polish Has&#45;<lb/>sidism or do you even think that you could induce a graduate to<lb/> be slowly pestered to death amongst the ritualistic Shochatim abounding<lb/> in the East End&#63; I can conceive of no lasting alliance between you and<lb/> their people&#63; They are outside of any calculation. I never forget<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;  I will serve them&#44; ameliorate their condition&#44;<lb/> anything;&#45;&#45; only as long as the influx from Russia continues<lb/> I cannot conceive the possibility of raising them to the high<lb/> intellectual status of an Italian Rabbi&#44; be he orthodox to the core&#33;<lb/></p>
            <p>Next&#44; the second element of your alliance is not to my liking. <lb/> It is composed of men who half between reform and orthodoxy. Of<lb/> these you have but a few. Jastrow and Szold&#44; representing a large <lb/> following stand back. Their position is inexplicable. They are neither<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; or &#91;Hebrew&#93;. But Dr Kohut&#34;yes I advise him as much as you<lb/> do for his learning and wonderful versatility. But he has unfurled<lb/>  his banner too soon. He broke the staff over our heads before he<lb/> was a month in this country&#44; before he had the faintest conception<lb/> of American reform. A man so hasty of judgment may be a. bookworm&#44; but not a leader. As I wrote you&#44; his position in Germany<lb/> is that of a reformer&#44; hated by the Neoorthodox&#44; whom leaders&#44; Hirsch&#91;&#63;&#93;&#44;<lb/>  Hildesheim&#91;&#63;&#93; and Lehman have long since reckoned him amongst<lb/> the irredeemable. Your third element is represented by a few<lb/> English gentlemen whose policy seems to introduce neology. I<lb/> am afraid of it. The holy Zohar&#44; the holy &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; the holy &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44;the<lb/> holy Gaon so and so&#44; this is the phra<del>s</del>seology of the neo&#45;ortho&#45;<lb/>dox and faintly echoed by their English  cousins&#44; the Messrs<lb/> Mendez&#33; You&#44; with your fine&#44; firm consistency are a reformer of<lb/> the deepest dye in the eyes of Lehman and his peers. Why&#63; Be&#45;<lb/>cause you have more than once admitted that you would not<lb/> object to a condensed ritual or an abbreviated Shulchan Aruth<lb/> on the basis of our modern wants&#33; That is a crime. In addition<lb/> I believe the Mendez&#39; are working&#44; not &#91;Hebrew&#93; but for position&#44; for<lb/> self &#45;elevation&#44; and with such men I can have no fellowship.<lb/> Call a convention of Rabbis and Ministers&#44;  place before them<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="7"/>
            <p>The Sabbath Visitor&#44;<lb/>
                Cincinnati&#44; Ohio.<lb/>
                Jacob Voorsanger&#44; Editor.<lb/></p>
            <p>your pure Judaism&#44; your lofty conceptions&#44; and I take God to witness of<lb/> any innermost conviction that you will find more adherents amongst<lb/> the reformers than amongst the Kohut&#45;Mendez&#45;Jastrow coterie&#33; <hi rend="underline">Your</hi><lb/> basis is &#91;Hebrew&#93;; their&#39;s is opposition to the west as the<lb/> basis of self&#45;elevation&#44; and if I am wrong in my opinions I hope<lb/> that God and they may forgive me. Now&#44; what else is left for me. I<lb/>  must join a party. My position is too uncertain to remain isolated. I<lb/> still believe that I shall make headway with my progressive&#44; not<lb/> aggressive idea of a conservative Judaism in America on the basis<lb/> of a complete alienation from all semblance of Hassidism&#44;<lb/>&#45;&#45;and this means the work of a lifetime; but I must have friends&#44;<lb/> in course of time followers&#44; and&#34;pardon me again&#44; my friend&#44;&#45;&#45;<lb/> either your schemes or mine&#33; Far better Abram Isaacs with his<lb/> honest idealism. He believes that the laymen will accomplish wonders.<lb/> Perhaps he is right. But this alliance of yours&#44; will it accomplish what<lb/> I am praying for all the days of my life&#44; what I have confessed to <lb/> myself with bitter mortification I am incapable of accomplishing<lb/>&#45;&#45;will it restore devotion in the households&#44; bring back the people to<lb/> the throne of the Sabbath queen&#44; fill our pews with devout<lb/> worshipers&#63; Emil Hirsch&#39;s pews are  crowded on Sunday&#44; and Fred<lb/> Mendez&#44; who permits the sale of &#91;Hebrew&#93; accompanied by organ music<lb/> has a thin guard on the Sabbath day. Can your alliance do<lb/>all this&#63; Another thing. Have the graduates of the Hebrew Union<lb/> College turned out so badly&#44; that they must be warred against&#63; The<lb/> platform of your new college is not materially different from<lb/> that of Cincinnati. You cannot have an old style &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; nor&#44; I<lb/> know well&#44; do you intend it. And if you admit science and philosophy<lb/> you forever bar the mind against believing in an infallible&#44; un&#45;<lb/>allayed&#91;&#63;&#93; and unchangeable law or tradition&#33;<lb/></p>
            <p>I must close now&#44; <del>for fe</del> lest you may think I forget that I am<lb/> merely writing a letter. To my mind&#44; radicals and conservatives<lb/> are both striving to find the proper means for restoring Israel&#39;s<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="8"/>
            <p>faith&#44; and if I am standing on the one side and you on the other&#44;<lb/> I am convinced we strive for the same object. Only do me the justice to<lb/> believe that my fealty to God and my faith has not diminished<lb/> nor am I estranged from those things to which I have ever been <lb/> passionately attached. I believe I am laboring in the interest<lb/> of intelligent conservatism though I seek&#91;&#63;&#93; for the means<lb/> amongst the radicals. Possibly after you have read this<lb/> letter this will not sound paradoxical to you. I am doing my<lb/> best for my people&#44; I labor to instruct and improve them&#44; and in<lb/> so far at least I am in the right path.<lb/></p>
            <p>Let me soon hear from you that you have read this long letter<lb/> and that my  frankness has not offended you. I would sooner<lb/> lose your favor by frankness that retain it by hypocrisy&#44;<lb/> though I know you well enough&#44; that you can both forgive frankness<lb/> and detect hypocrisy. Awaiting your answer&#44; then&#44; I am as<lb/>always<lb/></p>
            <p>Faithfully Yours<lb/>
                Jacob Voorsanger<lb/></p>
            <p>NB. My dear wife and children&#44; are&#44; thank God&#44; in their usual state of<lb/> fine health. The &#34;troubles in the nest&#34;<hi rend="underline">may</hi> have some influence on my <lb/> future. But I believe I am booked for San Francisco. Of this more in<lb/> a future letter.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
