<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF5_12</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_12_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_12_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_12_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_12_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_12_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_12_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_12_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_12_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_12_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_12_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_12_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_12_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_12_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_12_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_12_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_12_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>13 pages on 6 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Post Biblical
                55<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>In the course of my post Biblical lectures&#44; which<lb/> do not lay claim to any thing approaching com&#45;<lb/>&#45;pleteness&#44; but which are confessedly only brief sketches&#44;<lb/> I have found it necessary incidentally to introduce some points<lb/> foreign to the main subject.  In that manner&#44; I<lb/> tried to make clear what I principally wished to<lb/> elucidate.  The subject which I intend to set forth<lb/> this morning&#44; will be marked by the same character.<lb/>  We have seen Nachmanides rise nobly to the<lb/> defense of his religion and we felt grateful.  We must have admired<lb/> his indefatigableness in striving to illustrate the<lb/> the writings of Hebrew Sages&#44; and&#44; whatever opinion<lb/> we may have formed about his speculative mysticism&#44; we could but<lb/> honor the sincerity of a man&#44; who from conviction preferred the Kabbalah<lb/> to the philosophy of the Greeks and the Arabs.<lb/>  Now&#58; none can be surprised that persons who<lb/> had sat at the feet of such a master&#44; became tho&#45;<lb/>&#45;roughly imbued with the identical ideas which<lb/> he himself cherished.  Among the disciples<lb/> of the renowned Moses of Gerona&#44; no one surpassed<lb/> in mental acquirements a native of Barcelona<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>who <sic>travelled</sic> far in quest of knowledge.<lb/></p>
            <p>Solomon Ben Adereth or Rashba&#44; born in the year 1235 of the<lb/> common reckoning&#44; laid strong hold of the standard<lb/> which his preceptor had set up.  Talmud was<lb/> his delight.  The ritualistic To gain a perfect mastery<lb/> of all which it contains&#44; was his highest ambition.<lb/>  The ritualistic department of that immense work&#44;<lb/> he resolved to expound by productions&#44; relative to<lb/> dietary ordinances&#44; to the holiness of days set apart for religious convocations&#44; to the sanctity of marriages&#44; as well as to the solution<lb/> of casuisitcial questions.  But great as that<lb/> achievement assuredly was&#44; Ben Adereth aspired to attain<lb/> another which I deem still greater.  He made an effort to that effect and<lb/> partly succeeded.  Every Israelite&#44; without<lb/> possessing an intimate acquaintance with the<lb/> Talmud&#44; knows that it is not a systematically<lb/> arranged legislation&#44; where rules belonging to<lb/> the same category&#44; are so classified&#44; as to<lb/> enable the student readily to discover what<lb/> he may be in search of.  All are aware<lb/> that in the course of a discussion&#44; respecting<lb/> a certain law&#44; new topics are introduced and frequent&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly digressions are indulged in upon strange and<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>quaint notions.  These also the Barcelona Rabbi under&#45;<lb/>&#45;took also satisfactorily to explain.  Too profoundly he revered<lb/> the Sages &#44;to admit even tacitly that anything could<lb/> have emanated from them&#44; against which the human<lb/> understanding rebels.  But the task which he<lb/> assumed in that direction&#44; presented greater more serious difficulties<lb/> than he or and others who tried it&#44; could overcome.  How&#45; Still<lb/> &#45;ever&#44; in many several instances Ben Adereth labored to a purpose.<lb/>  I will cite an easy illustration of an easy sentence in<lb/> the legendary portion of the Talmud.  Rabbi Helbo<lb/> is reported to have said&#44; that whosoever offers prayers<lb/> in a regularly settled place&#44; will obtain the help of<lb/> Abraham&#39;s God&#44; and when he dies people will<lb/> lament his loss in the following language&#58; alas&#44; that<lb/> the pious and humble one&#44; among the disciples of the<lb/> founder of our the Hebrew people&#44; has gone.  In his comment&#44; Ben<lb/> Adereth remarks that it is reasonable to agree with<lb/> the Talmudist&#59; namely&#44; that by communing with the<lb/> Lord in an appointed locality and not anywhere<lb/> uphazard&#44; as spiritual advantage will be derived&#44; for<lb/> a degree of sanctity holiness will be attached to that spot&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>so that when there&#44; we may experience a reverent&#45;<lb/>&#45;ial awe.  Considering that we are standing in the presence<lb/> of a Supreme Being&#44; we will realize our own insignificance&#44;<lb/> in contrast with the almightiness of Him whom we ad&#45;<lb/>&#45;dress.  This influenced&#44; we must grow devout and<lb/> meek and deserve those appellations.  On the con&#45;<lb/>&#45;trary&#44; prayers recited wherever we may chance to<lb/> be&#44; would seem the discharge of perfunctory obli&#45;<lb/>&#45;gations&#44; very unlike the conduct of Abraham&#44; of<lb/> whome we read&#58; &#34;He rose up early in the morning to<lb/> go to the place&#44; in which he had stood before the<lb/> Lord&#34; to stand before the Lord&#44; meaning to pray with fervor.<lb/>  Now&#58; In connection with this elucidation by Solomon Ben Adereth&#44; of a legendary saying&#44; by<lb/> Moses of Gerona Solomon Ben Adereth&#44; I recall what one of his predecessors&#45;&#45;a<lb/> deep thinker and an incomparable poet&#45;&#45;wrote in the 12th<lb/> century.  Judah Hallevi in the famous Ciozari&#44; answering<lb/> his suppositious imaginary interlocutor tells us&#44; that were it not for the<lb/> spiritual associations clustering round a structure<lb/> where people congregate for religious exercises&#44; the<lb/> idea of pronouncing a building holy and believing that<lb/> the Shekinah rests thereupon and angels hover above it&#44;<lb/> might seem a species of idolatry.  The thought<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>therefore it is&#44; which imparts sanctity to us ap&#45; a place<lb/> &#45;pointed place for set apart for devotional purposes.  Coming back to Now the Barcelona<lb/> Rabbi I will say that he closely followed Nachmanides&#44; his venerated teacher&#44; in<lb/> another respects&#44; besides his evincing great fondness for Talmudism.<lb/>  He became enamored with Kabbalism&#44; and his love for<lb/> it&#44; he manifested in several of his writings. Cau&#45;<lb/>&#45;tious was&#44; indeed&#44; the wise scholar not to expose his<lb/> partiality for the mystic to the animadversion of its<lb/> opponents&#44;  but he clung to his belief that the<lb/> Kabbalah can boast of al very ancient and sacred<lb/> origin&#44; forgotten during the vicissitudes that befell our<lb/> f nation after the dispersion under the Romans.<lb/>  The views advanced by Ben Adereth&#44; are shared by<lb/> Adolphe Franck&#44; the nonaoctogenarian ex&#45;professor of phi&#45;<lb/>&#45;losophy in the Charlemagne college at Paris.  In his volume &#34;La Kabbale&#44; on<lb/> la philosophie religieuse des Hebreux&#44;&#34; the French<lb/> savant dilates upon that topic.  The curious read&#45;<lb/>&#45;er will find in the work just cited&#44; what will may<lb/> furnish him with a fund of information regarding<lb/> the disputed merits of a mysterious science&#44; which<lb/> claims to be founded on the highest authority.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>However&#44; Solomon Ben Adereth&#44; owed the wide repu&#45;<lb/>&#45;tation which he gained&#44; to his rare familiarity with<lb/> Talmud and kindred works learning&#44; more than to aught<lb/> else.  Wherever Jews had settled during the thirteenth<lb/> century&#44; the solution of theological questions was<lb/> sought at the hands of the Barcelona Rabbi.<lb/>  The queries multiplied vastly&#44; and as the answers<lb/> were sure to be satisfactory and couched in a friendly<lb/> style&#44; the kind instructor won universal admiration<lb/> and esteem.  It is easily conceived that a<lb/> far reaching renown will bring in its train to the possessor thereof un&#45;<lb/>&#45;looked for demands upon one&#39;s time and means.<lb/>  So it happened&#44; more than once&#44; with regard to Ben<lb/> Adereth.  Notable was the case of in reference to a grand&#45;son of<lb/> Maimonides.  David&#44; born in Egypt&#44; where<lb/> his immortal progenitor had honorably exercised the<lb/> medical profession&#44; stood well with the govern&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment and employed his influence to benefit his<lb/> coreligionists.  But at one time&#44; he lost cast with<lb/> the ruler&#44; who&#44; greedy of gold&#44; removed all Jews<lb/> from public offices&#44; and thus exposed them thus to<lb/> the ill&#45;will and annoyances of the low populace.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>David Ma&#239;mon&#44; who knew that only by re&#45;<lb/>&#45;plenishing the coffers of the unrighteous Sultan Prynce Prince&#44;<lb/> he himself and his brethren in faith could hope to<lb/> live unmolested&#44; turned eagerly anxiously to the Barcelona scho&#45;<lb/>&#45;lar for assistance.  He felt that rich Israelites&#44; would<lb/> not refuse a person so distinguished for learning lore Jewish lore and<lb/> piety&#44; when soliciting assistance aid&#44; in behalf of a lineal<lb/> descendant of the greatest Rabbi&#44; whom that Spain had<lb/> produced.  Nor was the expectation ill&#45;founded.<lb/>  At Toledo resided a certain Samson Ben Meir&#44; trust&#45;<lb/> worthy of Ben Adereth&#39;s confidence.  He was assigned<lb/> the charge to travel through Castile&#44; Navarre and<lb/> Italian cities&#44; and gather the offerings of the faith&#45;<lb/>&#45;ful.  The appeal met with a most generous response<lb/> everywhere&#44; and covetousness once gratified changed its<lb/> frowns into gracious smiles.  Now&#44; if like<lb/> Moses Ben Nachman&#44; Solomon Ben Adereth excelled<lb/> in Talmudism and like him remained attached to Kab&#45;<lb/>&#45;balism&#44; the copied Spanish Jew rivalled also his illustrious preceptor in<lb/> the moral courage manifested in vindicating the an&#45;<lb/>&#45;cestral belief.  Catholicism&#44; aiming at univer&#45;<lb/>&#45;sal conquest&#44; has sought converts at different times<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>with different means agencies&#44; now persuasive&#44; anon coer&#45;<lb/>&#45;cive.  That Church must be credited&#44; at all events&#44; with<lb/> having promoted the cultivation of Hebrew and its lite&#45;<lb/>rature&#44; with the ultimate objects that its priests exponents<lb/> may go forth well quipped to fight its battles&#44; and<lb/> it were unjust to deny that many did and as they do yet exhibited erudition.<lb/>  In the thirteenth century paper wars against the<lb/> Jewish people were waged with scholastic weapons.<lb/>  But the trenchant swords were blunted a by a keener<lb/> steel&#44; which such combatants as our Barcelona Rabbi<lb/> <sic>weilded</sic>.  He wrote and spoke and publicly debated<lb/> to prove Moses true and his disciples correct.<lb/>  Noteworthy especially is a controversy which he<lb/> held with an anonymous Mohammedan.  That<lb/> Moslem had apostatized from his religion and<lb/> become a Deist.  With much force he sought to over&#45;<lb/>throw the whole fabric of Revelation.  In his effort<lb/> to he spared neither Islam&#44; nor Christianity&#44; nor Judaism.<lb/>  Against our Scriptures&#44; he asserted that during a<lb/> thousand years&#44; the original Pentateuch had remained in the ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;clusive possession of the priests and Levites&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>who may have shaped it as they chose&#59; that<lb/> finally it was forgotten its existence fell into oblivion through the evil examples<lb/> which of kings of Israel and also of Judah showed by set who<lb/> relapsed into idolatry&#44; till Ezra&#44; after the restor&#45;<lb/>&#45;ation from the Babylonian exile&#44; presented it as the verit&#45;<lb/>&#45;able Law&#44; while it was not so&#44; and that hence<lb/> the authority of the five books is based upon the<lb/> testimony of a single man.  But the unbeliever&#44; who<lb/> abjured the Koran&#44; met more than his match in<lb/> Solomon Ben Adereth.  In a pamphlet entitled &#34;a<lb/> treatise against Ishmael&#44;&#34; the Rabinnical disputant showed the unreason&#45;<lb/>&#45;ableness of presuming that all Jews&#44; the largest num&#45;<lb/>&#45;ber left behind&#44; like the comparative few who returned<lb/> from the exile captivity&#44; would accept the rigorous ordinances<lb/> of the Pentateuch&#44; alleged to have been altogether or largely invented by<lb/> Ezra.  He demonstrated from internal evidences the<lb/> untenableness of the arguments advanced&#44; and victor&#45;<lb/>&#45;iously pointed out from a literary&#44; historical and<lb/> soundly logical standpoint&#44; the impossibility of at&#45;<lb/>&#45;tributing to the Scribe who wrote ten ceu centuries after<lb/> Moses&#44; the authorship of any of the holy volumes&#44; accepted<lb/> by Christians and Mohammedans&#44; as the genuine emanation<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>of the inspired son of Amram.  In reading of<lb/> the attempt of a descendant of Hagar in the thir&#45;<lb/>&#45;teenth century to fight attack the religion of the seed of<lb/> Abraham&#39;s posterity one is reminded of what some of the<lb/> would critics of the nineteenth century boldly advance.<lb/>  They too wish to strip Moses of the mantle of<lb/> glory donned at Sina&#239;&#44; and array with it&#44; one<lb/> of his disciples born many ages later.  but<lb/> in all truth&#44; we might as well more readily accept the sense&#45;<lb/>&#45;less theory that lord Bacon composed the Shakes&#45;<lb/>&#45;perian plays&#44; as to believe that Ezra penned in any shape or from the<lb/> code in which antediluvian&#44; patriarchal&#44; and Hebrew bondage<lb/> times are recorded&#44; whose desert wandering peregrination&#44; rules concerning the wander&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing tribes&#44; their complaints and their life and their<lb/> worship and their conquest of East&#45;Jordanic tribes<lb/> are minutely described.  Nay&#44; infinitely less credible<lb/> is that notion such an absurdity&#44; since language&#44; circumstances and<lb/> surroundings stand up and proclaim that idea the<lb/> summary of follies.  To believing Israelites I<lb/> will say with Ben Adereth.  The genuineness legitimacy<lb/> of the Torah is testified by a people who have<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p>received by a chain of traditions&#44; coming down from the summit of Horeb&#44; &#38; who<lb/> have lived through it and by it and who to this<lb/> day&#44; firmly declaring&#58; &#34;This is the Law which<lb/> Moses set before the Children of Israel.&#34;  &#34;Moses<lb/> commanded us a Law&#44; it is the inheritance of<lb/> the Congregation of Jacob.&#34;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
