<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF7_10</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1887-10" source="" attested="yes">October 1887</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_10_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_10_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_10_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_10_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_10_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_10_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_10_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_10_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_10_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_10_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_10_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_10_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>87</p>
            <p>On the statue for Meade&#44;<lb/>
                and the memorial fountain<lb/>
                at Stratford on Avon Oct. 87<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>It is refreshing to turn one&#39;s mind from subjects<lb/> full of vexation&#44; to others that breathe love for<lb/> what is noble&#59; respect for what is good.  Now<lb/> a days&#44; we may open a book in search of com&#45;<lb/>&#45;forting knowledge&#44; and find that where we looked<lb/> for solace&#44; insidious doubts lurk.  We address<lb/> a man whom we imagined distinguished reverent&#44; and hear<lb/> him scoff.  Papers ostensibly in the interest of<lb/> positive religion&#44; teem with irreligious discussions&#59;<lb/> weakening the child&#45;like faith which leads us creatures<lb/> in prayer to the footstool of the Creator&#44; shaking<lb/> our belief in a personal accountability to the<lb/> all&#45;seeing God.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Thus is truth missing&#44; and he who departs from<lb/> evil is considered foolish.&#34;  To be sure&#58; one<lb/> might spare himself much grief by avoiding<lb/>  both reading and arguing&#44; but then he might<lb/> as well change into a breathing corpse&#44; automatically mo&#45;<lb/>&#45;ving among sentient&#44; live beings.  Indi&#45;<lb/>&#45;viduals of that description are at times met&#44; but I recog&#45;<lb/>&#45;nize in their existence a vegetative growth.  not I fail to discover<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>an the intellectual soul.  Who that has<lb/> brains to think and a heart to feel&#44; would wish<lb/> to keep deathly passive to his surroundings&#44; even if<lb/> these do often inflict acute pain&#63;<lb/></p>
                <p>Still&#44; it is pleasure occasionally to avert<lb/> the eyes from that which disappoints and<lb/> distresses&#44; and fix the vision on what affords<lb/> real veritable satisfaction.  Such a transition I experienced<lb/> this week by reason of two incidents which<lb/> I witnessed&#59; one personally&#44; another mentally.<lb/>  A reformer to them in a Synagogue is not&#44; in my<lb/> opinion&#44; unsuitable&#44; because for&#44; I hold that what&#45;<lb/>&#45;ever teaching is calculated to elevates human nature&#44; enters largely into the<lb/> sphere assigned to the Jewish pulpit.<lb/></p>
            <p>In accepting the an official invitation to attend the exercises<lb/> at the unveiling of a statue raised to the victor<lb/> of Gettysburg&#44; I obeyed my a loyal instinct.<lb/>  I owe him profound gratitude to the gallant soldier who&#44; when the fate of the<lb/> Union&#44; but more immediately of Philadelphia&#44; trem&#45;<lb/>&#45;bled in the balance&#44; hurled back the raying wave<lb/> that rushed on madly to overwhelm our fair<lb/> city and lay waste the rich fields of our state.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>George Gordon Meade was the man of des&#45;<lb/>&#45;tiny whom God made invulnerable&#44; that he might<lb/> stand undoubtedly unscathed the fiery ordeal of the three first days<lb/> of July 1863&#44; so that the glorious fourth showed<lb/> and gladden Pennsylvania on the glorious fourth 4th with triumphal songs.<lb/>  Equestrian statues are not the monuments by<lb/> which a people can best eternize the memory<lb/> of its heroes.  A history recalling unflinching<lb/> devotion to a righteous cause&#59; a history whose<lb/> pages become will inspreing words that to future<lb/> generations with patriotism&#44; is the golden memento that the un&#45;<lb/>&#45;sparing hand of time will can never reduce powder&#45;&#45;into dust.<lb/>  But so long as granite and bronze are moulded<lb/> into figures for a recognition of splendid services<lb/> rendered to an <sic>imperilled</sic> nation&#44; the general who battled in<lb/> &#34;cemetery ridge&#34; and hushed into dead silence the<lb/> thunders of disunion&#44; must have such a statue<lb/> as that which the children of the great Republic<lb/> he helped to reconstruct&#44; have erected.  Feeling<lb/> thus&#44; I acknowledge the invitation with thanks&#44;<lb/> and applauded joined in the outbursts of patriotism enthusiasms which the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>solemn occasion evoked.  The utterances<lb/> that fell from the lips of the orators&#44; brought<lb/> back vividly to the my mind&#44; the four years of trials<lb/> which held civilization in fearful suspense&#44; lest<lb/> the wheel of progress be brutally with rudely thrust back.<lb/>  For had the country hallowed to freedom been<lb/> sundered in twain&#44; monarchical kingly <sic>pretentions</sic> wickedness would<lb/> have doubled its iron wheel and fiercely act crushed.  &#34;Divide et impera&#34;<lb/> is its motto&#44; and we all remember the<lb/> scheme of crafty Louis Napoleon&#44; and the<lb/> fatal end of his unfortunate tool&#44; Maximi&#45;<lb/>&#45;lian of Austria&#44; the would be emperor sent to of Mexico<lb/> to watch the result of our struggle for the maintenance of a United Republic.  But at Gettysburg the unhappy fratricidal<lb/> war&#44; which gave tyranny joy&#44; reached its turn&#45;<lb/>ing point&#44; crisis&#44; and the immortal chief&#44; who<lb/> vindicated right&#44; gained then and for ever a<lb/> niche in the Temple of undying imperishable fame.<lb/>  I met him the hero once at a family celebration in the house of<lb/> a brother Israelite.  His high stature formed a beauti&#45;<lb/>&#45;ful contrast with his lowly demeanour&#44; his2<lb/> martial carriage with his1 gentleness courteousness with.  Let us<lb/> be thankful as that as a Philadelphians&#44; by reason of<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>the military station assigned to him&#44; and<lb/> because of the handsome home which this ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;reciative city of ours prepared for his residence&#44;<lb/> Gorge Gordon Meade left a reputation un&#45;<lb/>&#45;sullied&#59; the heritage of a character ennobled by civic virtues.<lb/></p>
            <p>But the day before I personally witnessed<lb/> the solemn ceremonies in our picturesque Park&#44;<lb/> I had mentally stood at Stratford upon Avon<lb/> on the historic spot&#44; which despite all Mr<lb/> Donnelly&#39;s alleged discoveries&#44; will ever remain<lb/> sacred to the memory of William Shakespeare.<lb/>  Unpardonable arrogance it would be to add to the<lb/> sentiments that touching prose and flowing soul&#45;inspiring poetry<lb/> wafted across the Atlantic&#59; nor could I pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;sume to improve on what America&#39;s and<lb/> England&#39;s gifted orators said on Monday last.<lb/>  But I may with propriety point to the gift<lb/> and to the giver&#44; that elicited the celebration.<lb/>  Mr James Russel Lowel in his admirable letter<lb/> to the Mayor of London&#44; suiting his language<lb/> to that of Dante&#44; who called Virgil the Spring<lb/> from which whence copious floods of eloquence had issued&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>showed how preeminently fit was &#34;a memorial<lb/> fountain&#34; to honor the bard who poured forth<lb/> a river of mellifluous speech&#44; and Oliver Wendell Holmes<lb/> in his surpassing ode to that &#34;memorial fountain&#44;&#34; charming&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly portrayed the refreshing and sweet agencies<lb/> of its waves and sprays&#45;&#45;emblems of the human affect&#45;<lb/>&#45;ion&#44; of charity and friendship&#44; that swelling the breast<lb/> of our far famed renowned townsman.  That the weary<lb/> might slake their thirst&#44; the son of toil rest<lb/> awhile at noon under a cooling breeze&#44; and even<lb/> beasts plunge their nostrils in pure water after tiresome trots<lb/> in heat and dust&#44; was the aim of the munificent donor.<lb/>  But he would also beautifully illustrate the<lb/> title of the city in which he most usefully lives&#44;<lb/> by a present signification induction of brotherly love&#44; that<lb/> covers up all overlooks former trespasses&#44; even as the book<lb/> of truth teaches&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Hatred stirs up up strife&#44; but love covers up all sins.&#34;<lb/>  The sins of stains black stain on the escutcheon of Great Britain in the days of the<lb/> Rearsarge and the Alabama&#44; George W.<lb/> Childs sought to wash away by an abun&#45;<lb/>&#45;dant flow of fraternal kindness.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>The man in whose honor of whom an equestrian statue<lb/> was raised&#44; has won a2 golden page in the history<lb/> of freedom by1 his prowess and heroism&#59; he<lb/> who caused a well proportioned structure of great utility<lb/> to be raised in the town that produced the literary<lb/> genius of two English&#45;speaking nations has secured<lb/> a front rank in the annals noble order of real nobility&#45;&#45;that of large hearted bene&#45;<lb/>&#45;faction.  For he encourages industry&#44; rewards me&#45;<lb/>rit and with a spirit which disdains to set a<lb/> wall of partition between creeds and colors&#44; bes&#45;<lb/>tows his wealth upon whatever is deserving of<lb/> his countenance.  May Philadelphia never<lb/> need again the priceless services of a general<lb/> Meade&#44; but may she always count upon the<lb/> munificence broad generosity of citizens like her distinguished civilian George W. Childs.<lb/>  In the soul stirring prophecy of Isaiah&#44; that we<lb/> have read this Sabbath&#44; may peoples from afar off say to<lb/> of our city&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Enlarge Widen the space of thy habitation&#34;<lb/> &#34;For to the right and to the left shall there shalt<lb/> spread forth out&#44; and thy seed shall inherit nations.&#34;<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
