<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF4_11</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_11_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_11_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_11_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_11_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_11_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_11_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_11_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_11_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_11_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_11_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_11_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_11_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 3 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET.<lb/></p>
            <p>PHILADELPHIA&#44;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;189<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>63</p>
            
            <p>For the Sabbath before Passover &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>O Matzah&#44; Matzah&#44; thou hast in very deed been<lb/> unto Israel &#34;a bread of affliction&#34;&#44; yet&#44; we love thee<lb/> because sooner could our right hand forget her cunning&#44;<lb/> than we cease to recall the countless memories that cluster around<lb/> thee.  Always will we raise thee high in<lb/> the sight of our progeny&#59; always shalt thou hold<lb/> preeminence&#44; at this epochal season&#44; in the home<lb/> of the Jew.  Brethren.  You that are free<lb/> will not counsel the est enslaved to cast off the<lb/> memento reached down to us all&#44; by thousand gener&#45;<lb/>&#45;ations.  I heard it once and righteous indigna&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion seized my spirit.  A teacher of falsehood&#44;<lb/> whose sayings are oracularly listened to by many&#44;<lb/> spoke the iniquitous impious word.  &#34;If the Matzah ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;oses you to sufferings&#44; cease to partake of it.  Life<lb/> must not be <sic>imperilled</sic> because of a ceremonial law&#34;.<lb/>  But is it only the atrocious calumny invented against<lb/> the Matzah&#44; that has made Israel the target<lb/> of poisonous darts&#63;  Hearken to the cry of<lb/> tender mothers brought to the slaughter.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Why are ye&#44; women of my people&#44; slain by the<lb/> sword killed and burned&#63;  &#34;Because we would that our<lb/> male children be admitted into the covenant of<lb/> Abraham.&#34;  Say my brethren&#44; were the zealous Sages&#44; who<lb/> taught the law of Moses despite prohibition spared by the inveterate<lb/> foes&#44; who had sworn to force that Law into eter&#45;<lb/>&#45;nal oblivion&#63;  If the theory that we shall<lb/> crouch and bend and sacrifice cherished beliefs&#44;<lb/> to ward off persecution&#44; is to be carried to its<lb/> logical end&#44; sequence then we must even now exchange the<lb/> synagogue for the Mosque and accept baptism&#44; at<lb/> the hand of the Patriarch of Constantinople.<lb/>  For&#44; is the shah of Persia kindly considerate towards<lb/> his Hebrew subjects who deny the claims of the founder of Islam&#63; and is the Czar of Russia gently<lb/> tolerant towards those who reject the cross&#63;  No&#58; with<lb/> bleeding hearts and eyes swelling with tears this<lb/> message will we send to brethren&#44; who in very<lb/> deed eat the bread of affliction.  &#34;Sad is your lot&#44;<lb/> severe in the extreme are your trials&#44; but we look upon you<lb/> as our heroes.  Yield not to the direful pressure.<lb/>  Be firm&#44; be constant&#44; and through your constancy the<lb/> religion of Moses&#44; which we share&#44; will finally be vindicated.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Brethren.  Could you have imagined it possible&#44; that<lb/> we be obliged to send that message to our fel&#45;<lb/>&#45;low believers in a country&#44; for whose liberating from<lb/> the hated Turk&#44; Byron and political like enthusiasts<lb/> of only six decades ago&#44; staked their lives&#63;  While<lb/> I speak&#44; our coreligionists at Corfu may tremble&#44;<lb/> lest the brutality perpetrated against their<lb/> young and their old&#44; be reenacted&#33;  Greece of<lb/> George I&#44; has ensured our people unto the Hebrews citizenship and<lb/> and its attending immunities&#44; but what power<lb/> can roll back the surging of a wild populace&#44;<lb/> maddened by fanaticism&#63;  &#34;The Jew thirsts for<lb/> Christian blood.  He is enjoying it now in the<lb/> bread eaten on his Passover.  Tear down his<lb/> house&#44; demolish his place of worship&#44; let him<lb/> feel the keen edge of an avenging sword.&#34;  Irrepressibly&#44;<lb/> the a horrible scene turned the festival of the Lord last<lb/> year into mourning.  A peaceful community that<lb/> had long settled in the most flourishing city of the<lb/> Ionian isles&#44; was assaulted and plundered and murdered.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Many left behind substance and dear asso&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciations to escape from cruel death.  Heart rending was the sight of entire<lb/> families separating&#44; some fleeing in one direction&#44;<lb/> others elsewhere.  Italy we offered the nearest har&#45;<lb/>&#45;bor of safety&#44; and many not a few hastened thither&#44; but I have<lb/> read of an incident most touching concerning about the unfortunate refugees.  A <sic>centennarian</sic><lb/> was Nina Aboab.  Her ancestors had sought in<lb/> Corfu deliverance from the thumb screw and seething<lb/> cauldron of the Spanish inquisition.  Now the venerable mo&#45;<lb/>&#45;ther in Israel&#44; laden with years&#44; saw ruin all around&#44;<lb/> yet in the midst of a universal consternation&#44; she<lb/> appeared resigned to the sad fate&#44; almost serene&#44; the hoary&#45;headed matron she looked&#44;<lb/> under a compulsory exile.  Did she recall<lb/> at that sorrowful hour&#44; the trials of her race&#63;<lb/>  she did personify then Israel&#39;s endless trials tribulations&#45;&#45;Israel&#44; old<lb/> and beaten by all the winds of pitiless adversity&#44;<lb/> still uncrushed&#44; still trusting in Providence for the<lb/> final victory of truth.  Nina Aboab in the<lb/> bitterness of an inevitable banishment from a sweet<lb/> home and loved surroundings&#44; carried to a foreign<lb/> land the sustaining hope which never abandon&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed her martyred people.  She died soon after&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>in Alexandria of Egypt&#44; the country <sic>frought</sic><lb/> with reminiscences to dealthless&#91;&#63;&#93;.  Israel will she died&#44; breath&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing words of forgiveness to the persecutors of Abraham&#39;s progeny.<lb/>  Her action is the my counsel and tuition&#59; that I<lb/> follow&#44; not the unrighteous advice and instruction<lb/> of the time serving.  For&#44; by heeding the latter and<lb/> submitting to adverse circumstances adverse to the<lb/> retention of our the Mosaic precepts&#44; all that our fathers pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;served&#44; at such odds as made our continuance<lb/> upon earth possible&#44; will gradually disappear<lb/> and gentilism will have <sic>engulphed</sic> Judaism.  Are<lb/> you prepared for that issue&#44; Thy brethren&#63;  Are the re&#45;<lb/>&#45;ligious antagonistic to our creed so broad in their liberal<lb/> spirits&#44; so reasonably pure in their dogmas&#59; are&#45;&#45;I say&#45;&#45;the<lb/> votaries thereof so surpassingly moral&#44; so ennobled<lb/> by the humanitarian preaching of their clergy&#44; that<lb/> in order to improve our own doctrines&#44; to better our our conduct socially&#44;<lb/> relations&#44; to render us domestically more attached to<lb/> our fire sides&#44; we ought to abjure Moses and swear<lb/> by Jesus or Mohammed&#63;  What has happened<lb/> in Corfu&#59; what occurs every year in one spot or<lb/> in another of the globe or in another&#44; thunderingly answers&#58; &#34;No.&#34;<lb/>  Jews have faults many and glaring&#44; but bloodthirstiness<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>is not a vice of the adorers of the One God&#44; who<lb/> taught us all to believe that He made the earth&#44;<lb/> and created man to dwell thereupon.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; and again&#44; that He formed it<lb/> not to make become a waste&#44; but to be inhabit<lb/>&#45;ed by creatures&#44; who should acknowledge His<lb/> universal Fatherhood &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Jews would shrink with horror at<lb/> the bare idea of maligning a whole people&#44; by<lb/> giving credence to infamous accusations.  Jews<lb/> would not defy law and government&#44; to set up arm<lb/> a throne to calumny&#44; that it may tear away<lb/> from God&#39;s earth&#44; and destroy the innocent.  We are approach&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing the close of the nineteenth century of Grace&#44;<lb/> yet&#44; more than two hundred Rabbis in Germany&#44; have<lb/> felt morally compelled to make a solemn de&#45;<lb/>&#45;claration that the rules which intended for the guidance of Jews every&#45;<lb/>&#45;where&#44; are founded on rectitude and supported by<lb/> mercifulness.  In spite of that&#44; Rector Ahlwardt spits<lb/> his venom against Jews&#44; as the offscouring of society.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Two hundred and fifty years ago&#44; a defender of<lb/> his brethren&#44; an advocate of their rehabilitation<lb/> in England&#44; swore that the charge of ritual mur&#45;<lb/>&#45;der in connection with the Matzah&#44; is a lie and<lb/> a libel against every writing in possession of<lb/> the Jews.  He hoped prayed that if he prevaricated to<lb/> screen offenders&#44; curses innumerable and unending<lb/> might blight his existence here and hereafter&#44;<lb/> but a pretentious antisemitic Hebraist&#44; declared asserted&#44; a short time<lb/> since&#44; that to have found the imputation which<lb/> brought terror and desolation upon our Corfu fellow&#45;believers&#44; sub&#45;<lb/>&#45;stantiated in the Zohar.  A falsehood as black<lb/> as night.  But let me not sadden with<lb/> sombre reflections the arrival of the season&#44; commemorative<lb/> of our freedom from a spiritual&#44; not less than a physical&#44;<lb/> thraldom.  Let us make ready to greet it joyously<lb/> in the midst of our families.  Let us pray that like our&#45;<lb/>selves in this God&#45;favored America&#44; so all the outcasts<lb/> of Judea may raise the typical cups of salvation un&#45;<lb/>molested unshaken by fear.  May a voice be heard then on high promising in the<lb/> language of the prophet &#34;As in the days that ye went<lb/> out of Egypt&#44; I will show you wonders.&#34;  Amen.<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
