<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF12_3</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_3_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_3_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_3_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_3_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_3_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_3_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_3_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_3_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_3_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_3_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_3_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_3_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>A lecture for Beshalach<lb/>
                about keeping the Sabbath.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>A Rabbinical legend tells us that when the contem&#45;<lb/>&#45;poraries of Jeremiah became thoroughly il materialized&#44;<lb/> the prophet took the pot of Manna&#44; which Aaron<lb/> had set beside the ark of the covenant&#44; and showed it<lb/> publicly.  &#34;See&#34;&#44; he cried forth in the language of<lb/> the greatest Teacher&#44; &#34;See that the Lord hath given you<lb/> the Sabbath&#34;.  For you&#44; incredulous people&#44; was this<lb/> memento of Divine Providence befel left.  Like your<lb/> fathers&#44; you go in quest of what you do not need&#44; doubting<lb/> the Power that rained down a double portion of bread on the<lb/> sixth day&#44; to bless the seventh with sacred rest.<lb/>  Spirit of Jeremiah&#33;  Speak thou also to this generation<lb/> of Israel.  Words from uninspired lips have fallen hitherto<lb/> on listless ears.  Let thy glowing zeal which no trials<lb/> could abate&#44; breathe fresh love for the forsaken Law.<lb/>  Brethren&#33;  The immortal priest of Anathoth is being<lb/> still heard.  He does not present himself holding the<lb/> token of God&#39;s unaltered choice since the primeval days<lb/> of creation.  The pot of manna&#44; cannot&#44; any more<lb/> than the tables of testimony&#44; be produced&#44; to denounce<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>our unfaithfulness.  But Time has <sic>burried</sic><lb/> deep the venerated relics of biblical ages.  But an<lb/> undestructible monument rises gigantically from amidst<lb/> Holy Writ itself and looks down reproachfully on Sab&#45;<lb/>&#45;bath breakers.  It is the record of Jeremiah&#39;s earnest<lb/> protest.  &#34;Thus saith the Lord.  Take heed for your soul&#44;<lb/> and carry no burden on the Sabbath&#45;day&#44; nor bring it<lb/> through the gates of Jerusalem.  Nor shall you carry<lb/> forth a burden out of your houses on the Sabbath&#45;day&#44;<lb/> and no manner of work shall ye do&#44; but hallow ye the<lb/> Sabbath&#45;day&#44; as I have commanded your fathers.......<lb/>  But if ye will not hearken unto me to hallow the Sab&#45;<lb/>&#45;bath day&#44; and not to carry a burden&#44; and enter in at the<lb/> gates of Jerusalem on the Sabbath&#45;day&#44; then will I<lb/> kindle a fire in the gates thereof&#44; and it shall de&#45;<lb/>&#45;vour the palaces of Jerusalem&#44; and it shall not be<lb/> quenched.&#34;  A solemn declaration.  But against<lb/> whom do you think&#44; O Israelites&#33; that the protest is directed&#63;<lb/>  Not against those who abide in lowliness&#44;&#45;&#45;the inmates<lb/> of a hovel&#45;&#45;&#44; but against the possessors of princely<lb/> mansions&#44; against the affluent&#44; pl pillowed on the<lb/> bosom of ease.  Them the prophets holds responsible<lb/></p> 
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>for much of the defection which he laments.  For&#44; in<lb/> proportion to the divine gifts received ought to be their<lb/> gratitude&#44; viz&#44; their obedience to the Law and the precepts.<lb/>  And their example would&#44; to a certainty&#44; influence bene&#45;<lb/>&#45;ficially the community of their brethren.  The poor man<lb/> would not retail his wares&#44; if the rich man did not open<lb/> wide the doors of his wholesale store&#45;house.  The poor man<lb/> would not hawk his pithy merchandize&#44; if the rich<lb/> man did not tread on the sabbath the high&#45;places of traf&#45;<lb/>&#45;fic.  When those who have already gathered a double portion<lb/> of the world&#39;s goods&#44; go out in search of more&#44; they<lb/> who barely earn a subsistence&#44; will be incited to sin.<lb/>  Let the wealthy once understand that the <sic>yeilding</sic> of<lb/> the seventh&#45;day is fuel for the soul&#59; that it is&#44; as<lb/> Jeremiah describes it&#44; an inextinguishable fire&#59; let them<lb/> feel that temporal success met upon that day&#44; starts<lb/> back&#44; and in the long run turns to be our spiritual<lb/> adversary&#59; let them act upon the principle that the<lb/> displeasure of Almighty God at their defiance of His will&#44;<lb/> outweighs any gratification which a few additional pieces<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>of gold may procure&#44; and the result will<lb/> be seen in the general observance of the true Sabbath.<lb/>  A shame will be considered by a son of Israel&#44; to barter<lb/> away the holy hours belonging to God.  The daughter of<lb/> our people who now unblushingly struts along through<lb/> the thoroughfares to make her purchases&#44; would<lb/> learn that she can only be respected in the congregation<lb/> when she honors her faith.  Scarcely any would be found<lb/> so audacious to throw down the gauntlet in the face<lb/> of a religious public.  Not that I advocate hypocrisy&#59;<lb/> the wearing of a mask&#44; to hide a countenance wrinkled<lb/> with the contemptuous smile of unbelief.  Far be from me the<lb/> unworthy thought.  But I share the opinion of the<lb/> Rabbins&#44; that habits&#44; good and bad&#44; grow upon us<lb/> insensibly.  And individuals who conform at first to<lb/> the rules of piety out of deference for others&#44; may in<lb/> the course of time be drawn to them with pure affection.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  Is it not because imbued with<lb/> the same idea that we hope to shape aright the future<lb/> course of our sons and daughters&#63;  Are we not sanguine<lb/> that the force of our example will carry them away<lb/> from their froward dispositions&#44; and chain them to our will&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Such methods as I have described must the<lb/> rich follow&#44; and their brethren in humbler circum&#45;<lb/>&#45;stances will be palpably affected.  Let us acknow&#45;<lb/>&#45;ledge it&#44; money is power.  It may build up&#44; and<lb/> overthrow&#44; elevate and ruin&#59; the issue lies in the<lb/> hand of the possessor.  I say&#59; that if the upholding<lb/> of his religion be in the wealthy Israelite&#44; a ruling thought&#44;<lb/> he will direct towards himself the eyes of multitudes.<lb/>  He will be noted&#44; when on the seventh day he casts off<lb/> the burden of commerce&#44; and bends to assume the salutary<lb/> yoke of the Law.  He will be observed when&#44; grateful for<lb/> the twofold portion of gathered&#44; he withdraws his hands from<lb/> labor&#44; and his feet from pursuing his pleasure&#44; and he<lb/> will promote thereby a sacred purpose.  His conduct will<lb/> tacitly say tell his less prosperous coreligionists.  &#34;See that<lb/> the Lord hath given you the Sabbath&#59;&#34; and they will heed<lb/> and understand that th none have been reduced to a state<lb/> of destitution who clung to the word of God.<lb/></p>
            <p>But have American Hebrews so exercised the power&#44;<lb/> which affluence undoubtedly gives&#63;  Have they made<lb/> so open a recognition of the boons showered down plentifully<lb/> upon them by a loving God&#63;  Have they so ascribed<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>glory to their Benefactor&#63;...Persons whom you may<lb/> stir up to deeds of generosity&#44; you may soften to the<lb/> tenderest emotions&#44; for the sake of their fellow&#45;creatures&#44;<lb/> are immoveable&#44; adamant&#45;like&#44; when appealed to for<lb/> the reverence due to their Father and Legislator.  They<lb/> may be persuaded to act with self&#45;denial to advance<lb/> a good cause&#44; but to make a sacrifice for a most right&#45;<lb/>&#45;eous cause&#44; to return unto the Lord what He declared His<lb/> own&#44; they deem an impossible effort&#44; an action beyond<lb/> human power.  Alas&#33; that the fatal error&#59; this per&#45;<lb/>&#45;tinacity&#44; that is the word&#45;&#45;; this pertinacity is the<lb/> sword of Damocles hanging on the life of Judaism.<lb/>  You ask why&#63; because the Synagogue&#45;&#45;a mighty<lb/> agency in keeping up the our national vitality&#45;&#45;&#44; is<lb/> cast aside as valueless&#59; because the knowledge of<lb/> the Torah&#44; which in every stage of our history&#44; proved<lb/> our invulnerable shield&#44; cannot penetrate the minds of<lb/> Israelites who refuse to join in this weekly holy con&#45;<lb/>vocations&#44; where the law is expounded&#59; because our<lb/> children are forcibly driven away from the worship of God&#44;<lb/> and compelled to serve Mammon.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Alas Yes&#33; the last is the crowning of all evils.<lb/>  A terrible <sic>alterative</sic>&#44; O Jewish fathers and mothers&#33;<lb/>  The creatures we rejoiced to introduce into the covenant&#59;<lb/> the creatures we gladly presented before the Congregation<lb/> of the Lord&#44; to be confirmed in the ancestral faith&#44; we<lb/> must either hand over to idleness&#45;&#45;the parent of vice&#59;<lb/> or surrender to irreligion&#59; the engine of eternal death.<lb/>  In this overwhelming perplexity&#44; you&#44; a rich&#44; can open<lb/> for us a way of escape.  If a goodly number among<lb/> you&#44; resolve to give glory to Israel&#39;s God&#44; they can form<lb/> the vanguard of a sacred host&#44; sure to swell up rapidly<lb/> Let the streets&#44; in which conspicuous for the successful industry of the Jew&#44;<lb/> is exhibited to best advantage show on the seventh&#45;day&#44; a cessation of servile labor&#44;<lb/> and others will vary soon exhibit the same remarkable<lb/> change.  Once more will I say it&#44; my fellow&#45;believers.<lb/>  &#34;See that the Lord hath given you the Sabbath&#34;.  It is<lb/> none of those Rabbinical institutions&#44; which the<lb/> wise men&#63; of our century so greatly deride.  The<lb/> Sabbath received its credentials from on high in the<lb/> primordial days of the world.  It revealed itself with<lb/> a halo of undiminished sanctity amidst the thunders<lb/> of Sinai&#59; it bear the signet affixed by the hand of<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>our sainted prophets.  The Sabbath hath been given<lb/> by the Lord&#44; to make us feel that we are not beasts<lb/> of burden&#59; that their there are higher aims of life<lb/> than the incessant gathering of pelf&#59; that we<lb/> must detach ourselves from the lower earth&#44; and rise in the<lb/> scale of social greatness.  The Sabbath should be our instructor&#44;<lb/> and we ought to carry out its lessons into practice out during the six days in our<lb/> dealings with our fellow&#45;men.  Let us base consider&#45;<lb/>&#45;ation rob us of that celestial legacy.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> let the rich and the poor also rightly value it&#44; and<lb/> they will learn better how to live&#44; and how to die.<lb/>  When the hour of summon arrives&#44; they shall be able<lb/> to say &#34;Righteous Lord&#44; Thou didst give us the Sabbath&#44;<lb/> and we kept it&#44; according to Thy word.  Grant us now<lb/> a Sabbath of eternal rest in Thy heavenly abode.&#34;<lb/>  So may it be.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
