<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF14_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1896" source="" attested="yes">1896</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff14_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff14_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff14_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff14_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff14_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff14_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff14_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff14_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff14_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff14_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff14_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff14_1_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>96<lb/>
                On Haftorath Mishpatim<lb/></p>
            
            <p>42</p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>The present Jewish year is almost exceptional.  Unless<lb/> the year is happens to be bissextile&#44; when an additional month is in&#45;<lb/>&#45;troduced&#44; so as to equalize&#44; after a cycle of nineteen years&#44;<lb/> the lunar with and the solar years&#44; the Parashah read designated for this<lb/> morning&#44; has for its corresponding Haftorah&#44; what bears<lb/> some resemblance to the ordinance of Shekahim.  I mean that we read<lb/> about the action of King Joash&#44; who invited the priests<lb/> to collect silver enough for repairing the Temple.<lb/>  And as in olden times&#44; every Israelite was in duty bound to give&#44;<lb/> before in Adar before Nis&#91;s&#93;an set in entered&#44; one half shekel for the support of<lb/> the Temple Jerusalem sanctuary&#44; we ordinarily peruse a prophetic section&#44;<lb/> recalling in part that ancient ordinance commandment.  This year&#44; as it very rarely<lb/> happens occurs&#44; Sabbath Shekahim&#44; is&#44; according to by a Rabbinical<lb/> arrangement&#44; defferred to next Sabbath.  To day&#44; the<lb/> Haftarah is of an entirely different character.  We<lb/> hear Jeremiah speak.  The man of God raises the uplifts his voice<lb/> in sounds of admonition denunciation.  He summons to before the bar<lb/> of outraged justice&#44; the sinners of his century days.<lb/>  The priestly We may admit that the sacerdotal Seer&#44; who received a Divine mission in when<lb/> the days of his a mere only a youth&#44; as he said it &#91;Hebrew&#93; had not learned to rise al&#45;<lb/>&#45;ways in grandeur of style as Isaiah ever arose&#44; though<lb/> occasionally he does match the prince of oratory<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>in language surpassingly sublime majestic&#45;&#45;but surely in pathos<lb/> and in strains&#44; melting the heart with compassion&#44; Jeremiah<lb/> stands almost alone unique.  But And so long as we value abnegation above deception egotism he must remain the<lb/> dearest among the prophets&#44; candor above deception&#44; sincerity above cringing adulation who succeeded the son of<lb/> Amram&#59; the dearest to Jewish us hearts by reason of his<lb/> sufferings long endured not to dishonor the God who<lb/> had sent him to on a message of correction &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;I had said&#44;&#34; he exclaims&#44; &#34;I had said&#44; I will not men&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion Him&#59; I will not speak any more in His<lb/> name&#44; but a burning fire was ablaze in my heart&#59;<lb/> shut up within my bones&#45;&#45;I could not overcome<lb/> it.&#34;  Aye&#58; he Jeremiah did burn with zeal for the cause<lb/> he has espoused&#45;&#45;the defense of right against might.<lb/>  Yet he bore he was made to public he became the target of public contempt because of his the zeal he displayed Glowing<lb/> with patriotism&#44; still weak and he still felt the iron of wicked rulers with and<lb/> their misguided subjects&#44; branded him nevertheless with the stigma<lb/> of treason.  He who had entered into a solemn covenant<lb/> with Truth&#44; was publicly maligned and&#44; accused of lying.  He was<lb/> struck and enchained and dragged thrust into dungeons&#44;<lb/> like a culprit.  But he continued&#44; in all reality&#44;<lb/> to the very last&#44; what the first vision vouchsafed<lb/> to him had predicted &#91;inserted above&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#93;&#45;&#45;an iron pillar&#44; a brazen wall<lb/> against the whole corrupt land&#44; against kings and their sycophants&#44; fluttering lying<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>prophets&#59; unchangeable in his devotion to the<lb/> inherited Sinaic faith.  And when the sad hour arrived<lb/> the hour which<lb/> his illumined vision had foreseen &#44;when the enemy foe<lb/> battered down the gates of Jerusalem&#59; cast the all&#45;<lb/>consuming brand torch into the Holy of Holies&#59; scattered<lb/> Judah throughout Chaldea&#44; where penitent exiles<lb/> f hanging sat weeping with their harp hung on the willows&#44; Jeremiah offered refused<lb/> ease and comfort offered him by the mighty Nebuchadnezzar far from the soil he loved&#44; choosing<lb/> instead to abide among the ruins of Judea&#44; whose stones<lb/> he held dear&#44; and whose dust he cherished.<lb/>  Only force&#44; brutal force exercised by the overbearing few&#44; who<lb/> trusted treacherous Egypt&#44; could compel the plaintive<lb/> bard of our woes&#44; to pour forth lamentations in<lb/> the streets of Daphine and Memphis&#44; whither he<lb/> had been violently dragged.<lb/></p>
            <p>The subject of his complaint in the Haftarah&#44; which<lb/> we have read to day&#44; is the iniquity of the rich<lb/> against the poor.  All will remember that<lb/> immediately that immediately after the delivery<lb/> of the Decalogue&#44; which is the Magna Charta<lb/> of all civilization&#44; Moses was asked directed by God&#44;<lb/> to lay down ordinances statutes concerning persons kept in slavery.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Most pitiful among heathens was the condition<lb/> of such.  Suffice to read the history of antiquity to<lb/> be horrified at the cruelties perpetrated against the<lb/> Helots in Sparta&#44; the Bythemins in Byzantium&#44;<lb/> where the fear of a revolt by the bondmen&#44; occasioned merciless slaugh&#45; massacres<lb/> ters and not infrequently jealousy of too great an increase&#44; incited the masters to fiendish persecutions.  Hebrews who had suffered terribly for during<lb/> successive ages in galling bondage thraldom&#44; were commanded to treat<lb/> slaves very considerately.  Repeatedly has Moses em<lb/>&#45;phasized the obligation of keeping in mind engraving on the tablets of our mind the fact that<lb/> we also had been bound in fettered in bondage thraldom accordingly&#44; It the deliverance from Egypt is our molto<lb/> whether we greet the Sabbath day on the cup of<lb/> wine&#44; whether we hail the Passover&#59; at almost nearly<lb/> all our religious ceremonies&#44; &#91;Hebrew is echoed forth.  A tradition which<lb/> stands uncontradicted unrefuted&#44; teaches that only extreme<lb/> poverty&#45;&#45;an impossibility in Israel&#44; so long as the<lb/> ordinances of Moses were carried out&#45;&#45;or the commission of a theft<lb/> so to working subjecting the guilty one to work in servitude in order to make a restitution&#44; could consign a He&#45;<lb/>&#45;brew to slavery.  The Rabbis dwell dictate at great<lb/> length on that topic and justly conclude<lb/> that to bring a Jewish slave to one&#39;s home<lb/> is to buy a master&#44; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> so exceedingly thoughtful must the owner have<lb/> shown himself&#44; in order so as not unnecessarily to to wound<lb/> feelings and reduce a fellow religionist to abject humiliation.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Non&#45;Jewish slaves&#44; who were mostly&#44; were prisoners of<lb/> war atrociously dealt with&#44; must have sought the territory of Israel as a place<lb/> of safety&#44; for Moses had give left the following injunction<lb/> &#34;Thou shalt not deliver to his master&#44; a slave who<lb/> shall have escaped to thee from his master.  He<lb/> shall dwell with thee&#44; in thy midst&#44; of thee&#44; in<lb/> the place which he shall choose&#44; within one<lb/> of thy gates&#44; where he likes best&#44; thou shalt not<lb/> oppress him.&#34;  Even when bought to labor in the<lb/> house and in the field&#44; the his treatment was mild<lb/> in doors&#59; kind abroad&#59; privileged was that human being<lb/> to share with his master&#44; the Sabbath rest and the pleasures of the<lb/> sacred festivals. with his master. The Sabbatical year<lb/> entitled that bondman him moreover to the spontaneous growth<lb/> of the soil&#44; in common with those born in Israel&#44; for<lb/> so it is written&#58; &#34;The &#40;product of the&#41; Sabbath of the<lb/> land shall be unto you for food&#44; even nay&#44; for thee&#44; and for<lb/> thy man&#45;servant&#44; and for thy maid&#45;servant and for<lb/> thy hired laborer and for thy strangers that sojourn<lb/> with thee.&#34;  You must I recall with pride what was found the noble boast sentiments of the<lb/> righteous Job.  If I despise the cause of my man&#45;servant<lb/> or maid&#45;servant&#44; when they contend with me&#44; what would<lb/> I do when God rises&#44; what could I answer&#44; when He<lb/> searches me.  Did He not who made me&#44; make him born of woman&#63;&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>And the Talmud has recorded the action of Rabbi Gam&#45;<lb/>&#45;bil who&#44; contrary to the prevailing usage&#44; sat mourn&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing to receive the condolence over the loss of his worthy trusty<lb/> sa slave &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Aye&#58; the written<lb/> and the oral Law&#44; both have humanity as their found&#45;<lb/>&#45;ation stone&#44; kindness and forbearance as sustaining<lb/> pillars.  But the contemporaries of Jeremiah had<lb/> forgotten all religion&#59; they had entered into a league with irredeemable perversity.  Their degeneracy<lb/> offended the God of Sinai&#44; filled His prophet with right&#45;<lb/>&#45;eous anger.  King Zedekiah&#44; the last ruler of Judah&#44;<lb/> trembling perhaps at the impending fate doom&#44; may have<lb/> heeded the admonition of the Seer&#44; who pointed ot the<lb/> sword unsheathed for the slaughter.  He may have&#44; for a<lb/> time&#44; have proclaimed the binding force of the Mosaic behests&#44;<lb/> and have loosened the shackles which inhumanity bound pressed Jews<lb/> and Jewesses in bondage.  But soon he relapsed into his rebellion<lb/> wicked ways against the Torah.  His high officials and his &#91;&#63;&#93; vile partisans&#44;<lb/> the wealthy&#44; may have gladly copied the royal inequity.<lb/>  Then it was that Jeremiah&#44; denounced the brutality.<lb/>  He quoted Moses as in our Parashah&#59; portrayed the Nemesis<lb/> advancing with rapid strides to avenge God&#39;s word&#59; rebuked<lb/> wealthy opulent sinners&#44; chiefs and princes who had consigned plunged Judea to perdition. into a pit of corruption.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>You have heard his language&#58; Thus saith the Lord&#59; Ye<lb/> have not hearkened unto me&#44; to proclaim liberty&#44;<lb/> every man to his brother&#44; and every man one to his neigh&#45;<lb/>&#45;bor&#59; behold&#44; I proclaim unto you a liberty&#44; saith the<lb/> Lord &#40;to the liberty be delivered&#41; to the sword&#44; to the pestilence&#44; and to<lb/> the famine&#44; and I will make you to be tossed to and<lb/> fro along all the kingdoms of the earth..........<lb/> the princes of Judah and the princes of Jerusalem the<lb/> officers and the priests....and Zedekiah King of Judah and his<lb/> princes will I give into the hand of their enemies and<lb/> into the hand of them that seek their life and into<lb/> the hand of the King of the Babylon&#39;s army.&#34;<lb/>
                But the soul that reproached so fearfully in an out&#45;<lb/>&#45;burst of burning zeal for the Lord and His forsaken command&#44;<lb/> grieved to the core at the contemplation of the ap&#45;<lb/>proaching calamity. &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Oh&#33; that my head were waters and mine eyes a fountain<lb/> of tears&#44; that I might weep day and night for<lb/> the slain of m the daughters of my people&#34;<lb/>  And in that volume which none other&#44; but the man who<lb/> saw affliction by the rod of God&#39;s wrath&#44; could have<lb/> traced penned&#59; in the book of lamentations&#44; Jeremiah strikes<lb/> notes that pierce thrill every fibre of our being.  &#34;O wall of<lb/> the daughter of Zion&#44; let tears run down like a river<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>day and night&#44; give thyself no respite&#59; let<lb/> not the apple of thine eye cease.  Arise&#44; cry in the<lb/> night&#44; at the beginning of the watches&#44; pour out<lb/> thy heart like water before the face of the Lord&#59; lift<lb/> up thy hands toward Him for the life of thy babes&#44; that faint for hunger<lb/> at the top of every street....See O Lord and behold&#44; to<lb/> whom thou hast done thus&#33;&#34;  But let not what<lb/> I have quoted&#44; deceive any into the belief that the<lb/> priest of Anathoth has gained immortality only as<lb/> the elegist of our owes woes.  There were moments<lb/> in which the spirit of God uplifted him into the<lb/> heights of prophetic ecstasy.  Then Jeremiah sung<lb/> of a future streaming with Joys&#59; then he depicted<lb/> God&#39;s return&#44; drawn anew to the elect by the chords<lb/> of a love everlasting&#44; then he saw the virgins of Israel<lb/> go forth with timbrels among midst the merry dancers.  Lo&#33;<lb/> He looks again and beholds Samariah&#45;mountains bedecked<lb/> with vineyards&#44; the planters shouting for gladness&#44;<lb/> the tower&#45;watchers calling all to Zion&#44; then Rachel&#39;s<lb/> sobbings cease.  The mother greatly cherished is glorified by glories again over<lb/> the restoration of her children to the ancestral heritage.<lb/>  For that the faithful in Israel pray and bend low to the knee before the saving Lord in<lb/> all the countries of their dispersion&#44; may the redeemer come to Zion.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
