<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF2_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1868" source="" attested="yes">1868</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_1_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>A discourse before leaving the old<lb/>
                Synagogue<lb/>
                On Cherry st near 3rd in 1868<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Dear Brethren&#33;  That which in irrational<lb/> beings&#44; is the effect of instinct&#44; when exhibited by<lb/> man&#44; gives evidence of a tender heart.  The<lb/> frivolous&#44; whose affections are as mutable as their<lb/> purposes&#44; will deride their neighbour&#44; because<lb/> he heaves up a sigh even when parting with<lb/> inanimate objects worn out by age&#59; but methinks<lb/> that one capable of so much sentiment&#44; ought&#44;<lb/> on the contrary&#44; to command our high regard.<lb/>  For&#44; not the object itself&#44; but the ideas associated<lb/> therewith elicit his feeling of regret.  Beasts<lb/> of prey like their dens&#44; domestic animals their<lb/> abodes&#44; but man loves the spot in which a<lb/> mother&#39;s caress&#44; or a brother&#39;s innocent sports glad&#45;<lb/>&#45;dened his youthful days.  He loves the spot<lb/> in which when trouble overtook him&#44; he stole away<lb/> to weep over his reverses and his follies.  He loves that<lb/> where his infant lips were taught to sing the praise<lb/> of his Almighty Protector.  None among<lb/> you&#44; my dear friends&#33; can more than myself<lb/> loathe the deifying of perishable matter&#44; but I<lb/> disclaim any community of feelings with him that<lb/> that looks unconcernedly on the day decay of his parental roof&#59;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>who sees the dwelling in which his early life glided<lb/> by&#44; razed to the ground&#44; and does not experience <lb/>a single sensation of disquietude.  I am not a<lb/> disciple of stoicism.  It is a philosophy that<lb/> deadens the noblest impulses of our nature.  I<lb/> prefer the foibles concomitant with an oversensitive<lb/> temperament&#59; to the hardihood displayed by the fol&#45;<lb/>&#45;lowers of the Grecian Zeus.  Therefore it is&#44; that<lb/> while I address you&#44; painful thoughts will force<lb/> themselves on my mind.  The reflection that<lb/> this house&#44; wherein I&#44; with great trepidation&#44; did once<lb/> crave your indulgence to my deficiencies&#44; and the<lb/> assistance of my Maker in my humble endeavours&#44;<lb/> shall be no longer devoted to God&#59; the reflection<lb/> that we shall no more offer together in these holy<lb/> courts our supplications and thanks&#59; that yet a<lb/> little while and that sacred receptacle shall not<lb/> be known as the repository of our divine oracles&#44;<lb/> affects me greatly.  But I will not conceal<lb/> from you that another motive adds to my mental<lb/> agitation.  For nine consecutive years&#44; I have prayed<lb/> for you and with you&#44; my beloved brethren&#33; in a<lb/> manner which I deem befitting the present state<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>of our nation and most adapted to Synagogue<lb/> worship.  While we continued resorting to this<lb/> ancient place&#44; a longing after inconsiderate change<lb/> has been curbed.  Whether the spirit of the departed&#44;<lb/> who served here the Lord with modesty and meekness<lb/> protected this hallowed spot from the contaminations<lb/> witnessed in others&#44; I presume not to say&#59; but<lb/> hitherto the ritual handed down by our ancestors&#44;<lb/> has been adhered to unswervingly&#59; the transcendent<lb/> language in which god spoke&#44; has echoed from<lb/> these walls&#59; the harrowing&#45;&#45;though mellifluous&#45;&#45;<lb/> voice of a non&#45;believer of in Judaism&#44; did not blend<lb/> with our hymns and psalms&#44; pageantry in the ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;ternal garb of our Sabbath gatherings&#44; did not abstract<lb/> the faithful from their devotions&#59; but now this un&#45;<lb/>&#45;pretending building will be <sic>levelled</sic> with the earth and<lb/> superseded by another superior in of imposing magnificence.  Will<lb/> we preserve in that&#44; the simplicity we maintained<lb/> in this&#63;  Will the satisfaction of having erected a<lb/> more sightly structure in homage to our King&#44; suffice<lb/> us&#59; or will it engender vainglory and with it ostenta&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion&#63;  Will the sight of an attractively new edifice<lb/> excite a distaste for whatever is venerably old&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Will it give rise to innovations incompatible with<lb/> our time&#45;honored usages&#63;  Brethren&#33;  I ardently<lb/> hope that we all may sacrifice our private desires<lb/> on the altar of unity and peace&#44; but you must pardon<lb/> me&#44; if on the eve of abandoning for ever this sanctuary<lb/> of the Eternal&#44; gloomy thoughts and misgivings<lb/> will ruffle my spirits.  But need I indeed<lb/> solicit your forgiveness&#63;  This Sabbath must<lb/> surely more than in mine&#44; awaken in your breasts<lb/> sad emotions.  This day you will cast a retrospective<lb/> glance to the years that have sunk into eternity.<lb/>  The recollection of the delight you felt&#44; when in childhood<lb/> you first entered this habitation of the Most High&#44;<lb/> will flesh on your mind.  You will perhaps gaze<lb/> on the very spot on which your beloved parents then<lb/> seated you.  You will imagine to see before your<lb/> eyes those venerated authors of your existence.  There&#44;<lb/> a sainted mother pouring forth her entreaties&#44; here&#44;<lb/> a lamented father intently listening to the recital of<lb/> the law.  You will call back the utter dejection that<lb/> seized you&#44; when revisiting this dwelling&#44; after a<lb/> bereavement&#44; and the comfort obtained by communing<lb/> with your wise and merciful Creator.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>You will remember the anxiety which had prompted<lb/> you to seek his face&#44; for the life of those you love<lb/> above yourselves&#44; and the gratitude experienced at their<lb/> preservation.  All those and numberless other remi&#45;<lb/>&#45;niscences will at this hour recur to your conceptions.<lb/>  Could you then relinquish this consecrated home and<lb/> bestow2 not1 upon it one rueful thought&#63;  And they<lb/> who have seen the age of adolescence turn into full<lb/> maturity&#44; while steadily repairing hither&#44; will they<lb/> not&#44; especially&#44; regret that this Sabbath&#44; will sever<lb/> them from a spot wherewith the congregational history<lb/> of &#38; seventy2 eight1 years is connected&#63;  We may<lb/> reason with such&#44; and convince them that the requirements<lb/> of the time demanded the alteration&#59; that the<lb/> site of this Synagogue had grown totally unsuit&#45;<lb/>&#45;able&#59; that its much&#45;impaired appearance ill&#45;<lb/>became the dignity of the worship&#59; but we shall not<lb/> succeed in removing the pain that the severance<lb/> occasions.  I will not therefore venture on<lb/> an ineffectual task&#59; but as no other opportunity<lb/> will be afforded me to address you all&#44; ere we quit<lb/> this holy place&#44; I deem it a stringent duty to do<lb/> so in a manner&#44; which may hereafter remind you<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>of the last Sabbath we met within those its courts.<lb/>  Brothers and sisters&#33;  If these stones and this timber<lb/> were endowed with speech&#44; they would now charge<lb/> us with the committal of actions detracting from the<lb/> sanctity of a Synagogue.  They would reproachfully<lb/> stare him in the face&#44; who&#44; instead of being absorbed<lb/> in devotion&#44; jeered at his neighbour.  They would<lb/> point him out with the finger of disgrace&#44; who<lb/> indulged in censorious remarks and uncharitable hints&#59;<lb/> They would tell of some who evinced impatience&#44; when<lb/> the service was protracted beyond the hour he himself<lb/> had designed&#59; of others who were tardy in their attend&#45;<lb/>&#45;ance and listless at the performance of our rites.<lb/>  They would say that peace did not always reign<lb/> among those who had assembled to adore the same<lb/> God&#59; that even when fulfilling a religious obser&#45;<lb/>&#45;vance&#44; the seeds of discord were sown.<lb/></p>
            <p>I am aware that my allusions are poignant&#44; but<lb/> however expedient it might have been under different<lb/> circumstances to temper their keenness&#44; this day<lb/> imperatively asks that I should spare none.  No&#59;<lb/> if we must abandon a place fraught with solemn<lb/> recollections&#44; let us abandon also the evil habits exhibited<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>while we continued therein.  Let us cherish the<lb/> memorials of the past&#44; when tending to soften our<lb/> feelings&#44; but let us leave for ever behind&#44; what was<lb/> reprehensible in us.  In parting with this Synagogue<lb/> which by our demeanour frequently slighted&#45;&#45;we must pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;mise that the other we will soon occupy&#44; shall not<lb/> witness what I have exposed as derogatory.<lb/></p>
            <p>It has been said with justice that the interior of that<lb/> structure exceeds its exterior in beauty&#59; let it be&#44;<lb/> my friends&#33; the type of its attendants.  Let our<lb/> inward worship more than outward show&#44; prove<lb/> our piety.  In order to demonstrate it clearly&#44; we<lb/> should repair thither betimes&#44; and demean decorou&#45;<lb/>&#45;sly.  We should let our voice join in the praises<lb/> of God&#44; but not with clamour to gratify an inexcu&#45;<lb/>&#45;sable vanity.  We should evidence our attachment<lb/> to the sacred house we have reared&#44; by supporting<lb/> it with generous offerings&#44; but we should never<lb/> suffer the latter to encroach on the hours devoted to<lb/> prayers.  We should all strive to render that<lb/> edifice more the promoter of good&#45;will among the<lb/> living members of Israel&#44; than the propitiator for<lb/> the soul of their dead.  We should be exceedingly<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>wary not to lay our hand on that which is sta<lb/> founded stands on the broad foundations of the<lb/> Torah and its oral exposition&#59; not to be lured<lb/> to refashion our ancient usages in the mould of<lb/> individual opinions and crotchets&#59; but each of us<lb/> should contribute to enhance our present mode<lb/> of <sic>worshipping</sic>&#44; by preventing any act of irre&#45;<lb/>&#45;verence and levity&#59; of ill&#45;timed and vociferous<lb/> singing&#59; the winking of the eye&#44; and the<lb/> pratting of the tongue.  Thus improved&#44; the<lb/> regret of having bid this spot a last farewell&#44;<lb/> will be relieved assuaged by the reflection that in it we<lb/> promised our amendment.  This Sabbath on<lb/> which we end the third book of the law of and our stay<lb/> in this Sanctuary&#44; will then be ever remembered&#44;<lb/> we shall experience hereafter the satisfaction that<lb/> it was profitably spent&#44; that if our fathers came<lb/> in with joy&#44; we go went forth in peace&#44; &#34;and that the<lb/> glory of the latter house shall be greater than<lb/> that of the former&#44; for in that place the Lord of hosts<lb/> will grant peace.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Let us pray that it may be so.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>O Lord of hosts&#33;  Once more thy children delight<lb/> in prostrating themselves before the ark&#44; that<lb/> has treasured up the relics of their religion.  They<lb/> take pleasure even in the stones of the house&#44;<lb/> which the hand of their fathers founded and they<lb/> devoted to Thee.  Bless them&#44; and gladden<lb/> their hearts with the hope that thy glory<lb/> will hover above them&#44; wherever they shall gather<lb/> to pray.  That their supplications will from thence<lb/> ascend thy throne&#44; and be accepted as a grateful<lb/> offering.  O bless their old and their young&#44;<lb/> their widows and their orphans&#44; their temporal<lb/> leaders and spiritual guide&#59; And Mayest Thou<lb/> deign to add infinitely to the number of this holy Congregation.<lb/>  Lead them forth with thine own hand and establish them in<lb/> the place&#44; which they have wrought for Thy<lb/> residence O Eternal&#33;  And let their example<lb/> therein teach their sons and their daughters<lb/> to &#34;serve Thee with fear and rejoice with trembling&#44;&#34;<lb/> for&#59; &#34;holiness will grace thy house&#44; O Lord&#44; to<lb/> the utmost length of days&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Amen and Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
