<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF9_15</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1891-05" source="" attested="yes">May 1891</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_15_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_15_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_15_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_15_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_15_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_15_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_15_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_15_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_15_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_15_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_15_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_15_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/></p>
            <p>PHILADELPHIA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>7<lb/></p>
            <p>May&#47;91<lb/>
                On recent utterances by Radicalism<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Brethren.  All human beings are&#44; more or less&#44; influen&#45;<lb/>&#45;ced by circumstances.  It is not impossible that<lb/> any of us&#44; who feel attached to the laws and prac&#45;<lb/>&#45;tices of the Jewish religion&#44; if grown up among dif&#45;<lb/>&#45;ferent environments&#44; if schooled under a different<lb/> training&#44; might care little or nothing for rules and<lb/> usages which we now value.  This admission I<lb/> make in all candor&#44; to exclude the absurd preposterous idea that<lb/> I wish to be looked upon as if clothed at birth in sanctity at my birth&#59; ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;pointed a mentor appointed by nature as a mentor to rebuke whoever dares happens to disagree<lb/> with the views I hold.  There have been times<lb/> when&#44; impelled by the force of convictions&#44; I have allowed<lb/> my speech to criticize in strong terms teachings that<lb/> I consider inconsistent with religion in general&#44; and<lb/> Judaism in particular.  Upon hearing a denial of<lb/> God&#39;s absolute creative powers&#44; predicated on the lateste latest philosophical speculations&#44; or upon hearing reve&#45;<lb/>&#45;lation railed at&#44; where the Sinaic imparting is conspicuously at to view exhibited&#44; I was painfully affected&#44; and<lb/> I allowed let my feelings to draw from my lips con&#45;<lb/>&#45;demnations.  Not men&#44; but men&#39;s disloyalty&#44;<lb/> I denounced.  Still&#44; the preaching at which my a my censure aiming at certain preaching<lb/> censure aimed was construed into personalities&#59; zeal<lb/> was taken for bigotry&#59; warnings to my congregation<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>for excommunications against other Israelitish dissenting bodies.<lb/>  The latter resented as a premeditated offence&#44; what<lb/> was intended as a defence of the faith.  The mistake<lb/> gave rise to caustic remarks and heart burnings.  Experience has&#44;<lb/> however&#44; shown me the usefulness of complaints<lb/> about the deviation of those born in Israel from Holy<lb/> Writ&#44; whether in its doctrinal or ritual tenets.  Could<lb/> I indeed perceive a ray of hope that my words might<lb/> act as a restraint&#44; in any degree&#44; I would&#44; at any all<lb/> personal risks&#44; cry aloud and spare not&#44; but I recognize<lb/> the fact that individuals amidst surroundings&#44; which<lb/> urge an entire breaking away from the precepts of the five<lb/> inspired books and the historical truths they inculcate&#44;<lb/> will not be held back because I deprecate that<lb/> course.  Nevertheless&#44; with malice towards none&#44;<lb/> with charity for to all&#44; however falsely acting wrongfully in their proceedings&#44; I must<lb/> declare the advocacy of a settled del resolve to hallow a Sabbath&#44; which is not<lb/> in the Decalogue&#44; the advocacy of a Rosh Hashanah&#44; without<lb/> any of the ceremonies meant to stir up sacred<lb/> memories&#59; of a Yom Kippur&#44; conflicting with the<lb/> Scriptures and traditions&#59; the advocacy&#44; I say&#44;<lb/> of a reconstruction of the Mosaic holidays in an<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>anti&#45;Mosaic form&#44; and of a still quarter redacting of<lb/> Hebrew in public prayers&#44; until not a trace thereof<lb/> may be left&#44; I must pronounce such a scheme an<lb/> onslaught against the ancestral faith&#44; which ought should not to<lb/> go unnoticed&#44; though a rebuke avail nothing naught.  With a courage worthy of a better<lb/> cause&#44; all those changes and more yet have been championed&#44;<lb/> and now they are insisted upon with one avowedly ultimate<lb/> object&#45;&#45;to make the ranks of Jewish radicals swell with<lb/> Christian liberals.  Brethren.  Call this a Synagogue&#44; And that is interpreted as the perfor&#45;<lb/> or a temple&#45;&#45;never mind the name&#45;&#45;but strip it of the &#45;mance of Israel&#39;s mission among gentiles&#45;&#45;&#91;&#63;&#93; Judaism in<lb/> scroll order to popularize assemblages claiming a title which<lb/> does not rightfully apply to them.  Brethren.  Call<lb/> this a Synagogue&#44; or a temple&#45;&#45;never mind the name&#45;&#45;<lb/>but strip it of the yonder scroll of the Law&#59; hallow welcome in it Sun&#45;<lb/>&#45;day as the acknowledged day of public worship&#44; let the its<lb/> pulpit resound with the announcement novel doctrine that to fast on the<lb/> tenth of Tishri and implore pardon is to ascribe to God a <sic>revengful</sic> spirit&#44;<lb/> or that to admit our sons into the Abrahamic<lb/> covenant is an insult to the age in which we live in&#44;<lb/> and I will let the veriest dullard decide&#44; whether<lb/> this spot should be entitled to the appellation which<lb/> it bears.  No&#59; Mickv&#232; Israel&#44; Beth Israel&#44; or<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>even &#34;Keneseth Israel&#34; would most assuredly be mis&#45;<lb/>&#45;nomers.  I have read that persons have pointed as a clear evi&#45;<lb/>&#45;dence of an approximation to the church&#44; persons have<lb/> pointed to the modernizing of Divine services among<lb/> Hebrews&#44; in which men and women not of their creed<lb/> are given prominence&#59; also to weddings among Hebrews&#44;<lb/> strongly resembling the Episcopal&#59; to funerals among<lb/> Hebrews with and the borrowed ceremonies thereof&#44; beginning with the<lb/> inevitable oration at the head of the stairs&#44; and ending<lb/> at the grave with a conventional English sentence.<lb/>  How far this prurient wish to copy draw closer and closer to the stranger to our<lb/> belief will go&#44; it is impossible to predict&#44; seeing it<lb/> constantly on the increase.  Before Passover&#44; the corner stone of a new<lb/> Synagogue in Brooklyn was laid.  At times&#44; Masons&#44;<lb/> who claim profess to do all things with square and compass<lb/> and plumb line&#44; unexceptionally correctly to without exception&#44; building temples<lb/> to virtue&#44; and persons digging graves for vice&#44; they were brought into<lb/> requisition on such occasions&#59; at present&#44; church&#45;<lb/>men are asked to help us.  In Brooklyn&#44; Dr Hale&#44;<lb/> a leading clergyman of the Episcopal church&#44; was<lb/> the principal figure in the incident case to which I<lb/> have reference.  I cannot suppose that the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Reverend gentleman craved for the honor and sought<lb/> it.  He doubtless was solicited&#44; to accept the office so as to make<lb/> room for what a local journal wrote&#44; viz&#44; &#34;there has<lb/> been a remarkable crumbling away of denominational<lb/> walls in this vicinity of late.&#34;  For&#44; to all<lb/> appearances&#44; nothing pleases my brethren now<lb/> a days so much&#44; as their being made the subject of eulogy<lb/> in the secular press and in the church.  Every crumb<lb/> of laudation is gathered with the eagerness of famished<lb/> ones.  So accustomed to abuse has Israel been&#44; that it<lb/> hungers for praise.  I am not cynical&#59; I do<lb/> value the good opinion of my fellow creatures&#44; and re&#45;<lb/>&#45;joice when&#44; individually or collectively&#44; Israelites win<lb/> the respect of communities&#44; but this ceaseless quoting<lb/> of what Bishop A or Archbishop B says in exal&#45;<lb/>&#45;tation of the Jews&#44; of what Cardinal G. or Monsei&#45;<lb/>&#45;gneur H. tells of the debt civilization owes the Jews<lb/> for the birth of the man of Nazareth&#44; and the apostle&#45;<lb/>&#45;ship of his disciples&#44; all of that is abhorrent to<lb/> my nature.  A noted sensationalist among<lb/> the clergy&#44; who from Philadelphia removed to<lb/> New York&#44; delivered a harangue in his usual<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>declamatory style&#44; to prove that not all Jews<lb/> are unmannerly&#44; and all Jewesses loud&#44; that he him&#45;<lb/>&#45;self reckons among his acquaintances members<lb/> of the ancient race&#44; whom any no one might be glad could be ashamed<lb/> to acknowledge as friends.  Immediately&#44; our Week&#45;<lb/>&#45;lies seized upon those utterances&#44; and with a flou&#45;<lb/>&#45;rish reported the liberal preacher of the Reformed<lb/> Dutch Church.  Still&#44; neither the testimony of<lb/> Mr Peter that we are not ill&#45;bred&#44; nor the assertion<lb/> of Mr Paul that we are not obtrusive&#44; prevents cir&#45;<lb/>&#45;culars being sent far and wide to notify Hebrews<lb/> that they will not be allowed a room in summer<lb/> resorts&#44; where the gentry among Christians spends<lb/> the season.  I have it on reliable au&#45;<lb/>&#45;thority that some who braggarts who glory in repudiating dietary laws&#44; as<lb/> ordered in Leviticus and Deuteronomy&#59; some families who would regard<lb/> it an offence to be placed in the same category<lb/> with Orthodox Jews&#44; were refused admission to<lb/> sea sides and mountains&#44; notwithstanding their protes&#45;<lb/>&#45;tations of liberality.  Misguided brethren&#33;  You<lb/> fancy to have killed prejudice dead&#44; by letting<lb/> the world know that you have nothing in common<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>that your sub ambition is &#34;to stand at the head of Reform Judaism in this and other countries&#44;&#34;<lb/> with the followers of Moses and the Rabbis&#44; In vain&#33;<lb/> vain endeavours&#33;  Prejudice will not down because of them the thrusts you give your parents&#39; belief.  It rises unappraised by your<lb/> servility again and again to annoy&#44; to frighten you&#59;<lb/> not alone in Russia&#44; the land &#34;of darkness&#44; as dark&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness itself&#34;&#44; but even here where the light of freedom<lb/> has shone brilliantly.  Why then wast faculties&#44; ca&#45;<lb/>&#45;pacities&#44; learning&#44; eloquence&#44; influence on trifles things that<lb/> profit us not&#44; when our dearest interests demand from one and all a<lb/> concentration of powers. from one and all  Let us<lb/> unite our forces to noble purposes&#44; not scatter them<lb/> for ignoble ends&#45;&#45;to create schisms.  Instead of<lb/> demolishing the fabric which has served us as a<lb/> common shelter during so many ages&#44; let us bend our<lb/> energies on the strengthening of it.  We are faced<lb/> just now by a problem growing more intricate every<lb/> hour.  The deepest thoughts&#44; the kindest feelings&#44;<lb/> the strongest most sagacious combination of human contrivances are needed<lb/> to ease some of its appalling difficulties.  We must<lb/> help socially and politically throngs of the per&#45;<lb/>&#45;secuted in our race&#44; who seek American shores.<lb/>  You cannot thrust compel them back&#44; nor ignore them.  If They<lb/> circumstances would suffer you to do so will remain&#44; and you cannot avert your eyes from their multitudes.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>A generation will not have passed away&#44; before<lb/> the despised ones will constitute the bulk of the He&#45;<lb/>&#45;brew population from the Atlantic to the Pacific.<lb/>  We must determine whether they shall represent<lb/> the olden faith intelligently&#44; honorably&#44; or whe&#45;<lb/>&#45;ther unhappy divisions in our camp will drive<lb/> some outside of Judaism the Jewish fold&#44; and confirm others in their<lb/> clannishness&#44; superstitious and vulgar unrefined habits.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93; I exclaim with Isaiah&#58; &#34;Bless&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed be ye who sow seeds wherever water flows&#44;&#34; you<lb/> who leave nothing untried which may improve and<lb/> uplift the lowly.  You are the builders of our future<lb/> communities in this land of liberty and prosperity.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Through you &#34;my people will abide in peace&#44; in dwellings<lb/> of security ease&#44; of tranquil quiet repose&#59;&#34; and to conclude in the<lb/> language of the same inspired orator&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;The work of charity shall be happiness&#44; and the<lb/> exertions of charity tranquility and security<lb/> for ever more.&#34;  And so may it be.<lb/>  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
