<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF2_19</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_19_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_19_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_19_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_19_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_19_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_19_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_19_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_19_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_19_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_19_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_19_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_19_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Delivered on the 2d anniversary<lb/>
                of the Society for preventing cruelty<lb/>
                to children<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>You will pardon me&#44; Ladies and Gentlemen&#44; if instead<lb/> of addressing those who are present&#44; I direct my words<lb/> to persons who have stayed away.  I take it for<lb/> granted&#44; that croakers did not put in an appearance<lb/> at a meeting&#44; where the actors in a human under&#45;<lb/>&#45;taking&#44; exchange gratulations as the sole&#45;reward for<lb/> their good deeds.  Still&#44; individuals who habi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tually grumble may be reached by proxy.  We all<lb/> know of such.  The lugubrious looks they put on&#44;<lb/> their uniform lamentations over a social degeneracy&#44; point<lb/> them out.  Thus&#44; the little I mean to tell here&#44; being<lb/> repeated outside&#44; may perhaps enter unwilling ears.<lb/>  But....I must beg your pardon again.  Is it not<lb/> myself that wishes to lecture to absent fault&#45;finders.<lb/>  A preacher of much higher authority and wider experience<lb/> than a local minister&#44; calls them by the title of shallow&#45;<lb/>minded and foolish people.  The unenviable epi&#45;<lb/>&#45;thet may be seen imprinted in very legible characters in<lb/> a book written for a universal application.  He that runs<lb/> may read this sentence&#58; &#34;Do not say&#44; how it is that former<lb/> days were better than these&#44; for it is not wisdom that asketh<lb/> the question.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>You perceive&#58; it is plain talk.  One would<lb/> scarcely expect it from a preacher who lived upwards of<lb/> twenty five centuries ago.  And if he who moralized<lb/> in that fashion was really Solomon&#44; whose reign<lb/> has been described as the happiest to the Hebrew nation&#44;<lb/> when all sat at ease under their vines and fig&#45;trees&#44; and<lb/> silver could be obtained in larger quantities than even<lb/> in the United States of America after resumption&#44; the<lb/> rebuke has a more ringing sound.  It makes the ears<lb/> tingle with the preacher&#39;s cry against a circumstance<lb/> discreditable to human nature.  Persons who will<lb/> deliberately shut their eyes&#44; while the sun is bright<lb/> and cheering&#44; so that they may complain of the<lb/> dismal gloom prevailing&#44; have always existed.<lb/>  It does not matter that the social family is mani&#45;<lb/>&#45;festly improving.  It does not matter that excellent<lb/> men and women work to dislodge wrong from the<lb/> place where it is <sic>ensconsed</sic>&#44; and try to raise Right upon<lb/> a lofty pedestal&#44; the sullen noun will still be uttered.<lb/>  &#34;Oh&#33; for the good old times&#33;  What has been accomplished in<lb/> our days that begins to compare with the doings of our<lb/> grand&#45;fathers&#63;  Why&#44; the troubles now felt everywhere&#44; were<lb/> unknown then.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Well&#58; this murmuring might be attributed to a lack<lb/> of sense&#44; and thus be explained.  Ignorance is apt to<lb/> canonize the past&#44; and stigmatise the present as pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;fane.  But I search somewhat deeper&#44; and discover<lb/> that the sin&#45;&#45;I call it by its proper name&#45;&#45;the sin<lb/> lies in a measure at the door of the learned&#59; else they we<lb/> would not hear songs of praise to heroic eras.  The<lb/> learned by placing in the foreground peoples and<lb/> countries incomparably our inferiors&#59; peoples and<lb/> countries that ought to occupy a back seat on the<lb/> stage of the world&#44; contributes to keep up a notion&#44;<lb/> which does much injustice to the age we live in&#44; and<lb/> to our land&#44; which is confessedly a great motive power<lb/> in the march of social progress.  I blush for<lb/> mankind&#44; when Sparta and Rome are instanced as<lb/> models to students of history.  Gladly would I<lb/> hinder the young from receiving baneful impressions.<lb/>  Shall we extol a training which reared children as<lb/> savage hyenas&#44; which fired the civilized barbarian with<lb/> the ambition to dye himself in blood at a hand to hand<lb/> fight for the plaudits of inhuman spectators&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Or was it a virtue to expose children to cold&#44; that<lb/> the healthiest might be inured to hardships&#44; and the<lb/> feeblest be consigned to an early grave&#63;  Is the feeding<lb/> of all with the vilest of victuals that they might never<lb/> crave for dainties&#44; to command universal approval&#63;  Is<lb/> the winking at covert dishonesty by which foreign ene&#45;<lb/>&#45;mies should be overreached to be greatly admired&#63;  Is<lb/> the ruling of our sons and daughters with rigor&#44; or the<lb/> selling of them like chattel a theme to be rehearsed<lb/> in flowing rhymes&#63;  Nor Greek &#38; Latin volumes<lb/> alone disclose a state of society unworthy of the effusions<lb/> of poetry.  The history of much later periods obviously<lb/> demonstrates the superiority of the nineteenth century<lb/> and of the country made free by which the wise hearted made free.<lb/>  The Swiss who declared he could not deny quarter<lb/> to one speaking his language has been superseded<lb/> by Americans&#44; who will go in quest of both hapless natives<lb/> and strangers&#44; and will shelter&#44; sustain and protect any<lb/> creature&#44; who possesses endowed with the divine gift of speech.<lb/>  We owe it to ourselves to show the young&#44; the develop&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment of the principles of Righteousness&#44; whose practical<lb/> application gives our century preeminence&#44; and which will deservedly<lb/> entitle it hereafter to the name of &#34;a golden age&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>School&#45;books ought to mark very clearly between<lb/> a fancied glory&#44; and a real greatness&#59; thus making<lb/> our children appreciate what has been done by the<lb/> good and true&#44; to cleanse patriotism form the dross<lb/> of selfishness&#59; to sanctify home&#44; as the laboratory of<lb/> ennobling thoughts&#59; as the seat of comfort&#44; at which<lb/> strength will be gathered to fight the battles of<lb/> Right against Wrong&#44; and from whence many will<lb/> issue forth and gain immortality by devoting their ener&#45;<lb/>&#45;gies to the service of a broad humanity.<lb/></p>
            <p>Let croakers behold that greatness&#44; as partly revealed<lb/> in the working of &#34;a Society for the prevention of cruelty<lb/> to children&#44;&#34; a working of philanthropy reverting withal<lb/> the bond of fraternization among the zealous colaborers.<lb/>  Ladies and Gentlemen.  I was painfully affected&#44;<lb/> though not surprised&#44; to read that the accursed vice<lb/> of drunkenness is at the root of the evil&#44; you strive<lb/> to lessen.  And I can unfortunately predict that yours<lb/> will be a herculean task&#59; for the votaries of the debasing<lb/> infatuation&#44; receive encouragement from municipal laws un&#45;<lb/>&#45;enforced and inoperative.  But how higher your merit&#44; when<lb/> undaunted by obstacles you snatch precious souls out of an unholy fire.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>The sight of quivering flesh torn by the rod of brutal<lb/> masters&#44; inspired the compassionate thought which forged<lb/> thousands of shields to screen a dumb creature&#59; the ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;posure of sentient beings to a pitiless treatment from<lb/> unnatural guardians&#59; the dread of a fatal misapplica&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion of faculties&#44; as they unfold in the minds of the young&#44;<lb/> created a sacred legion.  It vowed to rescue the innocent&#44;<lb/> to elevate man&#39;s character&#44; and deliver society from an<lb/> oppressive incubus.<lb/></p>
            <p>I am thankful for the success thus far attained by<lb/> an organization&#44; whose views I advocated three years ago<lb/> in an inaugural address.  I am thankful not as<lb/> representing the victory of any denominational doctrines&#44;<lb/> nor the triumph of my belief dogmatic belief&#59; though the<lb/> religion I profess&#44; first taught mankind that the<lb/> proper training of children is the sustaining pillar of<lb/> the social edifice&#44; and that mercy is a Supreme act<lb/> of reverence.  But as a member of the human race family&#44;<lb/> I delight in and hail every improvement that widens<lb/> the sphere of modern civilization.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>If I command the century and the country&#44; I live in&#44;<lb/> it is not from a desire to copy a practice quite rife in<lb/> our midst&#45;boasting&#45;&#45;a practice&#44; as much to be shunned<lb/> as the habit of croaking.  But I pay the present a<lb/> just meed of praise because walking in the light of<lb/> history&#44; I see that we have distanced classic Greece and<lb/> imperial Rome and all heroic eras.  We have drawn as a body nearer to<lb/> the standard of Righteousness&#44; by which we all shall<lb/> be judged.  That notwithstanding our on&#45;<lb/>&#45;ward march&#44; an appalling amount of vice and crime con&#45;<lb/>&#45;fronts us by the way&#44; I readily admit.  But I am a<lb/> strong believer in the law of progress&#44; as the English bard<lb/> expresses it.  &#34;Yet I doubt not through the ages&#44; one increasing<lb/> purpose runs&#58; And the thoughts of men are evidenced with the<lb/> process of the suns.&#34;  Never will I despair of the future<lb/> of my race.  To harbor doubts about our perfectibility&#44;<lb/> would be to offend the good laborers in the cause of hu&#45;<lb/>manity.  Ladies and Gentlemen.  I wish you God&#45;<lb/>speed.  May the time arrive when your joint endeavours<lb/> will be crowned with the highest success&#59; when<lb/> &#34;A society for the prevention of cruelty to children&#44;&#34;<lb/> will no more be needed no more.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
