<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF4_14</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_14_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_14_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_14_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_14_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_14_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_14_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_14_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_14_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_14_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_14_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_14_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_14_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_14_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_14_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_14_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_14_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Post&#45;Biblical<lb/>
                34.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Not unsuitable is the comparison&#44; which Dr.<lb/> Morris J. Raphall has drawn in his post&#45;biblical<lb/> history between &#34;the reign of terror&#34; in the capital<lb/> of France during the revolution in the last century against King Louis XVI&#44;<lb/> and the political condition of Judea about the year 68<lb/> of the common era.  In both instances the worst pas&#45;<lb/>&#45;sions were let loose&#44; and innocent blood flowed like<lb/> rivers.  Many of the zealots in Jerusalem antici&#45;<lb/>&#45;pated the unscrupulous and <sic>ferocius</sic> behaviour of<lb/> the Jacobins of Paris.  Still&#44; it would be unjust<lb/> to consider all alike&#44; and brand them as lawless<lb/> ruffians.  Beyond doubt&#44; the ranks of the zealots<lb/> were filled with noble hearted men&#44; men ready to lay down<lb/> their lives for their country&#44; but a large number<lb/> were also unprincipled rebels&#44; eager to take advantage<lb/> of a state of anarchy.  Barione or robbers&#44; as<lb/> well as securii or assassins&#44; is the name by which<lb/> the Talmud distinguishes such&#44; occasionally alluding<lb/> to their seizing other people&#39;s property&#44; and attacking<lb/> the unsuspecting.  Those dangerous men were largely<lb/> found in the capital&#44; specially after the whole of Galilee<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>had fallen into the hand of the Romans.<lb/></p>
            <p>For whoever could escape fled to Jerusalem&#44; and<lb/> this city&#44; always vastly populated&#44; was then crowded<lb/> to excess with the inhabitants of different parts of<lb/> Judea&#44; who differed also in temper and in purpose.<lb/>  Among the refugees came John of Giskala&#44; about<lb/> whose character&#44; opinions are greatly at variance.<lb/>  for While Josephus&#44; his personal enemy&#44; paints him<lb/> that chief of the Zealots in the darkest colors&#44; others<lb/> have represented him as a bright model of patrio&#45;<lb/>&#45;tism.  He was received with an ovation by<lb/> the uncompromising anti&#45;Roman party&#44; for&#44; hatred<lb/> against a foreign power had grown more intense<lb/> since Jotapata&#44; Gamala and other moutnainous<lb/> cities which seemed impregnable&#44; had been stormed<lb/> and conquered by the enemy.  But unhappily<lb/> the union of feelings indispensable for making<lb/> an attempt&#44; at least&#44; to resistance&#44; was sadly<lb/> wanting.  The zealots saw&#44; or fancied to see<lb/> in everyone who did not fully share their views<lb/> an enemy to the cause of independence.  The mistaken<lb/> zeal of some&#44; the deliberate wickedness of others&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>plunged the metropolis into a civil war.  When<lb/> men of social standing&#44; men of influence&#44; men whose<lb/> only fault was that they had means at their command&#44;<lb/> were cast into prisons&#44; and then killed by order of a<lb/> self&#45;constituted &#34;assembly&#44;&#34; not unlike that under the<lb/> control of Robespierre&#44; and Danton and Marat&#44; the people arose<lb/> against so fierce a tyranny.  Once person deser&#45;<lb/>&#45;vedly esteemed stirred up multitudes.  Haudin or<lb/> Anamus&#44; was a temporal officer&#44; and also a priest gifted<lb/> with an eloquence to which sincerity and uprightness<lb/> lent additional force.  He exhorted his countrymen<lb/> to shake off the yoke of a faction&#44; more unsupport&#45;<lb/>&#45;able than even that of the Romans.  His words arou&#45;<lb/>&#45;sed a spirit of determination to put an end to<lb/> the reign of terror inaugurated by many of the Zealots.<lb/>  The latter prepared to fight&#44; but overpowered by a su&#45;<lb/>&#45;perior number&#44; they retreated within the first enclosure<lb/> of the Temple.  Anamus prompted by pious<lb/> motives ordered a cessation of arms.  He would not pol&#45;<lb/>lute the house of God with slain.  In chastising<lb/> the zealots his object had been to check their violence&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>and compel them to submit to rules&#44; but his<lb/> generosity cost him&#44; his associates and the country<lb/> very dearly.  For&#44; the zealots who had been blockaded<lb/> and watchfully guarded within the precincts of the<lb/> Temple&#44; succeeded in eluding detection&#44; and stealthily<lb/> sent a message to southern Jews&#44; living in Idumea.<lb/>  Those Jews&#44; originally heathens&#44; but converted to Judaism<lb/> through the unwise policy of John Hyrcanus&#44; the<lb/> Asmonean&#44; were a fair specimen of the adventurers<lb/> of the middle ages&#44; who hired themselves to any<lb/> party that held out a promise of gain.  Worthy<lb/> compatriots of Herod&#44; they flew to arms and 20&#44;000 strong<lb/> and mocked at the gates of Jerusalem to enter and<lb/> spill blood.  Ananus found himself shut up<lb/> between the fiery zealots and the murderous Idumeans.  What<lb/> followed is too harrowing to relate&#45;&#45;a night in which<lb/> the heavens appeared to hurl down curses upon<lb/> brothers killing brothers within sight of the Holy of Holies&#44;<lb/> was the night which succeeded the arrival of the Idu&#45;<lb/>&#45;means.  Peal on peal of deep thunders made the very<lb/> earth quake&#44; and when morning dawned&#44; it lighted upon<lb/> a slaughter.  The highest and most renowned<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>were pierced through by the arrow and the sword&#44;<lb/> and Ananus shared the fate of his illustrious com&#45;<lb/>panions.  A distinguished citizen called Zechariah&#44;<lb/> whose wealth had given the irrepressible zealots<lb/> umbrage&#44; was summoned before a Sanhedrin&#44; gotten<lb/> up for the purpose&#44; and accused of high treasonable<lb/> intercourse with Rome.  He easily proved his innocence and was acquitted&#44; but<lb/> two of the Barion&#232;&#44; the overbearing ruffians of whom<lb/> the Talmud speaks&#44; stabbed him&#44; as he was leaving<lb/> the court&#44; after they had treated the his judges with<lb/> shocking indignity.<lb/></p>
            <p>The conduct of John of Giskala under all those<lb/> sorrowful circumstances admits of a doubt.  To<lb/> believe Josephus&#44; he was plotting with the most violent of among the<lb/> zealots&#44; while professing friendship for Ananus and<lb/> the party of law and order.  But as Josephus was not<lb/> an eye witness of what happened then in the capital&#44;<lb/> since he had escaped to the Romans and enjoyed<lb/> their protection&#44; we may incline to judge the<lb/> Galilean chief more favorably.  It is not unlikely<lb/> that after the departure of the Idumeans&#44; who returned<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>to their country by reason of the ferocities atrocities<lb/> practised in Jerusalem&#44; at which even they revolted&#44;<lb/> John Giskala assumed absolute power to control<lb/> the zealots.  He certainly possessed military<lb/> abilities and personal qualities calculated to win<lb/> followers&#44; but a Joshua&#44; could not&#44; without a mi&#45;<lb/>&#45;racle&#44; have curbed spirits wild with mistakenly false&#44;<lb/> or wickedly destructive&#44; notions.  Feuds and quarrels<lb/> within the ranks of the zealots were a constant<lb/> occurrence&#44; and in the midst of them another self&#45;<lb/>appointed leader arose to add to the misery.<lb/></p>
            <p>Simon son of Gioras was at a fortress in Massada&#44;<lb/> situated on the South Western side of the Dead Sea&#44; when<lb/> he heard of the events&#44; which had given John of Giskala<lb/> the opportunity to take up the command.  Simon<lb/> was young&#44; of great physical strength&#44; courageous&#44;<lb/> daring and regardless of the means by which he<lb/> could gratify his ambition.  Among the zealots<lb/> he stood foremost as the sworn foe of Rome and of<lb/> her partizans&#45;&#45;the moderates&#44; as we might call<lb/> them&#44; or the peace&#45;party.  The son of Giorus<lb/> having left Massada&#44; gathered around him<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>all who had nothing to lose&#44; promised liberty<lb/> to slaves&#44; high wages of freemen.  Every day<lb/> the number of his followers swelled&#44; some joined<lb/> him out of fear&#44; some out of hope of gain&#44; and some<lb/> also out of admiration for his surpassing intrepidity.<lb/>  He raised an army&#44; and with it he threw himself<lb/> into the mountains&#44; forced his entrance into cities&#44;<lb/> fought back whatever dared oppose his movements&#44;<lb/> took rich spoil and left everywhere behind<lb/> the traces of his audacious will.  In Idumea<lb/> he met with stout resistance&#44; and his boldness<lb/> was put to a severe test&#44; but the treachery of<lb/> an Idumean made him victorious.  Success into&#45;<lb/>&#45;xicated Simon to a degree that he carried devasta&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion through the whole south of Palestine&#44; and<lb/> dashed down to the very gates of Jerusalem.<lb/>  The zealots&#44; who adhered to John of Giskala&#44; haras&#45;<lb/>&#45;sed Simon outside of the city walls&#44; and took his<lb/> wife a prisoner.  They thought that the husband to recover<lb/> the woman he fondly loved&#44; her husband would sue<lb/> for peace&#44; but he grew furious&#44; slew all that came<lb/> near him&#44; and swore that he would break down the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>walls and spare no one&#44; unless his wife<lb/> was restored to him uninjured.  The people saw<lb/> his dread earnestness and let his wife go free.<lb/>  Simon son of Geiras withdrew them&#44; for a time&#44; to<lb/> Idumea.<lb/></p>
            <p>Vespasian looked on with <sic>complancence</sic>&#44; and<lb/> reasoned himself against making a strong effort<lb/> to be<sic>seige</sic> Jerusalem.  &#34;Let opposite parties<lb/> tear each other&#44; and when weakened enough I<lb/> shall secure an easy conquest.&#34;  So must the Ro&#45;<lb/>&#45;man general have argued&#44; and to cut off any<lb/> chance of assistance which the capital might<lb/> receive&#44; he and the warlike Placidus&#44; scoured<lb/> all the country around with the besom of<lb/> destruction.  In vain the fugitives of<lb/> Gadara attempted to turn on their pursuers.<lb/>  They were impetuously set upon near the river Jor&#45;<lb/>&#45;dan when at spring tide its water swiftly overflowed<lb/> its banks.  But no Joshua was there to bid<lb/> the Jordan turn backward.  The ri historic river<lb/> which had ebbed away at the approach of<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>at the priests carrying the ark of the Lord&#44;<lb/> swelled on before the unhappy people of Gadara.<lb/>  Thousands found a grave where the successor of<lb/> Moses had raised the his twelve memorial stones&#44;<lb/> thousands were killed and multitudes dragged<lb/> the chains of captivity.  Bent upon lea&#45;<lb/>&#45;ving Jerusalem isolated&#44; Roman legions carried the<lb/> fire and sword through all the surrounding regions.<lb/>  Antipatrus&#44; Lydda&#44; Jammia&#45;&#45;cities famous in<lb/> Jewish literature&#45;&#45;forcibly submitted to a gal&#45;<lb/>&#45;ling yoke.  Woe to those who refused to<lb/> surrender&#44; no trace of their homes would remain<lb/> behind the army which like swarms of locusts<lb/> consumed every thing.  At Jericho&#44;&#45;&#45;fraught<lb/> with <sic>remiscences</sic> of God&#39;s wonders&#45;&#45;the soldiers<lb/> of Rome pitched at length their tents.  Judea<lb/> saw the plains of Jericho filled studded with<lb/> barracks stretched out by the enemy of a strange<lb/> language that had come from after.  The<lb/> delicious gardens and broad leaved palm trees<lb/> of the spot first conquered by the redeemed of<lb/> Egypt&#44; were enjoyed by the nation&#44; that<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>came flying like an eagle&#44; and thirsting but for<lb/> rapine and carnage.  The prediction<lb/> of our arch prophet registered in the 28th chap. of Deuteronomy were but too literally<lb/> fulfilled&#44; even before the final dispersion&#44;<lb/> which he also foretold&#44; became a sorrowful fact.<lb/>  We shall yet be brought face to face with  made to contemplate<lb/> the events that brought on the burning of<lb/> the Temple and the scattering of our people<lb/> from one end of the earth to its opposite end.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
