<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF2_15</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1880" source="" attested="yes">1880</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_15_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_15_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_15_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_15_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_15_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_15_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_15_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_15_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_15_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_15_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_15_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_15_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For the 20th anniversary<lb/>
                of the 7th st Synagogue.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  The days of childhood have passed&#44; and<lb/> the age of maturity is drawing close.  The portion<lb/> of the Law designated for this Sabbath&#44; and with<lb/> which the book of Numbers begins&#44; is that which was<lb/> first read in our new Synagogue last twenty years ago.<lb/>  It being so&#44; we should act like anxious parents towards<lb/> their sons when approaching majority&#45;&#45;provide for<lb/> the future&#59; try all means which a good understanding<lb/> and honesty suggest&#44; so that the temporal position of the<lb/> object of our affection may be well secured.<lb/></p>
            <p>I know that I am probing a sore&#44; nor do I forget that I<lb/> almost pledged myself not to touch it any more&#44; for<lb/> fear that instead of affecting a cure&#44; I may hurt my<lb/> own self&#59; or to speak plainly&#44; lest I raise a suspicion<lb/> as to my ulterior motive.  But there are considerations which riseing<lb/> above personal feelings&#59; which and these latter&#44; after all&#44; are but a species<lb/> of selfishness.  My attachment to the principles which<lb/> this building represents&#44; urges me to face adverse criticism&#44;<lb/> to risk even being tauntingly called the interested party.<lb/></p>
            <p>In consulting my register of the deaths occurring in the<lb/> congregation&#44; I perceive with painful concern that during<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>the past twelvemonth we have sustained severer<lb/> losses than ordinarily.  Contributors to the maintenance<lb/> of our worship&#45;&#45;some prominent and generous&#44; others oc&#45;<lb/>&#45;cupying with regularity the seats they held&#44; have gone to<lb/> their lasting reward.  Unhappily&#44; the instances in which<lb/> children supply the places left vacant by their deceased<lb/> parents is are rare in our midst.  Were it otherwise&#44; had the sons and daughters of Hebrews once actively engaged in upholding our sacred organizations&#44; identified themselves with us we would<lb/> now be very flourishing.  Besides&#44; a spirit of liberality&#44;<lb/> always to be praised&#44; induces the directors of this sacred in&#45; dwelling of<lb/> &#45;stitution prayer&#44; to admit here all who plead inability to give<lb/> it support&#45;&#45;though I while commending that course&#44; I can&#45;<lb/>&#45;not forbear remarking that those who are so considerately<lb/> treated&#44; might help to swell the number of attendants<lb/> at all times&#44; and not simply on Sabbath and Holiday&#45;morn&#45;<lb/>&#45;ings.  Then&#44; again&#44; several removals to another<lb/> city have lately injured this Synagogue quite materially.<lb/>  One needs not therefore possess a keen discernment to<lb/> foretell the final issue&#44; which&#44; I fervently pray to God&#44; may be<lb/> ar averted.  But I said it last week&#44; and I repeat it<lb/> now&#44; we must confide in a kind Providence&#44; but act<lb/> energetically withal and not rely on miracles &#91;Hebrew&#93; have taught our Rabbis.  &#34;It is not right to reckon upon wonders supernatural events&#34; and David wrote<lb/> &#34;Trust in the Lord&#44; but do right&#34; is the teachings of the Scriptures.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>We must exercise the judgment the Almighty has en&#45; gifted<lb/> &#45;dowed us with to good advantage&#44; in order to prevent<lb/> in time the downfall of conservatism&#44; of which this edifice<lb/> is a bulwark.  Specially the men of Israel entrusted with<lb/> the government of a Congregation must study deeply to<lb/> ward off dangers.  &#34;Those who are busy in public matters<lb/> should busy themselves to a glorious end&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; recommend the Rabbis Sages&#44; and they add&#58; &#34;then<lb/> paternal merits will assist them&#44; and their righteousness<lb/> will endure for ever&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> But not all the measures which the chosen repre&#45;<lb/>&#45;sentatives of our Congregation adopted&#44; have tended to<lb/> benefit it&#44; some have unwittingly crippled its means powers.  It would be<lb/> idle&#44; if not ungracious&#44; to allude to an irremediable<lb/> past&#59; suffice to say that it behooves those in whose<lb/> hands the fit future of this religious body is committed&#44;<lb/> to avoid miscalculations&#44; and to bestow the closest and<lb/> most anxious attention&#45;&#45;for the undertaking is holy&#45;&#45;on<lb/> a plan by which a threatening slowly but perceptibly advancing evil may be grappled<lb/> with and conquered overcome.  There is no denying&#58; we are grow&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing fewer in number&#44; and we may apprehend a gradual<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>decrease still more from material causes.  But<lb/> while many who can aid in upholding this mode of worship live<lb/> among us&#44; let them be asked to give when the time ar&#45;<lb/>&#45;rives that it may be so done honorably without the slightest breach of a triennial agreement&#59; let them be<lb/> asked to give again annually what was not at all<lb/> descried complained of as an exaction in former years&#59; let them no more<lb/> receive an unsolicited favor in the shape of a reduction<lb/> of their yearly contributions.  So long as a free Sy&#45;<lb/>&#45;nagouge endowed by the wealthiest must remain a <sic>eutopian</sic> idea&#44; let Israelites<lb/> who can afford it ought to compensate for the many others who are<lb/> able to offer only a mite or who can offer nothing.<lb/>  We need these children of our faith.  We need them imperatively.  They form a most important element<lb/> in the preservation of historical Judaism.  May the day<lb/> never arrive when&#44; the Aristocratic few will constitute a Congregation in Israel&#44; when the bearing of the large<lb/> contributors to the material support of the Synagogue&#44;<lb/> will deter those who can enter it only with a seedy<lb/> and threadbare garments from crossing its threshold.<lb/>  We should continue the policy which has marked out and<lb/> therefore distinguished for real nobility&#44; the Congregation organized body called<lb/> &#34;Mikv&#233; Israel&#44;&#34; even if our assets can never come near<lb/> those of corporations that pride themselves on a surplus<lb/> of thousands&#44; after having fed emeritus officials&#44; singers and players&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>But we must absolutely endeavour that the outlay<lb/> shall not&#44; as at present&#44; exceed the income.  A course<lb/> so ruinous&#44;&#45;&#45;which would hasten the downfall of any pri&#45;<lb/>&#45;vate individual&#44; will inevitably occasion also the over&#45;<lb/>&#45;throw of a congregation.  Economy is commendably practised by our managers&#59; none<lb/> and none can bring a charge of extravagance&#45;&#45;only what preserves the building.<lb/>  and only what pe ensures an attendance at the worship&#44;<lb/> and ensures the comfort of the <sic>worshippers</sic> being expended.<lb/>  But with a burden which weighs heavily upon us&#44;<lb/> difficulties difficulties have have necessarily to be encountered&#44; despite<lb/> retirement and a final return to the original seat&#45;<lb/>rent.<lb/></p>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  In two years to come&#44; a memorable event<lb/> will be celebrated&#45;&#45;the centennial jubilee anniversary of this Congregation.<lb/>  In thanking God the Almighty who has been with the children<lb/> as He was with the fathers&#59; in pouring forth united<lb/> praises to the Lord and Legislator&#44; whose laws have<lb/> found faithful interpreters in this religious body&#44;<lb/> during an uninterrupted period of a hundred years&#44;<lb/> we ought to present betake ourselves before Him with a gift&#44;<lb/> enter His courts with a present.  We should give over<lb/> to Israel&#39;s God the house called after by His holy name&#44;<lb/> and rescue it from the hands of a non&#45;Jewish Association.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>That will in very deed be a cause for spiritual<lb/> gratulation.  Not alone we shall we have rolled away<lb/> a reproach&#44; but we shall have&#44; as far as human<lb/> foresight can provide&#44; we shall have raised a high<lb/> peace to prevent the destruction of traditional Judaism&#44;<lb/> as entrusted to posterity by the men who established<lb/> a sacred organization under the significant title of<lb/> &#34;Hope of Israel.&#34;  Relieved from an oppressive<lb/> load&#44; our successors will move on with ease.  The<lb/> facilities which&#44; freedom from an untoward obligation&#44;<lb/> aye&#58; from an unwarra sacrilegious debt&#44; will be enabled<lb/> to offer all classes of Hebrews&#44; drawing hither the middle classes and the poor&#44; as well as the affluent&#44; will perpetuate the service<lb/> of our God&#44; to the benefit of the olden faith&#44; and to the<lb/> glory of the Sinaic revelation.  Such is the<lb/> ardent wish&#59; such is the fervent prayer of an<lb/> humble leader of the far remnant of believers&#44; on this Sab&#45;<lb/>&#45;bath&#44; the twentieth anniversary of our comely Synagogue<lb/> Grant my desire and my petition&#59; Thou who search&#45;<lb/>&#45;est the heart&#44; bless the efforts of Thy servant&#44; and<lb/> the exertions of his co&#45;workers.  Infuse a spirit of reve&#45;<lb/>&#45;rence and love into the hearts of the attendants at this house.<lb/>  &#38;c &#38;c &#40;The lecture will was continued at some length&#41;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
