<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF1_4</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_4_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_4_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_4_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_4_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_4_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_4_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_4_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_4_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_4_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_4_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_4_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_4_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_4_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_4_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_4_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_4_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For the opening of the month<lb/>
                Elul<lb/></p>
            
            <p>One of my early lectures<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Shall the cornet be sounded in<lb/> a city and the people be not afraid&#63;  Shall there<lb/> be evil in a city&#44; and the Lord hath not done it&#34;&#63;<lb/>  &#40;Amos 111. 6.&#41;  Brethren&#33;  After an intermission<lb/> of unusual length&#44; I resume the task&#44; to which<lb/> I am impelled by duty.  <del>Shall</del> Will it ever be<lb/> made a labor of love&#63;  Will those I address<lb/> timely and earnestly illustrate in their <del>religious</del> demeanour<lb/> the efficacy of my public teaching&#63;  How unutterable<lb/> the satisfaction I would feel in pointing out<lb/> their spiritual progress&#33;  How grateful to<lb/> your ears&#44; my dear friends&#33; to listen to an<lb/> acknowledgment of your success in the pursuit<lb/> of righteousness&#33;  But a result so greatly<lb/> to be desired&#44; has not yet been derived from my<lb/> public humble instruction.  Without an assumed humility<lb/> I declare my exhortations hitherto quite ineffectual.<lb/>  Even at the risk of meeting with the disappro&#45;<lb/>&#45;val of some who may have grown weary<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>of my oft repeated <del>complaints</del> admonitions&#44; I will say it&#63;<lb/> The house of God continues <del>to be</del> deserted.<lb/></p>
            <p>Again and again have I of late stood here vainly<lb/> to wait for the prescribed number&#59; that we might<lb/> hold worship in holy communion.  I cast no<lb/> reproach on them who have bid their homes a<lb/> temporary farewell&#44; to seek relaxation in some<lb/> more genial spots&#59;&#45;&#45;though&#44; alas&#33; in the majo&#45;<lb/>&#45;rity of instances it is <del>at the sacrifice</del> in violation of our time&#45;<lb/>honored practices.  Nor can I charge them with<lb/> neglect whom a great distance prevents visiting<lb/> these hallowed courts with more frequency than once<lb/> on the Sabbath <del>morning</del>&#59; but I grieve especially to<lb/> perceive the apathy of our youths &#38; the heedlessness of their parents.  Many<lb/> who&#44; not long since&#44; appeared joyful at having<lb/> reached the period&#44; which entitles them to be<lb/> counted among the Congregation of the Lord&#44; set<lb/> now little or no value upon that privilege.<lb/>  They prefer to it what may yield a momentary<lb/> diversion&#59; &#38; their natural guardians utter no complaint.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Thus is our God denied the worship&#44; for the<lb/> public performance of which&#44; we dedicated this<lb/> sightly structure to His holy name.  And<lb/> whereas to the merit <del>accruing</del> flowing from their attending<lb/> Divine service&#44; our youths would add a thorough<lb/> knowledge of the ritual&#44; they now exhibit <del>utter</del> a complete<lb/> ignorance of many a religious ceremony.<lb/></p>
            <p>I <del>might</del> should not perhaps have this day&#45;reverted to a subject<lb/> to which I endeavoured enlisting your attention on<lb/> a recent occasion&#44; but the month just ushered<lb/> into the Jewish world&#44; urged me to speak.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Shall the cornet be sounded in a city and the people<lb/> be not afraid&#59;&#63; shall there be evil in a city and<lb/> the Lord hath not done it&#63;&#34;  Brethren&#33;  To<lb/> propitiate the mercy of God&#44; ere justice declares<lb/> us unworthy of His pardon&#44; we will offer<lb/> daily unto Him prayers and supplications.<lb/>  That is the armour which the sages of Israel<lb/> taught us to put on in order to ward off celestial wrath.<lb/></p>   
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>And verily if it behooves us always at<lb/> the approaching of our most solemn festivals&#44;<lb/> to fall prostrate before the Judge of the world&#44;<lb/> this year the incentive must be still greater.<lb/>  A disease of virulent character stalks abroad&#44;<lb/> and threatens to <del>extinguish</del> <del>put on</del> consume our existence.<lb/>
                He who rules the elements and tempers them agree&#45;<lb/>&#45;ably to our fragile being&#44; has <del>show</del> vouchsafed<lb/> to impede the <del>onward fatal</del> baneful course of a contagion<lb/> in our midst.  But though comparatively<lb/> few have been hitherto its victims&#44; we dare<lb/> not imagine ourselves invulnerable.  We can<lb/> only be saved when folded in the arms of beneficent Providence.<lb/>  <del>are cast around us</del> Therefore will we pray&#59;<lb/> for it has been authoritatively written that a<lb/> heartfelt entreaty will avail to avert impending<lb/> sorrows.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  Friends&#33;  Together<lb/> with the customary supplications for the month<lb/> of Elul&#44; we shall address a special petition<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>to the throne of grace that the hand of the<lb/> Destroyer be withheld&#44; and we all may<lb/> walk at large in abundance of health.<lb/>  May I obtain the pleasing assurance that the requisite<lb/> number of faithful shall never be wanting&#63;<lb/>  In former years an appeal of this nature would<lb/> have been deemed superfluous.  A spirit<lb/> of devotion stirred up the minds and hearts<lb/> of our unsophisticated parents&#44; at the opening<lb/> of the month preceding Rosh Hashana.  Apart from the tradition&#44;<lb/> which declares it propitious&#44; because Divine anger<lb/> against idolatrous Israel was appeased thereat by<lb/> the intercession of the righteous Moses&#44; and the<lb/> second tables of the Decalogue were given him<lb/> as a token of reconciliation&#59; independent of<lb/> that&#44; I say&#44; our predecessors felt that to con&#45;<lb/>&#45;tinue inert until the day of judgment arrives&#44;<lb/> denotes an unpardonable recklessness in him<lb/> whose past conduct is about to be searched.<lb/>  They therefore sought <hi rend="underline">betimes</hi> the face of<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>the Sovereign Judge&#44; and chose <del>earnest</del> fervent entreaties<lb/> and godly deeds as their advocates before the<lb/> highest tribunal.  When all nature is yet<lb/> wrapped in darkness&#44; they arose to pour forth<lb/> their souls at the altar of the Lord.  They behind<lb/> that <del>the</del> a voluntary privation of rest&#44; accompanied<lb/> with the dispensation of charity&#44; <del>would must</del> will be regis&#45;<lb/>&#45;tered above as a merit&#44; which atones for many<lb/> <del>of their human</del> of our shortcomings.  <hi rend="underline">We</hi> have grown perhaps<lb/> weaker in body&#44; but I apprehend weaker also<lb/> in faith.  We will not disturb our slumbers&#44;<lb/> lest <del>we impair</del> our health be impaired&#44; but we<lb/> refuse likewise to evince our appreciation of the<lb/> solemn season approaching&#44; by doing that<lb/> which demands no sacrifice.  For&#44; the reason<lb/> that might militate against holding worship<lb/> in accordance with the ancient usage&#44; namely<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;in the morning&#45;watch&#34; does<lb/> not exist when the hour appointed is that<lb/> at which the laborer returns from his work&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>and the merchant closes his counting&#45;house&#44;<lb/> still the few who assiduously watch at the<lb/> portals of this synagogue&#44; are they who generally<lb/> constitute a congregation during the service held in the month of<lb/> Elul.  The craftsmen&#44; seemingly&#44; cannot<lb/> <sic>yeild</sic> a small portion of his leisure time to join<lb/> our daily gathering in this sacred spot.<lb/>  He whose thoughts are engrossed in commercial<lb/> pursuits&#44; will not <del>divert them</del> suffer them to be diverted from that chan&#45;<lb/>&#45;nel&#44; though it be for his spiritual advance&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment.  And parents who might exercise their<lb/> authority in directing their children&#45;&#45;who have<lb/> attained the requisite age&#45;&#45;towards this shrine&#44;<lb/> do not even intimate that such would be their<lb/> <del>desire</del> pleasure.  The cornet sounds in the city&#44; but<lb/> people are not afraid&#44; evil is in the midst<lb/> of the city&#44; but man thinks not that God<lb/> hath done it.  Understand me&#44; my<lb/> dear hearers&#33;  I am not of those who consider<lb/> a constant attendance at the <del>dwelling of sanctuary</del> dwelling of the Lord<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p><del>prayer</del> the main duty&#44; of life.  I know<lb/> full well that holier2 and higher obligations bind us with<lb/> the world at large.  Nor <del>h</del>is prayer the only<lb/> means <del>but</del> by which we can conciliate our offended<lb/> Father that is in heaven.  The Rabbins have told<lb/> us already that &#91;Hebrew&#93; must be accompanied by<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; purposing to signify that he who<lb/> repairs to the sanctuary&#44; and leaves <del>behind</del><lb/> his fellow man behind crying for <del>bread</del> help&#44; though he<lb/> <hi rend="underline">cry aloud</hi>&#44; he shall not be heard.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  But inasmuch as the book<lb/> which has been given for our standard&#44; teems<lb/> with sentences exhorting us to prayer&#44; and<lb/> is replete with illustrations of its efficacy.<lb/>  Since our own feelings&#44; <del>when</del> if not perverted&#45;&#45;find<lb/> a spontaneous utterance&#44; when raised towards<lb/> our beneficent Maker&#44; and we delight to extol<lb/> his name amidst a multitude of people.<lb/>  Since it was to compass that sublime object&#44;<lb/></p> 
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>that we consecrated this edifice to Israels<lb/> Protector.  And since the time&#44; the occasion&#44;<lb/> our wants and our <del>cravings</del> longings demand that we<lb/> seek now especially the Bestower of all good&#44;<lb/> I can but repeat my appeal &#34;Let us&#59;<lb/> my Brethren&#39; come to His tabernacle&#44; let<lb/> us worship at His foot&#45;stool. &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  With pure<lb/> lips and sincere hearts let us implore forgive&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness from Him who is a compassionate Lord.<lb/>  Before the day arrives&#44; when our past actions<lb/> shall be weighed on the scales of justice&#44; let<lb/> us by earnest entreaties cause mercy to prepon&#45;<lb/>&#45;derate.  But do you know&#44; my friends&#33;<lb/> how we can best silence the accuser&#44; and<lb/> conciliate the favor of the Almighty Judge&#63;<lb/>  By <del>uttering compelling</del> alternating our supplications with goodly deeds. &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Our<lb/> <hi rend="underline">righteousness must walk before</hi> us.  Our<lb/> righteousness must stand before the throne<lb/></p> 
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>of the Most High&#44; and be our advocate.<lb/>  It shall prove that the child of sin has<lb/> returned penitent to the parental fold&#59; im&#45;<lb/>&#45;pressed with his own insignificance and the greatness<lb/> of the Lord&#44; overflowing with sentiments of love<lb/> for the Author of his existence&#44; and with charity<lb/> for all the creatures of the earth.  Then will the<lb/> arch angel seen by Isaiah imprint also on his<lb/> <sic>prayful</sic> lips the seal of heavenly forgiveness&#59; as<lb/> it is has been prophetically written &#34;Thine iniquity is taken away&#44; and<lb/> thy sin is purged&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            <p>My Brethren&#33;  In the course of my remarks I said&#44;<lb/> that the existence of a pestilence in our <del>any country</del> &#38; neighboring cities ought<lb/> to elicit from us a special prayer for its removal.<lb/>  I have <del>composed</del> indited one in Hebrew&#44; which I purpose<lb/> to recite during the month we just entered&#44; &#38; subsequently until<lb/> the day of atonement.  But <del>in order that it to render</del> that it may be rendered<lb/> <del>should be it</del> intelligible to those among my hearers<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>who are not conversant with our sacred<lb/> language&#44; I will&#45;&#45;this morning&#45;&#45;translate it<lb/> into the vernacular&#44; after its having been<lb/> delivered in the original.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
