<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF4_5</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_5_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_5_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_5_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_5_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_5_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_5_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_5_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_5_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_5_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_5_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_5_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_5_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_5_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_5_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_5_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_5_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Post&#45;Biblical lecture<lb/>
                25th.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  When Several weeks ago I described<lb/> the death of Herod&#45;&#45;that king of foreign birth&#44; who<lb/> destroyed his health and happiness&#44; the lives of the his<lb/> nearest and dearest and the liberties of our people&#44; by<lb/> letting his worst lowest passions have their full sway.  On<lb/> that occasion&#44; I told how he determined to make the<lb/> Jews&#44; who hated him&#44; mourn&#44; at all events by necessity&#44; when he<lb/> would be taken from earth.  Fortunately&#44; his cruel<lb/> wish command was not carried out obeyed.  Whether out of fear of<lb/> popular revenge&#44; or whether prompted by better motives&#44; Salome<lb/> and her third husband Alexis&#44; who received the royal<lb/> order did not carry it out.  The were enjoined to have many some of the principal citizens&#44; already<lb/> shut up in the hippodrome killed as soon as the<lb/> king expired.  refrained from doing so&#44; They&#44; on the contrary&#44; allowed the men to go away unhurt&#44;<lb/> pretending that such had been Herod&#39;s last will wish.<lb/>  The bulk of the nation knew the character of the<lb/> tyrant too well to be deceived&#44; still many did<lb/> credit it&#44; believe the report&#44; and felt therefore kindly disposed towards<lb/> the new ruler.  Archelaus&#44; to whom the largest<lb/> portion of the country had been bequeathed&#44; ascended to<lb/> power under favorable circumstances.  Knowing this&#44;<lb/> he was full of rich and sweet promises.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>He would reduce the amount rate of taxes that lay<lb/> so heavily on the working classes&#59; he would see to a<lb/> proper administration of justice&#44; hear and settle<lb/> all causes of complaint&#44; and respect the national<lb/> religion.  We&#44; in America&#44; have learnt from sad<lb/> experience the true worth of good assurances given by<lb/> aspirants to popularity.  Archelaus could af&#45;<lb/>&#45;ford now to be smooth tongued and very condescending.<lb/>  Rome on whose pleasure he depended&#44; should see how fit he was to govern.  How&#45;<lb/>&#45;ever his first act first first public act was to give his father<lb/> a magnificent funeral.  The pageantry was in full<lb/> accord with the fondness for display which that<lb/> ambitious man who lay dead had shown during his whole career. entire life.<lb/>  A coffin of gold&#44; golden bier mounted with precious stones&#59; most<lb/> costly ornaments&#44; together with a diadem&#44; crown and<lb/> sceptre&#45;&#45;the emblems of royalty&#45;&#45;set off those ostentatious obsequies.  Then<lb/> foreign troops escorted in their shining steel armors<lb/> pompously escorted the body to Herodium&#44; the place<lb/> of interment.  The whole was a hollow exhibition attractive only to<lb/> the thoughtless.  But it could not blot out from the<lb/> memory of the reflecting&#44; the crimes of him who was<lb/> so paraded after his death he had become a corpse.  Archelaus desiring perhaps<lb/> to prove his respect for Jewish practices&#44; kept the seven<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>days of mourning very strictly&#45;&#45;though according to some say very hypocritically&#44; <sic>banquetting</sic> at night&#44; while sitting low in the day time.  At the expi&#45;<lb/>&#45;ration of the week&#44; he went to the Temple and in a set speech&#44;<lb/> said whatever might win for him the good will of<lb/> his subjects.  But scarcely had he finished<lb/> his discourse when a procession of Jews dressed in black<lb/> came forward and with a petition.  They asked that their relatives&#44; who<lb/> had been unjustly executed by Herod&#44; should be<lb/> avenged by having their accusers punished.  That<lb/> petition Archelaus could not grant without reflecting<lb/> too openly on his father&#39;s character.  He tried to<lb/> delay giving a definite answer&#44; by stating that before<lb/> he could consider himself dared act as a real king&#44; he must go to<lb/> Rome and have Herod&#39;s will ratified by the emperor<lb/> Augustus Caesar.  But this reason did not<lb/> appease pacify men&#44; who lamented the unnatural loss of<lb/> their relations.  Meanwhile The loud cries of the com&#45;<lb/>&#45;plainants drew many towards them&#44; and a riot<lb/> took place in which a body of soldiers sent to<lb/> dispose the disaffected was beaten.  Matters<lb/> took a more serious turn ve shortly after.  At<lb/> Passover the pilgrims who came to Jerusalem from<lb/> all parts of the country&#44; sympathising with the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>opponents of the Herod family&#44; caused an outbreak<lb/> which Archelaus could not put down till his<lb/> troops had killed three thousand men.  The festival<lb/> was stopped short&#44; for the people were ordered<lb/> to instantly to return home.  But sad as that in&#45;<lb/>&#45;cident was&#44; it became the forerunner of still<lb/> sadder events.  Archelaus had sailed<lb/> for Rome to be confirmed king by Augustus&#44; and<lb/> left a royal as governor during his absence his brother Philip.  The latter ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;peared satisfied with the districts which his father<lb/> had bequeathed to him&#59; but not so the other<lb/> brother&#44; Herod &#91;&#63;&#93; Antipas.  He too went<lb/> to Rome with the intention to dispute the will&#44; and prove that he<lb/> ought to be declared King&#44; in accordance with a previous<lb/> testament of by Herod.  Meanwhile the country<lb/> which was the bone of contention&#44; had been thrown<lb/> into a state of anarchy&#44; reminding one almost of the<lb/> days of the commune at Paris&#44; after the raising<lb/> of the siege by the Germans in 1891.  The<lb/> immediate cause were the arbitrary measures<lb/> and unbearable greed of Roman governors&#59; ever<lb/> hungry for gold.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>At the feast of Pentecost&#44; again Jerusalem was<lb/> again thronged with pilgrims&#44; amounting to several<lb/> millions.  They detested the foreigners who<lb/> sucked dry the land once divinely promised to flow with<lb/> milk and honey for its legitimate heirs and&#44; burning with anger&#44; they and de&#45;<lb/>&#45;termined to drive the Romans away beyond the hills of Zion.  The im&#45;<lb/>&#45;possible attempt was made&#44; and battles with a<lb/> terrible slaughter on both sides followed.  To these<lb/> calamities were added the horrors of political<lb/> factions which arose in sever various parts of<lb/> Judea.  Men exceptional for their physical strength&#44;<lb/> for their boldness and military skill&#44; but who<lb/> were unscrupulous about the means they used to<lb/> gain influence&#44; put up false claims to royalty&#44;<lb/> and robbed and killed their own countrymen&#44; who were sus&#45;<lb/>&#45;pected of favoring Rome.  Enraged by<lb/> this harassing warfare&#44; the legions which<lb/> the Caesars had stationed in the land of our fathers&#44;<lb/> became still more furious&#44; and out of revenge<lb/> they burnt ent whole cities&#44; and left leaving but ruins in their<lb/> train.  During this gloomy interval&#44;<lb/> Archelaus was pleading his cause in the capital of<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Italy&#44; and his brother Antipas was engaged<lb/> in the same undertaking.  But before Au&#45;<lb/>&#45;gustus had come to a decision&#44; an embassy<lb/> of fifty of prominent Jews arrived from Jerusalem.<lb/>  with a public They were request commissioned to request that their people might be permitted to govern<lb/> themselves by their own laws and dispose with a<lb/> king.  Eight thousand Hebrews&#44; who lied at<lb/> the time in Rome&#44; joined their entreaty to that<lb/> effect.  The emperor listened to the reasons<lb/> which the ambassadors alleged set forth.  In strong lan&#45;<lb/>&#45;guage they told their grievances. against because of Herod<lb/> and his family and showed that had done them irreparable injury&#44; and Archelaus had<lb/> already showed a disposition to despotism and<lb/> blood&#45;thirstiness.  A famous but prejudiced orator&#44; whom<lb/> Josephus often quotes&#45;&#45;Nocholas of Damascus&#45;&#45;<lb/> took the part of Archelaus against the<lb/> ambassadors.  Antipas the competitor for<lb/> the throne had also an eloquent advocate&#44; but<lb/> Augustus dismissed them all&#44; and&#44; declining<lb/> to receive the rich bequests left him by Herod&#44;<lb/> reduced very considerably the territory claimed by<lb/> Archelaus&#44; and assigned a larger one than provided for in the paternal testament to each of the other<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>two brothers.  Still&#44; Judea pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;per&#44; as then divided&#44; remained under the rule<lb/> of Archelaus&#44; whom the nation abhorred.  This<lb/> feeling of detestation increased&#44; when Archelaus&#44;<lb/> in defiance of Mosaic laws&#44; married the widow<lb/> of his brother Alexander&#44; son of Marianne<lb/> whom Herod had cruelly executed&#44; but who<lb/> had left children by his wife.  The act was an open defiance to Mosaic laws&#44; which permit marrying a brother&#39;s widow&#45;&#45;only when the deceased had left no offspring.  Thus&#44; in pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;portion as the dynasty of the Idumean Antipater<lb/> became more hateful in the eyes of our people&#44; that<lb/> of the Maccabees grew dearer in their recollection.<lb/>  This circumstance will account for a strange<lb/> credulity&#44; not single in history&#44; yet very curious.<lb/>  A Jew who lived in Sidon had such a striking<lb/> resemblance to Alexander&#44; son of Marianne&#44; that<lb/> the following story spread throughout Judea and<lb/> occasioned created a popular agitation.  It was said<lb/> that the order of Herod had not been performed<lb/> by the executioner&#59; that two criminals were sub&#45;<lb/>&#45;stituted for Alexander and Aristobulus&#44; inhumanly<lb/> condemned to death by their father&#59; that they were<lb/> allowed to escape and hide themselves away abroad&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>but that now they would come and govern to<lb/> the country of their birth and govern the people of<lb/> their love.  The man who <sic>personated</sic> Alex&#45;<lb/>&#45;ander&#44; had for his accomplice an old officer<lb/> in the service of Herod. who Hence he was supplied with all the<lb/> necessary instruction to give the fraud every ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;pearance of truth.  Throughout Europe&#44; where&#45;<lb/>&#45;ver the pseudo Alexander went&#44; the Jews living<lb/> there loaded him with presents&#44; paid him high<lb/> honors&#44; and promised to insure him a future<lb/> worthy of a king.  Emboldened by this ge&#45;<lb/>&#45;nerous treatment&#44; the would&#45;be Maccabean ven&#45;<lb/>&#45;tured to go to Rome&#44; and try his imposition on<lb/> Augustus&#44; with the view of receiving the crown.<lb/>  Not only the Jews who had known Alexander in<lb/> the capital of Italy&#44; hailed the pretender as the<lb/> son of Marianne&#44; but some of the Roman themselves nobility who<lb/> had b made the acquaintance of the two brothers<lb/> during their educational term in Rome&#44; believed<lb/> that Alexander stood now before them.  The<lb/> emperor gave the man&#39;s followers an audience&#44; keeping<lb/> his keen eye upon the imposter.  The sharp<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>intellect of Augustus detected the deception<lb/> at once with ease.  The questions which he put were not<lb/> answered in that refined manner and polished<lb/> language habitual with the real Alexander&#44;<lb/> who had been brought up in the royal courts<lb/> and in the eternal city metropolis of the Latin race.  Au&#45;<lb/>&#45;gustus noticed also in the man&#39;s hands a rough&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness contrasting with that delicateness and soft&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness of a person unused unused to manual<lb/> work.  The whole bearing of the pretender<lb/> lacked that dignity&#44; remarkable in the son<lb/> of Marianne.  The resemblance was very stri&#45;<lb/>&#45;king&#44; but only in looks and size.  The em&#45;<lb/>&#45;peror demanded a private interview&#44; during which<lb/> he pointedly directly charged the pseudo Alexander with<lb/> fraud&#44; promising that his life would be spared&#44;<lb/> if he confessed the truth.  Seeing himself<lb/> discovered&#44; he acknowledged that the Jewish<lb/> people had been duped by him at the insti&#45;<lb/>gation of one of Herod&#39;s servant.  The latter<lb/> was therefore executed&#44; and the impostor was condemned to<lb/> hard labor for life.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>Our ancestors were felt disappointed and humiliated<lb/> at such an outcome of their expectations&#44; but not<lb/> in the least reconciled to the domination of a son of Herod by<lb/> a strange woman.  For ten years Archelaus exer&#45;<lb/>&#45;cised his arbitrary power&#44; making and unmaking<lb/> high&#45;priests&#44; replenishing the treasury which he<lb/> exhausted in dissipations with the fruits of the<lb/> earnings of his subjects&#44; and publicly disregard&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing the laws and practices of Israel.  So frequent<lb/> and numerous were the complaints brought against<lb/> him to Augustus Caesar&#44; that the emperor weary<lb/> of condoning overlooking his glaring faults&#44; stripped him<lb/> at last of all pow authority&#44; and banished him to<lb/> &#91;&#63;&#93;&#44; an ancient town in Gael Gaul&#44; called<lb/> afterwards called France.<lb/></p>
            <p>Judea entered now into a new phase of its<lb/> sorrowful history.  The Asmonean dynasty had sunk<lb/> for ever in rivers of blood into which the murderous<lb/> Herod plunged it&#59; the dynasty of the wicked Idumenean<lb/> was swept carried off by the destructive all&#45;sweeping besom of Rome.<lb/>  Henceforth Judea will be known as a Roman<lb/> province&#44; ruled by a Roman governor&#44; and subject<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>to Roman tyranny.  Henceforth we shall<lb/> witness fierce struggles&#44; political strife&#44; ter&#45;<lb/>&#45;rorism&#44; carnage.  We shall see also deeds of valor worthy of<lb/> better times&#44; but also likewise inhuman actions which<lb/> called down the anger of the Lord&#44; and brought<lb/> on the dispersion and suffering of eighteen hundred<lb/> years.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
