<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF3_5</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_5_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_5_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_5_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_5_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_5_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_5_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_5_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_5_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_5_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_5_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_5_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_5_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>Some remarks on Parashat &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#40;&#91;Hebrew&#93;&#41;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Dear Brethren&#33;  It is a common saying among the Rabbis&#44; that<lb/> the rales of morality claim priority to the injunctions of the law<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;; for&#44; they believe that without the<lb/> former the social compact would soon verge on destruction&#44; while<lb/> the latter&#59; as far as it regards religious observances&#45;&#45;are binding<lb/> only upon a comparatively small portion of the human family.<lb/>  And so true is their axiom&#44; that if we consult the pages of sacred<lb/> history&#44; we shall discover that whenever Divine Justice scourged<lb/> the world&#44; it was either to repress crime&#44; or to blight the growth<lb/> of immorality&#44; which threatened to deaden the germs of all virtues.<lb/>  One hundred and twenty years did the Deity defer a chastisement&#44;<lb/> which increasing delinquencies had called for&#44; but when open<lb/> violence&#45;&#45;which implies a total abandonment to vice&#45;&#45;had<lb/> corrupted men&#39;s habits&#44; the annihilating deluge swept off<lb/> the sinners with the sinners.  And if Sodom and its adjacent<lb/> cities underwent subversion&#44; it was to preclude a further<lb/> inroad of the deeds of turpitude committed within their walls.<lb/>  Again&#59; could we recall to memory all the lessons bequeathed<lb/> to us in the heavenly volumes&#44; we would trace in them the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>same spirit&#44; which induced our Sages to give morality precedence<lb/> to ceremonial precepts.  Thus&#44; by way of example&#44; when<lb/> the shepherd King&#44; communing with his own mind&#44; asked who<lb/> shall reach the apex of eternal glory&#44; he answered his own<lb/> query&#44; by enumerating those moral virtues&#44; which alone constitute<lb/> true piety &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;He that walketh uprightly&#44; and acteth righteously<lb/> and speaketh the truth in his heart&#59; he that backbiteth not with<lb/> the tongue&#44; nor doeth evil to his neighbour&#44; nor taketh up a<lb/> reproach against his fellow&#45;man&#44; and so forth.  In like<lb/> manner when the same monarch inquired how could man attain<lb/> longevity and happiness&#44; the reply was &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Depart from<lb/> evil and do good&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;seek peace and follow it.&#34;  Nor<lb/> are the inspired bards of Israel less eager in inculcating a<lb/> similar instruction&#59; nay&#44; when they warn and when they<lb/> teach&#44; morality is mainly the substance of their themes &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Seek good and not evil that ye may live&#34;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Seek justice&#44; relieve the oppressed&#34; Such is<lb/> my friends&#33; the language employed by our prophets.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Let none of you&#44; however erroneously imagine that those godly<lb/> men attached no importance to the practices of our holy religion&#44;<lb/> for&#44; they&#44; on the contrary&#44; loudly condemned the desecrations of the<lb/> sabbath&#45;day&#44; the partaking of forbidden viands&#44; the blending<lb/> of our blood with that of gentiles&#44; the irreverence exhibited at<lb/> the altar of our God and of various ordinances disregarded even<lb/> in those ancient days by many an Israelite.  But if they more<lb/> repeatedly and emphatically lamented the laxity of morals<lb/> principles&#44; it was because they deemed the latter the basis where&#45;<lb/>&#45;upon the social edifice rests&#59; and without which the external<lb/> marks of religion would be valueless.  And in point of fact&#44;<lb/> if it is true &#40;and none should doubt it&#41; that <sic>cerimonial</sic><lb/> behests lend not only to the healthful maintenance of our<lb/> minds and bodies&#44; but also to the purification of our souls&#44; how<lb/> could the mere performance of the same&#44; divested of the sen&#45;<lb/>&#45;timents&#44; whence they should emanate&#44; secure to us spiritual<lb/> advancement&#63;  Let us in all sincerity ask ourselves&#58;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Can we with holiness and purity discharge those ordinances&#44;<lb/> whilst our mind is engrossed in conceiving deceit against our<lb/> neighbour&#44; or when it is bent on worldly cravings&#63;  If<lb/> pride elates our hearts&#44; and envy and jealousy harbour<lb/> within our breasts&#44; with our arraying ourselves with the<lb/> distinctive tokens of Judaism&#45;&#45;with the phylactories and<lb/> the four&#45;cornered robe&#44; entitle us to a seat among the blessed&#63;<lb/>  No&#44; my Brethren&#33;  They are important&#44; they are very essential<lb/> for the preservation of our creed&#44; but unaccompanied with<lb/> morality&#44; they are of no avail.  Morality&#44; yes&#44; morality<lb/> is the point pivot around which religion turns&#59; hence<lb/> have our Rabbins declared that &#34;the law of God cannot<lb/> subsist where morality is absent&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> and this seems to me to have been the main cause which<lb/> has&#44; at all periods&#44; rendered proselytism alien to our<lb/> institutions.  Judaism was not considered by our Teachers&#44;<lb/> the exclusive vehicle to salvation.  They taught in their<lb/> schools that &#34;pious men of other beliefs&#44; will also share<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>everlasting bliss &#91;Hebrew&#93;; so that while they<lb/> recommended their brethren to be scrupulously observant of all<lb/> their tenets&#44; they required from the stranger that inhabited Judea&#44;<lb/> strict adherence only to the seven Noachite precepts&#44; as those which<lb/> are binding upon every human being&#44; and on which the conti&#45;<lb/>&#45;nuance of society at large is depending.  Indeed&#44; if we<lb/> consult Talmudical authority&#44; we may conclude that the<lb/> promulgation of those Divine injunctions dates not alone from<lb/> Noah&#39;s age&#44; but that it is coeval with the existence of<lb/> man&#59; for&#44; we deduce it from a passage occurring in the<lb/> second Chapter of Genesis.  Hence&#44; Adam as the father of<lb/> all mankind was to teach his posterity&#44; that homicide&#44; theft&#44;<lb/> incest&#44; the mutilating of irrational animals&#44; blasphemy&#44; ar&#45;<lb/>&#45;bitrary judgment&#44; and the sacrificing to <sic>leud</sic> idolatry&#44; are<lb/> the seven abominations of God&#39;s heart &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  The<lb/> last may perhaps be objected to&#44; as an encroachment on<lb/> freedom of actions&#44; but when we call to mind the bacchanals&#44;<lb/> the carousals in which heathens indulged&#59; the human<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>victims they immolated at the shrine of their horrible gods&#44; no<lb/> one will censure a provision so necessary and so salutary.<lb/>  The Hebrews might&#44; as the benighted nations of antiquity com&#45;<lb/>&#45;monly practised&#44; have constrained the conquered to become con&#45;<lb/>&#45;verts to the faith of the conqueror&#44; but they shrank from<lb/> compulsory actions&#59; for&#44; however they prized the Mosaic code<lb/> and the Rabbinical institutions&#44; though they esteemed the<lb/> unflinching obedience to both imperative on all born of<lb/> Israel&#44; yet they had learnt to believe that from the <sic>fulfilment</sic><lb/> of the seven Noachite precepts&#44; happiness here and hereafter<lb/> would also accrue to the foreigners that dwelt within their<lb/> gates.  True&#44; history records that a descendant of the<lb/> Macabees demanded from the vanquished Idumeans a total<lb/> acquiescence in the religion of Israel&#44; but this act which no<lb/> authority sanctioned&#44; was requested by the innumerable sorrows&#44;<lb/> which it cost our forefathers&#44; for&#44; out of those forced proselytes&#44;<lb/> sprung Herod&#44; that viper that poisoned the life of Mattathias&#39;<lb/> noble race.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>My friends&#33;  To this long train of ideas I was led&#44; by the contempla&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion of the noble character whose virtues are narrated in the<lb/> section of this Sabbath&#44; for&#44; morality in the highest degree was<lb/> the principal characteristic of the immortal Abraham.  Some of<lb/> his actions have been animadverted on&#44; because they have been<lb/> misconstrued&#44; but to him who thinks and understands correctly&#44;<lb/> every tract in his life will appear loveable.  It might be<lb/> supererogatory to enlarge upon what we have just perused&#44;<lb/> but I cannot refrain from reverting to one passage&#44; which I<lb/> conceive to be <sic>transcendently</sic> beautiful &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;Abram said to the<lb/> King of Sodom&#44; I have lifted up my head into the Eternal&#44; the<lb/> Most High God&#44; possessor of heaven and earth&#44; that I will not<lb/> take from a thread even to a shoe latchet&#59; that I will not<lb/> take any thing that is thine.&#34;  The sword of a<lb/> ruthless enemy had brought penury and death.  Defenceless<lb/> women and innocent sucklings had been made to swell his<lb/> booty.  Lot and all his wealth had likewise fallen<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>victims to the rapacious host.  At so harrowing a tiding&#44; the<lb/> patriarch tarries not to deliberate.  The voice of nature&#59; the voice<lb/> of humanity that loudly spoke within him&#44; pointed out the course<lb/> he should forthwith pursue.  he quits his peaceful home&#44;<lb/> he relinquishes his profitable calling to don the armour.  A<lb/> heavenly shield renders him impervious to the inimical steel.<lb/>  &#34;He who raised up the righteous man from the east&#44; and called<lb/> him to his foot&#44; gave nations before him.  He gave them as the<lb/> dust to his sword&#44; and as driven stubble to his bow&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Thankful<lb/> because of a deliverance so unlooked for&#44; the King of Sodom <sic>profers</sic> that<lb/> to which the laws of war entitled the deliverer.  But the father of<lb/> the faithful was guided by a higher law than human conven&#45;<lb/>tionalities.  Morality not less than inborn philanthropy had<lb/> attained fro him the most glorious of all titles &#34;the friend of<lb/> God &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; and the same actuated him also on the occasion<lb/> to which we have referred.  The victor who entered the devastated<lb/> cities with the substance wrested from the spoiler&#44; did not<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>plume himself on his skill or prowess&#44; he did not vaunt his<lb/> well concerted actions by which he foiled the aggressor&#44; but<lb/> joyful at having discharged a solemn duty towards his relative<lb/> aid his fellow&#45;men&#44; he thrusts the sword away to respond to the<lb/> softer feelings of his excellent nature &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; &#34;He returned<lb/> all the goods.  Not a little of that which he might have<lb/> demanded&#44; would be appropriate to himself or receive&#44; for not to<lb/> conquer had he hastened to the battle&#45;field&#44; but to save life<lb/> and to restore peace.  Oh&#33; that his deportment were the exemplar<lb/> of modern <sic>combattants</sic>&#33;  How much would it contribute to<lb/> assuage the fierceness of the belligerents.  How greatly gr would<lb/> the horrors of war be lessened&#33;  If morality preceded the<lb/> hostile camps&#44; as their sacred car &#40;carroccio&#41; preceded the ancient<lb/> Italians in their war of independence&#44; the wanton depredation<lb/> which in these boasting times is continually perpetuated&#44; would<lb/> no longer shock our feelings.  Even when influenced by the<lb/> direst passion&#45;&#45;that of destroying human existence&#44; men would<lb/> learn to preserve intact those rules of equity&#44; the absence of<lb/> which will sop the foundation of society.  Thus wars would<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>terminate more speedily&#44; pacification might be more practicable&#44;<lb/> humanity would triumph&#44; and justice be vindicated.<lb/>  May the Almighty grant that the results of a such a<lb/> demeanour soon gladden our own hearts.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
