<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF13_6</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_6_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_6_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_6_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_6_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_6_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_6_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_6_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_6_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_6_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_6_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_6_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_6_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>An explanatory lecture<lb/>
                on Parashat Itr&#243;<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Now therefore&#44; if ye will obey my voice indeed&#44; and keep my covenant&#44;<lb/> then ye shall be a peculiar treasure unto me above all people&#34;.<lb/>  Brethren&#33;  The liberality of the present age&#44; as exhibited in America&#44; ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;ceeds the most sanguine anticipations of the progressists.<lb/>  The pulpit which to day is devoted to the cause of Unity&#44;<lb/> lends itself to&#45;morrow to the influences of the adherents of a<lb/> trinity.  I wish to be clearly understood.  I do not mean to<lb/> insinuate that a Jewish preacher is apt thoughtlessly to change<lb/> side.  For unless he be demented deprived of reason&#44; he surely will not display<lb/> so volatile a temper.  But I My words have reference to a novel method<lb/> of spreading light abroad.  It has become a practice among<lb/> the radicals in our religious camp&#44; to allow a non&#45;Israelite<lb/> to expound his doctrines in the synagogue&#44; so that the Rabbi<lb/> may on return be favored with the privilege of ventilating his<lb/> ideas inside of the church.  The advantage to be derived<lb/> from such a course&#44; I am at a loss to discover.  I can find no&#45;<lb/>&#45;where that we are enjoined to seek for proselytes converts.  On the con&#45;<lb/>&#45;trary&#44; impressed with the truth enunciated by our sages that<lb/> &#34;the pious among the nations of the world&#44; will have a share in<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>the world to come&#44;&#34; we use all the powers of persuasion to<lb/> <sic>dysaude</sic> the gentiles from embracing a faith fraught with<lb/> restrictions.  And only when the divine wisdom that has<lb/> &#91;&#63;&#93; them is sincerely confessed&#44; and the knowledge of<lb/> the One God who rules Supreme is obviously manifested&#44; ought<lb/> the applicant to be may gain admission into the pale of Judaism.<lb/>
                The charge brought against the Scribes and Pharisees&#44; that they<lb/> &#34;would compass sea and land to make one proselyte&#34; though given made<lb/> authoritatively in the books of our gentile neighbors&#44; is not at<lb/> all borne out by the history of our people nation.  Our shepherds of old<lb/> would positively I am certain have condemned as an unpardonable intermed&#45;<lb/>&#45;dling with other peoples men&#39;s people&#39;s conscience&#44; even that which our<lb/> modern pastors do to effect what they term &#34;the melting<lb/> of the icy crust of superanimated prejudice&#34;.  And for stronger<lb/> reasons our ancient teachers would have objected to a non&#45;Isra&#45;<lb/>&#45;elite publicly advancing his views&#44; in the house devoted to<lb/> Jewish worship.  For nothing that he could say&#44; would possibly<lb/> add force to the dogmas we have ever held&#44; while his attempt<lb/> to shake them&#44; might&#44; in all likelihood&#44; be attended wit heart&#45;<lb/>&#45;burnings&#44; rather than be promotive of kindly feelings.<lb/>  Surely&#58; True&#58; no one can who notes current events will deny that the<lb/> &#91;&#63;&#93; mystic belief of the Nazarenes is very slowly but perceptibly becoming<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>simplified&#44; and we&#44; who hope and pray that the world may<lb/> finally bend with the same mind before the universal Creator&#44;<lb/> must regard with satisfaction any step in advance towards<lb/> that goal.  But not by the exchanging of pulpits will the<lb/> prediction of our Seers be fulfilled.  That strange method may<lb/> be applauded by a few&#44; as the indication of prevailing tolerance&#59;<lb/> but I challenge my reverend colleagues to show that it has brought<lb/> round the standard of Christian Unity a perfect absolute Monotheism any defenders.  If it has<lb/> proved anything&#44; it has shown what neither I&#44; nor you&#44; I trust&#44;<lb/> will hail with pleasure&#59; namely&#44; that the few deems his religion<lb/> a mere abstraction&#59; and that anxious to &#91;&#63;&#93; <sic>to</sic> demonstrate it such he intimates that for free oneself gradually<lb/> from the restrictions ordinances and interdictions surrounding that idea is to<lb/> speed the time foretold.  o In short&#44; that &#34;God will be King over all the earth&#44;&#34; when Israel shall cease to be &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;a peculiar treasure above all poeple&#34; through their obedience of the Law and precepts..  Such is the inference mindful conclusion I have deduced forced upon my mind<lb/> on several occasions&#44; but specially of late from on the recital of a lecture&#44; which<lb/> a minister of our faith delivered on Sunday in a Unitarian<lb/> church&#44; to reciprocate the courtesy of a clerical gentleman<lb/> connected with the latter&#44; who had spoken in the synagogue on<lb/> the preceding Saturday.  An error seems to be gain&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing ground everywhere that there exists an avowed identity<lb/> between the principles of that denomination&#44; and those which<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>underlie Judaism.  In fact I sa read it plainly in the words<lb/> which dropped form the lips of the Hebrew preacher just alluded<lb/> to.  He says&#58; &#34;This exchange &#40;of pulpits&#41; betokens a spiritual affi&#45;<lb/>&#45;nity between the congregations directly concerned in it&#44; as war&#45;<lb/>&#45;ranted by the name Unitarians.&#34;  Now&#44; my Brethren&#33;<lb/> hear it precisely as the appellation would denote.  Were we<lb/> our neighbors who style themselves Unitarians&#44; to disavow disclaim<lb/> any belief in an intermediate being between us and God&#44; they<lb/> would nevertheless be as dissimilar to the Hebrews Israelites as the adherents<lb/> of Islamism whose formula of &#91;&#63;&#93; their faith is &#34;There is no other God but Allah&#44; and Moha<lb/>med is his prophet&#34;  But this I know&#44; that however wide may be the<lb/> chism that separates them those religionists from the body of christians&#44; they<lb/> still cling to notions&#44; which we would reject as because jarring with<lb/> the Mosaic creed.  I have a strong lively recollection of a sermon<lb/> given by a president distinguished Unitarian minister in this city.  It might<lb/> have fitted the Synagogue&#44; but for its concluding sentence.<lb/>  From that I learnt&#44; how far distant even the most advanced<lb/> of gentile denominations is from our perfect Hebrew our Monotheism.<lb/> But I am not here to cast reflection The deified man of Nazareth<lb/> holds yet a power over their minds&#44; which they cannot entirely entirely shake<lb/> off.  But I am not here to cast reflection on the re&#45; settled<lb/> &#45;ligious convictions of my fellow&#45;creatures.  I would<lb/> that you&#44; my Brethren&#44; respect any who honestly differ<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>from our views&#44; certain that a merciful Lord&#44; who judges<lb/> our intentions will accord to all His salvation.  But I am<lb/> impelled by duty to guard the religion we profess against the<lb/> admixture of falsehood&#44; the more dangerous&#44; because very plausi&#45;<lb/>&#45;bly brought forth.  My The text from our section<lb/> which I have placed at the head of my discourse&#44; tells you<lb/> what Judaism is&#44; and what a Jew must be.<lb/></p>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>  Now&#44; therefore if ye will obey my voice indeed&#44; and keep my<lb/> covenant&#44; then ye shall be a peculiar treasure unto me above<lb/> all people&#34;  Say&#44; dear hearers&#33; What is the covenant upon the dis&#45; maint&#45;<lb/> &#45;charge &#45;enance of which the fulfilling of God&#39;s promise depends&#63;  Is it<lb/> the simple acceptance avowal of an abstract principle&#63;  Our The eternal allegiance<lb/> we owe to the Unity&#63;  Listen to the answer which the son of Amram<lb/> gives to this query.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;The Lord our God made a covenant<lb/> with us in Horeb.....I stood between the Lord and you at that<lb/> time&#44; to show you the word of the Lord&#34;.  You have heard it.  The<lb/> abstract idea of the Unity is the trunk of the tree&#44; the observance<lb/> of the precepts commandments is the branching out of its strong boughs&#44; with fruit and<lb/> foliage&#44; sweet to the taste and charming to the eye.  The<lb/> Jew is a Unitarian&#44; but a Unitarian Jew is an anomaly.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>For how can he be so called who does not accept the whole performance<lb/> of the covenant&#44; that is&#44; of positive ay laws&#44; alike moral and ceremonial&#63; obligations&#63;  At Sinai we entered<lb/> into a compact with our living Redeemer.  We would f keep faithful<lb/> to the commandments word received&#44; and the Lawgiver would watch over<lb/> our preservation as a man&#44; who sets his whole heart on a precious heirloom.<lb/>  The Decalogue which imposes ritual as well as moral social duties&#44; is part of that<lb/> compact.  The Sabbath&#45;day with the prescriptions attending it&#44;<lb/> as derived&#45;&#45;not from the Rabbis now unheeded&#44; and little cared for contemned&#45;&#45;not from<lb/> the Rabbis&#44; but from Isaiah&#44; from Jeremiah&#44; Ezekiel and Nehemiah.<lb/>  The Sabbath day&#44; to speak of no other statute&#44; shows that to reduce<lb/> the Jewish religion into a metaphysical abstraction&#44; would be<lb/> as fatal an error&#44; as that into which some have fallen&#44; who saw<lb/> in it only a mass of external forms.  Verily&#44; the latter have tar&#45;<lb/>&#45;nished its lustre beauty&#59; but the former have would extinguished its beauty life.<lb/>  The nationalists placing reason above the Law&#44; sought to raise it on<lb/> stilts&#44; that it might come up to their level preconceived standard.  The<lb/> ceremonialists&#44; if I may coin the word&#44; have drawn it down&#45;<lb/>ward with a <sic>procrustean</sic> measure.  Both proceeded from<lb/> false principles.  Hence the blessed torah suffered obloquy&#44;<lb/> and the name of the heavenly Legislator is being profaned &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>But what we have read this morning&#44; should convince<lb/> us that neither can Judaism must not be confounded with Deism&#44;&#45;&#45;what&#45;<lb/>&#45;ever form it might assume&#45;&#45;&#44; and that neither nor can that indi&#45;<lb/>&#45;vidual be ranked high among the faithful&#44; who accepts a portion<lb/> of the covenant&#44; and rejects another portion.  Do you know&#44;<lb/> my Brethren&#33; Why the Decalogue was written upon two tables&#44;<lb/> each containing five commandments&#63;  The Rabbis explain it so.  In order<lb/> that their corresponding position might teach the recipients their<lb/> equal value.  For&#44; he that breaks the sixth will be adjudged<lb/> as culpable as if he trespassed against the first&#44; and in<lb/> like manner none can for instance may be said to be exonerated from the fourth&#44;<lb/> because he is obedient to the ninth.  The liberal spirit of<lb/> our age however&#44; has an entirely different system of instruction.<lb/>  Its rules are exceedingly easy&#44; and they are besides presented in<lb/> so engaging attractive a garb&#44; that pliant susceptible minds&#44; will soon become<lb/> enamored therewith.  Israelites&#33;  Choose between them and those the tenets I have<lb/> perused from the book of Exodus.  To continue &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;a peculiar<lb/> treasure above all people&#44;&#34; the sacrifice of human appetites&#44; the<lb/> sacrifice of means&#44; of time&#44; of feelings is demanded.  To follow<lb/> the path opened by the Hebrew Unitarians of America is<lb/> to enjoy freedom from many restrictions&#44; and be considered<lb/> enlightened.  I prefer privations declared to be acceptable<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>to the Lord&#44; and the name title of &#34;benighted&#34; for the sake of my<lb/> God.  You are free&#45;agents.  Reflect upon what I have said spoken&#44;<lb/> and act consistently.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
