<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF12_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_2_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_2_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_2_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_2_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_2_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>14 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>For Beshalach.<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  On a former occasion&#44; while endeavouring<lb/> to explain an important sentence in the scriptures&#44;<lb/> I made some allusions to the writings of a modern author&#44;<lb/> who stands ranks high as a commentator.  Guided by the<lb/> light emanating from his productions&#44; I removed apparent<lb/> discrepancies in Holy Writ&#44; and succeeded in making clear<lb/> to the minds of my hearers some of its obscure passages.<lb/>  Upon that occasion&#44; I chose as my standard the epic<lb/> poem&#44; very fittingly called the Hertz Wessely &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Songs of glory&#34;.  My The subject I then treated was the obstinacy of<lb/> Pharaoh in refusing to yield to the demand of Moses&#44;<lb/> and I sought to prove that a correct understanding of<lb/> the verb &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;to harden&#44;&#34; used variously in the text&#44; will<lb/> exclude the opinion that the King&#39;s <sic>persistance</sic> in sin&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing was the effect of a divine ordination by which he<lb/> lost his freedom of will.  I quoted every sentence in which<lb/> that verb is met&#44; in connection with my subject&#44; and<lb/> showed that its grammatical construction opposes the<lb/> notion generally entertained.  For&#44; by the different forms<lb/> of that very term&#44; we are taught&#44; that when the rivers<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>and streams of Mizraim ran blood for a whole<lb/> week&#44; and even after the land had been twice infested<lb/> by loathsome reptiles&#44; and devastated both by wild<lb/> beasts and by pestilence&#44; the obdinacy&#91;&#63;&#93; of the Egyptian<lb/> ruler&#44; was the result of his natural perversion&#44; and not<lb/> of a supernatural coercion.  True&#44; at a later period&#44;<lb/> when his <sic>wilful</sic> stubborness would have given away under<lb/> sore trials&#44; he was purposely hardened&#59; but that<lb/> must be regarded as a punishment due to his unbelief.<lb/>  The man who had denied the Almighty&#44; and become<lb/> pitiless.  The man who had wantonly oppressed and killed the in&#45;<lb/>&#45;nocent was not allowed to <sic>yeild</sic>&#44; through fear&#44; without<lb/> an open acknowledgment of his atrocious crimes.  For&#44; that<lb/> would have been contrary to the design of God in the go&#45;<lb/>&#45;vernment of His intelligent creatures.  Sincere repentance will<lb/> always obtain forgiveness&#44; but the abandoning of sin&#44;<lb/> when bodily infirmities disable us to follow it&#44; or<lb/> when the inexplicable dread of approaching calamities&#44; deters<lb/> us from indulging in deeds of inhumanity&#44; is not that<lb/> self control of one&#39;s passions which our Maker accepts as an ato&#45;<lb/>&#45;nement.  &#34;The sacrifices of God are a broken spirit&#44; a<lb/> broken and contrite heart thou O God&#33; Thou wilt not despise.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>said once a penitent king.  But&#44; as I conclusively proved con&#45;<lb/>&#45;vincingly while dwelling on that topic&#44; Pharaoh&#39;s<lb/> mind and heart remained closed continued inflexible&#59; perfectly closed against the admission<lb/> of truth&#44; in spite of all the appalling events experienced.<lb/>  When scourged with severity&#44; he twice confessed his iniquities&#44;<lb/> but no sooner were the pains he suffered mitigated&#44; than<lb/> he relapsed into his usual pertinacity.<lb/></p>
            <p>Some may advance in justification of a conduct so crimi&#45;<lb/>&#45;nal&#44; the foreknowledge of the Lord&#59; for&#44; since He had<lb/> revealed to His prophet that the deliverance of Israel&#44;<lb/> would be effected by means of fearful strokes upon their<lb/> task&#45;masters&#44; the latter were urged on by a Power<lb/> that could not be resisted.  I am not prepared to launch<lb/> into an argument of exceeding magnitude&#44; and which has<lb/> engaged the deepest attention of our theologians&#44; nor would its dis&#45;<lb/>cussion comfort with the object of my present lecture.  But<lb/> if I may very briefly state my the views I hold&#44; I will say&#58; that when<lb/> we reflect how to the eye of ubiquitous Providence the future<lb/> must be ever present&#59; or&#44; to speak more plainly&#44; how<lb/> time which we mortals reckon by the changes of day and night&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>is unchangeable before God&#44; for&#44; a thousand years to<lb/> come&#44; are in His eyes as yesterday when it is past&#44; we will<lb/> be able to reconcile Divine prescience and freedom of will.<lb/>  The Psalmist illustrated this idea&#44; when he penned this sentence.<lb/>  &#34;The Lord looketh from heaven&#44; He beholdeth all the sons of men.<lb/>  From the place of His habitation He watcheth over all the<lb/> inhabitants of the earth.  He fashioneth their hearts alike&#44; He<lb/> understandeth all their deeds.&#34;  Note down his weighty<lb/> words&#44; my Brethren&#33;  &#91;Hebrew&#93; God whose<lb/> knowledge is not like human <sic>knowledged</sic>&#44;&#45;&#45;derived from ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;perience&#44; but is coexisting with Him&#44; or as our immortal Maimonides expresses it &#91;Hebrew&#93; He and his knowledge are identical beholds not alone<lb/> what the mortals will perform&#44; but penetrates into all<lb/> the causes which will prompt them to act. for&#44; as our<lb/> immortal Maimonides expresses it&#44; &#91;Hebrew&#93; He<lb/> and His knowledge are identical.  If the future is<lb/> then necessarily present with respect to the Almighty&#44;<lb/> it follows that He must discern before&#45;hand all our<lb/> doings&#44; without influencing forcing them to any special direction.  So&#44; by way of elucidation.<lb/>  If I now see my neighbour stealing&#44; his crime can&#45;<lb/>&#45;not be attributed to my looking on&#59; for my knowledge<lb/> of his offence arose at the same time he committed the theft.<lb/>  In like manner&#44; when we say that at the hour of our birth<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>God is already aware of all our doings actions through life&#44; we mean<lb/> that whatever will befall happen to us&#44; has already stood passed on &#91;&#63;&#93; before<lb/> His all&#45;discerning eye.  And as man must unavoidably<lb/> notice what falls under his senses&#44; so does the Creator<lb/> <sic>instantenously</sic> behold that which will happen transpire through<lb/> all coming ages.  And this boundless knowledge it is that makes<lb/> every human action deed&#44; whether good or evil work out His<lb/> will design in the government of the world.  It does not<lb/> control man&#39;s free agency&#44; but it forces the results thereof<lb/> to promote the design intentions of kind Providence in the preser&#45;<lb/>&#45;vation of the universe&#44; and in the furtherance of social progress.<lb/></p>  
            <p>But I am admonished to cease speaking of a topic<lb/> so abstruse&#44; and resume explain that to explain the intended about which is the main object of my pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;sent lecture. is intended.  I have said&#44; that the brightness<lb/> which the Hebrew productions of Hertz Wessels reflect&#44;<lb/> lead us aright in our Biblical researches&#59; and they will that I have<lb/> be my standard I &#91;&#63;&#93; present before my mind also chosen as my guide this Sabbath in the remarks I am<lb/> about to offer.  The portion of the Law we<lb/> have read&#44; opens with a description of the motives&#44; which<lb/> caused the Lord to send His liberated people through<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>inhospitable regions&#44; instead of guiding directing their steps immediately<lb/> toward the land of promise.  Aside from the prediction&#44; which<lb/> required their appearance at the foot of Sinai to be invested<lb/> with a priestly mission&#44; it was manifest to the Supreme<lb/> that a race long held in bondage subjection&#44; could not boldly fight<lb/> their assailants.  We&#44; in fact&#44; discover their unacquaint&#45;<lb/>&#45;ance with the art of war at Rephidim&#44; for the defeat<lb/> of Amalek&#44; was accomplished by a supernatural inter&#45;<lb/>&#45;vention&#44; and that through the valor of the Hebrew Jewish<lb/> <sic>combattants</sic>.  Similar wonders would undoubtedly have<lb/> produced similar effects&#44; even if the battle had been waged<lb/> against the people of Canaan&#44; but our Sages have taught&#44; and<lb/> our reason agrees with their instruction&#44; that nature&#39;s God<lb/> will not invert his established laws and resort to miracles&#44; unless absolutely <sic>indepsensable</sic><lb/> to carry out His unsearcheable divine decrees.  Time was therefore<lb/> to erase from the mind of the enslaved the memory of their<lb/> former lowly condition&#44; before they could drive away before them formidable<lb/> nations. from their territories  But if the Sovereign Leader<lb/> willed that our ancestors be not affrighted by the clatter of<lb/> arms&#44; at the hour of their deliverance&#44; he had nevertheless<lb/> destined them to witness the <sic>marvellous</sic> sight of an<lb/> enemy routed and rooted out not by the sword or by the<lb/> spear&#44; but by the breath of the Omnipotent Lord.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>When the moaning of the dying&#44; and the shrieks of their<lb/> bereaved parents aroused the Egyptian king from his slumbers&#44;<lb/> he quickly loosened the fetters that bound his slaves.  But<lb/> what the hand performed&#44; the will would fain have refused.<lb/>  A series of misfortunes had spread upon him a dread of God&#39;s<lb/> messenger&#44; but his mind&#39;s eye would not perceive the higher<lb/> Power through which Moses wrought wonders.  The days of<lb/> horror had passed&#44; when the corpses of the first&#45;born lay un&#45;<lb/>&#45;buried in the land of Mizraim.  Israel had&#44; during that ter&#45;<lb/>&#45;rible interval&#44; reached Etham.  Protected against the scor&#45;<lb/>&#45;ching rays of the sun by a pillar of cloud which hovered<lb/> above their heads&#59; illumined at night by a soft light&#44; which<lb/> served also to guide their steps&#44; they confidently moved towards<lb/> the wilderness of Sinai.  They imagined that the last visitation<lb/> had brought their tyrants to a sense of contrition&#44; and they journeyed<lb/> undisturbed by any misgivings.  But what that which human eyes<lb/> could not have detected&#44; was disclosed to the all&#45;wise Being.<lb/>  He saw that Pharaoh and his subjects had scarcely wiped<lb/> the tears shed over a mid&#45;night slaughter by the aven&#45;<lb/>&#45;ging angel&#44; when they deemed it a folly to have given their<lb/> bondmen liberty.  He knew that to hold force them again in back into servitude&#44;<lb/> their every movements was watched.  But to prove to all<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>succeeding generations that the final judgment brought<lb/> upon Mizraim&#44; was the consequence of their perversity&#44; He<lb/> bid Israel retrace their steps. and encamp before &#91;&#63;&#93;<lb/> This was to be to be the test by which the sincerity of the Egypt&#45; of the Egyptian&#39;s repentance.<lb/> &#45;tians should be tried was to  If they had really reputed of sincerely regretted their<lb/> cruel treatment of the people of Israel&#44; they would not misconstrue the intention<lb/> of the Deity.  Experience should have told them the love He<lb/> bore the seed of the patriarchs&#44; and though the backward<lb/> movements made might indicate perplexity&#44; they should have not har&#45;<lb/>&#45;bored a doubt as to the fulfilment of God&#39;s declaration that God the God who had struggled for them&#44; would have also<lb/> brought them forth to enlargement.  But the unbelief deep&#45;rooted of  again betrayed itself.  The enemies fancied&#44; what<lb/> their wicked hearts desired.  &#34;Confusion&#44;&#34; the exclaimed &#34;con&#45;<lb/>fusion will disband our fugitive slaves.  Lo&#33; the sight of<lb/> the wilderness has filled them with terror.  The recreants fly<lb/> before the howling wildnerness regions.  They come&#44; they come an easy<lb/> victim to our invincible strength.&#34;  So they said in their over&#45;<lb/>&#45;weening pride&#44; and they would have waited&#44; while making<lb/> ready the chains fetters which would once more have shackled Israel.<lb/>  But they were doomed to die the death to which they had<lb/> consigned suckling babes.  God spurred them on.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>God who scrutinized their inmost hearts and found them<lb/> tight shut against truth&#44; added fresh hardihood that the over&#45;<lb/>&#45;throw of the wicked might instruct the survivors.  Thus<lb/> supernaturally urged compelled&#44; a blood&#45;thirsty soldier&#44; pressed eagerly<lb/> forward.  The impious king led the van&#44; and fell warriors bent<lb/> on destruction came in followed his train.  From a distance<lb/> Israel descried that formidable martial array and became horror&#45;stricken.<lb/>  Born in servitude they could not summon courage to face<lb/> their masters.  To wage the battle against men who had<lb/> held over them the flesh&#45;tearing whip&#44; was beyond their<lb/> thoughts.  Motionless they stood&#44; and Bleached are their cheeks with terror they are writhing their souls in an&#45;<lb/>&#45;guish.  The fierce enemy persecutors rolling forward down like an avalanche&#44;<lb/> draws nearer still and threatens to crush them.  Israel&#39;s hurt<lb/> has ceased almost to vibrate.  But the celestial decree had<lb/> gone forth.  Moses should conduct the tribes amidst<lb/> trackless waters.  At the stroke of his rod&#44; the waves would<lb/> open a path for the chosen of God&#44; and rush on with fury<lb/> impetus to overwhelm the the <sic>redoutable</sic> armys of Egypt  Reassured<lb/> by this heavenly promise&#44; the people quickly rapidly advanced&#44; and<lb/> ere night had spread cast its shades over creation&#44; upwards<lb/> of two millions of beings had entered deep in the sea.<lb/>  The pursuers and the pursued could then no longer distinguish<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>each other.  For&#44; the pillar of cloud which preceded the<lb/> redeemed&#44; had moved suddenly backward&#44; by the will of the Lord&#44;<lb/> and spreading around a bewildering mist concealed hid the pro&#45; course<lb/> &#45;gress of which the Hebrews were following&#44; on a ground surrounded by through in the midst liquid walls.  Yet&#44; the<lb/> twinkling stars gave light enough to illumine the way&#44; which show<lb/> the unbelieving foes&#44; who begrudged the persecuted slaves<lb/> the gift of liberty was the way they were condemned to tread walk.  So Egypt<lb/> marched speedily on ignorant of the course they followed treading the abyss upon their watery grave.  And if through<lb/> the night they tried in vain to discover how Israel proceeded&#44; they still confidently looked for eagerly expected exultingly waited the morning&#44; when their<lb/> glittering swords would awe the fugitives back into bondage.<lb/>  The breaking of the dawn through a dense fog&#44; mixing<lb/> its light with that of the distant pillar of fire&#44; which<lb/> had safely brought the tribes to the opposite shores&#44; revealed<lb/> to the haughty the inevitable danger&#45;&#45;a yawning gulph.<lb/>  Mizraim stood breathless&#44; when on the right and on the f left&#44;<lb/> they beheld the floods erect looked at them mockingly.  Shuddering &#91;&#63;&#93; Crushed to the earth&#44; mad&#45;<lb/>&#45;dened by so unforeseen a disaster&#44; their souls died within<lb/> them.  &#34;Surely the princes of Zoan are fools&#44;&#34; cries the<lb/> inspired Isaiah.  &#34;The wise <sic>counsellors</sic> of Pharaoh have given<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>a senseless advice.  Where are they&#44; those wise men&#59; let<lb/> them tell&#44; what the Lord of hosts hath proposed against<lb/> Egypt.&#34;  Too late did the memory of the wrongs per&#45;<lb/>&#45;petrated against humanity flash before their minds.<lb/>  Then was it felt that by trampling upon the weak&#44;<lb/> their heavenly Protector had been defied.  &#34;To the land&#44; to the Hayton land Oh let us<lb/> turn&#34; backward exclaimed cried the charioteers cried&#44; &#34;let us hasten<lb/> away from a conflict so unequal.  For the Almighty<lb/> Creator from heaven is combatting battling against us from on high.&#34;  They devise a<lb/> retreat&#44; but the ground refuses to give them support.  The wheels<lb/> of their superb chariots hinders the flight.  They are<lb/> sunk in deep mire.  They The troubled harried shuddering multitude remove that impediment<lb/> and hope to reach the dry land friendly ground land on the back of their swift<lb/> horses.  But the measure of their crimes is full.  They<lb/> cannot obtain mercy.  Nature&#44; which by the will<lb/> of her Maker&#44; had suspended her laws&#44; resumed her power.<lb/>  The floods&#44; held in check by the foot&#91;&#63;&#93; of the Eternal&#44; rushed<lb/> on to fill up the chasm&#44; and mounted high on the backs<lb/> of the wretched who attempted to flee.....A show song<lb/> of gratitude upheaved the breasts of the mothers that of joy resounds from afar.<lb/> saw it.  The abyss had swallowed up the unrelenting<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p>oppressors&#44; and they who had been cruelly oppressed&#44;<lb/> in with an outburst of gratitude shouted forth &#34;This is my<lb/> God&#44; and I will praise Him&#44; the God of my father and<lb/> will extoll Him.&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>Rightly have the Sages remarked that the glory of the Lord&#44;<lb/> became more visible on the Red&#45;Sea&#44; even to a Hebrew hand&#45;maid&#44; than to the prophet Ezekiel on the river Kebar.<lb/>  For never did the mighty hand of retribution justice reveal itself<lb/> so palpably as to the enfranchised of Egypt.  Never has<lb/> an event so thrilling been witnessed by a mortal eyes.<lb/></p>
            <p>Let scoffers style it credulity.  Let the would be wise set forth<lb/> their subtle arguments to explain away the divest that narrative occurrence of its supernatural cha&#45;<lb/>&#45;racter. of that narrative  The crossing of the red sea&#44; that<lb/> historical fact which explainings the transforming of Jacob&#39;s descend&#45;<lb/>&#45;ants from the African to the Asiatic regions&#44; that fact&#44; as<lb/> registered in the book of truth&#44; will ever attest the might<lb/> and the mercy of the living God.  We shall not need an<lb/> Aben Ezra to prove&#44; as he did demonstrate to the infidel<lb/> of his time&#44; that the passage could not have been made<lb/> at a low&#45;tide&#44; because the whole context points to the contrary.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="14"/>
            <p>We shall not require the testimony of <sic>travellers</sic>&#44; before<lb/> we believe that the narrow space of ground fancied by the rational&#45;<lb/>&#45;ists&#44; as having given our forefathers an entrance into the desert<lb/> of Shar&#44; lacks every requisite for such a purpose.  We will<lb/> not search into the traditions of unsophisticated gentiles&#44; to con&#45;<lb/>&#45;vince ourselves that ancestral traditions have they have also been left to then also<lb/> an account of the <sic>marvellous</sic> incident&#44; when the ceased to sea dried up<lb/> flow&#44; and a whole nation crossed it on foot.  No&#58; we will<lb/> base our faith upon a higher rock than man&#39;s reasoning and<lb/> man&#39;s evidence.  Aye&#58; we will base it upon the unerring word of<lb/> the Bible.  We will credit what Moses wrote&#44; what the<lb/> prophets repeated and our Psalmists sung.  With David will we<lb/> exclaim &#34;Come and see the works of God.  He is terrible in His<lb/> doings towards the children of men.  He turned the sea into dry land&#44; they<lb/> went through the floods on foot.&#34;  With Nehemiah we will daily<lb/> proclaim &#34;God showed signs and wonders upon Pharaoh&#44; and on all<lb/> his servants&#44; and on all the people of his land.  For He knew that<lb/> they dealt proudly against our fathers&#44; so did He get Him&#45;<lb/>&#45;self a name as it is this day.  And He divided the sea before<lb/> them&#44; so that they went through the midst thereof on the<lb/> dry land&#44; and their persecutors He threw into the deeps&#44; as<lb/> a stone into the mighty waters&#34;.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
