<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF9_16</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1891-05" source="" attested="yes">May 1891</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_16_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_16_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_16_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_16_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_16_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_16_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_16_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_16_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_16_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_16_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_16_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_16_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>95<lb/></p>
            
            <p>May&#47;91<lb/>
                On decoration day<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Every civilized nation sets apart certain days of<lb/> the year&#44; which have become memorable in its an&#45;<lb/>&#45;nals.  The practice is praiseworthy&#44; for the a mental<lb/> preservation of the sublime deeds of the anciently ancestors&#44; serves<lb/> as a sentinel guarding against watching to hinder the degeneracy of their pos&#45;<lb/>&#45;terity.  It That sentry should be made to stand conspicuously forth<lb/> to be viewed at stated times&#44; that its looks may in&#45;<lb/>&#45;spire patriotism.  America can justly boast of<lb/> her fourth of July.  It is the natal day of freedom.<lb/>  This dear city of ours witnessed its birth&#44; but like the<lb/> colossus of Rhodes&#44; the <sic>nurstling</sic> grew so gigantic that<lb/> peoples beheld it from afar&#44; and hailed its fast<lb/> increasing strength.  Wherever the exhilarating<lb/> air of liberty is breathed&#44; the sweet perfume thereof<lb/> is wafted over by the child given unto us in the<lb/> year 1776.  To keep fresh the record of that event&#44;<lb/> it behooves all who love the Republic of the North.<lb/>  More fittingly than by the deafening din and<lb/> dangerous discharge of fire arms&#44; the great day<lb/> would be honored by the sound of psalmody to the<lb/> God of battles&#44; who caused Right to conquer Might.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Israelites do not hold festivities commemorative<lb/> of the birth of human beings.  Patriarchs and Prophets&#44;<lb/> <sic>heros</sic> and Sages receive a venerated mention in<lb/> Jewish history&#44; but no season is appointed to<lb/> the exaltation of man.  The rigidness of the faith&#44;<lb/> which ascribes all achievements to the Sovereign<lb/> Lord form whom power and wisdom emanate&#44; prevents<lb/> it.  Nevertheless the 22nd of February is not inap&#45;<lb/>&#45;propriately devoted by the beneficiaries to the glorifi&#45;<lb/>&#45;cation of their mortal benefactor.  His prowess won<lb/> abundant happiness&#59; his sagacity dealt the seve&#45;<lb/>&#45;rest blow at Kings&#39; <sic>pretentions</sic>.  George Washing&#45;<lb/>&#45;ton&#44; who might have set a crown upon his head&#44;<lb/> or have become a dictator&#44; but who chose only to be enthroned<lb/> into the hearts of his countrymen&#44; is assuredly de&#45;<lb/>&#45;serving of all the grateful outpourings of multitudes.  The day<lb/> which recalls his entrance into the world may well<lb/> be devoted set apart to the narrative of his acts of nobility.<lb/>  Even Hebrews&#44; warned by their uncompromising be&#45;<lb/>&#45;lief against human deification&#44; may not scruple to ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;tol the prince of peace&#44; who bethought him&#45;<lb/>&#45;self of the seed of Abraham.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>A land which demanded and enforced the divorce<lb/> of the church from the state&#44; can scarcely assume<lb/> with consistency a religious office&#44; and ask of her<lb/> inhabitants to hold a general thanksgiving day.<lb/>  In like manner as she would resist an encroach&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment of ecclesiasticism upon her constitution&#44; so she it were<lb/> ought to better that she should disclaim the prerogative of exercising priestly<lb/> functions&#59; that she ought should not to counsel the observance<lb/> of public worship towards the end of the civil year.<lb/>  That privilege belongs to another department of<lb/> acknowledged authority.  Still&#44; the incongruity<lb/> may be overlooked&#44; by reason of the object to be<lb/> reached.  The meeting together of millions who<lb/> avow the blessings attending an unchecked pursuit<lb/> of trades and commerce&#44; and a heavenly bestowal<lb/> of plenty to render life pleasurable&#44; is a sight<lb/> worthy of the freest beings upon earth.  Would<lb/> that the President&#39;s proclamation were carried<lb/> out everywhere in a spirit of righteousness&#44; and<lb/> become not in too many instances a pretext for<lb/> an indulgence in intemperance and idleness&#33;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>But the occasion which Americans observe this<lb/> day has none of the just real or plausible motives&#44;<lb/> that I have named in connection with other national<lb/> celebrations.  I expressed my views without equivo&#45;<lb/>&#45;cation against the new devise&#44; shortly after it<lb/> had become an accepted institution&#44; and hoped that<lb/> it would not extend through the length and breadth<lb/> of the Union.  But what was originally partial&#44;<lb/> has grown to be universal.  Another day has been<lb/> added to the many in which the laboring man is<lb/> forced obliged to withdraw from his calling&#44; and the viciously<lb/> disposed are given opportunities to waste away their<lb/> earnings.  And why&#63;  Is the day calculated to<lb/> improve the majority morally&#59; politically&#63;  Let<lb/> us reflect.  A war&#44; the memory of which sends a<lb/> thrill of horror into the human soul&#44; was waged be&#45;<lb/>&#45;tween brothers.  During four sad years we in<lb/> the North raised fearful armies to fight unto death<lb/> men in the South&#44; and those in the South did<lb/> not sheathe the bloody sword until exhaustion<lb/> compelled the reluctant act.  Civilization stood<lb/> aghast at the terrible carnage.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>I shall waive the question as to whose side<lb/> high principles gave offered an incentive&#59; which of the<lb/> two contending parties in the fratricidal struggle<lb/> aimed at the victory of an ideal&#44; and which at<lb/> the subjugation of freedom.  Enough to bring<lb/> to mind the desolation of countless homes where<lb/> bereavement entered&#59; fields trodden down by the<lb/> heels of a soldiery&#44; enkindled with passions&#59;<lb/> enough to remember gaunt starvation where plenty<lb/> had smiled&#44; poverty where affluence had uninterrup&#45;<lb/>&#45;tedly flowed&#59; and then the assassin&#39;s shot&#44; the<lb/> agonies of prisoners preyed upon by vermin&#44; and<lb/> then the heavy taxation&#44; the demoralization which<lb/> bloodshed engenders.  Let us cast a veil over<lb/> that dreadful past.  It should not be flung<lb/> aside.  Thankful for the final issue that<lb/> redeemed the fair name of the Republic of the<lb/> North&#44; the stronger ought to help the weaker<lb/> in their ascent upon the ladder of progress&#44;<lb/> whether they aim strive to gain its top by efforts to&#44; raising<lb/> them intellectually&#44; socially&#44; morally&#44; commer&#45;<lb/>&#45;cially or politically.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>But how does the &#34;Decoration day&#34; contribute to that<lb/> end&#63;  Hypocrisy says to falsehood&#58; &#34;We will<lb/> go and honor the dead.  We have come to a spot<lb/> in which some who had tried to destroy the Union<lb/> like the sleep that knows no waking.  We must<lb/> lay a wreath over their tombs.  Were they not brave&#63;<lb/>  Here is coffined one who swore eternal hatred<lb/> against the upholders of slavery.  It matters<lb/> not that I considered <sic>negros</sic> human chattal fit<lb/> only for the market.  It mus plant a garland with the star<lb/> spangled banner on the sod that covers him whose<lb/> ideas I detested.&#34;  Can that be sincerity&#63;  Is it not&#44;<lb/> to the contrary&#44; offensive untruth&#63;  Is not deception that<lb/> the &#34;Decoration day&#34; fosters&#63;  If not it&#44; then<lb/> it is a mockery&#44; mere child&#39;s play&#44; a sense&#45;<lb/>&#45;less pastime&#44; an absurd display of military<lb/> array&#44; a wordy exhibition of frothy oratory.<lb/>  To assume that mutual magnanimity gave it<lb/> origin&#44; is fallacy.  Nature refutes the argument&#44; for<lb/> we cannot do reverence to what we had deemed treason&#44;<lb/> nor pay homage to such as we had looked upon as invaders.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>The institution ought never ot have had a begin&#45;<lb/>&#45;ning&#44; and gladly would I relate the end thereof&#44;<lb/> firmly believing that it keeps alive the memory<lb/> of an episode in the history of the United States&#44;<lb/> which time ought to obliterate&#59; so that our pos&#45;<lb/>&#45;terity may not inherit the least of the angry feel&#45;<lb/>&#45;ings which once divided a great nation into two<lb/> hostile camps.  As to the celebration on<lb/> this very day&#44; I shall not conceal the satisfaction I<lb/> experience at having hindered what I regard a profanation&#44; from<lb/> a Jewish standpoint.  The burial ground pertaining<lb/> to our Congregation was announced to be among<lb/> the cemeteries which would be visited by a mili&#45;<lb/>&#45;tary post&#44; so that the few interred there&#44; who<lb/> are credited with having fought battled for the perpetuation<lb/> of the Republic&#44; might received the awarded de&#45;<lb/>&#45;coration.  I opposed the plan on the same score<lb/> as others would have opposed it if the occasion had happened on a Sunday.  Sure&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly then it would have been postponed out of the<lb/> respect to the religious sentiment of the majority.<lb/>  Israelites should not appear less regardful of<lb/> their rules and practices usages than Christians are of their own.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>A correspondence and personal interviews secured a pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;mise that the usual ordinary exercises will not be held in our<lb/> burial place till the Jewish Sabbath is concluded.<lb/>  Let me trust that no double dealing will be <sic>pracitsed</sic>. &#94;<lb/>  But the simple fact that the Philadelphia paper&#44;<lb/> ostensibly devoted to the interest of our creed&#44; in urging a<lb/> collection to defray expenses&#44; and had published to the world<lb/> that the anticipated celebration to be in our cemetery would be on<lb/> our Sabbath&#44; is a painful illustration of the Rabbi&#45;<lb/>&#45;nical saying&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> a maxim&#44; which in plain English&#44; would mean&#58; familiarity<lb/> with sin&#44; makes the sinner callous.  So very general<lb/> is the desecration of the fourth commandment of<lb/> the Decalogue&#44; that even its supposed defenders forget<lb/> its sanctity.  Self&#45;respect&#44; at all events&#44; require that<lb/> we shall not degrade it in the estimation of our neigh&#45;<lb/>&#45;bors of another belief.  Let us be aware of Chillal&#45;<lb/> Ha&#45;shem&#44; but rather remember that we are in duty<lb/> bound &#34;to hallow the Holy One of Jacob&#44; in order that &#34;they who<lb/> err in spirit shall come to understanding&#44; and they that<lb/> murmur shall obtain instruction&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            
            <p>&#94;&#40;I learnt since that the decoration did take place before the Sabbath was<lb/> over&#41;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
