<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF2_3</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_3_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_3_1v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>3 pages on 2 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>For&#44; in the school of Samuel a rigid discipline taught self&#45;<lb/>denial&#44; and while the minds of the attendants was elevated by the cul&#45;<lb/>&#45;tivation of the arts of oratory&#44; poetry and song&#44; abhorrence for idolatry and<lb/> idolaters was instilled into the hearts.  Many&#44; so trained braved the displeasure<lb/> of potentates&#59; many preferred a life of constant suffering and privations to the relin&#45;<lb/>&#45;quishing of a sacred mission.  The history which chronicles the recreancy&#91;&#63;&#93;<lb/> of a Zedekiah son Chanaanah who&#44; to curry favor with an villanous impious<lb/> king&#44; struck Micojah&#44; son of &#91;&#63;&#93; on the face records also the impertur<lb/>bable conduct of that same Micajah&#44; whom nothing neither the stripes nor the prison could induce to utter a lie.<lb/>  And all acquainted with Holy Writ have read of Obadiah&#44; who risked his own existence by steal&#45;<lb/>thily feeding in a cave one hundred of the disciples of Samuel&#44; doomed to<lb/> destruction by the iniquitous Jezebel.  Now&#44; we may not choose<lb/> to credit the legend which makes the widow and her two sons&#44; the wife<lb/> and children of the godly man that I have just mentioned&#44; but we<lb/> have the testimony of the scriptural historian that the deceased had<lb/> carried out the principles imparted inculcated in the school of Samuel.  Addres&#45;<lb/>&#45;sing Elisha&#44; the distressed widow cried&#58; &#34;My husband is dead&#44; and thou<lb/> dost knowest that thy servant feared the Lord.&#34;  In her misery&#44; the memory<lb/> of the character of the one she loved&#44; was a ray of hope for Divine assist&#45;<lb/>ance.  She may have record recalled the teaching of the Psalmist that the<lb/> seed of the upright will not beg for bread.  She complained of men&#39;s<lb/> cruelty&#44; but she looked trustingly did not despair of receiving help from that Beneficent Being&#44; who works<lb/> wonders through human agency.  The sequel of the narratives is household words to<lb/> all the readers of the Bible.  Poverty was chased away to make room for ease and<lb/> comfort.  Now&#44; it is not likely that any woman&#44; surely not a Jewess&#44; be so sadly si&#45;<lb/>tuated as the widow of whom I have spoken.  The dread of being forced to deliver<lb/> one&#39;s children to slavery&#44; cannot&#44; thank God&#44; be felt by any in this land&#44; cleansed<lb/> of an horrid unnatural sin.  But some may at times grieve by reason of their inability to<lb/> adequately provide for their young offspring.  Let the faith which saved<lb/> a mother and her two orphan fatherless sons&#44; be a stay and support.  In that particular<lb/> instance a miracle was requisite&#44; because men had ceased to practice the mer&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciful commandment of the Law.  In our age a superhuman interposition is un&#45;<lb/>&#45;necessary&#44; because the spirit of universal pity which the religion of Sinai<lb/> breathes&#44; has humanized the world communities.  Means are constantly devised to<lb/> assuage sorrow to prevent the exposing of the indigent to shame and<lb/> to the loss of a forcible parting with their nearest and dearest.  The spreading of the book of books<lb/> among civilization&#44; has broadened our views of on charity.  Men are learning<lb/> to distinguish between degrading alms and elevating beneficence.<lb/>
                But let us turn our attention for a while to the other object presented<lb/> to our consideration by the prophetic section.  In the dwelling &#38;c<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>we have made this morning the acquaintance of two women of Israel.<lb/>  This position in life is very quite different&#44; but both women are worthy of our<lb/> deep earnest consideration.  We will know them more intimately&#44; after having taken<lb/> a mental survey of the habitations which they respectively occupy.  In the<lb/> dwelling of one&#44; traces of sure poverty are discernible everywhere.  Faces emaciated<lb/> and sunken in meet our eyes.  A widow and her two little sons are the<lb/> inmates of the dismal place.  The appearance of the mother betrays intensity<lb/> of grief.  Destitution had followed hard at the heels of a sad bereavement.<lb/>  And now a calamity is threatening her household&#44; the thought of which<lb/> harrows up her very soul.  A pitiless creditor has demanded her two child&#45; boys<lb/>&#45;ren as slaves in payment of his claims.  The hopes of a brighter future by<lb/> her children&#39;s growth and activity&#45;&#45;hopes so soothing to a mother&#39;s powerful heart will<lb/> be blighted.  Deprived of her only comfort&#44; she will pine away in utter lone&#45;<lb/>&#45;liness.  An appeal to the courts of justice would avail nothing.  The king&#45;<lb/>&#45;dom of Israel and that of Judah also&#44; corrupted by inauspicious matrimonial<lb/> alliances with the house of Omri&#44; have cast aside the merciful ordinances<lb/> of the Mosaic legislation.  To a people perverted by an idolatrous Jezebel<lb/> and her equally wicked daughter Athalia&#44; it did not matter if the Divine<lb/> code had peremptorily prohibited the selling of a Hebrew&#44; except tempo&#45;<lb/>&#45;rarily to make compensation for the commission of a theft.  The so&#45;called authorities&#44; trampled<lb/> on religion.  No redress could be expected at the hands of Powers allied<lb/> to iniquity.  Since an unhappy schism had divided the tribes of Ja&#45;<lb/>&#45;cob into two hostile camps&#44; the chiefs of the monarchy of Israel espe&#45;<lb/>&#45;cially&#44; encouraged a laxity of principles among the community at<lb/> large.  All will remember the denunciations of the fearless shepherd<lb/> of Tekoe.  Undaunted by at the menace of a false priest&#44; who<lb/> demanded that the Judean Amos should leave the royal city of the<lb/> king of Israel and go to his own land and prophesy evils there if he<lb/> so chose&#44; the man in whom the spirit of God was astir&#44; still charged a<lb/> depraved populace with selling the relig righteous for lucre&#59; the<lb/> poor for a mere pair of shoes&#59; for charged with their hypocrisy the wrong doers<lb/> who lay down by the altar on garments taken in pledge&#44; and drink&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing wines on which unjust fines had been imposed.  But despite<lb/> a general depravity&#44; some remained undefiled.  They were persons<lb/> principally belonging to &#34;the school of the prophets&#34;.  Samuel<lb/> the son of the righteous pious Hannah&#59; Samuel the lover of his people and re&#45;<lb/>ligion&#44; the stern republican&#44; who pictured the disastrous accompaniments<lb/> safeguard against a universal corruption.  He would counteract<lb/> the ill effects of the abuse of power by cringing priests and heathenish prophets.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
