<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF14_4</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_4_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_4_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_4_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_4_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_4_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_4_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_4_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_4_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_4_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_4_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_4_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_4_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>4th lecture on Revelation.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  When a person undertakes to lead the way<lb/> which others may follow&#44; he will&#44; now and then&#44; look<lb/> back and ascertain how far he has proceeded&#44; and how<lb/> clear of impediments of impediments he has left the road already crossed. of all impediments<lb/> In the same manner I think it is advisable that I should<lb/> act while treading pursuing a literary path&#44; which I have found<lb/> long and difficult.  Indeed&#44; I have ocasionally often been obliged to take<lb/> the shortest cuts&#44; as it were&#44; not so much to make my<lb/> labor easier&#44; as to spare my young brothers and sisters in<lb/> faith some of the fatigue attending our mental journey.<lb/>  Let me now show what was our gain through the the distance we have gone&#44; &#38; the success we met during the time<lb/> distance we have <sic>travelled</sic> together.<lb/></p>
            <p>Dropping all figures of speech&#44; I will remind my hearers<lb/> of the threefold object I mean to accomplish when<lb/> I set upon my voluntary task.  I wished to ef disprove<lb/> Atheism&#44; Infidelity and materialism.  I had cause to<lb/> fear that&#44; if the first named evil had not a hold upon the hearts of our<lb/> youths&#44; its evil baneful associate made itself felt.  Agnosticism&#44; which<lb/> is a species of religious indifference&#44; expressed by modern<lb/> philosophers in that newly coined word&#44; had to be attacked<lb/> and fought with the arms of dispassionate sound arguments.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>I necessarily compelled to agreed with the idea that<lb/> the self&#45;existence of God is above human comprehension.<lb/>  I still aimed The wisest and most penetrating intellect cannot unravel that mystery.  Yet&#44; I aimed to direct the attention to the evidences we possess<lb/> of a Sovereign Mind that rules the universe&#44; which it has<lb/> <sic>marvellously</sic> planned.  For it stands to reason that<lb/> in surveying a work&#44; which answers with precision<lb/> its every purpose we must plainly with great precision&#44; we must be forcibly led to infer the existence<lb/> of the worker&#44; though he may not be placed physically before<lb/> our eyes.  Thus&#44; to use an illustration which I have<lb/> not not presented as yet heretofore&#44; the water of rivers kept<lb/> fresh and hence fit for our use&#44; by their constant flow and that of seas prevented<lb/> from becoming foul by being and poisoning the air&#44; through its having been &#91;&#63;&#93; impregnated with salt&#44; are<lb/> not looking glasses showing the reflection of their Maker&#59;<lb/> nor does the countless variety of animals&#44; furnished<lb/> from their birth with covers for their skin&#44; and with<lb/> material weapons for their own defence&#44; visibly display a panorama<lb/> in which the wise Creator passes before our vision.<lb/>  No&#44; they and similar objects implying forethought in the making designing thereof&#44;<lb/> give no visible testimony of their artificer&#44; but one must<lb/> be mentally blind&#44; who cannot in behold in that<lb/> perfect arrangement a divine foreknowledge.<lb/>  The denial of God is inevitably the admission of folly.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Theism then asserts itself as the only solution to the con&#45;<lb/>&#45;struction and harmony of the universe.  But theism But basing our judgment on the evidences of the oldest written book we could conclude that theism<lb/> has &#45;&#45;or the belief in God&#45;&#45;proved inf insufficient to govern the human race aright.<lb/>  Not because the Sovereign Creator could have intentionally<lb/> left His creatures destitute of a moral guide conducive to happiness&#44;<lb/> but because innate principles of rectitude were gradually<lb/> overpowered by incentives of a lower nature.  He &#91;&#63;&#93; As a corrective of social dignity degeneracy the<lb/> Omnipotent granted revelation.  He rewarded&#44; with a more direct manifestation of<lb/> His will&#44; a man who&#44; amidst <sic>corruptive</sic> surroundings&#44; had<lb/> traced again the way of truth&#44; and followed it.  Abraham<lb/> became&#44; through Revelation&#44; the germ of a civilization<lb/> founded on righteousness and justice.  His lineal descendants&#44;<lb/> whom a sore bondage providentially saved from a fusion with<lb/> heathenism&#44; grew to be the choice plant&#44; from whose stock<lb/> the world&#39;s regeneration would evolve.  A universal ac&#45;<lb/>&#45;ceptance of the commandments of Sinai will should effect the in&#45; design<lb/> tention of the Most High in the creation of man.<lb/></p>
            <p>So far we have&#44; my dear hearers&#44; proceeded together in our<lb/> investigations&#44; and I believe we have&#44; in the main&#44; agreed<lb/> on the premises and conclusions.  But at this point of our mental survey I must show<lb/> a stumbling&#45;block against which many have struck.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>We should avoid it&#44; if we wish to remain the<lb/> appointed guardians of God&#39;s will.  The unqualified<lb/> supremacy accorded to the Decalogue over the Pentateuch is the<lb/> dangerous against thought which we must guard against.  Already<lb/> in early times days&#44; the Sages of Israel found it imperative to<lb/> abolish the daily recital of the ten commandments in the<lb/> Temple.  to They would thus oppose the rising theory that only what<lb/> a whole people had immediately heard from the Deity&#44;<lb/> and nought else was binding upon succeeding generations.  Since that<lb/> time the same faulty notion has met with secured strenuous<lb/> advocates&#44; and now even we read that Rabbis and pulpit preachers have<lb/> reduced Judaism and its mission to the narrowest limits.<lb/>  The observances and dissemination of the Decalogue is&#44;&#45;&#45;according to the new dispensation&#44; the<lb/> sum and substance of Revelation.  But from what&#45;<lb/>&#45;ever stand&#45;point I look upon that idea I detect its fallacy.<lb/>  It is illogical&#44; because of the impossibility of holding a<lb/> nation&#44; chosen as the depositary of humanising truths&#44; apart<lb/> from an erring world by a few general rules&#44; however<lb/> grand they may be in their form and essence. there may be It is unhistorical&#44;&#45;&#45;<lb/> conceding of course the genuineness of the narrative&#45;&#45;because the<lb/> people themselves requested Moses to become the interpreter<lb/> of all Divine communications&#44; which they would accept&#44; as it directly promising to obey them pay to them them respect<lb/> equal respect&#44; as if directly received from the Deity. received from the Deity God<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>It is moreover antagonist to a sensible exegesis&#44; for<lb/> the Pentateuch contains amplifications&#44; explanations and<lb/> practical illustrations of those very ten commandments.<lb/>  But the idea must be set aside as totally groundless&#44;<lb/> when consideration is made to this patient fact.<lb/>  The Decalogue was not offered for the whole world&#39;s acceptance&#44; any<lb/> more than the Pentateuch.  If proofs to my assertion were wanting required&#44;<lb/> the first sentence of that heavenly declaration and as well as its<lb/> context would furnish them.  For we read &#34;I am the<lb/> Lord thy God&#44; that brought thee out of the land of<lb/> Egypt&#44; out of the house of bondage&#44;&#34; meaning&#44; I have<lb/> shown Myself thy defender and deliverer&#44; and as such<lb/> I bid thee obey heed the injunctions I am about to impart.<lb/>  And again&#58; &#34;Thou shalt not take the name of Adona&#239; thy<lb/> God in vain&#34; that is&#44; thou shalt not swear falsely profanely swear by that<lb/> Being whom Thou recognizest as the Eternal Lord.  Do I<lb/> then contradict what I stated in my last lecture&#63; concerning the value and scope of the Sinaic manifestation&#63;  Not<lb/> in the least.  My study of the holy books has taught<lb/> me this belief&#44; which I strive to ha instill into the hearts<lb/> of my young coreligionists.  Israel is the recipient of the<lb/> entire code&#44; called Mosaic.  Both moral and ceremonial laws precepts<lb/> were enacted for the guidance and perpetuity of the priests of humanity.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>The Almighty did not legislate for the rest of mankind.<lb/>  He did not legislate in the early ages&#44; because He was<lb/> unknown&#44;&#45;&#45;except by the descendants of the patriarchs&#45;&#45;as<lb/> the only self&#45;existing&#44; all&#45;wise&#44; all&#45;seeing and all&#45;requiting<lb/> God.  Revelation to polytheists would have been fruitless&#44;<lb/> for they might have imagined that what this deity had just<lb/> laid down&#44; another deity could reverse.  He The Almighty did not legis&#45;<lb/>&#45;late for the rest of mankind at later times days periods&#44; because He had provided a more powerful<lb/> medium of instruction&#44; than a single revelation of His will&#44;<lb/> or &#91;&#63;&#93; even a succession of prophetic visions&#44; would have supplied&#59;<lb/> I mean a whole the example of an entire nation governed by laws&#44; which brought<lb/> happiness in proportion to the obedience paid thereto&#44; and<lb/> misfort calamities in the same degrees as those laws were<lb/> neglected disregarded.  A tuition so striking must have<lb/> been productive of the beneficial effects designed by the<lb/> Parent of all.  And truly it is thus that peoples of ancient<lb/> and modern days times have learnt to do righteousness towards the<lb/> Lord&#44; and Justice with man.  Gentilism is indebted to<lb/> Israel basking in the sun of prosperity&#59; to Israel in<lb/> the gloom of affliction.  Palestine and Rome&#44; Greece and Abyssi&#45;<lb/>&#45;nia&#44; the old and the new hemisphere continue still to draw knowledge at the same<lb/> school.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Now&#44; as far as the Pentateuch has a bearing on the Decalogue&#44;<lb/>&#45;&#45;which is a summary of fundamental duties&#45;&#45;it claims by its own<lb/> merits&#44; the acceptance adherence of all sentient beings.  But when it is na&#45;<lb/>&#45;tionally distinctive in its character&#44; having connection with agra&#45;<lb/>&#45;rain&#44; sacrificial and dietary and other laws of similar import&#44; then it remains&#44; in a more<lb/> exclusive sense&#44; the heritage of that portion of mankind&#44; sworn to<lb/> the service of its great voluntarily accepted Master.  Mark this.  Our prophets&#44; who<lb/> in their inspired orations&#44; often addressed gentiles&#44; did not reproach<lb/> them for having failed to conform with the rules of tithes&#44; or<lb/> offerings&#44; or food&#44; but for their having <sic>practised</sic> violence&#44; cruelty&#44;<lb/> and falsehood.  In rebuking the Hebrews&#44; however&#44; our Seers&#39;<lb/> complaints were directed also against the desertion pollution or neglect of the altar&#44; the<lb/> pollution irreverence or misapplication of the worship&#44; the eating of things mosaically declared<lb/> loathsome.  Trespasses of a communal like those of a social<lb/> character&#44; aroused kindled the wrath of the sainted preachers&#44; when<lb/> reproving the house of Jacob. bound by the whole Law<lb/></p>
            <p>The question whether a day will arrive in which the human<lb/> family will assume the observance of the Pentateuch in its<lb/> entirety&#44; I dare solve in the negative.  I bow most<lb/> profoundly reverently to the memory of pious and deep&#45;thinking writers authors<lb/> who have advanced a contrary opinion.  My superiors beyond<lb/> any comparison have searched out in the Bible a confirmation<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>to their devout aspirations.  I am not ignorant of the<lb/> support they have sought.  Scriptural passages may be<lb/> so construed as to favor the theory of a universality of Judaism&#44;<lb/> but I&#44; leaving considering that a number of precepts on the five books<lb/> of Moses draw originated with events in the checkered life of<lb/> Israel  a single people of the earth&#59; knowing that a multiplicity<lb/> of ordinances were intended to oppose heathen usages&#44; that others usages&#44; encouraging polytheism&#44; and that some<lb/> statutes were enacted as symbols of the selection of Israel as missionaries<lb/> of monotheism&#44; I&#44; noticing in the Torah ancestral code institutions peculiar to<lb/> a land and a community small in its compass&#44; believe have arrived at<lb/> the conviction.  The grand moral system of the Pentateuch&#44; with is destined to<lb/> become the common property of all the children of Adam.  They will<lb/> gratefully <sic>received</sic> it at the hands of the few who have jealously guarded it<lb/> as like the pupils of their eyes.  Yet the progeny of Abraham will retain&#44;<lb/> until unless exonerated by the slave driven Power who gave it highest Power and in the clearest manner&#44; and in the same public manner&#44; they will retain<lb/> all the testimonies&#44; and statutes tenets and rules of the volumes&#44; which<lb/> we bless as Torah Adona&#239;&#44; the legislation of the Everlasting One.<lb/></p>
            
            <p>&#40;To prove that it is a divine legation&#44; and Moses was its &#91;&#63;&#93; its &#91;&#63;&#93; messenger<lb/> &#91;&#63;&#93; contents&#44; will be my next effort.&#41;</p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
