<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF15_4</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_4_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_4_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_4_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_4_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_4_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_4_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_4_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_4_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_4_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_4_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_4_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_4_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_4_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_4_7v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>4th lecture on the<lb/>
                existence of God.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  To agreeably engage the attention of my hearers&#44;<lb/> while trying to afford some useful instruction would always<lb/> be my aim&#44; if I were equal to it&#59; but the difficulty to<lb/> accomplish both objects increases in proportion as the topics<lb/> to be discussed are abstract in their character.  I fear<lb/> therefore that last Sabbath&#44; instead of being pleasantly enter&#45;<lb/>&#45;tained&#44; you may have experienced considerable fatigue in following<lb/> me&#44; when I was giving a passing description of the phi&#45;<lb/>&#45;losophy originating with Benedict Spinoza.  I found<lb/> it&#44; however&#44; necessary to mention the pantheist of Holland&#44;<lb/> as a caution to the Jewish youths of America.  They are likely<lb/> to become fascinated by names.  The fictitious glory of<lb/> numbering among their celebrities as man of world&#45;wide<lb/> renown&#44; is very apt to mislead.  I have every desire to encourage<lb/> a sentiment of denominational pride&#44; which may act as an<lb/> incentive to noble endeavours&#44; but not when at the cost of truth.<lb/>  That sentiment has grown into a morbid sentimentality.<lb/>  Within late years all who by birth or descent might have claimed<lb/> a place in Israel&#39;s history if they so chose&#44; are appropriated as our own with&#45;<lb/>&#45;out discrimination&#44; despite the humiliating fact that many<lb/> of them drowned their extraction&#44; or deliberately did it Judaism injury.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Spinoza was a profound thinker&#44; but he did not<lb/> think Jewishly&#44; nor even Deistically.  He was a Biblical<lb/> scholar&#44; but he did not illustrate the Bible to the credit<lb/> of his people&#39;s credit.  I say nothing of his living and dying<lb/> among strangers to his father&#39;s faith&#44; because some may ac&#45;<lb/>&#45;count for it in the unfortunate <sic>excomunication</sic> hurled<lb/> against the pantheist by the Rabbis of Amsterdam Rabbis.  But<lb/> I do him no injustice when I pronounce his writings teachings anti&#45;<lb/>Mosaic&#44; and his whole life an eye&#45;sore to the Hebrews of all his<lb/> ages.  I must therefore disconnect his name<lb/> with from that of men of whose literary productions Israelites<lb/> have a legitimate right to boast.  My young<lb/> friends have&#44; no doubt&#44; heard of Maimonides&#44; the great theo&#45;<lb/>&#45;logian&#44; physician and philosopher&#44; and of his predecessor<lb/> Solomon Ben Gabriol&#44; the great poet and philosopher.<lb/>  We may not approve of all that those two Sages wrote&#44;<lb/> but we all will award to them the merit of having unequi&#45;<lb/>&#45;vocally taught the existence of God&#59; revelation and immortality.<lb/>  Hence I declare false the assertion of some that from<lb/> them Spinoza learnt the destructive theories&#44; which he<lb/> <sic>developped</sic> into a new system.  I am certain that if those<lb/> Spanish Rabbis were alive&#44; they would thrust back the charge<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>with righteous indignation&#44; in the same manner as the<lb/> German Mendelssohn repelled it the imputation of Spinos being weded to tinctured with Spinosim&#44; when an attempt was made<lb/> to fasten it upon him by persons who misunderstood that true Jew&#44;<lb/> gentleman and scholar.<lb/></p>
            <p>Maimonides is explicit in his famous book&#44; called &#34; a teachers of<lb/> the perplexed&#34;.  He says&#58; &#34;the belief of the adherents of to the Mosaic<lb/> Law is that every thing which has existence&#45;&#45;except the blessed<lb/> Creator Himself&#45;&#45;was brought forth out of absolute nothing by<lb/> God Almighty.  Nothing but Himself is self&#45;existing&#59;<lb/> nothing&#44; neither an angel&#44; nor a planet&#44; nor the force that<lb/> moves a planet.  All these have emanated from the free will<lb/> and pleasure of God.&#34;  And further on he observes&#58; &#34;According<lb/> to our opinion&#44; creation is the result of a design&#44; not of a<lb/> necessity&#44; for it is possible for Him who planned it to alter<lb/> it for some other purpose.&#34;  So also Gabirol in his splendid<lb/> poem&#44; entitled &#34;the royal crown&#44;&#34; addressing the Deity exclaims&#58;<lb/> &#34;Thou has created me not by necessity&#44; but by freedom of will&#44;<lb/> not by compulsion but through volition and love&#34;.  And<lb/> in his Arabic work &#43; rightly styled &#34;a choice selection of pearls&#34; he writes&#58;<lb/> &#34;A Sage was once asked to define God the Creator&#59; the answer was &#39;to<lb/> explain what can never be learnt is folly&#44; to deny whatever is above<lb/></p>
            <p>&#43; according to some&#44; it is a mere translation from Arabic &#38; Greek proverbs.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>our understanding is sin&#39;&#34;  And this heinous offence&#44; my dear<lb/> hearers&#44; they commit who would rob the world of the sus&#45;<lb/>&#45;taining hope in a universal Father&#44; because their most<lb/> audacious efforts to reach up to Him and palpably feel<lb/> that He is&#44; are like the endeavours of a fly that should try<lb/> to overtake an eagle and touch ride upon it&#44; as the king of birds&#44; spans<lb/> the sky with its outstretched wings.<lb/></p>
            <p>Atheists see the harmonious symmetrical position of the sun in relation to<lb/> <sic>to</sic> the planets&#59; they notice the cedar and the hyssop&#44; the<lb/> lily and the rose drink the refreshing dew&#44; and expand under<lb/> the solar rays&#59; they perceive a perfect agreement harmony between<lb/> man&#39;s wants and his capacities for enjoyment&#59; they know<lb/> that man thinks and acts by powers hidden but incontestable&#44;<lb/> and yet they deny.  The admirable arrangement point to<lb/> a Mind that regulated all with supreme wisdom&#44; the <sic>marvellous</sic><lb/> order&#44; majesty and beauties of creation which delights the soul<lb/> of the sensitive and meditative&#44; are not accepted as a con&#45;<lb/>vincing proof of the existence of God.  Why&#63; because<lb/> this existence does not fall under our their senses&#44; and because neither can<lb/> the finite intellect grasp it.<lb/></p>
            <p>Let us hear then what they give us propose for our acceptance&#44; which is more tangible&#44;<lb/> more comprehensible.  Oh&#33; human perversity&#33;  They chase away<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>They chase away the idea of God&#44; Creator and Disposer<lb/> of all things&#44; to offer instead&#44; as an alternative&#44; the hypothesis<lb/> of a combination of atoms accidentally building up worlds&#44;<lb/> and that of a blind necessity&#44; of or of a substance&#45;&#45;the God of Spinoza&#45;&#45;shaping matter into millions of<lb/> of objects&#44; all each performing a different task&#44; but all contributing to<lb/> preserve in its entirety the grand fabric of the universe.<lb/>  And that hypothesis they would dignify with the title of philo&#45;<lb/>&#45;sophy.  Brethren.  I cannot tell your impressions.<lb/>  but As to myself I prefer remaining unphilosophical&#44; but in<lb/> the possession of that plain logic which leads me directly from<lb/> the effect to the cause&#44; recognizing in this an Intellectual Power&#59; an Omnipotent<lb/> Being.  If that be ignorance I choose it in preference to that<lb/> learning implying the acceptance of theories which my reason<lb/> rejects&#44; and my feelings revolt against.  I could more<lb/> readily bow to the mighty luminary when it rides the heavens&#44;<lb/> and acknowledge it a god&#44; or bend the knee before the foaming<lb/> ocean&#59; when its waves swell majestically&#44; than believe that<lb/> the animal3&#44; the vegetable2 and the mineral1 kingdoms have sprung<lb/> up by casualty like the mythological Minerva from the<lb/> head of Jupiter&#59; or that a law of compulsion spread out the fir&#45;<lb/>&#45;mament as a curtain&#44; and bespangled it with starry worlds.<lb/>  Admit&#58; I am ignorant of the essence of my Creator&#59; I cannot<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>form the slightest conception of His preexistence to all<lb/> which has existence&#44; but in that I do not stand alone because<lb/> of my puny intellect.  Men gifted with the greatest genius&#44;<lb/> have felt the narrow compass of their mental faculties&#44; when<lb/> in search of the highest Divine Truth.  The wise will study<lb/> the developments of science&#44; while they humbly go in quest of<lb/> that truth&#44; and rest satisfied if they can raise in the smallest<lb/> degree a corner of the veil which conceals it from human understanding.<lb/>  The fools will observe the wonderful application of the God&#39;s laws<lb/> of nature and still say in their hearts &#34;there is no God&#34;.  This<lb/> so did The wisdom of It was the Psalmist declared when it that has warned<lb/> society of the baneful consequences of Atheism such folly by this sentence.<lb/>  &#34;They &#40;the godless&#41; have become corrupt&#44; they have done abominable works&#44;<lb/> there is none that go does good&#34;.  Yes&#44; friends&#44; without<lb/> the all&#45;supporting idea of God&#44; the foundations of the social<lb/> edifice will totters and finally crumble into dust.  Without a model of<lb/> goodness in Him who designed and brought out all for the<lb/> happiness of His creatures&#44; selfishness will rule to till it accomplishes utter destruction.<lb/>  Without a pattern of justice in Him who has destined<lb/> for all His creatures the varied products of the earth He made<lb/> fertile&#44; abnormal inequalities would crush the weak under the<lb/> powerful. powerful.<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="8"/>
                <p>The idea of God can solely uphold us in virtue.<lb/>  Not by the fear of punishment&#44; nor even by the expect&#45;<lb/>&#45;ation of a reward&#45;&#45;though both are certain to come here and hereafter&#45;&#45;&#44;<lb/> but by its offering to us an archetype of perfection&#44;<lb/> which to approach should be the loftiest aspiration of<lb/> your lives&#44; my intelligent young hearers.  God&#44; reflected<lb/> in the Sun which illumines warms and gladdens worlds&#59; God&#44;<lb/> reflected in the tiny <sic>flowret</sic> which sweetens the air&#44; is<lb/> the same copy of loving&#45;kindness set before your<lb/> vision.  Oh&#33; Do not turn away from it<lb/> to become entangled in a maze of insoluble questions&#44; I mean the<lb/> questions which they apparent suffering of the righteous&#44;<lb/> and the seeming prosperity of the wicked raise against<lb/> the principle of an even&#45;handed Justice&#59; the assumed pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;valence of evil against the doctrine of a celestial supervision.<lb/>  Atheists who do not see a Creator through that<lb/> which is clearly beneficial affords blessings in a superlative degree&#44; will<lb/> not acknowledge Him because of existing afflictions.<lb/>  For if the Artificer has not been at all at work&#44; then He<lb/> is no more the Author of what mortals call troubles&#44; than<lb/> the Maker of what brings veritable joys.  It is to the<lb/> believer that those questions are harrowing and perplexing.<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="9"/>
                <p>And yet if he be intelligent&#44; he will often&#44; if not al&#45;<lb/>&#45;ways&#44; justify the ways of Providence&#44; for he will<lb/> discover in innumerable instances that man himself has been<lb/> the Creator of his misfortune.  Appetites and ambition&#44;<lb/> loose passions and a defiance of the <sic>imprescribable</sic> rules of nature have<lb/> militated against his happiness.  And what is true of<lb/> individuals&#44; applies with equal or more force to fa&#45;<lb/>&#45;milies and to nations at large.  countless are those<lb/> who might have led a life of tran ease and contentment&#44;<lb/> but who voluntarily chose a harassing one full of<lb/> disappointments and regrets and disappointments.  And does not every day&#39;s<lb/> history show national disasters as the immediate issue<lb/> of national wrongs&#63;  God does watch and regulate&#44;<lb/> not to control our freedom of will&#59; nor to alter the laws<lb/> He has primordially established on the moral as well as<lb/> physical world&#44; so that the men we consider pious be<lb/> highly lifted up&#44; and those we regard as impious be<lb/> obviously cast down.  No&#59; He keeps a vigilant guard<lb/> over &#91;&#63;&#93; human events and however wicked He sublunary events&#44; to mould their to prevent them&#45;&#45;howsoever wicked grievous&#45;&#45;from thwarting His wise in&#45;<lb/>&#45;tentions&#44; and to makes them work out His paternal design wish<lb/> for the progress of the human race.<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="10"/>
                <p>That is my soul&#45;supporting dogma.<lb/>  Do I then deny the existence of evil beyond our control&#63;<lb/>  God grant I could.  I perceive it and lament it&#44; and<lb/> when trying to reconcile it with my conviction of a over&#45;<lb/>ruling Providence my brains reel and stagger.  But I deny<lb/> the prevalence of evil&#44; and deny that life is an uninterrupted series of<lb/> sorrows.  Felicity and infelicity are not to be measured<lb/> by the hour&#44; nor by the gauge that people mostly use&#45;&#45;<lb/>gold.  The pleasures derived from the performance of duty&#44;<lb/> from the well&#45;earned esteem of the upright&#44; from the love of our child&#45;<lb/>&#45;ren and from the contemplation of the glories of creation and its<lb/> Creator&#44; outweigh trials and hardships and annoyances we may<lb/> at times have endured.  And&#44; on the contrary&#44; the success<lb/> of the disho dishonest may be a hidden fire&#44; which will not<lb/> let him rest.  An Italian poet of great renown wrote these<lb/> lines&#58; &#34;If the piercings of the heart could be traced upon the fore&#45;<lb/>head&#44; how many that we envy&#44; might excite our deep pity&#33;&#34;<lb/></p>
                <p>Here I end discussing the first topic of my series&#44; not<lb/> because I presume to have spoken upon it exhaustively&#44; for had I the<lb/> acumen of a Socrates and the eloquence of a Demosthenes&#44;<lb/> I would fall short of the magnitude of the subject&#44;<lb/> but because I judge that the very little I have advanced in the<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="11"/>
                <p>in the last four lectures&#44; will suffice to awaken your<lb/> reflection&#44; my dear young friends.  Feeble as my<lb/> arguments may have been&#44; they may still serve as a shield<lb/> to screen you from the attacks of unbelief.  Happy<lb/> will I feel if you that have listened will carry further<lb/> the blessed conviction of the truth I sought to inculcate most happy<lb/> to know that you have become the means of rescuing the thought&#45;<lb/>&#45;less and the prejudiced from the curse of Atheism&#59; that<lb/> you have persuasively brought them to the footstool<lb/> of the Sovereign Lord&#44; to adore Him as the self&#45;existing&#44;<lb/> the powerful omnipotent&#44; the merciful and all&#45;loving<lb/> Creator and God.  So may it be.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
