<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF2_10</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_10_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_10_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_10_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_10_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_10_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_10_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_10_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_10_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_10_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_10_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_10_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_10_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_10_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_10_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_10_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_10_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>On Penitence<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA.</p>
            
            <p>Brethren.  When I consider the solemnity of the<lb/> occasion that brought us together&#44; and the still more<lb/> solemn day&#44; which is now fast approaching&#44; I<lb/> cannot but repeat to refrain from asking myself the question asked which was put<lb/> once put by an olden Hebrew Sage &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;I wonder whether there can be found in this gene&#45;<lb/>&#45;ration any that is fit to reprove&#44;&#34; for should he<lb/> he tell his neighbor &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;You ought<lb/> to take out that splinter sticking in your teeth&#44;&#34; the<lb/> other might retort resent the censure what he thinks an insult&#44; by answering &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;remove that large piece of timber which I notice between<lb/> your own eyes&#34;&#44; meaning of course&#44; as we would com&#45;<lb/> &#45;monly say in common talk&#58; &#34;those who live in glass houses should not<lb/> throw stones.&#34;  But yet&#44; among the serious thoughts that<lb/> crowd my mind always at this season time of year&#44; one spurs<lb/> me on to speak.  It is that not because I wish<lb/> to pass off as immaculate&#44; I admonish and exhort&#44;<lb/> but simply because I would fall short of my the duty&#44;<lb/> imposed upon me&#44; if I kept silent.  Let us then consider together<lb/> how best we may can employ a short time which may<lb/> prove of common mutual advantage.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>&#40;Is there perchance any here who refuses my pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;position&#44; because he can produce a stainless life&#44;<lb/> because he feels perfectly here that neither in thoughts&#44;<lb/> nor in words&#44; nor in actions he has ever been guilty<lb/> of a departure from the path of right&#63;  Why&#44; if<lb/> a being so extraordinarily blessed&#44; exists in this as&#45;<lb/>&#45;semblage&#44; let him come forward&#44; we will give<lb/> him the most prominent station that he may<lb/> be fully heard.  But&#44; be I assume that no one can flatter him&#45;<lb/>&#45;self to be an exception to that which the wisest<lb/> of men discovered&#44; viz&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;A human being upon earth cannot be so<lb/> righteous&#44; as to do always good and not to sin.&#34;  Nor<lb/> does He who created us of flesh and blood&#44; expect such it of<lb/> a conduct from weak mortals.  What He demands<lb/> is that we try to come draw ever nearer to holiness righteousness He demands<lb/> that when we have gone astray from the path leading<lb/> to it&#44; we retrace our steps and come back again to duty&#44;<lb/> and such is the object of the penitential days&#44; as in&#45;<lb/>&#45;stituted by the Sages of Israel.  For note this down brethren&#44; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> actually means &#34;a return&#34;.  Nine days have been<lb/> granted us at this solemn season to search ourselves out&#44; to find whether<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>when Yom Kippur dans arrives when the tenth day dawns&#44; we can honestly&#44; con&#45;<lb/>&#45;sistently as Jews&#44; stand before the all&#45;seeing Father and<lb/> exclaim &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Behold us&#44; we have<lb/> come back to Thee&#44; for Thou art the Lord our God&#34; &#40;Should<lb/> these nine days pass&#44; while we still rush headlong<lb/> after our usual faults&#44; fasting and supplications on<lb/> the tenth&#44; would have no weight.  So tell us our ancient<lb/> Teachers &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;The fast which is not worthily<lb/> kept&#44; is like the empty sound of loud voices&#41;.  If in<lb/> thronging these sacred &#91;&#63;&#93; on the day of atonement<lb/> we are actuated by a sincere wish to implore forgive&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness for past misdeeds the which whatever was faulty&#44; in the past and to petition the Parent<lb/> of good for His support in the future&#44; let each of these pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;bationary days see us engaged in righting what<lb/> has been wrong and adding to the number of our<lb/> merits.  So addresses us Isaiah in the name of <lb/> His master&#58; &#34;Wash yourselves&#44; make yourselves clean&#44;<lb/> put away the evil of your doings from before my<lb/> eyes&#44; cease to do evil&#44; learn to do good&#44; seek judgment&#44; relieve the op&#45;<lb/>&#45;pressed&#44; judge the fatherless&#44; plead for the widow&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>then come and let us reason together&#44; &#40;saith the<lb/> Lord&#41; though your sins be as scarlet&#44; they shall<lb/> become as white as snow&#44; though they be red<lb/> like crimson&#44; they shall become as wool &#34;Let<lb/> us reflect.  You may have noticed that in the<lb/> sentences just quoted&#44; nine things are proposed<lb/> to us on the performance of which the entire re&#45;<lb/>&#45;mission of our transgressions is made to depend<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; Exclaims Cries out the man of God.  Your hands<lb/> have made the black stains&#44; and they must remove wipe off the<lb/> black dark spots.  No vicarious agency is admitted in Israel.  We ourselves must work out our salvation.  No meditation&#44; except our own correct proceedings.  But&#44; &#34;how can I succeed&#63;&#34; says my brother&#44; &#34;I am<lb/> by nature so prone to evil&#44; that all my exertions<lb/> will avail nothing.&#34;  Don&#39;t believe it.  To think<lb/> so is an insult to offend the Lord.  Were it not in our<lb/> power to improve&#44; would we have been told &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Wash yourselves&#34;&#63;  Had the Almighty away far be the impious<lb/> thought&#33;  Had he given given us an inclination to<lb/> go wrong that we might be lost beyond recovery&#44;<lb/> to what purpose would have been his the ordinances of<lb/> the Torah&#63;  Does He not repeatedly call on us that in the volumes of Revelation to<lb/> desist from our vicious practices&#63;  Useless would that<lb/> admonition be&#44; if we must perforce run after our own<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>evil counsel.  Can an Israelite who has ever read studied his<lb/> Bible hold to a doctrine so subversive of society&#63; destructive&#63;<lb/>  I read again what Moses wrote in the name of the<lb/> Most High &#34;I take as witnesses this day the heavens<lb/> and the earth &#91;Inserted above&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#93;&#44; that I have set before you blessing<lb/> and curse&#44; life and death&#44; choose therefore life&#44; that<lb/> you and your progeny may live for ever.&#34;  It lies<lb/> then in our own power&#44; to live in righteousness and not to die in impiousness&#44; to become as<lb/> pure as the purest of mortals.  Naturally&#44; it is not<lb/> at the first attempt that we can conquer the ene&#45;<lb/>&#45;my of our character&#45;sin.  In order to cure the leprosy<lb/> of the Syrian general of old&#44; a sevenfold purification immersion<lb/> in the water of the Jordan was prescribed&#44; and that<lb/> was to take away a bodily disease&#59; more than such a stronger appliance<lb/> procedure than that is needed to heal a spiritual malady.<lb/>  Hence continues Isaiah &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;make yourselves perfectly<lb/> clean&#34;.  It is by constant purifications that the moral<lb/> stains spots will ultimately disappear.  If after having<lb/> led a life of dissipation&#44; we refrain once or twice<lb/> or even seven times from indulging&#44; in we cannot boast<lb/> of having entirely overcome our passions.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>We must become masters of our inclinations&#44; to the situation&#44; so to speak&#44;<lb/> keep thence our inclinations under&#59; be ceaselessly on the alert&#44; not<lb/> to allow the enemy insidious foe that we thought to have<lb/> defeated&#44; to attack us again.  It would be a<lb/> fatal indiscretion to let it lark around in ambush.<lb/>  Would we leave in our path a stumbling block<lb/> which had repeatedly made us fall&#63;  Or would we<lb/> voluntarily breathe a pestilential air which former&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly made us ill&#44; for the simple reason that apparent&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly we have now entirely recovered&#63;  &#40;Surely&#41; we are<lb/> not wiser than King Solomon&#59; he also thought him&#45;<lb/>&#45;self proof against seductions say the Talmudists &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; but<lb/> not withstanding the lesson of his father&#39;s suffering and<lb/> humiliation he abandoned himself to sins of a similar<lb/> nature to those that exposed David to shame&#44; therefore our text reads &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;take away the evil of your doings &#40;from before<lb/> my eyes&#34;&#41;.  Remove the causes of your moral down&#45;<lb/>&#45;fall.  No human regard&#44; no fear of being taunted<lb/> by those&#44; whom we were in the habit of consort&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing with&#44; should induce us to retain the vipers that<lb/> consumes our spiritual vitals.  This one may<lb/> say&#58; &#34;Don&#39;t you be so fastidious&#34; why&#44; you may<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>compensate atone for your indulging in worldly plea&#45; escapades<lb/> &#45;sures by some act of devotion&#34;; another may tell<lb/> us&#58; &#34;some external observances of your faith will<lb/> atone&#34; procure you absolution for indulging in worldly pleasures&#44;&#34; just as if we could compromise with<lb/> truth&#44; as if wrong would cease to be such&#44; because<lb/> we try to do something which is right.  Suppose<lb/> that at stated times we move our lips in prayers&#44;<lb/> will that pardon our compensate for compensate for a villainous and blasphemous<lb/> tongue&#63;  Or that while we abstain from forbidden<lb/> food&#44; we do not scruple eating up the wages of<lb/> the laborer.  Would that please be to serve the God of righteous&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness&#63;  No &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Cease to do evil&#34; continues<lb/> the prophet.  Give up your bad habits and chase<lb/> away what turns you to them vice sin.  Nor does that<lb/> suffice.  A negative virtue is that which guards<lb/> against misdeeds.  A positive religion it is to act<lb/> morally soberly at home&#44; and morally abroad&#44; and honestly&#44; all circumstances&#44; with all<lb/> men.  Do not say me if I &#34;Fine preaching.  It sounds well&#34; I hear one say&#44; &#34;but were I to follow such directions unde&#45;<lb/> viatingly to the letter&#44; what sacrifices I would be obliged to make&#44; and then my wealth will not would never increase.&#34;  Oh&#33; my Brother.  Look Remem&#45;<lb/> &#45;ber around and see the victims of dissoluteness.  Remember above all<lb/> the terrible denunciation of Jeremiah &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>&#34;He that getteth riches and be not by justice&#44;<lb/> shall leave them in the midst of his days&#44; and<lb/> in his latter end shall be considered low.&#34;  Daily<lb/> experience illustrates even very to the letter the prediction<lb/> of the inspired servant of God.  Hence we are<lb/> bid &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Learn to do good&#34;.  Determine that<lb/> none shall have ever bring to against you the charge<lb/> of immorality&#44; of insobriety&#44; of wantonness&#44; of fraudulence&#44; of chicanery&#44; of subterfuge&#44; of double<lb/> dealing&#59; resolve that integrity morality shall be your badge&#44; veracity<lb/> the girdle of your loins&#44; for that will give your strength&#44;<lb/> and ennoble your existence uplifting your character heaven&#45;<lb/>&#45;ward.  And although Isaiah when Isaiah recommended<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; to &#34;seek judgment&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93; he doubtless addressed<lb/> himself to persons clothed with judicial powers&#44; the<lb/> prophetic imparting may nevertheless be enjoined upon each of us with<lb/> great propriety.  Too apt we are to deviate from<lb/> it in our daily intercourse.  Often we pervert judg&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment when we condemn our neighbors for a word<lb/> he may have incautiously spoken&#44; for an action&#44;<lb/> which&#44; however objectionable&#44; did not spring from<lb/> a vile motive.  At times the ambition to be<lb/> considered learned among the ignorant&#44; will<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>goad us on to bettl belittle others&#44; a heinous<lb/> offence is that &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; which&#44; in the<lb/> mind of our Rabbis&#44; forfeits God&#39;s pardon.<lb/>  Surely it would pain us greatly to hear<lb/> our character aspersed&#44; and do we believe<lb/> our neighbor less alive to his dearest interests&#45;&#45;<lb/> the upholding h of his fair name&#63;  Admitting even that<lb/> his conduct reflects upon him&#44; does it justify<lb/> our publishing his errors&#63;  Who assures us that<lb/> we may well never become guilty of the same<lb/> faults he committed&#63;  We may at present be free<lb/> from them&#44; but with a nature so frail&#44; with a<lb/> knowledge so limited&#44; surrounded by many entice&#45;<lb/>ments&#44; are we certain always to come off victorious<lb/> in the battles against sin and vice&#63;  No one<lb/> could have foretold that Jedoash&#44; who at the<lb/> dawn of his reign had labored diligently to<lb/> restore the Temple to its n magnificence&#44; would<lb/> one day&#44; in order to satisfy an ambitions foe&#44;<lb/> strip the holy place of its riches&#59; &#40;or that Jehu<lb/> who destroyed the altar of Baal&#44; would on even&#45;<lb/>&#45;tually bend the knee f beofre the idol.&#41; yet&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>history records that melancholy fact.  Let us<lb/> not then deny to others what we might one day<lb/> need our own selves&#44;&#45;&#45;indulgence for our shortcomings.<lb/>  But more is demanded at our hands.  However praise&#45;<lb/>&#45;worthy a sense of justice must always be&#59; though<lb/> it is a virtue binding society together&#44; still pity&#44;<lb/> loving kindness&#44; charity are sentiments are more ennobling&#44; better calculated to hold mortals together more loftily and fitter<lb/> to bring us closer to to work out a reconciliation with the pardoning Lord&#44; and bring us closer to the source of all perfection.<lb/></p>
            <p>&#34;Relieve the oppressed&#34; we are asked&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93; Do not stand<lb/> idle while your fellow creature is being dealt foully<lb/> with&#59; hasten to his assistance&#44; afford him your a<lb/> brotherly advice&#44; and if he be fatherless&#44; be level<lb/> down the path on which he may he may proceed<lb/> to the attainment of what renders existence plea&#45;<lb/> &#45;surable a blessing and not a curse for the want<lb/> of a humane guidance &#91;Hebrew&#93; are the<lb/> concluding admonitions of the inspired son of<lb/> Amoz&#44; imposing upon us the solemn duty of<lb/> preventing deliberate wrong being done to the weak<lb/> and the powerless&#44; represented int our text by the orphan and<lb/> the widow in a state of destitution requiring calling for help.<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>goad us on to belittle others&#44; as impure heinous of&#45;<lb/>fense is that &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; which&#44; in the mind<lb/> of our Rabbis&#44; forfeits God&#39;s pardon.  Surely it would<lb/> pain us greatly to hear our name aspersed&#44; do we<lb/> believe our neighbor less alive to the interests of his<lb/> own character&#63;<lb/>
                Now&#44; brethren&#44; if the intervening period between<lb/> Rosh Hashanah and Yom Kippur&#44; will<lb/> see us engaged in carrying out Isaiah&#39;s<lb/> exhortations&#44; straightening our course&#44; if crooked&#44;<lb/> moving fast on in the way of rectitude&#44; holding<lb/> out our hands to raise the fallen&#44; to aid<lb/> the poor&#44; to build up again religion as outlined<lb/> by the prophets and sages of Israel&#44; then we<lb/> shall stand before God arrayed in spotlessness &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> and the shofar blast which announces the dying<lb/> out of the tremend awe inspiring day&#44; shall<lb/> &#91;&#63;&#93; thrill you with us all with the joyous<lb/> tidings belief that a life of happiness has been<lb/> allotted to the penitent here&#44; and a life of<lb/> ineffable delights hereafter.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
