<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF16_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_1_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>a few words of caution to youths&#44;<lb/>
                predicated on professor Tyndall&#39;s address&#44;<lb/>
                wherein he advances materialistic views.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  Were I even able from a long training on the<lb/> study of science&#44; to speak of it with precision&#44; I would consider<lb/> it inappropriate to to make Astronomy&#44; or Geology&#44; or Eth&#45;<lb/>&#45;nology&#44; or any of those results of the profound searchings of<lb/> the human mind&#44; the subject of lectures at the Synagogue.<lb/>  It must naturally be supposed that among a large body of<lb/> men formed promiscuously into a Congregation&#44; few are prepared<lb/> to listen with interest and profit to topics of that character.<lb/>  And as pulpit instruction ought to reach the bulk&#44; if not the<lb/> whole of the audience&#44; it would be unfair to dwell on that<lb/> which is intelligible only to the smallest minority.  Now&#58;<lb/> such a course deserving censure&#44; when followed by an individual preacher<lb/> conversant with sciences&#44; would be exceedingly presumptuous<lb/> in one&#44; like myself&#44; who knows them scarcely by name.<lb/>  I am certain&#44; I could not afford instruction&#44; while I might&#44;<lb/> by the attempt&#44; occasion annoyance.  And still a feeling I<lb/> cannot repress&#44; urges me to allude to literary works relating to<lb/> science.  Not to discuss the latter&#44; but to offer a word of<lb/> friendly caution.  I have observed that some of my brothers<lb/> and sisters in faith&#44; who possibly have not gone any deeper<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>than I have into a recondite knowledge&#44; not yet<lb/> mastered by the most capacious minds&#44; quote it to controvert<lb/> the declarations of the Bible.  Now it is Darwin&#44; whose<lb/> learned speculations have led him to discover our descent from<lb/> apes and gorillas&#44; that makes them bold&#59; anon it is Huxley<lb/> who sees on the nerves the seat of human reason.  The<lb/> latest authority is professor Tyndall in his address at<lb/> Belfast.  That renowned scientist seems to exercise at pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;sent a commanding influence.  In his essay he sums up<lb/> what philosophers and sages have written on the origin of<lb/> heaven and earth and all which is therein&#44; arranges every<lb/> thing in a manner&#44; revealing a skill truly extraordinary&#44;<lb/> and arrives at the startling&#44; and to me most painful con&#45;<lb/>&#45;clusion that the universe is not indebted for its creation<lb/> to a Supreme Intelligence&#44; that formed it with unerring<lb/> forethought.  It I say it is most painful&#44; because the singular<lb/> abilities of the man who proclaims that destructive theory&#44; gives<lb/> it immense weight with our susceptible youths.  The same<lb/> materlialistic idea has been advanced innumerable times<lb/> before.  It is embodied in countless volumes of ancient and<lb/> modern date.  But when conveyed in the shape and in&#45;<lb/>viting style chosen by professor Tyndall&#59; when backed<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>by so vast an array of erudition&#44; it has a fascination un&#45;<lb/>&#45;equalled perhaps by other writings.  I have cause to fear<lb/> it.  Not as a permanent injury to revealed religion&#44; for it has stood<lb/> stronger shocks&#44; but as a disturbing element&#44; poisoning the<lb/> hearts of some of my young brethren.  To those who have read<lb/> or intend reading that address&#44; I will therefore say.  Friends&#33;<lb/>  The following questions present themselves to the unbiased mind<lb/> in perusing that production.<lb/></p>
            <p>Is it more reasonable to believe that atoms striking against<lb/> each other for untold ages&#44; came at last to a convenient ar&#45;<lb/>&#45;rangement&#44; which produced the earth we dwell upon&#44; than<lb/> to believe that the will of a wise Artificer&#44; constructed this<lb/> beautiful world with such exactness&#44; which might fit it<lb/> for the habitation of man&#63;  Is it more reasonable to<lb/> believe that the glittering stars hanging in the sky&#44; shot<lb/> out of their own accord from some thin vapor or cloud&#44; than<lb/> to believe that an all&#45;powerful Designer fashioned them<lb/> and sent them kindled with an unquenchable fir light&#45;<lb/>sent them rolling through infinite space&#63;  Is it more reasonable<lb/> to believe that our senses and our faculties are the effect<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>of chemical combinations&#44; that to believe that we<lb/> a beneficent Maker gave us eyes purposely that we might<lb/> see and enjoy our surroundings&#44; and intellect that we might<lb/> independently act&#63;  Is it more reasonable to believe that<lb/> we can purchase peace by a voluntary death&#44; or in other<lb/> words shuffle off troubles by suicide&#44; than to believe that the<lb/> mind will survive the body of which it is the impelling<lb/> force&#63;  These questions&#44; my friends&#33; which I wil have with<lb/> reluctance touched upon&#59; these questions which Mr Tyndall&#39;s<lb/> address present to the thoughtful have been definitely<lb/> solved.  Their solution will be found in the very page&#44;<lb/> which stands as a frontspiece to the revealed book.<lb/>  Not scientifically given&#44; for that was not the aim of the<lb/> scriptures&#44; but in a clear&#44; concise&#44; and comprehensive manner.<lb/>  It tells us that the idea of an eternity of matter is false&#59;<lb/> that a personal God brought by His absolute will every<lb/> thing above&#44; around&#44; and beneath us into existence &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  It tells us that man is the most perfect<lb/> of beings not because he is the last link in the chain of<lb/> a gradual development among irrational animals&#44; but be&#45;<lb/>&#45;cause the Creator Himself moulded his wonderful frame&#44; and<lb/> because God breathed within him a living soul &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>This truth enunciated in the opening chapter of the Hebrew<lb/> Bible&#59; this truth which lies at the foundations of Mosaism&#44; to<lb/> use a phrase now a days in vogue&#44; is borne out by all Jewish<lb/> writings&#44; and nowhere more plainly than in the Haftarah desi&#45;<lb/>&#45;gnated for Sabbath Bereshoth.  &#34;Thus sayeth God&#44; the Eternal<lb/> Lord&#44; He that created the heavens and stretched them out&#59; He that<lb/> spread forth the earth and the things that come form it&#59; He<lb/> that giveth breath unto the people upon it&#44; and a spirit<lb/> unto those tht walk therein.  I am the Eternal Lord&#44; that<lb/> is my name&#44; nor will I give my glory to another&#34;.  Hear it&#44; my Brethren&#33;  To another&#44;<lb/> my Brethren&#33; whether it be an idol as heathens shape it&#44; or one in<lb/> a form of molecules and atoms.  This vital truth must be<lb/> considered inviolable.  Science will then be welcome to all her<lb/> investigations.  For&#44; boundless is the field through which she can<lb/> range.  She will be hailed by the intelligent theologian&#44; as<lb/> the brightest illustration of that freedom of will&#44; which Holy<lb/> Writ proclaims&#59; as the noblest exercise of man&#39;s distinguishing<lb/> powers&#59; but when failing to explain fathom what will ever remain inexpli&#45; unfathomable<lb/> &#45;cable&#45;&#45;the essence of God&#45;&#45;she attempts to substitute self&#45;&#45;ma&#45;<lb/>&#45;king and self&#45;<sic>developping</sic> matter for an all&#45;wise Creator and<lb/> Architect.  When she dares assail the citadel of religion&#44; and<lb/> storm its ramparts&#44; that is&#44; God and immortality&#44; then she is<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>an insidious enemy&#44; whom mankind must hate.<lb/></p>
            <p>I am disqualified to refute by a line of scientific arguments what<lb/> Mr Tyndall set forth in his address.  But common sense&#44; of which<lb/> I am not deprived&#44; because of my unacquaintance with science&#44; assures<lb/> me that the professor has overshot his mark.  He determined to<lb/> enter a province&#44; which is not more and less inaccessible to him&#44; than to the most<lb/> illiterate&#44; and in doing so&#44; he injured the cause of science with the<lb/> believer&#44; and sowed the seeds of disbelief in the hearts of science&#45;<lb/>loving youths.  This painful reflection led me to allude<lb/> to a subject otherwise foreign to the Jewish pulpit.  It is<lb/> not enough that in his closing remarks the lecturer admitted the<lb/> possibility&#44; nay&#44; the certainty that the views advanced will<lb/> undergo changes.  It is not enough that he conceded that our<lb/> inborn sentiments of religiousness&#44; as well as the claims of our<lb/> understanding must be satisfied&#59; that man is a superior being<lb/> not only because he thinks profoundly&#44; but because he feels<lb/> deeply&#44; and acts humanely.  No&#58; it is not enough&#44; for&#44;<lb/> the mind of the reader&#44; unless sustained by the declarations of<lb/> Holy Writ&#44; has been already impregnated with heresies&#44; rendered<lb/> more dangerous by the attractive form in which they are brought forward.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>But there is a sentence in that address&#44; which the author quotes<lb/> for a different purpose than I will apply it&#44; but which is at all<lb/> events&#44; edifying.  He writes&#58; &#34;A great man said to me once&#58;<lb/> &#34;Did I not believe that a Supreme Intelligence is at the heart of<lb/> things&#44; my life on earth would be intolerable&#34;  Yes&#59; beloved<lb/> youths&#33;  Life with its numerous trials would often be unendurable&#44;<lb/> were it not for the faith we must have in that all&#45;prescient<lb/> Wisdom&#44; that regulates events to a beneficial end.  This is<lb/> not blind faith&#44; but the result of a study of the workings of<lb/> nature&#44; as well as of the words of revelation.  For&#44; there cannot be a<lb/> contradiction between what god traced in the volumes of creation&#44; and <lb/>what He wrote in the grand old book.  When Holy Writ said&#58;<lb/> God saw all which He had made&#44; and behold&#44; it was very good&#44;&#34; it<lb/> meant to teach that perfect harmony exists in whatever proceeds<lb/> from the Almighty&#44; that the laws He has enacted&#44; carry out the precise<lb/> object He had designed&#44; and that by His constant direction of the same<lb/> laws&#44; no enduring evil can befall the individual or the social family.<lb/>  The science whose researches illustrate this principle&#59; that which<lb/> leads our thoughts upward with awe and gratitude to the Unseen<lb/> and Eternal Lord&#44; is the associate of religion.  But the science which<lb/> drags us downward&#59; that which does not open our ears to the<lb/> majestic voice of the Lord speaking through nature and revelation&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>but would make us hear only the striking of atoms&#44; and the<lb/> shocks of chance&#44; is blasphemy.  It is even worse.  It is a hot<lb/> blast drying up the source of virtue in the human heart.<lb/>  Let not its breath wither your noble instincts&#44; O youths of my<lb/> people&#33;  In the figurative language of the ancient moralist&#44; I&#44; who<lb/> sincerely desire your happiness&#44; say now &#34;Go not astray in her path&#44;<lb/> for she hath cast down many wounded&#44; many strong men have been<lb/> slain by her.  The ways to the nether world in her home&#44; leading<lb/> down to the chambers of death&#34;  Better would it be for the peace<lb/> of your mind&#44; for the advantage of Judaism&#44; and for that of the<lb/> human race at large&#44; that you remain in ignorance of abstruse studies&#44;<lb/> than you be godless.  Better that you be crowned with deeds of<lb/> piety&#44; flowing from a love of the Creator&#44; and a sense of your account&#45;<lb/>&#45;ability to Him&#44; than you be <sic>laurelled</sic> a prodigy of learning.  Yet&#44; you<lb/> can wear the adornments lent both by religion and science&#44; if you<lb/> will be guided through life by this truth&#44; which Moses taught&#44; and<lb/> civilized communities have accepted&#44; namely&#44; God is the Maker&#44;<lb/> God is the upholder&#44; God is the Ruler and Judge of the universe.<lb/>  Oh&#33; may He who has gifted His creatures with the capacity to soar<lb/> high and dive deep in their investigations&#44; be your escort.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>You will neither be seized with a vertigo&#44; which misrepresents<lb/> ofje objects&#44; nor be entangled into a maze of fatal errors.<lb/>  And for our young brother&#44; who has been added to the number<lb/> of observant Israelites&#44; I implore a blessing.  May he become<lb/> strong in faith&#44; vigorous in intellect&#44; prosperous in worldly<lb/> undertakings&#44; and noted for deeds of goodness and philanthropy.<lb/>  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
