<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF19_6</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1894" source="" attested="yes">1894</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_6_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_6_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_6_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_6_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_6_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_6_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_6_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_6_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_6_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_6_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_6_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_6_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>31</p>
            
            <p>94<lb/>
                On the need for more religious schools<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Some of the persistence with which Christians labor<lb/> to accomplish their a perverting object&#44; might well be copied by<lb/> Jews to defeat that same object.  The efforts of a single<lb/> individual&#44; or of a few persons separately&#44; however<lb/> earnest&#44; will not compass the end in view.  but In<lb/> union there is the strength needed for a determined<lb/> purpose.  In the Southern section of our city&#44;<lb/> where a vast number of our coreligionists of foreign<lb/> birth congregate&#44; a danger faced Judaism on all<lb/> sides.  It The peril encountered is a plan insidiously laid out&#44; to bring the<lb/> young of Israel to be the acknowledgment of a creed abhorrent to our<lb/> soul.  Mission schools are planted and measures<lb/> adopted to fill those schools with boys and girls who should shun such schools them as we would avoid the verge of a precipice&#59; boys and girls whose<lb/> every fibre should thrillingly respond to the daily declaration Adona&#239;<lb/> Echad&#44; &#34;The Lord is One.&#34;  I stealthily wit&#45;<lb/>&#45;nessed the exercises of gone through at those schools&#44; and felt deep&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly pained as hearing children who ought to learn<lb/> the history of the patriarchs&#44; the lessons of our pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;phets and sages&#44; rehearse a catechism which taught<lb/> the deification of perishable man&#44; the dogma of a blood atone&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment for inherited sin and the hurling of curses on Jews<lb/> as God&#39;s son killers murderers of an incarnate god.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>The brother who acted as my escort on those oc&#45;<lb/>&#45;casions said to me&#44; like the voice which spoke<lb/> to Ezekiel &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;You will<lb/> further see still greater abominations.&#34;  And so I<lb/> did to my sorrowfully under the guise of an institution in which the<lb/> knowledge of Hebrew is acquired&#44; an apostate<lb/> Jewess&#44; in the pay of the church&#44; gathered around<lb/> her many of our little ones&#44; allured by a variety<lb/> of promises for&#44; the larger the number the larger the reward.  Burning with indignation&#44; I visited<lb/> the premises of rank deception&#44; but only once&#44; for the princi&#45;<lb/>&#45;pal of the abominable school&#44; furiously remonstrated<lb/> against my having entered it&#44; as an act of unpardon&#45;<lb/>&#45;able intrusion&#44; as an act which would force her to call for in the<lb/> intervention of the police.  I did not put her threat<lb/> to the test&#44; fearing scandal.  In that instance I con&#45;<lb/>&#45;sidered discretion the better part of valor.  But<lb/> more than once I stood watching in the neighborhood<lb/> to note down the names of the children who issued<lb/> from a building&#44; where a net is spread for the unwary&#44;<lb/> so that I might caution the parents.  Hence The sad<lb/> humiliation which I experienced sprung from that very circumstance.  Reckless fathers<lb/> and unprincipled mothers deliberately exposed their<lb/> offspring to the seductions of a people&#44; who do not<lb/> scruple to employing base means in order to carry out their object design.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>A woman whom I had endeavoured to aid through charities&#44; while<lb/> her husband&#44; either voluntarily&#44; or by accident kept<lb/> aloof from her&#44; did not show the least compunction for<lb/> sending her young ones to the school of apostasy.  Positively Perfectly<lb/> knowing aware of the aim of the institution&#44; she with a brazen<lb/> countenance she disputed me and declared that Judaism was<lb/> taught there&#44; and that she p rejoined because added that together with the ins<lb/>&#45;truction&#44; a number of gifts were received.  The ingrate<lb/> doubtless appreciated the latter better than the former.<lb/>  Now&#44; I may often have been censured charged with cruelty<lb/> to speaking animals&#44; as I call persons in whom greed<lb/> silences the best moral instincts&#44; still&#44; I could not forbear saying<lb/> that persons again and again the almoners to whom the administration of charity beneficence our free will offer&#45;ing to the<lb/> indigent is entrusted&#44; ought invariably to inquire of the appli&#45;<lb/>&#45;cants&#44; whether their children are under religious as<lb/> well as secular tuition and whether they attend Jew&#45;<lb/>&#45;ish worship.  I know of many who are regular recipients<lb/> of help from our United Hebrew Charities&#44; whose re&#45;<lb/>&#45;cognition of the faith in which they were born con&#45;<lb/>&#45;sists in the acceptance of assistance rendered by that Jewish<lb/> institutions and kindred ones.  Their sons and daughters never enter a Syna&#45;<lb/>&#45;gogue&#44; nor learn at home the first rudiments of our belief.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Must we set a premium on the resolute <sic>wilful</sic> defection<lb/> of the rising generation among the need&#63;  In ages<lb/> past a saying ran thus &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Take good care of the children of the poor&#44; for they<lb/> will be the custodians of the Torah.&#34;  But Now adays&#44;<lb/> we do take care of them through their parents&#44; too much<lb/> so perhaps&#44; bodily not&#44; so in equally but we do not bestow equal care on that which concerns their<lb/> spiritual wants.  True&#44; we have free Sunday schools<lb/> and free Hebrew schools&#44; but how inadequate their number to the<lb/> vast increase of our brethren&#44; who have sought here in<lb/> Philadelphia security from Russian persecution&#33;  Many more such schools<lb/> ought we to set up&#44; precisely in the localities which<lb/> our religious adversaries craftily choose&#44; to establish theirs&#44;<lb/> because the plans selected overflowing with a Jewish population.  I am<lb/> reliably informed that on 7th st between Pine and Lombard<lb/> sts&#44; a furnace is in full blast&#44; lighted for the destruction<lb/> of our creed&#44; exists.  Not a few are the incautious<lb/> that fall into it.  Some&#44; whose natural guardians have<lb/> been warned&#44; are offered to that Molock the parents<lb/> arguing with an indifference which <sic>exites</sic> wrath anger&#44; that&#44;<lb/> after all&#44; they do not fear the burning flames.  They<lb/> cannot scathe their children&#39;s soul.  Their sons and daughters<lb/> know that they are born of <sic>Jews&#45;&#45;emplary</sic> Jews for sooth&#44; who<lb/> trifle with the spiritual welfare of creatures committed to their<lb/> safe&#45;keeping.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Most worthy Jews&#44; who resolutely wilfully resolutely expose a precious<lb/> treasure given in their charge to the danger of being lost&#33;<lb/>  I find that our moralist asks in the book of Proverbs<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Can one walk upon<lb/> hot coals and his feet not be scorched&#63;&#34;  Bad<lb/> enough&#59; wrong enough that Jewish tax payers&#44; who<lb/> contribute to the support of public secular schools must<lb/> submit to an outrage perpetrated against the faith which<lb/> we they profess.  I mean&#44; in the obligations imposed upon our their children.<lb/>  For&#44; the latter are expected to listen to the recital reading of<lb/> the new testament&#44; to join in hymns totally at variance<lb/> with our belief and specially at the church festivities<lb/> now approaching to take part in recitations that<lb/> ill&#45;accord with the religion&#44; which proclaims the all saving<lb/> powers of one God&#44; and as we of the Sephardic ritual sing &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Without conjunction&#44; without division<lb/> of parts&#44; great and all mighty.&#34;  Private and public remonstrances<lb/> have availed little.  They are met by the trite remark&#58;<lb/> &#34;the majority rel rules&#34;&#44; although the boast of this<lb/> land is that it has written a bill of divorce&#44; which holds<lb/> the church severely apart from the state.  Shame upon<lb/> some of my would be patriotic coreligionists&#44; who called<lb/> those their brethren to task who&#44; from time to time&#44; have ventured to<lb/> dispute the right of that majority&#33;  But if we are<lb/> unjustly dealt with in the instance just cited&#44; it does<lb/> not follow that we shall allow open enemies to undermine Judaism<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>We must not tolerate their insidious artifices&#44; dictated<lb/> by the immoral maxim that &#34;the end justifies the means.&#34;<lb/>  We must thwart their intentions&#44; and I think that if<lb/> we planted schools of our own very close to those which<lb/> they establish as a bait&#44; and offer some of the inducements<lb/> which they hold out&#44; we shall would finally drain them out mission factories dry<lb/> of their resources and recover what is our own.  But we<lb/> should choose the same hours and the same days as<lb/> well as a near spot near to their meetings houses.  The afternoon of Saturdays and Sundays afternoons are is the leisure time of which hired &#91;&#63;&#93; apostatizers take advantage.  We should utilize that time to defeat their object.  Indeed&#44;<lb/> for several years I have been anxious to set up in<lb/> such localities an afternoon Sabbath service&#44; accompanied<lb/> by a lecture in conversational style and easy instruct&#45;<lb/>&#45;ion in books of our literature.  I hold that it am of opinion that the effecting of that plan would serve a<lb/> double purpose.  It would prevent the estrangement<lb/> of the young form the ancestral fold and act as an<lb/> object lesson to our fellow believers who pray much but<lb/> not well&#44; whose worship with great frequency and large<lb/> attendances but neither quietly nor decorously.  Could<lb/> I make it compatible with the duty which I primarily owe<lb/> this congregation&#44; I would deem it a merit to assume<lb/> the task as highly meritorious.  I was asked by a sister in faith who shares my<lb/> views upon that score subject&#44; whether I could suggest any one<lb/> qualified to undertake the task.  I answered negatively.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>In my mind&#44; the prerequisites for its proper performance are fondness of the<lb/> Hebrew language and its preference to other languages in<lb/> our prayers&#59; sympathy with those untrained in American<lb/> manners and habits and willingness to impart in&#45;<lb/>&#45;struction within the line of Hebrew the Jewish traditions.<lb/>  But if unfortunately we cannot just now over&#45;<lb/>&#45;come the difficulties presented in that respect&#44; we<lb/> should try with might and main to arouse a spi&#45;<lb/>&#45;rit whose up &#91;&#63;&#93; the rising up of which will result in the creation of<lb/> schools proportionate to our increasing wants needs.<lb/>  We must not suffer permit either sworn adherents of the<lb/> trinity to steal away the hearts of our children&#44; or<lb/> our looking on passively on the recreancy of their parents.<lb/>  If the maxim aphorism &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;each Israelite is a guaranteed for his coreligionist&#44;&#34; conveys any sense&#44;<lb/> it signifies&#44; as the immortal Rashi explains it&#44; that we<lb/> shall keep vigilant watch so that the underlying ordinances<lb/> principles of Judaism suffer no detriment.  To whom<lb/> shall I appeal for the consummation of the all import&#45;<lb/>&#45;ant object&#63;  My heart replies &#34;to the women of Israel&#34;<lb/>  Their zeal does not abate because the demands on<lb/> their exertions for the sake of to furthering the Jewish<lb/> cause&#44; are increasing augmenting continually.  Let them take coun&#45;<lb/>sel together.  Associated with men who have never<lb/> shrunk from duty and proved a main stay to our free schools<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>they will enrich us with institutions&#44; which&#44;<lb/> under God&#39;s blessing&#44; may rise as impregnable<lb/> fortresses against the open or covert attacks of<lb/> trinitarians.  Women of Israel&#44; whom&#44; in the days<lb/> of old&#44; Talmudists extolled for the practice of taking<lb/> their children to the School house &#91;Hebrew&#93; will win a<lb/> still higher merit&#44; that of having disarmed the<lb/> adversaries of our religion and supplied us with<lb/> spiritual weapons of self&#45;defence.  May I not<lb/> have spoken in vain.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
