<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF4_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_2_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_2_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_2_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_2_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_2_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>13 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Post&#45;biblical history<lb/>
                22.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  In resuming my post&#45;biblical lectures&#44; which<lb/> I will try endeavour to condense in order not to tire&#44; and while trying to<lb/> be plain&#44; so as to interest many more than a few&#44; I may say this.<lb/>  that Herod the Idumean whose people was forcibly converted to Judaism by Hrycanus I&#44; is the man who virtually<lb/> bound our people hands and feet to the victorious<lb/> chariot of conquering Rome.  Herod ought therefore<lb/> to be named by every Jew&#44; not with the title<lb/> of &#34;the great&#44;&#34; as bestowed upon him by historians&#44; but<lb/> rather with that of &#34;the accursed&#34; which he fully deserves.<lb/>  A satisfaction which the right&#45;minded thinking derive from reading<lb/> his life&#44; is that of knowing that it was one a life of misery&#44;<lb/> notwithstanding the glare of the throne and the dazzle<lb/> of the crown.  Herod was singularly successful in the general acceptation of the words&#44; but<lb/> never happy&#59; nor could he be possibly so&#44; who defied the laws of<lb/> nature and the laws of God.  Having been de&#45;<lb/>&#45;clared King of the Jews by the Roman Senate&#44; through<lb/> the interposition of his friend&#44; the profligate Mark<lb/> Antony&#44; his Herod&#39;s first undertaking in rushing back to<lb/> Palestine was to fight Antigonus&#44; the Asmonean&#44; who<lb/> had taken possession of the capital.  Roman cohorts<lb/> stood by the man who had bought protection in the<lb/></p> 
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>seven&#45;hilled city with Jewish gold&#44; Parthians<lb/> soldiers assisted the rival in the hope of humbling<lb/> the power of aggressive Rome.  But it could not be<lb/> crushed.  The seige of Jerusalem which lasted<lb/> about five months&#44; called forth deeds of wonderful valor but also of wholesale slaughter<lb/> in both armies&#59; but finally the party that had<lb/> stood up for helped Antigonus to <sic>yeilded</sic> to the superior<lb/> forces sent by which the Latin Republic on the Tiber had sent.  It is<lb/> asserted by some and denied by others&#44; that Antigonus<lb/> did not behave with the dignity&#44; which a descend&#45;<lb/>&#45;ant of Judah Maccabee ought ot have shown even<lb/> in misfortune.  Whether he fell on his knees<lb/> and wept before the Roman general&#44; and this derisively<lb/> called him &#34;Antigona&#34;&#44; meaning a woman&#44; instead of<lb/> Antigonus&#44; is a point which I will not attempt<lb/> to settle&#44; but all writers agree that Herod paid a<lb/> large sum to have his rival put out of the way igno&#45;<lb/>&#45;miniously.  Accordingly&#44; the brutal Mark Antony<lb/> had the last prince of the house of Asmonean house tied to a<lb/> stake&#44; and after having his body unmercifully scourged&#44;<lb/> as a malefactor&#44; cut off his head if he were a criminal&#44; he ordered that the head of Herod&#39;s opponent be cut off.  Thus perished<lb/> the last ruling high&#45;priest of a most illustrious race.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Herod had now nothing more ot fear from the stock<lb/> of Mattathias.  He had rooted out the last shoot that might<lb/> have proved a thorn in into his side.  Breathing freely&#44;<lb/> he began the work of revenge personal revenge vengeance whoever had mani&#45;<lb/>&#45;fested any opposition aversion to his rule&#44; felt the weight of<lb/> his rancor.  Death and exile were apportioned to the<lb/> highest in the land.  A record is left in the Talmud&#44;<lb/> which tells that with two exceptions&#44; Herod proscribed<lb/> some and killed many of the members of the national council&#44; or Sanhedrin&#44;<lb/> whom he knew to have been his irreconcilable enemies<lb/> on religious and political grounds.  He filled their<lb/> vacancy with creatures subservient to his will&#44; and<lb/> even ventured to raise to the high priesthood a man<lb/> of no worth social standing whatever&#44; but of whom he could dispose at pleasure.<lb/>  The usurper had cleared for himself the path to absolutism.<lb/>  But justly has the book of Proverbs written &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; &#34;the way<lb/> of the wicked is like darkness itself&#59; they do not<lb/> know against what they may stumble.&#34;  Herod<lb/> found a cause of constant dread in within the walls of his own house.  He<lb/> had married Miriam or Marianne&#44; grand&#45;daughter of the imbecile<lb/> Hyrcanus II&#44; who had been an easy tool in the hands of the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>wily Antipater.  The marriage was one<lb/> of convenience.  Herod believed that by mixing with<lb/> with the family of the Maccabees&#44; he might gain po&#45;<lb/>&#45;pularity&#44; but Marianne realized too keenly her false position.<lb/>  She could be a faithful wife&#44; an obedient wife&#44; but<lb/> a fondly loving wife she could not be.  Herod&#44; on the<lb/> contrary&#44; was seized with a passion akin to distraction&#44; for the woman&#44; who<lb/> to the extraordinary charms of her person&#44; added those<lb/> of the intellect.  But unhappily for him&#44; the passion<lb/> of dominion was equally strong&#44; and in gratifying that&#44;<lb/> he mortally offended the woman he had wedded.<lb/>  Marianne had a young brother&#44; as handsome as<lb/> herself&#44; named Aristobulus.  Since Hyrcanus&#44; her maternal grand<lb/> parent had been made unfit for the high&#45;priesthood<lb/> by Antigonus who cruelly had cut off his ears&#44; she<lb/> anticipated to have seen her brother minister at<lb/> the altar.  For the <sic>fulfilment</sic> of that natural wish&#44;<lb/> she may have earnestly begged her husband&#44; but<lb/> he had already appointed another to suit his own pur&#45;<lb/>&#45;poses.  He In fact he feared the effect impression which the comely youth<lb/> of the Asmonean race might create among the people&#44;<lb/> when officiating as Pontiff in the Temple.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>But Alexandra&#44; the mother of Marianne&#44; was<lb/> too proud of her two children&#39;s descent to stoop before<lb/> the Idumean.  She would would not condescend to ask as<lb/> a favor&#44; what she considered her right.  She<lb/> stealthily sent addressed a letter to Cleopatra queen of Egypt&#44;<lb/> whose influence on Mark Antony needs not to be as<lb/> described here.  In it sh the mother set forth her grievances&#44; and<lb/> pleaded for her own son against her cunning son in law.<lb/>  Herod received a missive from the Roman Triumvir upon<lb/> the subject&#44; and&#44; discovering danger&#44; pretended that his<lb/> previous election of a high&#45;priest was only temporary&#44;<lb/> becaused of and being occasioned by the tender age of Aristobulus.  But now he<lb/> would clothe the youth with sacredotal authority&#44; as<lb/> he had always intended.  What Herod had foreseen and<lb/> dreaded&#44; was fully realized  brought to pass.  The entrance of the<lb/> splendid&#45;looking Aristobulus at the Temple robed<lb/> in the sacred garments which his ancestors had worn&#44; evoked<lb/> a perfect ovation.  All seemed to view in him again<lb/> the founders of that family of <sic>heros</sic> who had struck<lb/> for freedom and won it over for their country and<lb/> their laws.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>But those popular demonstrations were so<lb/> may many wounds to the heart of Herod.  He re&#45;<lb/>&#45;solved therefore to remove from earth an object that<lb/> excited his envy.  At an entertainment&#44; Herod<lb/> engaged in gymnastic exercises with his young brother<lb/> in law.  Towards evening&#44; the weather being warm&#44; the<lb/> King proposed that all the men present&#44; should go to a neighboring stream<lb/> and bathe.  Aristobulus also went but never to return.  He<lb/> was drowned.  Sorrow overspread the land&#59; but but&#44; the hypocritical pretended assumed grief of Herod and<lb/> the costly funeral made for the body of the unhappy<lb/> scion of the Maccabean race&#44; could not deceive the<lb/> Jews.  They knew had reason to surmise suspect that the death was not accidental&#44;<lb/> but <sic>premidated</sic> and pre arranged by the iniquitous king.<lb/>  Hatred for the son of the stranger who murdered the<lb/> best and dearest in the nation was intensified&#44; but<lb/> none felt it more poignantly more deeply than the bereaved mother.<lb/>  At the news that the son upon whom she had built<lb/> her hopes for a revival of Asmonean power&#44; had been drawn<lb/> a corpse out of the water into which he had plunged at the<lb/> instance of Herod&#44; she became frantic.  She would have<lb/> laid hands on her own life&#44; but the thought of revenge<lb/> held her back.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Again she appealed to Cleopatra to imploring that she would use her<lb/> good offices with Antony and bring Herod to grief.<lb/>  The unprincipled Egyptian who <sic>covetted</sic> Judea and<lb/> was but too glad of an opportunity to stir up against<lb/> its Idumean King the ill will of Rome&#44; promised assistance.<lb/>  Mark Antony demanded that Herod should come meet<lb/> before him and explain how Aristobulus had come at Laodicea and prove that no foul play had brought Aristobulus to an<lb/> his death untimely end.  Herod dared not disobey&#44; but before<lb/> he set off&#44; he appointed as provisional governor his uncle<lb/> Joseph&#44; who had married his sister Salome&#44; To him he and<lb/> gave entrusted to him a secret commission.  Should Antony detain<lb/> Herod as prisoner&#44; or order command his execution&#44; Marianne must<lb/> be killed&#44; to prevent her falling into the power clutches of the<lb/> dissolute Roman. triumvir  The Idumean who was by no<lb/> means deficient in the art of speaking&#44; who was adroit&#44;<lb/> who possessed self&#45;reliance and winning manners&#44; and<lb/> who knew the power influence of gold&#44; succeeded in justifying beyond his expectations in clearing<lb/> his conduct&#44; and returned in high spirits to the capi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tal of his kingdom.  But the scout commission order had<lb/> not been kept from Marianne.  Joseph unguardedly<lb/> told it&#44; as an illustration of Herod&#39;s conjugal affection&#44;<lb/> when Alexandra sharply cast doubts upon it.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>But Who can blame Marianne for putting her own construction&#63;<lb/>  She was horrified&#44; and interpreted the secret<lb/> order as another instance of Herod&#39;s savageness dispo&#45;<lb/>&#45;sition  Remembering&#44; moreover&#44; the recent loss of<lb/> her promising brother&#44; she could not hypocritically<lb/> welcome home the Idumean&#45;&#45;though he were the father of<lb/> her children.  Salome whose malicious spirit<lb/> made her a worthy sister of her wicked brother&#44; fan&#45;<lb/>&#45;ned into blaze the fire of domestic strife.  She mad&#45;<lb/>&#45;dened Herod&#44; by arousing within him horrid suspicions<lb/> against Marianne&#39;s character.  In a fit of jealousy&#44; he had<lb/> his uncle Joseph&#45;&#45;the very husband of Salome&#45;&#45;put to<lb/> death&#44; without even giving affording him an opportunity to<lb/> defend his course.  Alexandra&#44; accused of having plan&#45;<lb/>&#45;ned a conspiracy&#44; was confined into a dungeon.<lb/>  Thus Herod thought to have purchased security&#44;<lb/> but it was not <sic>tranquillity</sic> that he had procured.<lb/>  His home gave him no comfort&#44; and in the compul&#45;<lb/>&#45;sory silence of his people&#44; he could hear their curses<lb/> against a man who had become their executioner&#44; and who<lb/> ruled only through the consent of hateful Rome.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>A new source of trouble to Herod were the am&#45;<lb/>&#45;bitious schemes of Cleopatra.  She had prevailed on<lb/> Mark Antony to assign to her some territory properly<lb/> belonging to the kingdom of Judea.  But unruly<lb/> as she was in all her cravings&#44; she now pushed<lb/> her desires still further.  She would sit as Queen of in<lb/> Palestine.  Antony&#44; infatuated as he was&#44; dared<lb/> not nonetheless comply with that wish&#44; and Cleopatra<lb/> having accompanied him beyond the Euphrates&#44; where<lb/> he was going to fight the Parthians&#44; paid a state visit<lb/> to Herod.  The latter with masterly prudence avoided<lb/> being entrapped in the net of laid by her artifices&#44; and escorted<lb/> her out of his dominions with every demonstrations<lb/> of a respect to which she was not entitled.  The<lb/> woman&#44; however&#44; who was a complete adept in<lb/> state political intrigues&#44; managed to involve Herod in a<lb/> fearful war with the Arabs&#44; tributaries to her crown.<lb/>  If he had Should he been defeated&#44; Cleopatra would have might<lb/> attained her object.  For a time it looked<lb/> as if her greed was bout to be gratified.  The<lb/> issue of many a battle varied.  Teacher&#44; and nature<lb/> seemed to conspire against Herod.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>Egyptian auxiliaries&#44; acting on the secret instruction<lb/> of their queen&#44; deserted his cause&#44; and a terrible earth&#45;<lb/>&#45;quake in Judea created a panic.  Still&#44; fortune<lb/> did not desert her favorite.  Herod&#39;s skill as<lb/> a general&#44; and his great presence of mind finally<lb/> triumphed.  The Arabs&#44; routed and decimated&#44;<lb/> sued for peace.  But the king of Judea had<lb/> scarcely rested from the last struggle&#44; when a politic&#45;<lb/>&#45;al storm burst upon him.  Mark Antony&#44;<lb/> his friend and protector&#44; had paid dearly for years<lb/> of wanton inactivity.  At Actium&#44; a city in<lb/> Greece&#44; Petavious Caesar&#44; who afterwards reigned<lb/> under the title of Augustus&#44; had put an end to the<lb/> power of the corrupt associate of Cleopatra.<lb/></p>
            <p>These tidings filled Herod with dismay.  Might<lb/> no Octavious&#44; who was aware of the relations that<lb/> had existed between the ruler of Judea and the last<lb/> triumvir&#44; vent his spleen&#63;  Herod imagined himself abandoned by Rome&#44;<lb/> dethroned&#44; stripped of all authority in favor of the rival<lb/> house of the Asmoneans&#44; and dark suspicions led him<lb/> again to the commission of a foul shocking crime.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;The wicked are like the raging sea&#44; that cannot<lb/> never be at rest.&#34;  Hyrcanus II had lived<lb/> for years in for a period&#44; in voluntary exile among the Parthians and was greatly honored<lb/> by the Jews who largely inhabited the cities beyond the<lb/> Euphrates.  Shortly After Herod became king&#44; he<lb/> invited the former ruler sovereign of Judea with flattering<lb/> promises to return to his own country.  Anxious<lb/> to revisit the place of his birth and of his checkered history&#44;<lb/> the unfortunate man accepted.  But Herod now<lb/> in danger fancied he saw even in the impotent octo&#45;<lb/>&#45;generian a powerful enemy.  It has been stated that<lb/> Alexandra induced her aged father to seek of the king of<lb/> the Arabs the means of for fleeing away and watching coming events from a distance&#44; and that the com&#45;<lb/>&#45;munication and its reply fell into the hands of Herod.<lb/>  But it is more likely&#44; as many have surmised&#44; that<lb/> the whole was an invention of the crafty Idumean&#44;<lb/> who used it as a pretext to utterly destroy every<lb/> hope that the house beloved by the people&#44; might<lb/> entertain.  Hyrcanus through whose fatal weakness<lb/> Antipater had mounted up to a height greatness&#44; was<lb/> beheaded sent to the scaffold&#44; when on the verge of the grave&#44; by the son<lb/> of the stranger whom he had so immensely <sic>benefitted</sic>.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p>It was then that the heart of Marianne<lb/> revolted against her inhuman husband.  Her<lb/> nuptials had been celebrated&#44; while a carnage was<lb/> being perpetrated committed among the adherents of her family&#59;<lb/> the first months of her married life chronicled the<lb/> ineffaceable insult to her family in the scourging<lb/> and beheading of her uncle Antigonus.  A few years<lb/> later&#44; she was made to weep from sorrow and<lb/> anger rage&#44; over the murder of her brother&#44; and now<lb/> her grand&#45;father&#44; old and inoffensive had been<lb/> put under the axe of delivered to the executioner.  And<lb/> all these deeds of horror had proceeded from the<lb/> man with whom she had been doomed to share<lb/> her earthly existence.  To honor such a husband&#44;<lb/> to show him any conjugal consideration became a natural<lb/> impossibility.  A gulph was opened between<lb/> Marianne and Herod&#44; which nothing could<lb/> bridge over.  The sequel will tell how this<lb/> domestic unhappiness affected the destiny of<lb/> our people.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
