<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF4_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_2_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_2_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_2_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_2_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_2_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>A moral lecture on<lb/> Parashat Vayer&#225;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  When the professors of a religion&#45;&#45;which<lb/> has drawn existence from Jewish inspiration&#45;&#45;ignore its<lb/> origin&#44; and with self&#45;complacency proclaim to the world&#44;<lb/> that from it alone the springs of pure morality issue forth&#44;<lb/> one may be pardoned&#44; if in vindication of truth&#44; he endeavours<lb/> to disprove the assertion.  Men are too apt blindly to<lb/> accept opinions&#44; which have acquired popularity.<lb/>  And our youth&#44; alas&#33; our youths upon whom Judaism<lb/> in America has built its hopes&#44; hearing incessantly<lb/> the praises of another faith&#44; learn to regard with<lb/> contempt or indifference that in which they were born.<lb/>  It is their minds&#44; O beloved hearers&#33; my fellow&#45;believers&#33; that ought chiefly to<lb/> be disabused of an error fatal to our dearest interests.<lb/>  Do we not witness already its baneful effects&#63;<lb/>  The maidens of Judah aspire to shine amid a circle of<lb/> non&#45;Israelites.  The sons of Hebrew&#45;parents seek to win<lb/> the graces of the daughters of gentiles.  They withdraw<lb/> from the association of a people&#44; whose laws are pronounced<lb/> obsolete&#44; and whose practices excite the derision of the&#45;<lb/>so&#45;called&#45;enlightened.  They twin traitors to a cause&#44; the<lb/> sublimity of which&#44; their perverted minds have failed<lb/> to comprehend.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>For I ask in all earnest&#44; what nobler end could man&#39;s religion ever be assigned<lb/> than that which God Himself designed for our faith&#63;<lb/>  O household seed of Jacob&#33;  Inveterate prejudice or presumption<lb/> may deny its claim to <sic>unequalled</sic> excellency &#38; award it to a mere popular creed&#44; but ignorance&#44;<lb/> unpardonable ignorance alone can draw the assent of a<lb/> Jew or a Jewess to that biased judgment.  Attend.<lb/>  When the wrath of God was kindled against p the people<lb/> of Sodom&#44; why was the ancient patriarch divinely ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;prised of their impending doom&#63;  Because2 he&#44; who<lb/> was righteous&#44; would command his children and his household<lb/> after him&#44; to keep the way V of the Lord&#44; by doing charity<lb/> and justice.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Yes&#44; let the whole world hear it&#44;<lb/> these are the solid foundations whereupon Israel&#39;s faith rests.<lb/>  Charity and justice.  The twin virtues&#44; whose practice<lb/> will ultimately <sic>humanise</sic> all the inhabitants of the<lb/> terrestrial globe&#44; demolishing the barriers that separate<lb/> them&#44; subjecting national policy to the rules of high<lb/> morality&#44; forming of all men wheresoever they dwell a single family&#59;<lb/> uniting heaven and earth in one sweet accord.<lb/>  Not in a spirit of self&#45;glorification&#44; but in defense of truth<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>I say it. that They in whose veins courses the blood of<lb/> Abraham the Hebrew&#44; have ever been quickened by the<lb/> impulses of those two noble virtues.  The lesson early<lb/> taught by the venerated father&#44; was not lost on his children.<lb/>  The charity which impelled Abraham to paternally rear<lb/> the orphan child of his brother&#44; and that which he exhibited<lb/> when he restored peace in the homesteads made desolate by war.<lb/>  The charity which elicited from his righteous lips a prayer<lb/> for irreclaimable sinners&#44; and that which he displayed beneath<lb/> his roof towards weary <sic>travellers</sic>.  His The justice in wresting<lb/> the oppressed from the hand of their oppressors&#59; in keeping<lb/> faith unto heathens&#44; who did not scruple to rob him of<lb/> the wells he had dug his wealth&#44; and in prev peremptorily refusing<lb/> to become enriched with that which was not his legitimate<lb/> property&#59; this lesson&#44; I repeat it&#44; took struck deep root into the<lb/> heart of his descendants.  And if the religion&#44; that has<lb/> borrowed light from the bright pages of the Mosaic legislation&#44;<lb/> can justly glory in men and women&#44; whom it has inspired<lb/> with exemplary self&#45;denial&#59; we can&#44; point out with national<lb/> pride point to to our own philanthropists.  Even in this age&#44;<lb/> Florance Nitingale has been <sic>rivalled</sic> by Miriam Randager&#44;<lb/> and the name of Moses Montefiore evokes grateful emotions<lb/> in the breast of thousands of gentiles&#44; whom&#44; like his own brethren&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>he strove to benefit.  Shall we then with such<lb/> bright exemplifications of the purity of our faith<lb/> before our eyes&#44; admit as facts the <sic>pretentions</sic> of enthusiasts&#63;<lb/>  Accord to their religion&#44; preeminence in the scale of human<lb/> civilization&#63;  No&#44; as the God of Abraham liveth&#44; I shall&#44;<lb/> with my last breath&#44; assert the superiority of the law which<lb/> governs Israel over that to which the gentile world adheres.<lb/>  Let others magnify Christian generosity and christian mag&#45;<lb/>&#45;nanimity&#59; I trust never to be denied the privilege of extolling<lb/> Jewish charity and Jewish justice.<lb/></p>
            <p>But let us beware&#44; my Brethren&#44; not to misapprehend the sense<lb/> of those two words&#59; not to confound charity with alms&#45;<lb/>giving&#44; and justice with the inflexible sentence of judi&#45;<lb/>&#45;cial tribunals.  In the work of beneficence&#44; alms represents<lb/> the feeblest instrument&#44; while justice distributed at the<lb/> bar&#44; is the mere result of social self&#45;protection.<lb/>  Charity is not alms&#44; because the latter humbles the<lb/> recipient&#44; the former endeavours to elevate him.<lb/>  Alms is not <sic>unfrequently</sic> granted but to be ridden<lb/> of importunate mendicants&#59; charity is a sweet<lb/> emanation of the heart&#44; which awakens corresponding<lb/> emotions in others&#59; for&#44; not so much the benefit we derive<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>from our brother &#44;as his kindly consideration&#44; pene&#45;<lb/>&#45;trates our soul.  We may freely open our hands&#44; but<lb/> unless our hearts are also open to fraternal sentiments&#44;<lb/> the charity attributed to us will be a misnomer.<lb/>  The illustration of that virtue recommended by our godly<lb/> progenitor&#44; is not to cast abroad scatter about coins of precious metals&#44;<lb/> that some may gather them&#44; but to raise the spirit<lb/> of the lowly &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; to tend the soul barren<lb/> of joy&#44; that it may blossom and <sic>yeild</sic> a harvest of<lb/> delights.  He who pours the balm of consolation upon<lb/> the wounds of the afflicted&#44; is said to belong to the house&#45;<lb/>&#45;hold of Abraham.  And they who knew well how<lb/> to interpret our code of morals &#44; have written&#44; that &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> which is&#44; mercy to the living and to the dead &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; and the promotion of good&#45;will to between<lb/> man and man&#44; is what is required of the man constitute the piety&#44; which<lb/> the Almighty will consider pious reward here and hereafter.  Yes&#44; our heartfelt<lb/> commiseration for all who suffer&#44; our personal exertions<lb/> to restore <sic>tranquillity</sic> in the dwelling of man&#44; to secure<lb/> his independence&#44; to further his social elevation&#44; is the charity&#44;<lb/> we are demanded by our religion&#44; to exercise.  Oh&#33; my beloved<lb/> hearers&#33;  The light of the sun to him who has long<lb/> dwelt in darkness&#44; is not more reviving&#44; than our<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>eyes beaming with compassion&#44; for to the hapless<lb/> and the sorrowful.  They who are tossed upon the<lb/> bed of sickness.  They who bemoan the loss of parents&#44;<lb/> or children&#59; of brothers or dear relatives&#44; will tell y tell relate<lb/> how comforting is the presence of our <sic>sympathising</sic> fel&#45;<lb/>&#45;low creatures in the hour of affliction trials&#44; how their words<lb/> solace soothe our pain&#44; mitigate the sole poignant grief they we endure&#44; and lightens<lb/> the <sic>burthen</sic> of our misfortune.  It may be&#44; my brethren&#44; that our separate efforts may cannot<lb/> not&#44; in all instances&#44; prove of sufficient efficacy in relieving the distressed&#44;<lb/> but our joint actions&#44; will&#44; under all circumstances&#44; accomplish<lb/> much in the pursuit of charity.  Suffer me then<lb/> to offer a few words of counsel.  Friends&#33;  The institutions<lb/> that with fostering care train the child of poverty<lb/> and sorrow&#44; that exalt the lowly so that they<lb/> may sit among the magnates of the land&#59; that<lb/> wipe the tears from the eyes of widowed mothers&#44; such&#44;<lb/> should most especially command your unwavering<lb/> attention and cooperation.  More than to alms&#45;<lb/>giving&#44; the progeny of Abraham should be engaged<lb/> in devising means to prevent its urgent necessity.<lb/>  We will define our meaning.<lb/>  A liberal loan to the honest poor man&#44; may raise him<lb/> above want&#44; and inspire him with self&#45;reliance.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>His latent faculties will awaken to activity by<lb/> the prospect of a brighter future.  He will rise<lb/> in the full consciousness of his manhood&#44; and scorn to<lb/> ask of others what he can attain by his industry.<lb/>  Societies having such a tendency&#44; must command<lb/> themselves to the patronage of those who are enjoined<lb/> &#34;to keep the way of the Lord&#44; by doing charity and justice.&#34;<lb/>  Aye&#44; a sense of justice as well as that of charity should prompt incite<lb/> us to follow such a course&#44; for&#44; the universal Creator did not<lb/> intend that some of his children should luxuriate in<lb/> affluence&#44; and others should continue remain to be the heirs of indigence.<lb/>  and by Through his inspired servant&#44; he told us that revealed to showed one us the means we must employ to extinguish pauperism.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>  &#34;God He is the a good man who is gracious and lendeth.&#34; away.&#34;<lb/>  We must labor to elevate the poor&#44; to make them<lb/> feel that they are inferior to none&#44; that God has<lb/> endowed them with faculties which they must employ advan&#45;<lb/>&#45;tageously to themselves and their fellow&#45;creatures.  When<lb/> our assistance shall aim at teaching the needy self&#45;depend&#45;<lb/>&#45;ance&#44; the number of those who watch at our doors&#44;<lb/> to receive a pittance&#44; will amazingly diminish.<lb/>  But another instrument does justice prompt us to employ<lb/> in &#91;&#63;&#93; with uplifting from the earth our needy necessitous brother&#59; that is&#44; Knowledge.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>It has been rightly said&#44; that ignorance is the parent<lb/> of vice&#44; and we also know&#44; that poverty is an ill&#45;adviser&#44;<lb/> but healthful learning will more forcibly repel the attacks<lb/> of vice&#44; than the powerful shields &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Therefore have our Sages attached more sanctity<lb/> to the temples of knowledge&#44; than to the dwellings of<lb/> prayer.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Conscience is undoubtedly an efficient monitor&#44; but when<lb/> men are reared in perfect ignorance of their duties&#44; the<lb/> still small voice that speaks to us&#44; is not heard by remains silent within them.<lb/>  To awaken arouse it&#44; we must develop quicken our brother&#39;s intellectual<lb/> faculties.  We must afford the bread of the soul to<lb/> those who most require it.  Let their capacities be<lb/> ever so narrow&#44; we must inspire them with the noble<lb/> desire of contributing their share to the progress of<lb/> mankind.  Our father Abraham&#44; who is<lb/> our <sic>prtotype</sic>&#44; endeavoured by genial and suasive<lb/> manners to enlighten his benighted beings contemporaries &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> so likewise must we&#44; gently but perseveringly&#44; strive<lb/> to tear away the veil which obscures our brother&#39;s mental<lb/> vision&#44; and fill the mind with high and noble aspirations.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Such are the principles that underlie the religion you profess&#44; my<lb/> beloved hearers&#33;  To exercise towards our fellow&#45;men<lb/> that kindly consideration&#44; we would wish that<lb/> it might be shown us if similarly situated.<lb/>  To comfort them in sorrow to assuage their pangs in sickness to aid them in their want&#44;<lb/> to instruct them&#44; and socially elevate them to the<lb/> standard intended by God for all those whom He created<lb/> in his celestial image. that they might rule the earth&#44; Has any religion taught its<lb/> and in professors purer virtues&#63;  Or do they who<lb/> boast of a code of morals superior to the Sinaic<lb/> revelation&#44; exhibit in their walks of life&#44; more<lb/> genuine charity and justice than the progeny<lb/> of the Hebrew patriarch&#63;.....My friends&#33;<lb/> &#40;and you&#44; my young fr brother&#44; who have this day<lb/> assumed the performance of God&#39;s holy law&#33;&#41; be<lb/> not inveigled away by the vainglorious expressions<lb/> of men who belittle Judaism.  Light<lb/> vapors ascending the sky&#44; can no more dim<lb/> the refulgence of the Sun&#44; than the aspersions of<lb/> enthusiasts&#44; the brightness of your religion.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>Only be faithful to it&#44; prove yourselves worthy<lb/> of the name you bear.  Act virtuously towards all<lb/> men&#44; irrespective of their nativity or country or race. or<lb/> country.  Sow broadcast the seeds of charity<lb/> and justice upon earth&#44; and let your unim&#45;<lb/>&#45;peachable characters vindicate the cause of<lb/> Israel.  It shall yet triumph.  It shall yet<lb/> call forth the admiration of all mortals.  &#34;Many<lb/> people shall come and say &#34;Let us go up to the<lb/> mountain of the Lord&#44; to the house of the God<lb/> of Jacob&#44; and He will teach us his ways&#44; and<lb/> we will walk in his paths&#44; for out of Zion shall<lb/> go forth the law&#44; and the word of the Lord from<lb/> Jerusalem.&#34;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  May the <sic>fulfilment</sic> of this prophetic<lb/> declaration&#44; soon gladden our hearts.  And may<lb/> the Almighty vouchsafe to lay his healing hand on our<lb/> suffering brothers&#44; to bind up their wounds&#44; to breathe hope<lb/> into the desolate hearts&#44; and gladden his creatures with the<lb/> assurance of a happiness&#44; glorious and everlasting.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
