<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF9_3</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1890-10" source="" attested="yes">October 1890</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_3_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_3_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_3_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_3_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_3_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_3_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_3_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_3_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_3_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_3_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_3_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_3_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. Fifth St.<lb/>
                Philadelphia&#44; October&#47;90<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>97<lb/></p>
            
            <p>A sequel to the lecture on<lb/>
                Russia and education<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Brethren.<lb/></p>
            <p>Whatever wrongs misguided anarchists of Jewish birth<lb/> and Russian nationality may have lately perpetrated elsewhere<lb/> to grieve observant Israelites&#44; here they refrained from<lb/> causing vexations.  Last year they would have heinously<lb/> offended&#44; had they not been foiled in the wicked at&#45;<lb/>&#45;tempt.  This year they had contemplated renewing<lb/> the intended insult to the Hebrew community&#44; on our<lb/> most solemn day.  I heard with deep mortification<lb/> that a few among those in whose behalf I made stre&#45;<lb/>&#45;nuous contributions of a noble&#45;hearted friend&#44; were num&#45;<lb/>&#45;bered with the unrighteous ones&#44; who sought to outra&#45;<lb/>&#45;geously desecrate the day of atonement.  But I let<lb/> my displeasure be manifested in time to prevent the im&#45;<lb/>&#45;pious act&#44; and felt relieved.  My reference to<lb/> that distasteful circumstance is merely by way of a<lb/> sequel to some remarks which I offered on the first<lb/> day of the present festival.  I said that we cannot<lb/> overrate the difficulties which we/ must prepare<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>ourselves to meet in the event of an <sic>unprecedently</sic> vast<lb/> immigration from Russia.  I stated that while ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;perience tells on one hand that we persons entertaining<lb/> subversive notions on social government will provokingly<lb/> face us&#44; on the other we shall find individuals lacking<lb/> a proper understanding of our religious duties&#44; and of<lb/> what constitutes worship.  Of the latter deficiency<lb/> we have too palpable a proof among those already<lb/> established in our cities&#59; more particularly and pain&#45;<lb/>&#45;fully we receive that proof during the solemn days<lb/> which preceded this festival.  With profound<lb/> humiliation have I noticed in secular journals reports<lb/> of a behavior in places meant to be devoted to<lb/> the service of Israel&#39;s God&#44; instances which must shock any<lb/> sensible Israelite&#44; and scandalize the community<lb/> at large.  In New Jersey&#44; some difference be&#45;<lb/>&#45;tween the reader at the sacred desk&#44; and an official<lb/> of the Congregation&#44; ended in a brawl&#44; which would<lb/> not have been tolerated at a gathering of habitual<lb/> &#91;&#63;&#93;.  A reprehensible conduct of a similar<lb/> character was exhibited in the Southern section of<lb/> Philadelphia in some of the assemblages&#44; which<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>unhappily abound greatly to our disrepute during Rosh Hashanah<lb/> and Kippur and are improvised for the occasion as<lb/> means of economising expenses in religion.  For&#44; a<lb/> mere trifle will secure a seat where some ill qualified<lb/> persons chant a ritual which is beyond their compre&#45;<lb/>&#45;hension.  But to cap the climax of shame&#44; a few<lb/> days ago our Common Pleas Court witnessed the debasing<lb/> scene of one Levi&#44; lodging complaints against the Pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;sident of his Congregation and asking Judge Ellison<lb/> that an injunction be issued to restrain that officer<lb/> from interfering with the plaintiff&#39;s right to attend<lb/> the services at the synagogue.  In conversation<lb/> with a Rabbi&#44; whose preaching is supposed to be<lb/> devoted to the improvement of his countrymen&#44;<lb/> I protested against holding convocations ostensibly in<lb/> obedience to the Lord&#44; but which are in offence to<lb/> the Lord and to Moses His servant.  I urged<lb/> that Reform is imperatively needed&#44; a reform which<lb/> will imbue foreign Jews with a sense of dignity<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>of the worship.  I recommended less &#91;&#63;&#93; and<lb/> quivering for effect&#44; and more decorum&#44; as a savory<lb/> offering to God&#44; whose inspired psalmist taught us<lb/> to bow in reverence before His holy oracle &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> But Rabbis of the Russian stamp in America&#44; are evi&#45;<lb/>&#45;dently powerless.  They have sadly failed to work out last&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing benefits in New York&#44; where the field of operations<lb/> calls for unremitting labors&#44; and they will fail every&#45;<lb/>&#45;where among us to arouse their compatriots senti&#45;<lb/>&#45;ments of devotional awe.  Meanwhile for because of that and<lb/> for numerous other reasons the honor of the respectable<lb/> portion of the Jewish community is <sic>imperilled</sic>.<lb/>  We owe it then to ourselves to go in quest of the<lb/> means of self&#45;<sic>defence</sic>.  It is not selfishness<lb/> that I recommend.  To be sure&#44; nothing can be more<lb/> precious to us than the honor of Israel.  To prevent that<lb/> name being dragged into the pit of disgrace is our<lb/> bounden duty.  But a still higher motive should im&#45;<lb/>&#45;pel us to strong exertions&#45;&#45;humanity.  Those that<lb/> may soon crowd our city are fellow creatures who have<lb/> suffered what an American&#44; born and reared in freedom&#44;<lb/> shudders at&#44; but a greater claim on our humanity<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>they have in the fact that they have suffered thus<lb/> because they refuse to forswear their allegiance to<lb/> the God we adore.  Nor does the latest document from<lb/> our Secretary of State throw a less lurid light on<lb/> the exceptional condition of our brethren under the Czar.<lb/>  It sounds as a mockery of sorrows and woes to hear<lb/> &#34;that the Russian government does not contemplate<lb/> any change form the present lenient enforcement<lb/> of the Jewish edicts of 1882&#44;&#34; when it is immediately<lb/> after admitted &#34;that the general legislation in regard<lb/> to Hebrews in Russia&#44; if applied&#44; would be of an<lb/> oppressive character.&#34;  It is that general legis&#45;<lb/>&#45;lation carried out by irresponsible governors and their subor&#45;<lb/>&#45;dinates and weighing brushingly upon men&#44; wo&#45;<lb/>&#45;men and children of our faith&#44; that makes them<lb/> flee to our shores as from a raging fire.  Were<lb/> they willing to abjure the faith&#44; exchanging the Syna&#45;<lb/>&#45;gogue for the Greek Chapel&#44; public sho schools and<lb/> universities would be opened to them&#44; promotions in ci&#45;<lb/>&#45;vil and military positions might be secured&#44; and the<lb/> right to own property and bequeath it would be<lb/> theirs.  In our Union of States those immunities<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>are the badge of every human being.  Let us help<lb/> our foreign coreligionists to become worthy of the fran&#45;<lb/>&#45;chises belonging to the free.  With the elderly among<lb/> the new comers we can hope to accomplish little or<lb/> nothing.  Their mode of thinking&#44; and their habits&#44; years<lb/> and surroundings have made a second nature&#44; but the<lb/> young we must take under our watchful supervisions&#44;<lb/> and that we must do at their earliest age&#44; in order to<lb/> shape their thoughts and their manners aright&#44; never<lb/> relinquishing them till the years of maturity find<lb/> them noble representatives of Judaism and of liberty.<lb/>  Education must be the agency we shall sedulously<lb/> employ.  It was on the festival of Tabernacles<lb/> two years ago that I introduced the subject of a school<lb/> of vast dimensions in a locality&#44; where the majority<lb/> of Jews from Northern Europe have taken up their homes.<lb/>  Since then&#44; I have dwelt at different intervals upon the<lb/> pressing necessity for a building to draw in the young among<lb/> the lowly and afford them varied instruction.  I would<lb/> weary my hearers by an often repeated description of<lb/> the character of that school&#59; how from object teaching<lb/> in its primitive state to the knowledge of skilful<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>handicraft&#44; from the knowledge Hebrew and English alphabet to a correct understanding of our language<lb/> of prayer and the vernacular&#44; the pupils should rise stage<lb/> by stage&#44; and grow in usefulness and in a sense of<lb/> self dependence and respect.  But I may be<lb/> allowed to say that the tardiness shown here in res&#45;<lb/>&#45;ponding to my appeal&#44; led me to seek other chan&#45;<lb/>&#45;nels whence to derive the needful means.  A long<lb/> and at times hopeful correspondence with some of the<lb/> confidants of Baron de Hirsch was opened&#44; and I have <lb/>reasons to believe that had not the philanthropist de&#45;<lb/>&#45;cided to make a large remittance annually to<lb/> America for educational purposes&#44; my pleading in<lb/> behalf of the comprehensive school I projected would<lb/> have proved successful.  My eager wish now<lb/> is to see the edifice rise in its vast proportions on<lb/> the spot already purchased&#44; and to receive the assurance<lb/> that the design of the munificent donor of one hundred<lb/> and twenty thousand dollars a year&#44; will be carried<lb/> out by devoting a considerable portion of his rich<lb/> grant to the maintenance of the minding broadening<lb/> institution&#44; destined to honor Philadelphia and Judaism.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>But with my to that earnest wish is added an ardent pra&#45;<lb/>&#45;yer of God&#39;s approval of generous acts proceeding<lb/> from my wealthy coreligionists of Philadelphia.  The<lb/> structure will not speedily tower high nor be ours in<lb/> all reality&#44; unless free will offerings swell the sum<lb/> gathered that far for the noble undertaking.  What<lb/> glory to our men and women who possess what exceeds<lb/> by far their own needs&#44; to say&#58; we have set an immoveable<lb/> basis a school which will fo improve the generation<lb/> we live in&#44; and generations yet unborn.  Our names<lb/> shall remain a blessing for ever upon earth&#44; and our charity<lb/> will gain the approval of our God in heaven.  And<lb/> may &#34;He who giveth to the faint strength&#44; and to<lb/> the powerless He imparteth fresh power&#44;&#34; endow me<lb/> with the capacity to help in a work preeminently<lb/> civilizing and most practically advancing the cause<lb/> of religion.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
