<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF4_6</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_6_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_6_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_6_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_6_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_6_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_6_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_6_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_6_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_6_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_6_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_6_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_6_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_6_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_6_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_6_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_6_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Post&#45;Biblical<lb/>
                26<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>The portion of the Torah&#44; which we have read<lb/> this Sabbath&#44; demands that half a shekel be<lb/> given by each person for the use of the Sanctuary&#44;<lb/> as an atonement&#44; whenever the Hebrew population<lb/> was is numbered.  This ordinance found in the books of<lb/> Moses made our people&#44; at all times&#44; averse to having<lb/> a census unnecessarily taken.  But their dislike<lb/> of such a measure turned into perfect consternation&#44;<lb/> when the proconsul sent by Rome to govern Judea&#44; after<lb/> the banishment of King Archelaus&#44; compelled every<lb/> Jew to hand in to him the not alone his name and age&#44;<lb/> but a full account of his property to be taxed accord&#45;<lb/>&#45;ingly.  Such an act&#44; aside from the opposition<lb/> it raised on religious ground&#44; was hateful for<lb/> political reasons.  It was a wound sore and deep<lb/> into the hearts of our people.  It meant that they<lb/> had last every vestige of independence&#44; that they<lb/> were chained to the will of a foreign heathen power.<lb/>  At that trying time&#44; the influence of the offi&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciating high&#45;priest fortunately succeeded in prevent&#45;<lb/>ing a general outbreak and bloodshed.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Still a Galilean called Judah&#44; put<lb/> himself then at the head of a party that were sworn<lb/> to resist taxation&#44; and to acknowledge no ruler<lb/> save God and kill Romans and their adherents<lb/> who favored peace at any price.  The new<lb/> sect took the name of &#34;Zealots&#34; and&#44; if contempt<lb/> of dangers and a willing sacrifice of one&#39;s life<lb/> for a cause&#44; is bravery&#44; the Zealots&#45;&#45;though fierce<lb/> and fanatical&#45;&#45;deserve the appellation of <sic>heros</sic>.  But<lb/> Judea lay at the feet of Rome.  All attempts<lb/> to keep off from it the crushing blow were in<lb/> vain.  Greedy governors came from the<lb/> seven hilled city to the city of David and were<lb/> replaced in turn by others more or less rapacious&#44;<lb/> but among all of them none gained the unenviable<lb/> notoriety of Pontius Pilate.  If christians<lb/> remember him with abhorrence&#44; Jews have rea&#45;<lb/>&#45;sons to recall his memory with a feeling of detest&#45;<lb/>&#45;ation.  The first indication of that wicked man&#39;s<lb/> wish to insult our people and our religion was<lb/> the cowardly way in which he introduced unto Je&#45;<lb/>&#45;rusalem banners and shields bearing images hated by Jews.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Under the shades of night he planted those en&#45;<lb/>&#45;signs conspicuously in the capital&#44; as to inti&#45;<lb/>&#45;mate that Judaism had died by the blows g<lb/> which Paganism had dealt against it.  At the<lb/> sight of such emblems&#44; our fathers hastened to the<lb/> Governor&#39;s residence and insisted upon their removal.<lb/>  Pilate ordered the deputation to leave his presence&#44;<lb/> or prepare to die.  The representatives of our people<lb/> then bared their breasts&#44; ready to be pierced by<lb/> the sword rather than <sic>yeild</sic>.  Their earnestness<lb/> conquered the vile Roman official&#44; and the objection&#45;<lb/>&#45;able bucklers and standards were taken away.<lb/></p>
            <p>But it was not long after before another act of<lb/> Pontius Pilate outraged our people.  On the plea of<lb/> repairing and extending waterworks&#44; he seized upon<lb/> the treasury of the temple&#44; and used it as he chose.<lb/>  The Jews enraged at such an arbitrary conduct tried to stop<lb/> the laborers&#44; but Pilate sent stealthily among the crowd<lb/> soldiers dressed in oriental costumes&#44; with daggers con&#45;<lb/>&#45;cealed in their clothes&#44; and wherever our people collected<lb/> together&#44; they were stabbed by the Romans in disguised Romans<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>A large number were thus dastardly set<lb/> upon and murdered.  It can scarcely be<lb/> a matter of surprise that amidst such constant<lb/> sufferings&#44; the hope of a Divine interposition<lb/> was fondly entertained by the majority of our people.<lb/>  The belief in the restoration of a kingdom of David<lb/> at some distant future was founded upon Scrip&#45;<lb/>&#45;tural authority.  How it should take place&#44; no<lb/> one could definitely tell&#44; but that it would happen<lb/> and bring to Israel independence and honor&#44; was a<lb/> doctrine permeating all classes.  They would have<lb/> welcomed the daring scion of the Judean race&#44; who<lb/> assumed the championship and struck for liberty.<lb/>  Jeshua&#44; or&#44; as better known&#44; Jesus of Nazareth was<lb/> not the first&#44; and we know well from history that<lb/> he was not the last&#44; to imagine himself inspired<lb/> to accomplish a deliverance.  He came from that<lb/> district of Palestine&#44; where Judah and many of the<lb/> zealots were born.  Like them&#44; he was a <sic>Galiliean</sic><lb/> enthusiast&#44; but unlike them&#44; he held out ideas&#44; which<lb/> could satisfy only a few disposed tamely to submit to the<lb/> inevitable&#44; and turn their thoughts from surrounding<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>evils&#44; to the contemplation of promised pleasures<lb/> beyond this life.  He could not possibly call bring<lb/> to his side the masses who expected freedom from a galling yoke&#44; by asking them to give Caesar<lb/> what belonged to Caesar that is tributes and taxes from among<lb/> the most humbly stationed in society.  Them he taught<lb/> high morality&#44; as inculcated by our prophets&#44; and he<lb/> illustrated his instruction by parables well taken chosen and adopted adapted from<lb/> the innumerable sayings of our sages.  His preaching<lb/> if correctly reported&#45;&#45;reveals a mind nobly elevated but full<lb/> of exaggerated notions&#44; carrying charity and purity<lb/> to impracticable extremes&#59; but that he was allowed<lb/> to preach in the Synagogues&#44; is an evidence of the<lb/> tolerance of Judaism&#44; even in those revolutionary<lb/> times.  The man of Nazareth would<lb/> not have run any risk&#44; if he had limited himself to<lb/> reproaching pretenders and hypocrites&#45;&#45;though he<lb/> used very strong language&#44; naturally irritating to men<lb/> against whom it was directed.  Nor would the account<lb/> of his miraculous cures have exposed him to a public<lb/> accusation before a Jewish tribunal<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>It was because he proclaimed himself the<lb/> expected &#34;Messiah&#44;&#34; without any act to warrant the<lb/> claim&#59; because he took the title of &#34;the son of God&#44;&#34;<lb/> not in a figurative but in a positive material sense&#44; and<lb/> that of the &#34;king of the Jews&#44;&#34; inciting thereby a Roman<lb/> soldiery to brutal excesses&#59; it was by reason of these<lb/> circumstances that he met the fate which he ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;parently courted&#44; in order to be remembered by his adher&#45;<lb/>&#45;ents as a martyr and a saint.  I refer to this<lb/> even in post&#45;biblical history with a great mistrust<lb/> in my capacity to furnish an adequate idea of the causes that<lb/> brought it about&#44; and I would have let it go unnoticed&#44;<lb/> if it were not closely connected with the governorship<lb/> of Pontius Pilate in Judea.  We&#44; as Jews&#44; cannot<lb/> accept as facts all which the New Testament&#45;&#45;not un&#45;<lb/>&#45;frequently self&#45;contradictory&#45;&#45;states.  The Talmud has<lb/> a few passing allusions to the crucifixion hanging of a son of<lb/> Miriam&#44; supposed to have been executed before the Passover festival.  But<lb/> as Christianity really took its start under the reign<lb/> of Constantine at the end of the third century after the<lb/> birth of its founders&#44; the early Talmudists took no<lb/> pains to leave extensive records&#44; of a comparatively<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>obscure and small sect branched out of Judaism.  Some<lb/> modern authors have denied altogether the existence<lb/> of the teacher of the new religion&#59; others&#44; have made<lb/> him a mere myth typical of human meekness and innocence.  What<lb/> may now be readily admitted is that he lived in troublous<lb/> times&#44; when Judea was a prey to contending parties&#59; that<lb/> he was fired into a state of extravagant self&#45;reliance&#44;<lb/> which led to blasphemy&#44; in accordance with the Jew&#45; as interpreted by the Hebrew<lb/>&#45;ish code&#59; that he was&#44; accordingly&#44; declared guilty by<lb/> the high&#45;priest Joseph Caiaphas&#44; President of the San&#45;<lb/>&#45;hedrin&#44; and as the latter had been deprived by the Ro&#45;<lb/>&#45;mans of the power of carrying out the sentence of death&#44;<lb/> Pontius Pilate&#44; then governor&#44; had him executed at the<lb/> instance of Jewish authorities.  It has also<lb/> been asserted that Pilate&#44; on hearing that Jesus was from Galilee&#44; referred the case to Herod Antipas&#44; the son of Herod<lb/> the Great&#44; who was then the acknowledged ruler<lb/> of that part of the country&#44; but that Herod refused<lb/> to condemn sentence the accused&#44; out of conscientious scruples.<lb/>  This story is hardly credible&#44; for Antipas was both<lb/> irreligious and cruel.  If we consider a passage<lb/> in Josephus authentic&#44; Herod Antipas beheaded<lb/> Zechariah&#44; afterwards called Johanan or Jon the Baptist&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>out of simply from fear that the influence of that bold<lb/> preacher might be too great&#44; and if we accpet<lb/> the &#91;&#63;&#93; statement of the New Testament&#44; he<lb/> committed that crime in consequence of having per&#45;<lb/>&#45;petrated another.  Herod Antipas was a worthy<lb/> child of his profligate father.  For being on a visit<lb/> at Rome&#44; where a step&#45;brother of his lived in<lb/> retirement&#44; he induced his wife Herodias to<lb/> desert her husband and follow him to Galilee.<lb/>  This impious act was denounced condemned by John&#44; who suf&#45;<lb/>&#45;fered imprisonment for his denunciation&#44; and finally&#44;<lb/> at the instigation of Herodias&#39; daughter&#44; was killed by<lb/> order of the same unprincipled Herod Antipas.<lb/>  But while the ruler of Galilee cared little for<lb/> the ordinances of his faith and the code of morals&#44;<lb/> he took good heed to ingratiate himself with the<lb/> Roman emperor.  At the death of Au&#45;<lb/>&#45;gustus&#44; Tiberius ascended the throne.  To do<lb/> the new Caesar a great honor&#44; Antipas built<lb/> a city which he called Tiberias&#44; a name which<lb/> it retains to this day&#45;&#45;though nothing is left<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>to remind the visitor of its primitive<lb/> splendor.  The history of Tiberias<lb/> is interesting.  To raise that city on its<lb/> foundations&#44; Herod Antipas was obliged to level<lb/> down many old graves and likely and also tamper with the remains.  Orthodox Jews refused to<lb/> go and live where the dead lay and where their<lb/> place of rest had been wantonly made to disappear.<lb/>  Antipas despairing to draw conscientious Hebrews<lb/> to his new capital&#44; invited the poorest classes<lb/> to whom he granted many privileges&#44; and heathens<lb/> who naturally were not deterred by religious scruples.<lb/>  Still Tiberias&#44; with all the advantages it offered&#44; would<lb/> have remained for ever sparsely populated&#44; had not<lb/> the great authority of Rabbi Simeon Ben Jochai&#44; a<lb/> century later&#44; unexpectedly removed all objections to<lb/> taking up one&#39;s residence there.  That sage who<lb/> had hidden himself for years in a cave&#44; on account of<lb/> of Roman persecutions&#44; and who had suffered severely<lb/> in his health&#44; found a restorative in the hot springs<lb/> of Tiberias.  Grateful for his cure&#44; he went<lb/> about and by some appliance&#44; inexplicable to us&#44; discovered<lb/> the spots where graves had existed&#44; and declared the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>the rest of the city free from impurity&#44; and<lb/> and equal in sanctity to any part of the Holy Land.<lb/></p>
            <p>Tiberias did in truth become sacred&#44; not espe&#45;<lb/>&#45;cially because its thermal waters affected the<lb/> cure of Simeon Ben Jochai&#44; but because the<lb/> fountain of our literature was made to flow<lb/> from thence copiously.  After the destruction<lb/> of the Temple and the extinction of famous Hebrew Academies seminaries<lb/> is the capital and its vicinity&#44; of learning&#44; some of our ancient<lb/> teachers who would not quit the paternal soil&#44;<lb/> opened there academies.  In Tiberias the immortal<lb/> Judah the Prince collected the oral traditions&#59; in<lb/> Tiberias Rabbi Johanan&#44; who gave a strong impulse<lb/> to the composition redaction of the Palestenian Talmud had<lb/> his flourishing school&#59; in Tiberias it is believed&#44; were the authors<lb/> of the vowel points&#44; so indispensable to the<lb/> understanding of Holy Writ&#44; disseminated know&#45;<lb/>&#45;ledge&#44; and in Tiberias the Massorites tried to give<lb/> posterity an accurate text of the Hebrew Scriptures.<lb/>  These glorious <sic>reminscences</sic> surrounds the ancient capital<lb/> of Galilee built by Herod Antipas with a halo of sanctity&#44;<lb/> which entitled it yet to the name of &#34;a holy city.&#34;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
