<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF16_5</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_5_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_5_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_5_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_5_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_5_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_5_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_5_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_5_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_5_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_5_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_5_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_5_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>7 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>An admonishing lecture<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Three times has happened2 to me within1 late months what<lb/> I had not experienced in twenty nine years&#39; ministration.<lb/> I expected on different Sabbaths different lads&#44; each<lb/> to be acknowledged in our presence Bar Mitzvah.  They<lb/> had expressed the wish directly or indirectly to be called<lb/> to the Law as such&#44; but they failed to put in an ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;pearance.  How shall we account for the absence&#63;<lb/>  Was it voluntary&#63;  Why then the application to be allowed<lb/> a privilege in this Synagogue&#63;  Was it involuntary&#63;<lb/>  Why then did I not then receive information of about the cause preventing attendance&#63;<lb/>  I have reason to look on the strange occurrence&#44; thrice repeated&#44;<lb/> as the effect of growing indifference.  And I charge with it not the lads but their parents.  I will not speak<lb/> with positiveness regarding the cases in point&#44; lest I con&#45;<lb/>&#45;demn rashly&#44; but I know that in many instances child&#45;<lb/>&#45;ren are forced by their father or their mother to overcome<lb/> a natural strong aversion.  They are compelled to qualify themselves gain the qualification&#44;<lb/> to as it is termed&#44; for standing before a Congregation&#44; on the Sabbath they reach<lb/> their religious majority.  But mark you the fre&#45;<lb/>&#45;quent anomaly.  Neither that father nor that<lb/> mother&#44; in Israel so persistent respecting an outward ceremony&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>is a member of the Congregation&#44; neither<lb/> holds a seat in its place of worship&#59; neither<lb/> attends any of the divine services&#45;&#45;save&#44; perhaps&#44;<lb/> an hour so or so on the day of atonement&#44; but their<lb/> son must go through a form the import of which<lb/> he does not understand&#44; and that in a place he never or<lb/> rarely entered.  Do you wonder at the aversion<lb/><lb/>  Can it be at all surprising that he tries to avoid<lb/> an occasion&#44; at best&#44; very <sic>embarassing</sic> to a youth&#63;<lb/>  When he asked the minister&#44; he may have acted under<lb/> parental direction&#44; but if he can succeed in showing<lb/> himself incapable of fulfilling the obligation urged<lb/> upon him&#44; the lad will feel but too glad.<lb/></p>
            <p>For&#44; Hebrew&#45;&#45;the language in which the people to whom<lb/> he belongs prays&#45;&#45;is foreign to him.  Often Possibly&#44; he has<lb/> not been taught even its alphabet.  Some words in English<lb/> characters&#44; which he pronounces with great difficulty<lb/> are literally beaten into his head&#44; and that is repre&#45;<lb/>&#45;sented to the intelligent lad child as the needed qualification<lb/> for the event in which he is to play a conspicuous part.<lb/>  But if he can allege as an excuse his incapacity inability to over&#45; <sic>fulfil</sic><lb/> &#45;come the task imposed&#44; he will be delivered from its con&#45;<lb/>sequences.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>He will escape the ceremony ordeal called Bar Mizvah.<lb/>  And well he may under such circumstances.  Well he may<lb/> endeavour to hinder the performance carrying out of an unmeaning&#44; a<lb/> hollow form.  For it is shockingly so&#44; when ignorance of the sacred<lb/> language recited&#44; and lack of home instruction&#44; and home examples&#44;<lb/> indisposition on the part of the parents to attend join in public worship&#44; and unwillingness<lb/> to give it the least support&#44; are the attendants of that<lb/> performance.  And I must acknowledge myself<lb/> accessory to the wrong.  I have more than once been per&#45;<lb/>&#45;suaded against my judgment to encourage the continuance<lb/> of a practice when contrary to the object of the Sages who had in view in instituting it.<lb/>  I have written out in the vernacular the benedictions and&#44; at times&#44;<lb/> even the portion of the Law&#44; not to refuse parents whose false<lb/> pride led them to make their sons prominent conspicuous&#44; without<lb/> the least claim to conspicuity prominence.<lb/></p>
            <p>But the evil has not stopped there.  It has spread<lb/> so far as to blunt the keen remorse which a Jew would formerly feel&#44;<lb/> in the event of a family bereavement&#44; for having neglected<lb/> the duty of familiarizing his children with the observances<lb/> of the prayers of his race.  Now&#44; to <sic>accomodate</sic> Israelites<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>who still attach importance to the recital of<lb/> the Kaddish&#44; this has been printed in English letters.<lb/>  and The stricken conscience is thus lulled.  The A panacea has<lb/> was found to the diseased soul.  Fathers and mothers&#33; do not fear&#44; you the lever has been discovered to move you up to heaven.  In sober earnestness I<lb/> declare it the outlook sad&#44; very sad when such scenes are witnessed<lb/> as those I repeatedly behold see.  Jewish families of counting<lb/> a number of sons&#44; of whom none shows acquaintances with<lb/> our usages&#44; and all must resort to an irregular method in<lb/> order to conform with a custom&#44; which has degenerated<lb/> into a superstition.  The &#34;Kaddish&#34; which means the<lb/> acknowledgment of the omnipotence and Sanctity of God&#59; a<lb/> confession of his illimitable Greatness&#44; which is beyond all<lb/> praise&#44; and an entreaty for the happiness of ourselves in&#45;<lb/>&#45;dividually and of Israel collectively&#59; the &#34;Kaddish&#44;&#34; which&#44;<lb/> by reason of its pithy contents&#44; has been chosen as a prayer<lb/> in which that the spirit of the departed may delight to know<lb/> that the survivors it is devoutly recited in the Congregation&#44; public by the survivors amidst congregational<lb/> responses&#59; the &#34;Kaddish&#44;&#34; originally intended to as a conclusion to the<lb/> study of the Law&#44; and finally prescribed to the mourners as a<lb/> substitute for longer meditations and supplications&#44; and have a subject for<lb/> reflection&#44; has grown into an outward form offensive<lb/> to a sense of righteousness.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Just notice its hurried repetition&#44; unreflectingly and not rarely from<lb/> an English transcription.  Observe the shameless rushing<lb/> out of the Synagogue on the Sabbath and holidays as<lb/> soon as the supposed orison presumably grateful to the dead is gabbled over&#44;<lb/> leaving the service incomplete&#44; and going to the store or the<lb/> office against the command of the living God.  That I do<lb/> not exaggerate&#44; you who enter early this holy edifice can<lb/> attest&#44; and you can also testify that some who so act have<lb/> no claim whatever to the forbearance of the Congregation&#44; since<lb/> they do not contribute to its maintenance.<lb/></p>
            <p>Now&#44; I am not disposed to agree with some of my colleagues<lb/> who refuse to countenance any Israelite who is not affiliated<lb/> to a synagogue&#44; in applying to him the Rabbinical epithet<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;a seceder from the Hebrew community&#59;&#34; I will could<lb/> never be induced to go to the length that a Western Minister went when<lb/> he recently decided that burial should be denied to a Jew who has<lb/> kept away from the Synagogue &#91;&#63;&#93; minor Sanctuary&#44; and never offered his mite towards<lb/> the continuance of the worship.  No&#44; I am anxious that<lb/> liberality should continue to be the characteristic of our Sy con&#45;<lb/>&#45;nagogue &#45;gregation.  The culpable negligence of our brethren&#44; shall<lb/> not receive punishment at our hands.  They who choose<lb/> to crowd our courts to on a certain day&#44; as a quietus<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>to their souls&#44; shall not be denied Jewish privileges<lb/> nor will I administer the deserved rebuke&#44; but this<lb/> I pledge myself not to repeat&#58; to favor parents<lb/> by a stultifying of myself&#59; by writing in English<lb/> characters what must be studied&#44; and understood<lb/> in the language of our Seers and Sages.<lb/></p>
            
            <p>&#40;This address was continued at some length length&#44; by<lb/> an address to a Foster&#45;home Bar Mitzvah&#41;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
