<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF2_12</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_12_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_12_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_12_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_12_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_12_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_12_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_12_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_12_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_12_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_12_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_12_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_12_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>An explanatory lecture<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  Those among my hearers&#44; who are familiar with Holy Writ&#44;<lb/> know that the enmity evinced by the Samaritans&#44; impeded for a series of<lb/> years the reconstruction of the second Temple.  From the book of<lb/> Ezra&#44; they must have also learnt that shortly after the ascension of<lb/> Darius to the throne of Persia&#44; the1 sacred work was resumed through3<lb/> the exhortation of two prophets&#44; and under the auspices of a brave<lb/> general and a priest.  The Haftara of this morning bears<lb/> strongly upon the same subject&#44; and  I will purpose offering some necessary elucidations.<lb/>  Mark therefore&#44; my friends&#33; its contents&#44; while I dilate thereon.<lb/>  The obstacles encountered in the prosecution of their undertaking&#44;<lb/> had greatly abated the ardour felt by the Hebrews on their return<lb/> to the land of the patriarchs&#44; after the Babylonian captivity.<lb/>  The main object of their enfranchisement at the hands of King<lb/> Cyrus&#44; remained unaccomplished&#59; and few exhibited the interest it<lb/> commanded claimed.  Zachariah&#44; like his contemporary Haggin&#44; perceived<lb/> that the absence of a point of Union&#44; would have continually exposed the<lb/> people of Judea to the wiles of their idolatrous opponents.<lb/>  He therefore labored with zeal to reinstate the national worship.<lb/>  In the language of inspiration&#44; he assured the desponding of a<lb/> brighter success than heretofore&#44; through the interposition of the Deity.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>The visions&#44; which were the offspring of a mind bent upon the<lb/> stability of Judaism in its ancient glory&#44; purported to convey the same<lb/> happy tiding.  Jerusalem would again become the centre&#44; towards<lb/> which the heart of a vast population would converge.  The second<lb/> Sanctuary would rival the first in greatness and splendour.<lb/>  A Divine protection&#44; would&#44; like a wall of fire&#44; awe&#45;back the<lb/> enemy who sought to destroy Israel.  Accordingly&#44; the section we<lb/> have perused&#44; opens with a beautiful apostrophe to the daughter of<lb/> Zion&#44; and a promise that the completion of the Temple&#44; would invite<lb/> to her borders&#44; new votaries from among the heathen world&#44; from Persia&#44;<lb/> from Media and Idumea.  But while the soul of the prophet&#44;<lb/> was glowing in the anticipation of so joyful prosperous a future&#44; he was<lb/> shown a cause&#44; which might have militated against its con&#45;<lb/>&#45;summation.  The angle who had addressed him pointed out a<lb/> man&#44; who though commissioned to aid in the great work of the<lb/> Lord&#44; was the chief of a defiled household.  The children of<lb/> Joshua the high&#45;priest&#44; had contracted a matrimonial alliance with<lb/> with the daughters of the Stranger.  The loving parent had not<lb/> possibly exercised due authority to restrain them&#59; hence the sea they<lb/> had committed&#44; became his Satan&#44; or accuser before the &#91;inserted above&#58; of the&#93; Supreme2 tribunal1.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  For&#44; let it be&#44; my friends&#44; clearly understood&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>that the Hebrew &#34;Satan&#34; bears no analogy whatever with that<lb/> invented by mythological fiction&#44; and admitted into other creeds as the<lb/> implacable foe of mankind. author of all evil.  The God of Israel who is Almighty has not delegated<lb/> his a power to so malignant a to any celestial or terrestrial being.  To believe that He who is God the Lord<lb/> of justice and mercy&#44; would deliberately deliver his creatures into the<lb/> hand of one&#44; who delights in evil in perverting &#38; destroying its unjewish and blasphemous<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; Satan&#44; from the root &#91;Hebrew&#93; Satah&#44; means &#34;to thwart&#34; and it may apply<lb/> to individuals&#44; as in the case of Hadad the Edomite&#44; who arose against<lb/> Solomons &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; or to our own misdeeds&#44; which<lb/> conspire against our happiness&#59; conformably with the Rabbinical<lb/> axiom &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;He who does a wrong&#45;act acquires<lb/> to himself an <sic>accusor</sic>&#34;  And if there are passages in the scrip&#45;<lb/>&#45;tures&#44; or in the Talmud&#44; that seem to gainsay&#44; our assertion&#44; a<lb/> mature examination of the whole context&#44; will prove us per&#45; irrefutably<lb/> fectly correct.  At all events&#44; in the subject under discussion&#44;<lb/> it was a trespass&#44; which had not been timely prevented&#44; that stood as<lb/> an adversary to the progress of the national cause.  But in the<lb/> metaphorical style of prophecy&#44; the Eternal&#44; who would restore Israel&#44; to his former height&#44; and re&#45;establish his divinity in Jerusalem&#44;&#45;&#45;rebuked that trespass&#44;<lb/> in order that it might be wiped off expunged.  For&#44; we read&#44; that not in<lb/> vain had he snatched from the consuming fire of exile&#44; the righteous<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>son of Jeozadak&#44; but that he should minister before his reconstructed<lb/> altar.  To render him worthy in every respect of that noble vocation&#44;<lb/> he was divested of his stained garments&#44; and arrayed in habiliment of<lb/> purity&#59; that is&#44; the progeny of the same chosen priest&#44; cast off as filthy<lb/> raiment&#44; the women with whom they had been united in guilt&#44; and<lb/> made a public atonement.  That act measure&#44; which the time and the<lb/> preservation of Judaism imperatively demanded&#44; silenced the all accusations&#44;<lb/> and the angel&#44; who had spoken to Zechariah&#44; directed to Joshua<lb/> words of promise and consolation &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  By rectitude and piety he<lb/> would secure to himself and offspring the sublime station he held.  He<lb/> would remain the steward of the house of god&#59; the guardian of divine insti&#45;<lb/>&#45;tutions&#59; and at his decease&#44; inherit a place amidst the Seraphic<lb/> host that exist for evermore.  Thus must be understood the<lb/> phrase &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  But that declaration so<lb/> joyful to a faithful heart&#44; could not be effected&#44; while the walls<lb/> of the Temple continued unbuilt&#59; for&#44; only within their limits<lb/> were the sacerdotal functions to be exercised.  Therefore the same<lb/> divine heavenly messenger proclaimed in the presence of all the assembled<lb/> priests&#44; that a branch of the root of Jesse&#44; would soon flourish<lb/> and cast its protecting shade over Zion.  That as it shot forth&#44; the<lb/> work of re&#45;edification would no longer be impeded&#44; for&#44; each<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>stone set into the ground&#44; would be guarded by numerous watchers<lb/> sent from above&#59; and thereupon the hand of the Most High&#44; would<lb/> engrave the following significant inscription &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;In one day the iniquity of this land shall depart&#34;  Then would Israel Judah<lb/> enjoy <sic>tranquillity</sic> as during the reign of Solomon&#44; when from Dan<lb/> to Beer Shebang&#44; men sat under the vine and fig&#45;tree&#44; without<lb/> fear of molestation.  But as the angle made an end<lb/> of speaking thus&#44; the mind of the prophet became absorbed in<lb/> deep thoughts.  The interpretation of what he had heard&#44; was not<lb/> entirely disclosed to his understanding.  He had failed to learn who was<lb/> typified by the promised Branch&#44; that would speedily grow.<lb/>  Wherefore was he aroused from his meditation&#44; to behold another<lb/> vision.  He saw a golden candlestick&#44; on the top of which there<lb/> stood a large bowl&#44; and around it seven lamps&#44; whereto was<lb/> attached an equal number of pipes.  Into these a fresh supply<lb/> of pure oil was incessantly poured from the upper bowl.  But the<lb/> igniting substance itself was spontaneously pressed into the latter<lb/> vessel from two branches of an olive tree&#44; placed on its right and left.<lb/>  At that unwonted sight&#44; the inspired servant of God relapsed into<lb/> his meditative mood.  He could define the allusion conveyed<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>by the candlestick and its seven lamps&#44; for&#44; it obviously signified the<lb/> re&#45;edification of the Temple&#44; which that perpetual light would<lb/> adorn as formerly.  But he could not comprehend what was<lb/> meant by the olives which were by some invisible power converted<lb/> into oil.  To enlighten him&#44; the heavenly messenger accosted it him<lb/> anew&#44; and pointed to the emblamatic branch&#44; whose signification purport<lb/> he could not the Seer had not yet fathomed.  Like the oil It was even Zerubabel&#44; the<lb/> chosen scion of Judah&#39;s stock&#44; that would erect the Temple<lb/> in all its pristine glory&#44; and re&#45;instate the national worship.<lb/>  But like as the oil which was formed into the bowl&#44; without<lb/> the pressure of a human hand&#44; so would the structure dedicated<lb/> to the Most High&#44; be completed&#44; not through man&#39;s strength<lb/> or valour&#44; but by the interposition of Providence on behalf of<lb/> his liberated Israel people.  Sustained by the spirit of Him that<lb/> rules the universe&#44; Zerubabel would become the terror of his<lb/> adversaries&#44; None should dare to obstruct his work&#44; for&#44; led<lb/> forth by the Lord of hosts&#44; he would level with the earth&#44; a power<lb/> as lofty as a gigantic mountain.  And as at the<lb/> termination of his holy task&#44; he would crowned the building<lb/> with its superstructure&#44; a shout would burst forth<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>from a multitude of grateful hearts&#44; greeting the finishing&#45;<lb/>&#45;stone with the words &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  It is comely and graceful.<lb/>  Such is&#44; my friends&#33; according to some of our authorities&#44; the exposition<lb/> of the Haftar&#225; we have rehearsed this morning.  Our Rabbins<lb/> designated it also for the Sabbath Hanucc&#225;&#44; and very appositely too&#59;<lb/> for&#44; the events which gave it origin&#44; were nearly reproduced in the<lb/> days of the Maccabees.  The valiant Judah became the Zerubadel<lb/> of his time&#44; who lowered the pride of Antiochus our sworn enemies&#44; and re&#45;dedicated<lb/> the Temple&#44; despite internal and external impediments.<lb/></p>
            <p>I am not ignorant of the fact&#44; that the whole section has been<lb/> applied by sundry commentators to the f hoped&#45;for advent of<lb/> the Messiah&#44; of whom Zerubabel is made the type.  But<lb/> without denying that few scattered sentences may appear to favor that<lb/> construction&#44; I hold it as my opinion&#44; that in this instance&#44;<lb/> the inspired Zechariah did not cast his vision to a remote future&#44;<lb/> when the present&#44; offered ample scope for his prophetic exhortations.<lb/>  That he believed the restoration from Chaldea imperfect and very short<lb/> of the glorious predictions uttered by his predecessors&#44; we may deduce<lb/> from his subsequent writings&#44; but the tenor of the first seven<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>chapters of his book&#44; fully justifies our conclusion.<lb/></p>  
            <p>My Brethren&#33;  Consult then in the text&#44; and judge according to<lb/> your discernment.  And may God enlighten our minds&#44; that<lb/> we may ever comprehend the words of Holy Writ&#44; and teach<lb/> them suitably to their true signification.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
