<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF16_3</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1894" source="" attested="yes">1894</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_3_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_3_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_3_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_3_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_3_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_3_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_3_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_3_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_3_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_3_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_3_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_3_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_3_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_3_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_3_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_3_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>On Parashat Ki Tissa &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>&#34;Remember ye the Law of Moses My servant&#44; whom<lb/> I commanded in Horeb for all Israel statutes and or&#45;<lb/>&#45;dinances.  Behold&#33;  I send to you Elijah the prophet&#44;<lb/> before the great and dreadful day of the Lord cometh.&#34;<lb/>  Moses and Elijah are in the parting thought of the last<lb/> Hebrew Seer.  Moses and Elijah&#44; the zealous avengers<lb/> of God&#39;s word.  Brethren.  In exceptional times&#44;<lb/> exceptional men must rise&#44; and carry into action ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;ceptional measures.  Striking illustrations of that<lb/> truth are the two episodes in Biblical history&#44; offered<lb/> this sabbath to our contemplation.  At Sinai&#44;<lb/> when loose dancing and carousels usurped the domi&#45;<lb/> &#45;nion place of devotional awe and veneration pertaining which belongs to the<lb/> Law&#44; the son of Amram stood up in all the majesty<lb/> of a righteous indignation anger that burned the wicked un&#45;<lb/>&#45;sparingly.  At Carmel&#44; when the parasites of a wretched<lb/> queen&#44; had made the land of Israel reek with the fumes of corrupt&#45;<lb/>&#45;ion&#44; the Tishbite fearlessly defied crowned heads&#44; and<lb/> cut off vile seducers.  Perhaps the people who demanded of<lb/> Aaron a representation of the Deity&#44; supposing that the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>champion of their liberty and their inspired guide&#44;<lb/> had died&#44; may not have originally have intended by the<lb/> molten image a denial of the Omnipotent&#44; and<lb/> a the raising of a throne to rank idolatry&#44; but simply<lb/> to possess a medium for consulting oracles like the superstitious Teraphim.  Indeed&#44; in that<lb/> light has their wish request been viewed by very learned inter&#45;<lb/>&#45;preters of our Scriptures.  Nevertheless&#44; to have suf&#45;<lb/>&#45;fered so debasing an error to go unpunished&#44; would have<lb/> been to connive at the violation of the second command&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment of the Decalogue&#58; &#34;Thou shall not make for thy&#45;<lb/>&#45;self any graven image.&#34;  Nay&#58; Soon that error begot the<lb/> sin of foul depravity.  For we read&#58; &#34;The people sat<lb/> down to eat and drink&#44; and they rose up to play&#34;&#44;<lb/> meaning by the Hebrew word to revel in licentious feasts.  At the<lb/> foot of the holy mountain&#44; the trusty attendant had wait&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed for the return of his master.  They meet again&#44; but<lb/> not to rejoice over the fealty of all who had vowed al&#45;<lb/>&#45;legiance to the covenant.  In the thundering noise<lb/> which rends the air&#44; the shouting of warriors battling<lb/> against enemies who had assailed the armor&#45;bearers of<lb/> God&#39;s Unity&#63;  Or is it the cry of gallant soldiers who<lb/> fought with prowess valor&#44; but were compelled to <sic>yeild</sic> to a superior<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>number&#63;  No&#58; the din of riotous merriment over<lb/> a brute&#44; fashioned in gold&#44; is the unwelcome sound.<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Who is on the Lord&#39;s side&#63;&#34; a voice echoes<lb/> forth throughout the camp.  The enormity of the<lb/> sin must be realized by an act of condign severity requital.<lb/>  Moses&#44; the compassionate saviour of the enslaved&#44; Moses&#44;<lb/> willing to be blotted out from life and memory&#44; so that<lb/> Israel might live and enjoy an everlasting remem&#45;<lb/>&#45;brance&#44; is keeps unmoved&#44; when the honor of his God is<lb/> publicly outraged.  A reflection of the man<lb/> who had ascended the top of Sina&#239;&#44; was he who<lb/> journeyed far in fasting and solitariness&#59; hiding in the<lb/> cleft of the rock&#44; where the archprophet had stood<lb/> to receive a message of pardon&#44; so dear to his poster&#45;<lb/>&#45;ity &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;The Lord&#44; the Lord is a God merciful and gracious&#44; slow to<lb/> anger&#44; and abundant in loving&#45;kindness and truth&#34;<lb/> Brethren.  Elijah has been called &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;the angel<lb/> of the covenant&#34; and the title is justly applied.  If <sic>to</sic> big<lb/> to rescue from extinction religious principles&#44; which all have<lb/> declared irrecoverably lost&#44; is the manifestation of to exhibit noble courage&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>if to assert the eternity supremacy of righteousness&#44; is to<lb/> serve the Lord of righteousness&#44; then the Tishbite deserves<lb/> the height to which a popular belief has raised him.<lb/>  Not the comparatively few&#44; as in the days of the golden calf&#44; had bent<lb/> the knee to falsehood.  Altars of pollution beclouded with<lb/> their soul&#45;stifling incense the whole country&#44; ruled<lb/> over by the house of Omri&#44; illicitly allied to the hea&#45;<lb/>&#45;then house of the Phenician Sidonians.  For&#44; none was ever<lb/> so domineered by a ferocious woman&#44; implacable in her<lb/> fanaticism&#44; as Ahab by his queen Jezebel.  She con&#45;<lb/>&#45;trolled the destiny of the empire.  She had forbidden&#44; under<lb/> penalty of death&#44; the worship of the One spiritual God.<lb/>  Hushed where the sacred songs of the Levites.  Closed were<lb/> the schools of prophets&#44; designed by Samuel of old to keep<lb/> the fire of the national religion aglow&#44; for&#44; the bloody sword<lb/> of Jezebel hung over the heads of the disciples of those schools.  Where<lb/> the patriarchs had proclaimed an all&#45;perfect God&#44; now<lb/> the immortal rites of Astarte or &#34;queen of heaven&#59;&#34; the fierce horrid dances round the<lb/> brutal Moloch&#44; were alone allowed.  But Elijah dared<lb/> the throne which iniquity personified had mounted.  Against<lb/> royal threats&#44; he set a faith unconquerable.  Hunted by in&#45;<lb/>&#45;veterate enemies&#44; he still found secret friends allies within the palace<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>of cruelty.  Despising a protection gained by<lb/> recreancy and flattery&#44; he made the wilds of<lb/> deserts his home&#59; his meal a scanty loaf&#44; his bed<lb/> the naked earth.  Austere was his nature&#44; per&#45;<lb/>&#45;haps too stern&#44; when compared with that of pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;phets who before and after him announced the<lb/> will of the Most High.  Perhaps Who can tell but that the vision in which<lb/> he heard the voice of the Lord not through a whirl&#45;<lb/>&#45;wind&#44; not through an earthquake&#44; not through a<lb/> consuming fire&#44; but only through &#34;a still small voice&#34;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; may have been a gentle rebuke to<lb/> his impetuosity.  But&#44; brethren&#44; I have said it&#59;<lb/> in exceptional times&#44; exceptional men must arise and<lb/> carry into action exceptional measures.  In the<lb/> lesson from Exodus&#44; we have seen to&#45;day Moses<lb/> vindicating the claims of the entire decalogue to im&#45;<lb/>plicit obedience&#44; by a deed which spread terror upon<lb/> shameless offenders.  The lesson from the first book<lb/> of Kings&#44; shows us Elijah challenging with irrepres&#45;<lb/>&#45;sible wrath the sycophants that styled themselves<lb/> &#34;prophets of Baal&#34; and exposing chastising their friend in a fearfully manner.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Four hundred and fifty white robed priests of the<lb/> sun&#45;god&#44; marshalled by their idolatrous king&#44; faced<lb/> the man of weird looks&#44; strangely appalling&#44; with<lb/> his flowing locks of hair&#44; his coarse mantle and a<lb/> leathern girdle round his loins.  He rises to his<lb/> full height and speaks&#58; &#34;How long hath ye between<lb/> two opinions&#44; if the Lord be God follow Him&#44; but<lb/> if Baal&#44; then follow him.&#34;  So the intrepid pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;phet addresses the multitude assembled to witness<lb/> the contest.  Israel has terribly sinned.  All the<lb/> influences which royal authority and the seductions<lb/> of a licentious worship could exert have contributed to<lb/> estrange the progeny of the upright from the an&#45;<lb/>&#45;cestral belief&#44; but still they are still Elijah&#39;s brethren.<lb/>  For their redemption he yearned&#59; to restore them<lb/> to the forsaken covenant&#44; was his ardent longing.<lb/>  Now the occasion had arrived&#44; when he might awa&#45;<lb/>kened the national sentiment&#44; so long dormant.<lb/>  Upon the eastern slope of Carmel&#44; commanding<lb/> the last view of the Mediterranean sea&#44; an altar<lb/> had once been dedicated to the Eternal&#44; ere the im&#45;<lb/>&#45;pious Jezebel had risen to demand its overthrow.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>By its side Elijah takes his stand.  Opposite<lb/> to him are arrayed those he invited to an encounter&#44;<lb/> thrilling but decisive.  &#34;You are the many.  With you<lb/> is power.  Your teaching is supported by says kingly &#38; queenly decree.<lb/>  Your adherents are countless.  I am one&#44; the deserted<lb/> servant of Adona&#239;&#44; unshielded in my faith by mortals power&#59;<lb/> left alone in my confiding trust.  Choose you then the<lb/> offering and present it first.  Let the sun&#45;god that you<lb/> adore&#44; flash his fire and consume you oblation.<lb/>  That shall be the test of the doctrine which you pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;fess.  If you fail&#44; I will entreat the God of my<lb/> fathers to sanctify His belief by His a miraculous inter&#45;<lb/>&#45;position.&#34;  Thus spoke Elijah.  It was early<lb/> morning&#44; when the prophets of Baal began their<lb/> wild dances&#44; and their shrill songs&#44; crying aloud and<lb/> leaping high.  The cloudless sun of the Orient poured<lb/> his scorching rays upon them&#44; best it discharged not its<lb/> fire across their altars.  Frenzied with ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;citement&#44; they tossed their swords and lances&#44; as<lb/> was their practice in their mad worship&#44; till<lb/> blood streamed from their bodies.  Exhausted&#44; they<lb/> paused.  The sun is now bending now westward.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Elijah rises calmly and gather twelve stones&#44;<lb/> typical of the founders of a united nation.<lb/>  The kingdom of Israel had sold itself to the<lb/> idol&#44; but the prophet will not cast off the<lb/> progeny of the righteous.  Let the ten tribes return<lb/> to God.  Penitence will save them.  The wood is<lb/> arranged.  The sacrifice is laid.  A prayer in which<lb/> every fibre of a sincere heart joins&#44; ascends to<lb/> heaven.  &#34;O Lord God of Abraham&#44; Isaac and Israel&#44;<lb/> let it be known this day that Thou art the Lord<lb/> God in Israel&#44; and that I am thy servant....answer me&#44;<lb/> O Lord&#33; answer me&#44; that His people may know<lb/> that Thou art the Lord God&#34;.  Aye &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;The Lord He is God&#59; the Lord He is God&#34;&#44;<lb/> burst forth from lips long sealed against the utter&#45;<lb/>&#45;ance of the dreaded name&#44; as the sky flashed down<lb/> the fire that burned consumed the offspring&#44; but purified Israel.<lb/>  Brethren.  In exceptional times&#44; exceptional men must<lb/> rise&#44; and bring into action exceptional measures.<lb/>  The persecutors became the victims.  In the deep<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>channel of Kishon&#44; the prophets of Baal felt<lb/> their blood flow into the distant sea. at the rising of a<lb/> storm.  &#34;Remember ye the Law of Moses My servant&#44;<lb/> whom I commanded in Horeb for all Israel statutes<lb/> and ordinances.  Behold&#33;  I send to you Elijah the<lb/> prophet before the great and dreadful day of the<lb/> Lord cometh.&#34;  Moses and Elijah were in the<lb/> parting thought of the last of Hebrew Seers&#45;&#45;the<lb/> two zealous avengers of God&#39;s holy word.<lb/>  Grand figures&#33;  Magnificent models in human<lb/> history&#33;  Which should we copy&#63;  To me&#44; the son<lb/> of Amram is the archetype of a perfect manhood.<lb/>  Severe when severity is a healing to souls deeply diseased&#59;<lb/> but meek&#44; forgiving&#44; living only to educate his people&#44; dying<lb/> with a blessing for that people lingering on his sainted lips.<lb/>  The Tishbite is all ablaze with the love of Divine justice&#44;<lb/> he&#44; the un<sic>yeilding</sic> defender of right against might.  He&#44;<lb/> the self denying apostle&#44; forced to become a wanderer&#44;<lb/> assumes before our vision an aspect unapproachably<lb/> stern.  Yet&#44; it is he whom Malachi invests with<lb/> the power to turn back the heart of fathers to the<lb/> heart of children to that of their<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>fathers&#44; lest division in the household&#44; bring<lb/> a curse upon the earth.  Or&#44; as the Talmudist ex&#45;<lb/>press it &#91;Hebrew&#93; When Elijah<lb/> cometh again&#44; his mission will be to bring backsliders<lb/> nigh unto God&#44; not to thrust them off.<lb/></p>
            <p>Brethren.  They are the modern Elijahs who work<lb/> to that end.  They who lay their fall weight into<lb/> the balance of righteousness.  God&#39;s servants are<lb/> those clothed in purity&#44; not in egotism.  Those who<lb/> value the honor of the Lord above popular applause&#59;<lb/> above their very life.  They need not bear a distinguishing<lb/> title for to perform the godly work.  Are we not all a King&#45;<lb/>&#45;dom of priests&#63;  Let us then unitedly enter our<lb/> realm.  Let each of us ascend the throne wrought<lb/> by the finger hand of God for the seed of His first adorer&#44;<lb/> Abraham the faithful.  From thence we shall proclaim<lb/> that &#34;Adona&#239; He is God&#44; Adona&#239; He is God.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
