<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF10_4</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1894-10" source="" attested="yes">19 October 1894</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_4_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_4_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_4_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_4_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_4_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_4_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_4_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_4_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_4_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_4_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_4_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_4_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET.<lb/></p>
            <p>PHILADELPHIA&#44; 189<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>145<lb/></p>
            
            <p>For the day of Kippur &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <p>It was nearly published as a whole nearly entirely<lb/>
                in the Jewish Exponent<lb/>
                with some corrections &#38; emendations<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Miss O&#39;Reilly&#39;s Report&#44; which all must have read<lb/> in Philadelphia papers on the 24th day of last month&#44;<lb/> was a very sad revelation the sadder to Jewish hearts&#44; because<lb/> it bore on its face the aspect of genuineness.  That to the<lb/> dishonor of the fair name of Israel&#44; out of 555 black<lb/> spots&#45;&#45;not homes and not houses&#45;&#45;the writer should have<lb/> discovered the largest elements of wretchedness among our<lb/> people of foreign birth&#44; is a record offensive to the re&#45;<lb/>&#45;ligion which we profess&#44; discreditable to merchants<lb/> of our faith&#44; while humanity shudders at the nar&#45;<lb/>&#45;rative.  Inequity alone could have conceived<lb/> the sweating system&#44; so prolific of evils&#45;&#45;a system<lb/> stunting the growth of children employed under it&#44;<lb/> bending with premature old age men and women in<lb/> the prime of life&#44; tainting the atmosphere with<lb/> foul vapors&#44; bereaving many a mother of her young.<lb/></p>  
            <p>Incredible it would seem&#44; if the informant were<lb/> not reliable&#44; that in this century of undoubted pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;gress&#59; in this century and in this country&#44; whose inven&#45;<lb/>&#45;tive genius has increased a hundred fold what contributes<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>to indoors and outdoors comforts&#44; morals should ne&#45;<lb/>&#45;vertheless be still so low&#44; that an Isaiah would with righteous<lb/> indignation would repeat his denunciatory address against<lb/> the rich&#58; &#34;Ye have in your houses what ye have<lb/> robbed out of from the poor&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;What<lb/> mean ye that crush my people and grind the face<lb/> of the poor&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Brethren.<lb/>  The spirit of Moses spoke then by the lips of the<lb/> son of Amoz&#44; for&#44; none more compassionate than<lb/> the legislator who had stood in holy communion<lb/> with the God of Sinai.  Not alone in the denial of<lb/> rightly earned wages Moses condemns as wicked&#44;<lb/> but even the delay of payment he declares a sin.<lb/>  The inspired Lawgiver who in the book of Leviticus<lb/> asked that we shall not let our journeyman<lb/> go home at night without his daily hire &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; respected the same commandment with<lb/> greater emphasis in Deuteronomy&#44; shortly before<lb/> his death &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Thou shalt not defraud a hired man poor<lb/> and needy&#34;&#45;&#45;that is&#44; thou shalt not take advantage of his<lb/> unfortunate condition&#45;&#45;&#34;whether he be one of thy brethren&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>or of the strangers that are in thy land&#44; within thy<lb/> gates&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;On the same day thou shalt give him his wages&#44; let not<lb/> the sun go down upon it&#44; for he is poor&#44; and he has<lb/> set his heart upon it&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;He may cry unto the Lord against thee&#44; and it will<lb/> be a sin unto thee.&#34;  How the soul of our immortal<lb/> teacher would kindle with wrath at the thought<lb/> of such scenes&#44; as recently witnessed in Philadel&#45;<lb/>&#45;phia&#33;  Families vegetating in holes&#44; poisoned<lb/> with pestilential air&#44; stitching&#44; and stitching and<lb/> stitching&#44; twelve or fourteen hours a day to receive<lb/> what does not suffice to procure a scanty meal.<lb/>  For&#44; among the heartrending sights described&#44; was the<lb/> terrible spectacle which met Miss O&#39;Reilly&#39;s searching in Alaska St.<lb/>  A man&#44; his wife and five children occupying a single<lb/> room in which all ate&#44; worked and slept.  The<lb/> father being in poor health&#44; was unable to help any.<lb/>  The mother was blinding herself over a work that<lb/> brought almost nothing.  She complained of the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>hard times and said&#58; &#34;I can get only bread for my child&#45;<lb/>&#45;ren&#34;  The proof of her statement was evidenced in<lb/> the five little ones being gathered about a very small<lb/> table&#44; upon which had been placed a loaf of rye<lb/> bread.  Like a lot of young wolves they made a<lb/> scramble for possession&#44; until each had succeeded<lb/> in getting a share&#44; as much as the tiny would hands of the smallest tightly holding what it could grasp.<lb/>  That was their noonday meal.  How the soul of<lb/> Moses would burn with indignation at man&#39;s revolting<lb/> cruelty against his fellow&#45;man&#44; he that forbade<lb/> the least unkindness to dumb animals&#44; he who would<lb/> not allow&#44; young a nest of birds to be taken off while the mother<lb/> is there lying by her young&#59; he would would not allow two<lb/> beasts of unequal strength to be tied together yoked abreast<lb/> when at work&#59; not even to muzzle an ox so as to<lb/> prevent its eating of the grass of the field&#44; in which<lb/> he it labors for the benefit of its owner.  Upon this<lb/> day of atonement&#44; our supremely humane legislator would thus<lb/> address a people whom he sought to instruct nobly&#58;<lb/> &#34;Progeny of Abraham&#44; the merciful.  Let those who are<lb/> guilty of a heinous crime&#44; go in search of the places<lb/> which testify against their inhumanity and bring there<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>an atonement offering&#44; which will change disease<lb/> into health&#44; hunger into full satisfaction&#44; gloom<lb/> into light.  That will be a Kippur most accept&#45;<lb/>&#45;able to the Lord&#34;.  Brethren.  I pray fervently<lb/> hope that none whom I address is stained with the grie&#45;<lb/>&#45;vous sin which Miss O&#39;Reilly imputed against to heartless<lb/> merchants and the agents of their insatiable greed.  I gladly<lb/> buoy myself up with the belief that not one comes under the condemnation of<lb/> Jeremiah&#58; &#34;Woe unto him that builds his house by<lb/> unrighteousness and his chambers by injustice&#59; that<lb/> makes his neighbor work without wages and gives<lb/> im not his hire.&#34;  But I beseech all within reach<lb/> of my voice to bring an expiatory sacrifice for any<lb/> trespass committed.  by Let it be the exercise of beneficence&#44; which<lb/> has life as a reward the enjoyment of a terrestrial life&#44; as a reward&#44;<lb/> and immortality &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            <p>It is not a figure of speech in which I indulge&#44; but a truth very melancholy indeed which I must report.  Star&#45;<lb/>&#45;vation with its gaunt visage has stood at the gates<lb/> of the United Hebrew charities.  For the twenty fifth year<lb/> of its existence was marked by suffering unforeseen and<lb/> unprecedented.  Not infrequently poverty<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>follows close at the heels of improvidence.  A father&#39;s<lb/> intemperance&#44; or his disposition to venture his earnings<lb/> at the gaming board&#44; has plunged a families into the<lb/> lowest depths of misery.  But it was not the fault<lb/> of many wage&#45;earning men and women&#44; if in the<lb/> year 1894&#44; idleness inactivity refused them bread.  A far extended<lb/> stagnation in trade&#44; the impossibility to obtain situa&#45;<lb/>&#45;tions&#44; when forges and factories were closed&#44; or had reduced<lb/> their workings to a minimum&#44; when shop&#45;keepers<lb/> dismissed their helps&#44; or retained only very few&#44; compelled<lb/> the industrious to beg and brought our United charities<lb/> to a strait never before experienced.  The news that<lb/> the institution had closed its doors&#44; spread abroad&#44; and<lb/> all who have the honor of Philadelphia Jews at<lb/> heart&#44; lamented the circumstance.  But that honor was<lb/> soon redeemed&#44; for thousands were poured in into the trea&#45;<lb/>sury to prevent scenes&#44; too distressing to behold.<lb/>  Still&#44; more than the emergency fund supplied was<lb/> spent&#44; and now the United Charities looks to us<lb/> <sic>prayfully</sic> and hopefully for donations&#44; which will<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>exceed by far those of past years.  I rejoice<lb/> to notice that among donors&#44; some of our Mickv&#233;<lb/> Israel figure prominently&#44; but I mean no reflection<lb/> on any of my brethren especially&#44; when I add that&#44; contrasted with<lb/> other congregations&#44; we stand below the mark.<lb/></p>
            <p>Nothing human is perfect and it is not impossible<lb/> that in the administration of a most difficult&#44;<lb/> arduous and delicate trust&#44; errors may occur&#44; but<lb/> personal experience warrants me to say that<lb/> our generous gifts are now distributed with a sys&#45;<lb/>&#45;tem that commends itself to our approval.  The of&#45;<lb/>ficials are entitled to our confidence&#44; for each m labors<lb/> in his sphere with a zeal which practical religion<lb/> inspires&#44; and while the oldest member of the<lb/> Mickv&#233; Israel congregation presides by an honorary<lb/> title due to his venerable age and character&#44; the<lb/> actual President&#44; his coadjutor&#44; the unwavering<lb/> and untiring corps of women&#44; at whose head stands<lb/> an Esther&#44;&#45;&#45;the queen of charity benefactions&#45;&#45;labor unitedly to a blissful<lb/> end.  &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Happy is he who<lb/> considereth the poor&#44; the Lord will deliver him<lb/> in the day of sorrow trouble&#34;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
