<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF8_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1888-01" source="" attested="yes">1888</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_2_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>80</p>
            
            <p>On the two social meetings of Orientalists<lb/>
                in Philadelphia&#47;88<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  I was surprised at having recently lately received<lb/> an invitation to attend two sociable meetings of Orien&#45;<lb/>&#45;talists&#44; at the respective residence of two noted Christian<lb/> gentlemen of Philadelphia.  My astonishment arose from<lb/> the circumstance that&#44; with the exception aside of Hebrew and<lb/> Aramaic&#45;&#45;which I have tried to study with diligence&#45;&#45;my knowledge of Eastern languages is a tabula<lb/> rasa&#44;&#45;&#45;in plain English&#44; a blank&#45;&#45;and I confess that<lb/> I felt inexpressibly relieved at not having been called<lb/> upon before an assemblage of the learned to offer my views<lb/> on the cultivation of Syriac or Assyriology&#44; or on the<lb/> probable results to science from the Babylonian expedition<lb/> under the auspices of the university of Pennsylvania.<lb/>  However&#44; from what I could gather&#44; my presence at those<lb/> meetings was due to my presidency of the Jewish Theolo&#45;<lb/>&#45;gical Seminary in New York&#44; and in recognition of<lb/> the respect paid to that institution&#44; which lies so close to my<lb/> heart&#44; I deviated from a practice habitual with me.<lb/>  In obedience to the maxim of the author of Proverbs&#44; recom&#45;<lb/>&#45;mending thus&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Stand not in the place of<lb/> great men&#44; for better it is that &#91;&#63;&#93; it be said unto thee &#39;come<lb/> up hither&#39; than those shouldst be put lowered in deference to that wholesome aphorism before the magnates whom thy eyes have seen.&#34;  I have<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>ordinarily shrunk from seeking to mingle among<lb/> persons highly famed for their scholarly literary attainments.<lb/>  Still&#44; I had no cause to regret the exception I made&#44;<lb/> for through it I was inspired by it through with greater constancy in the<lb/> pursuit of the principles which I hold.  The papers read at the<lb/> first social meeting&#45;&#45;varied as they were in character&#45;&#45;bore<lb/> nevertheless a strong resemblance to each other in one feature.<lb/>  The writers agreed&#44; that to understand the scriptures cor&#45;<lb/>&#45;rectly&#44; the original must be studied&#59; that they do not<lb/> manifest a proper appreciation of it&#44; who rest satis&#45;<lb/>&#45;fied with translations&#59; that a mere rudimentary knowledge<lb/> of the test is below the mark which a public expon&#45;<lb/>&#45;nent of the book wherein Hebrew prophecies were pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;served&#44; should strive to reach.  Upon hearing<lb/> that from Christians&#44; I wished that Jews&#44; to whom<lb/> Moses bequeathed the Torah as an inheritance had been<lb/> there in great large numbers&#44; thoughtfully to listen.  What<lb/> a scathing rebuke the uniform remarks of Orientalists&#44;<lb/> might then have appeared to some Congregations and<lb/> their ministers&#44; who combine their forces to evict the<lb/> Hebrew out of the dwelling&#44; which is its own by right of<lb/> a heavenly heritage&#45;&#45;from our God&#39;s out of the consecrated dedicated sanctuary.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Christians see in a wider culture of the Hebrew<lb/> a power for good&#44; even the arms to repel infidelity&#44; Israel&#45;<lb/>&#45;ites can discover in it only a regrettable cumbersome hindrance to<lb/> the worship of Israel&#39;s God.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>  We reject our own heirloom&#44; cast it behind our back as if it were<lb/> dregs&#44; others to whom it does not legitimately belong&#44; gather it up as a prize.  A brother<lb/> in faith of ours&#44; not of a low scale of intelligence&#44; nor<lb/> unacquainted with the holy language&#44; riding with me<lb/> this week to a funeral&#44; strongly advocated the abolition<lb/> of Hebrew&#44; 26 condemned its retention as tending to alie&#45;<lb/>&#45;nate the young from the synagogue.  Forcibly I argued<lb/> from an historical stand point to prove how the Hebrew tongue<lb/> was Israel&#39;s appointed guardians&#59; how the changelings<lb/> in their recklessness&#44; apply the axe at the national tree<lb/> and cut it down to the very root&#59; how parental ne&#45;<lb/>&#45;glect of an essential teaching is opening a chasm gulf<lb/> threatening to separate a so miscalled &#34;Ameircan Ju&#45;<lb/>&#45;daism&#34; from that far&#45;extending Judaism which has most indubitably&#44;<lb/> outlived for a Divine purpose&#44; has outlived outlived long ages of<lb/> persecution.  And as the person with whom I was<lb/> reasoning&#44; had evinced heretofore an interest in educational<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>schemes&#44; I showed that to one Hebrew school set up<lb/> by the Church&#44; scores ought to arise to maintain the<lb/> venerableness of the Synagogue&#44; and the the imposingness of<lb/> its services and our solidarity.  Here  And I improved the occasion by pleading before my interlocutor for the urgent want of a building to<lb/> enlarge the aim and scope of institutions of sacred learn&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing &#38; social advancement in a locality where those children of foreign birth grow numerous&#44;<lb/> by whom the knowledge of Hebrew may be promoted and<lb/> perpetuated.  I am not positive as to about the effect of<lb/> my speaking&#44; but I drew the confession that jud&#45;<lb/>&#45;ging of the needs of Judaism from the anciently accept&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed standard&#44; I was correct in my conservative views.  To this admission<lb/> of a fellow&#45;Israelite&#44; I rejoice to be able to add the<lb/> tacit&#44; yet significant approval of a Christian gentleman<lb/> I will explain&#58; The second social gathering of the Orientalists in our<lb/> city&#44; was very agreeable to me&#44; because of the a total<lb/> absence of formality.  I talked familiarly with<lb/> eminent scholars and derived satisfaction.  The host&#44; the Reverend<lb/> H. Clay Trumbull&#44; editor of the Sunday School Times&#44;<lb/> had studied in advance the tastes of his guests&#44; and had resolved<lb/> to gratify them fully.  Accordingly&#44; they were mentally<lb/> transferred to an Eastern atmosphere&#44; all the surrounding ob&#45;<lb/>&#45;jects&#44; the parlor&#39;s ornamentations&#44; the nationalities<lb/></p> 
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>represented in a striking garb&#44; the Arabic songs&#44;<lb/> the Syrian playing&#44; the sherbet&#44; the fragrant hand wash&#45;<lb/>ing&#44; the moca coffee&#44; the Hebrew&#44; Chaldaic&#44; and<lb/> Armenian manuscripts&#44; all savored strongly of the lands of the Orient through<lb/> which the fathers of the our race journeyed.  Adjoining to<lb/> the room of the unceremonious meeting&#44; a collation had<lb/> been prepared.  A young friend present&#44; called me aside<lb/> and whispered&#58; &#34;The meats were purposely ordered of a Jewish<lb/> caterer&#44; to enable observant Israelites to partake thereof.&#34;<lb/>  I did not choose to avail myself of that invitation&#44; any<lb/> more than of the other on the previous evening&#44; but I &#91;&#63;&#93;<lb/> I help admiring the refinement&#44; the delicacy of a de&#45;<lb/>&#45;meanour which unobtrusively tells the consistent Jew &#34;stand<lb/> by your colours&#59; you are respected for it.&#34;&#63;  What a re&#45;<lb/>&#45;flection on the conduct of many of our brethren&#59; how sadly<lb/> their actions contrast with that of one not born in the<lb/> Law Torah&#59; one not bound by its tenets behests&#33;  Some Israelites caring<lb/> nothing for the feelings of ministers&#44; whom they invite<lb/> to hallow their marriages &#34;according to the law of Moses<lb/> and Israel&#44;&#34; or to hail with Hebrew hymns the admission of a<lb/> male child into the Abrahamic covenant&#44; place load the table before the<lb/> officiating Rabbi with prohibited food&#59; they even fancy to<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>do him honor&#44; if they ask that he will taste a fruit&#44; or sip a<lb/> drink&#44; while his coreligionists are eating &#38; &#91;&#63;&#93; swallowing to their fill<lb/> things declared in the Levitical code abominations.<lb/>  Shame on such&#59; a general defection has blurred their<lb/> moral vision&#59; it has blunted in them every sense of<lb/> propriety.  I know that if the attempt were made<lb/> in this country&#44; which is now tried again in Switzerland&#44;<lb/> I mean to enact a statute forbidding our people to<lb/> follow the traditional rules oral injunctions in preparing animals whose<lb/> flesh we eat&#44; the intolerance would be cried down as<lb/> a deliberate affront insult to our belief.  Yet persons profes&#45;<lb/>&#45;sing that belief do not hesitate offending one of<lb/> its representatives by an invitation to an unJewish<lb/> repast.  Such individuals ought to sit at the feet<lb/> of the Rev. H. Clay Trumbull&#44; and learn human respect&#59;<lb/> if they do not regard Divine ordinances.  He certainly<lb/> could have been excused from heeding the scruples of<lb/> two or three of his guests&#44; not pertaining to his creed&#44;<lb/> and have none could have blamed him for having felt satisfied that he had provided enough<lb/> which they could freely enjoy&#44; but a sentiment<lb/> which I term genuine gentlemanliness&#44; impelled him<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>to go beyond social requirements and manifest his<lb/> veneration for religious consistency.  How different are with Israel of America&#33;  It would<lb/> seems preposterous&#44; nevertheless it is so in our days&#44;<lb/> among our people.  Obedience to the Law&#44; is expected<lb/> to offer an bow low and make apologiesy.  There was a time when its<lb/> opposite would hide itself&#44; to avoid detection&#59; now<lb/> a public display is made of contempt for the<lb/> precepts is offered to view&#44; and the conscientious must beg pardon<lb/> for being conscientious.  Well&#58; I will not point<lb/> out whence the aggravation&#45;&#45;if not the origin&#45;&#45;of the evil emanates&#59; why<lb/> so whence so much arrogance receives encouragement.  I<lb/> will not try to prove tat a desertion of their post by<lb/> the custodians of the traditions has emboldened the<lb/> <sic>wavarers</sic>&#44; I will not do so&#44; lest I be condemned as a<lb/> gratuitous mentor lest I also hear the Dathans and Abrians<lb/> who&#44; according to the Rabbinical legend&#44; asked of the Arch&#45;<lb/>&#45;prophet &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Who has made thee a chief<lb/> and a Judge over us&#63;&#34;&#44; but disclaiming any wish this morning to<lb/> chide and censure&#44; I must appeal to the sense of<lb/> right and my brethren hearers&#44; and let them it decide whether<lb/> propriety does not dictate that where Jewish<lb/> rites are performed&#44; unjewish practices should not be violated.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>As to myself&#44; rather than an affront&#44; I will<lb/> consider my exclusion from doubtful banquets&#44;<lb/> a personal favor.<lb/> &#40;Here follows an address to a Bar Mitzvah who was a Levite&#41;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
