<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF15_4</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_4_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_4_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_4_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_4_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_4_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_4_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_4_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_4_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_4_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_4_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_4_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_4_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_4_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_4_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_4_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_4_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>On Terumah<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;I will meet with thee there&#44; and I will speak with thee<lb/> from above the mercy seat&#44; from between the two cherubim&#44;<lb/> which are upon over the ark of the Testimony&#44; all that which<lb/> I will command thee for the children of Israel.&#34;<lb/>  Presuming that I am addressing Israelies&#44; who do not<lb/> impiously scoffingly say &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Our fathers<lb/> inherited falsehood&#44; vanity which has no utility&#59;&#34; Is&#45;<lb/>&#45;raelites who are none of those who blindly subscribe to<lb/> recent pulpit utterances&#44; intimating that the scroll of<lb/> the Law enshrined in yonder ark is simply a Jewish<lb/> idol and many of its ordinances are relics of heathenism&#44;<lb/> fancying that my hearers still do yet reverence to the Sepher<lb/> Torah and respect its precepts&#44; I have quoted a sen&#45;<lb/>&#45;tence from our Parasha&#44; to a purpose.  Since now a days Mosaism is supplanted by prophetism&#44; I wish to<lb/> show the wide difference distinguishing the inspira&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion of Moses from that of succeeding prophets.<lb/>  Guided by From Under Following the tuition of Holy Writ we learn that the chief of<lb/> all Seers &#91;Hebrew&#93; did not undergo any change<lb/> in his bodily sensations&#44; when his spirit communed<lb/> with God.  He entered the Sanctuary and a super&#45;<lb/>human voice&#44; from the outstretched wings of the typical Cherubs<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>resounded within his ever&#45;wakeful mind.  The<lb/> sages call that &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;A transparent<lb/> vision&#44;&#34; as clear as the reflection of one&#39;s own person<lb/> in a perfect mirror.  Therefore the scriptures attest<lb/> that &#34;the Lord spoke to Moses face to face&#44;&#34; as a man<lb/> speaks to his neighbor&#34;.  Not to encourage the<lb/> subversive idea notion that the invisible&#44; but omnipresent&#44;<lb/> God has a corporeal form&#44; but to give us a faint notion idea<lb/> of the incomparable superior faculties unexcelled spiritual height of the arch&#45;pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;phet.  For&#44; let me say it with all emphasis&#59;<lb/> to apply to the Almighty human senses and functions&#44;<lb/> would be more than an error&#59; it would be blasphemy.<lb/>  Maimonides devotes a considerable part of the first<lb/> treatise of his famous Moreh Nebuchim&#44; or &#34;Guide to<lb/> the perplexed&#44;&#34; to the subject of the incorporeity of<lb/> God&#44; to exclude erroneous ideas thoughts which readers of the<lb/> Hebrew Scriptures might form conceive.  And what the Sage<lb/> of Cordova writes in his philosophical work&#44; he<lb/> briefly repeats&#44; but still more incisively in his mo&#45;<lb/>&#45;numental Mishn&#233; Torah&#45;&#45;the codification of traditional<lb/> laws&#44; while laying down rules regarding penitence.<lb/>  He places in the same category with the Atheist&#44; a person<lb/> who attributes to God a bodily form.  To that strong<lb/> declaration&#44; a French Rabbi antagonistic to the Spanish<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>school of philosophy took exception&#44; still Maimo&#45;<lb/>&#45;nides was standing on Rabbinical ground&#44; which he so<lb/> wrote asserted.  For the Talmudists&#44; not once but repeatedly frequently<lb/> caution us against harboring the most false of<lb/> all beliefs&#44; by telling us that the Bible unavoid&#45;<lb/>&#45;ably uses human language &#91;Hebrew&#93; How unpardonably wrong it is then to cite the<lb/> anthropomorphism of the Pentateuch with a view to belittle its<lb/> worth and impugn its authority&#33;  Those Sensuous expressions<lb/> are not derogatory of the honor due to the Supreme&#59;<lb/> not in the least with men who reflect that lan&#45;<lb/>&#45;guage must per force adapt itself to the<lb/> understanding of those who are to be instructed<lb/> by it.  By way of So for example&#44; in addressing children we would not&#44; employ in<lb/> addressing children&#44; employ terms above their compre&#45;<lb/>&#45;hension&#44; so also by comparison&#44; the Bible&#44; in order to im&#45;<lb/>&#45;part Divine knowledge&#44; was compelled to materialize&#44;<lb/> so to say&#44; the Omnipresent&#44; whose self&#45;existence is so&#45;<lb/>&#45;lely and purely spiritual.  Moses who stood nearer<lb/> to God than any mortal being&#44; notwithstanding his<lb/> having necessarily described the Creator as hearing and an&#45;<lb/>&#45;swering&#44; descending and ascending&#44; reproving and praising<lb/> and in various other manners&#44; all material&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>cautioned warned us strenuously solemnly nevertheless against entertaining the idea that God<lb/> can be represented under any form.  To our ancestors&#44;<lb/> prone to idolatry&#44; he thus gave warning gave admonition spoke before his depar&#45;<lb/>&#45;ture from earth&#58; &#34;Be exceedingly heedful of for your souls sake&#44;<lb/> for you did not see any likeliness on the day that<lb/> the Lord spoke to you in Horeb from the midst of<lb/> the fire&#44;&#34; meaning&#44; you shall take assiduous diligent care not to represent God<lb/> materially.  Because the son of Amram alone could rise to<lb/> a full comprehension of Him&#44; whom the hearer of<lb/> heavens cannot hold&#44; hence the figurative expression is used<lb/> &#34;there never arose a prophet in Israel like Moses&#44;<lb/> whom the Lord knew face to face&#34;; He signifying he alone communed<lb/> with the Deity&#44; while in the full possession of<lb/> his sensations and faculties.  Not so other prophets.<lb/>  The vision of the Supreme overpowered their whole being<lb/> so entirely&#44; that they lost a consciousness of their<lb/> surroundings and&#44; for a time&#44; remained as if bereft of<lb/> their senses.  Thus of Ezekiel we read that he felt<lb/> completely overcome and Daniel relates that for se&#45;<lb/>&#45;veral days he remained&#44; as if sunk into a state of<lb/> bewilderment.  At times&#44; it happened that the vision<lb/> appeared in a dream at night&#44; clothed in imageries&#44;<lb/> illustrating the subject to be employed as a threat&#44;<lb/> exhortation&#44; or admonition correction.  Of that&#44; the book<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>of Zechariah supplies examples.<lb/></p>
            <p>But the distinction between the archprophet and his<lb/> others among our Seers is nowhere so forcibly stated&#44; as on<lb/> the occasion&#44; when Aaron and Miriam&#44; for reasons not defi&#45;<lb/>&#45;nitely stated known set forth&#44; disparaged their brother&#39;s character.<lb/>  They had boasted of being endowed with the same powers&#44;<lb/> without sharing&#44; what they termed hinted at&#44; his assumption&#44; and they<lb/> received a humiliating rebuke in the following sentence&#58;<lb/> &#34;Hear now my words&#44; if there be a prophet among you&#44; I&#44; the<lb/> Lord&#44; will make myself known unto him in a vision&#59; I<lb/> will speak unto him in a dream.  Not so My servant<lb/> Moses&#59; he is faithful in all My house&#44;&#34; namely&#44; he is<lb/> like the confidential friend of a King&#44; from whom nothing<lb/> possible to be granted is withheld&#44; because implicit trust<lb/> is reposed in him.  So our sages comment on that passage.<lb/>  Every part of the royal mansion stands lies open to his inspection.<lb/>  Brethren.  According to my mode of thinking&#44; the above stands<lb/> as a most striking proof of the profound sanctity of Mosaic tenets.<lb/>  It tells every Jew how binding the teachings of Moses the Torah must<lb/> be deemed&#44; and how determinedly a refusal must be given<lb/> to any instruction clashing therewith.  For&#44; as to none can<lb/> be accorded a clearer conception of God&#39;s will&#44; none can claim<lb/> superiority to him&#44; who was declared the greatest.  Penetrated<lb/> by that verity&#44; the Psalmist so wrote concerning the statutes&#58;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;They are established for ever and<lb/> ever&#44; they are made enacted with truth and righteousness.&#34;  And such<lb/> was the belief our of our illustrious deepest thinkers&#44; fo from Saadia of<lb/> the ninth century to Mendelssohn of the last century namely&#44;<lb/> that laws whose performance is not connected with a national<lb/> residence in Palestine &#91;Hebrew&#93; are still obliga&#45;<lb/>tory upon the house of Israel.<lb/></p>
            <p>But a few weeks ago&#44; conversing with some Jewesses who<lb/> are by no means cavillers&#91;sic&#63;&#93;; women who go in search of sight on Judaism&#44;<lb/> I was met with an objection&#44; which seems strongly founded.<lb/>  Those sisters in faith of mine admitted the ligation of Moses &#38; its authority&#44;<lb/> but they could not explain satisfactorily to themselves how<lb/> his instruction Pentateuchal teachings could reach the tribes.  They argued&#58; the total<lb/> number of those taught instructed must by far have exceeded a million.<lb/>  Seeing that to settle disputes rising among the people&#44;<lb/> the archprophet was compelled to choose coworkers How<lb/> could the archprophet he impart to every individual ordinances Divinely<lb/> received&#63;  The question does appear weighty&#44; yet in reality<lb/> it is not so.  It can easily be solved.  In most instances&#44;<lb/> the teaching was conveyed by means of accredited representatives.<lb/>  Who they were&#44; Holy Writ has intimated on many an oc&#45;<lb/>&#45;casion.  I will cite only one for brevity sake&#59; that will<lb/> serve as a criterion.  Moses was directed to prepare<lb/> the people&#39;s mind to rece for the delivery of the Decalogue&#45;&#45;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>&#34;so saying to the house of Jacob&#44; and telling the children of Israel.&#34;<lb/>  &#34;Ye have seen what I did unto the Egyptians&#44; and how I bore<lb/> you on eagles&#39; wings and brought you unto Myself.  Now&#44;<lb/> therefore&#44; if you will obey My voice indeed and keep My<lb/> covenant&#44; ye shall be unto me a peculiar fol treasure and<lb/> a kingdom of priests unto the above all people&#44; though all the earth is mine&#44; but<lb/> you shall be unto Me a kingdom of priests and a holy<lb/> nation.  These are the words which thou shalt speak unto the<lb/> children of Israel&#34;.  But immediately after&#44; we are informed<lb/> that in descending from the mountain &#34;Moses called the<lb/> elders of the people and laid before them all the words<lb/> which the Lord had commanded him.&#34;  Then follows&#58; &#34;And all<lb/> the people answered together and said&#58; &#34;All that the Lord<lb/> hat spoken we will do&#34;.  The elders were then&#44; evidently<lb/> the intermediate agency between the leader and the vast<lb/> multitude.  As in Egypt those noted for wisdom and<lb/> learning&#44; formed a distinct class&#44; so did the most eminent<lb/> among the Hebrews constitute the medium&#44; through which<lb/> the mission of freeing the enslaved&#58; &#34;Go and gather<lb/> the elders of Israel.&#34;  It was so&#44; when Moses and Aaron<lb/> first presented themselves to the children bondmen<lb/> in the name of the God of the patriarchs...&#34;They<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>went and gathered all the elders of Israel.&#34;  That<lb/> the elders were distinguished from all others among the tribes&#44; is obviously<lb/> informed from the fact that at the meal prepared<lb/> in honor of Jethro&#44; they sat by the side of a senate&#45;&#45;a word<lb/> derived from Senis&#44; meaning old&#45;&#45;who helped to disseminate<lb/> the knowledge of the Torah.  They formed the links of<lb/> that chain &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; which&#44; proceeding from the<lb/> great legislator&#44; reached the humblest in Israel.  The<lb/> elders became the subordinate teachers directed by the<lb/> highest master.  We meet them in every stage of Bi&#45;<lb/>&#45;blical history.  From the dark days of Egyptian ser&#45;<lb/>&#45;vitude&#44; to brighter times at the return from the Ba&#45;<lb/>&#45;bylonian captivity they &#91;Hebrew&#93; bore a distinctive appellation.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Admit&#59; not always were they entitled<lb/> to universal respect for their an unswerving fidelity to their<lb/> charge&#44; but they always formed constituted a cas class prominent<lb/> for their influence.  I imagine that I do not presume<lb/> too much&#44; when I assert that the Sanhedrin of the second<lb/> Temple&#44; were but a reproduction or rather a continuation of an assemblage of<lb/> learned&#44; that had ever existed among the people of God.<lb/>  When I consider how&#44; notwithstanding the frequent relap&#45;<lb/>&#45;sing of Israel into idolatry&#44; that wonderful book which is our peculiar heritage was<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>preserved&#44; I see with my mind&#39;s eye the followers successors<lb/> of that body of sages&#44; who during forty years imbibed<lb/> truth from the sevenfold purified lips of the archprophet&#59;<lb/> I see our elders treasuring up what others had&#44; in their<lb/> infatuation&#44; cast aside&#44; as valueless.  They covered the<lb/> holy Torah&#44; with an invulnerable shield&#44; that it might<lb/> not be scathed.  The elders of Israel&#44; so called so not<lb/> necessarily because by reason of their advanced age&#44; but because<lb/> of their staid wisdom and gravity of manners&#44; supposed<lb/> to be the characteristic of the old&#59; the elders of Israel&#44;<lb/> aided by priests and levites&#44; stood at the breach and<lb/> prevented the inroad of false notions into the sacred<lb/> ground of Judaism.  Thanks and praises to<lb/> them and their legitimate disciples&#44; the Rabbis of<lb/> the Mishnah and Talmud.  The hedge which the lat&#45;<lb/>&#45;ter set around the Law may have been pointed and sharp&#44;<lb/> yet it proved our salvation.  When the blandishment of<lb/> egotism gentilism or modern liberalism would have lured us away&#44; we found<lb/> ourselves surrounded by a fence hindering our exit.  &#34;We<lb/> cannot come over&#44; brother Grecianist.&#34;  We cannot leap<lb/> across&#44; brother ethic&#45;culturist.  We cannot reach your<lb/> camp&#44; brother Unitarian.  Our superiors have set us to<lb/> watch the garden.  To desert our past&#44; is to meet fearful dan&#45;<lb/>gers.&#34;  Thus Brethren&#44; have we been preserved during vicissitudes which<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p><sic>which</sic> would have swept away the mightiest<lb/> nations.  Little foxes&#44; &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; to use the<lb/> language of the book of Canticles&#44; little foxes try&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing to destroy the vineyard which the Lord of hosts<lb/> planted&#44; did not and will not succeed.  Moses&#44; the<lb/> prophets and the sages of Israel will sound the alarm<lb/> and ward off the evil. &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; Devise projects&#44; ye opponents of the Torah they will come to naught&#44;<lb/> give forth make speeches&#44; they will avail nothing&#44; for God is with<lb/> the defenders of His word.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
