<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF2_9b</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_9_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_9_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_9_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_9_8v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_9_9r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_9_9v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_9_10r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_9_10v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_9_11r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_9_11v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_9_12r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_9_12v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_9_13r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_9_13v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_9_14r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_9_14v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_9_15r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_9_15v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_9_16r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_9_16v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>20 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>26</p>
            
            <p>What a vast difference exists&#44; my dear brethren&#44; between the<lb/> law of the living God and that of perishable men.  That<lb/> of the latter <sic>weilds</sic> a sword which is ready to strike the<lb/> offender&#44; but the ordinance of the Lord are preventives against<lb/> the committal of offence.  The one hews down with its<lb/> might&#44; the branches of the tree&#44; which bear poisonous fruit&#44;<lb/> the other watches the root with peculiar care&#44; so that<lb/> its shoots may grow healthily.  The law of man provides<lb/> that no individual should with impunity disturb the harmony<lb/> of the social compact&#44; but the law of God early trains the<lb/> individual to live in peace with all his fellow&#45;beings.<lb/>  This truth will appear very obvious to you&#44; when you reflect<lb/> on the injunction laid down in the thirty first chapter of<lb/> Deuteronomy.  There we read that the people of Israel were<lb/> ordered&#44; that at the Sabbatical year&#44; when they went to<lb/> seek the Eternal&#44; in the place where his glory dwelt&#44; they<lb/> should conduct with themselves their little ones&#44; that they<lb/> also might learn from the mouth of his chosen servants<lb/> the principles of rectitude.  That this practice<lb/> was calculated to mould the young minds in a fashion<lb/> consonant with the tuition received&#44; is very evident&#59;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>for&#44; we all know that early impressions strike in a deep<lb/> root&#44; and more especially so&#44; when derived from circumstances<lb/> attended with striking solemnity.<lb/></p>
            <p>And what&#44; my dear friends&#44; could be more imposing than to have<lb/> seen myriads of human beings&#44; from various cities of Palestine&#44;<lb/> throng the metropolis&#44; to hear the highest authority in the<lb/> nation &#40;for according to tradition the duty devolved on the king&#41; ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;plain the law of God&#44; and avow himself subordinate to its will&#63;<lb/>  How must his words have thrilled in every heart&#44; when he&#44; who<lb/> was raised above his brethren&#44; proclaimed that there is but one<lb/> God&#44; and one immutable law&#63;  What a beneficial influence<lb/> must that early lesson have exercised over his young listeners&#44;<lb/> if followed by a well directed parental education&#33;  Whatever<lb/> they beheld&#44; tended to excite feelings of reverence for their religion.<lb/>  The grandeur of the Temple&#44; the devotion of the <sic>worshippers</sic>&#44;<lb/> the dignity of the speaker&#44; must have inspired them with<lb/> a noble pride for the name of Israel&#44; which they bore&#44; and<lb/> for the heavenly trust which they also would one day be<lb/> summoned to discharge.  But now&#44; my friends&#33;<lb/> that the glory of the past has departed&#44; and we can no longer<lb/> make our young offspring partakers of the spiritual knowledge<lb/> dispensed by the elect of God in his holy sanctuary&#44; what have<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>we in substitution thereof&#63;  We convey our children to the house<lb/> of prayer&#44; but alas&#33; when there&#44; neither their minds nor their<lb/> demeanour is at all improved thereby.  The language in which the law<lb/> of God is read&#44; is not their vernacular tongue&#44; so that the dictates&#44;<lb/> the admonitions&#44; the exhortations therein contained&#44; sound un&#45;<lb/>&#45;meaning to their ears.  They then naturally grow weary&#44; and<lb/> contrive to divert their minds&#44; not by perusing the translation<lb/> of that which their minister recites&#44; but by engaging in a<lb/> conversation&#44; and by disturbing the public worship as they repeatedly quit<lb/> or return to&#44; the Synagogue.  It is time dear Brethren&#44; that we<lb/> should reform this evil&#44; that glaringly exists among us&#59; and<lb/> the means are in our power.  Let the parents imbue<lb/> their children with due regard for the house of prayer&#44; enforcing<lb/> their tuition by example&#44; and their deportment there&#44; will be<lb/> decorous&#44; let them initiate their little ones in the knowledge<lb/> of the sacred tongue&#44; and they will improve so well by attending<lb/> to a correct reading&#44; that the desire of becoming familiar<lb/> with its signification&#44; as well as with its recital&#44; will grow<lb/> spontaneously.  But the ministers must also<lb/> aid the parents in rendering the Synagogue a place of moral<lb/> enjoyment for the young.  Let them occasionally<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>address the latter in a manner adapted to their comprehension.<lb/>  Let them not disdain to couch their diction in an unadorned form&#44;<lb/> so that it might be accessible to the untutored youth&#44; let<lb/> them remember the maxim of our Sages&#44; and be gratified by the<lb/> certainty that they will &#91;&#63;&#93; more benefit by occasion more good through a course<lb/> so simple&#44; than by the display of great erudition.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;Short and easy must be the instruction imparted<lb/> to young pupils.&#34;  In pursuance of this Rabbinical<lb/> direction and with the view of enlisting the attention of the<lb/> junior portion of this Congregation&#44; I have prepared for this<lb/> morning a few remarks which I have likewise endeavoured to elucidate<lb/> by Biblical facts.  In the hope that my labour may have not<lb/> been altogether be spent in vain&#44; I shall with no farther delay&#44;<lb/> commence my discourse.<lb/></p>
            <p>My dear young friends&#33;  A feeling which we cannot<lb/> sufficiently loathe and which most prevails among children<lb/> is Envy  This detestable passion&#44; like so many others&#44;<lb/> develops itself gradually&#59; till it grows gigantically and<lb/> drags man into vice and crime.  If we once cherish it&#44;<lb/> if we once allow it to harbour in in our bosom&#44; we become<lb/> its slaves&#59; and it is but seldom that we can free ourselves<lb/> from it.  Two brothers have been blessed with<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>kind parents&#44; who strenuously exert themselves to rear them in<lb/> the love and fear of God.  One of these youths responds to their an&#45;<lb/>&#45;xious cares&#44; by unremitting study&#44; by strictly adhering to their<lb/> bidding&#44; by never allowing himself to contradict their words.<lb/>  The other on the contrary&#44; chooses a different course&#44; is careless&#44; sulky<lb/> and spurns the admonitions of his parents&#44; so that whilst the<lb/> latter lavish all their fondness on the dutiful son&#44; they chide<lb/> and often chastise the disobedient one.  This inconsiderate<lb/> child misconstruing his parents&#39; conduct towards his brother&#44;<lb/> mistaking a just and well&#45;deserved affection for a partiality&#44;<lb/> conceives evil thoughts against his relative.  He envies him.<lb/>  Instead of striving to reform his own blamable demeanour&#44; and<lb/> by taking pattern from his brother&#44; endeavour to captivate the<lb/> love of his parents&#44; he acts in a manner that virtually alienates<lb/> them from him.  Stirred up the direful passion of<lb/> envy&#44; he esteems every thing lawful which may lead to the<lb/> achievement of his contemptible purposes.  Mindless of the<lb/> ties of nature&#44; deaf to fraternal love&#44; he strives to mar the<lb/> happiness of him who was intended by the Almighty as<lb/> a companion&#44; as a friend of his younger days.<lb/></p>
            <p>A dreadful instance of the mischief accruing from the indulgence<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>of the baneful passion we have in the first pages of the<lb/> Pentateuch.  Envy stimulated Cain to stain his<lb/> hands with the guiltless blood of Abel&#44; envy blended him so&#44; as<lb/> to believe that he could conceal his foul deed from the all&#45;seeing<lb/> eye of the Deity&#44; envy drew upon him the terrible indignation<lb/> of heaven.<lb/></p>
            <p>&#125;In like manner&#44; several children frequent the same school&#44; their<lb/> teacher instructs with equal zeal every one of them&#59; he guides<lb/> their tottering steps in the path of virtue&#44; he wishes to make them<lb/> youthf useful members of society.  Some give heed to his<lb/> salutary lessons and profit by them&#44; others slight his lessons<lb/> tuition&#44; and meet with the disapprobation of their instructor.<lb/>  But this which ought to be a caution to them of the wrong<lb/> they are committing&#44; which ought to open their mind&#39;s eye<lb/> to the duties that they have neglected&#44; which ought to give<lb/> rise to the noble feeling of emulation&#44; which is the precursor<lb/> of great and generous actions&#44; awakens in those obdurate child&#45;<lb/>&#45;ren the hateful feeling of envy.  Jealous of the attach&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment which their preceptor evinces towards their school&#45;<lb/>&#45;fellows&#44; of the rewards that they receive from him as a recom&#45;<lb/>&#45;pense for their laudable conduct&#44; they endeavour to injure them&#44;<lb/> regardless of the means they employ to attain their malicious object&#125;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Yet this passion so baneful&#44; so destructive by itself has&#44; when<lb/> allied to ambition&#44; no control.  With an invisible hand it lures<lb/> man to his own ruin&#59; darkens his intellect that he does not<lb/> see the pit in which he is about to fall.  It makes him run<lb/> after a shadow which recedes from him as he advances towards it&#44;<lb/> it beguiles him so&#44; that he believes he can gain happiness by<lb/> encroaching upon that of another&#44; but happiness is not the lot<lb/> of the envious&#44; or the ambitious man.  Nay&#44; &#123;he forges the weapons<lb/> which will sooner or later strike him a deadly lo blow.&#125;  Believe me&#44;<lb/> my dear young friends&#33;  The life of the envious is most wretched.<lb/>  Like the moth he whirls around the blaze which will consume<lb/> him.  He falls into it and no friendly eye sheds a tear at his<lb/> fall.  Hence in many p we are strongly warned against this<lb/> heinous passion&#44; in the following aphorism of our Sages.<lb/>  &#34;Envy&#44; wantonness and ambition wear out a man&#39;s life&#34;<lb/>  The story Some incidents in the life of Daniel to which I intend directing your attention<lb/> will illustrate my assertion.<lb/></p>
            <p>Among the captives that Nebucadnezar conveyed from our<lb/> holy land to Babylon&#44; were several&#44; who by special order of<lb/> that Sovereign were to reside in his palace&#44; and there for the<lb/> lapse of three years to remain&#44; till they had acquired skill<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>in the language of that country.  During that period they were<lb/> made the recipients of to enjoy all the luxuries of their master&#39;s table&#44; and<lb/> under the guardianship of an officer of the king&#44; every comfort was<lb/> procured for them.  But&#44; my young friends&#44; are the<lb/> comforts of life&#44; to be attained at the expense of one&#39;s religious<lb/> principles&#63;  Are the transient gratifications of the earth&#44; to be<lb/> so valued&#44; that a rational being should sacrifice to them<lb/> his everlasting felicity&#63;...These reflections which<lb/> just now strike our mind&#44; must have arisen in Daniel&#39;s<lb/> mind also&#44; when he had been selected to dwell in the<lb/> royal court.  Staunch in the precepts of our holy religion&#44;<lb/> he would not defile himself with forbidden viands&#44; but with<lb/> gentle entreaty requested the king&#39;s officer to change his<lb/> sumptuous repast for the slender diet of pulse and water.<lb/>  Daniel&#44; who of noble extraction&#44; as recorded in Holy Writ&#44; must<lb/> have been wont to sit at a luxurious table&#44; deliberately refused<lb/> it&#44; when detrimental to his religious duties.  God grant that<lb/> you may imitate his righteous example through life&#33;<lb/></p>
            <p>The novitiate of that outcast of Judea&#44; was not yet at an end&#44;<lb/> when a very strange incident summoned him before the potent<lb/> Monarch of Babylon.  An uncommon dream came to disturb<lb/> the slumber of the Autocrat.  He could obtain no rest till<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>he had learnt its interpretation.  To that effect he sends<lb/> for all his magicians and wizards who throng into his presence.<lb/>  The king speaks&#44; he wishes to make them acquainted with the<lb/> cause of his summons&#44; to relate to them the dream that had<lb/> disquieted him&#44; but alas&#33; the dream has escaped his memory.<lb/>  Exasperated at so unfavorable an occurrence&#44; that tyrant<lb/> of old&#44; seeks of them that which no man ever ventured to<lb/> ask.  He threatens them with certain death if they do not&#44; without<lb/> delay&#44; disclose to him the dream and its interpretation.<lb/>  In vain they remonstrate&#44; to no purpose they strive to call<lb/> Nebucadnezar to reason.  He has pronounced a sentence&#44; and he<lb/> will not recant.  The morrow&#39;s sun will witness a mourn&#45;<lb/>&#45;ful sight&#44; till the Sages of Chaldea are doomed to destruction.<lb/>  Helpless&#44; forlorn&#44; they are perhaps bidding a last fare&#45;well<lb/> to their dear ones.  But when every ray of hope seemed ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;tinguished&#44; the celestial Father&#44; whose endless mercy extends<lb/> to all his creatures&#44; commissioned one of his servants&#44; to<lb/> rescue those innocent lives from the imminent danger impen&#45;<lb/>&#45;ding over them.  In a vision by night&#44; the Almighty<lb/> revealed to Daniel the dream&#44; which had so much perturbed<lb/> the spirits of Nabucadnezar.  By the lips of his faithful<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p><sic>worshipper</sic>&#44; He vouchsafed to acquaint that potentate with<lb/> a series of fearful events&#44; long before they sprang forth&#59; by<lb/> the means of this noble exile&#44; he made that haughty&#45;prince<lb/> bow before his Creator&#44; he made him feel&#44; at least momentarily<lb/> that he was but crowned dust&#44; and caused him to retract his<lb/> fierce mandate.<lb/></p>
            <p>&#125;So wonderful a disclosure filled every one&#44; and above all&#44; the<lb/> Sovereign&#44; with amazement and awe.  He publicly acknowledged that<lb/> God of whom he recognized Daniel as the messenger&#44; loaded<lb/> the latter with favours&#44; and promoted him to the highest<lb/> honors&#44; to which any man could have aspired in his realm.<lb/>  But I should digress too much from my topic&#44; if I were<lb/> to trace the course of the story as narrated in the Bible&#44; I<lb/> must therefore confine myself to dwell only on those passages<lb/> which are more intimately connected with it.  Know<lb/> then&#44; my dear young friends&#44; that the reign of Nebucadnezar<lb/> was exposed to dreadful vicessitudes&#44; through which the<lb/> divine knowledge which Daniel possessed was brought into action&#44;<lb/> and his virtues conspicuously shone&#125;  After the<lb/> demise of the aforenamed King the empire devolved to his<lb/> son whom the Deity had who after a short reign bequeathed it to his successor destined by the Deity to witness its utter overthrow.<lb/>  Addicted as almost every Persian and Babylonian monarch was&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>to degrading appetites&#44; and more especially to that noxious and<lb/> brutalizing one of intoxication&#44; King Belsh&#225;zzar&#44; &#40;so he was named&#41;<lb/> one day at a banquet&#44; when the fumes of the wine in which he<lb/> had previously indulged&#44; clouded his intellect&#44; dared to desecrate<lb/> the holy vessels which adorned the Sanctuary of the Lord in Jerusalem.<lb/>  While raising profane songs to his false divinities&#44; he polluted<lb/> with his impure lips the hallowed cups of the Temple.<lb/></p>
            <p>Insane that he was thus to insult the living God&#33;  On a<lb/> sudden the king appears agitated.  This potent monarch on<lb/> whose nod the lives of millions depended&#44; trembles and shudders<lb/> with horror.  What does he dread&#63;  What can cause this pertur&#45;<lb/>&#45;bation in him&#63;  Is he not guarded by myriads of solders&#63;  Is<lb/> he not not surrounded by his nobles and princes&#63;  What earthly<lb/> power can intimidate King Belshazzar&#63;  With a fixed look his<lb/> eyes stare upon the wall.  He beholds a mysterious hand tracing<lb/> unintelligible characters.  The profound learning of his wizards<lb/> is eagerly appealed to&#44; every one awaits in great suspense the result<lb/> of their meditation.  But their wisdom this time fails them.<lb/>  Despondence reigned everywhere throughout the palace&#44; when the queen mindful who remembered<lb/> of the supernatural talents displayed by Daniel&#44; recalled them<lb/> to the mind of her lord&#44; by an emphatic description of them&#59; and caused<lb/> that illustrious Jew to be immediately brought before his presence.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>Daniel&#44; the devout adorer of the true God&#44; constant to his mission<lb/> which he would not debase&#58; through lucre&#44; rejected the rich gifts<lb/> proffered to him&#59; but invested with that moral courage which<lb/> an unflinching belief in a supreme justice can only inspire&#44; boldly<lb/> charged the Sovereign with having provoked the wrath of the Al&#45;<lb/>&#45;mighty&#44; upbraided him with having turned a deaf ear to the<lb/> lessons which the circumstances of his grand father sire&#39;s sad life had<lb/> afforded him&#59; with having followed the froward career of<lb/> Nebuchadnezzar&#44; and finally he warned him of the chastisement<lb/> hanging over him&#59; and of which the mysterious characters were<lb/> the presage.  The prophetic wisdom of Daniel became thus so un&#45;<lb/>&#45;questionable&#44; his talents repeatedly and successfully exhibited<lb/> were so universally acknowledged&#44; that they could not remain<lb/> concealed from Darius the Mede.  When Babylon was<lb/> vanquished by the armies of Persia&#44; the monarch above&#45;men&#45;<lb/>&#45;tioned&#44; sensible to the qualities which so brilliantly distinguished<lb/> Daniel&#44; raised him above all his subjects.  Hapen<lb/> Having deputed a hundred and twenty governors over his<lb/> extensive empire&#44; and three presidents at their head&#44; he chose<lb/> Daniel the hebrew exile as supreme chief of the latter.<lb/>  This remarkable token of deference aroused the direful feeling<lb/> of envy in the breasts of the courtiers of King Darius.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p>They felt indignant that an outcast should bear sway over<lb/> them.  They beheld with rage so many boons bestowed on a<lb/> stranger to their land and to their gods.  Their pride felt wounded&#44;<lb/> and they vowed never to pause&#44; until they had healed it.<lb/></p>
            <p>Daniel became then the object of their persecution.  Hearkening<lb/> solely to the advice prompting of the heinous passion which swelled their<lb/> bosoms&#44; they breathed but to see Daniel divested of the authority<lb/> which he held&#59; envy portrayed to them in fascinating colours<lb/> the gratification which the attainment of their desire would afford<lb/> them&#59; but in spite of all their endeavours&#44; their malice could<lb/> not find a fault in Daniel which may might palliate their machination.<lb/>  In their perplexity&#44; they owned it impossible to stain the his irreproach&#45;<lb/>&#45;able character. of  Yet envy never gives up her arms.  The<lb/> <sic>counsellor</sic> of iniquitous deeds&#44; she is always ready to suggest new<lb/> and more contemptible means.  And so it occurred with the enemies<lb/> of Daniel.  Despairing of injuring him by tarnishing his repu&#45;<lb/>&#45;tation&#44; they resorted to more crafty and as they intended&#44; more<lb/> hurtful measures.  And indeed had not the outstretched arm<lb/> of the Lord interposed in behalf of his pious servant&#44; he might<lb/> have become the victim of their plots.  You will be astounded<lb/> when you hear of the manner in which they sought to<lb/> gain their object.  You will be astounded&#44; for thanks to an<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="14"/>
            <p>all&#45;wise Providence&#44; we live in times&#44; when the knowledge<lb/> of a Divine Creator has spread its beneficial influence over<lb/> a vast portion of the globe&#44; and wrought wonderful changes<lb/> in the opinions and habits of man&#44; but in the time when our<lb/> story happened&#44; the grosses ignorance on religion prevailed among<lb/> nations.  Profane histories are replete with instances when<lb/> Kings grown proud of their success in battle&#44; or puffed up<lb/> with health&#44; claimed of their subjects the homage paid due only to their<lb/> God.  This custom which would seem sacreligious1 in the<lb/> present age&#44; existed and in full vigour amongst the Persians&#44;<lb/> and it was that which supplied the enemies of Daniel with<lb/> the weapons by which they purposed to strike the blow.<lb/>  They made their appearance before Darius and disguising their<lb/> aim under the cloak of a deep&#45;felt reverence for their sovereign&#44;<lb/> prompted the latter to sign a decree that&#44; forbid any one&#44; under<lb/> the penalty of being devoured by lions&#44; to offer supplications during<lb/> thirty days either to God or man&#44; except to Darius the King.<lb/>  The edict was promulgated&#44; and all the subjects of that vast empire<lb/> obeyed the command.  But not so Daniel.  Although conscious<lb/> that he was forfeiting his life&#44; he&#44; three times every day&#44; spread his<lb/> hands towards heaven&#44; and to the Almighty poured forth his<lb/> prayers.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="15"/>
            <p>Daniel on the verge of a peril which he might have averted&#44; by<lb/> neglecting for a short period an outward expression of adoration to God&#44;<lb/> forbore making the omission of it the implement of his salvation.<lb/>  But do you know&#44; my dear young friends&#44; what afforded Daniel so<lb/> much fortitude as to intrepidly face death&#63;  A true sense of his religious<lb/> duties.  Because he loved God with all his heart&#44; he would not suffer<lb/> any human reason to intervene between him and the performance of<lb/> his duties&#44; as an Israelite&#59; because he loved him with all his soul&#44;<lb/> he welcomed set no value on riches and honors of no value so that he might speak<lb/> the truth undauntedly before the rulers of the earth&#59; because he<lb/> loved him with all his might&#44; he cheerfully jeopardized his existence&#44;<lb/> to teach man that the death of the body is preferable to sacrilege<lb/> and impiety.  Such an adoration Daniel offered to the Almighty&#44; and<lb/> such it behooves every one of you to imitate.  Your faith may not be tried<lb/> so severely&#44; but you will have during life many difficulties to<lb/> surmount&#44; many temptations to conquer.  Be then&#44; my dear young<lb/> friends as Daniel&#44; unflinching in your belief&#59; between the sacrifice<lb/> of terrestrial good and the dereliction of your religion&#44; choose always<lb/> the former&#44; be as our Rabbins teach us &#34;As swift as an eagle<lb/> as strong as a leopard&#44; and as courageous as a lion&#44; to perform<lb/> the will of our Father that is in heaven&#34;.  &#91;&#63;&#93;<lb/></p>
            <p>But the life of Daniel was too precious in the sight of his God&#44; that<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="16"/>
            <p>He should deliver it a prey to raging envy.  The prophetic spirit<lb/> with which He had endued him&#44; was reserved to foretell wonderful<lb/> events that concerned the future of mighty kingdoms and formi&#45;<lb/>dable nations.  His inspired words were destined to keep alive during<lb/> a long captivity the flame of hope in the life of afflicted Israel&#59;<lb/> he was to supply frail mortals with a staunch prop in the<lb/> trials of life by the picture of an everlasting happiness.  &#34;And<lb/> they that be wise shall shine as the brightness of the firmament<lb/> and they that turn many to righteousness&#44; as the stars&#44; for ever<lb/> and ever&#34;  His mission upon earth was not yet fulfilled&#59; and<lb/> what human power could thwart the decree of the Omnipotent&#63;<lb/>  His inveterate foes surprised him whilst <sic>worshipping</sic> the Lord impeached him before the King Darius demanded<lb/> the consummation of the mandate he had issued&#44; saw the<lb/> object of their hatred cast in a den of lions&#44; rejoiced already at<lb/> their success&#44; but He who had endowed Samson with strength<lb/> to overcome the lion ready to rend him&#44; He who had spared<lb/> the life of the sweet Psalmist of Israel from the ravenous<lb/> mouths of a lion and of a bear&#44; tamed the ferocity of those<lb/> insatiable animals and preserved his pious servant unscathed.<lb/>  At the break of the day which followed the execution of the sentence<lb/> pronounced against Daniel&#44; the king whose sleep had the previous<lb/> night been broken by remorse&#44; speedily repaired the to the cave den.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="17"/>
            <p>Arrived there&#44; he uttered in a doleful tone the name of Daniel&#44;<lb/> whom he dearly loved.  What was his surprise and joy&#44; when<lb/> he beheld him unhurt among terrific beasts&#33;  Struck with<lb/> deep awe for the author of that miraculous deed&#44; he publicly<lb/> avowed his blessed name&#44; acknowledged Daniel the faithful messenger<lb/> of the living God&#44; and restored him to his former station.<lb/></p>
            <p>But Oh&#33; what a different fate befell the envious accusers&#33;  We<lb/> shrink with horror whilst narrating the chastisement which<lb/> Darius inflicted upon them.  The heavy doom they had<lb/> devised against Daniel was awarded to them&#44; to their wives and<lb/> children.  Those impious men who goaded by the baneful passion<lb/> of envy sought to injure their fellow&#45;creature&#44; drew not alone<lb/> upon themselves and but also upon their dear relatives a fierce<lb/> punishment.  Envy stirred them to deprive of his life a guiltless<lb/> man&#44; and they beheld&#44; alas their &#91;&#63;&#93; their own flesh and blood<lb/> share with them the retribution of their own perversity.  They<lb/> spread a net&#44; and their feet were caught in the net which they<lb/> had spread.  Yet let us not rejoice at it&#44; my dear young friends&#33;<lb/>  Is let not the fall of the sinner gladden our hearts&#44; let us rather<lb/> bemoan it.  We must abhor sin&#44; but pity the sinner&#44; yes&#44; we<lb/> must pity him the more&#44; for he is truly unhappy&#44; since he has<lb/> called down upon his head the anger of the Lord.  Would you<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="18"/>
            <p>entertain an ill&#45;feeling against one of your school&#45;mates<lb/> whose sluggishness and negligence in his studies had exposed<lb/> him to the rub rebuke of his teacher&#63;  Would you not rather avert<lb/> it from him&#44; by advising him to relinquish his indolent habits&#44;<lb/> by helping him in acquiring learning&#63;  In like manner&#44; we<lb/> must not&#44; my beloved ones&#44; harbour an ill&#45;feeling against<lb/> our sinful brother&#44; but animated with love for that unfor&#45;<lb/>&#45;tunate&#44; we must endeavour to withdraw him from sin&#44; to<lb/> supply him with our counsel&#44; to warm his mind and soul<lb/> with the sacred fire of our holy religion.  If he desists from his<lb/> wicked doings&#44; you will experience a joy&#44; which no material pleasure<lb/> can equal&#44; you will feel the ineffable gratification of having<lb/> redeemed his soul from destruction.  If he persists refractorily<lb/> you will raise your eyes towards heaven&#44; and earnestly solicit<lb/> the mercy of God upon your sinful brother.<lb/></p>
            <p>But let not your heart whilst praying for the sinner&#44; exult at<lb/> your own righteousness&#44; remember that &#34;sin lieth at the door&#34; and<lb/> that frequently it will seize us unawares.  Remember&#44; and this<lb/> I must reiterate ere I conclude&#44; remember that no sin is so<lb/> seductive as envy.  It commences sometimes in the innocent<lb/> desire of bettering one&#39;s condition&#44; but if we are not on the<lb/> alert&#44; it will so obscure our intellect as to lead us to the way<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="19"/>
            <p>of crime&#44; aye&#44; to fraudulence and theft.  Avoid it&#44; my beloved<lb/> young hearers&#33; emulate the good and the virtuous&#44; but envy none.<lb/>  Strive with lawful means to raise your position&#44; but if your efforts<lb/> are abortive&#44; prefer an humble station&#44; to a higher one acquired<lb/> by <sic>subtelty</sic> and deceit.  Believe what experienced men have said&#44;<lb/> that happiness is not the lot of the rich and powerful&#44; but of him<lb/> who is contented with the little he possesses&#44; remember the maxim<lb/> of our Rabbins and act accordingly.  &#34;Envy&#44; wantonness and ambi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion wear out a man&#39;s life&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            <p>Our Sovereign and our Lord&#33;  In the hour of affliction we<lb/> turn our eyes towards Thee and receive consolation.  Thou<lb/> art the fountain of all good&#44; and good alone can proceed<lb/> from Thee.  When Thou givest and when Thou takest away&#44;<lb/> it is for our eventual happiness.  We frail mortals may<lb/> not discover how the trials to which humanity are exposed<lb/> are as decree of Thy wisdom&#44; and as we smart beneath<lb/> them&#44; we may even pray that they should be removed&#44;<lb/> but Thou knowest when to grant and when to refuse.<lb/>  God&#33; from the beginning Thou didst assign a place and<lb/> a power to every element of nature&#44; and through them<lb/> Thy mercy and Thy justice are visibly shown.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="20"/>
            <p>When the earth&#44; irrigated by a timely rain&#44; brings forth her<lb/> increase to the inhabitants of the universe world&#44; when the air that<lb/> they breathe refreshes and revives them&#44; when fire is subservient<lb/> to their will&#44; it is the light of Thy countenance that shines<lb/> upon them.  But when the earth becomes as iron and the heavens<lb/> above as brass&#44; when they inhale pestilential air and fire devours<lb/> their wealth&#44; then it is justice that exacts her due.<lb/></p>
            <p>Omnipotent Being&#33;  Thy ways are too recondite for human<lb/> investigation&#44; a mist of ignorance dims our minds and<lb/> we cannot penetrate them.  Oh&#33; could it fling aside&#44;<lb/> we would then discern the transcendence of Thy wisdom.<lb/>  But in our ignorance we commit ourselves to Thee.  Thou<lb/> wilt guide us uprightly and we shall be saved.<lb/></p>
            <p>Father&#33; restore to health the sorrowful hearts&#44; wrest from the<lb/> hand of the destroyer that weapon which has already made<lb/> some victims in our midst.  Console those who mourn<lb/> for the loss of their darling children&#44; and they that weep<lb/> for the decease of their venerable parents.  Cure them<lb/> that lie upon the couch of sickness&#44; and maintain<lb/> alive and happy those that Thy goodness has rescued<lb/> from death&#59; for Thou art a faithful Physician<lb/> and a merciful God.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
