<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF4_19</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_19_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_19_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_19_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_19_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_19_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_19_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_19_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_19_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_19_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_19_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_19_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_19_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_19_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_19_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_19_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_19_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Post Biblical<lb/>
                39<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Who was he that bared his arm to thrust back the<lb/> iron clad legions of imperial Rome in the oppressive days of Hadrian&#63;  Whence did he<lb/> come who struggled for the deliverance of his<lb/> brethren in the oppressive days of Hadrian&#44; when<lb/> Israel verged on the brink of the brink ruin&#63;  None can tell<lb/> it.  The national champion is known by a<lb/> name which a world&#45;renowned sage of his time ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;plied to him&#45;&#45;&#34;Bar Cocheb&#224;&#44;&#34; meaning in the Aramaic<lb/> language&#44; &#34;the son of the star&#34;.  To have deserved that<lb/> appellation&#44; the newly arisen defender must have shown<lb/> splendid characteristics.  It is asserted that on<lb/> seeing his stately form and daring valor&#44; Rabbi<lb/> Akiba said exclaimed &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#58; &#34;he is the star of Balaam&#39;s prediction&#44;<lb/> shooting out of the race of Jacob.&#34;  The surmise<lb/> that the hero called himself Simon&#44; has no reliable<lb/> foundation&#59; more plausible is the theory that &#34;Bar<lb/> Koziba&#34;&#44; as the Talmudists often style him&#44; was <lb/>not a term of contempt reproach&#44; signifying&#44; &#34;the son of lies&#44;&#34;<lb/> but that such was possibly his real name.<lb/>  Now&#58; setting aside as improbable much of what has<lb/> been written by Jewish and Greek authors regarding that<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>extraordinary personage&#44; it cannot never&#45;<lb/>&#45;theless be denied that he must have possessed an<lb/> irresistible magnetism in his looks and speech nature.<lb/>  Warriors sprung up almost instantaneously at<lb/> his summons&#59; myriads of patriots rallied round<lb/> his banner&#44; eager to measure arms again with<lb/> despotic Rome.  Rufus was the com&#45;<lb/>&#45;mander whom Hadrian provokingly sent to force<lb/> the <sic>Palestenian</sic> Jews to subjection submit to impious rules.  Rufus had a<lb/> hateful name&#44; recalling disasters.  But this<lb/> one deepened the wound which others bearing his<lb/> appellation had opened.  The Rufus of Hadrian<lb/> occupies a prominent part in Talmudist legends&#44;<lb/> because of his subtle arguments with which he<lb/> fancied that he might perplex our Sages.  But<lb/> more than for his cunning queries&#44; Tinnius or<lb/> Tyrannus Rufus is remembered with detestation<lb/> by reason of his shocking brutality.  The<lb/> cruelties he committed fired the hearts with a burning<lb/> indignation.  The Roman garrisons in Palestine&#44; could<lb/> not stand the outburst of wrath which found vent<lb/> into a mighty insurrection.  They quacked at its<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>uprising.  Bar Cocheba was the soul of the re&#45;<lb/>&#45;volution.  All looked upon him as the heaven ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;pointed leader&#59; as a resurrected David who would<lb/> set his throne in Zion&#44; and&#44; like his prototype&#44;<lb/> subscribe himself &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;the Messiah of the God of Jacob.&#34;<lb/>  Not alone these of his faith  considered him a being<lb/> destined to tear down the Roman Eagle and plant<lb/> the flag of a rejuvenated nationality on the top<lb/> of Moriah mountain&#44; but foreigners strangers regarded the<lb/> hero with awe&#44; and voluntarily enlisted in his army.<lb/>  The moral support he received from the most distinguished<lb/> Rabbi of his age&#44; was in itself a tower of strength.  Who<lb/> so universally revered as Akiba Ben Joseph&#63;  He<lb/> was consulted like an oracle upon the Law and tra&#45;<lb/>&#45;ditions.  The very history of his life had won for him<lb/> <sic>unequalled</sic> popularity.  A legend made the Sage<lb/> descend from a Pagan warrior&#44;&#45;&#45;Sisera the general<lb/> in chief of King Jabin&#44; who fought against by Deborah and Barak.  What<lb/> a merit to have drawn his blood from proselytes&#44; who had<lb/> washed away the impurities of heathenism&#44; and plunged<lb/> into the soul&#45;cleansing waters of Sinaic truths&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>In his early days Akiba had served the<lb/> owner of a large estate as a shepherd boy.  He grew up in the pursuit the growth&#44; and of his humble vocation&#44; and the<lb/> daughter of his rich employer had promised the youth<lb/> love as a reward for his modest virtues.  Driven<lb/> away indignantly by her father&#44; as an illiterate<lb/> boor&#44; he was not forsaken by the woman who<lb/> had vowed to him abiding affection.  Both lived<lb/> in poverty rather than seek help at the house of<lb/> the harsh parent who had unkindly disinherited his child.  The<lb/> young wife&#44; appreciating the inborn talents of her<lb/> husband&#44; urged him to leave her and go where he could<lb/> acquire learning&#44; which would secure to him celebrity.<lb/>  The legend tells that he studied twelve years and came<lb/> back with a wealth of knowledge&#44; and yet his<lb/> Rachel&#44; ambitious to ensure Akiba&#39;s preeminence&#44;<lb/> advised that he would travel still further and gain<lb/> such erudition as would might raise him above all his con&#45;<lb/>temporaries.  He finally returned gratefully to the<lb/> wife of his youth&#44; followed by a train of choice pupils disciples&#59;<lb/> to be acknowledged by his own the once harsh father in law as his su&#45;<lb/>&#45;perior&#44; whom every Israelite should honor&#44; and to whom<lb/> his rehabilitated daughter should cling with undying affection.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Now&#58; to be favored by a man who moulded religious<lb/> opinions&#44; and sat as chief in the Sanhedrin&#44; was a gain<lb/> which Bar Cocheba knew well how to value.  But<lb/> it seems to me gratuitous on the part of modern his&#45;<lb/>&#45;torians to assert that Rabbi Akiba lent his personal<lb/> aid to the warlike Messiah.  Maimonides does write<lb/> that the illustrious Sage was &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;the armor bearer of Bar<lb/> Cocheba Koziba&#44;&#34; but in all humility say that it would be difficult to find Talmudical<lb/> authority for the statement.  The Rabbi was confessedly<lb/> very aged&#44; when the insurrection broke out.  To believe&#44;<lb/> as held by some&#44; that at his time of life&#44; he could journeyed<lb/> to great distances&#44; harangued the people and mustered<lb/> them as soldiers in the national cause&#44; is to admit believe<lb/> the incredible.  That Rabbi Akiba <sic>travelled</sic>&#44; at different<lb/> periods of his life&#44; through the East Orient and also to Europe&#44;<lb/> there are strong proofs&#44; but it is unreasonable to admit<lb/> that he undertook to leave his home and his college&#44; in<lb/> the interest of the popular revolution&#44; when he had reached<lb/> his hundred and twentieth year&#44; or even a lesser age&#44; if that<lb/> be deemed an Oriental Eastern exaggeration.  Besides&#44; the<lb/> renowned Sage suffered imprisonment and martyrdom&#44; not<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>as a penalty for having been involved in<lb/> the political struggle&#44; but for having defied the ordi&#45;<lb/>&#45;nance which forbid studying and teaching the imparting teaching the Jewish<lb/> religion.  Still&#44; that the mastermind of<lb/> <sic>Palestenian</sic> schools should have applied the words<lb/> of Holy Writ to Bar Cocheba&#39;s mission&#44; sufficed<lb/> to surround it with a halo of sanctity.  Inspirited<lb/> by the prediction&#44; the insurgents marched on to victory.<lb/>  Wherever they advanced&#44; Rufus retreated.  The fearless<lb/> leader of our ancestors&#44; conquered with ease and <sic>profitted</sic><lb/> of by his conquests with moderation.  He signalized his rule by stamp&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing upon old coins new emblems typical of a res&#45;<lb/>&#45;toration to freedom.  For two years Bar Cocheba<lb/> had made Roman cohorts pale at the boldness of<lb/> his army.  Hadrian&#39;s additional forces could not<lb/> unseat him who had proclaimed himself the king<lb/> Messiah&#44; that would humble the arrogance of<lb/> tyrannic gentilism.  It is certainly a<lb/> cause of boast&#44; that while other nations were brought&#44;<lb/> with comparative ease facility&#44; under that Power which claimed<lb/> dominion over the known world&#44; the Jews compelled<lb/> Rome to employ against them the most formidable<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>hosts and the greatest generals in history.<lb/>  Pompey&#44; Caesar&#44; Vespasian&#44; Titus&#44; witnessed the<lb/> determined tenacious will of a small but resolute people&#44; and<lb/> now the emperor Hadrian felt it necessary to called Julius Severus<lb/> from distant <sic>Brittannia</sic> to come and crush the rem&#45;<lb/>&#45;nant of Israel.  Severus found Bar Cocheba<lb/> master of fifty castles and nearly one thousand vil&#45;<lb/>&#45;lages.  The Roman general did was sagacious enough not to venture there&#45;<lb/>&#45;fore on a pitched battle&#44; but with consummate<lb/> skill he harassed the Jews by a species of guerillas&#44;<lb/> cutting off small bands at a time&#44; depending on his<lb/> cavalry to prevent a flight&#44; watching every oppor&#45;<lb/>&#45;tunity to stop supplies&#44; and thus gradually bring on<lb/> great famine.  It was a long slow and wearisome war&#44; but<lb/> of sure success to him who could always fill his ranks<lb/> afresh&#44; and set against wild enthusiasm a mili&#45;<lb/>&#45;tary discipline unparalleled.  One year this<lb/> irregular warfare dragged on&#59; at length after<lb/> dire suffering on both sides&#44; it centred itself into a<lb/> town&#44; made famous in the annals of Judaism for<lb/> the noble resistance of our forefathers even in the<lb/> face of an impending and overwhelming defeat.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Bither has been topographically put in different<lb/> localities.  While some have imagined to have found discovered<lb/> its remains in a village not far from Jerusalem&#44;<lb/> others have looked for it near the coasts of the Medi&#45;<lb/>terranean.  At all events&#44; in Bither But wherever the ominous spot stood was there&#44; Jewish<lb/> independence received its final death blow.  Bar<lb/> Cocheba had hoped to send from thence the Roman legions flying<lb/> beyond the sea.  The bravest of his soldiers stood<lb/> fast by him in that last struggle&#44; and every man<lb/> was fired up for the tremendous fight.  It taxed<lb/> the military skill of a famous chief like Julius<lb/> Severus to humble to the Dust a high&#45;spirited<lb/> people&#44; sworn to die&#45;&#45;if it must&#45;&#45;sword in hand.<lb/>  Why Bither became the charnel house of a<lb/> ruined host&#44; why the hoofs of Roman horses trampled<lb/> upon the Jewish corpses&#44; and waded through rivers<lb/> of Jewish blood&#44; none has ever satisfactorily cause has been learned.<lb/> assigned.  A Josephus to thrillingly describe the<lb/> fall of Bither&#44; as he had portrayed the surrender<lb/> of Jotapata and Gamala after deeds of <sic>marvellous</sic> valor&#44;<lb/> did not live in the year 135 of the common era.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Few&#44; contradictory and unreliable are the<lb/> fragments of history touching this stirring period&#44;<lb/> nor can the Talmud be always taken to the letter&#44;<lb/> in its account interspersed and varied in a diver&#45; through a variety<lb/> &#45;sity of books.  The Sages did say that not a drop<lb/> of rain came to refresh the weary <sic>combattants</sic><lb/> during a whole inauspicious summer.  Peoples<lb/> dropped dead from devouring thirst&#44; as many perished from<lb/> hunger.  It has been also intimated that treason<lb/> placed into the power of the enemy&#44; an under&#45;<lb/>&#45;ground passage through by means of which a commanding<lb/> position was gained&#44; and a bloody slaughter of<lb/> the defenceless was perpetrated.  But in truth<lb/> a veil hangs still over the scenes of horror&#44; which<lb/> culminated into the crushing of the national re&#45;<lb/>&#45;volution.  A tradition tells that the same<lb/> fatal day of the ninth of Ab&#44; which saw the<lb/> Temple reduced to ashes under Nebuchadnezzar and<lb/> under Titus&#44; beheld the fond anticipations which<lb/> the valor of Bar Cocheba had inspired&#44; rudely<lb/> scattered to the four winds.  The elegies which<lb/> observant Israelites recited on the yearly fast&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>commemorative of our past sorrows&#44; trace also in<lb/> plaintive language the butchery&#44; the shame&#44; the<lb/> torturing which attended the overthrow of Bither.<lb/>  One of the saddest incidents was the martyrdom<lb/> of Hebrew Sages which soon followed&#45;&#45;that of Rabbi<lb/> Akiba being the most heart&#45;rending because of the<lb/> illustrious teacher&#39;s far advanced age&#44; and the uni&#45;<lb/>&#45;versal reverence in which he was deservedly held.<lb/>  He had been entreated by well meaning friends<lb/> to desist imparting the Law&#44; since Hadrian had<lb/> so peremptorily ordered&#44; and the lynx eyed Rufus<lb/> would detect his doing&#44; and punish it cruelly.<lb/>  Akiba refused to listen to a counsel which he<lb/> considered treasonable to his faith.  He was inform&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed against&#44; imprisoned&#44; and condemned to have<lb/> his flesh torn with sharp&#45;pointed irons.  Rufus<lb/> looked on with fiendish pleasure&#44; but observing<lb/> that the Sage&#44; in the mist of excruciating torments&#44;<lb/> read the Shemang &#40;the declaration of God&#39;s Unity&#41;<lb/> with a placid smile upon his countenance&#44; the tyrant said&#58; &#34;Akiba<lb/> thou must be a sorcerer&#44; else there would I feel agonies.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>To which the Rabbi replied &#34;I am no magician&#44;<lb/> but I have ever been anxious to illustrate the precept<lb/> of the Law&#58; &#39;thou shalt love the Lord thy God&#44; with<lb/> all thy heart&#44; and with all thy soul and with<lb/> all thy might.&#39;  I experience now a spiritual joy<lb/> because even to my last hour I have has proved<lb/> me true.&#34;  Akiba expired uttering the words<lb/> Adonai Echad&#44; &#34;the Lord is One.&#34;  We&#44; his<lb/> fellow&#45;believers and disciples&#44; we that have survived<lb/> the brutal persecutions of Hadrian and the fall<lb/> of Bither&#44; we that have nationally remained<lb/> immortal&#44; while kings&#44; and emperors and dynasties<lb/> that aimed at our extermination have perished<lb/> from the earth globe&#44; still rejoice in the knowledge<lb/> of that One God&#44; and hope to transmit it to<lb/> the remotest ages&#44; that its verity may ultimately triumph<lb/> through the seed of Abraham&#44; by which all the<lb/> families of the earth shall be blessed.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
