<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF3_15</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_15_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_15_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_15_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_15_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_15_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_15_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_15_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_15_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_15_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_15_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_15_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_15_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Post Biblical lecture<lb/>
                15th<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  The grand son of Mattathias the As&#45;<lb/>&#45;monean&#44; is fully worthy of a golden record in the<lb/> history of Israel.  He For John Hyrcamus inherited the bravery and<lb/> administrative abilities of his predecessors.  In his charac&#45;<lb/>&#45;ter were combined the patriotism of Judah Maccabee&#44; and<lb/> the sagaciousness of his own father Simon.  When by<lb/> the treachery infamy iniquity of Ptolemy of Jericho the treacherous Jewish governor of Jericho to whom I alluded in<lb/> my last lecture of the course&#44; Judea was exposed laid open again to the<lb/> invasion&#44; of the Syrians&#44; John Hyrcamus strongly resisted<lb/> the foe foreigners.  Notwithstanding the fearful sufferings endured&#44;<lb/> he showed no disposition to surrender&#44; and leave his country<lb/> at the mercy of the foreigner heathen foe.  Still&#44; he sensibly <sic>profitted</sic> of a<lb/> circumstance to gain some respite.  The feast of<lb/> Tabernacles was drawing nigh.  Hyrcamus ventured<lb/> to ask for a suspension of arms during seven days.<lb/>  That truce would enable his people to duly celebrate<lb/> one of the three national holidays &#38; it would and afford them some rest.  Antiochus<lb/> Sidetes who had none of the fanaticism of his name<lb/>&#45;sake of former years&#44; consented.  Whether out of fear of<lb/> a remonstrance from the Roman Levite with which the<lb/> Asmoneans had a treaty&#44; or from pure kindness&#44; he did more.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>He sent rich presents of animal offerings for the<lb/> altar&#44; and objects of silver and gold for the Temple.<lb/>  Touched by this act of generosity&#44; Hyrcamus proposed to<lb/> come to terms.  He would never would agree to have a Syrian<lb/> garrison stationed in his land&#44; but rather than expose<lb/> this again to the horrors of a <sic>seige</sic>&#44; he paid a war<lb/> indemnity&#44; and remained for a time&#44; a nominal vassal<lb/> to Syria.  Shortly after&#44; Hyrcamus with deep pene&#45;<lb/>&#45;tration&#44; joined <sic>yeilded</sic> to the wish of Antiochus Sidetes and joined him in a campaign against<lb/> the Parthians&#44; who had been heretofore subject to Syria.<lb/>  On that occasion&#44; the Asmonean and his troops&#44; distinguished<lb/> themselves so notably signally&#44; that they placed their ally under<lb/> great obligations.  The keen eyed Hyrcamus turned that<lb/> to his advantage.  The following year&#44; when Antiochus<lb/> lost his life in battle&#44; the Judeans judged that the<lb/> hour glar their independence had struck.  They fought for<lb/> it liberty with severity&#44; but a determined will&#44; and gained it completely.  Syria<lb/> which&#44; at different intervals&#44; from the days of Laomedon&#44;<lb/> a general of Alexander the great Macedonian&#44; and afterwards under the<lb/> rule of Antiochus III the Great&#44; had held dominion over Palestine&#44;<lb/> lost its entire hold control altogether.  Hyrcamus pushed his victories further.<lb/>  Anxious to free his country from the annoyance of semi&#45;heathens<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>as well as of real entire heathens&#44; he directed his arms against<lb/> the Samaritans.  It is scarcely necessary<lb/> that I should explain who this people were.  The seven&#45;<lb/>&#45;teenth chapter of the second book of Kings and several<lb/> passages in Ezra and Nehemiah furnish the inform&#45;<lb/>&#45;ation.  Still&#44; it may not be considered out of place&#44;<lb/> to epitomise here their history in a few words.<lb/>  After the breaking up of the kingdom of Israel&#44; its<lb/> inhabitants were transported to Assyria&#44; and their<lb/> deserted cities were given to colonists sent over<lb/> from Assyria.  The country&#44; being thinly populated&#44;<lb/> was infested by ferocious beasts.  The new settlers<lb/> who <sic>worshipped</sic> a variety of idols&#44; and believed that each locality had they<lb/> were troubled that its local deity&#44; fancied that they which must be propitiated&#44; fancied that were <sic>trobled</sic> in that manner&#44; because they did not know how<lb/> to serve the particular god of those regions.  They<lb/> therefore petitioned the home government to let some<lb/> priests of the exiled Israelites come back&#44; and be their re&#45;<lb/>&#45;ligious teachers.  The Divine code was then in&#45;<lb/>&#45;troduced among those heathens&#44; who were called &#34;Samaritans&#34;<lb/> from Samaria&#44; the former capital of the Kingdom<lb/> of Israel&#44;. But with some of the the acceptance of a number of Mosaic commandments&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>pagan customs were still adhered to.  At the<lb/> return of the Judeans from the Babylonian captivity&#44;<lb/> the Samaritans proposed to join hands in participate in the rebuilding<lb/> of the Jerusalem Temple.  Our leaders objected.<lb/>  The Talmudists state that the image of a dove<lb/> was found discovered among those tribes.  Possibly&#44; the dove<lb/> was the symbol of the country form which they had originally<lb/> come from.  For&#44; a fable tells that Semiramis&#44; the<lb/> first queen of Assyria was nursed by doves.  That<lb/> symbol may or may not have been tendered homage to&#44;<lb/> but the heads of our nation&#44; who would not tolerate<lb/> anything savoring of idolatry&#44; opposed the alliance.<lb/>  An irreconcilable hatred arose ensued&#44; and it was intensified<lb/> by as time rolled on through the circumstance that the cities of the Samaritans<lb/> became a refuge to disaffected Jews&#44; while the Sa&#45;<lb/>&#45;maritans themselves changed side&#44; according as our<lb/> fortune changed.  At one time they proposed Mosaism&#44; at others paganism.  In the lapse of ages&#44; after<lb/> having been&#44; like ourselves&#44; persecuted by Christians&#44; the<lb/> Samaritans were cleansed from some many of their false no&#45;<lb/>&#45;tions&#44; but as they had altered the Pentateuch to suit<lb/> their own views&#44; our people generally kept them generally<lb/> at a distance.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Towards the end of the seventeenth century&#44; a learned<lb/> German&#44; Job Rudolf put to them&#44; by a letter entered into a correspondence with them&#44; and put correspondence a number<lb/> of questions&#44; which they answered in wretched Hebrew.<lb/>  They proposed alleged to have issued from the twofold tribe of Joseph&#44; and<lb/> to be the sole possessors of the genuine copy of the five books<lb/> of Moses.  By degrees they dwindled into away down into a shadow of their former selves.  About two hundred of them still live yet<lb/> in Naplus&#44; which is the ancient Shechem of the Bible&#44;<lb/> and&#44; I believe&#44; on high festivals&#44; they offer sacrifices on<lb/> Gerizim.  When Hyrcamus conquered their ancestors&#44;<lb/> they had upon that mountain a gorgeous temple&#44; in<lb/> opposition to that in Jerusalem.  The demolition of<lb/> that the said edifice&#44; and the subjugation of those who <sic>worshipped</sic><lb/> in it&#44; was a great triumph to the Jewish cause.<lb/>  No rival sanctuary would raise its spires in the land<lb/> devoted to the One only Lord.  The faithless in our<lb/> ranks could not find an asylum among our adversaries.<lb/>  But the Asmonean chief was over zealous.  Having secured<lb/> Judea against religious opponents&#44; who claimed the<lb/> same parentage&#44; he determined to rid it of political<lb/> enemies&#44; descending from one stock with Israel.<lb/>  The Edomites or Jed Idumeans&#44; whose founder was Esau&#44;<lb/> had displayed in every stage of our history&#44; an open hostility<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>against their cousins&#44; the progeny of Jacob.  They<lb/> had moreover enlarged their borders by seizing several<lb/> cities that had belonged to us.  John Hyrcamus brought<lb/> them under his power&#44; and placed before them an harsh alter&#45;<lb/>&#45;native.  They should either emigrate in a body&#44; or embrace<lb/> Judaism.  The accepted the latter&#44; simply as a shield<lb/> against banishment.  But the measures taken by to which<lb/> our ruler resorted&#44; is doubly to be doubly regretted.  First&#44; because<lb/> our religion does not favor proselytism&#59; &#38; surely and most assuredly not by<lb/> force coercion&#59; secondly&#44; because from those very Idumeans sprang<lb/> up a serpent that coiled itself round our body politic&#44;<lb/> and eventually caused our political death.  I have<lb/> reference to Herod the destroyer of the Asmonean family&#44;<lb/> and the vile hireling of Rome.  I do not remember to<lb/> have met with any Rabbinical writing in our post<lb/> biblical literature&#44; condemning John Hyrcamus for<lb/> his act.  The Sages doubtless appreciated the motives<lb/> that brought it about and looked thereupon as a dire ne&#45;<lb/>&#45;cessity.  in self defence.  Perhaps so&#44; for however we For however we may deprecate the incident&#44; none can deny For it must be acknowledged that Hyrcamus studied<lb/> may deplore it&#44; we can never deny it that Hyrcamus<lb/> with singleness of heart the welfare of his nation&#59; that he was a<lb/> studied the welfare of his nation&#44; that he was a single hearted valiant general&#44; a good ruler and not less than a true patriot&#44; and a valiant general.<lb/> patriot<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>But our Rabbis who have bestowed merited praise on<lb/> that prince and high priest of Judea for his zeal and bravery<lb/> and glorious important conquests&#44; point him out also as an illustar&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion of their saying&#44; that we dare not believe ourselves<lb/> above reproach&#44; till we have died.  Whether the achieve&#45;<lb/>&#45;ments attained&#44; finally created engendered in the son of Simon an<lb/> overweening sense of self&#45;importance&#44; or whether some<lb/> of his countrymen began to fear the effects of Church and<lb/> State authority centred in one man&#44; it is impossible to ascertain<lb/> at this distance of time.  But what happened towards<lb/> the close of the life of Hyrcamus&#44; shows that he was not<lb/> proof against ambition&#44; and but that he suffered evil counsel finally<lb/> to lead him astray.  He had made a<lb/> banquet&#44; to which he invited some of the leading members of<lb/> the Pharisees.  For the latter&#44; as I have explained in a<lb/> former lecture&#44; constituted the most numerous and popular<lb/> sect.  Having entertained these his quests sumptuously&#44; he addressed<lb/> them nearly as follows&#58; &#34;Gentlemen.  You are aware of my<lb/> intention to do what is right&#44; conformably with our<lb/> national laws.  I presume that my conduct has met<lb/> with your approval.  Nevertheless&#44; if you see aught that<lb/> seems to you unbecoming to my station&#44; or injurious to our<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>common interest&#44; I will be thankful for your corrections<lb/> and suggestions&#33;  The distinguished company answered<lb/> that they were satisfied with the course he had followed&#44;<lb/> and that his personal virtues challenged respect.  Hy&#45;<lb/>&#45;canus looked happy.  But suddenly a voice was heard<lb/> to spoke thus&#58; &#34;Sire&#44; since thou wishest to hear but the<lb/> truth&#44; I will say that hear this.  Thou shouldst not <sic>weild</sic> the scepter<lb/> and wear the mitre.  Leave the priesthood to the seed of<lb/> Aaron.&#34;  All turned with astonishment to the bold speaker.<lb/>  Hyrcanus insisted upon knowing for what reason he<lb/> ought to relinquish the ministry at the altar.  The<lb/> answer was indeed offensive.  It cast doubts on the legiti&#45;<lb/>&#45;macy of the prince&#39;s birth.  A prominent member of<lb/> the sect of the Saducces the sect the antagonistic to the Pharisees&#44; and who may have been the insti&#45;<lb/>&#45;gator of the unfortunate occurrence&#44; added fuel to the fire.<lb/>  He urged Hyrcanus to demand justice at the hands of<lb/> the Pharisees themselves as a test of their sentiments ideas of the gravity of the crime.  The Sanhedrin condemned<lb/> the accuser him who the person who had aspersed the character of the mother of the high Pontiff to suffer imprisonment and stripes.  But this<lb/> penalty was not considered a sufficient separation.<lb/>  On the contrary&#44; it its moderation was interpreted as a connivance<lb/> at the insult&#59; as a screening of the offender.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Wounded in his pride&#44; Hyrcanus after nearly<lb/> thirty years of a pious life&#44; in the service of<lb/> the largest multitudes of his people&#44; abandoned<lb/> the Pharisees&#44; and declared himself in favorable to of the<lb/> Saducees.  A fatal error&#44; pregnant with evil<lb/> consequences.  These did not become manifest during<lb/> the last days of him that consulted it.  The brilliant<lb/> career and noble of the son of Simon prevented his spared him<lb/> a sorrowful end.  We shall see&#44; however&#44; how<lb/> his severance from those who had stood by his side in the days of national trials and<lb/> had loved him well in the days of national trials&#44; worked<lb/> injury&#44; when the successors of the last Asmonean<lb/> worthy of that name&#44; became rulers in Judea.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
