<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF2_6</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_6_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_6_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_6_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_6_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_6_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_6_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_6_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_6_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_6_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_6_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_6_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_6_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_6_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_6_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_6_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_6_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>14 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>On penitence<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  The section of the Sabbath&#44; preceding Rosh<lb/> hashan&#225;&#44; was suggestive of momentous thoughts.<lb/>  I felt prompted therefore to offer to view&#44; those which<lb/> I deemed best calculated to spiritually benefit my<lb/> congregation.  But the lesson imparted&#44; reached<lb/> only a few.  The attendance happened on that day<lb/> to be unusually sparse.  This circumstance&#44; elicited<lb/> a request that I would repeat my sermon&#44; on the<lb/> present occasion.  After due consideration&#44; I respect&#45;<lb/>&#45;fully declined to comply with the wish expressed by some<lb/> of my appreciative audiences.  Nevertheless&#44; I judge<lb/> that a cursory mere exposition of the remarks ideas then set forth&#44;<lb/> will not be inopportune.  My brevity will prevent I will thus guard against<lb/> a trespassing on the patience of those who heard the<lb/> entire discourse&#44; while a mere stricture thereto&#44; will I acquaintance others that who were absent&#44;<lb/> suffice the intelligent. with the purport thereof.  Lend me then your kind<lb/> attention.  A perusal of the inspired admonitions<lb/> given towards the end of his career&#44; by the man who<lb/> had educated a whole generation&#44; had impressed me deeply.<lb/>  I behold the besetting sin of this age&#44; mirrored it were<lb/> in his parting words&#44; and sought the aid of the latter&#44;<lb/> in my eagerness to correct the former.  That sin&#44;<lb/> my friends&#33; is the denial of three cardinal points<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>in the religion of Israel&#44; namely&#58; divine providence<lb/> bestowed alike on individuals as on nations&#59; the return<lb/> of the chosen people to absolute independence in the<lb/> patriarchal land&#44; and the permanence of the ceremonial<lb/> as well as the moral laws of the Mosaic code.<lb/></p>
            <p>The arguments which I advanced to strengthen my fellow&#45;<lb/> Israelites in the belief of special Providence&#44; were drawn<lb/> from a single expression of the heaven&#45;directed legislator.<lb/>  He had previously asserted&#44; that the estrangement from<lb/> the law by any one appertaining to the Hebrew race&#44;<lb/> would bring down a curse upon the head of the delinqunet minor&#59;<lb/> but lest a wicked soul be found that said &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;I shall have peace&#44; though I walk after<lb/> the dictates of my imagination&#34;.  My happiness is blended<lb/> with that of the Community in which I life&#59; I shall enjoy<lb/> it&#44; though I trespass against my religious obligations&#59; lest&#44;<lb/> a man might be so perverted to defy the Omniscient<lb/> God&#44; therefore the Biblical sentence concludes thus&#44;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;The Lord shall separate<lb/> him&#44; to his own hurt&#44; from all the tribes of Israel&#34;.<lb/>  The storm that he has raised by his iniquities&#44; shall<lb/> sweep him away&#44; the guiltless will be sheltered beneath<lb/> the wings of the Almighty Protector.  He shall<lb/> be a branch cut off from the parental tree.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>The dew shall continue to irrigate the main stock&#44;<lb/> and its healthful ramifications&#59; the sun shall still<lb/> foster its produce&#44; but their benign influence will not<lb/> be felt by the impure bough struck down by the hand<lb/> of Divine justice&#59; In other words&#58; The rod of chastisement<lb/> shall go unscathed &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  And this<lb/> fundamental principle of Judaism&#44; my beloved hearers&#33;<lb/> set upon the immoveable rock of the Sinaic revelation&#44;<lb/> is amplified&#44; commented on and illustrated in every page<lb/> written by all the great prophets of Israel.  Study the<lb/> volume that has taught mankind civilization&#44; and<lb/> this verity will be deepened into your minds&#59; viz&#44; None<lb/> can divert from him the searching eye that measures<lb/> man&#39;s steps to the end that he may be requited according to after his ways&#44;<lb/> and he may reap the fruit of his own doings &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Let not the seeming prosperity<lb/> of the wicked&#44; and the apparent misery of the righteous&#44;<lb/> deceive the believer in special Providence.  For&#44; abundant2<lb/> in mercy&#44; and slow1 to anger is3 our heavenly Maker&#59; but<lb/> &#34;though a sinner do evil a hundred times&#44; and his days be<lb/> prolonged&#44; yet surely I know that it shall be well with<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>them that fear God&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;; so exclaimed the inspired<lb/> preacher&#59; and the royal shepherd&#44; grown wise by experience&#44;<lb/> said &#34;I have seen the wicked in great power&#44; spreading<lb/> himself like a green bay&#45;tree&#44; yet he passed away&#44; and lo&#33;<lb/> he was not&#59; yea&#44; I sought him&#44; but he could not be found.<lb/>  Yet Mark the perfect man&#44; and behold the upright&#44; for the<lb/> end of that man is peace&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Now&#44; my friends&#33; with regard to the second point&#44; which<lb/> I discussed in my last address&#44; I will freely candidly acknowledge<lb/> that notwithstanding it is irrefutably established&#44; yet&#44;<lb/> I conceive that I might have better succeeded to bring conviction<lb/> home to the mind of my hearers&#44; had they been the subjects<lb/> of the Roman Pontiff&#44; or of an Arabian Sheik.  Their<lb/> hearts would then have joyfully open to my imparting&#44;<lb/> touching the declarations of the Most High that foretell<lb/> our glorious future destiny.  The testimony adduced from Jewish<lb/> annals&#44; to prove that the <sic>fulfilment</sic> of the predictions<lb/> registered in the thirtieth chapter of Deuteronomy&#44; is<lb/> still reserved for a regenerated Israel&#44; would have been<lb/> a soothing balm to our unfortunate brethren&#44; who<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>bleed under the scourge of persecution.  They who<lb/> despite the sublime deeds of the self&#45;denying Moses<lb/> of our age&#44; are still exposed to refined cruelty&#44; would<lb/> have fixed an eager look on the picture of our independence<lb/> in the heritage of Abraham&#44; which as I delineated it.  They&#44;<lb/> who in the name of a pseudo religion of peace&#44; are inhumanly<lb/> robbed of their tender offspring&#44; and compelled to see<lb/> them bend the knee to gods which our fathers feared not&#44;<lb/> would&#44; in earnest conviction&#44; have breathed a prayer for<lb/> the speedy accomplishment of God&#39;s unfailing promise.<lb/>  But I spoke to American Israelites&#44; to men&#44; long<lb/> accustomed to regard religious liberty as an inalienable birth&#45;<lb/>right&#59; for&#44; whatever may be said to the contrary&#44; this is&#44;<lb/> and will&#44; I trust&#44; eternally remain&#44; the country where<lb/> proscription by reason of one&#39;s avowed faith&#44; will never<lb/> be instituted.  My audience may have found it impossible<lb/> to rebut my arguments&#44; but I imagine that the reasoning<lb/> I employed&#44; did not impress the free&#45;men of this generous<lb/> republic&#44; as it would have penetrated the minds of the<lb/> Hebrews&#44; scattered in benighted regions.  But does<lb/> that invalidate the truth I set forth&#63;  Is God&#39;s word<lb/> to be measured by the mete&#45;yard of a finite understand&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing&#63;  Or shall we doubt it its veracity&#44; because we have<lb/> been mercifully spared the untold sorrows which its long<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>deferred <sic>fulfilment</sic>&#44; has brough on the outcasts of<lb/> Judea&#63;  Far be from us the impious thought&#33;<lb/>  As well might our ancestors who had attained the high&#45;<lb/>&#45;est honors in the Persian court&#44; have rejected the prediction<lb/> of Jeremiah&#44; that at the completion of seventy years the Lord would<lb/> grant them rest &#38; peace within the walls of Jerusalem.  Or&#44;<lb/> the Israelites&#44; who under the dominion of the Moors in<lb/> Spain&#44; <sic>weilded</sic> an almost boundless power&#44; have regarded<lb/> Moses a false prophet&#44; because he wrote &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;The Lord thy God will bring back thy<lb/> captivity&#44; and have pity on thee&#34;&#44; No&#44; they cast<lb/> their vision beyond their narrow sphere.  They beheld<lb/> millions of their fellow&#45;beings carried dragged to the slaughter&#44;<lb/> because they acknowledged a belief identical with theirs&#44;<lb/> and they felt drawn towards those unhappy ones with intensity of religious<lb/> love&#44; they felt that they were the sheep of one flock&#44; guided by<lb/> one Almighty shepherd&#59; they felt that the same final<lb/> destiny had been decried for all the seed of Jacob&#44; and&#44;<lb/> amidst the grandeur of their station&#44; they prayed in<lb/> common with their brethren &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;oh&#33; may<lb/> our eyes view again2 Zion1&#34;.  My beloved hearers&#33;  It<lb/> must be so even with us.  Grateful to the Supreme<lb/> for the enlargement of our condition&#44; we will ne&#45;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>vertheless deem consider ourselves indissolubly connected with<lb/> our coreligionists who moan in streets secluded lanes and in ghettos.<lb/>  Like them we will petition the Throne of mercy for the<lb/> end of all the tribulations endured by the residue of Israel&#44; and like them<lb/> credit the prediction vaticination that &#34;those of Judah who are scattered<lb/> abroad&#44; shall be gathered intogetherspot&#44; from the four<lb/> corners of the earth&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>  The third part of the sermon I recently delivered&#44; was<lb/> designed as a timely caution to the unwary.<lb/>  I would sought to arraign at the bar of Jewish public opinion&#44;<lb/> those&#44; who&#44; professing Judaism&#44; as derived from the Scrip&#45;<lb/>&#45;tures&#44; preach the abrogation of many of its behests.<lb/>  Shall I&#44; my friends&#33; direct now your eyes to the spot<lb/> where they are now standing&#44; who divide Israel into two hostile<lb/> camps&#63;....Thanks be to God&#33;  I search&#44; but find none<lb/> within these holy precincts.  Men stained with sin&#44; can<lb/> doubtless be pointed at in the midst of this assemblage.<lb/>  Alas&#33; my own image is reflected on the ark&#44; where the<lb/> testimony of our Lord is enshrined&#59; but the heinous crime<lb/> of seducing the simple and the untutored from their allegiance<lb/> to the Almighty&#44; does not pollute our souls.  We may<lb/> have violated biblical commands&#44; to gratify our appetites.<lb/>  Bedimmed by the passions&#44; our mind could may perhaps have no longer<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>perhaps distinguished between the pure and the impure&#59;<lb/> but the arrogant thought that to disregard the injunctions<lb/> of our legislator&#44; is to rise above prejudice and bigotry&#44;<lb/> was not harbored by any of us.  In fact&#44; how could<lb/> we pronounce such a heresy and remain within the fold<lb/> of Judaism&#63;  If Who cannot perceive that if the code of Moses may be abrogated<lb/> in some of its parts&#44; who will warrant us against there will exist no security from<lb/> the violation of the remaining portion&#63;  If&#45;&#45;by way of illustration&#44;&#45;&#45;the change<lb/> wrought in our political condition&#44; exonerates us from<lb/> abiding by the dietary laws&#44; why may we not be also<lb/> exempt from the observance of the Sabbath&#63;  Will not<lb/> the same process of reasoning lead us directly to the conclusion&#44;<lb/> that to hallow the day set apart by the majority<lb/> of our fellow&#45;citizens&#44; would best suit our present<lb/> state and social relations&#63;  Brethren&#33;  Verily&#44; the<lb/> effect of the theory now propounded from some of<lb/> our pulpits&#44; is too mournful to contemplate.<lb/>  It would&#44; if successful&#44; reduce our ancestral faith creed to<lb/> an indefinable myth&#44; which every one could construe<lb/> as most consonant with his own wild crotchets and strange<lb/> vagaries.  Let those who have cast off the fear of<lb/> the Lord&#44; follow that path which is surrounded by<lb/> thorns and snares &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; but you who<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>believe that a positive religion has been vouchsafed<lb/> unto us for our guidance here below&#44; I will earnestly recommend<lb/> to ponder well on the words of the arch&#45;prophet&#44; of our nation. even of Moses son of Amram.<lb/>  To him whose countenance shone with a heavenly irradiation<lb/> the future of his people was unfolded as the volumes of<lb/> the past.  He portrayed their backsliding in distant generations and the<lb/> evil results accruing from it.  But he would not<lb/> abandon them the sinners to their fate.  Amidst their aberrations When verging on their spiritual<lb/> destruction a messenger from above venerable with age&#44; and of godly appearance&#44;<lb/> would resort to exhort to repentance &#38; reclaim them to virtue.  That divine messenger&#44;<lb/> my friends&#33; is even now with us&#44; as it has been and it will<lb/> ever be with all Israel.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;This song shall stand as a witness before<lb/> him&#44; for it shall not be obliterated from the mind of his<lb/> posterity&#34;.  From the distance of thirty five centuries&#44;<lb/> the sound of that celestial voice has&#44; this morning reverbe&#45;<lb/>&#45;rated in our ears.  It bids us return to God.  Will you heed<lb/> it&#63; my beloved Brethren&#63;...You say&#44; yes&#59; Listen<lb/> then.  &#34;When  Moses had made an end of speaking all these<lb/> words to all Israel&#44; he said unto them&#59; set your hearts<lb/> unto all the word which I testify among you this day&#44;<lb/> so that ye may command your children to observe to<lb/> do&#44; all the words of this law&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>Are the ceremonial laws now&#45;adays set at nought and<lb/> inveighed against&#44; excluded from that general rule&#63;<lb/>  I appeal to your understanding.  Reflect on the question&#44;<lb/> and act up to its solution.  As for myself&#44; I hold<lb/> it as my deeply&#45;set conviction&#44; that whosoever denies<lb/> the binding authority of external observances&#44; sins of<lb/> infidelity &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> It will not suffice that we answer&#58; outward practices<lb/> are&#44; so to day&#44; the body of our religion&#59; the eternal principles<lb/> of justice and humanity&#44; it has enunciated are the soul thereof.<lb/>  No&#44; I have2 also1 been taught&#44; that &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;the precepts were given&#44; only to purify our mens minds&#34;&#44; but<lb/> just as the promptings of the immortal spirit within us&#44;<lb/> are reflected in our daily walks&#44; so are the sublime<lb/> teachings of our faith&#44; are brought to light through its<lb/> votaries&#44; where they curb their appetites&#44; check suppress their desires&#44;<lb/> and control their passions&#44; for the sake of principles.<lb/>  Brethren&#33;  If I have succeeded by the arguments advanced<lb/> in this and in a former discourse&#44; to establish upon<lb/> the basis of the Sinaic revelation&#44; the three fundamental<lb/> points at issue&#44; I may consider to have completed my<lb/> task.  Still&#44; this is not an ordinary occasion&#44;<lb/> and I would be guilty of dereliction from duty&#44; were<lb/> I to let it pass away unimproved.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>I will therefore venture upon a friendly counsel.<lb/>  You are all aware that oftentimes we oppose in practice&#44;<lb/> a truth&#44; to which in theory we fully assented.  This contra&#45;<lb/>&#45;diction&#44; which can be detected in almost every man<lb/> in the offspring of in proceeds from want of caution.  Impressed by the lesson obtained we may at one time have resolved to follow it to the letter.  He who possesses a<lb/> valuable object&#44; will encase it in a well&#45;secured chest.<lb/>  He who desires to guard his choice vineyard against intrusion<lb/> will raise a high fence around it&#59; but we after having sought<lb/> to cleanse our hearts&#44; exposes them to the touch of pollution.<lb/>  Impressed by the lesson obtained&#44; we may at one time have resolved to follow it to the letter.<lb/>  We would aspire to the glory of having reformed our irreligious<lb/> habits we would of experienceing the joy of being at peace with our heavenly<lb/> law&#45;giver&#44; but we neglected to forego the occasions which<lb/> had heretofore led us astray from Him.  We placed undue trust<lb/> on our power of resistance&#44; and fell unwilling victims<lb/> to the delusions of our eyes.  But if we sincerely wish<lb/> to remain steadfastl in our righteous determinations&#44; we<lb/> must pursue the course pointed out by Solomon<lb/> in the fifth chapter of his proverbs.  In beautiful<lb/> language&#44; he personifies human wantonness.  She<lb/> attracts the unwary by her seductive mien.  Her<lb/> coral lips drop words which are sweeter than honey&#44;<lb/> softer than the most fragrant ointment&#44; but if<lb/> we bend our ears to them&#44; they will turn into a poison<lb/> bitter than gall&#44; into arrows sharper than two&#45;<lb/>edged sword.  How shall we escape the enticement&#44; you ask.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Remove thy way far from her&#44; and come not nigh the<lb/> door of her house&#34;.  Approach not&#44; my friends&#33; the<lb/> places where sin impiety abides&#59; avoid the conversation of those<lb/> who lay snares to your souls.  Cast away the volumes<lb/> on which heretical doctrines are inscribed.  And whereas<lb/> you found delight in sin in the gratification of the senses indulging the animal passions&#44; go now in quest of spiritual<lb/> pleasures.  Watch at the portals of the dwelling of<lb/> prayer.  Lend serious attention to the word therein ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;pounded.  Consult&#44; about your religious obligations&#44;<lb/> those you regard as learned and pious.  Court<lb/> the association of men&#44; whose life is a constant<lb/> exemplification of the precepts of our holy Torah.<lb/>  Acknowledge to the world&#44; without reserve&#44; the principles<lb/> which will henceforth guide your steps on earth.  In fine&#44;<lb/> be Israelites theoretically and practically&#59; you will then<lb/> draw towards yourselves the respect of the community<lb/> among whom you live&#44; the love and praise of your<lb/> faithful brethren&#44; and the favor of the Lord God&#44;<lb/> who says &#34;if the wicked will turn from all his sins that he<lb/> hath committed&#44; and keep all my statutes&#44; and do that which<lb/> is lawful lawf and right&#44; he shall surely live&#44; he shall not die. &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>  All his transgressions which he hath committed&#44; shall not<lb/> be mentioned unto him&#44; in his righteousness which he hath<lb/> done&#44; he shall live&#34;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="14"/>
            <p>Oh&#33; may this merciful decree of the universal judge&#44; be<lb/> the portion of my penitent hearers.  May life and joy<lb/> be allotted to this congregation in Israel&#44; to its rulers<lb/> and its functionaries&#44; to its young and its old&#44; to<lb/> its maidens and its matrons.  May unity and<lb/> peace ever grace this hallowed edifice&#44; the voice<lb/> of discord find no echo in our midst&#44; from now to<lb/> evermore.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
