<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF2_8</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1872" source="" attested="yes">1872</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_8_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_8_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_8_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_8_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_8_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_8_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_8_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_8_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_8_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_8_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_8_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_8_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>8</p>
            
            <p>A lecture for the 12th anniversary<lb/>
                of the 7th St Synagogue<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33; a person in possession of means will have a house built<lb/> with a view to promote his comfort and that of his family.<lb/>  Such being his object&#44; he will from time to time&#44; inspect the<lb/> premises&#44; to ascertain whether they continue in a condition equal<lb/> to his expectations.  Should he detect any defects&#44; he will<lb/> provide for the removing of what might expose the inmates<lb/> of his dwelling to inconvenience.  That plan&#44; which<lb/> wisdom dictates&#44; I propose this day for your adoption.<lb/></p>
            <p>The house you have raised for your spiritual comfort and that<lb/> of your children&#44; has just completed its twelfth year.  Have<lb/> its foundations remained in their original strength&#63;  Are the pillars<lb/> thereof unimpaired&#63;  Can those who take shelter therein feel<lb/> secure from danger&#63;  I think that a close examination at the<lb/> present season&#44; might be a sensible undertaking.  But<lb/> you fully comprehend me&#44; dear Brethren&#33;  It is not to the ma&#45;<lb/>&#45;terial components of the edifice&#44; that I would direct your inquiring<lb/> thoughts.  They may&#44; in a measure&#44; contribute to effect<lb/> your purpose&#44; because an attractive exterior in any object&#44; should<lb/> not be despised&#44; as long as the mind will be influenced by the<lb/> senses.  But your structure was not made to stand upon clay&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>traditional Judaism was to be its bases&#44; divine worship<lb/> and public pulpit public instruction its supporting columns.  Have<lb/> then the twelve years that passed rolled away&#44; since you devoted it to<lb/> holiness&#44; proved it so firmly established&#63;  Is the future likely<lb/> to carry out your original primitive design&#63;  Afford the attendant at this<lb/> habitation of the Lord religious knowledge&#44; spiritual edification&#63;<lb/>  I am perhaps disqualified for the investigation&#44; and fain would I<lb/> that some among you&#44; my beloved hearers&#33; would undertook to discuss the subject.<lb/>  I might bare what possible bias hides from my sight.  But<lb/> as it is expected that I shall assume the task&#44; I promise that<lb/> my representations shall will not be overdrawn&#44; that they will be not intentionally &#91;&#63;&#93; of<lb/> partiality.  Let me then say&#58; The service of our<lb/> God has been offered in this consecrated place with frequency.<lb/>  I would prefer to have stated that it was held daily&#44; but when<lb/> I consider how far apart my constituents reside from one another&#44;<lb/> how the demands by of commerce and trade upon their time&#44; are&#44;<lb/> in many instances quite urgent&#44; and how furthermore attendance is<lb/> not compulsory by reason of any compensation arising therefrom&#44; but<lb/> it is in every case entirely voluntary&#44; I have cause to look with<lb/> satisfaction upon that feature of our religious standing.  Yes&#44; my<lb/> brethren&#44; your sanctuary has been opened much oftener than upon<lb/> the return of each Sabbath&#44; and from that circumstance Judaism&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>so I flatter myself&#44; has derived conside a decided support.<lb/>  For&#44; several of our fellow&#45;believers&#44; attached to various rituals&#44; but<lb/> denied for the time being&#44; the opportunity to join in public prayers&#44;<lb/> united with us in holly communion.  Your synagogue became the<lb/> centre whence the petitions of Israel ascended the heavens&#44; and likewise<lb/> the means of drawing together members of the Hebrew family&#44; who<lb/> might otherwise have never met&#44; and learnt to feel mutual kindness.<lb/>  Nor should the improvement&#44; notably perceived in the recital of your<lb/> hymns and psalmody fail to be regarded as promotive of your object.<lb/>  It confessedly adds solemnity to our assemblies&#44; and unction to<lb/> the faithful.  According to my manner of judging&#44; the fact that<lb/> a whole congregation of the Lord are privileged to praise their Maker<lb/> in unison of voices&#44; avoiding a report recourse to mercenary singers&#44; is peculiarly<lb/> gratifying.  I shall not&#44; however&#44; conceal in this respect&#44; my<lb/> disappointment at the silence of some&#44; and at the slight efforts<lb/> of others upon whom I depended for a better effect of our popular chaunting.<lb/>  Neither extreme modesty nor personal considerations ought to<lb/> militate against our religious interests.  Both should be<lb/> overcome for the sake of the cause to be advanced.<lb/></p>
            <p>But is it in all truth advanced&#63;  Does traditional Judaism<lb/> obtain efficient aid&#44; and its adherents spiritual benefit from<lb/> the continuance of the Synagogue dedicated twelve years ago&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>I honestly answer in the affirmative&#59; and am ready to<lb/> meet the object of some who point to defections in our<lb/> midst&#44; notwithstanding the existence of this Institution.  Those desertions form our ranks would have happened in any event.  They<lb/> would have occurred&#44; if the most rampant&#44; the most extrava&#45;<lb/>&#45;gant innovations had been here advocated and introduced.  The sin lies not at<lb/> the door of this house&#44; but at that of the parents of our disloyal<lb/> Jews and Jewesses.  An occasional visit at the Synagogue&#44;<lb/> could not counteract the constant evil example of fathers<lb/> and mothers&#44; or the reprehensible weakness which leads to<lb/> a conniving at what cannot be openly sanctioned.  For with&#45;<lb/>&#45;out being intolerant or exclusive&#44; we should guard against an unrestricted<lb/> association of our youthful offspring with non&#45;Israelites.  It<lb/> cannot work but injuriously to the ancestral religion.  We<lb/> may show that we repine every confidence in our sons and daughters&#44;<lb/> that we believe them incapable of an infatuation&#44; that would bring<lb/> sorrow upon our heads.  Yet the mild exercise of authority will<lb/> always act wholesomely.  But if it is true that since your<lb/> habitation of prayer was erected&#44; you sustained some loss&#44; I<lb/> contrast your gain&#44; and find that it the latter outweighed the former by<lb/> far.  Your simple and democratic method<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>of conducting the service worship&#44; has attracted to it many who<lb/> might not have coalesced have applied coalesced with other bodies of Hebrews.<lb/>  The absence of religious any distinction among the attendants of the Sy&#45;<lb/>&#45;nagogue&#44; is a feature most pleasing to all.  The humblest in circum&#45;<lb/>&#45;stances and the wealthiest enjoy precisely the same privileges in<lb/> the distribution of honors&#44; consequent on your mode of conducting regulating the<lb/> service.  Indeed&#44; my Brethren&#33;  It would greatly redound to your<lb/> credit&#44; and to foster also the progress of our common cause&#44; were you further<lb/> to extend your liberal system&#44; and abolish a difference of grades<lb/> in the seats occupied in the dwelling of prayer.  But to ac&#45;<lb/>complish that desirable end&#44; and constitute an equality consonant<lb/> with the principles of our faith belief&#44; and with the institution of<lb/> the country we live in&#44; as spirit of generosity should prevail&#44;<lb/> which I have not succeeded to awaken.  The adjusting<lb/> of your obligation to a society of our gentile neighbors&#44; ought<lb/> to be deemed a an imperative duty by such whom Providence has blessed with<lb/> affluence.  The liquidation of a debt&#44; with which the house of<lb/> God&#44; ought never to be burdened&#44; may facilitate the following<lb/> of my suggestion.  To that should be added the bequests made by<lb/> those who have are about to exchanged a mortal for an immortal life existence.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>That practice&#44; rife among persons of another creed&#44; but set aside<lb/> entirely by our wealthy brothers and sisters in faith&#44; would enrich your treasury&#44;<lb/> and thus justify our presenting to Israel the noble example of a<lb/> Synagogue where equality is not a &#91;&#63;&#93; fictitious name by a veritable<lb/> fact.  I do long to see a sanctuary of the Lord so constituted.<lb/>  The service solemnly performed alone by a single God&#45;fearing officer&#45;&#45;call him salaried if<lb/> you so choose&#44; since he can scarcely be otherwise&#45;&#45;and the assembly of believers<lb/> without invidious difference of place and station&#44; joining in the communion<lb/> of brethren&#44; feeling that there at least no line of demarcation is drawn<lb/> between those who contribute to the preservation and elevation of Judaism&#44; perpetration of Judaism&#44; and the exalting<lb/> of its heavenly author.  But the possession of ample means&#44;<lb/> would enable you moreover to draw hither on the Sabbath and festivals many who<lb/> are deterred from attending from because unaccustomed to our ancient ritual.<lb/>  It has long been the occasion of complaint&#44; and I think of injury to your<lb/> Synagogue&#44; that&#44; unprovided with books&#44; an Israelite not raised in your<lb/> midst&#44; cannot follow the prayers&#59; and that the purchasing of the same<lb/> entails too great an expense&#44; on persons in moderate circumstances.<lb/>  But you might supply&#44; for a nominal sum&#44; copies of our liturgy&#44; and<lb/> of the Pentateuch&#59; the accession to your number&#44; and the increase<lb/> of devotion would fully compensate any reward your endeavours.  and This house you<lb/> built twelve years ago&#44; would extend the sphere of its spiritual usefulness&#44;<lb/> reaching still beyond your holy anticipations.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>For this&#44; my dear Brethren&#33; should now occupy your serious thoughts.<lb/>  When all around us is <sic>yeilding</sic> to the caprices of the changelings&#59;<lb/> you should look well to the foundations and the pillars of your<lb/> Institution.  Its future will not belie its past&#44; if you but strengthen repair<lb/> what the ungracious hand of time may have awakened impaired.  What avails to disguise it&#63;<lb/>  Many who were with you&#44; when first engaged in the undertaking&#44;<lb/> sleep now in death.  Others have grown lukewarm&#59; and<lb/> some have deserted your ranks.  To expect that the children of<lb/> those who become disloyal recreant to our cause&#44; will ever enter these<lb/> portals would be such folly.  You must then for the sake<lb/> of the principle it represents&#44; for the sake of traditional Ju&#45;<lb/>&#45;daism&#44; which has saved us at all times form lapsing into genti&#45;<lb/>&#45;lism&#44; for the sake of religious instruction which is the manner<lb/> of everlasting life&#44; you must&#44; I say infuse into the synagogue<lb/> a new element of strength.  You can gather it from among<lb/> many various scattered members of our race&#44; who have not been sold<lb/> to the Molach of reform&#44; but who are withheld from becoming affiliated<lb/> with to your congregation for various motives.  Invite them in your midst by<lb/> all the facilities you can consistently offer.  Seek Strive to<lb/> interest them in your worship by its imposing appearance&#44;<lb/> by the impressiveness of the manner you tender your devotions to<lb/> the Supreme.  Let those who have with you a community of<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>belief&#44; of history&#44; of traditions&#44; of hopes be impelled to seek<lb/> your religious association.  Make every advance&#45;&#45;without damaging<lb/> the interests of sister congregations&#45;&#45;to draw to your midst your<lb/> fellow&#45;Israelites reared in other rituals&#44; their attendance will<lb/> prove fruitful of exceeding advantage to the cause you have at<lb/> heart.  And when you have succeeded in inducing many<lb/> to swell your number&#44; exhibit a demeanour fitting to the sacred&#45;<lb/>ness of your consecrated dedicated sanctuary.  Let decorum&#44; punctuality<lb/> regularity characterize your deportment and that of your children.<lb/>  Chide the latter when at fault in the habitation of the Lord.<lb/>  Repress a pernicious custom of walking to and fro&#44; at a cer&#45;<lb/>&#45;tain stage of the service&#44; to the annoyance of the devout ones&#44;<lb/> and the just derision of the stranger who frequently visit your<lb/> Synagogue.  In fine&#44; let freedom prove any encumbrance&#44; equality&#44;<lb/> harmony in the rehearsal of your beautiful unions&#44; and a willing<lb/> disposition to listen to the word of instruction&#44; however humbly<lb/> imparted&#44; render this house you consecrated twelve years ago<lb/> the true exponent of the religion of Moses&#44; and of the Sages&#44; so<lb/> that all may exclaim in seeing it &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;This is the gate &#40;that leads&#41; to the Lord&#44; the righteous shall enter therein.&#34;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
