<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF1_14</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_13_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_13_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_13_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_13_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_13_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_13_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_13_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_13_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_13_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_13_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_13_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_13_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>7 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For a Bar Mitzv&#225;h<lb/>
                on &#39;Shelach Lecha&#39;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  What we have read this morning in the scroll of<lb/> the law&#44; is suggestive of useful ideas.  I would have liked<lb/> to give expression to some&#44; from which practical instruction might be<lb/> drawn&#59; but the service has been somewhat protracted unusually&#44; and<lb/> the heat of the season has become oppressive.  I am therefore<lb/> admonished to forbear and bring the prayers to a close.<lb/>  Yet&#44; the practice of addressing a lad at the age that a Rab&#45;<lb/>&#45;binical rule qualifies him to form a quorum for holding public<lb/> worship&#44; will necessarily occasion a detention.  I shall not<lb/> trespass long&#59; but I would not omit in this instance the<lb/> performance of a usage&#44; which I thought fit to introduce<lb/> and ordinarily to follow.  For&#44; the youth to whom I will<lb/> direct my speech attends at the Divine Service with regularity&#44;<lb/> and evinces an interest in its ceremonies.  Moreover&#44; his<lb/> training in the Hebrew language&#44; has not been confined to<lb/> the bare portion just recited&#44; but he is taught through the<lb/> scriptures and the books of our ritual.  If a few words<lb/> opportunely spoken&#44; can encourage pious habits&#44; and love<lb/> for sacred learning&#44; my silence would be an inexcusable<lb/> fault.  I do not sanquinely2 look1 forward<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>to the results of my endeavours.  I know that often&#44;<lb/> too often&#44; they will prove abortive&#44; either by reason of paren&#45;<lb/>&#45;tal heedlessness&#44; or the counsel of the worldly.  But I<lb/> must so with good seed.  That is my duty and earnest wish.<lb/>  The fructifying process depends upon influences which<lb/> I cannot control.  Still&#44; what is implanted in virgin<lb/> soil&#44; may sink deeply&#44; and show at some distant future&#44;<lb/> that it could not be entirely rooted out.  It behooves<lb/> me especially so to act&#44; when a disposition to righteous<lb/>&#45;ness is discovered in the young.  Yes&#58; my dear Bar Mitzvah.<lb/>  I saw you among the few of your coevals&#44; who take part in<lb/> the rites of our worship and felt pleased gratified.  I heard that your<lb/> parents offer you the opportunity of progressing in<lb/> religious knowledge and rejoiced.  But that is only a<lb/> satisfactory beginning.  How the end may prove&#44; depends<lb/> in a great measure upon your exertions.  The principal<lb/> study which you must pursue&#44; when a little further ad&#45; riper<lb/> &#45;vanced in years is the study of yourself.  You must<lb/> examine the degree of your strength or weakness&#44; so<lb/> that you may be prepared against the occasions that might circumstances calculated<lb/> to lead you astray.  If you perceive that the temptations<lb/> lying in your way are very great&#44; and you cannot trust your<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>ability to overcome them&#44; call to mind the wholesome lessons<lb/> imbibed in the days of your innocence&#44; and you will feel invested<lb/> with new vigour.  Pray to God for help&#44; and &#34;He who is night<lb/> unto all that call upon Him in truth&#44;&#34; will uphold your<lb/> steps.  You shall not fall in the net spread by the transgressors.<lb/>  You have read a section in the Pentateuch&#44; which is very signi&#45;<lb/>&#45;ficant&#44; and upon which you might advantageously reflect.<lb/>  You repeated before us that historical incident when to judge<lb/> of the climate&#44; natural productions and condition of the inha&#45;<lb/>bitants of the land of Canaan&#44; Moses sent thither explorers.<lb/>  He chose among each of the twelve tribes a person of high<lb/> standing&#44; whose character would vouch for the proper fulfil&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment of the mission.  The Bible speaks of them&#44; &#34;as men<lb/> who were the heads of the children of Israel&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> But those individuals so much relied upon&#59; those individuals<lb/> regarded as the cream of society&#44; the very essence of honor&#44;<lb/> abused the confidence reposed in them.  Not alone did<lb/> they misrepresent facts&#44; and stir up a mutiny&#44; but they<lb/> involved in their guilt the whole nation.<lb/>  involved in their guilt the whole n<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>The account of that event is written in Holy Writ plainly<lb/> enough to be universally understood.  I shall not refer to it<lb/> any further&#44; but I will point out the moral it conveys.<lb/>  Among the twelve chiefs that went to search out the country&#44;<lb/> two remained uninfluenced by evil example  The pernicious surroundings.  Joshua and Caleb could not be swayed by the conduct of their evil associates.  Truth was<lb/> their aim.  The inspiring of humility was the drift of their words<lb/> and actions.  They urged the affrighted people to look for safety<lb/> to the heavenly Power which nothing can resist.  They spoke<lb/> of the loving&#45;kindness of the Lord&#44; and deprecated the sin of<lb/> rebellion.  Notwithstanding their remonstrances they beheld<lb/> those that were esteemed wise&#44; set up themselves in opposition<lb/> to the will of God and his prophet.  They beheld defection spread<lb/> in every rank.  But they did not wavered not.  All might swerve<lb/> from the path of righteousness&#44; they would follow it up<lb/> unflinchingly.  So <sic>copy</sic> that example should be&#44; my dear<lb/> young brother&#44; your highest ambition.  I might show<lb/> how signal was the reward of the fidelity of those two incor&#45;<lb/>&#45;ruptible men.  I might describe to you the honors that Joshua<lb/> reaped as the fruit of his rectitude&#59; the many and happy<lb/> years bestowed upon Caleb for his adherence to uprightness.<lb/>  But I prefer to recommend that you will be good&#44; that<lb/> you be religious&#44; without the expectation of a recompense.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>&#34;Be us servants that wait upon their master regardless of<lb/> the wages to be got received&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> is the maxim of our Rabbins.  It is certain&#44; beyond the<lb/> possibility of a doubt&#44; that a Divine reward awaits attends the just both<lb/> agreeable delightful of requitals for their good deeds in the consciousness<lb/> of having discharged their duty.  As a human being you are<lb/> indebted to God for all earthly terrestrial blessings.  For&#44; he has showered<lb/> down favors on your parents&#44; and through His mercy they and<lb/> yourself enjoy life.  As a newly admitted member of the<lb/> Hebrew family congregation&#44; you owe the Almighty the privilege of<lb/> knowing is name&#44; and having been taught command&#45;<lb/>&#45;ments supremely wise by w keeping the which&#44; you will become&#44;<lb/> even while on earth&#44; a little lower than angels who worship in<lb/> purity of spirit.  Be then grateful&#44; and exhibit your feelings<lb/> of thankfulness to the Lord by guarding against pollution.<lb/>  Do not suffer any selfish motive&#44; the love of gain&#44; and<lb/> the indulgence of <sic>apetites</sic>&#45;&#45;to make you forget the lessons of<lb/> the good book.  Cherish them&#44; and the advice of our godly Sages.<lb/>  Be an Israelite in deeds and not in mere professions.  You<lb/> may not outweigh then out strip others in the possession of objects material and perishable&#44;<lb/> but you will exceed many in that which is spiritual and everlasting.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>That is my wish&#44; briefly expressed&#44; and with that I this day<lb/> cease speaking to speak.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
