<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF16_6</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_6_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_6_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_6_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_6_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_6_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_6_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_6_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_6_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_6_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_6_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_6_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_6_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>94</p>
            
            <p>The senseless boasting of some Jews.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>It would seem sheer hollow pretense in me on my part in my one to make<lb/> frequent professions of kindness towards all human beings&#44;<lb/> and be nevertheless harping on the religious errors<lb/> of human beings.  Yet&#44; it is a real truth that&#44; while<lb/> I feel naturally drawn closer to persons who hold the<lb/> same belief as mine&#44; I do not entertain vul&#45;<lb/>&#45;gar prejudices against those who follow another<lb/> creed.  I fully understand that parentage&#44;<lb/> early training&#44; surroundings and numberless<lb/> circumstances enter into the formation of our<lb/> ideas.  I am by conviction a Jew because<lb/> the underlying principle of Judaism&#45;&#45;One God one origin to mankind&#45;&#45;satisfies<lb/> my reason&#44; and the commandments of Judaism<lb/> do not conflict with my obligations as a<lb/> citizen of the world&#44; but&#44; on the contrary&#44; encourage<lb/> me in the performance of all duties in the mul&#45;<lb/>&#45;tifarious relations of life.  Still&#44; I recognize that<lb/> had my birth&#44; education and associations been dif&#45;<lb/>&#45;ferent&#44; I would&#44; in all probability&#44; be now<lb/> an adherent of gentilism.  But because I am<lb/> an Israelite&#44; and a teacher in the service of Israel&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>I feel scandalized when men who claim to<lb/> represent us socially&#44; stultify themselves by<lb/> their pseudo liberalism&#44; and place our faith in<lb/> a questionable position.  I had occasion recently<lb/> to refer to the praises bestowed by a dignitary of<lb/> the Catholic Church upon Rabbis&#44; who think<lb/> it fit to put the alleged founder of Christianity<lb/> on a level with Hebrew prophets&#44; but since I spoke<lb/> of that&#44; I have read of other irritating instances&#44;<lb/> in which Jews have set themselves on record<lb/> as unqualified eulogists of the man of Nazareth.<lb/>  Two have specially hurt my feelings&#44; for&#44;<lb/> their objectionable utterances were pointedly<lb/> offensive to our people.  A young student<lb/> of our persuasion is in the law department of Yale College&#44; being on a<lb/> vacation&#44; delivered a lecture on the eve of this<lb/> month of January before a Young Men&#39;s Hebrew<lb/> Association in which he pictured a lecture which found its way in the public press&#44; and in which lord Beaconsfield<lb/> was pictured as &#34;the grandest English Jew&#44;&#34; regardless of the<lb/> fact that Isaac Disraeli father of lord Beacdonfield gave his son deliberately<lb/>to the poet Samuel Rogers to be raised as a<lb/> Christian.  That without so degrading a step&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>he who was born a Jew in the Law introduced into the covenant could not mount<lb/> so high as to become prime minister of the United Kingdom&#44; all will ad&#45;<lb/>&#45;mit&#59; that Benjamin Disraeli exercised his<lb/> literary talents to show to advantage the people<lb/> from which he sprung&#44; whoever has read his<lb/> novels will acknowledge&#44; but ought that to Jus&#45;<lb/>&#45;tify making him a model to youths&#44; who<lb/> should be taught by precept and example to<lb/> keep in the face of under all temptations <sic>immoveably</sic> steadfast in the religion of their<lb/> fathers&#63;  And Again&#58; if the mania of making a boasting<lb/> that that all who enjoy celebrity belong to<lb/> our race is so uncontrollable&#44; is it becoming fitting in<lb/> an Israelite&#44; addressing a young men&#39;s Hebrew<lb/> association&#44; to speak of the reputed author of a creed which<lb/> supplanted ours&#44; as &#34;the sublimest Hebrew that ever<lb/> lived&#34;&#63;  Yet&#44; such are the precise words which<lb/> the orator used in connection with the virtue of<lb/> Christian forgiveness&#44; which he desired his hearers to put<lb/> into practice.  But what some may overlook<lb/> in a youthful speaker as the effect of incon&#45;<lb/>sideration&#44; or want of sufficient knowledge of our<lb/></p> 
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>eventful history&#44; cannot be so explained&#44; in  about<lb/> a man ripe in years&#44; well read&#44; and full of the<lb/> world&#39;s experience.  That Israelite&#44; justly<lb/> smarting under a second indignity laid upon<lb/> him shortly after he suffered the humiliation of a first&#45;&#45;I mean the outrage of having been denied the outrage of denying him admission into contemptuously treated by<lb/> two different associations&#44; wrote thus to the<lb/> editor of a secular journal&#58; &#34;I am at a loss to<lb/> understand the motives of those voting to reject<lb/> me.  IT does not worry me in the least.  A<lb/> better man than myself was rejected more than<lb/> eighteen hundred years ago.  He was a Jew&#44; and<lb/> I have never denied that I am of his faith.&#34;<lb/>  In this manner&#44; the older Israelite condemned his<lb/> ancestors for not having accepted Jesus as a redeem&#45;<lb/>&#45;er&#44; while the younger declared the deified man<lb/> superior to Moses and all the prophets.  There<lb/> was a time when to utter the name of one whom<lb/> the church proclaimed coexistent and coequal with<lb/> the Almighty&#44; would have been considered by some<lb/> Jews a violation of the Biblical injunction &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Do not mention the name of<lb/> other gods&#44; let it not be heard out of thy mouth.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Such an application of that Biblical passage<lb/> was evidently overstrained.  The opinion of Maimo&#45;<lb/>&#45;nides&#44; expressed in his comment to a Mishnah.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Know that the people called Nazarenes&#44; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> who go astray after Jesus&#44; though their laws vary &#40;from those of old paganism&#41;&#44;<lb/> are nevertheless all idolators&#44;&#34; that opinion&#44; I say<lb/> has not been generally received universally acceptance among us.  When a Rashi<lb/> did not refused to a contemporary of the early crusaders&#44; refused to hold it&#44; we may agree that to compare<lb/> Christians to the heathens&#44; whose deities our Bible<lb/> prohibits to mention&#44; would be unjust.  False as<lb/> the belief in a trinity is because it impugns the <sic>incorporeity</sic>&#44; and Omnipotence of God&#44; it does not foster any<lb/> of the immoralities and cruelties by which paganism polytheism<lb/> disgraced humanity.  We may freely recognize<lb/> in it a vast improvement upon the polytheism debauching religions<lb/> of the Greeks and the Romans which it superseded.<lb/>  Maimonides himself&#44; who in one of his writings<lb/> was so pronounced against the new creed&#44; has left<lb/> us in his voluminous work &#34;Yad Hachazakah&#44;&#34;<lb/> which is a methodical abridgment of all Talmudical<lb/> laws&#44; a sentence showing that he admitted both<lb/> Christianity and Mohammedanism as two steps<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>in advance towards monotheism.  Now&#44; all<lb/> that I have stated&#44; ought to serve as a convincing<lb/> proof of my freedom from low prejudices&#44; but does<lb/> it therefore follow that I should endorse an<lb/> open or tacit condemnation denunciation of my own people&#44;&#63;<lb/> that I should deem it an offense in our<lb/> progenitors to have rejected the man of Nazareth as a redeemer the Messiah<lb/> or that I consider him above our patriarchs and our<lb/> seers &#38; should tolerate his being publicly so extolled by Jewish speakers&#63;  Never&#58; the liberalism that comprises<lb/> the honor of our race will&#44; under no circumstance&#44;<lb/> find in me an advocate.  A deplorable mistake<lb/> is in my sight that which some men of Israel who wield<lb/> influence commit.  They wish to convince persuade genti&#45;<lb/>&#45;lism that Judaism has assumed quite a different<lb/> phase from that which it bore in past ages&#59; that<lb/> it does not concern itself now with in a discrimination of creeds&#44; but<lb/> takes in all beliefs&#44; or no unbeliefs at all&#44; in its an&#45;<lb/>&#45;xiety for a universal fraternization.  I call it a<lb/> deplorable mistake&#44; because it kills in our<lb/> rising generation every sense of the superiority<lb/> which monotheism rightfully possess&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>it fosters breathes apathy into the hearts that should<lb/> be kindled with religious fervor.  But what is the<lb/> gain we socially derive from such liberalism&#63;  Has<lb/> the oratory of our orators&#44; or the writing of our writers<lb/> <sic>levelled</sic> down fictitious inequalities set up to our detriment&#63;<lb/>  I will not point to the report that&#44; in a town of<lb/> Louisiana&#44; during about the period of the late Christian festivities an<lb/> attempt was made in a towns of Louisiana to expel Jews&#44; on the plea on<lb/> their monopolizing all branches of trade.  The account may have<lb/> been exaggerated&#59; but without searching far&#44; each<lb/> of us may recall his own experience of petty<lb/> annoyances&#44; arising from the circumstance that his name or from his looks&#44;<lb/> indicateding his Hebrew descent.  No&#44; let us not com&#45; lower<lb/>&#45;promise the dignity of Judaism.  To make it honor&#45;<lb/>&#45;able by our conduct&#44; is a most sacred duty.  A<lb/> prayer in our daily ritual&#44; quoted by ancient com&#45;<lb/>&#45;mentators on the Talmud&#44; is a strong reminder<lb/> of that obligation.  For it reads so&#58; Lord&#33; &#34;sanctify<lb/> Thy name in Thy world through the people<lb/> who are to sanctify Thy name.....blessed shall<lb/> he be who sanctifies Thy name in public&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; But that benediction will not be<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>ours through a pseudo liberalism which estranges<lb/> our offspring from our fold&#44; and robs us of their<lb/> cooperation in the maintenance of the ancestral<lb/> faith.  By precept&#44; consistently exemplified we<lb/> may prove to elicit from our opponents the confession that a son of Israel<lb/> is the embodiment of whatever ennobles human<lb/> nature.  A Rev. Mr. Morgan of New York&#44;<lb/> will not find cause to open a mission school&#44; in order<lb/> to enlighten young foreign Hebrews&#44; when we ourselves<lb/> shall take care of our own.  Thousands do stand in<lb/> need of mental education&#44; tens of thousands of indus&#45;<lb/>&#45;trial training&#44; but alas&#33; how few are those who<lb/> labor to that to promote such tuition&#33;  &#40;They may be<lb/> easily counted&#41; and how many the obstacles besetting<lb/> their every effort&#33;  Why try to appear broad<lb/> minded before the stranger&#44; when we are so nar&#45;<lb/>&#45;row hearted towards our own&#63;  Israelites.  Let us build up<lb/> a God&#45;exalting Judaism among the unspiritual of<lb/> our race&#44; and let that be our pride&#44; not the senseless<lb/> boast of having a community of extraction with the far&#45;<lb/>famed and with the author of trinitarianism.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
