<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF14_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_1_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>1t Lecture on Revelation.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  The anxiety which I felt in approaching the sub&#45;<lb/>&#45;ject of God&#39;s existence&#45;&#45;spoken upon at some length in my last four lectures&#45;&#45;is<lb/> intensified now that&#44; to <sic>fulfil</sic> a promise&#44; I must try to conceive endeavour to present<lb/> clearly before my hearers of the truth of God&#39;s revelation.  When I first<lb/> assumed my task&#44; I knew that those whom I addressed were<lb/> not tainted with atheism.  I knew also from reading&#44; that even<lb/> philosophers who habitually doubted&#59; persons who had reasoned<lb/> themselves into a denial of a Supreme Architect in the<lb/> structure of the symmetrical universe&#44; were finally compelled&#44; by their own<lb/> the line of thinking&#44; to acknowledge a Prime Mover&#44; so as<lb/> not to be in contradiction with good common sense and experience.  My The<lb/> deep concern which I then felt arose then principally from a fear of that the inade&#45;<lb/>&#45;quacy of my arguments might frustrate defeat my intentions.  For&#44;<lb/> I wished to strengthen the belief of confirm Jewish youths so in their belief&#59; to supply<lb/> them with the faculty a medium to influence their coevals healthfully.  I greatly<lb/> desired they that they might aid me in raising man up&#45;<lb/>ward to see the glory of the Deity through His created nation&#44;<lb/> and offer heartfelt adoration.  But now I must undertake<lb/> to show confirm strengthen the conviction that the Deity has let His glory downward and holding<lb/> communion with man through the means of the same created nation.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Yes&#58; I will not be hypocritical.  I shall say it<lb/> boldly.  Revelation is&#44; in in my mind&#44; a voluntary<lb/> derogation of the majesty of Him that is the Spirit enthroned in eter&#45;<lb/>&#45;nity.  Hear my confession.  I believe that the<lb/> Almighty who created in forming man sought to give scope to His celestial<lb/> love&#44; implanted within our soul the seeds of virtue&#44; and<lb/> hence of happiness.  Those Our inborn sentiments&#44; intended<lb/> to have grown with our growth&#44; ought to have gained additional depth<lb/> by a study of the model which the Creator offered set forth in His<lb/> handiwork&#59; a model of justice&#44; in apportioning to all a share<lb/> of benefits derived from the earth which He made fertile&#44; and<lb/> from the sky He made resplendent&#59; of justi goodness&#44; in<lb/> furnishing mortals with more than their actual needs&#44; and with<lb/> ample capacities for enjoyment.  But man allowed those<lb/> innate principles&#44; which should have sufficed as a guide<lb/> in social intercourse&#44; to be overcome by passions that hu&#45;<lb/>&#45;man flesh conjured up.  It is idle&#44; in my opinion&#44; to<lb/> inquire why we were not formed angel&#45;like&#44; free from<lb/> passions.  As well might we ask wherefore was not the<lb/> store whole animal kingdom endowed with man&#39;s faculties.  It pleased the<lb/> all&#45;wise One to associate in us body and soul&#44; so that in the<lb/> struggle ensuing&#44; the nobler part of us might issue forth sublimely victorious.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>But in that contest the material conquered the spiritual&#44;<lb/> savageness threatened to overthrow society from its foundations.<lb/>  Violence ruled&#59; men&#44; who by brutal force had obtained a mastery<lb/> over their fellow&#45;beings&#44; set arrogated to themselves up as the title of gods &#38; they were <sic>worshipped</sic> as such.  The<lb/> knowledge of a beneficent Lord who had designed His creatures for a<lb/> sweet fellowship and mutual improvement was mostly for&#45;<lb/>&#45;gotten.  The high sentiments of justice and goodness that should have stirred&#91;&#63;&#93;<lb/> within the breast were stifled by the fumes of low cravings.<lb/>  Thus In the dark colors traditional history paints the remote stages of the world.  The object of man&#39;s creation&#44; might have been frustrated&#44;<lb/> had not the Almighty prevented the effects of a wide&#45;spread evil by an<lb/> act of Fatherly condescension.  He beheld a prevailing<lb/> corruption&#44; and noted in His omniscience perceived that it could not<lb/> be rooted out at once.  He bethought Himself therefore of<lb/> the means to remove it by gradual steps&#44; through a<lb/> teaching which would appeal more immediately to the senses&#44;<lb/> than originally provided for by the work of nature. namely by He mercifully He resolved to vouchsafe unto man&#44;<lb/></p> <p>Revelation.<lb/></p>
            <p>Was the selection of Abraham&#44; as the first missionary of<lb/> God&#39;s expressed will&#44; a the result of a verbal communication from above&#44; or<lb/> of a spiritual breathing of the soul of the universe into the soul of<lb/> the patriarch&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>That question I do not presume to solve&#44; but I must<lb/> show that the divine choice was well merited.<lb/></p>
            <p>Idolatry and its demoralising accompaniments surrounded<lb/> the son of Terah in his home and country.  Without having<lb/> recourse to vague traditions and legends&#44; we need only turn<lb/> to the last chapter of the book of Joshua&#44; which naturally cling to the character of one so great and we shall<lb/> discover that the pattern of believers was reared under<lb/> heathen influences.  The leader of Israel who succeeded Moses expressed that<lb/> fact clearly&#44; when&#44; previous to his death&#44; he gathered the<lb/> tribes in solemn assembly at Shechem&#44; and briefly rehearsed<lb/> the ancestral history&#44; to draw from them a vow of alle&#45;<lb/>&#45;giance to the Unity &#91;Hebrew&#93; What a superhuman&#45;mental<lb/> effort must that have been&#44; which severed Abraham for<lb/> ever from a predominant falsehood&#44; and fastened his soul<lb/> indissolubly to an unknown or long neglected Truth&#33;<lb/></p>
            <p>Genius has at times compelled nature to disclose her secrets.  Galileo<lb/> in the cathedral of Pisa&#59; Newton in his orchard saw what<lb/> no eyes but theirs could see with equal results.  The swing&#45;<lb/>ging of a lamp suspended from the ceiling&#44; and the falling of an apple from a tree<lb/> are not phenomena that attract special attention.  But genius<lb/> made those casual circumstances reveal time&#45;measure<lb/>ment and the law of gravitation.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>So also Again&#58; the same nature which Gave Galvani<lb/> his battery&#44; and Morse his telegraph&#44; is that which ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;tensively rewards Edison for his untiring researches.<lb/>  But let not genius&#44; nor the power of invention be con&#45;<lb/>&#45;founded&#45;&#45;as they have profusely been blended mixed identified with the highest of<lb/> God&#39;s gifts.  To unfold what lay hidden in the work<lb/> of creation&#44; to apply it in a manner redounding to uni&#45; general<lb/> &#45;versal use and comfort and advantage and comfort is indeed the evidence of a vast share<lb/> of spirit in man.  But to elicit from creation a truth which will<lb/> affect the whole human race in its dearest interests civilly and religiously&#44; which<lb/> will make man&#39;s dwelling on earth a foretaste of paradise&#44;<lb/> and feel to be then seized with an irrepressible wish to impart it that truth at all risks<lb/> and despite all obstacles&#44; is more than the act of mental su&#45;<lb/>&#45;periority&#59; of talents and lofty conceptions&#59; it is veritable inspiration.<lb/>  And inspiration was that which summoned Abraham from<lb/> Ur Chasdim and bid him go leave country and kindred<lb/> to go preaching a verity that would make him an ever&#45;<lb/>&#45;lasting blessing&#44; as the promoter of universal blessings.  The Scriptures which make us delight in expatiating<lb/> acquainted with on the qualities of the heart which distinguished<lb/> the ancient patriarch&#44; tells us relate nothing of the attributes of<lb/> <sic>of</sic> his intellect.  They still must have been singularly great powerful&#44;<lb/> since their possessor could so eminently rise above his surroundings&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>since he could with so much certainty point out the<lb/> only Author of nature amidst a most degrading poly&#45;<lb/>&#45;theism. Thos but Those attributes were only the invisible<lb/> magnetic force which attracted towards of attraction that brought the Spirit enthroned in eternity down to commune with the spirit of the righteous first saintly Hebrew. a divine<lb/> afflatus.<lb/></p>
            <p>Men who dispute revelation&#44; quote philosophers who<lb/> taught the existence of One God by unaided reason.<lb/>  Well&#58; I will not deny the merits of a Plato&#44; of a Cicero&#44;<lb/> of an Epictetus and many others among the Greeks and<lb/> Romans&#44; whose writings have reached us posterity.  Indeed&#44; the<lb/> memorabilia of Socrates alone are a monument of to extraordinary wisdom.<lb/>  We must admire the depth of thought&#44; the purity of<lb/> sentiments pervading the whole and comparing favorably<lb/> with the lessons of Jewish prophets and Sages.  I am<lb/> not even inclined to accept the views of some ol modern authors&#44;<lb/> that whatever is good in the productions of the men of<lb/> antiquity is an emanation of Holy Writ&#44; with which<lb/> they became familiar either by personal intercourse with<lb/> some Israelites&#44; or by a consolidation of the Septuagint translation version of the<lb/> Bible&#44; supposed to have been made in the days of Ptolemy Philadelphus.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>No&#58; I will give those writings the credit for origina&#45;<lb/>&#45;lity.  Yet&#44; I must draw a line marked out with great<lb/> precision to distinguish between what the Jewish people have<lb/> inherited from their righteous founder&#44; and what the disciples of the<lb/> philosophers of Grace and Rome had learnt.<lb/></p>
            <p>All will remember that Socrates was accused of atheism&#44; which<lb/> then in the language of the time meant a want of respect for the gods of a certain land or a<lb/> city.  What did the defense set up to endeavour to deliver<lb/> the Sage from capital punishment&#63;  That he did sacrifice<lb/> to the popular deities&#59; that he sacrificed to them sometime at home&#44; frequently at the public<lb/> places of common worship&#44; and that he was in the habit of practising divinations.<lb/>  We know also have read likewise that he recommended to his pupils to offer<lb/> to the gods according to their abilities. All this may have<lb/> been a compromise&#59; the philosopher may have feared perhaps<lb/> too openly to oppose public opinion.  I am not here to<lb/> condemn Socrates&#44; but to point to the heavenly spirit that<lb/> moved Abraham&#59; to show my intelligent young friends that he who imagined<lb/> himself an ambassador of God to the Athenians&#44; and the real<lb/> messenger of the Omnipotent to the gentile world&#44; bear no<lb/> resemblance in point whatever in the character of their mission.  Abraham<lb/> travelled journeyed abroad and built altars&#44; but in the face of heathens steeped<lb/> in polytheism&#44; he proclaimed solely and exclusively the name of<lb/> the Eternal Lord.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Abraham&#44; urged requested by the King of Sodom to appropriate to<lb/> himself what he had earned by rescuing the powerless from<lb/> their assailants&#44; refused the pressing offer swearing declined the offer accompanying the refusal with an oath in the name of &#34;the<lb/> God Most High&#44; the Maker Possessor of heaven and earth.&#34;  G Abraham&#44; pray&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing for the wicked&#44; addressed the Deity as &#34;the Judge of the whole earth&#59;&#34;<lb/> planting an orchard for to give pilgrims shelter and refreshment food&#44;<lb/> &#34;he called on the name of the Eternal&#44; the everlasting God&#44;&#34;<lb/> and when giving delivering to his trusty Eliezer an important charge&#44; he<lb/> made him swear by &#34;the God of heaven and earth.&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>No compromise sullies the demeanour of the great believer.  The<lb/> Omnipotent from whom all things have sprung&#44; is the only<lb/> object of his adoration&#44; and what he feels he commits as a<lb/> precious truth to Isaac&#44; his son of promise&#44; who again transmits<lb/> to Jacob till it reaches the seventy persons that took up<lb/> their abode in polytheistic Egypt&#44; waiting for the mi&#45;<lb/>&#45;ghty redemption and revelation which would knit them into<lb/> an apostolic nation.<lb/></p>
            <p>This I have deemed necessary to preface before I enter more fully into a<lb/> subject of vital importance to us&#44; of the seed of Abraham&#44; and to<lb/> mankind at large&#44; who are destined to accept our teachings&#44; and bend the<lb/> knee before our God.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
