<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF9</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff9_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff9_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff9_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff9_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff9_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff9_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff9_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff9_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff9_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff9_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff9_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff9_1_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff9_1_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff9_1_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff9_1_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff9_1_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>21</p>
            
            <p>On Shekalim<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  Like the political sky&#44; so is the religious<lb/> atmosphere over laden with threatening clouds.  The<lb/> storm of conflicting opinions has already burst upon<lb/> us.  A warfare is being carried on in the Church<lb/> and the press between unsparing critics&#44; who treat the<lb/> Bible precisely as they would use any secular book&#44;<lb/> and conscientious people&#44; who are greatly scandalized<lb/> at such proceedings.  In that strife we ought not<lb/> to side with either party.  To be sure&#58; as Israelites<lb/> we cannot possibly agree with men who deny Moses<lb/> the inspired authorship of the five books&#44; that have<lb/> been our polar star&#45;&#45;even the sole anchor of our salva&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion.  We cannot agree&#44; because our belief in Mo&#45;<lb/>&#45;saism is founded on more solid ground than mere<lb/> hereditary sediments.  Internal evidences numerous<lb/> and infallible support our creed.  The intimate<lb/> acquaintance which the author of the Pentiteuch<lb/> shows with the language&#44; manners and practices<lb/> of Egypt&#44; should suffice&#44; if other proofs were want&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing&#44; to convince the unprejudiced that we have<lb/> been handed down and have jealously kept authentic records&#44;<lb/> the history and legislation of the Hebrews&#44; as they emanated<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>from the heaven&#45;illumined mind of one born and bred<lb/> in the land of the Pharaohs.  But not because<lb/> we dare not do violence to our convictions and rob<lb/> Moses of his right to our credence and gratitude&#44; do<lb/> we set our faces against all Biblical criticism&#44; as<lb/> an act of impiety.  Th Our position is clear.<lb/>  The planks of our platform are reason and a<lb/> practical good understanding.  No Jew has<lb/> ever been demanded to subscribe to the dogma that<lb/> the Scriptures are from beginning to end a verbal<lb/> communication of the Supreme&#44; miraculously guarded<lb/> against any mistake by amanuenses or copyists.<lb/>  An absurdity of so stupendous a nature belongs to<lb/> other religions.  It was never an article of faith<lb/> in ours.  We venerate the Mikra&#44; or<lb/> &#34;the reading&#44;&#34; as our Bible is termed by way of pre&#45;<lb/>eminence.  We cherish for it the deepest regard<lb/> because its study softens the heart&#44; exalts the<lb/> mind&#44; spiritualizes the soul&#59; because it leads us<lb/> on to goodness&#59; it beckons us back when we have<lb/> swerved from righteousness.  We feel the divine<lb/> breathing in psalms&#44; which bring us penitent<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>to the footstool of Grace&#59; in prophecies which<lb/> picture the tender mercies of the Creator and the<lb/> beauties of godliness.  We see the Divinity in<lb/> sublime morals and in touching poems&#44; even in<lb/> the lives of men and women that figure con&#45;<lb/>&#45;spicuously in the pages of Holy Writ.  But we<lb/> know that Isaiah spoke in a style all aglow<lb/> with a poetry of unsurpassed excellency&#59; that<lb/> Jeremiah is tame in comparison with Ezekiel in his<lb/> bold metaphors.  We do believe that to speak as<lb/> they fearlessly spoke&#44; those teachers of Israel and<lb/> their coworkers at different times must have been&#44;<lb/> beyond doubt&#44; unkindled with a fire from above<lb/> which irresistibly burst forth in words of reproof&#44;<lb/> of admonition&#44; or consolation.  But we recognize<lb/> in them originality.  The language was theirs&#44; not<lb/> God&#39;s.  The influence which prompted the impassioned<lb/> oration was Divine&#59; the oration itself was human.<lb/>  Holding this sensible&#44; and theologically sound idea&#44;<lb/> we are not shocked when critics point to pos&#45;<lb/>&#45;sible errors in narratives&#44; in chronology&#44; in the<lb/> names of persons&#44; or in their age.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Thus by way of illustration&#58; It matters little to<lb/> us&#44; if the copyist misplaced the story of the<lb/> first meeting of Saul and David and gave us is confusedly<lb/> a puzzle in that passage&#44; where presented so that after the vic&#45;<lb/>&#45;torious fight with Goliath&#44; David who had who is supposed to have often<lb/> before played the harp to divert the gloomy thoughts<lb/> of Saul&#44; appears to be a complete stranger to<lb/> the latter.  Enough that the event which<lb/> knit together two kindred souls&#45;&#45;the generous Jona&#45;<lb/>than and the brave David&#45;&#45;is recorded for our edification.<lb/>  So in like manner&#59; it is of no actual importance to<lb/> history&#44; whether Jeojachin reigned only three months<lb/> as stated in one place&#44; or three months and eleven ten<lb/> days&#44; as asserted in another.  What concerns us is<lb/> the sad account of the forfeiting of his crown through<lb/> an unwise conduct&#44; attended as it was by national ca&#45;<lb/>&#45;lamities.  So also no one needs consider it a<lb/> defect in Jewish history that Uzziah should<lb/> differently be called Azariah.  Our interest is en&#45;<lb/>listed in the military genius of that king of Judah&#44;<lb/> and in his successes&#44; which finally engendered pride<lb/> and culminated into an act of impiety.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>It is in a spirit of enquiry to learn to do right&#44;<lb/> and eschew evil&#59; it is in such a spirit of meek&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness that we must read our Bible&#44; admitting<lb/> always without equivocation that discrepancies<lb/> have crept in&#44; despite the exceeding care exercised by<lb/> the Scribes&#44; and never attempting to distort the<lb/> sense&#44; or explain away evident mistakes.<lb/>  Nor should we allow our zeal anxiety for the intact pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;servation of the good book&#44; to overpower truthfulness<lb/> and lead us to deny that&#44; with much which is<lb/> noble in the lives of men of the Bible&#44; there is<lb/> mixed&#44; at times&#44; an alloy of ignobleness and hu&#45;<lb/>&#45;man weaknesses.  We should use the purest<lb/> candor&#44; and thus disarm unsparing criticism&#44; and&#44;<lb/> what is most essential&#44; we would present Holy Writ<lb/> before our intelligent sons and daughters in its pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;per light&#44; extenuating no fault&#44; and setting in<lb/> bold relief what is matchlessly grand.<lb/></p>
            <p>To day our Haftarah invites us to contemplate<lb/> characters&#44; admirable in many respects&#44; yet by<lb/> no means all perfect&#44; if weighed on the scales<lb/> of impartiality.  Indeed&#44; we may consider it fortunate<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>that in the loss sustained of Scriptural books<lb/> which we know only by name&#44; was not also in&#45;<lb/>&#45;volved that of the books of Kings and Chronicles&#44;<lb/> for they supplement each other&#44; and enable us<lb/> to form a just criterion of our ancestors and their<lb/> times.  The scene which the prophetic<lb/> lesson of this Sabbath opens to our views&#44; lies in<lb/> the temple.  We behold a lad crowned with a<lb/> diadem&#59; a priest of commanding appearance stands<lb/> by&#44; and multitudes shout &#34;long live the king.&#34;<lb/>  You recognize in the first Joash&#44; or Jehoash<lb/> as he is variously called.  That scion of the<lb/> stock of Judah was a brand plucked out of<lb/> a burning fire.  His unnatural grand mother<lb/> Athaliah had probably left him for dead among<lb/> all of her own son&#39;s children whom she cruelly<lb/> murdered.  She would reign an absolute queen<lb/> and avenge the blood of the godless prophets&#44; when<lb/> Elijah had slain at the brook of Kishon.<lb/>  Athalia had not forgotten the lessons of her mo&#45;<lb/>&#45;ther Jezebel&#45;&#45;the idolatrous Sedonian who polluted<lb/> the land with her people&#39;s worship.  She vowed<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>to reinstate the brutal Molock and demoralize<lb/> Israel with her abominations.  But to defeat<lb/> her wicked purposes&#44; Providence had raised ano&#45;<lb/>&#45;ther woman.  We do not see her in the group&#44;<lb/> which the picture discloses to our vision.  For<lb/> like a veritable Jewess she labored unseen&#44; yet<lb/> most effectually.  Jehosheba was a sister to the<lb/> late king&#44; but not born of Athalia.  In her<lb/> veins flowed the blood of a mother purely Jewish.<lb/>  On the fatal day of the massacre of the innocent&#44;<lb/> Jehosheba snatched the infant Joash from the jaws<lb/> of death.  With a throbbing heart she had hasten&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed out of the chamber of horrors.  Carrying her<lb/> burden in her arm&#44; she looked for a place of safety.<lb/>  She found it in the Temple&#44; and there Joash was<lb/> hidden from all human eyes.  Our Haftarah<lb/> makes Jehosheba&#39;s concealment of her infant<lb/> nephew six years&#59; an ancient Greek translation<lb/> of the Bible makes it longer&#44; which&#44; for obvious<lb/> reasons&#44; might seem more probable.  But to<lb/> us that point is of minor importance.  We are<lb/> deeply interested not in the lapse of time&#44; that the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>compassionate Jehosheba kept watch over her<lb/> charge that he might not be discovered&#44; but in<lb/> the principles which the guardian angel of that<lb/> child instilled.  She taught him the religion<lb/> of Moses&#44; and the necessity of vindicating the<lb/> outraged Law&#44; working upon his tender mind to<lb/> prepare it for the wholesome reform&#44; which that<lb/> same child was destined to enforce.  But<lb/> Jehosheba was not alone in the holy task.<lb/>  Her husband aided in it with singleness of purpose.<lb/>  We have seen him&#44; the priest of commanding ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;pearance&#44; standing by the young diademed king.<lb/>  Johojada was a worthy colaborer of his wif wise&#45;<lb/>hearted wife.  His abilities&#44; his zeal and his<lb/> sacerdotal influence were brought to bear on the co&#45;<lb/>&#45;education of Joash.  He shaped his feelings aright&#44;<lb/> that he might prove himself a Jew in very<lb/> deed.  He watched for the time when he might<lb/> strike a blow for God and His Torah&#44; and when<lb/> ready to act&#44; he admitted into his secret some<lb/> trusty officers of the government&#44; who held Athaliah&#39;s<lb/> iniquities in abhorrence&#44; and laid out a plan for<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>dethroning the usurper and placing the crown<lb/> on the head of the legitimate descendant of David.<lb/>  The Haftarah for this Sabbath begins with a verse<lb/> on which the entire section hinges.  I need not<lb/> say that the Sages&#44; who arranged the prophetic<lb/> lessons to correspond&#44; as far as possible&#44; to the Pen&#45;<lb/>&#45;teteuchal lessons&#44; chose this because it has refer&#45;<lb/>&#45;ence to the offering of silver shekels for the Temple ser&#45;<lb/>&#45;vice&#44; or as the book of Chronicles calls it &#34;the con&#45;<lb/>&#45;tribution fixed by Moses the servant of the Lord&#34;.<lb/>  I could but repeat myself by speaking of that<lb/> institution&#59; its origin and object&#44; but I can<lb/> never be guilty of self&#45;plagiarism by an allu&#45;<lb/>&#45;sion to the nature of the agreement into which<lb/> the newly proclaimed king sovereign and his<lb/> subjects entered.  Let me read it&#58; &#34;Johojada made<lb/> a covenant between the Lord and the king and the<lb/> people that they would be the Lord&#39;s people.&#34;<lb/>  Understand it.  They all should be on a par in the<lb/> discharge of sacred obligations.  He that were<lb/> the insignia of royalty and the humblest inhabitant<lb/> of Judea should equally bow to a superior power.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>Mosaism was the constitution to which every Jew<lb/> should swear allegiance&#44; and every Jew both the<lb/> highest and the lowliest should constitute himself<lb/> a sentinel sounding the alarm and repelling the<lb/> intruder who dares to attack that bulwark of our<lb/> defence.  Joash seated on a throne could claim<lb/> regard only so long as he&#44; like the least in his kingdom&#44;<lb/> obeyed the ordinances of the Law.  What a lesson<lb/> to our crownless kings and queens&#44; who no sooner<lb/> ascend a step higher in the social ladder than they turn around<lb/> to look down with contempt upon the adherents of<lb/> the precepts&#33;  What a rebuke to those whom the<lb/> will of the faithful has uplifted to a congregational<lb/> height&#44; but who from thence beckon the people<lb/> up to the road of infidelity&#33;  If thou who are<lb/> elevated by reason of their commercial standing or<lb/> their learning&#44; would enter into a covenant with God<lb/> to be His people&#44; we might boast of a Philadelphia<lb/> community of Hebrews&#44; eminently consistent&#44; and uni&#45;<lb/>&#45;versally respected&#44; because self&#45;respecting.  To the<lb/> women of Israel especially does the history of Joash<lb/> commends itself.  It unfolds for their contemplation<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>the labors of years spent by one of their sex to train a<lb/> Jew Jewishly&#44;&#45;&#45;to shape mould his mind so that<lb/> he might find it in his power to restore<lb/> a polluted faith religion to its pristine purity.  Jeho&#45;<lb/>&#45;sheba&#39;s example tells her sisters in faith&#44; more<lb/> forcibly than I could&#44; that a woman has the heart<lb/> of the child in her hand&#44; and&#44; under the guidance<lb/> of Providence&#44; it rests with her to make that child<lb/> a champion of godliness or a leader of infidelity disbelief.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
