<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF10_5</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1894-01" source="" attested="yes">1894</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_5_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_5_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_5_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_5_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_5_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_5_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_5_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_5_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_5_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_5_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_5_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_5_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>94<lb/></p>
            <p>The same lecture&#44; recast&#44; shortened<lb/>
                &#38; somewhat improved upon.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>The story is old&#44; very old&#59; so is nature exceedingly<lb/> old&#44; but who that possesses an appreciative soul<lb/> ever tires in contemplating nature&#39;s beauties&#63;&#45;&#45;so varied&#44;<lb/> so manifold are the glories it exhibits&#44; that it may<lb/> truly be said in the language in our ritual&#58; God reneweth<lb/> every day the wonders of His creation.  Still&#44; there<lb/> exist nearer objects of a greater attraction than even<lb/> the sublime handiwork of the Eternal Lord&#44; manifested<lb/> in the starry firmament.  Those objects of the profound&#45;<lb/>&#45;est admiration are men and women at the portals of<lb/> whose hearts vice lies in ambush to no purpose&#45;&#45;<lb/> men and women whose hearts are steeled against the<lb/> furthest approach of wickedness.  May I not<lb/> sin of impiety&#44; when in the face of such incidents as<lb/> have earned the founder of our people the title of<lb/> &#34;friend of God&#44;&#34; I venture to say that if the first<lb/> book of our Torah had transmitted to posterity only<lb/> the narrative of the sterling virtues of one of Abra&#45;<lb/>&#45;ham&#39;s descendants&#44; it would have deserved our homage&#59;<lb/> our everlasting gratitude.  Let me show in part&#44; for<lb/> the special instruction of Jewish youths&#44; the<lb/> grandeur of that character.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>This morning we are admitted into a family<lb/> circle.  There sits the aged father&#44; whose brow<lb/> early cares have furrowed.  When young&#44; he had become<lb/> the object of the fondest love to a mother indiscreet&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly partial.  His obedience to her order&#44; involving<lb/> the perversion of truth&#44; made him an exile from the<lb/> home in which his affections were centred.  In<lb/> manhood&#44; avarice&#44; which like horse leach of described<lb/> in the book of Proverbs&#44; incessantly cries &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;give&#44; give&#34;&#44; stood up against him to hinder<lb/> his temporal progress.  When after exposure<lb/> to draught in the day and frost in the night&#59; after<lb/> having been overreached ten times by the greed of an<lb/> unnatural relative&#44; he gained a competence through<lb/> means not approvable but excusable under provoking<lb/> circumstances&#44; he travelled to hail again the country<lb/> of his birth&#44; he met what overwhelmed him with<lb/> dread.  The brother he had once offended might<lb/> wreak the vengeance which he had matured in<lb/> his bosom.  When that danger was overcome by<lb/> a Divine interposition that softened the heart of Esau&#44;<lb/> he suffered shame and peril and horror by the<lb/> abduction of his only daughter and the cruel revenge<lb/> taken by two of his sons.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>He had almost arrived at the <sic>threshhold</sic> of the parent&#45;<lb/>&#45;al dwelling&#44; where he hoped to meet joy&#44; when the<lb/> sorest of domestic afflictions was awaiting him.<lb/>  The woman whose love had sweetened his toil and<lb/> made drudgery a pleasure&#44; was prematurely torn<lb/> from his arms by the messenger of death.  Yet&#44; time<lb/> that heals our wounds&#44; had become a restorative also<lb/> to Jacob in his declining age.  Humanly speaking&#44;<lb/> the hoary patriarch might then have enjoyed a<lb/> state of serenity to the end of life&#44; if one of the basest<lb/> passions that man can harbor in his breast&#44; had not<lb/> disturbed the harmony of his household&#45;&#45;envy &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Rottenness to the bones is envy&#34; writes our<lb/> moralist.  A passionate disposition Pride is<lb/> despicable&#44; still while in a latent state&#44; it may<lb/> gratify the silly individual who is flushed with it&#44;<lb/> and do no actual harm to his fellow&#45;creatures.<lb/>  An passionate irritable disposition is very reprehensible.  It<lb/> may&#44; when bursting forth into a furious temper&#44; tear asunder the most<lb/> sacred ties&#44; nevertheless there may exist with it<lb/> generous impulses and by gentle reasoning and <sic>swavity</sic><lb/> of manners the evil disposition may be brought under control.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>But envy&#44; even in a passive state&#44; shows its<lb/> pernicious effects.  Have you ever observed in<lb/> summer nights the feather winged moth&#44; whirling<lb/> round the flame&#44; which will at last consume it&#63;<lb/>  Even like it is envy.  Aye&#58; <sic>rotteness</sic> to the bones&#44;<lb/> as Solomon calls it.  Woe to the mind poisoned with<lb/> it&#44; woe to the unfortunate being against whom<lb/> envy levels its arrows.  It was measurably<lb/> pardonable in Jacob to show Joseph a higher<lb/> degree of affection over the rest of his children.  Joseph<lb/> was the son anxiously looked for&#44; <sic>prayfully</sic> asked<lb/> for by his dear Rachel&#44; and now that she lay<lb/> in her grave&#44; ti seemed as if a twofold spring of<lb/> life ran through the child&#39;s veins.  It seemed<lb/> as if he claimed a double portion of affection.  And&#44;<lb/> as it naturally happens when we love strongly&#44;<lb/> Jacob imagined that the object on bestowed the ten&#45;<lb/>&#45;derest care was so perfect&#44; as to call forth in every<lb/> one the feelings which he cherished.  So did the fond<lb/> parent believe&#44; when he gave Joseph tokens of his<lb/> predilection.  Most sensibly have the Talmudists<lb/> recommended that fathers and mothers will never openly<lb/> show a preference of a child over their other children.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Jacob did not know that his indiscretion sowed<lb/> the seeds of his own misfortune.  Joseph so obviously<lb/> preferred had not been loth to show some degree of<lb/> superiority.  In fact&#44; his dreams&#44; humanly speaking&#44; were<lb/> a manifestation of the ideas which he entertained.<lb/>  To prove that it was so&#44; I have the support of the<lb/> Sages who hold that dreams are mostly the reflect&#45;<lb/>&#45;ion of our thoughts.  For&#44; say they&#44; a person will not<lb/> be likely to see in his sleep&#44; a field sowed with gold golden date tree of<lb/> nor an elephant going passing with through the eye of a needle.  All<lb/> remember the sorrowful sequel of a youth&#39;s ambitious notions.<lb/>  But &#34;there&#39;s a Divinity that shapes our ends&#44; rough<lb/> hue them how we will&#44;&#34; said the greatest of English poets.<lb/>  The Sovereign mind that guides earthly events&#44; had<lb/> discovered in the envied lad a man fit to rule a nation&#44;<lb/> lead chiefs by his sagacity and teach senators wisdom<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#45;&#45;&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> How puny&#44; how utterly insignificant are man&#39;s designs against<lb/> the will of the Omnipotent&#33;  The lad that envy had<lb/> marked out for its victim&#44; the lad whom envy would<lb/> have humbled to the earth&#44; was he that God discovered<lb/> as the fittest to wear the badge of mobility&#44; a crown of<lb/> glory that righteousness weaves for those who fol&#45;<lb/>&#45;low her directions.  Joseph was the impersonation of righteousness.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>How many of us&#44; seeing ourselves the target of rank&#45;<lb/>&#45;ling ill&#45;will&#44; mere chattel in the hand of slave<lb/> traders&#44; falsely accused&#44; unjustly imprisoned&#44; compelled<lb/> to exchange an existence&#45;&#45;the sweetest in the embrace<lb/> of a most loving father&#45;&#45;for an existence of suffering<lb/> and contumely&#44; might have rebelled and denied that<lb/> Providence watches over human affairs.  Joseph under<lb/> his woeful trials might have conceived the idea that<lb/> falsehood yields delicious fruits&#44; truth bitter adversities&#59;<lb/> that cunning is profitable&#44; honesty calls for stripes.<lb/>  Terrible may have been the seductions inciting to wrong.<lb/>  But they lost all power when seeking to master one<lb/> who had made a covenant with the fear of the Lord.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;How can I do this great<lb/> evil and sing against God&#63;&#34;  While under his father&#39;s<lb/> indulgent care&#44; Joseph may have exhibited failings<lb/> attending one in his unripe age.  But when thrown<lb/> on his resources&#44; he arose to the height of full man&#45;<lb/>&#45;hood&#44; armed to resist temptations.  It mattered<lb/> nothing to him&#44; if Potiphar owned him as a slave<lb/> and could have disposed of him at pleasure.  Enough that<lb/> the Egyptian chief had bought him to do him service&#44; &#38; expected fidelity.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>An outcast&#44; poor and unprotected&#44; he did not covet ends riches<lb/> easily gotten by treachery&#44; pleasures which impunity of&#45;<lb/>&#45;fered.  The gloom of a dungeon was a refulgent<lb/> light to Joseph&#44; compared with the dazzling sun of iniquity<lb/> To the chief whose approaching release he predicted&#44; the<lb/> cruelly imprisoned youth did not relate the sad past in<lb/> all its brutality&#44; did not murmur against a doom which<lb/> to others must have appeared an injustice from Him&#44;<lb/> whom Abraham his ancestor proclaimed &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;the<lb/> Judge of the whole earth.&#34;  The imprisoned youth simply<lb/> said&#58; &#34;Do remember me&#44; when it will be well with thee&#44; show<lb/> me kindness to me I pray thee and make mention of me<lb/> to Pharaoh and bring me out of this house&#44; for indeed<lb/> I was stolen away out of the land of the Hebrews&#44;<lb/> and here also I have done nothing that they should<lb/> put me in a dungeon.&#34;  Not a complaint against<lb/> God&#39;s ordination&#44; perfect submission to the decrees of<lb/> a Divinity that shapes our ends&#44; rough hue them<lb/> how we will.  How magnificently shapen by an<lb/> invisible but all watching God&#33;  Goodness coming<lb/> forth to hail her beloved&#44; greatness sent to reward<lb/> preeminent virtues in a being&#44; whose filial&#44; fraternal<lb/> and social qualities reached the loftiest pinnacle<lb/> of sublimity.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Who wonders that Moses himself went in quest of<lb/> the remains of him&#44; who in every relation of life<lb/> performed in advance the moral injunctions&#44; which<lb/> the son of Amram was destined to promulgate<lb/> for the spread of human civilization&#63;  Say the<lb/> Rabbis.  On the night that the bondmen&#39;s fetters<lb/> were loosened&#44; and Israelites looked for the silver<lb/> and gold with which the Egyptians willingly<lb/> parted&#44; Moses was searching for the dead bones of a<lb/> Hebrew&#45;&#45;the midst of virtue&#44; the prince of goodness&#44;<lb/> the type of generosity.  To Moses who would incul&#45;<lb/>&#45;cate the principles of righteousness as the soul of our<lb/> existence &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Righteousness&#44; righteous<lb/>&#45;ness pursue that they mayest live&#44;&#34; to the Moses what<lb/> had been left of that body which had enshrined a ground<lb/> spirit was more precious than the treasures which seas<lb/> and mountains hold.  Children of my people&#44; study<lb/> the life of Joseph in all its vicissitudes&#44; take the son<lb/> of our patriarch Jacob&#44; as a model&#44; and I feel assured<lb/> that you will become splendid representatives of<lb/> our faith&#44; noble men and women of the Hebrew<lb/> race.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
