<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF8_16</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff8_16_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff8_16_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff8_16_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff8_16_2v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 1 sheet<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For a funeral<lb/></p>
            <p>There are sorrows so profound&#59; so crushing of the human spirit<lb/> that an attempt to relieve them must inevitably prove of no a&#45;<lb/>&#45;vail&#59; utterly fruitless.  Nay&#58; to speak thereof sympathetically&#44;<lb/> might be to add intensity to grief&#44; and why should mortals<lb/> make the burden beneath which fellow creatures bend still hea&#45;<lb/>&#45;vier&#44; when it does not lie in their power to lighten its weight&#63;<lb/>  I will not increase the agony of a father bereft of his only<lb/> son&#45;&#45;so necessary to his happiness&#45;&#45;&#44; shortly after having sus&#45;<lb/>&#45;tained the irreparable loss of a fondly loved wife.  I will not aggravate<lb/> the distress of sisters&#44; whose eyes were yet moistened with<lb/> the tears shed for the deprivation of the companionship of a<lb/> revered mother&#44; when a newer misfortune befell them.  I shall<lb/> keep silent on the sudden crash which has overwhelmed a<lb/> family in Israel with dread and its numerous friends with dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;may.  But wrong as it might be in me to deepen a wound<lb/> opened afresh by untimely speaking&#44; I would be surely at fault<lb/> in withholding a meed of praise from real merit&#44; when my words<lb/> may serve as an incentive to good&#44; even if they do not bring<lb/> soothing comfort to the mourners.<lb/></p>
            <p>Henry M. Meyers possessed traits of character&#44; worthy of a laudable<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>mention at this hour&#44; when the body through which<lb/> those qualities were manifested is about to be removed from<lb/> among the living. He was a man of generous impulses.<lb/>  To do his neighbor good&#59; to promote the cause of public<lb/> education and Jewish worship&#44; he did not stop to calcu&#45;<lb/>&#45;late how much would his time and his purse be taxed.<lb/>  He gave without stint and the act made him not<lb/> boastful but joyful.  Within late years our lamented<lb/> brother afforded me the opportunity of observing his voluntary<lb/> contributions to the maintenance of the dwelling of prayer&#59; I have<lb/> heard likewise of his frequent visits to schools of which he<lb/> was a director&#44; and of his gifts to enhance their usefulness&#44;<lb/> and I was told of his sympathetic aid to persons reduced<lb/> from a high to a lowly condition and of his benefactions<lb/> which are the noblest&#44; because performed stealthily&#44; un&#45;<lb/>&#45;ostentatiously.  If it be true&#44; and we dare not doubt<lb/> it&#44; that &#91;Hebrew&#93; Charity delivers from the<lb/> power of Death&#44; then the soul of our departed brother<lb/> is being wafted to the serene regions of eternity&#44; where<lb/> a sainted being awaits to greet his entrance.<lb/>  Still&#44; it is not rare to meet individuals who promptly res&#45;<lb/>&#45;pond to the occasional calls made on their liberality&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>but who are remiss in duties which demand constant self&#45;<lb/>control and denial.  Filial obedience&#44; fraternal consideration and<lb/> forbearance are obligations requiring the continual exercise of ab&#45;<lb/>&#45;negation.  Who will say now in the presence of the dead one that<lb/> he failed or wavered in the practice of that virtue&#63;  Whatever<lb/> early years may have been&#44; I can only who can judge but of later times testify to<lb/> the veneration of Henry M. Meyers for his mother while she walked<lb/> in the land of the living.  I have witnessed the anguish of his<lb/> soul at the decease of her that had given him birth&#59; I have<lb/> noted the evidences of his respect to her memory&#59; and all my<lb/> hearers are aware of his endeavours to surround the home of<lb/> his father and relatives with comforts.  Now&#58; Israelites&#44; if this<lb/> existence held the full measure of our desires&#59; if when the spirit<lb/> which quickens our body leaves its earthly abode&#44; we were to strand<lb/> and go adrift and be lost perish be wrecked for ever&#44; then we might murmur<lb/> and charge our Creator with injustice&#44; for our brother ought<lb/> to have continued here for as long a term again as that which<lb/> he had been permitted to enjoy hitherto.  But reason and<lb/> faith proclaim the deathlessness of our sentiments and aspi&#45;<lb/>&#45;rations.  Reason tells us that the spirit which quickens us vitalizes<lb/> our being can no more perish be lost perish than the harmony of music be<lb/> lost&#44; because the instrument which gave forth sweet sounds<lb/> was broken.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Religion points to immortality as our destined<lb/> heritage.  Imagine&#44; say the Rabbis that a parent<lb/> bids his child fetch from the roof young unfledged pigeons&#44; and<lb/> that the obedient youth after having put the hen to flight&#44; the<lb/> hen&#44; which might not grieve at the seizure of her young&#44;<lb/> falls and dies in the act of coming down&#44; where would<lb/> be the truth of the divine declaration that filial duti&#45;<lb/>&#45;fulness and kindness even towards animals secure hap&#45;<lb/>&#45;piness&#44; where&#44; if immortality were not our final<lb/> habitation&#63;  Oh that it were in my power to make the<lb/> disconsolate feel at this hour so certain a hereafter as our<lb/> prophets and sages felt&#59; of a hereafter in comparably more<lb/> pleasurable than the fleeting present&#33;  They would remembers<lb/> the virtues of the deceased and look upwards with consolation.<lb/>  But who is it that has asked me whether I can declare Henry M.<lb/> Meyers virtuous&#63;  Let him come forward and tell the history of the<lb/> departed.  I did not undertake to recite it.  Were I even fully<lb/> conversant with it I would not relate it at this time.  I simply<lb/> desired to set forth merits which I have discovered that they may<lb/> be reproduced in our offspring to the honor of our belief &#38; the advantage of society at large.  The sins of youth&#44; the shortcomings<lb/> of riper age&#44; the neglect of ancestral ordinances are not a sub&#45;<lb/>&#45;ject which I feel called upon to discuss as an accuser.<lb/>  &#40;The address was lengthened by exhortations &#38; prayers.&#41;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
