<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF3_11</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_11_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_11_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_11_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_11_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_11_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_11_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_11_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_11_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_11_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_11_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_11_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_11_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Post&#45;biblical lecture<lb/>
                No 11<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>All may have been a high hippodrome&#44; but to judge<lb/> from2 that which we understand now by it of1 what<lb/> it was with the ancient Greeks would be to fall into an error.<lb/>  A hippodrome among the would&#45;be polished plo polytheists<lb/> of old Hellas meant more than the name denotes.  Horse ra&#45;<lb/>&#45;cing was alternated with entertainments which entered<lb/> to the savage taste of the general public.  In Judea&#44;<lb/> so long as the laws of Israel were respected&#44; a hippodrome<lb/> and kindred places of amusement would not have<lb/> been tolerated.  Societies to prevent cruelty to animals<lb/> and to children&#44; or to guard the young against demora&#45;<lb/>&#45;lization were not needed.  Only when to ape Grecian&#45;<lb/>&#45;ism became the fashion&#44; and our rulers aimed to ingra&#45;<lb/>&#45;tiate themselves with foreign potentates&#44; objectionable<lb/> sights were introduced into the Holy Land.  Our Sages<lb/> loudly condemned such diversions&#44; but too often with<lb/> no effect&#44; for who can stem the current of popular<lb/> perversion wrong&#44; when set in by those in who <sic>weild</sic> power&#63;<lb/></p>  
            <p>It happened Not long ago it happened that King Alfonso of the Spaniards Spain<lb/> Spain wished to celebrate magnificently his the second<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>marriage of King Alfonso with the Arch&#45;Duchess of Austria.  The<lb/> latter requested as a favor that the festivities might be inexpen&#45;<lb/>&#45;sive&#44; devoting the amount thus saved to the relief<lb/> of people&#44; who had shortly before had suffered by disastrous<lb/> floods.  But the humane queen designed principally wished &#91;&#63;&#93;<lb/> that to prevent the full bull&#45;fights in which the gallant Span&#45;<lb/>&#45;niards take great delight on holidays special festive occasions.  We dispensed<lb/> with Yet so deep&#45;rooted is that barbarous custom&#44;<lb/> that the authorities at Madrid declared it impoli&#45;<lb/>&#45;tic to dispense with that national pastime recreation.<lb/>  So&#44; she whose feelings revolted at a contest between<lb/> infuriated beasts and human beings&#44; may have found it<lb/> necessary to witness the an abhorrent strife for to gain a brutal<lb/> history.  However&#44; it is neither to Spain<lb/> nor to Judea that my thoughts are just now at this moment di&#45;<lb/>&#45;rected.  The shocking spectacle present<lb/> now in my mind took place in Egypt of the Ptolemies.<lb/>  On the occasion which I am about to describe&#44; intoxi&#45;<lb/>&#45;cated ef elephants were exhibited at the hippodrome<lb/> at in Alexandria.  They had been made drunk with<lb/> wine and furious with mixed drugs&#44; for to accomplish a terrible<lb/> purpose.  In a large enclosure&#44; men&#44; women<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>and children might be seen chained in irons bound in fetters.  The<lb/> unfortunate creatures had been doomed to gratify<lb/> the spectators by on being set upon and devoured by<lb/> the elephants.  Immense was the crowd and<lb/> restless in its eagerness for the performance to come off.<lb/>  But this the amusement could not begin till the king arrived&#44; and<lb/> the king was long waited for in vain.  A night<lb/> spent in <sic>banquetting</sic> and debauchery had so stupefied<lb/> Ptolemy Philopater that he forgot the inhuman<lb/> order given.  For it was he&#44; who&#44; to take revenge<lb/> o the Jews in whose Temple at Jerusalem he had<lb/> felt humiliated&#44; determined to make a horrible<lb/> sport of his Hebrew subjects at home.  The more<lb/> was he urged to it&#44; because our people not alone had refused<lb/> to appease his anger by <sic>apostatising</sic>&#44; and but had treated with<lb/> open contempt the few who had among their coreligionists who purchased safety<lb/> by selling their souls to idols.  Accordingly&#44; Phi&#45;<lb/>&#45;lopater had destined many of the recusants to be mangled and torn<lb/> by elephants.  The heathen populace at Alexandria&#44;<lb/> may have looked forward to that issue with pleasure.  to that issue<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>For then&#44; like always&#44; Jews aroused excited jealousy through<lb/> their success in industrial and intellectual pursuits&#44;<lb/> and history tells that our ancestors in Egypt of<lb/> the Ptolemies had risen high.  Disappointed at<lb/> the absence of the King&#44; the ill&#45;natured assemblage dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;persed.  The sight was postponed to the next<lb/> day&#44; but with the same results as on the preceding one.<lb/>  Upon the third day&#44; however&#44; the herald announced the<lb/> coming of their King Sovereign&#44; and the Israelites in fetters chains were<lb/> brought out to confront the infuriated elephants.<lb/>  It has been asserted&#44; and but I am too ignorant of the<lb/> subject to express an opinion&#45;&#45;that the elephant is of<lb/> a nature so sagacious that it can distinguish discern on<lb/> people&#39;s countenance the distress of their minds.  Be it<lb/> so or not&#44; a tradition relates that those animals instead of attacking the wobe&#45;<lb/>&#45;gone Jews bound in chains whose looks implored pity&#44; exhausted their fury on the<lb/> riotous spectators&#44; killing a large number of them.<lb/>  This unexpected occurrence&#44; recalled the wicked ruler<lb/> to his senses.  He saw in it the interposition of Divine<lb/> justice&#44; and altered his conduct towards our people.<lb/>  But the Israelites could not wherever they dwelt did could not easily forget the trials they had<lb/> experienced experienced because of a man&#44; maddened by dissoluteness<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>and fanaticism.  The loyalty which had<lb/> distinguished their intercourse with the dynasty house of the<lb/> Ptolemies&#44; was blotted out from their hearts.  They must have longed for the moment in which they could safely swear fealty to another potentate dynasty.  It is not<lb/> therefore surprising that when Philapater&#44; brought on<lb/> his death prematurely by dissipation&#44; Palestine wel&#45;<lb/> &#45;comed hailed as a liberator Antiochus the great&#44; who claimed<lb/> possession of Syria.  Our ancestors forefathers did not scruple<lb/> breaking off their connection with the young offspring of a<lb/> old former tyrant&#44; and declaring themselves in favor of tributary to<lb/> one who fought to conquer Western Asia.<lb/>  There are records left of letters written by Antiochus III<lb/> expressive of his appreciation of the friendship of the Jews&#44;<lb/> and offering important immunities&#44; useful to our nation<lb/> both socially and politically.  Our progenitors had<lb/> a very good motives reasons for attaching themselves to preferring a ruler&#44; who<lb/> relinquished taxes&#44; and tribute&#44; who encouraged immigra&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion and forbid heathens from offending Jewish laws&#59;<lb/> who filled peopled his dominions with Hebrews&#44; and supplied<lb/> them with means to promote their material welfare.<lb/>  Whatever we may think of his the uncontrollable ambition<lb/> which hastened his the ruin of Antiochus III we must admit that while<lb/> Antiochus III he lived&#44; Palestine enjoyed a degree of internal<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>prosperity and independence rather unusual to a degree almost exceptional during<lb/> the second Temple.  But truly changes<lb/> do not always realize the anticipations which had led<lb/> to their adoption.  After all Not many years elapsed before our ancestors had<lb/> cause to rue the moment hour day that they transferred their<lb/> allegiance from Egypt to Syria.  On the death<lb/> of Antiochus&#44; Seleucus his oldest elder son Seleucus mounted the<lb/> throne to find that the crown rest set uneasily upon<lb/> his head.  His father had left him ample territories&#44; but<lb/> with them heavy obligations to inexorable exactors.<lb/>  Rome once despised in Asia as an impotent upstart&#44; had grown gigantic.  She had humbled Carthage and her notwithstanding the heroism of a Hannibal.  Her eagle soaring<lb/> high&#44; spied from afar a rich prey.  Soon would<lb/> all Asia the world send her its treasuries to the seven&#45;hilled city.<lb/>  Antiochus having dared to measure arms with Roman<lb/> legions was crippled broken in his power and crippled in his means.<lb/>  He pledged himself to pay an enormous tribute to<lb/> the Senate Commonwealth upon the Tiber&#44; and in order to raise the amount&#44; he<lb/> began to plunder the temples of his own Grecian<lb/> idol gods.  His son and successor&#44; in the early part of<lb/> his reign&#44; kept back refrained from indulging in that offensive<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>practice&#44; feeling knowing that it was very it would make him exceedingly unpopular.<lb/>  Still&#44; Seleucus felt the pressure of the yearly payment<lb/> due to Rome.  He welcomed therefore an event&#44;<lb/> which he thought would put him in possession of vast<lb/> sums.  &#91;&#63;&#93; Unfortunately&#44; that event took place in<lb/> Judea.  Onias III was the high priest.  He<lb/> is represented as a God&#45;fearing man&#44; studying the interest<lb/> and honor of his people&#44; and guarding against whatever<lb/> might be detrimental to his religion.  History<lb/> does not relate the origin of a quarrel between Onias and<lb/> a certain Simon a Benjamite.  The latter occupied a public posi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion connected with the Temple.  Having failed to bring<lb/> over to its views the righteous priest over to the views he entertained &#40;whatever these may have been&#41;&#44; he turned traitor<lb/> to his country.  He informed Seleucus that in<lb/> the Temple there were lay large deposits of money&#44; which<lb/> could be seized and laid into on behalf of the royal treasury.  The<lb/> King was not long in <sic>despatching</sic> Heliodorus&#44; an officer<lb/> at his court&#44; to fetch the treasures gold he greatly needed.<lb/>  Onias did not suspecting any foul play&#44; and received Helio&#45;<lb/>&#45;dorus with marked respect.  But when asked to sur&#45;<lb/>&#45;render what had been entrusted to his honor&#44; he protested<lb/> and urged the official not to attempt to forcibly take<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>what belonged to the worship of the sanctuary&#44; and what<lb/> had been placed into his safe&#45;keeping for orphans and wi&#45;<lb/>&#45;dows.  Heliodorus insisted&#44; but his rashness was punished<lb/> like that of Ptolemy Philopater.  Terror&#45;struck&#44; he fell<lb/> insensible and was carried away from the sacred courts.<lb/>  A legend&#44; preserved in the second book of the Maccabees&#44; adds<lb/> that a vision appeared a warrior on horse back magnifi&#45;<lb/>&#45;cently armed and accompanied by two splendid looking youths&#59;<lb/> that while the horse trod upon Eliodorus&#44; the youths scourged<lb/> him severely&#44; and that only through the prayers of Onias the<lb/> King&#39;s officer was brought to&#44; and that when he acknowledged his<lb/> fault and <sic>counselled</sic> Seleucus never to attempt again so heinous an offense. again.  Whether we accept or reject the story&#44; it is at<lb/> all events generally agreed that Heliodorus did not touch the gold which his<lb/> master <sic>covetted</sic> for&#44; and hence the sacrilege was not committed.<lb/>  But treachery had not was still plotting shame and ruin.<lb/>  Senior&#44; the recreant faithless Jew&#44; to screen himself from the hatred<lb/> which he richly deserved&#44; charged the high priest with<lb/> having himself occasioned the event which had so outraged<lb/> the nation&#59; that he had craftily acted in a manner which<lb/> might increase his influence&#44; and further his selfish ends.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Unhappily&#44; men are very apt to listen to<lb/> slander and believe it when directed against one individuals in<lb/> a high positions.  Two factions were the consequence<lb/> of the accusation.  Onias anxious to avoid a conflict<lb/> attended already with blood&#45;shed&#44; went personally to<lb/> Seleucus&#44; convinced the King of the infamy of Simon&#44; the<lb/> informer&#44; and succeeded in having the wicked informer banished<lb/> from Judea the land of Israel.  But it is easier to pour into human<lb/> ears the poison of calumny than to drive it from the mind.<lb/>  Onias The worthy high priest could never regain the universal confidence of<lb/> his countrymen&#44; and of this circumstance men&#44; still more inequitous perfidious<lb/> than Simon&#44; availed themselves to throw Judea into a<lb/> state of anarchy.  But I must put off<lb/> to another lecture the narrative of an episode in our<lb/> history&#44; which&#44; if it brought to light atrocious crimes&#44; it<lb/> unfolded also the goodness self&#45;denial and heroism of the children of<lb/> our race.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
