<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF4_9</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_9_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_9_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_9_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_9_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_9_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_9_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_9_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_9_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_9_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_9_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_9_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_9_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_9_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_9_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_9_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_9_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For Sabbath before Pesach<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  The festival of Passover&#44; soon to be celebrated&#44;<lb/> is religiously and historically of supreme importance.<lb/>  Religiously&#44; because it is the first holds the first ranks first &#91;&#63;&#93; stands prominent among the commandments which<lb/> the descendants of Abraham received&#44; when&#44; according to<lb/> a Divine promise&#44; they they were constituted a nation.<lb/>  Historically&#44; because it proved&#44; at different epochs&#44; a<lb/> standard round which disaffected members of the house<lb/> of Israel finally rallied.  An obvious proof evidence of its ha&#45;<lb/>&#45;ving even been held preeminently in a religious sense&#44; is the<lb/> circumstance that the expression &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;A me&#45;<lb/>&#45;morial of coming out of Egypt&#34; was made to accompany the ordi&#45; dis&#45;<lb/> &#45;nance &#45;charge of almost every ceremonial act.  Our wise teachers<lb/> deemed that even the corner stone upon which all that<lb/> is holy in Judaism rests for support. was built up.  They appear to<lb/> have meant that deliverance from bondage qualified our<lb/> ancestors for duties&#44; the merit of whose performance depended<lb/> on the possession of a free&#45;will.  The evidences&#44; which<lb/> history offers of the great deference ever paid to Pass&#45;<lb/>&#45;over&#44; are various.  Thus we learn that the entrance of<lb/> the tribes into the promised land was signalized by<lb/> its the observance of that religious rite.  Before the war of conquest&#44; they our progenitors<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>encamped in Gilgal&#44; and becomingly preferred them&#45; to<lb/> &#45;selves the for solemnize the aforecited occasion.  Again&#58; centuries<lb/> afterwards&#44; at the restoration from the Babylonian<lb/> captivity&#44; when the rearing of the Temple&#44; which had<lb/> been suspended&#44; by reason of the enmity hostility of Samaritans<lb/> and other inimical hostile inimical peoples&#44; was at length completed&#44; the<lb/> Judeans &#34;kept the feast of unleavened bread seven days with<lb/> joy&#44; for&#44; the Lord had made them glad&#44; and turned the<lb/> heart of the King of Assyria unto them to strengthen their hands<lb/> in the work of the house of God&#44; the God of Israel&#34;.<lb/>  And But very notably during the monarchy twice were our backsliding<lb/> predecessors recalled brought back to the worship of the One Lord Everlasting Being&#44; by<lb/> the public celebration of the holiday&#44; now fast approaching.<lb/>  King Hezekiah and his royal successor Josiah&#44; nearly<lb/> four score of years subsequently&#44; succeeded in reestablishing<lb/>&#44; for a time&#44; the supremacy of the Mosaic code&#44; by<lb/> summoning their subjects to Jerusalem at the Passover<lb/> season.  The measures by which Josiah encompassed<lb/> his righteous end formed the topic of a discourse on an occasion a festive day<lb/> similar to like the present.  Let me present set to view this fe sabbath&#44;<lb/> some of the features in the character of the other noble<lb/> scion of the stock of Judah&#45;&#45;Hezekiah.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  That the minds and hearts of children are fa&#45;<lb/>&#45;shioned in a parental mould is a trite truism&#44; which ever and needs<lb/> renewing experience illustrates. not illustration facts frequently reproduced elucidation.  In like manner&#44; duly<lb/> occurrences undoubted facts demonstrate&#44; that evil &#91;&#63;&#93; companions may gra&#45;<lb/>&#45;dually erase the impressions of a healthful education.<lb/>  But that youths rea brought up amidst seething corruption<lb/> and surrounded by the corrupt should grow excellent<lb/> in morals and wise in understanding would seem im&#45;<lb/>&#45;possible.  Yet&#44; Hezekiah&#44; happily for his nation&#44; pro&#45; forms<lb/> &#45;ved a bright exception to a rule which experience has<lb/> laid down as definitely settled.  Perhaps a mother&#39;s piety influence coun&#45;<lb/>&#45;teracted the baneful effect of a father&#39;s ungodliness example&#44; for&#44;<lb/> the sacred historian&#44; who&#44; in relating to the lives of histo no&#45;<lb/>&#45;tabilities makes frequent at times occasional mention of their maternal origin&#44; may<lb/> have wished to convey that idea in the present instance.<lb/>  But whether the surmise be correct or not&#44; the merit of the<lb/> illustrious monarch is equally deserving of unqualified admiration.  Scarcely<lb/> had he ascended the throne&#44; when he saw ten tribes of Israel<lb/> ready to be swept away by the all&#45;crushing the unsparing besom of Assyria.  Civil<lb/> wars and the weak wavering policy of the last ruler Hoshea the son<lb/> of Elah&#44; had shattered the remains of a once potent nation.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Hezekiah strove with might and main to avert from<lb/> Judah the doom sentenced against the kindred tribes.<lb/>  The signs of the time foreshadowed sore calamities. un&#45;<lb/> &#45;abated energy in following as high national purpose could per<lb/>&#45;chance temper their severity.  Ahaz the impious<lb/> father of a godly son&#44; had basely truckled with <sic>imperilled</sic><lb/> the national cause future of his subjects.  Wit ha sacrilegious hand he had<lb/> robbed the treasury of the Temple to win therewith the favor of Assy&#45;<lb/>&#45;ria.  To With the view of pandering to the wishes of the heathens&#44; human sacrifices&#44;<lb/> so hateful to Jewish hearts&#44; were publicly offered&#44; and when&#44;<lb/> despite such abominations&#44; the principal actor failed to obtain the assist&#45;<lb/>&#45;ance he so craved for&#44; he blasphemed his God and totally<lb/> abolished the service of the Most High.  That his wickedness<lb/> found imitators among all grades of society no needs not<lb/> be demonstrated astonish us&#44; for the vices of the great are always crowned heads are too closely<lb/> copied&#44; but that the conduct was suicidal the insulting lan&#45;<lb/>&#45;guage of held soon after by the Assyrian general forcibly proves.  &#34;I will<lb/> deliver thee two thousand horses&#44; if thou be able on thy part<lb/> to set riders upon them&#34;.  The Hebrew government<lb/> was stood on the verge of decay&#44; Hezekiah lay strong hold<lb/> thereon&#44; and rescued it from the pit of destruction.<lb/>  The good king must have asked himself &#34;how can I<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>stem a current which has swelled up immeasurably<lb/> and overflowedwhelmed vast empires&#63;&#34;  But if he hesitated at<lb/> the though of that Sinnacherib&#45;&#45;the that thunder of war&#45;&#45;Sennacherib&#44; created<lb/> a momentary trepidation&#44; the belief in Almighty God<lb/> suggested the instrument by with which he could to accomplish<lb/> salvation.  An uncompromising reinstatement of the<lb/> Mosaic Sinaic law&#59; a love for the teaching of the Redeemer<lb/> of Jacob&#44; must should be the flaming fire which will put to arrest the<lb/> out advance of the overhwelmingflowing water.  With a zeal that<lb/> has deservedly called for the praises of Seers and<lb/> Sages&#44; Hezekiah era obliterated effaced every monument vestige<lb/> of idolatry and superstition.  The symbolic brazen ser&#45;<lb/>&#45;pent of brass which Moses had made in the wilderness&#44;<lb/> when the Israelites were punished by a bite from a live<lb/> reptile of that nature&#44; he cut into atoms&#44; because it had be&#45;<lb/>&#45;come an object of adoration.  Tradition narrates that<lb/> he even suppressed a book that on the healing art&#44; the<lb/> contents of which was calculated to lead astray.  But the<lb/> efforts to reconstruct the barrier that should have separated Judah<lb/> from the a heathen world&#44; would have been ineffectual&#44; without<lb/> the means to direct enchain the attention to a pure worship.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>The King therefore convened together the descendants of<lb/> Aaron and with in a fatherly admonition address exhorted them<lb/> to rise equal to the emergencies requirements of the time&#44; to appear<lb/> worthy of their extraction and of the divine mission.<lb/>  Then did the imposing sight of the consecrated renovated edifice&#44;<lb/> the familiar sound of Davidical hymns&#44; the harmony<lb/> of the devoted devout consecrated choristers&#44; stir up anew the souls estranged<lb/> from the ancestral religion&#44; &#38; all the Congregation<lb/> bowed in humble adoration and vowed allegiance to the great &#34;I am.&#34;  Like an electric spark shock<lb/> the feelings which prompted the sovereign were com&#45;<lb/>&#45;municated to his subjects&#44; and his pious example these turned upwards<lb/> wrought a reconciliation with to bring about downward ng of from the heavenly King tokens of reconciliation.<lb/>  Hence we find written recorded that God had prepared the hearts<lb/> so suddenly converted&#44; but truly&#44; my Brethren&#44; the Almighty<lb/> acts through human agencies.  It is usual&#44; in Biblical<lb/> style&#44; to ascribe to the Director of the Universe immediate to the a miraculous interposition of&#44; events of a<lb/> very striking character&#44; but although they&#44; like all&#44; assume<lb/> in His the hand of the Almighty Omnipotent a form agreeable to His wise designs&#44; they<lb/> are nevertheless the offspring of our freedom of will.<lb/>  The happy effects of E Hezekiah&#39;s endeavours&#44; partook<lb/> no more of the miraculous wonderful&#44; than the baneful results&#44;<lb/> which attended the misdeeds of his predecessors.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Providence will shape our course&#44; yet&#44; He has granted<lb/> to man the power to follow what is right.  Thus&#44;<lb/> may each of us minister at the altar of the heavenly Director<lb/> Father of the Universe&#44; when he will exercise liberty of action&#44; to the<lb/> benefit advantage of his fellow&#45;beings.  Its influence weight will not be<lb/> so generally felt as that of the illustrious subject of<lb/> our consideration upon the Sabbath&#44; but at home always&#44;<lb/> and abroad&#44; occasionally&#44; it will be productive of abund&#45;<lb/>&#45;ant good.  Mark&#44; my hearers&#44; a further corrobora&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion to this assertion of the result influence of example in the historical incidents we are<lb/> engaged to discuss.  The zealous exertions of Hezekiah<lb/> had been crowned with success.  The service of the Eternal had<lb/> set aside that of <sic>demoralising</sic> deities.  The gates of the<lb/> Temple were opened daily to receive a throng of worship&#45;<lb/>&#45;pers.  But so long as an inimical spirit&#44; harbored<lb/> in the breasts of Abraham&#39;s descendants against one another&#44;<lb/> the labor nobly undertaken that must remain incomplete.<lb/>  Therefore the ruler of Judah sought to rouse again a<lb/> sentiment of national affection&#44; by means of a most solemn<lb/> gathering.  No season appeared to &#91;&#63;&#93; more propi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tious than that which recalled the memory of a com&#45;<lb/>&#45;mon deliverance.  On the fourteenth of Nissan<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>had been proclaimed issued the declaration of Hebrew inde&#45;<lb/>&#45;pendence. that was the dignified assertion of one&#39;s in&#45; &#34;Moses had said to the people&#44; remember this day that you came<lb/> &#45;herent right to act manly&#44; it was the resolve of a out of Egypt&#44; from a house of bondage&#44; remember that the Lord brought you out<lb/> few to form and to remain a compact power. hence&#44; with a strong hand.&#34;  That was the teaching of one&#39;s God&#45;given right to act manly.<lb/>  It was of exhortation to the few to form and remain a compact power under the<lb/> guidance of correct laws.<lb/>  Times had sadly changed since the offspring of<lb/> Jacob had marched to freedom at the light of a heavenly<lb/> pillar&#44; but their righteous monarch trusted to the effects relied on the<lb/> of the imposing occasion thrilling occasion forthcoming to fasten the ancient bond.  And nothing was indeed omitted&#44; which<lb/> might rivet together the hearts of God&#39;s chosen children.<lb/>  Alas&#33; that Holy Writ&#44; however&#44; records the had to chronicle a most humiliating circumstance.<lb/> that The conciliatory and admonitory letters sent by<lb/> Hezekiah to the a residue of the seceding tribes of<lb/> Israel excited general derision&#59; that his messengers mostly met<lb/> with reproaches.  Few only would join their Judean brethren<lb/> in the holy city&#59; and fewer still would qualify themselves&#44; by the<lb/> prescribed purification for offering the Passover.  It was<lb/> principally among those governed by a man who<lb/> <sic>practised</sic> and enforced the behests of God&#44; that the<lb/> festival was celebrated with devotional joy.  For seven<lb/> consecutive days the magnificent courts of the Temple&#44;<lb/> echoed forth the invocations of the faithful.  Backsliding<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>children had unitedly returned to their celestial Parent.<lb/>  What gladness must to the author of that auspicious<lb/> occurrence&#33; have experienced&#33; He had weaned away from<lb/> superstitious creeds a vast number of the recipients of<lb/> a pure religion.  He had inspired reverence for the<lb/> Mosaic law&#44; and had infused withal a spirit of na&#45; patriotism<lb/> &#45;tionality&#44; which promised years of <sic>tranquillity</sic> and inde&#45;<lb/>&#45;pendence.  If the god&#45;like king failed to imbue all the seed of the<lb/> patriarchs with the same feelings for&#44; Alas&#44; those the fault lay in the utter depravity of men sold to idolatry&#44; vice unhappily those Is had become most of them left<lb/> in the former kingdom of Israel were cankered in their<lb/> very vitals.  No power could rescue them&#44; reform heal a moral disease so dep deep&#45;set&#44; but he Hezekiah had heard<lb/> Judah with one voice avow again his allegiance to the<lb/> everlasting Redeemer and his holy word.  Well might<lb/> he now Hezekiah assure his subjects&#44; when threatened with a<lb/> devastating war&#44; that they possessed superior forces than superior to those of<lb/> mighty Assyria &#34;With him there is an arm of flesh&#44; but<lb/> with us there is the Lord our God&#44; ready to help us and fight<lb/> our battles.&#34;  The memorable Passover he had proclaimed<lb/> and the seven additional days of festivty festivity left<lb/> an indelible impression upon the people and on their<lb/> King&#44; and the effect thereof was mirrored in all<lb/> subsequent actions events.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>Dear Brethren.  We The season in which we also will<lb/> sing the hymn of redemption is very nigh.  Let me<lb/> pray that it may not be barren of wholesome fruits.<lb/>  The ceremonies connected wit hit are peculiar&#44; but they offer<lb/> the opportunity to imitate&#44; in a our limited sphere&#44; the<lb/> conduct of the illustrious subject of my remarks whose character and deeds<lb/> I have briefly sketched.  Gather round your table the<lb/> charges committed to your care by Providence.  Instruct<lb/> them by through a rehearsal of the events of the glorious past.  Exhort them to<lb/> steadfastly cling to the Eternal Saviour.  Speak to<lb/> them of the task assigned to the redeemed of thraldom&#44;<lb/> of the bright future promised to Israel.  Let them feel<lb/> that it is a privilege to be the first born of children<lb/> of the Creator&#44; the witnesses of His truths&#44; the indestruct&#45; undying<lb/> &#45;ible messengers of happy tidings to the world.  Our Passover will then&#44;<lb/> like that observed by our ancestors&#44; under the auspices<lb/> of Hezekiah&#44; yield real happiness to our households&#44; and<lb/> blessings to the community of our brethren.  Oh&#33; render<lb/> it Thou so&#44; Omnipotent Lord.  May it be the herald of<lb/> righteousness&#44; of peace&#44; of joy&#44; and increased pros&#45;<lb/>&#45;perity.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
