<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF5_3</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_3_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_3_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_3_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_3_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_3_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_3_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_3_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_3_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_3_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_3_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_3_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_3_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_3_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_3_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_3_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_3_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>13 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>The fear of God<lb/>
                Parashat Nejekeb<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Every thing depends<lb/> upon the will of God&#44; except man&#39;s fear of God.&#34;<lb/>  Brethren&#33;  Whoever studies Holy Writ&#44; with the view to<lb/> learn the duties of life&#44; will be impressed with a principle<lb/> pervading its inspired pages&#59; namely&#58; The creatures of the<lb/> earth and their Creator&#44; stand together in immediate <sic>con&#45;<lb/>&#45;nexion</sic>.  As it im is impossible for the Omniscient<lb/> Lord to be ignorant of human actions&#44; so man cannot<lb/> violate with impunity the laws of the Divine Legislator.<lb/>  &#34;The eye that seeth&#44; and the ear that heareth are constantly<lb/> open&#44; and all our deeds are registered with precision &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Obedience to the Paternal<lb/> will&#44; insures happiness&#44; disobedience entails misfortune.<lb/>  This principle which underlies the religion of Israel&#44; is<lb/> nowhere more forcibly imparted enunciated&#44; than in the lesson<lb/> of this Sabbath.  Attend my friends to the words<lb/> in which Moses addresses the nation at large.<lb/>  Health and prosperity&#44; he says&#44; will flow from<lb/> your observance of God&#39;s commandments.  By faith<lb/> in the Almighty Deliverer&#44; difficulties which you<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>may think insurmountable will be removed&#44;<lb/> and you shall abide at ease.  But take heed not<lb/> to overrate the importance of material wealth&#44; lest<lb/> you be led to covet a gold&#44; the acquisition of which<lb/> will prove a snare to your souls.  For&#44; few are<lb/> man&#39;s real wants&#59; nor does his subsistence depend<lb/> altogether upon the food he eats&#44; but on the dispo&#45;<lb/>&#45;sitions of Providence in his government of the world.<lb/>  A little will comparatively suffice&#44; when the body<lb/> is sound&#44; and the mind contented&#44; while dainties will<lb/> be loathed&#44; if sin has called down upon us celestial<lb/> inflictions.  Affluence&#44; moreover&#44; the inspired<lb/> speaker continues to say&#44; unless acknowledged a spe&#45;<lb/>&#45;cial blessing from the Supreme&#44; may engender pride&#44;<lb/> and sever the bond of human brotherhood.  Expe&#45;<lb/>&#45;riencing none of the hardships that his fellow&#45;being<lb/> endures&#44; to provide for his household&#44; the rich man<lb/> may conceive a false idea of his superiority&#44; forget<lb/> his origin&#44; the gracious favors by which the Omnipotent<lb/> raised him from his lowly state&#59; and ungratefully exclaim&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;My strength&#44; and<lb/> the might of my hand have gotten me this wealth.&#34;<lb/>  But if you bear constantly in mind that the power by<lb/> which you have acquired substance&#44; emanates directly<lb/> from God&#59; that He has vouchsafed it unto you as a<lb/> Divine grace&#44; and not because of nay titles you<lb/> can lay to its possession&#44; then will opulence simply<lb/> furnish you with another evidence of the Providential<lb/> care bestowed by the great Ruler of the universe&#44; and<lb/> humility&#44; charity and thankfulness will be its attendants.<lb/>  And in order to dispel from the mind of Israel&#44; the<lb/> baneful thought of self&#45;sufficiency&#44; or self&#45;righteousness&#44;<lb/> the arch&#45;prophet recapitulates their history&#44; and<lb/> dwells especially on that portion&#44; which testifies to the<lb/> lack of their moral strength&#44; and to their backslidings.<lb/>  He proves by that not alone the folly of claiming<lb/> for oneself undue superiority&#44; but our absolute helpless&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness and the utter dependence of every creature upon<lb/> the mercy of God.  And truly&#44; my Brethren&#33;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>when we see Moses a suppliant at the footstool of<lb/> the Lord&#44; for the sin of Aaron&#44; we may ask in the<lb/> language of Elisha&#44; the Gemanite &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;What is man that he should be pure&#44;<lb/> and the born of a woman that should be declared right&#45;<lb/>&#45;eous&#63;&#34;&#44; &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Behold&#33; he<lb/> putteth no trust in his holy ones&#44; yea&#44; the heavens are<lb/> not pure in his eyes.&#34;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;How much more than the filthy and corrupt&#44; a human<lb/> being&#44; who drinketh iniquity like water&#63;&#34;  No&#59; power<lb/> and wealth should not inspire haughtiness&#44; for the more<lb/> lofty is our position&#44; the greater are the dangers taht<lb/> surround it.  The higher is the step we have ascended&#44;<lb/> the severer really be our fall.  But gratitude to the<lb/> Bestower of all good&#44; will beget a spirit of meekness&#44;<lb/> and the latter a wish to gladden other hearts with<lb/> the fruition of the divine blessings we enjoy.<lb/>  Impressed with the thought of our common origin&#44; and<lb/> common destination&#44; feeling that the Sovereign Creator<lb/> of mankind&#44; could not have destined some of his<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>creatures to abject misery and some to overtowering<lb/> greatness&#44; we shall employ the means at our<lb/> command to alleviate sufferings&#44; to extend to our fel&#45;<lb/>&#45;low&#45;mortal the hand wi which will uplift him<lb/> from the dust.<lb/></p>
            <p>Nature&#45;&#45;the hand&#45;maid of heaven&#45;&#45;has imparted<lb/> imprinted on the human soul&#44; sentiments of beneficence2<lb/> and compassion1&#44; but self&#45;love&#45;&#45;which is also an<lb/> inborn passion&#45;&#45;asserting higher claims&#44; often destroys <sic>paralizes</sic><lb/> our noblest instincts.  Religion then intervenes and<lb/> teaches us the obligations we owe to ourselves and those<lb/> due unto others.  It tells us&#44;&#45;&#45;what we have heard in<lb/> the section of this Sabbath&#45;&#45;that we have not been<lb/> placed upon earth&#44; to scramble for the largest share<lb/> of goods&#59; that it is intended we should labor<lb/> for our future further advancement&#44; but that in stri&#45;<lb/>&#45;ving to progress in the road of honors&#44; we must<lb/> not overlook or push aside our brother the feeble<lb/> and the needy.  It tells us to remember that what&#45;<lb/>&#45;soever we possess is not our inherent right&#44; but a<lb/> favor &#91;&#63;&#93; from the Omnipotent Guides of our existence.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>That to Him we are amenable for our actions&#44;<lb/> because He has granted us unrestrained freedom of<lb/> will.  Therefore my beloved hearers&#33; the same voice that spoke to<lb/> our ancestors&#44; addresses us also in these terms &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;And now O Israel&#33;<lb/> what doth the Lord Thy God require of thee&#44; but only<lb/> to fear the Lord Thy God.&#34;  He that provides for the<lb/> sustenance of the smallest animalcules&#44; will not suffer<lb/> thee to hunger.  Health and social distinctions may<lb/> likewise be thine&#44; if He so disposes&#44; for every thing<lb/> depends on His will&#44; bu tthe heart to feel that He<lb/> is the sole author of thy earthly prosperity&#59; the mind<lb/> to consider thyself bound to his obedience&#44; is that<lb/> which proceeds not from above.  Thou must exercise<lb/> thy reasoning faculties and become penetrated with the<lb/> fear of the Lord.  &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Every<lb/> thing is &#91;&#63;&#93; in the power of God&#44; except man&#39;s fear<lb/> of God.&#34;  But why&#44; my Brethren&#33; have<lb/> we been asked to so train our thoughts&#44; that a reveren&#45;<lb/>&#45;tial awe for the Creator may pervade them&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Will it benefit Him&#44; whose glory the boundless space<lb/> cannot contain&#44; whether we bend the knee before<lb/> His August Majesty&#44; or refuse to pay Him homage&#63;<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Thy wickedness&#44; said the<lb/> eloquent Elihu to Job&#44; may hurt a human being<lb/> as thou art&#44; and thy righteousness may profit the<lb/> son of man&#44; but God what can He receive at thy<lb/> hands &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#63;......Not for his<lb/> but for thy good&#44; exclaims Moses&#44; must the fear<lb/> of the Lord be continually before thine eyes.  It will<lb/> prevent the commission of misdeeds&#44; injuriouses alike<lb/> to the individual and to society.  Regard for ill&#45;<lb/>gotten wealth&#44; judicial skl skill misused in the<lb/> <sic>defence</sic> of wrong&#44; the oppression of the weak and<lb/> powerless&#44; will b not be observed among those who<lb/> dread the displeasure of the ubiquitous and impartial<lb/> Judge.  vice shall be be loathed&#44; because God<lb/> abhorreth it&#59; virtue shall be respected&#44; because it<lb/> is acceptable to the Lord.  The orphan and the<lb/> widow will readily find protection&#44; and the foreigner<lb/> will meet among strangers a brotherly reception&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>for&#44; a merciful King has singled them out<lb/> as the special objects of consideration.  The<lb/> fear of the Lord will draw man to man&#44; with kindness<lb/> and forbearance&#44; for&#44; it teaches that to cast off our fellow&#45;<lb/>creatures&#44; is to offend <sic>theyr</sic> Maker &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  The fear of<lb/> the Lord will awaken a desire to withdraw the guilty<lb/> from the way of perdition&#44; and counsel the wavering&#44;<lb/> for&#44; we2 are told&#44; that its1 object&#44; is &#34;to disentangle us<lb/> from the snares of death.&#34;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> The fear of the Lord will set upon earth a high and exalted<lb/> throne to justice and charity&#44; for those two virtues are<lb/> mirrored in all the dealings of Providence&#44; and He taketh<lb/> delight in their exercise&#44; as we read&#44; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;He loveth charity and justice&#34;.  The fear of the<lb/> Lord sanctifies domestic affections.  The husband<lb/> who discovers everywhere the eye that watches his<lb/> actions&#44; will remain faithful to his trust&#59; the wife<lb/> who is so heavenly proceeds under the same direction&#44; will never falter in the<lb/> discharge of her duties.  Children will&#45;&#45;under all<lb/> circumstances&#45;&#45;honor their parents as the delegates<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>of heaven&#44; and they who have been nustled nurtured<lb/> at the same breast&#44; will deem it their mutual<lb/> support an obligation to Him who bid His angels<lb/> guard their infant frames.  Let it not surprise<lb/> us therefore&#44; that the Lord doth require that we learn<lb/> to fear Him&#44; for&#44; we must needs perceive in the<lb/> request a token of Divine love.  To sow the<lb/> seeds which will <sic>yeild</sic> individual and social<lb/> happiness&#44; has the wise Creator commissioned his<lb/> prophets&#44; to teach us the manner of securing it.<lb/>  Having endowed his rational creatures with freedom<lb/> of action&#44; he cannot control the religious bent of their<lb/> minds&#44; but like a fond parent He exhorts them<lb/> to incline it their thoughts to that&#44; which will work their<lb/> salvation here and hereafter&#59; namely&#44; the fear<lb/> of God.  Friends&#33;  A happy coincidence<lb/> has made it the privilege of a young scion of from the<lb/> stock of Israel&#39;s household to recite the portion&#44; which contains<lb/> a lesson of so great a moment.  How deeply<lb/> significant are the words&#44; which his lips first uttered<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>before the congregation of the Lord&#33; To us they<lb/> sounded as the exhortation of innocence&#44; to him they were<lb/> a public confession of faith&#44; the foreshadowing of<lb/> his future career.  At an age when the heart is<lb/> unsullied  by worldly passions&#44; he approaches with a<lb/> blessing the altar of his God.  He offers thanks that<lb/> he can be reckoned among those who hold communion with<lb/> the living Redeemer&#59; that he is a member of that<lb/> family&#44; who hold selected as the repository of the law of Truth. divinely taught&#33; Oh&#33; may you<lb/> my young brother&#44; find strength to <sic>fulfil</sic> the precepts<lb/> enjoined therein&#33;  To impl exemplify in your life the<lb/> principles you have this day declared.  You  cannot well<lb/> understand&#44; how wishes yet unfelt&#44; may challenge<lb/> your ability to stand <sic>immoveably</sic> by the ancestral<lb/> religion&#44; but they may rise&#44; and you will need<lb/> manly courage to resist them.  Set the fear<lb/> of God be your armour&#44; and the victory will be you shall come forth victorious<lb/> yours&#44; when assailed by wicked passions.<lb/>  A fortune has been bestowed upon you&#44; of which<lb/> some among your coevals deprived.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>your habits&#44; like those of the youth I addressed two sabbaths ago&#45;&#45;<lb/> your habits are fashioned in a sound mould&#44; you<lb/> will never be placed in the terrible alternative&#44;<lb/> either to disobey your parents&#44; or prove false to<lb/> your professions.  Under your own roof&#44; you daily<lb/> learn that religion is preeminently entitled to your<lb/> regard.  What Israel has been commanded to<lb/> revere&#44; is sanctified within the walls of your house.<lb/>  That which the Mosaic code <sic>prounces</sic> unholy&#44; does<lb/> not pollute your hearth.  You need not apprehend<lb/> that extreme anxiety for your material temporal welfare&#44;<lb/> may cause your parents to neglect your spiritual<lb/> happiness.  With solicitude will they go in quest<lb/> of the means by which you may obtain competency&#44;<lb/> but with still more earnestness&#44; they will endeavour<lb/> that you become rich of in those ideas that will endear<lb/> the word of the Creator to your heart&#44; that you may<lb/> prize it highly&#44; and pride distinguish yourself for the possession of that possess knowledge&#44;<lb/> for your piety&#44; for your incorruptible morals.<lb/>  Bow then reverently before Him who has so incal&#45;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p>&#45;culably blessed your existence.  Give praise<lb/> to Him who has so diligently guarded your tender<lb/> feelings from prevailing corruption&#44; and let this day<lb/> which forms an epoch in your life&#44; be the herald of<lb/> good tidings to those who have gladly witnessed your<lb/> religious initiation.  Promise in your mind again&#44; &#34;to<lb/> fear the Lord thy God&#44; to walk in His ways&#44; and<lb/> to love Him&#44; and to serve Him with all your heart and<lb/> with all your soul&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  So may it be.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
