<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF2_12</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_12_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_12_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_12_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_12_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_12_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_12_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_12_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_12_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_12_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_12_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_12_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_12_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>on penitence<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Thou has forgotten the Lord Thy Maker&#44; He who<lb/> stretched forth the heavens&#44; and laid the foundation of the<lb/> earth&#44; and art continually every day afraid&#44; because of the fury<lb/> of the oppressor&#34;  My Brethren&#33; When the words of <sic>Isiah</sic><lb/> just quoted from the prophetic section of this Sabbath&#44;<lb/> recur to my mind&#44; I feel really pained at heart&#44; for&#44; in<lb/> them I see a graphic description of an evil which is acquiring<lb/> preponderance even among the seed of Jacob.  I mean&#58; the<lb/> absence of faith&#59; of that faith in the justice of Providence&#44;<lb/> which the Talmudists declared to be the characteristic of<lb/> Israel &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; and which did form the noblest<lb/> feature in their national countenance&#44; ere they it became<lb/> disfigured by the touch of a contaminating world.<lb/>  They who in every page of the written and oral law<lb/> are shown the never&#45;slumbering eye that watches their human<lb/> steps&#44; say nowadays to themselves&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;What is the Almighty that we should serve<lb/> Him&#44; and what will avail us when we beseech Him&#63;&#34;<lb/>  Nations or individuals may write under the strokes of<lb/> adversity&#59; but few will seek the cause within themselves&#59;<lb/> few will follow the counsel of our wise Teachers&#44; that<lb/> when calamity befalls us&#44; we should scrutinize our actions&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> No say they God is too exalted to take cognizance of those<lb/> who dwell in tenements of clay.  He who is enthroned<lb/> above the sky&#44; will not lower his vision&#44; to note man&#39;s<lb/> outgoings and coming in.  Are our fondest anticipations<lb/> frustrated&#63;  Why&#58; it was the effect of chance.  Are our<lb/> commercial schemes brought to naught&#63;  Has the vessel which<lb/> conveyed abroad our precious machinery gold become a prey to the waves&#44;<lb/> or to the enemy&#39;s hatred&#63;  Are we domestically afflicted&#63;<lb/>  It is the effect of chance.  Is the soil once smiling with<lb/> pasture&#44; converted into arid earth&#63;  Do the clouds refuse to<lb/> discharge aid us with their benign influence&#63;  Is the face of the land<lb/> shrouded in darkness&#63;  Is a deluge of blood sweeping away<lb/> her inhabitants&#63;  It is all but chance.  Oh human stupidity&#33;<lb/>  We will invest with supernatural powers that which<lb/> has no existence&#44; and impiously deny that there does exist<lb/> above us &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;An eye that seeth&#44; and an<lb/> ear that heareth&#34;.  To be sure&#59; God in dealing with<lb/> his creatures does not work constant miracles &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Nature follows its fixed laws.  But He who is the<lb/> author of nature&#44; has not foregone His hold thereof.<lb/>  Its various workings are but the messengers of His<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Divine will.  Sublunary events are shaped by the finger<lb/> of the Lord&#59; they subserve His wise purpose &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; whether to chastise the wicked&#59; to<lb/> benefit his people&#44; or to show mankind compassion.<lb/>  Such&#44; my Brethren&#44; is the imparting of your religion&#59;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;The Lord is high&#44; but<lb/> He looketh below&#34; Such is also the doctrine which our Rabbins<lb/> exemplified in their lives&#44; and in which they gloried.<lb/>  It is narrated in the Talmud&#44; that an individual personage<lb/> of acknowledged piety met with reverses.  Those who<lb/> really wished his welfare&#44; advised that he should search&#44;<lb/> whether he had in his daily walks swerved form the<lb/> path of rectitude.  The intimation occasioned displeasure&#44;<lb/> and it found utterances vent.  &#34;Am I suspected by you&#44; to have<lb/> acted wrongly&#34;&#63;&#44; asked the same individual&#44; but his friends<lb/> inquired in return&#34; Do you suspect God to do what is injustice&#34;&#63;<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93; The reproof kindly intended&#44;<lb/> was meekly received&#44; and amendment followed.<lb/>  Aye&#44; my friends&#33; when the heart is not tainted with<lb/> the skeptical notions so prevailing in this degenerate<lb/> age&#44; afflictions&#44; whether public or private will soften<lb/> it&#59; out of the crucible of tribulations it will issue forth<lb/> purified sevenfold.  But when man looks upon<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>this nether world&#44; as on a ship without a pilot&#44;<lb/> and on its denizens as mere jugglers striving to supplant<lb/> and overreach eachoneanother&#59; when the mind either puffed<lb/> with mundane knowledge&#44; or void of all intelligence&#44;<lb/> attributes to blind chance that which is the emanation<lb/> of supreme wisdom&#44; then neither the gentle admonitions<lb/> of friends&#44; nor the paternal corrections of heaven will effect<lb/> a change.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  &#34;They have laid hold of<lb/> deceiving &#40;thoughts&#41;&#44; they refuse to repent&#34; But in our<lb/> text we read &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;thou hast forgotten the Lord<lb/> thy Maker&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; but therefore art thou continually<lb/> every day not in dread of the fury of the oppressor&#34;; that is&#44;<lb/> thou wilt not confide in Him who alone can save and<lb/> comfort&#44; consequently art thou agitated by forebodings of<lb/> sad reverses.  For the disbelief in Providence&#44; does not imply<lb/> a perfect freedom from any apprehension of approaching<lb/> evils.  On the contrary&#58; while he who has the Almighty<lb/> constantly before his mental vision&#44; will be calm amidst<lb/> the storms of adversity&#45;&#45;for he knows and feels that<lb/> the Father of mercy will not lay upon him a heavier burthen<lb/> than he can bear&#45;&#45;he who hardens himself against<lb/> that belief&#44; has a sound of dread terror in his ears&#59; even<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>in prosperity&#44; he imagines that the destroyer is hastening<lb/> toward him &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Thus we read in the book of Job&#44;<lb/> and so true it is&#44; that if you attentively observe&#44; you<lb/> will discover that they who boast of their free&#45;thinking&#44;<lb/> are nevertheless swayed by superstition&#44; which will be discarded<lb/> by him who only fears the Lord God.  Faithful to the<lb/> teaching of his religion&#44; he will acknowledge that<lb/> suffering is at the heel of sin.  Let me say it in<lb/> the language of Ezekiel.  &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;hath the<lb/> rod blossomed&#63;  It is because &#34;pride hath budded forth&#34;.<lb/>  Is the arrow <sic>levelled</sic> at us and shot&#63;  It is we that<lb/> gave it the impetus &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Oh&#63;<lb/>  What carnage &#38; a devastation&#33; look at human unrighteousness I say.<lb/>  Oh what plunder and conflagration&#33; see the prevailing<lb/> dishonesty and peculation&#44; I exclaim&#44; We ourselves build the steel<lb/> which traces our condemnation upon adamant.  God<lb/> reviews our deeds in his tribunal&#44; we are faced to pronounce<lb/> our own verdict.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> The inequities he hath committed overtake the wicked man<lb/> he is held by the cords of his sin.  Mark&#44; my Brethren&#33;<lb/> the words employed by the moralist &#91;Hebrew&#93;.<lb/>  He himself has spun and woven the bands that<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>irresistibly consign him to misery.  It is not<lb/> the world of chance&#44; but the effect of his own<lb/> deliberate doings&#44; judged by the omniscient Being whose spirit<lb/> pervades the universe.  Beautifully is<lb/> this truth illustrated by one of our Sages.  He says<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;A King had<lb/> a watch&#44; of which he made a present to his beloved<lb/> child&#34;  God in his infinite love has gifted us<lb/> with freedom of will&#59; by guiding it aright&#44; we can<lb/> secure our happiness.  That is the watch of which<lb/> the Talmudist allegorically speaks.  If we incessantly<lb/> attend to its mechanism&#59; it will ever remain under our<lb/> control.  For&#44; It is in our power either to restrain the rapidity<lb/> of its wheels&#44; or to impart to them a quicker motion.  We<lb/> can also direct the hands and they will register the<lb/> correct hour of the day&#59; but if we suffer it to proceed<lb/> without guide and regulation&#44; it will surely lead us astray.<lb/>  We may then be induced to go hurriedly forth when we should<lb/> have been at rest&#44; or we may keep inert at times that<lb/> we should be steady at work.  The application<lb/> is obvious&#44; and you have already comprehended to<lb/> Freedom of will is an inestimable boon of the Deity.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>By it are we distinguished from and raised above<lb/> all animated beings.  Accompanied Guided by reason and the<lb/> expressed word of God&#44; we can through it its medium become a<lb/> Moses or an Abraham&#44; and gain a proportionate reward<lb/> here and hereafter.  Abandoned to itself&#44; it may will<lb/> abuse its powers&#44;&#45;&#45;through the allurements of passions&#45;&#45;&#44;<lb/> and turn us into a Jeroboam&#44; drawing upon us a corresponding punish&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment and everlasting shame.  Therefore it is Hence we find written in<lb/> the section of last Sabbath &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Behold I set before you this day&#44; a blessing and a curse.  The<lb/> blessing if you will hearken unto the commandments of the<lb/> Lord your God&#59; and the curse if you will not hearken to them&#59;&#34;<lb/> purposing to signify that as the Almighty has endowed<lb/> every man with unrestrained liberty of action&#44; it rests with<lb/> him to choose whether to follow he will adhere to the Divine prescriptions and &#91;&#63;&#93; obtain<lb/> at peace spiritual repose&#44; or to cling to the dictates impartings of his feeble<lb/> conceptions and be never at rest repose &#91;&#63;&#93; spiritual be never at peace.<lb/></p>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  The opening of this month&#44; which&#44; they<lb/> who follow our ritual&#44; devote to <sic>prepratory</sic> prayers<lb/> and deeds of abstinence voluntary penance&#44; has suggested my brief remarks.<lb/>  Take them to heart.  When struck by the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p><sic>appaling</sic> disaster with which we have been<lb/> nationally afflicted let each of you ask himself &#34;Have my misdeeds<lb/> been in any degree a cause to this celestial heavenly infliction&#63;<lb/>  And if you discover that you have been relaxed in the rules<lb/> of morality&#59; that your religion was not pure love for<lb/> God&#59; if you perceive that in the turmoil of business<lb/> you became insensible of the cry of justice and charity voice that constantly cries<lb/> that says &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; &#34;righteousness&#44; righteousness<lb/> alone thou shalt pursue&#34;; that&#44; fearing some impending reverse&#44;<lb/> you forget the Lord your Maker who saves and comforts&#44; and<lb/> labored strove only to place of your substance gold beyond the reach of the<lb/> enemy&#39;s hand&#44; though to the detriment of the interest of your interest fellow&#45;creation.<lb/>  If you&#44; in short&#44; detect anything in your conduct antago&#45;<lb/>&#45;nistical to the dictates of conscience and Holy Writ&#44; speedily<lb/> amend your course&#44; that you may&#44; according conformably to the expression<lb/> of King David&#44; uplift your hands on high&#44; cleared of all<lb/> pollution&#44; on the solemn days now fast approaching &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Then He who spread out<lb/> the heavens and land the foundation of the earth&#44; will mer&#45;<lb/>cifully decree that they who are held in the captivity of<lb/> sin&#44; shall not die in the pit dungeon&#44; nor ever lack their the means<lb/> daily bread of supporting their existence from now and evermore.  Amen<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
