<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF2_6</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_6_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_6_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_6_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_6_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_6_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_6_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_6_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_6_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_6_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_6_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_6_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_6_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>On Joseph&#39;s political administration&#47;50<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>From whatever point of view we look upon<lb/> Joseph&#44; we see him tower high and reach a moral<lb/> altitude nearing close to perfection.  The love of man nobly<lb/> illustrated exemplified by his immortal ancestor&#44; who prayed to did not grow weary<lb/> in praying to God for the deliverance of the a most sinful among<lb/> peoples&#44; stirred within the heart of the wise coun&#45;<lb/>sellor&#44; who gave Pharaoh timely directions to save<lb/> a country from famine &#91;Hebrew&#93;  When<lb/> he so mercifully advised&#44; Egypt had been an engine<lb/> of torture to both his the his mind and body of the guileless youth&#44; but vindictive&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness&#44; resentment&#45;&#45;vulgar passions&#45;&#45;had no dwel&#45;<lb/>&#45;ling place where humanity was stood enthroned.  The<lb/> forgiving disposition of Abraham evinced towards<lb/> the orphaned nephew he had reared watched over with parental<lb/> tenderness&#44; was also engrafted upon the soul of Joseph.<lb/>  It revealed itself even more luminously than in<lb/> the dealings of his illustrious predecessors.  Lot had<lb/> separated from his the benefactor of his childhood youth early days youth with<lb/> apparent indifference&#44; caring principally to secure<lb/> a spot which promised the best pasture ground.<lb/>  Abraham&#44; responding to his generous instincts&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>risked nevertheless his own existence to save rescue the the inconsiderate selfish egotistical Lot when<lb/> threatened with the loss of life and property imminent danger&#59; but<lb/> Joseph exceeded that generosity&#44; he clasped to his breast bosom those who had sought<lb/> his death&#44; or what is more bitter still his would deliver consign him to abject his abject slavery.<lb/>  He nourished them his envious brothers&#44; he made provisions for their<lb/> future welfare&#44; and with a gentleness which partook<lb/> of the Divine&#44; endeavoured to draw out of their<lb/> guilty consciences the sting of remorse.  If it is<lb/> within reach of mortals to become godlike&#44; the virtues<lb/> of Rachel&#39;s beloved son gave him a title claim to that<lb/> title.  The sacred pages which tell of his history<lb/> are an ode to his sublime qualities&#44; and our<lb/> feelings reecho spontaneously the utterances of the dying father&#44;<lb/> as he pours forth the richest blessings on the head of<lb/> the child who grew to be &#34;the shepherd&#44; the foundation<lb/> stone of the household of Israel&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>  But readers of the inspired writings&#44; justly<lb/> filled with admiration for the character of the<lb/> typical Hebrew illustrious noble glorious in his conduct glorious whether as a servant&#44; and or<lb/> as a master exemplarily great as a son and as a brother&#44;<lb/> readers have failed to notice one prominent feature.  It<lb/> stands out conspicuously now&#44; perhaps more than<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>ever&#44; by reason of a social problem&#44; enga&#45; on whose<lb/> &#45;ging the attention solution the minds of thinkers in all civilized everywhere<lb/> lands are deeply interested engrossed.  To that feature&#44; I will direct the atten&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion of my hearers for a few moments.<lb/></p>
            <p>The famine had become exceedingly sore.  The <sic>mar&#45;<lb/>&#45;vellous</sic> foresight of Joseph had prevented starvation&#44;<lb/> and brought to Egypt a a wealth unprecedented.<lb/>  The Scriptures attest that the countless sums<lb/> gathered by the sale of corn during five years&#44; Joseph carefully stored up away to<lb/> fill the king&#39;s treasury.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Ought that to be accounted a merit to the prime<lb/> minister&#44; I mean&#44; the circumstance that he enriched made the rich sovereign richer&#44; and impoverished let<lb/> the poor be more impoverished&#63;  We must Let us All will give Joseph all credit for<lb/> his thorough honesty.  He studied the interest of<lb/> his superior&#45;&#45;the monarch whom he served.  No&#45;<lb/>&#45;thing that belonged to Pharaoh&#44; according to the<lb/> notions of the time&#44; or&#44; as we would say&#44; nothing<lb/> to which the government had conceded a right&#44; he appro&#45;<lb/>&#45;priated to himself.  And we all might well wish<lb/> that such principles guided all persons so public&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly employed.  We would not then be put<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>to the blush by an daily revelations of breaches<lb/> of trust&#44; peculations&#44; defalcating forgeries&#44; all manner of corrupt&#45;<lb/>&#45;ion in high places.  But would an administra&#45;<lb/>tion that reduced the labour to penury&#44; even to beg&#45;<lb/>&#45;gary&#44; accord with the humanitarian views which<lb/> we the creatures of One God ought to entertain&#63;  It might have been<lb/> justifiable during the five seven years of plenty to exact<lb/> one fifth of the produce for further use&#44; as as we are told that<lb/> Joseph suggested according to the Biblical narrative.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> The people possessed then an overbundance<lb/> and were willing to be so taxed&#44; but when hunger want<lb/> began to be felt&#44; and gaunt was famine stared in the face&#44; when money was was exhausted to in<lb/> buying the necessaries of life&#44; was it kind in Joseph<lb/> to demand the exchanging of people&#39;s cattle and<lb/> beasts of burden for corn&#44; thus creating destitute com&#45;<lb/>&#45;munities in order that the king might own subject to the tyrannical will of a king&#44; who could en&#45;<lb/> even their bodies with their grounds&#63; &#45;slave millions who that hungered for bread&#63;  The transaction<lb/> does seems very cruel.  But when we follow it up to<lb/> the end&#44; and when we bear in mind&#44; besides&#44; that<lb/> the history up to which we are referring takes us back<lb/> neary four thousand nearly 35 hundred years&#44; we must and that a sovereign<lb/> Sovereign was then absolute master&#44; of his subjects&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>as clearly indicated in the words &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;I am Pharaoh&#44; but without<lb/> thee no man shall lift up his hand or his foot in all the<lb/> land of Egypt&#59;&#34; when we reflect upon consider all that&#44; we<lb/> must look turn with grateful admiration upon towards the<lb/> ancient viceroy for the merciful arrangement into which<lb/> he finally entered.  He dared not say to an autocrat<lb/> &#34;thy subjects are famishing&#44; thou art in duty<lb/> bound to support them with the immense surplus<lb/> thou hast at thy disposal&#44; which was theirs&#44; and<lb/> which my own sagacity procured.&#34;  For had he<lb/> spoken so&#44; he might have endangered his position&#44;<lb/> perhaps his life&#44; and accomplished no good.  But the<lb/> prudent man trusty official acted with that foresight th which so distinguished<lb/> him and with broad philanthropy.  He nominally<lb/> bro bought the entire land and declared Pharaoh<lb/> the sole proprietor&#44; but furnished farmers and agri&#45;<lb/>&#45;culturists with the means to follow their callings<lb/> prosperously&#44; allowing them four parts of their<lb/> earnings&#44; asking simply one fifth as a yearly<lb/> tribute to the king.  Then to prevent the overcrowding of one spot&#44; breeding many evils&#44; he <sic>parcelled</sic> out the<lb/> population&#44; moving families to different cities&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>so that the country at large might enjoy<lb/> the increase of able bodied capable of inhabitants apt to improve it.<lb/>  The monarch&#44; claiming the ownership of all the land&#44;<lb/> was naturally n interested in its productiveness&#44; and<lb/> he would encourage industry and retain on the ground&#44;<lb/> only nominally tenanted&#44; but of which whose <sic>yeilding</sic> he received only one<lb/> fifth&#44; those who became attached to it and enhanced<lb/> its value.  The rent or tax would never become<lb/> too oppressive&#44; for Pharaoh would have to bear under any circumstance the<lb/> share of loss by poor cross under any circumstance. through a failure of or insufficiency shortness of the crops.<lb/>  The misery into which landlordism has plunged<lb/> Ireland&#44; and occasioned so bitter and bloody a strife and would<lb/> not have occurred under the beneficent provisions of<lb/> the Hebrew statesman.  Rightly therefore said<lb/> farmers and agriculturists to Joseph &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;thou<lb/> hast given us a new life&#34;.  The philanthropist<lb/> could not effect a total revolution in the admi&#45;<lb/>nistration of the laws.  It lay not in his power&#44;<lb/> for instance&#44; to put an end to a privileged caste&#44;<lb/> that enjoyed clothed with exclusive rights.  The priests of Egypt&#44;<lb/> believed to be of a nature superior to the commonalty&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>and therefore taught arts and sciences&#44; while the<lb/> bulk of the nation vegetated in ignorance&#44; had<lb/> lands exempted free from all taxation&#44; inalienable and<lb/> considered sacred.  Joseph could not put an end to that extinguish an<lb/> hereditary aristocracy&#44; whose powers were secondary<lb/> only to those of arbitrarily exercised by the Pharaohs.<lb/>  An attempt to interfere with what concerned the<lb/> religion of the country&#44; would have defeated all<lb/> his humane efforts&#44; and proved fatal to the<lb/> interests of his father&#39;s family.  But with<lb/> a diplomacy which aimed at righteous results&#44;<lb/> he left untouched what he dared not lay his<lb/> hand upon&#44; and exerted his stupendous abilities<lb/> to work out as much general happiness as<lb/> it was given one so hampered to bring about.<lb/>  At this distance of time we may still feel<lb/> proud that Joseph sprung from the stock<lb/> of Israel.  From every point of view we<lb/> may can gladly look at him and direct our children&#39;s at&#45;<lb/>&#45;tention to a Hebrew undeniably preeminently good&#44; and mercifully<lb/> wise&#44; mounting high from stage to stage to reach a<lb/> degree of perfection unsurpassed&#44; if it was ever <sic>equalled</sic>.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Here follows a somewhat lengthy<lb/> address to two boys Bar Mitzvah on<lb/> the religiousness of Joseph.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
