<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF1_16</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1890-06" source="" attested="yes">June 1890</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_15_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_15_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_15_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_15_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_15_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_15_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_15_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_15_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_15_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_15_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_15_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_15_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. Fifth St.<lb/>
                Philadelphia&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>On the Haftorah for Behangalotecha<lb/>
                for a Bar Mitzvah<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>June&#47;90<lb/></p>
            <p>Whatever may be the real origin of the prophetic section<lb/> read on Sabbaths&#44; holidays and fasts in the Synagogue&#59; whe&#45;<lb/>&#45;ther it be&#44; as Elias Levitas of the 16th century wrote<lb/> that it was intended to substitute the recital of the<lb/> Pentateuch&#44; which Antiochus Epiphanes in his unta&#45;<lb/>&#45;mable fanaticism had forbidden&#44; or whether it be as Ra&#45;<lb/>&#45;poport the Hebrew critic of our days learnedly tries to<lb/> prove&#44; that it was instituted to pay regard to the<lb/> seers of Israel&#44; whose teachings orally commented on<lb/> served as a sort of lecture&#44; suiting the occasion&#44; certain<lb/> it is that in very many instances the connection be&#45;<lb/>&#45;tween the Haftorah and the Parasha was cleverly found.<lb/>  The prophecy which our young brother has just read to us&#44;<lb/> as his first worthy commendable endeavour&#44; is rather peculiar&#44; in&#45;<lb/>&#45;asmuch as it answers for two occasions&#44; for the<lb/> Sabbath of Hanuccha&#44; and for this Sabbath.  But<lb/> in both cases the leading idea is the same&#44; namely&#44;<lb/> to set to view the mission of the Cohen&#44; or priest of<lb/> the Lord.  He must give us light&#44; as celestially received.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Zachariah&#39;s vision the seven ranched Menorah<lb/> obtained an unceasing supply of pure oil&#44; which<lb/> kept it miraculously unquenched.  A fitting symbol emblem<lb/> was that as applied to the permanence of God&#39;s<lb/> people through luminous knowledge.  When this<lb/> seemed about to die off&#44; because Grecianism&#45;&#45;the rest&#45;<lb/>&#45;less spirit of the time&#45;&#45;had very nigh blown it out&#44;<lb/> a family of priests kindled it again into a blaze.<lb/>  The Asmoneans vindicated the outraged Torah.  They<lb/> became the richly laden olive trees that invisibly let in a<lb/> current of the fluid&#44; maintaining the lamp of God<lb/> vividly alive.  Sensibly was therefore that<lb/> section of the prophet Zachariah chosen for the<lb/> occasion commemorative of the stirring Maccabean<lb/> epoch.  It became suited it well metaphorically<lb/> by anticipation.  But that Haftorah properly<lb/> belongs to this Sabbath&#44; whose portion of the Law<lb/> opens with the ordinance given Aaron to so prepare arrange<lb/> the candlestick in the Sanctuary&#44; that its flame may spread<lb/> a clear light all around.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  The Cohen&#39;s function was to provide for a<lb/> far reaching and all illumining medium.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Joshua son of Jehozadak&#44; figuring conspicuously in<lb/> Zechariah&#39;s vision&#44; was a worthy successor of<lb/> the first priest to whom that charge was entrusted.<lb/>  Patriotism stirred in burned within his heart&#44; with piety was he<lb/> guided.  He loved his fathers&#39; hearthstone&#44; he loved<lb/> his people dearly.  To contribute to the resuscita&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion of both he had headed&#44; with some noble coworkers&#44;<lb/> that band of faithful who left Persia Persia of Cyrus &#38; Darius which pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;mised comparative ease and prosperity&#44; to share the<lb/> difficulties and dangers attending the looked for res&#45;<lb/>&#45;toration of a national Temple in Palestine.  The<lb/> prophet calls that Joshua &#91;Hebrew&#93; a brand<lb/> plucked from the fire&#44; meaning a Cohen who passed<lb/> unscathed through a prevalent consuming evil&#45;&#45;dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;loyalty to the faith.  Zachariah sees that zealous<lb/> priest diademned in silver and gold.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>  Yet&#44; he could not avert his eyes from certain spots which<lb/> impaired the beauty of the sacerdotal garments of worn by one otherwise<lb/> stainless.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Joshua son of Zehozadak himself was all enthusiasm<lb/> for the Jewish cause.  Not so his children.  They<lb/> made him feel the keen sorrow&#44; unhappily neither<lb/> singular nor rare in our own days.  Four of his sons<lb/> had wedded heathen gentile women.  They had polluted<lb/> his priestly robe.  Should he have been held accountable&#44; so<lb/> long as his conduct at home as well as abroad re&#45;<lb/>&#45;mained unexceptionable&#63;  Never&#59; therefore even<lb/> before the sinful children of the sinless father<lb/> had promised to carry out the harsh but imperati&#45;<lb/>&#45;vely necessary measure of Ezra the priest&#44; to break off their<lb/> unlawful marriages&#44; Zechariah heard in his vi&#45;<lb/>&#45;sion the voice of the Just God rebuke the accu&#45;<lb/>&#45;ser who would have laid upon the parent the guilt<lb/> of his offspring &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Joshua is promised there &#38; then the association of the saints who<lb/> stand in the presence of the Lord&#44; if he will hold<lb/> to his assigned post unswervedly&#44; do what is right<lb/> though all may go astray&#44; serve the Almighty<lb/> with singleness of purpose&#44; watch over the in&#45;<lb/>&#45;terest of the whole people&#44; be an inextinguish&#45;<lb/>&#45;able light in the sight of Israel.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Well&#44; brethren&#44; I will not trespass too long on this<lb/> summer morning.  My few remarks on our<lb/> Haftorah&#44; are simply prefatory of a friendly ad&#45;<lb/>&#45;dress intended for a Bar Mitzvah&#44; in whose future<lb/> I feel sincere interest.  My dear young<lb/> brother.  Looking backward I dare predict a marked<lb/> progress.  Humanly speaking your social promotion<lb/> is assured.  Unusually well <sic>developped</sic> in body<lb/> during past years&#44; kept wakeful in mind all along&#44; and sur&#45;<lb/>&#45;rounded by refining influences&#44; you will&#44; under<lb/> Providence&#44; succeed hereafter in what is conducive to your<lb/> temporal welfare.  But looking backward&#44; I<lb/> discover also spiritual forces at work&#44; impelling<lb/> you forward.  You cannot remain immoveable when<lb/> so incited.  Wise is the saying in the book of Job<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; With the aged dwells know&#45;<lb/>&#45;ledge&#44; and with those who have lived many days un&#45;<lb/>&#45;derstanding&#44; and practically to be carried out is the<lb/> teaching of Moses in his last warning of to the tribes<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; Ask of thy father<lb/> and he will tell thee&#44; and of thy elders and they<lb/> will say to thee what the history of the past demands.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Acting conformably to such maxims you will not<lb/> degenerate.  The living and the dead will point out<lb/> to you where the light abides which will fill you<lb/> with ardor&#44; with the warmth of enthusiasm&#44; which<lb/> you may infuse into others.  A descendant of<lb/> Phineas the zealous priest of Joshua son of Jehozadak the patriotic priest of Johanan<lb/> and Mattathias the Asmoneans&#44; the heroic priests you will consult<lb/> the annals of your predecessors&#44; and if immediate<lb/> advice be not at hand&#44; a study of those annals<lb/> will create a glow of racial pride&#44; and you will take<lb/> your stand by the side of those among your<lb/> ancestry&#44; who lived in thorough loyalty to the<lb/> Torah.  I must express my satisfaction<lb/> at having heard you read both the Law and the<lb/> Prophets on this sabbath which you will always<lb/> remember.  The greater is my satisfaction&#44; because<lb/> you will not be compelled&#44; like many of your<lb/> coevals to abandon your religious studies&#44; and<lb/> withdraw your presence form the house of God&#44;<lb/> in order to go in quest of a situation&#44; either<lb/> to help with small earnings destitute parents&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>or to follow a too prematurely an ambition for self<lb/> dependence.  You will let sacred know&#45;<lb/>&#45;ledge keep pace with secular learning&#44; and<lb/> when your suave reputation shall have arisen high among the<lb/> dwellers of Philadelphia in the scale of science&#44;<lb/> you will still be known as the Jew learned in<lb/> his faith&#44; bearing with pride the name of Mayer<lb/> Cohen.  Such is my great hope and earnest<lb/> prayer on your Bar Mitzvah day.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
