<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF2_3</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_3_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_3_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_3_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_3_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_3_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_3_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_3_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_3_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_3_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_3_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_3_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_3_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_3_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_3_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_3_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_3_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For the Sabbath of penitence.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>The spirit of God rested on the prophet Isaiah&#44; and<lb/> he heard a voice that bid him loudly to cry.  Aroused<lb/> by the call&#44; the inspired son of Amoz asked &#34;What<lb/> shall I cry&#63;&#34; and the same supernatural voice answered.<lb/>  &#34;Cry that all flesh is grass&#44; and all the goodliness<lb/> thereof is like the field flower of the field.&#34;  Cry that<lb/> that human flesh so bent intent upon worthy pursuits&#44;<lb/> is like grass which is soon mowed down.  Cry&#44; that<lb/> all the acquirements of which it boasts are like the<lb/> flower that blooms in the morn&#44; and but which the<lb/> scorching rays of the sun soon wither.  Let this be<lb/> thy solemn mission&#44; and thou mayest bring many back to<lb/> virtue.  Dear Brethren&#33;  What our merciful Father<lb/> in heaven&#44; wished to bring to pass through the agency<lb/> of men saintly and of a staub stainless life&#44; our Sages<lb/> sought to accomplish by means of fallible but God&#45;<lb/>fearing men.  They commissioned the spiritual<lb/> guides of Judah&#39;s remnant to reclaim sinners by<lb/> picturing to them the instability of human &#91;&#63;&#93;.<lb/>  When the Universal shepherd inspects the flock<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>of his pasture &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> at the period which follows immediately the closing<lb/> of a years that may have been <sic>mispent</sic> in the vain attempt of grasping<lb/> shadows&#44; the Rabbins ask their disciples to hasten<lb/> and loosen the prisoners fettered in the bonds of wickedness&#44;<lb/> ere the verdict be pronounced&#44; and the sentence sealed.<lb/>  Tell the house of Israel&#44; say those zealous teachers of old&#44;<lb/> that &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;the day is short&#44; a but<lb/> the work great&#34;  Es In obedience to the order<lb/> of my superiors&#44; I shall on this penitential sabbath&#44; pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;claim from the pulpit a truth startling but necessary for<lb/> all to la learn.  Let youths who are wedded to<lb/> wanton pleasures hear it&#44; and wean themselves away<lb/> from what they must relinquish.  Let the gentle<lb/> sex hear it&#44; and direct their thoughts to higher aims than<lb/> the enhancing of personal charms&#44; the cultivating of<lb/> arts intended to attract and captivate the senses.  Let<lb/> those vested with authority hear it&#44; and beware of wield power<lb/> with g kindly consideration and not with imperiousness. the<lb/> power which is theirs Let those who can command possess wealth hear<lb/> it&#44; and seek strive to gather riches of which inconstant<lb/> fortune cannot rob them.  Let all who are swayed<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>by the the corruptive flesh hear it&#44; and approach the fountain<lb/> of purification.  Aye&#44; my Brethren brother&#44; whosoever<lb/> that art&#44; whether in a lofty or in a lowly condition&#44;<lb/> at the climax of prosperity&#44; or in a state of abjection &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Thou must die&#34;....<lb/></p>
            <p>&#34;But is this the appalling tiding which was to effect<lb/> our conversion&#63;  Methinks I hear many deridingly ask<lb/> of themselves.  Who knows not that there is no man who<lb/> liveth and seeth not death&#59; we did not need a prea&#45;<lb/>&#45;cher to tell us what we witness every day.&#34;  Well&#44;<lb/> full well you know that &#34;like birds caught in a net&#44;<lb/> so are men taken in the evil day&#34;&#44; but you do not set<lb/> your minds on it&#59; hence the general neglect to maker<lb/> proper previsions again for the endless futurity.<lb/></p>
            <p>To secure some temporal advantage&#44; men will use<lb/> all means within their reach.  They will consult persons<lb/> of experience&#44; advice with their intimate friends&#44; seriously<lb/> and maturely reflect.  If a scheme&#44; which we deem<lb/> advantageous is set afloat&#44; it will entirely accepb our thoughts will be entirely engrossed<lb/> with by it.  In the day&#45;time it will obtrude itself amidst<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>other occupations.  At night it will disturb our<lb/> sleep&#44; and until it is accomplished&#44; we will continue<lb/> perfectly restless.  Not so&#44; however&#44; with regard to the<lb/> all&#45;important project of freeing ourselves from the mes<lb/> meshes of vice and to irreligion.  Oh no&#33; we cannot<lb/> bestow devote our best years to the barren exercise of upright&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness.  We cannot&#44; we cannot give up the br buoyant<lb/> days that yeld yield so much definite positive good&#44; because at<lb/> some indefinite period we may be forced to forego abandon what<lb/> we now possess.  Time enough&#44; time enough.  When<lb/> we grow older&#44; we will be better suited to respond to the<lb/> call of religion.  This we fallaciously reason forgetting that perhaps the old destroyer is treading on our heels&#44; as forgetting<lb/> that &#34;no man has power over the spirit to retain it&#34;; forget&#45;<lb/>&#45;ting that to the sinners of Zion who considered all men mortal<lb/> but themselves&#44; the prophet was predicted that that they would be first lost in<lb/> the scourge which was to pass over Judea.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> But I will not do all of us injustice by declaring that<lb/> we are utterly reckless&#59; that we rush headlong after vanities<lb/> without any pause.  No&#44; there are moments in our life&#44;<lb/> sacred moments&#44; sent as a warning by the Almighty&#44;<lb/> moments aroused by some startling events&#44; when we ack&#45;<lb/>&#45;nowledge that all pomp and grandeur&#44; all that which<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>we in fancied would excite the admiration of the world&#44; is<lb/> but a shadow.  Then we fell feel like bending low at<lb/> the foot stool of our Maker&#44; and seeking for pardon.  But<lb/> how fleeting these moments&#33;  Strong passions rise again&#44;<lb/> and drive over goodly feelings sentiments forcibly away.<lb/>  No&#44; says ambition&#44; I cannot listen this day&#44; it would shut<lb/> against me the avenues to greatness.  No&#44; says covetousness&#44;<lb/> it might involve the retrenching of expenses necessary to<lb/> keep up credit.  No&#44; says avarice&#44; it would enrich others<lb/> at to my own detriment.  How could I suffer my next&#45;door<lb/> neighbor to gain by my loss&#63;  Not to&#45;day&#44; some<lb/> other time&#44; when this task I is completed&#44; I will be<lb/> in a better frame of mind to attend the to the calls from<lb/> within.  But the task is never completed&#59; for no sooner have<lb/> we disposed of that in which we were busily engaged&#44; than<lb/> others claim our undivided attention.  Now&#44; were we<lb/> really impressed with a sense of our mortality.  No&#44; not<lb/> that&#45;&#45;for if death was but the dissolution of our corruptible<lb/> bodies we might with good some show of reasons indulge in every excess&#44;<lb/> gratify every appetite&#45;&#45;&#44; but were we impressed with<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>the truth that &#34;there is an eyes that seeth&#44; an ear that<lb/> heareth&#44; and that all our deeds are written down&#34;; that<lb/> we must give an account of the manner in which we<lb/> employed the faculties mercifully granted &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; we would not attend to our spiritual<lb/> wants earlier than when all ex else is finished.  Nay&#44; we<lb/> would postpone the latter to the former.<lb/>
                Eliezer the faithful servant of Abraham undertook a long<lb/> journey in quest of a suitable wife for the son of his master.<lb/>  Providence prospered his way&#44; and he reached the city of<lb/> Nabor&#44; where a dear kinsman of the patriarch resided.<lb/>  As customary among hospitable people&#44; he was asked<lb/> to partake of some food that he might be refreshed after<lb/> a fatiguing journey.  But the trusty servant <sic>premptorily</sic><lb/> refused.  &#34;No&#34; said he&#44; &#34;I will not eat until I have<lb/> told my errand&#34;.  And he proceeded to describe the happiness<lb/> that might be derived from a matrimonial alliance between<lb/> one of their daughters and the rich and respected son of his<lb/> master&#44; and nor would he allow the himself rest&#44; <sic>un&#45;<lb/>&#45;till</sic> he received positive evidences of that his mission<lb/> had been crowned with success.  But why such haste&#63;<lb/>  You will inquire.  Did he fear that the opportunity<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>might fail him to do his duty&#63;  Was it imperative<lb/> that he should refuse food until he obtained the consult of<lb/> Rebecca&#39;s relatives&#63;  No&#44; my friends&#33;  I have said it&#44;<lb/> What concerns us most will be performed first.  Let us now<lb/> draw a healthful lesson.  If to serve a mortal being&#44;<lb/> so much readiness&#44; so much zeal was displayed&#44; what<lb/> promptness&#44; what alacrity ought not we to be exhibited in<lb/> doing what is pleasing to the everlasting Master above&#33;<lb/>  Yet few will say&#44; &#34;this morning I committed a wrong.<lb/>  I will not eat&#44; till I have write righted it.&#34;  &#34;This day<lb/> I have <sic>practised</sic> deceit&#44; and exacted from my neighbor more<lb/> than my due.  I will not eat&#44; until I have made proper<lb/> reparations.&#34;  &#34;This week I have given vent to my<lb/> passions&#44; and brought trouble and sorrow on my<lb/> nearest and dearest&#44; I will not eat&#44; until I have<lb/> solemnly vowed never to relapse into my former habits.&#34;<lb/>  &#34;This month I have raised myself high by treadin<lb/> mounting up treading on the ruin of my neigh fellow man&#39;s<lb/> character and reputation.  I will not eat&#44; until I<lb/> have humbled myself and sought his forgiveness.&#34;<lb/>  &#34;This year I have been irreverent towards my<lb/> parents&#44; overbearing towards my children&#44; tyrannical<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>towards my dependents.  I will not eat&#44; o this year<lb/> I have been recreant to my trust&#44; This year I have.....<lb/> But why shall I describe more at length what is<lb/> painful to behold.  What I meant to prove&#44; my<lb/> dear Brethren is&#44; that even when we are not altogether<lb/> lost to shame&#59; when we feel know our fallibilitybleness&#44; we will<lb/> not cast out our backslidings as encumbrances on our spirit.<lb/>  We delay&#44; and put off till a more favorable opportunity<lb/> will present itself&#59; till our minds are better prepared<lb/> for a change in our course.  But the opportunity may<lb/> never present itself.  &#34;Oh sacred veil that encirclest hidest<lb/> the throne of &#91;&#63;&#93; decree secrets of heavenly justice&#33;  What human power can tear<lb/> thee asunder&#63;  What human eye can peer penetrate into the<lb/> awful mysteries that thou concealest&#63;  How many we stalwart frames&#44; that we<lb/> imagined destined to work wonders have been broken down<lb/> like a reed&#33;  How many were blighted in the bloom of<lb/> youth&#44; when we fancied would have outlived the<lb/> myriads&#33;  But this absence of the knowledge<lb/> of our end&#44; was not intended&#44; my dear hearers&#44; to terrify<lb/> us into a state of inactivity.  Not to spread upon<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>us a dread of being soon ushered into the august presence<lb/> of an merciful God infallible Judge&#44; but rather to incite us to work&#59;<lb/> to work steadily for the elevation of our soul&#44; to work<lb/> in the way of beneficence&#44; in the way of truth&#59; to<lb/> work for the moral and intellectual advancement of<lb/> the creatures of the same Father.  It is intended to<lb/> incite stimulate us to say like the old patriarch &#34;I know not<lb/> the day of my death&#34; It may overtake me while<lb/> I am engaged in the pursuit of sin running counter to the dictates of morality and religion.  How could I then<lb/> bear the gnawing remorse of having offended the best my kindest<lb/> of Benefactor&#33;  Of having misused the faculties with<lb/> which He has endowed me&#33;  How could I endure<lb/> the pain of having cut off myself from the association<lb/> of the righteous ones in the land of spirits&#63;  Which<lb/> of the transient pleasures of this world can &#91;&#63;&#93; counterbalance<lb/> the sorrow of being denied the contemplation of<lb/> the Essence of Goodness&#63;  Well then&#59; of when passions<lb/> arise again within my breast&#44; I shall take the chart<lb/> given to me from on high&#44; consult it&#44; and if I discover<lb/> that the sentiments I cherish are in contravention to with<lb/> the rules of the heavenly Legislator&#44; I shall forthwith<lb/> suppress my will&#44; that His will be done.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>For&#44; I know that all my steps are watched&#44; and my<lb/> deeds will be weighed upon in the balance of justice.<lb/>  Dear Brethren&#33;  It is to strengthen these feelings&#59; to<lb/> confirm us in this belief&#44; that the Almighty has<lb/> set apart the present solemn season of our year.<lb/>  Listen then&#44; O house of Israel&#33;  Were you destined&#44; that<lb/> as I fervently hope&#44; to outlive the time allotted to men<lb/> on earth&#59; were you destined&#44; as I most ardently pray&#44;<lb/> to be all inscribed in the book of uninterrupted prosperity&#44;<lb/> still even at an advanced age you would consider the<lb/> long past like yesterday that has gone departed&#44; and as a watch<lb/> in the night.  But what if the morrow was to<lb/> fail you&#63;  &#40;For&#44; who can say&#44; what the morrow will bring<lb/> forth&#63;&#41;   Not without reason have the Sages compared<lb/> this world to a porch leading to the King&#39;s palace.<lb/>  Sudden may be the summons to come in.  Let us always<lb/> be ready to make a presentable appearance.  &#34;Let<lb/> thy garments be always at all times white&#34; said the<lb/> ancient preacher.  Those garments are the consciousness<lb/> of having never deliberately sullied our lips with falsehood.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>Never having deliberately defrauded our neighbor&#59;<lb/> never having deliberately defied God and His command.<lb/>  Leave then the rest in the hand of Him whose attributes<lb/> are mercy and compassion&#44; and who delights to pardon.<lb/>  When the passage which divides us from the world<lb/> unknown shall have been crossed over&#44; you will be<lb/> carried aloft in the realms where a purling stream<lb/> of perennial water flow&#59; when a sun that never<lb/> sets shall irradiate your immortal souls.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
