<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF7_3</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_3_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_3_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_3_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_3_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_3_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_3_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_3_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_3_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_3_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_3_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_3_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_3_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_3_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_3_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_3_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_3_8v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_3_9r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_3_9v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_3_10r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_3_10v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>15 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>A lecture for Vayesheb<lb/>
                contrasting the characters of<lb/>
                Joseph and Absalom.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  The heroic actions&#44; which delivered us from<lb/> the lowest state of human bondage&#45;&#45;idolatry&#45;&#45;.  The<lb/> events which gave the family of the Asmoneans a bright<lb/> page in history&#44; and occasioned the feast called Hanuc&#45;<lb/>&#45;cah&#44; or Dedication&#44; are household words with us Israelites.<lb/>  Even those among my coreligionists&#44; who have not read<lb/> the portion of our annals&#44; which contains a detailed ac&#45;<lb/>&#45;count of the wards waged in the defence of our sacred<lb/> rights&#44; find it condensed in the simple language of<lb/> our ritual.  I shall therefore advance ideas that<lb/> struck me in reading last week&#39;s section&#44; in lieu of<lb/> those&#44; which I have yearly set forth.  I am urged<lb/> to this course&#44; moreover&#44; by the circumstance that I have<lb/> promised to lecture to&#45;morrow twice upon the subject of<lb/> the present celebration.  In the morning before a<lb/> gathering of Hebrew children&#59; in the evening at a<lb/> meeting of a literary association.  But in order<lb/> not to ignore altogether&#44; the recurrence of a season&#44;<lb/> which must call forth thanksgiving&#44; I shall make<lb/> allusion to it in a prayer at the close of my discourse.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>The aim of my speaking to&#45;day&#44; will be<lb/> to direct the eyes which brighten up at the prospect<lb/> of a long and successful career towards the object which<lb/> will safely conduct man in the way he should go.<lb/></p>
            <p>Youth&#33;  How charming is thy look of self&#45;depend&#45;<lb/>&#45;ence&#59; that quick step with which thou movest&#44; as<lb/> to the conquest of a world&#33;  Hope walks before thee&#44;<lb/> and carries thy banner.  Wherever thou settest foot&#44; fields<lb/> appear carpeted with flowers&#59; the air is clothed with a<lb/> mantle of light&#59; joyful voices echo around&#59; pleasures<lb/> are seen coming to meet thee by the way.  In whatever<lb/> place thou showest thy countenance&#44; sadness must<lb/> flee away&#44; and make room for mirth.<lb/>  Yes&#44; dear hearers&#33;  Beautiful is blooming youth&#44; which<lb/> manifests that warmth of feelings&#59; that open&#45;heart&#45;<lb/>&#45;edness of a nature overflowing with generous emotions.<lb/>  It is a mirror of the first days of creation&#59; of that short<lb/> space of time&#44; when happiness weaved garlands for<lb/> innocence.  Can it then be so&#44; that the<lb/> many gifts which youth displays&#44; change notinfre&#45;<lb/>&#45;quently&#45;&#45;into so many defects&#63;  Can out of blossoms<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>so promising and lovely&#44; grow only bitter fruits of a<lb/> late repentance&#63;  Alas&#33; the history of a number of<lb/> human beings&#44; proves that possibility.  Here&#44; a son<lb/> who might have filled the cup of his mother&#39;s joy&#44; im&#45;<lb/>&#45;bittered the spring of her delights&#44; with the vile dregs<lb/> that poisoned his own happiness.  There&#44; a daughter who<lb/> formed a father&#39;s pride&#44; made his head to bend under the<lb/> weight of shame&#44; while she sunk whelmed with the<lb/> world&#39;s contempt.  Why such baneful results from<lb/> such glowing anticipations&#63;  Because the incautious<lb/> youths left behind the chart necessary to be consulted<lb/> in the journey of life.  A ship without the rudder&#44;<lb/> must suffer wreck.  A youth who proceeds in his<lb/> career&#44; without the fear of God&#44; must end in degradation.<lb/>  That heavenly escort&#44; says the book of Proverbs&#44; is man&#39;s<lb/> strong support.  Accompanied by that fear&#44; con&#45;<lb/>&#45;tinues the same inspired volume&#44; we shall avoid the<lb/> snares of death.  A model of a youth&#44; that<lb/> may be very profitably copied is Joseph&#44; the childs of<lb/> Jacob&#39;s predilection.  A figure of a youth&#44; that<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>you all must shun like fire is Absalom&#44;<lb/> the favorite son of David.  Both of an exterior<lb/> strikingly handsome.  Both endowed with bright<lb/> talents&#44; both possessed of manners&#44; at once genial<lb/> and engaging.  Yet how immense the difference&#33;&#33;<lb/>  How immeasurable the distance which separated the<lb/> inmate of a palace&#44; from the lad reared in a shepherd&#39;s<lb/> cottage&#33;  The comeliness of Joseph&#39;s face&#44; did not<lb/> lead into temptation.  If it was perchance a cause<lb/> for self&#45;gratification&#44; it could never have become the<lb/> arm of self&#45;destruction.  For&#44; the feelings it may<lb/> have aroused&#44; were under the absolute control of a more<lb/> powerful sentiment&#45;&#45;the fear of God.  Divine<lb/> Guide&#33; pointing out the dangers into which they run&#44;<lb/> who allow the imagination complete sway.  Laying<lb/> bare to our view the serpent hidden&#44; where we thought<lb/> we would lie down at ease.  Showing grief&#44; disgrace and<lb/> remorse close by the spot&#44; in which we fancied to<lb/> have discovered ever&#45;new delights.  Joseph<lb/> was beautiful&#44; but the gift&#44; which to some has<lb/> proved a bane&#44; was in him an instrument to work<lb/> therewith for the welfare of other men.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>They who saw that countenance read upon it honesty&#44;<lb/> and trusted the guileless youth.  So I interpret that<lb/> sentence of the Scriptures&#44; which connects the description<lb/> of the confidence placed by the Egyptian master in<lb/> his Hebrew bondman&#44; and the picture of the goodly<lb/> form and handsome appearance of the latter.  I believe<lb/> there is truth in the theory that features are indicative<lb/> of character.  And Holy Writ gives it support&#44; when<lb/> it writes that &#34;a man&#39;s wisdom maketh his face to shine.&#34;<lb/>  But it must present the reflection of what the sacred<lb/> Word calls wisdom&#44; that is&#44; &#34;the fear of the Lord&#34;.<lb/>  A reverential awe for the Parent of virtue&#59; a dread<lb/> to offend the Divinity&#44; whose image we bear.  Such<lb/> a quality softens every lineament&#44; bespeaking in man<lb/> a heart&#44; which is ever open to noble instincts&#44; but<lb/> closed&#44; firmly closed against the admission of wicked passions.<lb/>  For&#44; to say it again&#44; as Solomon tells it&#44; wisdom imparts<lb/> a moral force ten times greater than royal powers.<lb/>  Through the possession of that quality&#44; Joseph was<lb/> a freeman&#44; while unjustly laden with chains.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>For the want of that quality&#44; Absalom<lb/> was a slave&#44; while bearing the tokens of princely<lb/> rank.  Absalom&#44; the handsomest of all men in<lb/> Israel&#59; Absalom&#44; of whom we read&#44; that &#34;from the<lb/> sole of his foot up to the crown of his head&#44; no blemish<lb/> could be found on him&#34; had not one redeeming feature<lb/> left&#59; because his own impure hand effaced the<lb/> impress of beauty.  Having cast aside the fear<lb/> of God&#44; he proceeded in the race of life destitute of<lb/> a guide&#44; and he met ambition coiling itself round<lb/> his heart like an asp.  He found a spirit of revenge&#44;<lb/> advising treachery&#44; unruly appetites inviting to<lb/> wantonness.  David&#39;s son also could win con&#45;<lb/>&#45;fidence and gain favor.  But not by candor&#44; shining<lb/> in every look of his sparkling eyes&#59; not by the<lb/> guilelessness of his persuasive tongue&#44; but by flattery&#44;<lb/> by dishonest promises&#44; by covert falsehood.  He that<lb/> buried the sword to kill in cold&#45;blood in his sinful&#44; yet<lb/> defenceless brother&#59; he that brought defilement to the<lb/> home of his birth&#44; used the capacities with which he<lb/> had been endowed&#44; to poison with the seeds of dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;loyalty the subjects of his royal father.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Joseph in a dungeon&#44; rose in the morning to the<lb/> task&#44; which is his confiding superior hand imposed.<lb/>  To attend to the wants of the prisoners&#44; and cheer them<lb/> in loneliness was his occupation.  Gifted with a<lb/> keen perception&#44; and a mind br lighted up by<lb/> a supernatural knowledge&#44; he made those talents<lb/> subserve noble ends.  See him enter the ward&#44;<lb/> where Pharaoh&#39;s officers had been confined.  Concerned<lb/> by reason of their sad looks&#44; he inquires of into the<lb/> cause&#44; and speaks of God&#44; who may render him<lb/> the means of calming their agitation.<lb/></p>
            <p>Absalom awoke the dawn&#44; and took his stand<lb/> by the way&#45;side.  He cared naught for his<lb/> neighbor&#39;s troubles and woes.  Himself was the central<lb/> point&#44; towards which all must tend.  That object<lb/> once reached&#44; he would soon cast off the mask of bene&#45;<lb/>&#45;volence and humility.  &#34;Could I wear the crown&#44; I would<lb/> do justice to all&#34;.  So he was heard often to cry by<lb/> the Israelites&#44; who passed the gates of Jerusalem.  He<lb/> let the honey of his language flow&#44; that the unwary<lb/> might gather it&#44; and return for more.  A master<lb/> in cunning&#44; he knew how to persuade alike the defe<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>plaintiff and the defendant&#44; that the king would not<lb/> even grant them an audience.  And affecting making pretensions of a love for<lb/> the people&#44; which he entertained only for himself&#44; he would<lb/> reach out his hand&#44; and clasp in his arms whosoever<lb/> paid him obeisance.  Thus he succeeded in stealing the<lb/> affection of a multitude&#44; that he might created dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;affection among the defenders of his father&#39;s throne.<lb/>  A monster with a beauty unsurpassed.  A savage<lb/> with a high degree of refinement.  A madman<lb/> full of worldly knowledge.  Absalom&#33;  Absalom&#33;<lb/>  What did change the qualities&#44; with which nature<lb/> had so lavishly enriched thee into the arrows&#44; that<lb/> pierced thy heart&#44; and the hearts of thousands of<lb/> thy countrymen&#63;  You do not need his answer&#44;<lb/> my young friends&#44; you see it written in the conduct<lb/> of that illustrious youth&#44; who did hold fast to the<lb/> fear of God&#44; wherever he bent his steps.<lb/></p>
            <p>Joseph&#39;s well proportioned limbs&#44; and well&#45;stored<lb/> mind&#44; were directed in the way of truth&#44; by wisdom.<lb/>  Therefore he avoided the meshes of sin&#44; and the stones of wickedness.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Absalom rejected the companionship of real wisdom.<lb/>  Absorbed in the thought of self&#45;aggrandizement&#44; he<lb/> never heeded the obstacles to his right promotion.  He<lb/> sought to reach the highest point of human greatness&#44;<lb/> by a leap of artifice&#44; but through a fatal misstep<lb/> he fell never to rise.  The son of Jacob earned glory<lb/> by sagacious deeds&#44; and works of righteousness.  He became<lb/> great&#44; because he exemplified human greatness in all<lb/> the relations of life.  To forgive offenses&#59; to bear with<lb/> sinners&#44; to return good for evil&#59; to postpone self&#45;<lb/>interest to honesty of purpose.  To give his father<lb/> the fondest cares&#44; and his brothers their daily sustenance&#59;<lb/> To teach thrift and industry&#59; the principles of govern&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment&#44; and the rules of social progress&#44; was the aim<lb/> of his whole life.  Joseph lived long&#44;and gained a name<lb/> before which nobility pales.  The son of David<lb/> labored during the existence to sow mischief&#44; and soon<lb/> reaped a full harvest of destruction.  Early cut<lb/> off&#44; he passed away unhonored and unwept by<lb/> the people he had foully deceived.  Joseph&#39;s<lb/> remains were carried&#44; as precious relics&#44; by Moses and<lb/> Israel during forty years&#44; and at length&#44; were laid<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>in a distinguished spot&#44; which his patriarchal father<lb/> had brought in Shechem.  The slain body of<lb/> Absalom&#44; taken down from the high bough of the<lb/> oak&#44; in which his luxurious hair became entangled&#44;<lb/> was thrown into a pit&#44; and like an <sic>anumal</sic> that<lb/> perishes&#44; covered with a heap of stones.  Neither the<lb/> royal valley he had destined for his future resting<lb/> place&#44; nor the monument he intended to perpetuate<lb/> his memory&#44; held the corpse of him&#44; who had hatched<lb/> rebellion and schemed a parricide.  In the<lb/> unnatural son of David was fulfilled the Scriptural<lb/> sentence&#44; that &#34;the way of the wicked is like thick<lb/> darkness&#44; they know not against what they stumble.&#34;<lb/>  In the upright child of Jacob have been verified the<lb/> words which declare that &#34;the path of the righteous&#44;<lb/> is a brightness itself&#44; continually shining to the<lb/> perfect day.&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>That is the path which you&#44; O Young hearers&#33;<lb/> must early choose.  While treading it&#44; beauty never<lb/> fades&#44; the endowments of the mind are more brilliantly set off.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>Not the fruits of repentance&#44; but the flowers<lb/> of self&#45;approval&#44; you will gather in that path.<lb/>  For&#44; chastity and temperance meet there together&#44; good&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness and esteem kiss one another.  Follow that<lb/> path&#44; in which Joseph found a name sweeter than<lb/> precious ointment.  Flee away&#44; flee away from<lb/> that which hides destruction&#44; under the cover of seduct&#45;<lb/>&#45;ive pleasures.  You that have begun of<lb/> late the journey of this life&#33;  Keep the fear of God as<lb/> your guide.  It does not hold back the honest and lawful<lb/> pleasures&#44; which nature benignantly offers.  He could<lb/> be wrong&#44; and misunderstand duty&#44; who thought you are<lb/> denied all the enjoyments&#44; which your age notably ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;preciates&#44; and which add strength to your freshness&#44;<lb/> buoyancy to your spirits.  The fear of God deters you<lb/> only from seeking those pleasures which will mar your<lb/> goodly appearance&#44; deform the intellect giving pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;mises of a vigorous existence.  God has inspired<lb/> your hearts with sentiments of admiration for what is<lb/> lovely&#59; with hope for a future towards which you<lb/> move on with alacrity.  Let such sentiments be not<lb/> crushed by false apprehensions&#59; but let them be guided&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p>tempered&#44; purified&#44; and sanctified by the fear<lb/> of the Lord.  It becomes your age to feel the<lb/> warmth of enthusiasm.  Yours is a period of life&#44; the<lb/> most happy&#44; for it has not suffered yet the difficulties<lb/> of rising equal to the demands of onerous callings.<lb/>  Nor has it experienced the withering effect of bitter<lb/> disappointments.  Let then that felicity be an<lb/> incentive to confess and thank supreme Goodness.<lb/>  With that head you carry aloft&#59; with those eyes casting<lb/> rays of a pure light&#44; with those steps firm and rapid&#44;<lb/> enter the first ranks among the servants of God&#45;&#45;the<lb/> adherents of virtue and beneficence.  You are&#44; O<lb/> youths&#33; the best interpreters of the love&#44; that brought<lb/> forth creation.  Bend the knee before the sovereign<lb/> Maker of heaven and earth.  Like Joseph let your<lb/> watchword be. &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;I fear God&#34;.<lb/></p>
            <p>Saviour of Israel&#33;  Worker of wonders&#33;  Few and feeble<lb/> were they who feared Thy name above the mighty hosts<lb/> of a heathen King.  But Thou madest each man&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="14"/>
            <p>a thousandfold strong&#59; and the stroke of his sword<lb/> more terrific than the clap of the rolling thunder.<lb/>  As smoke is driven off by the wind&#44; as wax melteth<lb/> before the fire&#44; so were the enemies of Thy Law&#44; dispersed at<lb/> the uprising of Thy servants&#59; consumed by their burning<lb/> zeal.  Mattathias and his five sons&#44; who called to the<lb/> breach a residue of the faithful&#44; and rolled away reproach<lb/> from Thy land and Thy people&#44; we hold in grateful remem&#45;<lb/>&#45;brance.  But to Thee&#44; O Lord&#33; who didst breathe I hope&#44;<lb/> when all looked hopeless.  To Thee&#44; who didst not suffer<lb/> the truth of Thy Unity to be buried under the stones of pagan<lb/> altars&#44; we give thanks and ascribe everlasting glory.<lb/>  For&#44; the world which has moved onward&#44; by the light we shed<lb/> on its way&#44; would not have advanced&#44; if the tyrannic Antro&#45;<lb/>&#45;chus had succeeded in causing our fathers altogether to bow to<lb/> his idolatrous belief.  Thou who dwellest in heaven&#33;&#44;<lb/> sawest his machinations&#44; and hildest them in derision.  The<lb/> decrees he issued forth to set aside Thy commands&#44; were&#44; by Thy<lb/> rebuke&#44; turned into chaff.  The Sabbath he would abolish&#59;<lb/> the Abrahamic covenant he forbid&#44; and the reading of Thy<lb/> inspired book he interdicted &#44;are to this day kept as the<lb/> cherished observances of the Hebrew race&#44; and they will still<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="15"/>
            <p>remain as such to the end of time.  May it even<lb/> be so&#44; O Most High&#33;  Grant that the religion which<lb/> persecution could not destroy&#44; may stand proof<lb/> against the blandishments of a misapprehended and<lb/> abused liberty.  Let every return of Hanuccah&#44; give us<lb/> more light on the discharge of our duty&#44; as the<lb/> witnesses of Thy word&#44; and the instructors of all Thy<lb/> creatures.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
