<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF11_7</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1897-02" source="" attested="yes">February 1897</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_7_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_7_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_7_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_7_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_7_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_7_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_7_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_7_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_7_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_7_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_7_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_7_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS<lb/>
                546 N. Fifth St.<lb/></p>
            <p>Philadelphia&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>140<lb/></p>
            <p>Feb.&#47;97<lb/></p>
            <p>On Russian affairs<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>On the 19th day of January&#44; I stood before a large represen&#45;<lb/>&#45;tation of Episcopal clergymen.  It was in obedience to the<lb/> urging of respectable and kindly disposed women of a Christ&#45;<lb/>&#45;ian denomination&#44; that I addressed that dignified Minis&#45;<lb/>&#45;terial body.  They Those well&#45;wishers of mankind&#44; believed that my pleading&#44; on the<lb/> score of humanity&#44; in behalf of Jews who suffer almost<lb/> unprecedentedly sore persecutions&#44; would stir up a community<lb/> to healthful actions.  The influence of a church<lb/> powerful by reason of its wealth&#44; so highly regarded be&#45;<lb/>&#45;cause of the general culture of its members&#44; and so defe&#45;<lb/>&#45;rentially listened to in view on account of the vast number of its<lb/> adherents&#44; would clearly show itself in Washington.  Such<lb/> were the hopes&#44; and therefore I overcame my natural hesitancy.<lb/>  I was told that our government&#44; traditionally on very<lb/> amicable terms with that at St Petersburg&#44; would inter&#45;<lb/>&#45;pose its merciful offices&#44; so as to change for the<lb/> better the situation of our unhappy coreligionists in the<lb/> empire of the Czar.  Nearly a month has elapsed<lb/> since my effort in the guild room of the Church of the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Epiphany&#44; and the beneficial result of my having<lb/> spoken has not yet been reported to me.  Even at the<lb/> very meeting of the 19th to which I have alluded&#44;<lb/> I was made painfully to feel that the sympathy<lb/> which good people&#44; belonging to another creed from ours&#44;<lb/> anticipated&#44; was not universal.  For at the conclusion<lb/> of my address&#44; one of on whose support I had confidently<lb/> relied&#44; caustically remarked that&#44; as Jews in Russia&#44; tho&#39;<lb/> more numerous than elsewhere&#44; form nevertheless a very<lb/> small minority amidst the vast immense population&#44; they should ward off ill&#45;will by re&#45;<lb/>&#45;nouncing the peculiar practices of their faith.  Upon hear&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing such sentiments&#44; I imagined that the spirit of Gold&#45;<lb/>&#45;win Smith had entered the speaker&#39;s body and it echoed<lb/> forth the advice which that worthy gave shortly before&#44;<lb/> in response to an inquiry from a New York Messenger<lb/> claiming to be a Jewish mouth&#45;piece.  Well&#58;<lb/> a conforming with the counsel given would really<lb/> expedite matters much more quickly than even the<lb/> thumb&#45;screw of the inquisition could possibly dispatch.<lb/>  Better still&#44; the voluntary abjuration of Mosaic and tradi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tional ordinances&#44; would secure each neophyte ten rubles&#44;<lb/> as a reward for his admission to baptism acceptance have knelt at the baptismal font.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Thanks&#44; many thanks reverend sir&#44; but my brethren are not pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;pared ready to rush into the embrace of the Greek church.<lb/>  In However&#44; in a letter to a colleague of mine&#44; I am assured that<lb/> those I addressed are&#44; with me&#44; with a single exception&#44;<lb/> with me&#44; and that they labor quietly but yet effectually.<lb/>  Perhaps so&#59; meanwhile the manly remonstrance of Mr<lb/> Cummings&#44; more guardedly worded than that of Mr Baker&#44;<lb/> was set aside by Congress&#44; and another by Mr Hitt was<lb/> offered for approval&#44; as milder yet still than either of the<lb/> preceding ones.  What will be its fate&#63;  Is diplomacy<lb/> likely to change its heart of stone into a heart of flesh<lb/> and melt at the tidings that reached our shores on Wed&#45;<lb/>&#45;nesday last&#63;  Or&#44; will the United States&#44; whose foundation stone<lb/> lays on a protest against tyranny&#44; still continue to look on unconcerned&#44;<lb/> when an ally is crushing mankind to death&#63;  Surely&#58; the strong Or&#44; will<lb/> free America can and should heed the commandment of the greatest Legis&#45;<lb/>&#45;lator &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Stand not idly when the<lb/> the blood of thy neighbor is being shed.&#34;&#63;  For the<lb/> honor of the country&#44; deemed held by the oppressed as an anchor of<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>salvation&#44; I fondly cherish the hope that a voice<lb/> of disapprobation will be raised&#44; and despotism will<lb/> blush at its inequities.  I have said it&#58;<lb/> the Czar will not fling away&#44; in a fit of anger&#44; a<lb/> friendly communication from the Chief Executive of sixty<lb/> millions&#44; asking for a less inhuman treatment of three<lb/> millions and a half of creatures&#44; whose greatest crime is<lb/> that they were born Jews.  On the Christian<lb/> New Year&#44; the emperor of all the Russians&#44; read with a<lb/> complacent smile a set of resolutions passed by American<lb/> residents at St Petersburg&#44; thanking him for the liberty<lb/> which they were allowed to enjoy.  Englishmen might<lb/> not have fared so well.  Probably they the subjects of queen Victoria would not have drawn<lb/> such resolutions&#44; for&#44; open in undersigned are the political animosities<lb/> of the Autocrat against Great Britain&#44; and if we needed<lb/> an illustration&#44; the result which attended the Guildhall<lb/> famous meeting would furnish it most strikingly.  None<lb/> should wonder that our unfortunate brethren lament the kindly<lb/> interposition of England.  When a despot of old&#44; made<lb/> our fathers&#39; yoke heavier&#44; because of Moses and Aaron&#39;s<lb/> intercession&#44; the Hebrews enslaved exclaimed &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>&#34;May the Lord see it and charge a you with having made<lb/> us hateful in the sight of Pharaoh and in the sight<lb/> of his officers&#44; as if putting a sword into their hand to<lb/> tell us.&#34;  It is the language of the down trodden&#44; who<lb/> feel the iron heel on their bare necks.  &#34;Let us alone&#44;<lb/> for pity&#45;sake&#34;&#44; they cry &#34;a word in our favor is the spade<lb/> which g digs out our grave.  So likewise it has happened<lb/> in the Egypt of the nineteenth century.  The memo&#45;<lb/>&#45;rial of Dukes and prelates&#59; of literary celebrities&#44; and<lb/> parliamentary magnates&#44; was returned in insulting<lb/> silence&#44; and we have read last on Wednesday thus&#58; &#34;British sympathy<lb/> has aggravated the Jews&#39; hard lot&#44; which was already<lb/> so wretched that it seemed impossible to be worse.....<lb/> The daily severities practised against the families unoffend&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing men&#44; women and children are incredible and wanton.<lb/>  Russia&#39;s reply to the Lord Mayor&#39;s respectful petition<lb/> consists of secret circulars&#44; ordering her officials to<lb/> rigorously administer the anti&#45;semetic laws&#44; and<lb/> to supply the legal deficiency by their own decisions&#44;<lb/> in harmony on with the government&#39;s intolerant spi&#45;<lb/>&#45;rit.&#34;  But American sympathy will insure a<lb/> hearing&#44; if not for a corresponding feeling&#44; for&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>America has no territorial jealousies&#44; bristling up their<lb/> angry crests against Russia.  The two lands clasp each<lb/> other&#39;s right hand across the Atlantic&#44; and give one<lb/> another warm assurances of uninterrupted good&#45;will.<lb/>  In the face of such horrors&#44; as reported by late despatch&#45;<lb/>&#45;es&#44; will not our Secretary of State instruct Mr Charles<lb/> Emory Smith&#44; our plenipotentiary&#44; to seek ask for an audience<lb/> and&#45;&#45;Oh&#33; soul&#45;degrading anomaly&#33;&#45;&#45;lat at the foot of as des&#45;<lb/>&#45;potic throne the humble request of republicans&#63;  My eyes<lb/> are strained looking intently for that hoped for advent and its issue.<lb/></p>
            <p>But ardently praying for the relief of our enslaved breth&#45;<lb/>&#45;ren&#44; we must prepare nevertheless for adverse cir&#45;<lb/>&#45;cumstances&#59; for an influx of a foreign population<lb/> that will hamper us our exertions fearfully.  Already it has<lb/> been stated that one hundred and sixty Jewish families are <lb/> are on their way to Dakota&#44; supplied with means by<lb/> Baron de Hirsch&#44; but I am reliably informed that that<lb/> distant Western territory state has proved inauspicious to<lb/> the colony planted there&#44; and that its unsuccessful<lb/> farmers travel on foot to St Paul&#44; to Minneapolis<lb/> and neighboring cities&#44; in quest of food to satisfy hunger.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>And now the knowledge that two millions and four<lb/> hundred thousand dollars&#45;&#45;which is the principal of the<lb/> ten thousand dollars interest sent heretofore monthly&#44;<lb/> have been forwarded to the trustees of the Hirsch fund<lb/> as a permanent fund capital &#91;&#63;&#93; to be invested at pleasure by the committee&#44;<lb/> that knowledge&#44; I say&#44; will encourage many to seek our shores making heavier thus still heavier the incubus<lb/> oppressing our hearts.  For&#44; however we may choose<lb/> to boast in the secular press&#44; that we are able<lb/> to take care of all who need our assistance&#44; the work<lb/> of dispensing charity wisely and efficaciously&#44; is<lb/> daily assuming proportions&#44; which appall those en&#45;<lb/>&#45;gaged in the tremendously difficult task.  I shall not presume<lb/> to suggest to men who enjoy the confidence of the<lb/> world&#45;renowned philanthropist&#44; how best to carry out<lb/> the intention of the incomparable singularly great donor.  I am aware<lb/> that in New York&#44; a school for youths has been<lb/> opened under the auspices of the unique benefactor&#44;<lb/> and it is not improbable that similar institutions<lb/> will increase in the metropolis and elsewhere by through<lb/> the munificent gift of the German Austrian Baron&#44; but I&#44; who<lb/> study the wants of my fellow believers in Philadelphia&#44;<lb/> eagerly wish for an object&#44; the realization of which<lb/> has occupied my thoughts very nigh three years.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>For its sake I have spoken in this pulpit with<lb/> a frequency which perhaps became wearisome&#59; for<lb/> its sake I repeatedly consulted an un an untiring laborer in the<lb/> noble scheme&#59; for its sake I opened a correspond&#45;<lb/>&#45;ence with persons&#44; who&#44; I was assured&#44; could approach<lb/> the Jewish Croesus&#44; and influence him favorably to my<lb/> plan.  My endeavours&#44; have proved so far abortive.<lb/>  The latest communication from Paris&#44; directed me to<lb/> the President of the New York Branch of the Uni&#45;<lb/> &#45;versal Israelitish Alliance&#44; who is also President<lb/> of the Hirsch fund.  He should exercise his judgment as<lb/> to the advisability fittest mode of furthering my project.  I did<lb/> not follow the course pointed out&#44; because I hold that<lb/> the Philadelphia trustees ought to be alive to the ne&#45;<lb/>&#45;cessity of devoting a notable portion of their quota<lb/> of the yearly interest&#44; to the erection&#44; and maintenance<lb/> of a comprehensive institution&#44; mainly to the an institution promotive<lb/> of industry&#44; of the teaching cultivation of mechanics and trades&#44; of<lb/> English&#44; &#38; of Hebrew&#44; of religion and morals.<lb/></p>
            <p>But as I wish desiring to address a lad who has just completed<lb/> his thirteenth year&#44; I shall further refer in my next to this import<lb/>&#45;ant topic.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
