<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF8_11</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1889-05" source="" attested="yes">May 1889</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_11_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_11_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_11_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_11_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_11_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_11_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_11_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_11_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_11_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_11_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_11_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_11_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For the centennial of<lb/>Washington taking the oath<lb/>
                of Presidential office<lb/>
                1789.		1889.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  It becomes the oldest Congregation religious body of Hebrews<lb/> in this city&#44; that had long been regularly organized years be&#45;<lb/>&#45;fore the memorable important event celebrated this day hap&#45;<lb/>&#45;ened&#44; to respond to the call summons of temporal authorities.<lb/>  Unless my knowledge of the past history of our<lb/> congregation is greatly at fault&#44; the immortal ge&#45;<lb/>&#45;neral&#44; called first subsequently to preside with his wisdom over<lb/> the people he saved by his sword&#44; was asked<lb/> to witness the consecration dedication of the Mickv&#233; Israel&#39;s<lb/> Sanctuary Synagogue at Philadelphia in 1782.  How broad<lb/> was the mind of George Washington was relatively<lb/> to all creeds built on Divine revelation&#44; a number of letters he wrote in<lb/> answer to representative Jewish corporations of his<lb/> time&#44; luminously show.  And I confess that in read&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing the proclamation of Benjamin Harrison&#44; in&#45;<lb/>&#45;viting Americans to <sic>devotionally</sic> commemorate a<lb/> signal occasion in their annals&#44; I felt much<lb/> gratified.  For I noticed that observed the spirit of the<lb/> most illustrious among his predecessors&#44; striving with&#45;<lb/>&#45;in him.  Our chief Executive said that Christians and<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Hebrews had suggested to him urged the<lb/> possibility fitness of holding public worship on this<lb/> memorable centennial.  How are as we are&#44; in<lb/> comparison with other denominations&#44; the wel&#45;<lb/>come fact was this officially published to the<lb/> world that we are nevertheless valued as an integral part<lb/> of the American commu nation at large was thus officially published to the world.  It is well that all know it.<lb/>  As to the object of it our prayful assemblages to day&#44;<lb/> needs not be explained no explanation is needed required&#44; but since they are it is meant<lb/> to keep alive a sense of gratitude to God for ha&#45;<lb/>&#45;ving raised a mighty deliverer and a glorious far sighted counsel&#45;<lb/>&#45;lor in time of need&#44; they who meet ought to take<lb/> to hear the words of the Sage whom they deservedly re&#45;<lb/>&#45;verence.  I fain would that his very ad&#45;<lb/>&#45;dress at his inauguration as the highest official<lb/> in the Republic&#44; which his military genius<lb/> created&#44; were seriously pondered on.  It breathes<lb/> sterling piety&#59; it is the inspiration of one who<lb/> sees the Almighty through all the vicissitudes<lb/> that brought salvation to a people destined as<lb/> a polar star of life hope to all who sigh for freed&#45;<lb/>&#45;om.  That address is indeed a telling<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>sermon.  It preaches reliance on the Ruler<lb/> of the Universe It emphasizes the truth&#44;<lb/> that achievements upon the battle field&#44; and the<lb/> results of human sagacity in framing liberal<lb/> laws&#44; may prove abortive&#44; of virtue&#44; founded<lb/> upon religious sentiments&#44; does not hold complete of way sway contract and influence multitudes.<lb/>  So said Washington in his speech to the Senate<lb/> and house of Representatives on the 30th day of April<lb/> 1789.  &#34;No people can be bound to acknowledge<lb/> and adore The Invisible Hand which conducts<lb/> the affairs of men&#44; more than the people of the United<lb/> States.  Every step to by which they have advanced<lb/> to the character of an independent nation&#44; seems to have<lb/> been distinguished by some tokens of Providential agency.<lb/> ....We ought to be fully persuaded that the pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;pitious smiles of Heaven can never be expected on<lb/> a nation that disregards the eternal rules of<lb/> order and right&#44; which Heaven itself has ordain&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed.&#34;  Simple words simply uttered told&#44; but to which<lb/> history affixes its indelible seal.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>America has progressed unprecedentedly<lb/> since those admirable words were uttered&#44; and to the vindication vindication of &#34;order and right&#34; she arose magnificently and took the a front rank<lb/> token in civilization&#44; when she erased every vestige<lb/> of serfdom from Maine to the Gulf of Mexico.<lb/>  She deservedly unquestionably stands also foremost also in every<lb/> department of practical science making handiwork<lb/> easier to the laborer&#44; opening wide avenues which lead&#45;<lb/>ing to the prosperity of sixty millions of beings&#44;<lb/> who constitute the grandest Republic over upon which<lb/> the sin sun has ever shone&#44; and singularly promoting relief and comfort<lb/> and pleasure seize in endless directions.  But are those who pride<lb/> themselves on Washington similarly actuated by<lb/> godly impulses&#63;  Were they so&#44; they would not<lb/> allow speculative science&#44; the mistress of modern incre&#45;<lb/>&#45;dulity&#44; the large control which it exercises over<lb/> the minds.  of multitudes For that it is which dethrones God&#44; and crowns fallible reason.  A literature less copious<lb/> perhaps&#44; but sounder more spiritualizing would find votaries&#44; a literature resting upon the firm<lb/> basis of God&#39;s Law and His Personal Providence would<lb/> be cultivated among the children youths whom&#44; we hope&#44;<lb/> will perpetuate the ws popular self&#45;government established by<lb/> the heroism and administrative wisdom of Washington him the one great one<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>who that was &#34;first in war&#44; first in peace&#44; first in<lb/> the hearts of his countrymen.&#34;  It is opportune<lb/> the to deprecate the evils effects of a wide&#45;spread skepti&#45;<lb/>&#45;cism&#44; which is fostered by lear the learning of our age.<lb/>  Oh&#33; may never the land of Washington never be threat&#45;<lb/>&#45;ened with the evils which has so often afflicted&#44; and<lb/> still afflict&#44; the land that lent it us generous help<lb/> in the hour of trial&#33;  For in France infidelity is<lb/> very nigh legalized&#44; and those at the helm of<lb/> the ship of state&#44; take for their compass nation&#45; military<lb/> &#45;al vestige&#44; not national virtue.  Ours rudder and anchor must be<lb/> religion&#44; that is&#44; a child like dependence implicit reliance upon<lb/> a Higher Power&#44; who sanctifies makes gives righteousness<lb/> the final victory.  That Power was with America at its<lb/> small beginning&#44; has continued with it as a<lb/> reward for past excellencies&#44; and will never de&#45;<lb/>&#45;part so long as we look up to it for salvation.<lb/>  Gladly I would interpret this centennial public celebra&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion as a pledge of our adherence to the advice of<lb/> the illustrious first President who took the oath<lb/> of his office this day a century ago.  No cant&#44;<lb/> I verily believe&#44; dictated the proclamation of<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Benjamin Harrison.  His invitation to Christ&#45;<lb/>&#45;ians and Hebrews to render thanks to the<lb/> omnipotent Lord for His manifold favors du&#45;<lb/>&#45;ring a century the the hundred years of our national well&#45;organized existence&#44; and to of&#45;<lb/>&#45;fer supplications for His countenance and protection<lb/> at all times&#44; was dictated urged by sincerity.  Parades<lb/> and banquets and flag displaying may minister to a<lb/> pardonable vanity&#44; while they gratify the senses&#44; but<lb/> real delight is the consciousness of national political purity&#44;<lb/> what gives a nation lasting glory is the uprightness<lb/> thereof.  So said the Biblical moralist and so believes holds as<lb/> true the American who now guides this nation holds as true.  Upon the<lb/> day that brings to memory the services of the man&#44;<lb/> who reflected the widest share of honor upon the Republic of<lb/> the North&#44; and whose name will ever remain a cause<lb/> of blessing to humanity at large&#44; let us determine to so act<lb/> that his own fervent supplication entreaty in performing discharging his first offi&#45;<lb/>cial act may be fulfilled&#59; namely that the Almighty<lb/> Being who rules the universe...may consecrate to the liber&#45;<lb/>ties and happiness of the poeple of the U. S&#44; a govern&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment instituted by themselves for noble and &#91;&#63;&#93; soul elevating purposes.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Lord God&#33;  Not as a holy convocation&#44; ordained<lb/> in the Law of Moses Thy servant have we we now assembled<lb/> in Thy holy courts&#44; but in earnestness and sincerity we<lb/> have come to acknowledge the great benefactions Thou<lb/> hast bestowed upon us&#44; as inhabitants of this favored<lb/> land.  Listen Thou in heaven when the people Thou<lb/> hast blessed with freedom&#44; prays to Thee&#44; and vouch&#45;<lb/>&#45;safe always wonderfully to help all the children<lb/> of America.  Unfeigned gladness is theirs&#44; when<lb/> they remember that this day&#44; one hundred years<lb/> ago&#44; Thou didst raise as their Chief Executive a<lb/> true man.  He was Guided with righteousness valor for<lb/> Thy name&#45;sake&#44; and after he had saved with<lb/> his trenchant sword a vast people from the<lb/> power of an overbearing king&#44; he and afterward swore by Thy<lb/> sacred name to judge all impartially.  Now&#44;<lb/> recalling the oath and so which he took&#44; and kept<lb/> with unswerving fidelity&#44; we have entered Thy<lb/> sanctuary to bless Thy name&#44; O Lord&#33;  For<lb/> there art the Dev Divine Being who chose him&#59;<lb/> Thou didst endow him with po the power to<lb/> succeed&#59; Thou didst lead him with Thy righteous<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>counsel&#44; that he might perform what<lb/> he promised.  Therefore he stood firm in<lb/> the path of rectitude from the day that Thou<lb/> didst raise him&#44; as a guide&#44; till the eight<lb/> years of his high trust expired.  May<lb/> the name of George Washington endure for ever&#44;<lb/> and may the liberty be wrought&#44; remain<lb/> in all generations among the people for<lb/> whom he fought and whom he delivered.<lb/>  Lord God&#33; fulfil speedily the promise of Thy<lb/> Seer&#44; that Thou shalt reign over all creatures&#44;<lb/> and all the in dwellers of the earth will<lb/> join in a union of states for mutual protect&#45;<lb/>&#45;ion and to fear and love Thy name forevermore.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
