<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF1_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff1_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff1_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff1_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff1_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff1_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff1_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff1_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff1_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff1_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff1_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff1_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff1_1_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <p>For Sabbath Bereshith<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>The holidays have just ended.  A sense of <sic>Duty</sic> and an eager<lb/> wish to be of some use&#44; suggest to my mind the<lb/> propriety of saying a few words in relation to the<lb/> sacred work&#44; which the Congregation Mickv&#232; Israel <sic>pur&#45;<lb/>&#45;poses</sic> to accomplish.  Its Sunday School&#44; being<lb/> comparatively small in the number of students&#44; ought<lb/> to give evidences of a progress not so as easily attain&#45;<lb/>&#45;able where very many receive instruction simultaneously.<lb/></p>
            <p>In one of my visits to a kindred <sic>instilation</sic>&#44; I learnt<lb/> with satisfaction that the old system of committing compelling to<lb/> to memoryize questions and answers from a catechism&#44;<lb/> had virtually been abandoned there.  A wise determin&#45; measure<lb/>&#45;nation I consider that&#44; because the receptive mind of<lb/> a child will imbibe lessons when imparted orally by a teacher&#44; who<lb/> is alive in the performance of a holy task&#44; whereas<lb/> the printed lines of a book may fail to create an<lb/> impression.  But I have said it&#59; the teacher<lb/> must be alive&#44; and in order to feel in that wakeful<lb/> condition&#44; preparations are necessary.  Not<lb/> by way of dictation&#44; but as a brotherly and friendly recom&#45;<lb/>&#45;mendation I would ask of all who have assumed the<lb/> charge of familiarizing our children with the history of<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>the Hebrew Bible&#44; to study what is most fit to<lb/> be taught and learn practice how to teach it.  The earliest<lb/> impressions are the most lasting&#59; the instruction given<lb/> should therefore aim to produce that effect.  Ac&#45;<lb/>&#45;cordingly&#44; instead of dwelling on such events as have<lb/> no immediate connection with the history of our people&#44;<lb/> the narrative of incidents events that present in a clear light the character of<lb/> patriarchs&#44; of priests and prophets ought to enchain<lb/> the attention of the young scholars.  Without<lb/> extenuating faults to be detected in from which the best of men are not free&#44;<lb/> our objective point should be to inspire love and ad&#45;<lb/>&#45;miration for whatever is loveable and admirable in<lb/> the life of our predecessors.  Our christian neigh&#45;<lb/>&#45;bours pride themselves on the alleged self sacrifice<lb/> of a mystic being whom they set forth as the embodiment incarnation<lb/> of perfection.  We&#44; who reject the idea of deifying the living<lb/> or the dead&#44; must prove to our children that we<lb/> can cite in our ancestry virtues not unsurpassed.  The<lb/> experience which long years of study may have afforded<lb/> me&#44; shall always be at the disposal of teachers who<lb/> are willing to avail themselves thereof.<lb/></p>
            <p>The Hebrew School of the Mickv&#233; Israel congregation&#44;<lb/> will still command my unfailing assistance.  Would<lb/> that all my efforts and those of others to enlarge its usefulness met with all the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>encouragement deserved&#33;  Parents who contribute to<lb/> the support of this religious body owe it to consistency&#44;<lb/> at least&#44; to offer their offspring the opportunity of<lb/> becoming acquainted with the reading&#44; translation and<lb/> chanting melodies of our the ritual&#44; followed in our Synagogue.<lb/>  Unless possessed of the means of attaining that object gaining the same point<lb/> by private tuition&#44; they should not deny deprive their<lb/> children of the merit of participating intelligently<lb/> and heartily in the service tendered to the God of<lb/> Israel in these holy courts.  Gladly indeed&#44;<lb/> as I would endeavour to extend the teaching to Holy<lb/> Writ in the original from beginning to end&#44; I realize<lb/> the difficulty which a the very limited time allotted to the instruction places<lb/> against the attainment of that object.  But the<lb/> usual ordinary prayers ought to be household words&#44; not simply<lb/> in the recital&#44; but in the appreciative comprehension<lb/> of them by our youthful fellow&#45;congregants.  Fathers<lb/> and mothers should recognize that truth and act accord&#45;<lb/>&#45;ingly&#44; to ward off the danger which like the sword of Damocles hangs over my head&#59; the danger of a radical change in<lb/> the language of our liturgy and of another break in Jewish<lb/> unity and solidarity.  In my mind&#44; the voices of our little ones raised<lb/> aloud&#44; when the scroll of the Law is taken out of the Ark&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>and when again enshrined therein&#44; are an offering of sweet in&#45;<lb/>&#45;cense to the Lord.  I am anxious that the same voices<lb/> be heard harmoniously throughout.  To reach that<lb/> goal I shall act diligently in conjunction with colleagues&#44;<lb/> but the attendance at the school must increase very and the teach&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing facilities increase proportionately greatly.  I regret am glad that a fear I entertained has been removed.  I labored under the apprehension that the plan of the<lb/> &#34;Mickv&#233; Israel Association&#34; to facilitate promote the cultivation<lb/> of the Hebrew language was ineffective and had therefore been relinquished.  I do not<lb/> know the system which had been adopted to promote further the desirable object end but the<lb/> simple circumstance that some of my sisters in faith evinced<lb/> simple interest in that branch of learning&#44; was to me a rainbow<lb/> of promise.  Let the women of Israel show that the<lb/> study of Hebrew is a duty&#59; that it surpasses by far<lb/> in importance some of the accomplishments which<lb/> modern society exacts&#59; let them assign to it a front rank&#44;<lb/> let them make it an ideal and you may rely on<lb/> results wholesome and general.  I rejoice that efforts to that effect will be resumed.  Had I not con&#45;<lb/>&#45;sented to serve the Association in a manner which ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;pears more acceptable to it and in the pursuit of<lb/> which I devoted a number of sessions during two con&#45;<lb/>secutive terms&#44; I might undertake to receive by have pledged my<lb/> personal exertions what has suffered decay on behalf of Hebrew learning.<lb/>  But I dare not venture to jeopardize my usefulness<lb/> in other directions&#44; which claim my time and thoughts&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>by widening still now the sphere of my literary la&#45;<lb/>&#45;bours.  I commend the cause of the Hebrew lan&#45;<lb/>&#45;guage&#44; which involves that of a consistent permanence<lb/> of this Congregation&#44; to the mothers and daughters<lb/> born in my faith&#44; who worship in our with me in this minor sanc&#45;<lb/>&#45;tuary.  Praised be Bet the Lord who.  He saw that<lb/> this &#34;Hope of Israel&#34;&#45;&#45;the pioneer of Jewish learning in Phi&#45;<lb/>&#45;ladelphia&#45;&#45;wished to live up to the name it bears and<lb/> carry on improvingly the righteous work once begun&#44;<lb/> and not altogether relinquished&#44; the our Beneficent God before whose vision the future is ever present&#44; miraculously<lb/> led to hand in the act of penning a last will and<lb/> testament.  In the language of Isaiah we may ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;claim &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;This also proceeded from the Lord of Hasts&#91;&#63;&#93;&#44; wonderful<lb/> in counsel&#44; excellent in wisdom&#34;.  The veteran treasur&#45;<lb/>&#45;er of this venerable religious body&#44; possibly did not<lb/> imagined that the remote contingent upon which his bequest<lb/> in our trust depended could was unlikely to occur&#44; but it did happen to<lb/> the elevation of a learning most valuable&#44; and a to the lasting<lb/> honor to reputation of the giver and the honor of the trustworthy recipients.  You<lb/> have read the resolutions&#58; &#34;The Gratz college shall be<lb/> devoted to the dissemination of the knowledge of Jewish<lb/> history&#44; of the Hebrew language&#44; of Jewish literature and<lb/> the Jewish religion.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>&#34;Jewish history&#34;.  What an immensely vast field for culti&#45;<lb/>&#45;vation&#44; and that to be a field not open to a privileged few&#44; but<lb/> accessible to all youths&#44; the coheirs of that history.  Unfolded<lb/> to before their minds will be our exaltation and humiliation&#44; our<lb/> victories and our trials.  They all will learn to heroism of princi&#45;<lb/>&#45;ples&#44; the martyrdom&#44; for attending cherished which to sanctified ideals&#44; the sanctification hallowing of faith.<lb/>  In that study they our youths will acquire the ability&#44; so essentially<lb/> needed&#44; of imparting in their turn to others with a full mastery of the<lb/> subject&#44; the knowledge of the checkered annals of Israel.<lb/></p>
            <p>&#34;The Hebrew language.&#34;  The recalling of Sinai and Zion&#59; of<lb/> Moses &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;the chief of prophets&#34;&#44; of Isaiah<lb/> who could well rightly boast&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;The Lord God<lb/> has given me a fluent tongue that I should know how to sustain with words him that so weary&#34; the Hebrew language&#44; a poetry<lb/> that thrills to ecstasy&#44; a rhythm that charms&#44; a pathos<lb/> that affects to tears.  It is the heart&#44; overflowing with<lb/> natural emotions that speaks&#44; it is sincerity that chides<lb/> and approves in accents which inspiration dictates.<lb/></p>
            <p>&#34;Jewish literature&#34;.  Have you seen the ocean surging up&#63;<lb/> over waves overtower waves&#44; compare to it the literature of<lb/> your people.  The Talmud alone has been likened to a<lb/> bottomless sea&#44; and that is but a fragment of the learning&#44;<lb/> which the thousands of years of our existence has produced.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>&#34;The Jewish religion&#34;  Reason illumined by Revelation&#44; a spi&#45;<lb/>&#45;ritual relationship between God of Justice and the undying<lb/> witnesses of His righteousness&#59; memorials of an unparalleled<lb/> past&#44; promises of a glorious future.  Will the acquisition<lb/> of all that learning constitute flow directly from the Gratz<lb/> college&#63;  If it shall accomplish but a portion of<lb/> that very far reaching undertaking&#44; this &#34;Hope of Israel&#34;<lb/> will redeem its name so luminously&#44; as to compel a<lb/> universal acknowledgment of noble deeds it will have has wrought.<lb/>  May the discernment of those to whom the charge of<lb/> placing the institution on solid foundations has been com&#45;<lb/>&#45;mitted&#44; overcome the difficulties which the selection of pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;ceptors will present.  May God be with them and decree<lb/> for the college unlimited success.<lb/></p>
            
            <p>&#40;an address to a Bar Mitzvah followed&#41;<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
