<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF19_3</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff19_3_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff19_3_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff19_3_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff19_3_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff19_3_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff19_3_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff19_3_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff19_3_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff19_3_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff19_3_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff19_3_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff19_3_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 3 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>For Vayekra<lb/>
                on charity before Pesach<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  Every one knows that an organization to<lb/> suppress mendicancy&#44; and to aid the deserving poor systematic&#45;<lb/>&#45;ally and effectually&#44; is busy at work in Philadelphia.<lb/>  About its operations and prospective success&#44; popular opinion<lb/> varies.  Some think it correct that all applications for<lb/> assistance should be closely questioned or their antecedents and<lb/> present condition&#44; and that an inspection of the premises they<lb/> occupy be made by a committee capable of discerning and<lb/> discriminating.  Others object to inquiries and visits&#44; which<lb/> they call term inquisitorial&#44; fearing they may raise a blush<lb/> or wound susceptibilities and they foretell a failure of the enterprise.  Each Both opinion has strong a basis<lb/> grounds to rest upon&#44; but the truly sensible and sympathetic<lb/> must hope that experience will show high wisdom in<lb/> the undertaking now only in its &#91;&#63;&#93;.  For the avowed<lb/> intention of the designers promoters is very progressive&#44; and some of<lb/> the managers are noted for their clear keen sightedness and<lb/> philanthropy.  I hold that if the society will it can steer entirely<lb/> clear of denominationalism&#44; leaving clergymen in the Church back ground&#44;<lb/> if only naught but a broad religion which hides shame&#44; and brings forth<lb/> the dormant the instincts of of our better nature&#45;&#45;an inherent desire for<lb/> advancement by means of education and industry&#45;&#45;is put into given full<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>play&#44; it may the society will ultimately prove a blessing to the indigent<lb/> themselves&#44; and a great relief to the charitable themselves.<lb/>  These will not be denied the spiritual enjoyment of<lb/> doing good personally&#44; for exceptional occasions will<lb/> always arise to that effect&#44; but by entrusting committing to charging trustworthy cor&#45;<lb/>&#45;porations with with the distribution of alms they will be spared<lb/> the annoyance of importunate beggars at their residence<lb/> and in the streets&#59; They and will receive a moral assurance<lb/> that their gift is not converted into a the accursed bane&#44; poisoning<lb/> the spring of life and domestic joy.<lb/></p>
            <p>Hebrews&#44; however&#44; have in all ages and in all countries&#44;<lb/> taken a noble pride in contributing to state and<lb/> civic associations of beneficence&#44; without drawing upon<lb/> their funds.  They have looked well that the<lb/> indigent needy among the people of God of Abraham&#44;<lb/> may not become a burden to the community at large.<lb/>  Travel wherever you choose&#45;&#45;and scarcely a place<lb/> exists under the sun in which Jews do not congregate&#45;&#45;<lb/> and the same fact will strike the mind.  The<lb/> descendants of the patriarchs make special provisions<lb/> to prevent their coreligionists applying to institutions<lb/> of a general character.  They voluntarily waive their<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>right so to do&#44; and mark it an offence in any&#44; who<lb/> under on the plea of destitution&#44; stand as petitioners mendicants at the<lb/> doors of non&#45;Israelites.  Occasionally&#44; I have been addressed<lb/> by kind&#45;hearted Christians who&#44; under the impression<lb/> that individuals or families of my people had been<lb/> cup culpably neglected&#44; sought my interposition.<lb/>  But with scarcely any exception&#44; I discovered on in&#45;<lb/>&#45;quiry&#44; that our neighbors of another creed had al&#45;<lb/>&#45;lowed their feelings to warp their judgment.  The sub&#45;<lb/>&#45;jects of their generous thoughts had repeatedly received<lb/> from us a large share of assistance.  I cannot suf&#45;<lb/> &#45;ficiently denounce in sufficiently strong language the<lb/> conduct of such as disgrace the name inherited&#44; by traf&#45;<lb/>&#45;ficking with their children&#39;s souls&#44; by sending the young<lb/> to mission schools&#44; that their elders may malign Israel&#44;<lb/> and thus gain clothing&#44; and fuel and money.  And If<lb/> there be any&#45;&#45;I trust not&#45;&#45;within reach of my voice hearers who<lb/> act so impiously&#44; let them understand that they are<lb/> placing themselves beyond the reach of Jewish charities.<lb/>  Still&#44; the latter which do a vast deal of good&#44;&#45;&#45;whatever<lb/> croakers may say to the contrary&#44; must be kept<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>in a condition equal to all emergencies and those<lb/> who have accepted the direction must exercise perform their<lb/> very onerous arduous but merciful task with a proper regard<lb/> to times and circumstances.  It is a cause of<lb/> unfeigned satisfaction to know that notwithstand&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing the p depression of trade and the universal<lb/> falling off of income derived from any source&#44; the<lb/> treasury of our combined organization&#44; depleted at the<lb/> end of the fiscal year&#44; was replenished.  Nothing<lb/> can better illustrate the verity that benevolence is an<lb/> ornament of which we will not become divested&#44; how&#45;<lb/>&#45;ever stripped we may be of other religious qualities&#59;<lb/> that the cry of humanity sounds louder in our breasts ears<lb/> than self&#45;&#91;&#63;&#93; promotion the dictates of selfishness.  But now the capacity of<lb/> our treasury to meet the demand will be put to the<lb/> severest test.  Therefore has my heart urged me to speak.<lb/>  My ministerial official recollection goes far back.  I can remember that<lb/> on the approaching of Passover some who do not<lb/> regularly ask relief&#44; advised with me about obtain&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing the means to celebrate the holiday in ac&#45; agreeably<lb/> &#45;cordance with to the ancient prescriptions.  Then either the<lb/> congregation&#45;&#45;differently situated&#45;&#45;or its generous head&#44; would comply with<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>my request&#44; and thus misfortune maintained its<lb/> respectability.  But never did I suffer the pain<lb/> experienced this week&#44; for I saw modest poverty<lb/> cast off its veil&#44; so great potent was the pressure from wi&#45;<lb/>&#45;thin which prevented further concealment.  Parents<lb/> who have a numerous households to feed&#44; but who during<lb/> the last six months&#44; scarcely earned enough to allay<lb/> their hunger&#44; inquired whether they could be supplied<lb/> with the bread of the festival.  I at once answered affirmatively&#44;<lb/> but wishing to spare a humiliation&#44; I suggested how<lb/> to compass the object without calling at the rooms of<lb/> the society.  This My proposition elicited this sad remark &#34;We must<lb/> make our situation condition known for the sake of wife and our dear<lb/> children&#34;.  Now&#44; I beg of the president and through<lb/> him of the directors of our United Charities to use excuse more<lb/> than ordinarily&#44; a thoughtful consideration finding on the<lb/> ensuing week and that which follows it.  I am aware<lb/> of the strain brought about.  It is unprecedented.  It naturally counsels administrative prudence.  Well&#44;<lb/> economy is a commendable virtue&#44; specially with means<lb/> entrusted to our care by a confiding public&#44; but the eco&#45;<lb/>&#45;nomy which curtalils the unhappy man&#39;s allowance&#44;<lb/> the economy which creates the alternative either to<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>stint our little ones food victuals&#44; or disobey the law of God<lb/> by the introduction of the prohibited leaven&#44; ceases<lb/> to be a virtue&#44; and enters into the category of vice.<lb/>  I do not underrate the difficulties which surround attending the<lb/> office.  They are indeed serious.  To discharge the duties honorable<lb/> attending their but onerous duties&#44; firmness must blend with gentleness&#44;<lb/> sagacity caution with promptness.  For no doubt imposition<lb/> is practised&#44; at this season particularly&#44; just by reason<lb/> of the rigidness with which the coming holiday is should be kept.<lb/>  It may be that Perhaps some who do not scruple setting<lb/> aside the very day of atonement&#44; play the religious the<lb/> week of Passover.  Yet better to risk the deception of the unprincipled&#44;<lb/> than expose the worthy and the sincerely observant<lb/> to suffering.  Notably this year&#44; when to judge<lb/> of the state of the applicant by his appearance or<lb/> surroundings might be to do him a grievous wrong.<lb/>  How many&#44; alas&#33; who live in seeming comfort have<lb/> a cheerless foreside&#59; how many neatly dressed&#44; dread<lb/> the wearing out of garments which cannot perhaps be easily<lb/> be replaced&#33;  Let then our association give liberally<lb/> for the sacred Pesach we are about to solemnize&#44; and He who has implanted in our<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>breasts the seeds of compassion will provide hereafter.<lb/>  But let us our our own selves individually supplement what<lb/> it our organization cannot accomplish alone.  Brethren&#33; As much Greatly<lb/> as I feel interested as a social being &#45;&#45;as a human member of the human race&#45;&#45;in the right suc&#45;<lb/>&#45;cess of the society to suppress mendicancy&#44; I am nevertheless an&#45;<lb/>&#45;xious&#44; as a Jew&#44; to prevent my fellow&#45;believers becoming<lb/> its beneficiaries.  But indigence is a tempter&#44; whose<lb/> seductions few can resist.  Therefore ought should we to hasten<lb/> to the rescue of those apt to be overcome.  do not rest then con&#45;<lb/>&#45;tented with directing the man or the woman&#44; who<lb/> pictures to you the distress at home to the rooms of<lb/> the United Charities room&#44; and closing after the petitioners<lb/> the door of the your house after the petitioner retire ensconced in your finely tapestried drawing<lb/> room.  Do not fancy that by that act you have thus performed your obli&#45;<lb/>&#45;gation.  But stir yourselves and seek farther into the case brought under your notice at junctures<lb/> like the present&#59; bestow of your own upon the hapless.<lb/> Now is the time that tries men&#39;s souls.  The Rabbis tell<lb/> us that he who grieves over the sorrows of the community&#44;<lb/> will live to behold its restoration to enlargement and<lb/> happiness.  But our sympathies must assume a<lb/> practical form.  What avail that we shake our heads&#44;<lb/> and cry &#34;times are very hard&#44;&#34; and then but fold our arms&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>I hear all cry &#34;times are very bad hard&#34;&#44; but we can&#44; in a<lb/> measure&#44; soften their asperities.  We can bring joy<lb/> where gloom prevails.  We all have are constrained to reduce our<lb/> expenses conformably with the changes undergone&#44; but<lb/> let us not reduce our charity&#44; because whereas we<lb/> have lost a little portion&#44; our other creatures have lost their<lb/> all&#59; whereas our labor yields a small income&#44; other<lb/> creatures go in quest of work and find none.  Let<lb/> us resolve to devote what we can dispense with to<lb/> our flesh and blood&#44; that stand fearfully in need there&#45;<lb/>&#45;of.  Let us not only give&#44; but consider the poor&#44; as<lb/> David expresses it&#44; that is the mercy which beatifies the<lb/> soul&#44; imparadising it in the contemplation of the source<lb/> of goodness.  Oh may He who promised by the mouth<lb/> of Isaiah&#44; as read today in the Haftarah&#44; that He<lb/> would invigorate our seed as the soil irrigated by water&#44;<lb/> and would let His blessing rest on our offspring&#44; as re rain<lb/> rests on arid ground and fructifies it&#44; may even He&#44; our<lb/> Universal Parent&#44; verify that declaration&#44; in through our as a reward<lb/> to our charity beneficence&#44; in our country&#44; in our city&#44; and in<lb/> our homes.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
