<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF9_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_2_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>An explanatory lecture<lb/> on Vayechi<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  This Sabbath we have completed the<lb/> reading of the first book of Moses.  I say it<lb/> emphatically if Moses&#44; whatever critics of modern<lb/> or ancient schools may teach to the contrary.  The<lb/> name of the greatest of prophets does not&#45;&#45;it could not&#44;<lb/> of course&#45;&#45;figure in its pages&#44; but his inspired genius<lb/> pervades them&#59; his hand and that of none other could<lb/> have traced the narrative of events treasured up in that<lb/> venerable volume.  For&#44; disconnect the latter from the<lb/> writings which follow it&#44; and the whole Pentateuch<lb/> becomes a chaotic mass&#44; a confused account without<lb/> sequence and coherence&#44; incomprehensible and perplexing.<lb/>  Aye&#58; Moses born of the seed of the first believer&#44; had<lb/> learnt the history of Abraham and of the patriarchs&#44;<lb/> and set it down as a link in the chain of successive<lb/> incidents&#44; in which he played the most important part&#44;<lb/> and which have eternized his name.  Moses born and<lb/> reared in Egypt&#44; knew its laws&#44; its practices and man&#45;<lb/>&#45;ners so thoroughly as unerringly to allude to them&#44; when<lb/> describing the checkered life of Joseph and the settlement<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>of Jacob&#39;s family in the country of the Pharaohs.<lb/>  Moses walking in a light sent from above gathered<lb/> the records of circumstances preceding the departure of<lb/> the founder of our nation from Ur of the Chaldeans&#44;<lb/> and what he transmitted&#44; the discoveries of scientists&#44;<lb/> and of <sic>travellers</sic> now corroborate with an almost li&#45;<lb/>&#45;teral exactness.<lb/></p>
            <p>But I am addressing an audience&#44; who stands not in<lb/> need&#44; I trust&#44; of being confirmed in the belief of the au&#45;<lb/>&#45;thenticity of any of the five volumes which our fa&#45;<lb/>&#45;thers preserved at the cost of their lives&#39; blood for the<lb/> enlightenment and spiritual solace of all mankind.<lb/>  It might be a reflection on the religious sentiments<lb/> of my hearers&#44; to declare in their presence&#44; that<lb/> doubts cast of on the veracity of the writing which has<lb/> weekly engaged our attention since the close of our<lb/> fall holidays&#44; is tantamount to the impugning<lb/> of the truthfulness of the Sinaic revelation.  But<lb/> when men whose calling and duty it is to strengthen<lb/> the olden faith&#44; preach heresy&#59; when to display<lb/> erudition Jewish leaders echo forth the theories which<lb/> ultramontane Neologists have advanced with great<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>great assurance&#44; it may not be deemed out of time&#44;<lb/> nor out of place to caution the youths of my people<lb/> and say to them &#34;Friends&#33; Put credence in o no one<lb/> blindly Examine Exercise the faculties wherewith God<lb/> has endowed you.  Search for yourselves&#44; that you<lb/>  may arrive at a conscientious conclusion.&#34;  I have<lb/> no fear of the ultimate result&#44; provided that insidious<lb/> influences are not set at work to warp the minds.<lb/>  The natural intelligence of our sons and daughters will<lb/> suggest that the further we remove the book of Genesis<lb/> from the Biblical period to which it rightly belongs&#44;<lb/> the less can it be made to correspond with the following annals<lb/> and ordinances of Judaism&#44; and the more inexplicable<lb/> some of its contents will necessarily appear.  Thus&#44;<lb/> to cite a single example&#59; if the prophetic blessing of<lb/> Jacob to his twelve sons is an invention of later ages&#45;&#45;<lb/>supposing the patriarch incapable of shaping his utter&#45;<lb/>&#45;ances in a poetic form&#44; and of peering into the future&#45;&#45;<lb/> if that is a fiction&#44; then the benediction of Moses agreeing therewith on some fronts to the tribes<lb/> tribes is must be also a myth&#44; &#38; then the allotted division<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>of Palestine in the days of Joshua must have been<lb/> an act of arbitrariness&#44; and then we may fittingly<lb/> ask by what claims the descendants of Joseph re&#45;<lb/>&#45;ceived a double inheritance&#44; and Levy had only<lb/> some cities located in various sections of the holy land&#63;<lb/>  But it is not my purpose to animadvert on the<lb/> schools of critics&#44; and show on which side reason&#44; lo&#45;<lb/>&#45;qual and sound preponderates in the struggle which<lb/> has been carried between the skeptics and the conservatives<lb/>  Still&#44; I feel it binding on me to caution warn my brothers<lb/> and sisters&#44; whose age renders their hearts most im&#45;<lb/>&#45;pressible&#44; against accepting without deep consider&#45;<lb/>&#45;ation what is calculated to rob them of their<lb/> dearest wealth&#44; of the belief in the five volumes&#44;<lb/> forming the cornerstone of Israel&#39;s religion&#44; and the<lb/> ground upon which men have built up the constitutions<lb/> of mighty empire and republics.  I repeat it&#44;<lb/> the five volumes&#44; because the first is an integral<lb/> part of a connected lever&#59; it is the &#91;&#63;&#93; history<lb/> of the Monotheistic idea&#44; of which the other four<lb/> are the development and amplification.  Genesis is&#44;<lb/> if I may be allowed the simile&#44; the Chrysalis&#44; whence<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>the winged creatures gradually issues forth in all<lb/> perfection.  A sentence in to&#45;day&#39;s lesson bears out<lb/> my meaning and to it I will&#44; for a few moments&#44;<lb/> direct your attention.  Joseph&#39;s brothers returned from<lb/> the burial of their father with heavier feelings than<lb/> those pervading the heart of the viceroy of Egypt.<lb/>  Dread mig mingled with sadness.  They could not forget<lb/> that he who&#44; during seventeen years&#44; had exhibited a<lb/> generosity almost superhuman&#44; had been at one time<lb/> the target of their poisonous arrows&#59; that through their<lb/> ill&#45;will the steps whence he arose to power had<lb/> been spread over with wasps stinging to the core.  Had<lb/> Rachel&#39;s son forgotten the wrongs&#63;  Or&#44; was it filial<lb/> reverence which held him back from wreaking vengeance<lb/> upon their heads&#44; while the fondly cherished parent<lb/> lived&#63;  To calm their agitated spirits they had re&#45;<lb/>&#45;course to a stratagem&#44; which the distress suffered at<lb/> that hour can alone exculpate in a measure.  They<lb/> charged some friends to carry a message to Joseph&#44; and<lb/> lead him to think that Jacob&#39;s last thought had been<lb/> a request for a full&#44; unconditional pardon of his child&#45;<lb/>&#45;ren who had once most grievously offended.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Mark the incident well.  They who conveyed the<lb/> communication&#44; having repeated the <sic>suppositious</sic><lb/> words of the patriarch&#44; added &#34;Now&#44; do forgive the<lb/> trespass of the servants of thy father&#39;s God.&#34;  Here we<lb/> see unfolded before our mind&#39;s eyes the bond which<lb/> already united indissolubly together the progeny of<lb/> the man who had preached Monotheism amidst a<lb/> polytheistic world.  Long ere we became a nation<lb/> was formed that sacred tie&#44; which grew stronger<lb/> with our numerical growth till it created a solida&#45;<lb/>&#45;rity that time can never dissolve.  The idea of<lb/> one Omniscient and Omnipresent God inspired senti&#45;<lb/>&#45;ments of mutual forbearance and kindliness.  If the<lb/> excellent Joseph had felt disposed to slight the peti&#45;<lb/>&#45;tition&#44; which he may have suspected not to emana&#45;<lb/>&#45;te from his father&#44; he dared not resist the appeal<lb/> associated with the name of his father&#39;s God.<lb/>  Listen as the noble man speaks &#34;Fear not&#44; for&#44; am<lb/> I in the place of God&#34;&#33;  It signifies.  &#34;Have I not<lb/> been taught by our common belief that we are all<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>the agents of the Supreme&#59; that our intentions&#44; however<lb/> wicked&#44; cannot frustrate the will of the Almighty&#44; but<lb/> that in His hand they are made to subserve His wise<lb/> ends&#63;  It is for the Creator to punish thoughts.  As<lb/> to myself&#44; I recognize in your action&#44; the workings of<lb/> a beneficent Providence&#44; and as such will I reward it.&#34;<lb/>  And when the time drew night for Rachel&#39;s elder son<lb/> also to be gathered to his people&#44; the idea of a<lb/> union derived from a community of religious sen&#45;<lb/>&#45;timents&#44; not less than from <sic>consaguinity</sic>&#44; manifested it&#45;<lb/>&#45;self palpably in the sentence which concludes the his&#45;<lb/>&#45;tory of the first stage of Monotheism.  Joseph ad&#45;<lb/>&#45;jured the children of Israel thus&#58; &#34;God will surely visit<lb/> you&#44; then ye shall carry my bones away from this place.&#34;<lb/>  United have we been in faith while on earth&#44; and<lb/> conjointly must we our dust mingle in the spot destined<lb/> by our fathers God as our heritage....Yes&#44; Brethren&#33;<lb/>  Abraham stands at the basis of the grand edifice into<lb/> which all mankind will one day seek shelter.  His<lb/> offspring in the third generation were became the materials<lb/> with which its construction was begun.  The law<lb/> of Moses set up its massive pillars&#44; the preaching<lb/></p> 
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>of the prophets vaulted and roofed it&#44; the enact&#45;<lb/>ments of our Rabbins have walled it around.  We are its sworn custodians.  Woe<lb/> unto us if a spirit of <sic>Kepticism</sic>&#44; now prevailing&#44;<lb/> incites us to desert our post.  Woe unto us&#44; if the<lb/> fear of bantering makes us fainted hearted&#59; if to escape<lb/> the derision of those who call a denial of belief and en&#45;<lb/>&#45;lightenment&#44; and reverence to religion&#44; ignorance&#44;<lb/> we suffer our powers to grow weary in watching<lb/> the fabric of human civilization&#44; &#34;the Law testimony<lb/> which He established in Jacob&#44; and the Law He<lb/> set in Israel&#44; which He commanded co our fathers&#44;<lb/> that they may cause them to be known by their<lb/> children&#44; so that the latter generation&#44; the childrens generation<lb/> yet to be born may be acquainted therewith&#44; and<lb/> they may rise and relate then to their own children.&#34;  Let us vow<lb/> allegiance thereto in the presence of our Lord&#44; and<lb/> in this oracle consecrated to His name&#59; that we may<lb/> deserve the <sic>tittle</sic> of witnesses of the One&#44; eternal<lb/> and all&#45;saving God.  So may it be Amen.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
