<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF4_16</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_16_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_16_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_16_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_16_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_16_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_16_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_16_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_16_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_16_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_16_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_16_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_16_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_16_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_16_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_16_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_16_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Post Biblical<lb/>
                36<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>A Talmudical legend tells that the ninth of Ab<lb/> was doomed&#44; from an early stage in Jewish history&#44;<lb/> to be conspicuous inauspicious to our race.  When ten of the<lb/> twelve men sent by Moses to explore the Holy Land<lb/> of promise&#44; exaggerated the difficulties of conquering<lb/> Canaan&#44; and our people fearing to venture upon<lb/> a battle&#44; murmured and wept aloud&#44; a superhuman<lb/> voice spoke.  It exclaimed so&#58; &#34;This same night<lb/> on which you have shed tears without a just cause&#44;<lb/> will see you in future ages weep because of great<lb/> disasters.&#34;  The legend may have had its origin<lb/> in much later times than the Rabbis claim&#44; still<lb/> the strange fact remains that even in post&#45;Tal&#45;<lb/>&#45;mudic times ages&#44; sorrowful incidents&#44; affecting Hebrew whole<lb/> communities of Hebrews&#44; did take place on the ninth or tenth<lb/> of the month of Ab.  None&#44; however&#44; has<lb/> <sic>equalled</sic> in its widespread and long continued horrors&#44;<lb/> the event which happened in the year 70 of<lb/> the vulgar era.<lb/></p>
            <p>Immediately after Titus had ordered that the fire<lb/> which was fast destroying the outer part of the Temple<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>be put out&#44; a council of war was hastily<lb/> summoned.  Six of the highest officers in the army<lb/> attended it.  They were divided in their opinions<lb/> as to the final disposition which should be made<lb/> of the Temple.  Some forcibly argued that so long<lb/> as it was allowed to stand&#44; the Jews would use<lb/> it as a rallying point and never submit to terms.<lb/>  It is said that Titus opposed those views and<lb/> prevailed&#45;&#45;the grandeur magnificence of the edifice on whose em&#45;<lb/>&#45;bellishment countless treasures had been spent&#44; had<lb/> excited the ambition of the victor.  He would leave<lb/> it&#44; as the grandest trophy of his conquest&#44; but the<lb/> Jews had otherwise determined.  They would resolved to pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;tect the sanctuary from heathen intrusion&#44; or<lb/> perish with it.  Having recovered from the<lb/> bewilderment by which they were at first seized at the<lb/> sight of the conflagration&#44; they attacked the<lb/> Roman guards&#44; and compelled a precipitate<lb/> flight.  Titus came ran to the rescue and forced the<lb/> Jews to retreat&#44; but they rushed on again to the<lb/> bloody struggle.  Overpowered once more by a<lb/> superior number&#44; and exhausted by starvation&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>they were thrust by the bayonets driven into the interior inner<lb/> part of the Temple.  The evening of August the<lb/> 10th&#44; corresponding with the ninth or tenth of Ab&#44;<lb/> had come on&#59; darkness had put a stop an end to the clank&#45; deadly<lb/> &#45;ing clang of the wood swords and the whizzing of javelins.<lb/>  Roman guards stationed in the holy House paced it<lb/> up to and down fro&#59; others were busy in quenching the fire<lb/> still smoldering in some of the cloisters&#44; when they<lb/> suddenly felt the sharp steel in the hands of the Jews pierce their bodies.<lb/>  A terrific fight ensued&#44; and with it a shriek that<lb/> echoed from mountain to mountain.  A Roman<lb/> soldier furious because of the unexpected attack onslaught&#44; had<lb/> mounted upon the shoulders of another&#44; and thrown<lb/> a blazing brand into a gilded window&#44; communicating<lb/> with the interior of the sanctuary.  The flames spread<lb/> wildly&#44; and in their midst Jews and Romans throt&#45;<lb/>&#45;tled one another&#44; trampled upon each other.  The<lb/> defenders and the assailants&#44; stirred by irreconcilable<lb/> hatred&#44; breathed but revenge.  Then forward pressed<lb/> new destroyers hurling fire brands&#59; madly dashed on<lb/> fresh legions to hew into pieces women and children&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>together they lay swam in rivers of blood<lb/> with the helpless hoary headed sires.  Titus awakened<lb/> from his sleep&#44; thundered down rushed to the scene of<lb/> carnage.  He commands that order be restored&#44; none<lb/> hears.  He demands that the conflagration be<lb/> quenched&#44; none obeys.  His voice is drowned in<lb/> the shouts of an infuriated loose soldiery&#44; thirsting for bent upon<lb/> plunder&#59; in the cries of despairing thousands<lb/> ghastly with agonized with from terror&#59; in the crash of buildings en&#45;<lb/>&#45;vellopped in volumes of columns of flames.  Titus&#45;&#45;the delight<lb/> of mankind&#45;&#45;as he has been flatteringly called&#44; would have spared<lb/> for his own triumph the gorgeous structure&#44; whose golden surroundings spark&#45;<lb/>&#45;ling through sheets of fire&#44; dazzled his vision&#44; but no<lb/> word of mercy sparing pity for the unarmed lying in heaps round<lb/> the altar of God&#44; escaped his lips.  His favored<lb/> prisoner&#44; who wrote such a history as might be<lb/> stamped with an imperial seal&#44; did not feel<lb/> his hand tremble&#44; and his pen refuse its wonted office&#44;<lb/> when about to record the last agonies of a dying an expiring<lb/> nation.  Josephus could&#44; without an outburst<lb/> of Jewish anguish&#44; tell posterity how some priests servants<lb/> of the Lord plunged into the flaming fire abyss.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>With the coldness of a Chronicler of d passing events&#44;<lb/> he could describe the wanton butchery made by Titus<lb/> of priests&#44; who&#44; pining with hunger and thirst had trustingly sur&#45;<lb/>&#45;rendered.  In the midst of thrilling episd epi&#45;<lb/>&#45;sodes of in the last final hours of our political existence&#44; the<lb/> Romanized Jew could describe detain us with the notions he entertained<lb/> about on an inevitable fate&#44; and the about on extraordinary signs of approaching<lb/> evils&#44; which his people coreligionists did not heed&#44; preferring the<lb/> prediction good prognostics of false prophets. which occasioned sufferings<lb/>and death By a Jew&#44; the pages that narrate the planting<lb/> of the Roman Eagle where the Shekinah had hovered&#44; the<lb/> profanity of Roman soldiers cohorts and their abominable<lb/> sacrifices where Solomon had invoked the visible influence<lb/> of Israel&#39;s God should have been traced in lines breathing<lb/> the keenest mortification&#44; the most poignant grief.<lb/></p>
            <p>About six centuries before the catastrophe delineated<lb/> by Josephus had occurred&#44; a man of his own tribe&#45;&#45;<lb/> a priest&#45;&#45;had witnessed the burning of the Temple&#44; and<lb/> the dispersion of his people.  He also had discovered<lb/> the impossibility of coping with the foreign a formidable heathen enemy&#44;<lb/> and had <sic>counselled</sic> a temporary submission.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>He also pictured the downfall and desolation&#44;<lb/> the affliction and death&#44; but in his <sic>protrait</sic>&#44; the<lb/> tears of him who <sic>pencilled</sic> it are still seen to flow.<lb/>  We may hear yet his groans in his elegies.  &#34;Oh<lb/> that my head were water&#44; and my eye a fountain of<lb/> tears&#59; I would weep day and night over the slain<lb/> of the daughter of my people&#34; so mourned the priest<lb/> of Anathoth&#45;&#45;the high souled deeply distressed patriot&#45;&#45;Jeremiah.  And in his im&#45;<lb/>&#45;mortal book of lamentations&#58; &#34;O wall of the daughter of<lb/> Zion&#33;  Let thy tears run down like a stream river day and night&#44; give<lb/> thyself no rest&#59; let not the apple of thy eye be still.<lb/>  Rise&#44; cry out in the night&#44; in the beginning of the watches&#44;<lb/> pour out thy heart before the face of the Lord&#44; lift up<lb/> towards Him thy hands because of the life of thy young<lb/> children&#44; that faint for hunger at the corner of<lb/> every all streets.&#34;  Josephus could calmly relate that<lb/> innumerable were his brethren sold as slaves&#59; that the<lb/> aged and the sick who could not unfit to be so disposed of&#44; the<lb/> Roman sword cut to pieces&#59; that among the insurgents<lb/> the youngest and the handsomest were reserved to<lb/> enhance the triumph&#44; the rest were killed like<lb/> cattle&#44; that twelve thousand died of starvation&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>that during the <sic>seige</sic> over one million<lb/> perished&#44; and nearly hundred thousands were made<lb/> prisoners and scattered through the world.  Josephus could insult us&#44;&#45;&#45;who must<lb/> he read his history for want of another&#45;&#45;by praising<lb/> the loving kindness long suffering and magnanimity of Tiutus his patron&#44; telling us in the same<lb/> breath that Caesar Titus sent multitudes of Jews to work in<lb/> Egyptian mines&#44; that others he destined for the<lb/> arena&#44; where they might fight with wild beasts&#44;<lb/> or kill each other as gladiators for the amusement of brutal spect&#45;<lb/>ators....<lb/></p>
            <p>Jerusalem stormed&#44; dismantled&#44; razed to the ground &#34;sitting soli&#45;<lb/>tary like a widow&#44; she that was a princess among<lb/> provinces&#44;&#34;&#45;&#45;as her true&#45;hearted elegist painted her&#45;&#45;Jeru&#45;<lb/>&#45;salem in her utter desolation could not offer any further<lb/> resistance&#44; yet no mercy was shown to the living&#59;<lb/> rapacity led a loos soldiery into caves and<lb/> grottos in search of gold.  Woe to those who<lb/> had sought there a refuge&#33;  Still&#44; two men&#44;<lb/> most prominent in the fatal war&#44; had escaped.<lb/>  They had unhappily headed two opposite functions&#44;<lb/> and caused untold misery&#44; but they had stood<lb/> shoulder to shoulder on the day of extreme danger.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>John of Giskala and Simon son of Gibras<lb/> had sworn never to lay down their arms.  Jose&#45;<lb/>&#45;hus&#44; who calls theat always chiefs always by the<lb/> names of &#34;tyrants and robbers&#44;&#34; is the ma authority<lb/> for the report of a proposition which Titus made<lb/> to them.  He The Roman general offered to spare their lives&#59; and be<lb/> a mild master&#44; if they unconditionally surrendered.  They did not<lb/> accept the terms&#44; and expressed the wish to retire<lb/> in a desert.  Their request being denied&#44; they kept<lb/> out of sight for a time&#44; hiding underground in deep caverns.  But<lb/> famine forced out John and his few followers.<lb/>  Titus condemned the Galilean chief to life impris&#45;<lb/>&#45;sonment and finally had him transported to Italy&#44; to drag<lb/> there the chains in a low dungeon.  Simon had<lb/> tried to dig a passage underground&#44; which  might<lb/> carry him beyond the reach of the Romans.<lb/>  His labors were unsuccessful.  Then clothed in<lb/> white and with an upper mantle of purple&#44;<lb/> he walked in front of the Temple ruins.  He<lb/> looked like a ghostly apparition&#44; but the Roman<lb/> guards recognized him and bound him in fetters.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Meanwhile Titus&#44; after having munificently<lb/> rewarded his officers with the riches of rapine and<lb/> pillage&#44; visited the surrounding provinces and enter&#45;<lb/>&#45;tained their inhabitants with splendid shows in honor<lb/> of the birth day of his father Vespasian and<lb/> his brother Dornitian.  &#34;The delight of mankind&#44;&#34;<lb/> had a vast number of Jews burnt above at those spectacles to<lb/> illustrate the manner in which he had finally forced<lb/> to submission from a city intolerably rebellious to against his power.  To<lb/> add to the public diversions&#44; he had many Jews also<lb/> thrown to ferocious animals amidst the ribald jests<lb/> of a savage population.  At length&#44; in the<lb/> spring of the year 71; he left the scene of his<lb/> greatness&#44; acquired by the horrors of a protracted<lb/> war&#44; by fire&#44; plunder&#44; and sacrilege&#44; to receive<lb/> the plaudits of a remorseless people&#44; verging<lb/> on dissolution&#44; but still craving for military<lb/> conquests.  The glory which awaited Titus<lb/> at the Capitol was jointly shared by Vespa&#45;<lb/>&#45;sian&#44; and both were saluted Emperors.  In<lb/> the triumphal march&#44; the trophies carried<lb/> away from the sanctuary of the Eternal Lord&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>were borne aloft&#45;&#45;the golden table&#44; and the golden<lb/> candlestick with its seven branches&#44; the silver trumpets<lb/> and the censer.  The scroll and the Law adorned headed likewise<lb/> the impious procession.  The most notable prisoners<lb/> followed&#44; John of Giskala and Simon of Gioras being<lb/> conspicuous.  Arrived at the capital&#44; the herald<lb/> announced that the subjection of the most obstinate proudest<lb/> of all cities was completed by the execution of the<lb/> most indomitable of her defenders&#44; To Simon son<lb/> of Gioras had fallen the lot of being dragged<lb/> by a rope to the Forum scourged and then beheaded.<lb/>  So writes Josephus&#58; &#34;When it was related that there was an end<lb/> of him&#44; and all the people had set up a shout of<lb/> joy&#44; they then began to offer those animal sacrifices which<lb/> they had consecrated in the prayers used in such solemn&#45;<lb/>&#45;ities.&#34;....They Strangers who visit the seven&#45;hilled city strain<lb/> their visions to trace in the triumphal arch of Titus the engravings<lb/> of the Jerusalem trophies. taken at Jerusalem.  Time has blurred them&#44;<lb/> the Latin inscription may perhaps still be read&#58; Judea Judea<lb/> devicta&#44; Judea capta.  Yes&#44; conquered&#44; but not<lb/> crushed&#59; in captivity but not self&#45; debased.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>Israel has outlived the death of his country&#44;<lb/> because he draws vitality from the spirit<lb/> of the Torah&#45;&#45;ever quickening&#44; imperishable.  Israel<lb/> conscious of a sublimer possession than that of a trust<lb/> of land&#44; has not lost his national character.  But Rome&#44;<lb/> that Rome which stole our precious relics to adorn<lb/> Jupiter Capitolinus is dead beyond resurrection.<lb/>  The silver trumpets of the Jerusalem Temple might sound<lb/> again&#44; but never will she rise from her sepulchre&#44;<lb/> Israel alone is everlasting deathless&#44; as his God is eternal.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
