<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF3_3</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_3_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_3_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_3_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_3_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_3_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_3_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_3_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_3_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_3_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_3_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_3_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_3_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>3d Historical lecture.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  You have heard me explain&#44; how under<lb/> the lead of Zerubabel&#44; appointed by Cyrus as Pasha<lb/> or governor&#44; many among our ancestors&#44; who had returned<lb/> from the Babylonian exile&#44; settled again in Palestine&#44; and<lb/> began to rebuild the Sanctuary.  I also brought back<lb/> to your memory the circumstance that owing to the obstacles<lb/> raised by surrounding tribes&#44; tributary to the home govern&#45;<lb/>ment in Persia&#44; the completion and dedication of the holy<lb/> edifice&#44; did not take place till nearly twenty years after&#45;<lb/>&#45;wards&#44; under the auspices of Darius Hystaspis.  Were<lb/> I now asked for an uninterrupted account of our fathers&#39;<lb/> history since that event happened&#44; I would be compelled<lb/> to confess my inability.  The same absence of authentic records<lb/> existing with regard to the whole period of the Chaldean<lb/> captivity&#44; is noticeable respecting the first sixty or seventy half&#44; or three quarters of a<lb/> century subsequent to the reconstruction of the Jerusalem Temple.<lb/>  Nevertheless&#44; it is not difficult to form a general<lb/> idea of the state of affairs.  References in posterior writings<lb/> give us to understand what must have occurred in<lb/> Judea shortly after Jeribi Zerubabel and his zealous co&#45;worker Joshua the high priest&#44; had died.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>The enthusiasm which the colony had shown at<lb/> the outset&#44; and the spirit which Hagga&#239; and Zechariah<lb/> had rekindled&#44; gave away yielded to chilling indifference.  A gradual<lb/> falling off from religion became specially perceptible among those in office.  New govern&#45;<lb/>&#45;ors&#44; whose names have not come down to posterity&#44; abused<lb/> their authority.  Merciless&#44; while in the pursuit of gain&#44;<lb/> their greed made the poor poorer&#44; and stirred up Israelites<lb/> in easy conditions to follow an example of rapacity and un&#45;<lb/>&#45;righteousness.  The worst feature in the conduct of<lb/> those persons who enjoyed some means and position in society was<lb/> the mixed marriages they contracted.  For it tended to<lb/> defeat the main object of the restoration in the days of Cyrus.<lb/>  The very tribes whose association our leaders had avoided shunned&#44; in order to<lb/> keep the Jewish blood uncontaminated&#59; the very tribes<lb/> who had harassed the first Judean colonists to prevent<lb/> the rearing of the Temple&#44; and the reestablishing of the worship&#44;<lb/> and who still undisguisedly displayed an inveterate ill&#45;will&#44; supplied<lb/> wives for the so called upper classes.  The consequence<lb/> was the a neglect of the observances&#44; and the estrangement<lb/> of the young from national habits and the national language.<lb/>  Had this state continued another half a century&#44; the insi&#45;<lb/>&#45;dious schemer of the enemies of our faith would might have succeeded too well.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>The all&#45;seeing God would not suffer it that calamity&#44; at that<lb/> juncture&#44; Providence raised three men to stand at the breach&#44;<lb/> and stay back the treasonable defection.  Though all the three<lb/> figure in Holy Writ&#44; and the prominence they occupy in<lb/> its pages cannot fail to attract a reader&#39;s attention&#44; I p must point<lb/> them out&#44; to speak&#44; p however briefly&#44; of the good work they<lb/> prepared for their illustrious successors in post&#45;biblical times.<lb/>  The first in order&#44; in my humble opinion is Malachi.  We know<lb/> nothing positive about his birth&#45;place and parentage&#44; but<lb/> the contents of the small book issued from his prophetic pen&#44;<lb/> leave no doubt as to the period in which he lived.  He<lb/> walked the streets of Jerusalem&#44; when unfaithful priests<lb/> and recreant chiefs were fast demoralising the commu&#45;<lb/>&#45;nity&#44; which the generous edict of Cyrus had formed.<lb/>  Fearlessly he charged the officiating ministers with dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;gracing their office and bringing religion into contempt<lb/> by conniving at impiety&#44; by allowing the Sanctuary to become a mere cover to people&#39;s<lb/> dishonesty and hypocrisy.  He then drew a picture of an ideal<lb/> minister&#45;&#45;alas&#33; very seldom a reality.  Truth has its lod&#45;<lb/>&#45;ging place upon his tongue&#59; falsehood is not allowed to come<lb/> near his lips.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Uprightly he walks proceeds in search of peace&#44; and he gathers<lb/> knowledge only to light therewith the way&#44; &#91;&#63;&#93; to many who might<lb/> go astray.  And with an outburst of feelings worthy<lb/> of an Isaiah&#44; Malachi denounces the treason committed disloyalty to the covenant&#44;<lb/> in preferring the daughters of the stranger to the women of<lb/> our race.  He thrillingly lays the altar under a curse&#44;<lb/> because the blood of impure sacrifices mingles with the stream&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing tears of deserted Jewish wives that who believed in One God.  To the waverers&#44; who&#44;<lb/> at the sight of prosperous Iniquity&#44; would fain call the Deity<lb/> to an account&#44; our prophet promises the final triumph<lb/> of justice&#44; and the extirpation of wrong.  Thus did Malachi<lb/> try to check the growing evil which contact with gentiles<lb/> had engendered.  Thus did the earnest servant of God endea&#45;<lb/>&#45;voured to remove the stumbling blocks placed against the<lb/> progress of Judaism&#44; after the decease of Zerubabel and the<lb/> aged among the Judeans who had returned from the Ba&#45;<lb/>&#45;bylonian captivity.  But I do not know indeed of<lb/> an instance a case in our history&#44; when a s certain saying<lb/> of the Rabbis finds a fitter application than in the pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;sent instance.  &#91;Hebrew&#93; is the Talmudical adage &#34;A wise man<lb/> is superior to a prophet.&#34;  What the voice of inspiration<lb/> could not fully penetrate&#44; was pierced to the core by words of saga&#45;<lb/>&#45;cious teaching.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>A second Moses was made to perform miracles&#44; not by<lb/> his mind&#44; but by his instruction.  I am far from<lb/> accepting everything which apocryphal books and legend&#45;<lb/>&#45;ary tales relate concerning Ezra the Scribe&#44; but even<lb/> confining oneself to Scriptural narratives&#44; we can prove<lb/> that to him is due the principal merit of having resurrected<lb/> Judaism and set it up immoveably.  We simply<lb/> guess at the reason which induced that great man to quit<lb/> Persia where he must have been born&#44; and emigrate to Palestine.<lb/>  The news of the a decline in the religious conduct demeanour of the Judean<lb/> colony may have reached his ears.  Too saddening was the<lb/> knowledge that the next generation of those whose sole<lb/> ambition had been to raise the home of the patriarchs from<lb/> its ruins and worship there the One God on its soil the Lord of Abraham&#44; had soon degenerated.<lb/>  But Ezra was evidently a man of action.  He felt that<lb/> his the learning at his command lent him a powerful influence&#44; and he would<lb/> exercise it for good.  At the court of Artaxersces Longi&#45;<lb/>&#45;manus that the eminent Hebrew must have held some im&#45;<lb/>&#45;portant position&#44; for&#44; we perceive that the king handed<lb/> him a document bearing the royal signature and the approval of<lb/> seven ministers of state&#44; and that the &#91;&#63;&#93; granted spe&#45;<lb/>&#45;cial privileges to the Jews&#44; and immunities to the officials at the<lb/> Temple.<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="7"/>
            <p>About two thousand of his brethren&#44; residing in Chaldea&#44;<lb/> placed themselves under the guidance of that a personage so<lb/> highly esteemed favored.  His p fame renown had preceded him&#44; for<lb/> shortly after his arrival at the capital&#44; a deportation<lb/> of the well&#45;disposed among the heads of our people await&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed on the distinguished newcomer regarding a subject of vital interest to the na&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion.  A revival of Mosaic practices must have been<lb/> the object of the conference&#44; but it was doubtless agreed on all sides<lb/> that so long as children of Jewish fathers were educated<lb/> under the influence of idolatrous mothers&#44; every attempt<lb/> to accomplish a permanent improvement must inevitably fail.<lb/>  Ezra resorted therefore to a plan which would act as a test<lb/> of the support he might be likely to receive in a fear&#45;<lb/>&#45;fully harsh&#44; and but imperative&#44; measure which he contemplated.<lb/>  He evinced signs of extreme grief at the defection met specially principally among<lb/> chiefs and priests.  In the presence of a large concourse of<lb/> people&#44; which increased as the day wore on&#44; he sat<lb/> with down cast looks in meditative unbroken silence and fasting&#44; like<lb/> one who mourns over the severest misfortune.  Towards eve&#45;<lb/>&#45;ning he arose&#44; and on bent knees he invoked the Deity&#44; and offered a fervent &#91;&#63;&#93; supplication and<lb/> confession.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Men&#44; women and children listened breathlessly and then burst forth into<lb/> loud weeping.  From amidst that crowded assemblage&#44;<lb/> a person stepped forward and spoke.  He addressed Ezra and urged &#91;&#63;&#93; him<lb/> to use his authority for and saveing Israel from a threatening extinction&#59;<lb/> to demand a peremptory separation from heathen wives and their pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;geny.  Within three months from that memorable meet&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing&#44; over a hundred&#44; comprising officers at the Temple&#44;<lb/> and private individuals&#44; voluntarily dissolved their ma&#45;<lb/>trimonial connection with unconverted women.  It<lb/> cannot be ascertained Whether after having effected that<lb/> radical reform&#44; Ezra remained in Judea cannot be ascertained.  I am inclined<lb/> to believe that political agitations during the protracted<lb/> reign of Artaxersces Longimanus may have impelled<lb/> the illustrious messenger of the Persian king to return<lb/> home.  The more strongly I lean to that opinion&#44; be&#45;<lb/>&#45;cause I notice a relapse into the very sin&#44; which that<lb/> benefactor of our race sought to root out.  The Jews&#44; lovers<lb/> of every thing foreign to Judaism &#38; who unhappily have not<lb/> ceased yet&#45;&#45;may have taken advantage of the absence of<lb/> Ezra to bring back the women from whom they had separated.<lb/>  It seems incredible that priests&#44; for instance&#44; would publicly defy the great&#45;<lb/>&#45;est of living priests&#44; and a favorite besides of with the government.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>I judge therefore that twelve years of a weak or<lb/> wicked administration&#44; neutralized much a vast deal of the good per&#45;<lb/>&#45;formed by the energetic and righteous Ezra.  It was at<lb/> the end of that term that the third man destined by<lb/> Providence to carry farther and more effectually the work<lb/> of reformation&#44; appeared on the scene of action&#59; Perhaps at his<lb/> instance solicitation&#44; the illustrious godly scribe may have been brought out<lb/> again to impart his sagacious extensive learning&#59; to correct&#44; im&#45;<lb/>&#45;prove and edify the congregation of the Lord.  But<lb/> I must reserve for another lecture my description of that<lb/> man and of his successful endeavours.  Short as I desire<lb/> to make it that description&#44; in order to proceed with hasten on to the account of persons individuals<lb/> and events not found in Biblical history&#44; I dare not dismiss<lb/> it in a few sentences.  When I speak again I shall<lb/> present to you a brave patriot and whose deeds proved him a self&#45;denying chief and<lb/> a glorious leader.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
