<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF4_10</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_10_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_10_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_10_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_10_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_10_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_10_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_10_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_10_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_10_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_10_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_10_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_10_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For the Sabbath before Pesach<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>It is &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Let our actions illustrate the name it<lb/> bears.  Our forefathers called this day specially great for a<lb/> motive applicable to their time.  We should render it so&#44; suitably<lb/> to our own age and existing circumstances.  To them the great&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness of this Sabbath consisted of quantity&#44; if I may so inelegantly express<lb/> the idea&#59; to us it should be a greatness of quality.<lb/></p>
                <p>Among the various opinions advanced regarding the ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;pellation anciently given thereto I agree with that which attributes its origin to<lb/> a practice introduced by the Rabbis.  The attention which<lb/> a rigid keeping of the Passover demands&#44; suggested the<lb/> propriety of detaining the Congregation in the Synagogue&#44;<lb/> longer than ordinarily&#44; before the festival set in.  Then<lb/> the preacher warned and exhorted&#44; dwelling forcibly on the<lb/> importance of the approaching occasion&#44; and explaining<lb/> minutely the obligations that devolved on Israelites&#44; and<lb/> the scrupulousness with which they must be discharged.<lb/>  He gave an exceptional sermon.  For admonitory<lb/> discourses were not so usual with the Hebrews of past<lb/> ages&#44; as with ourselves.  Till within the beginning of the<lb/> present century&#44; the pulpit mostly delivered learned<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>discussions rather than studied orations.<lb/></p>
            <p>They might have been appropriately styled lectures&#44; as<lb/> the English word itself primitively implies&#59; that is&#44; a<lb/> reading for instruction.  The minds of the hearers&#44; trained<lb/> in the knowledge of the subjects brought forward&#44; could<lb/> follow the speaker&#44; and derive gratification.  The spirit<lb/> of the time was in full accord with the prevailing system&#44;<lb/> hence its popularity.  It seems&#44; pe however&#44; that when<lb/> the holiday we are about to celebrate&#44; drew near&#44; the<lb/> Rabbi&#39;s lecturing took a different turn form&#59; that it became<lb/> a lengthy discourse on the importance of guarding against<lb/> the slightest violation of the rules laid down by the Sages.<lb/>  So that our dwellings and the peculiarly Jewish rites per&#45;<lb/>&#45;formed might evidence the soundness of our faith.  It<lb/> kept the assembled multitude to a later hour than custo&#45;<lb/>&#45;mary&#44; and therefore the day was given&#44; by way of distinct&#45;<lb/>&#45;ion&#44; the name of &#91;Hebrew&#93;  Need I say<lb/> that this century has produced very material changes&#63;<lb/>  All know&#44; that whereas our ancestors considered it a<lb/> religious duty to become conversant with Hebrew knowledge lore&#44;<lb/> we have drawn a dividing line between the laity and the<lb/> clergy&#44; terms not at all of Jewish origin.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>We leave altogether&#44; as the exclusive department of a few&#44; what<lb/> was formerly cultivated as a field of common property.<lb/>  It is not surprising therefore that our taste and that of our<lb/>fathers are is entirely unlike that of our fathers.  We would reject as wearisome what<lb/> they relished as edifying.  Naturally the pulpit had<lb/> to <sic>accomodate</sic> itself to circumstances&#44; and the old &#34;Derasha&#34;<lb/> was forced to make room for the modern sermon.  It now<lb/> forms a constituent constitutes an integral part of the Divine worship&#44; so that<lb/> the opportunities for enlarging upon the sacredness of the<lb/> Passover&#44; or of any of our observances&#44; are continual&#44; and no<lb/> necessity exists for making the greatness of this Sabbath<lb/> to consist of an unusually long discourse.  You heard&#44;<lb/> my Brethren&#33; before the month of Nissan was ushered in<lb/> that of which you must needfully be reminded at this<lb/> period.  And to say it briefly again&#44; I will quote the Bible.<lb/>  &#34;Seven days shall ye eat unleavened bread&#44; but on the first day<lb/> ye shall have put away leaven out of your houses&#44; for&#44; who&#45;<lb/>&#45;soever eateth leavened bread from the first day until the<lb/> seventh day&#44; that soul shall be cut off from Israel.  And on<lb/> the first&#45;day there shall be a holy convocation&#44; and on the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>seventh day shall there be a holy convocation&#59;<lb/> no manner of work shall be done on them&#44; save<lb/> what is eaten by every person&#44; that only may be prepared<lb/> by you.&#34;  These two sentences contain the summary<lb/> of all I have already said explained.  Not by repeating it&#44; do<lb/> I wish to illustrate the name&#44; which distinguishes this<lb/> Sabbath from others&#44; but by securing from my hearers&#44;<lb/> and by performing myself&#44; acts of justice.<lb/></p>
            <p>Friends&#33; Fellow Israelites&#33;  You had a man in this land&#44; whom you considered deemed<lb/> a fit representative of the principles of civil and religious<lb/> freedom&#59; and so thus you addressed him.  &#34;Brother&#33;  Gird thy<lb/> loins with strength&#44; and go forth among to the help of the enslaved.  Loosen<lb/> their fetters&#44; and let them walk at large.  We will&#44; from<lb/> a distance look on approvingly&#44; and infuse into thy heart<lb/> fresh courage by unmistakable proofs of our confidence.&#34;<lb/>  Animated with zeal&#44; he did as you bid.  Country&#44; friends&#44;<lb/> purists were relinquished&#44; and vast seas placed between<lb/> them and the accomplishing of a holy mission.<lb/>  The new apostle of truth cried aloud and spared not the<lb/> workers of iniquity&#44; bars of iron he broke asunder&#59;<lb/> some he brought out of the dark and horrid dungeon&#44; many<lb/> he delivered form the fear of the extortioners.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>And if he could not gather all into the fold of political<lb/> security&#44; he prepared the way&#44; which will finally lead<lb/> to the desired goal.  Ought such a man&#44; and such a<lb/> Jews to strain his looks&#44; and turning anxiously towards our shores&#44; see<lb/> that you have withdrawn your sustaining arms&#63;<lb/>  Never&#58; Not long ago I urged that the station he has<lb/> occupied with lasting credit to himself&#44; and with honor<lb/> to American Judaism&#44; might be made remunerative and<lb/> and permanent&#44; through your united actions.  And&#44; at<lb/> the instance of our Roumanian consul himself&#44; I solicited<lb/> the influence&#44; which the President of this Congregation&#44; deser&#45;<lb/>&#45;vedly possesses&#44; to that effect.  Unfortunately&#44; several<lb/> adverse circumstances have since arisen to prevent the completion<lb/> of that project object design.  The necessity of providing for the<lb/> increasing wants of a large population&#44; during a severe<lb/> season&#44; and the illness which has detained at home the<lb/> principal actor in the undertaking&#44; hindered its progress.<lb/>  Meanwhile&#44; hope deferred sickened also the heart of<lb/> your distant missionary.  And now&#44; it beats only for<lb/> America and her exhilarating air.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Let Benjamin Franklin Peixotto return to the<lb/> country of his birth&#44; but not laden with an oppressive<lb/> weight.  He has contracted obligations abroad&#44; consequent<lb/> to the position held&#44; and the maintenance of a numerous<lb/> family.  To leave those obligations undischarged would<lb/> be a wrong we commit towards a faithful servant&#44; and a<lb/> reflection upon his character&#44; which he dreads to contemplate.<lb/>  Again&#44; I ask that you hasten to relieve the mind of one<lb/> who has a right to your exertions in his behalf.  When I<lb/> first presented the subject to your consideration&#44; I had looked<lb/> forward to the happy occasion of Purim&#44; on which I might<lb/> cheer the distant brother with the assurance of our affectionate<lb/> support.  That season has passed&#44; and now I earnestly request<lb/> that you will illustrate the greatness of this Sabbath by<lb/> an act of justice.  I will confer with our Parnass&#44; and<lb/> let me pray that whatever plan he may devise as best conducive to the fulfilling &#91;&#63;&#93; realization you seek&#44;<lb/> will render successful&#44; through a spirit appreciative of<lb/> the self&#45;denial of your fellow religionist and citizen&#44;<lb/> and a resolve to be generous as he has been true.<lb/></p>
            <p>But I have said&#44; that I myself wish to make this a<lb/> veritable &#91;Hebrew&#93; by justice.  The extreme<lb/> painfulness which my endeavours to effect that object<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>causes me&#44; shall not deter me withhold my lips from speaking.<lb/>  I have schooled my mind for it&#44; and now&#44; the pressure<lb/> of the time admits of no delay.  Brethren&#33; circumstances&#44;<lb/> not of my creation&#44; have given rise to feelings&#44; among my<lb/> constituents&#44; that may work injury&#45;&#45;material injury to some&#44;<lb/> for whom the memory of the estimable dead bids me to entertain<lb/> kindly sentiments.  Passover&#44; which we all&#44; with God&#39;s<lb/> blessing&#44; will soon joyfully greet&#44; may bring to individuals<lb/> long in the service of the Mikv&#233; Israel Congregation mental<lb/> suffering.  And should I&#44; in the remotest way&#44; occasion<lb/> that grief&#44; I would be harassed and harrowed by the thought.<lb/>  In all honesty I assert Declare that I would rather bear the poisonous<lb/> bite of calumny&#44; than the sting of remorse.  If I have<lb/> then ever uttered words or wishes&#44; affecting prejudicially my<lb/> neighbor&#39;s interest&#44; I recall them totally.  For&#44; while<lb/> I am exceedingly earnest in the desire anxious to keep away from<lb/> this Synagogue a disturbing element&#44; I would <sic>depracate</sic><lb/> changes not detrimental to the welfare of my fellow&#45;<lb/>being.  Let then the members of this respectable<lb/> body&#44; meet not to evince displeasure at that which is past&#44; but to provide for the future.  To study together how to raise on a permanent<lb/> basis their institution of prayer&#59; how to place it beyond<lb/> the possibility of a downfall&#44; through the ravages of<lb/> death&#44; or the defection of a reckless generation.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Let the temporal officers&#44; join hand to hand and shoulder<lb/> to shoulder to uphold the dignity and religious standard<lb/> of the house entrusted to their charge.  Let the salaried<lb/> officers invitingly draw to it multitudes&#44; in order that<lb/> a new infusion of life may be imparted to traditional<lb/> Judaism.  Let each of us labor in his sphere for the spread&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing of the principles&#44; dear to our fathers&#44; and which<lb/> we have hitherto tenaciously preserved.<lb/></p>
                <p>&#40;This lecture was lengthened considerably&#44; by an address<lb/> to a Bar Mitzva&#44; an inmate of the Foster&#45;home&#41;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
