<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF4_12</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_12_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_12_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_12_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_12_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_12_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_12_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_12_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_12_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_12_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_12_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_12_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_12_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_12_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_12_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_12_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_12_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>13 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For the Sabbath before Pesach<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>May I be permitted&#44; after a long silence&#44; to address<lb/> this audience with the affectionate utterance of<lb/> former days&#63;...A custom which I dare not<lb/> disregard&#44; lest I prove false to my vocation&#44;<lb/> demands that I shall this Sabbath&#44; speak to<lb/> instruct.  I must respond to the sacred call.<lb/>  Not in the capacity of my superiors&#44; who exercise<lb/> Rabbinical functions&#44; but as one&#45;&#45;though the least&#44;<lb/> of God&#39;s servants administering relief to spiritual<lb/> wants.  This mission I did once assume with<lb/> a trepidation&#44; which time and circumstances have<lb/> rather increased than abated.  Yet&#44; a sense of<lb/> duty set the misgivings of my heart at rest&#44;<lb/> and gave my thoughts full scope.  I therefore<lb/> frequently expounded in your presence the<lb/> spirit of our religion and its behests.  But<lb/> when the solemn season arrived&#44; which directs Israel&#39;s<lb/> vision to the hand&#44; holding the scales of inflexible<lb/> justice&#59; or&#44; when the memorable period of<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>our enfranchisement was approaching&#44; my mind<lb/> received a stronger impulse&#44; and I addressed my<lb/> congregation on the topic&#44; suggested by the stirring<lb/> occasions.  Beloved hearers&#33;<lb/>  With the cup of salvation uplifted in honor to our<lb/> Living Redeemer&#44; we shall again&#44; on the second night<lb/> of the ensuing week&#44; sit at the domestic board.<lb/>  Let us then recall to mind our origin&#44; our destination<lb/> and our duty.  The ancestry which we claim&#44; is<lb/> not famous because of its remote antiquity&#44; but<lb/> because it constitutes the true nobility of human<lb/> nature.  &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;the princes<lb/> of nations have assembled together&#44; even the people<lb/> of the God of Abraham&#44;&#34; thus sang the inspired<lb/> bard&#44; with an outburst of devotional enthusiasm.<lb/>  We are&#44; if I may use the bold expression&#44; we are<lb/> the aristocracy of the world&#59; for the seal of the Eter&#45;<lb/>&#45;nal has impressed on our brows that mark of<lb/> distinction.  Not to set us up as rulers over<lb/> the powerless&#44; but as a beacon&#45;light to the wandering.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Not to excite in our breasts vainglory&#44; but to incite<lb/> us to righteous deeds.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  &#34;Ye shall<lb/> be holy&#44; for I am holy&#34; says the Lord.  Each of us<lb/> is the minister of a sublime faith.  The uni&#45;<lb/>&#45;verse is the altar at which we officiate.  Here<lb/> in this regenerated country of our love&#44; and likewise<lb/> in the benighted climes of the Eastern hemisphere&#44;<lb/> we burn continual incense to the Father of all<lb/> mankind&#44; when we proclaim His Unity in the sight<lb/> of the gentiles.  The promised vouchsafed to the<lb/> sincerest of all believers&#44; was not to be circumscribed<lb/> within the limits lying between the Nile and the<lb/> Euphrates.  IT was to comprehend a much wider<lb/> range.  Aye&#44; the length and breadth of the habitable<lb/> globe &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;All the families of the<lb/> earth would be blessed in him&#59;&#34; all would acknow&#45;<lb/>&#45;ledge Abraham the friend of God&#44; and the father of<lb/> the faithful.  From that noble fountain&#44; O<lb/> my Brethren&#33; we have sprung.  Rivulets and<lb/> streams have branched off from the primary source&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>but turbid are yet the waters that course through<lb/> them.  From us alone will issue forth the sea<lb/> of light&#44; in which the human race will cleanse<lb/> itself of all impurity.  Such is our origin&#44;<lb/> and such our final destination.  Let none<lb/> therefore charge our Sages with narrow&#45;mind&#45;<lb/>&#45;edness&#44; because they asserted&#44; that &#34;the world was<lb/> created for the sake of the law&#44; and for that of<lb/> Israel&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;  Those wise teachers<lb/> of old&#44; saw in the heavenly mandate the germs<lb/> of a universal civilization&#44; and they regarded the<lb/> descendants of Abraham as the propagators of<lb/> that blessing.  That their assumption was<lb/> correct&#44; the history of nearly twenty centuries ir&#45;<lb/>&#45;refutably prove.  The legislation upon which<lb/> the code of morals delivered at Sinai is not<lb/> engrafted&#44; represents barbarism.  The people<lb/> who do not avow their obligation to the seed<lb/> of Jacob&#44; have yet to awaken from the<lb/> lethargy of the dark ages.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>But&#44; on the contrary&#44; my dear hearers&#59; wherever<lb/> the volume which is our peculiar heritage is held<lb/> in reverence&#44; there&#44; the law of progress is at work&#59;<lb/> wherever we are recognized as the legatees of that<lb/> heavenly boon&#44; there&#44; can the path of enlightenment<lb/> be traced.  What shall then&#44; I ask&#44;<lb/> be the duty of those whom the Almighty &#34;King<lb/> hath delighted to honor&#63;&#34;...To stand immo&#45;<lb/>&#45;veably at their assigned post&#44; for by so acting<lb/> they will preserve and strengthen the basis of the<lb/> social edifice  One of our instructors&#45;&#45;who<lb/> was also the last surviving member of that<lb/> venerable body&#44; headed by Ezra the priest&#45;&#45;<lb/> was wont to say&#44; that &#34;the maintenance of<lb/> the world depends&#44; upon the acknowledgment<lb/> of Divine revelation&#44; upon worship and the<lb/> practice of beneficence.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#45;&#45;.<lb/>  A belief in God&#39;s manifestation at on the summit of Horeb for the love<lb/> of man&#44; will inspire the heart with gratitude&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>and call forth praises and thanksgivings&#59; while<lb/> the effect of a holy communion with our Maker&#44;<lb/> will be to soften our feelings towards all his<lb/> suffering creatures.  Each of those three points<lb/> is connected with &#40;and it substantially rests upon&#41; the<lb/> other&#44; and the absence of either of them would<lb/> endanger society by sapping its main supports.<lb/>  I assert&#44; that if the laws of human governments<lb/> do not acquire validity from the sanction given<lb/> by the expressed word of God&#59; if men bow not<lb/> before the merciful Being&#44; whose providence em&#45;<lb/>&#45;braces all the offspring of Adam&#44; the channels<lb/> of natural compassion will also dry up&#44; and<lb/> self&#45;interest will become the ruling power on earth&#44;<lb/> the lever of all our actions.  As for<lb/> ourselves&#44; my fellow&#45;Israelites&#44; for ourselves whose<lb/> lives must stand as a bright exemplar&#59; we cannot<lb/> more significantly evince our conviction of the<lb/> revelation at Sinai than by our acquiescence<lb/> in the rites of the approaching festival.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>For&#44; our freedom from Egyptian bondage&#44; was but the<lb/> &#91;&#63;&#93; step to the attainment of a spiritual deli&#45;<lb/>&#45;verance.  The result of your redemption&#44; said the<lb/> Lord to Moses&#44; will be that &#34;you shall worship me<lb/> at this mountain&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Or&#44; as the Rabbis express it&#44; our moral<lb/> existence depended upon our acceptance of the<lb/> celestial imparting &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> To our praise it may now be said&#44; that the celebration<lb/> of Passoever has scarcely lost any of its freshness<lb/> and healthful influence.  It is hailed everywhere<lb/> in Israel with a cheerful spirit.  Its arrival<lb/> seems to lend our firesides a more genial and<lb/> bright appearance.  Even to the letter of the<lb/> Mishn&#225;&#44; the most needy obtains the means<lb/> to observe it in the manner anciently<lb/> prescribed.  And as he shares with his dear<lb/> ones the symbolic herbs and the unleavened bread<lb/> in the night of the fourteenth&#44; he forgets<lb/> the present privations&#44; solely to glory in the con&#45;<lb/>templation of the feast.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>He sees the pillar of fire pointing out to his<lb/> ancestors the path of salvation&#44; and a hallelujah<lb/> to the great God bursts forth from his lips.<lb/>  Would that we testified to the truth of revelation<lb/> by as rigid an adherence to other equally<lb/> important precepts&#33; for&#44; then we would exhibit<lb/> a consistency of action&#44; which must needs im&#45;<lb/>&#45;press favorably the gentile world&#44; and add<lb/> credence to the declarations of Scripture.<lb/>  As it is&#44; the conduct of many Hebrews&#44; in other<lb/> instances&#44; might be interpreted as a denial of<lb/> the truths which by the solemnizing of Passover they clearly<lb/> attests.  Of the three grand principles of religion<lb/> described above&#44; they show unwillingness to carry out<lb/> any save the last.  But the desecration of the<lb/> day appointed by the Lord&#44; and the neglect of<lb/> Divine service&#44; is a sin for which the bestowing<lb/> of charity cannot atone.  For our duty to God<lb/> precedes our obligation to man.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; wrote Simon the Just.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>The moral world revolves on three hinges&#44; the first<lb/> and principal is the acknowledgment of revelation&#44; the<lb/> next in order is divine worship&#44; the third and last<lb/> is beneficence.  Understand it well&#58; in the religion<lb/> of Israel we profess&#44; the performance of a single virtue&#44; however<lb/> great&#44; does not procure us absolution from deliberate<lb/> transgressions.  This is a subject&#44; my Brethren&#33;<lb/> on which I might dwell at length&#44; and utter<lb/> some&#44; perhaps&#44; unf distasteful truths.  But as<lb/> I earnestly desire&#44; that my words this day&#44; may<lb/> not leave a sting in any breast&#44; I will forbear&#44;<lb/> and trust that a mere allusion to our derelictions<lb/> may lead to our improvement.  Yet what I can&#45;<lb/>&#45;not omit to descant upon this time&#44; is the third<lb/> cardinal point of all faith creeds&#59; namely the exercise<lb/> of beneficence.  I have already just now declared that<lb/> to be ever ready to stretch forth a helping hand&#44;<lb/> is the characteristic of Abraham&#39;s progeny.<lb/>  But circumstances have now arisen which will<lb/> fathom the whole depth of your kindly nature.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>From the smouldering ashes of a doomed city<lb/> a voice of lament resounds.  Not long ago&#44; the<lb/> same voice uttered loud provocations and treats.  But<lb/> He who chastiseth to correct&#44; has turned its boasting<lb/> into humiliation.  What does your generous instinct<lb/> dictate&#44; omen of Israel&#63;  I know it.  I feel it already.<lb/>  To rejoice with meekness&#59; to spare the conquered&#44; and to<lb/> respect his dignity&#44; is the quality of the man of honor.<lb/>  But to clasp our foe to our bosom&#44; to feed him with<lb/> our bread&#44; to raise to his lips the restorative draught&#44;<lb/> denotes a mind fraught with rare virtues.  These you<lb/> do possess&#44; and will exercise towards your fallen ad&#45;<lb/>&#45;versary.  A sudden glance&#58; and the mystical<lb/> chain that binds your hearts together is revealed.<lb/>  The memory of past wrongs vanishes away&#44; and<lb/> the inextinguishable love of Jewish brotherhood is kindled<lb/> anew.  Our Parnass has shown me apathetic<lb/> appeal on behalf of the Hebrews of Columbia.<lb/>  It pictures the desolation of those whom from affluence<lb/> have suddenly been reduced to indigence.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>The misery of aged sires and innocent infants seeking<lb/> a shelter&#44; of those who beg good to allay their hunger&#44; &#38;<lb/> a covering for their flesh.  Brethren&#33;  Providence<lb/> has averted from us the woeful calamity which has<lb/> befallen our coreligionists of South Carolina.  Not by<lb/> reason of our national righteousness&#44; but for the sake<lb/> and defence of Truth&#44; has He deigned to smile upon<lb/> our cause&#44; and crown the North with victory.<lb/></p>  
            <p>Let then the tribute of our gratitude be a liberal<lb/> response to the petition of the necessitous.  The<lb/> means of the Congregation are scanty&#44; but those at<lb/> the disposal of its component members are ample&#44;<lb/> and cannot be distributed more philanthropically.<lb/>  Your timely contributions&#44; beloved hearers&#33; will draw<lb/> forth delicious tears of reconciliation.  You will<lb/> experience the ineffable satisfaction of having<lb/> cooperated towards that reunion of hearts&#44; which<lb/> is now the ardent supplication of every good and<lb/> loyal man.  And when celebrating your<lb/> deliverance from Egyptian bondage&#44; the memory<lb/> of those whom you will have rescued from<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p>despair and tribulation&#44; will rise as an angelic<lb/> spirit amidst familiar delights.  It will an&#45;<lb/>&#45;nounce that your actions have been approved<lb/> by the Most High God&#45;&#45;the Father of all mankind&#44;<lb/> but the special Protector of Israel.  Oh&#33; let me<lb/> pray that it may be so&#59; let me pray that the<lb/> genial sun that now spans our heavens&#44; may<lb/> dissipate all clouds&#59; bring i healing in its<lb/> wings&#44; and create within us the warmth of friendship<lb/> and brotherhood&#44; so that with an harmonious voice<lb/> we may sing the joyous song of peace and<lb/> contentment always and evermore.  Amen<lb/> &#38; Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
