<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF9_10</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1890-03" source="" attested="yes">March 1891</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_10_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_10_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_10_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_10_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_10_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_10_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_10_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_10_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_10_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_10_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_10_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_10_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. Fifth St.<lb/></p>
            <p>Philadelphia&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>March 91<lb/>
                A few remarks on the Alliance<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Among our public spirited brethren of France&#44; who<lb/> responded to the call of humane Judaism in 1860&#44;<lb/> there was an eminent lawyer that Providence has<lb/> spared to this day.  Narcisse Leven signed the<lb/> call which summoned first appeal that urged upon our people in countries of<lb/> either complete or partial freedom&#44; to practically<lb/> show their coreligionists in oppression fraternal<lb/> aid commiseration.  Since then&#44; many of that Frenchman&#39;s<lb/> colleagues have bone to their lasting home&#44; but<lb/> the cause which they warmly espoused exists still&#44;<lb/> and appeals to our noblest instincts. claims our united exertions.  The original motive<lb/> that gave it origin is not precisely what prompted a noble host to band together over three decades of years ago&#44; is not precisely the same as what de&#45;<lb/>&#45;mands our vigilance watchfulness at present.  The Pope could not<lb/> reenact now the part of his predecessor in the<lb/> Vatican.  He could not sanction the abduction<lb/> of a Jewish child to and insist that the lad be raised in the Catholic church&#44;<lb/> despite the remonstrances and protest of civilization.  Yet&#44; we know of<lb/> millions on whose heads hangs the sword of Damo&#45;<lb/>&#45;cles&#44; simply because of our the faith which we profess.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>In a circular&#44; which I&#44; like several others&#44; received<lb/> three four weeks ago&#44; Mr Leven&#44; one of the few survivors<lb/> of a band the original league of zealous laborers&#44; appeals for assistance<lb/> towards carrying out the self&#45;imposed task of the<lb/> Universal Israelitish Alliance.  It The organization cannot break<lb/> off the bands of wickedness and send Russian slaves<lb/> free&#44; but it strives with might and main to seek<lb/> outlets for the imprisoned.  When found&#44; the agencies<lb/> of deliverance redemption are set to work.  For&#44; whereas formerly<lb/> the Alliance closely watched kept sentry over the civil and politi&#45;<lb/>&#45;cal interest of Hebrews&#44; trying to hold in check ini&#45;<lb/>&#45;mical attacks&#44; now it has found deems it imperative to<lb/> centre its forces almost exclusively on the labors of<lb/> education.  It hopes to redeem save Israel by means<lb/> of wide culture&#44; which must eventually challenge<lb/> respect and secure the recognition of inborn rights.<lb/>  About ten thousand boys and girls receive tuition<lb/> under its auspices in very many cities of the old<lb/> world and they where learning was <sic>ostracised</sic>.  Those youths of ours&#44; form the nucleus of a host of<lb/> missionaries&#44; that will spread further the belief<lb/> in self&#45;reliance and self&#45;elevation.  In the circular&#44; issued<lb/> on behalf of the central Committee at Paris&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Mr Leven recapitulates what the organization has<lb/> accomplished with a limited means revenue&#44; and argues to<lb/> prove that a larger capital income would extend the<lb/> benefit of a knowledge&#44; which has already made of a con&#45;<lb/>siderable number of our people in a state of degra&#45;<lb/>&#45;dation&#44; useful farmers&#44; mechanics&#44; professors and<lb/> law abiding members of society.  I feel a<lb/> degree of pardonable degree of pride in because of the fact that the<lb/> Jewish community of Philadelphia&#44; notwithstanding<lb/> its local needs ever on the increase&#44; realized at<lb/> once that solidarity&#44; which ignoring geographical<lb/> lines&#44; renders Israelites a comp indissoluble unit&#44; nothwithstanding &#91;&#63;&#93; of a wide<lb/> spread dispersion.  Like in France he here also we have met with<lb/> losses which were not replaced.  Our Branch<lb/> of the Alliance&#45;&#45;first and foremost on this side of<lb/> the Atlantic&#44; in aiding our coreligionists of France<lb/> in their humanizing efforts&#44; saw the removal<lb/> from our city of several of its contributors&#44; and in<lb/> too many instances their departure from earth.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Nevertheless&#44; I experienced the melancholy satis&#45;<lb/>&#45;faction of replying to Mr Leven&#44; on the autho&#45;<lb/>&#45;rity of Miss Emily Phillips&#44; that her never to<lb/> be forgotten sister Ellen did not leave the world&#44;<lb/> without sending the Alliance a farewell which<lb/> will entitle the dear deceased to a bright page<lb/> in the history of the Association.  &#43; &#34;May the<lb/> memory of the righteous one be blessed.&#34;  But<lb/> my brethren&#44; Purim is supremely the season of brotherly greetings&#44;<lb/> &#38; that joyful festivity now fast approaching ought to be signalized<lb/> by donations which will gladden the parent<lb/> association in France.  Mr Leven<lb/> feels confident that his written appeal support&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed by my personal pleading will augment the<lb/> funds to be hallowed to the cause of learning and<lb/> civilization.  He writes on so upon this subject&#58; thus&#58; &#216;<lb/></p>
            <p>&#43; In acknowledging receipt<lb/> of my communication of the 18th of February Mr Leven pays a merited tribute<lb/> to the noble minded departed&#44; adding the following&#58; &#34;We<lb/> knew already that the lamented Jewess took a lively part<lb/> in words of beneficence in your city&#59; at various intervals<lb/> she and other members of her family gave the Alliance<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>tokens of sympathy.  &#34;And we who knew her character<lb/> best&#44; may can exclaim scripturally&#58;<lb/> &#216; &#34;I am particularly thankful for the valuable<lb/> cooperation which you are pleased to lend our asso&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciation&#44; and I cherish the conviction that your<lb/> words on Purim in favor of the Alliance will<lb/> find strike a responsive chord among its Phila&#45;<lb/>&#45;delphia friends.&#34;  May I express a fond<lb/> wish that the latter will multiply tenfold&#63;  The<lb/> annual contribution to the parent organization is so<lb/> small&#44; that an effort to cause the list of sub&#45;<lb/>&#45;scribers to swell&#44; would be comparatively easy.<lb/>  Let me solicit that exertion from my hearers&#44; and likewise&#44; upon<lb/> this Sabbath&#44; their gifts of my hearers and those of my<lb/> Philadelphia coreligionists&#44; promoting of the cause<lb/> of education&#44; and hence of moral exaltation and<lb/> freedom among the myriads of Israel&#44; for whose<lb/> sake schools of industry and general knowledge instructions are<lb/> set up far and wide by the Universal Israelitish<lb/> Alliance.<lb/></p>
            <p>In the absence of a treasurer&#44; I will take charge of<lb/> donations and hand them to the President of our Branch&#44;<lb/> and have them acknowledged in the Jewish Exponent.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
