<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF26_3</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff26_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff26_3v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>2 pages on 1 sheet<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA<lb/></p>
            
            <p>Brethren.  Because I have made it a practice&#44; for a long time&#44; to address a lad&#44;<lb/> who belongs to our congregation&#44; on the Sabbath of after his having entered the thirteenth<lb/> year of his birth&#44; I am impelled to speak a few words this morning.<lb/>  But before I speak direct my speech to my young brother&#44; I wish to offer a few some passing remarks<lb/> concerning myself.  The solemn days&#44; fast approaching&#44; involve entail<lb/> physical and mental labors&#44; which I undertake willingly&#44; but with trepida&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion.  For&#44; I recognize the weakening of the flesh and the increasing poverty<lb/> of the mind.  Saying that much&#44; I must tell that I am bid to spare my voice.<lb/>  Hence I feel that I may venture to ask of my fellow&#45;worshippers a great favor.<lb/>  All know that it is my earnest desire to hear every one join me in<lb/> chanting our ritual.  I have always disapproved of a service con&#45;<lb/>&#45;ducted by proxy&#59; a service in which the attendants at the Synagogue<lb/> are silent spectators&#44; and a paid choir&#45;&#45;shame on us that it is<lb/> very often composed of trinitarians&#45;&#45;receives a stipulated compensation to<lb/> vocally entertain the congregation.  It does not require a vast<lb/> amount of learning to realize that the minor sanctuaries&#44; established<lb/> during or shortly after the Babylonian captivity&#44; were intended for the people<lb/> at large to that they might pray in concert&#44; and not for a few elect to sing at the sound of instruments.<lb/>  In fact&#44; even the Law was originally expected to be read in turn by each<lb/> person&#44; who is called to it&#59; as the very expression employed on the occasion denotes.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;to read the Law&#34;.  Pity&#44; that the growing inability of a vast number<lb/> of us to recite the Torah understandingly&#44; compelled the abandonment<lb/> of that usage.  But surely&#44; every one may easily gain familiarity<lb/> with the ordinary melodies of our liturgy.  Perhaps&#44; an exception may be made<lb/> with regard to thy chanting of the poems and propitiatory prayer for Rosh<lb/> Hashanah and Yom Kippur&#44; mention to the Sephardic School&#33;  Hence&#44; the request to which I am about to make.<lb/>  I would beg of all to modulate their voices and singly correctly&#44; gently&#44; harmoniously&#44;<lb/> and never hurriedly&#44; so that I may not lest I be obliged to strain my own voice&#44; upon<lb/> which I cannot&#44; by any means&#44; rely at all times&#44; in order the attempt to drown stronger<lb/> voices than mine.  But even more strenuously than that&#44; I would<lb/> urge my congregation to maintain a very decorous demeanour&#44; especially<lb/> on the day of the holy fast drawing nigh.  It pains and confuses me to no&#45;<lb/>&#45;tice the unsteadiness of many&#44; who go to and fro during the service&#44; or<lb/> remain in the vestibule&#44; speaking&#44; or motioning to female relatives in the<lb/> gallery to come down. All may have observed such an objectionable<lb/> deportment&#44; and I recommend an improvement&#44; for the honor of this house of<lb/> our Lord&#44; and for the respected name which this ancient congregation still bears.<lb/>  Let me hope that words dictated by a kindly spirit&#44; will be received with the same spirit of<lb/> friendliness and brotherhood.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>I shall now address myself to Lionel Levy&#45;&#45;our young brother Bar Mitzvah.<lb/>  It has been your mother&#39;s wish that you could recite a portion of the Torah&#44;<lb/> designated for this Sabbath.  So she has stated to me&#44; and only her knowledge of your<lb/> retiring disposition and bashfulness&#44; wh withheld her from asking that you would<lb/> so gratify her.  While for your dear mother&#39;s sake I would that you<lb/> could have overcome a natural timidity so as to do her pleasure&#44; I do not particu&#45;<lb/>&#45;larly you regret your having abstained from undertaking the task.  The commit&#45;<lb/>&#45;ting to memory a short or even a long section of the week&#39;s parashah&#44; is not an<lb/> assurance of remaining faithfully attached to the Torah.  Many who did study<lb/> the whole portion&#44; and even the prophetic lesson of the day&#44; made the future belie<lb/> the hopes which their young early days had awakened.  What I pray for your sake<lb/><lb/> for the sake of this congregation&#44; and for the sake of our religion&#44; is that you may<lb/> grow an honest&#59; a consistent Jew.  What I do devoutly pray for is&#44; that in your<lb/> manhood&#44; even in your old age you may be found among such as feel it a pride to<lb/> be reckoned among Israelites&#44; who rather bear the world&#39;s undeserved contempt&#44;<lb/> than desert our camp.  I believe that I voice the sentiments of both your parents&#44;<lb/> when I so address you.  I shall be glad to continue to greet your presence<lb/> always at our Hebrew and at the Sunday schools&#44; and to encourage your progress in the know&#45;<lb/>&#45;ledge of our national language and our Bible.<lb/></p>
            <p>May those who love you and watch over your welfare&#44; discover that you have<lb/> followed the lesson imparted in the book of Proverbs&#44; namely &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Listen&#44; O my son to the instruction of thy father&#44; and forsake not the teaching of thy mo&#45;<lb/>&#45;ther.&#34;  So may it be.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
