<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF2_19</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_19_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_19_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_19_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_19_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_19_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_19_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_19_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_19_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_19_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_19_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_19_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_19_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_19_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_19_7v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>A penitential sermon &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>The Lord sits upon the throne of justice &#34;to requite every one according to<lb/> his ways&#44; and according to the fruit of his doings&#34;.  Children of the<lb/> earth&#33; bow reverently before your Maker.  Oh&#33; tha tI might an<lb/> instant cast off this mortal coil which envelops my undying spirit.<lb/>  Like the Seraph described by the inspired son of Amoz&#44; I would seize from<lb/> the altar of the Omnipotent a live coal wherewith to purify my<lb/> existence&#44; ere my voice be heard anew among the chosen people of God.<lb/>  But when I consider on the solemnity of the occasion that has convened<lb/> us hither&#44; and the duties devolving on me&#44; I cannot&#44; though deeply<lb/> stained with sin&#44; I cannot forbear giving utterance to the thoughts that<lb/> now crowd my mind.  Brethren&#33;  It is the pentitential Sabbath&#44;<lb/> the herald of a new period in our life.  A year has sunk into eter&#45;<lb/>&#45;nity with all its unspeakable sorrows&#44; and another has just opened<lb/> on us.  Who&#44; save the all&#45;seeing eye of Providence&#44; can pierce<lb/> through the darkness in which it is enshrouded&#63;  In the<lb/> prayers which we poured forth in his consecrated dwelling&#44; we besought<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>the Lord&#44; during the festival that has preceded this day&#44; that happiness<lb/> might be vouchsafed unto Israel&#44; but it greatly depends on our&#45;<lb/>&#45;selves&#44; my friends&#33; to propitiate that celestial blessing&#44; for &#34;the<lb/> eyes of the Eternal are upon the righteous&#44; and lies ears are open unto<lb/> their exclamation&#34;.  It therefore behooves us diligently to scrutinize<lb/> our inward selves&#44; in order to discover where the dark spots lie&#44;<lb/> that have alienated from us the Friend of the pure and the faith&#45;<lb/>&#45;ful.  Seel&#33;  He beckons us to hasten ere the verdict be<lb/> pronounced and we sink beneath the weight of our delinquencies.<lb/>  Awake then O house of Israel&#33;  Awake&#44; listen to the words of ad&#45;<lb/>&#45;monition and bethink thyself.<lb/></p>
            <p>&#34;According to their pasture&#44; so were they filled&#44; they were filled&#44; &#38;<lb/> their heart became elated&#44; therefore have they forsaken me&#34;<lb/>  This dismal picture which Hosea displays to our vision&#44; is &#40;to our<lb/> confusion be it acknowledged&#41; literally applicable to us.  Aye&#44; my<lb/> Brethren&#33;  It is because we have long enjoyed the bounteous gifts<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>of Providence that we have become unmindful of the Rock whence<lb/> we were hewn.  It is because the Creator of the universe was<lb/> pleased to bestow on us signal benefits that we have deliberately<lb/> refused to recognize his power.  I know&#44; that if a man were to<lb/> grant us one of the numberless favors showered down upon us by<lb/> the Almighty&#44; we would most assuredly strive with eagerness<lb/> to evince gratitude.  Who would not express sentiments of thank&#45;<lb/>&#45;fulness to a kindly being who presented him with the house<lb/> wherein he comfortably dwells&#44; with a field which enables his family<lb/> to supply with ease their daily necessities&#63;  And if he could receive<lb/> at the hands of the same benefactor the air he breathes&#44; the light<lb/> which illumines him&#44; what affection&#44; what unutterable love would<lb/> bind the recipient with the donor&#63;...But why is our demeanour so<lb/> very different towards our beneficent God&#63;  Is it because the gifts<lb/> are so frequent&#44; that we are must appreciate them the less&#63;  Do we<lb/> abhor the light of the glorious luminary of the day&#44; because it irradiates<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>the earth every morning&#63;  Do we not&#44; on the contrary&#44; rejoice at his<lb/> appearance&#44; and admire his powerful and exhilarating influence&#63;<lb/>  Oh&#33; ingratitude&#33; &#34;they have denied the Lord&#44; they have said &#34;It is<lb/> not He&#34; dolefully cries Jeremiah.  When a plentiful harvest<lb/> falls to our lot&#44; we do not lay upon the altar of the Most High<lb/> a sacrifice of thanksgiving.  We eat to repletion at the table<lb/> spread out by our universal Father&#44; but refuse to acknowledge<lb/> the dispensation of his bounty.  It is the effect of chance&#44; says<lb/> he categorically&#44; whose spirit swells with arrogance.  It is<lb/> the result of the husbandman&#39;s industry&#44; remarks another &#34;but they<lb/> do not say in their heart&#44; let us now fear the Lord our God&#44; that<lb/> giveth rain&#44; both the former and the latter in his season&#34;.  When<lb/> our commercial enterprises succeed even beyond our expectations&#44; we do<lb/> not offer a portion of the gold we have <sic>ammassed</sic> to the exaltation<lb/> of the worship of our God&#59; to the firm establishment of a hallowed<lb/> mansion in honor to his name.  No&#44; we then devise means<lb/></p> 
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>how best to enjoy our possessions.  We watch more closely over<lb/> the wealth we have garnered.  Why shall I give that away&#44;<lb/> for which I have labored so strenuously&#63; that which I have<lb/> earned by dint of my unbounded sagacity&#63;  so we inwardly think&#44;<lb/> and refuse to believe &#34;that promotion cometh neither from the east&#44;<lb/> nor from the west&#44; nor from the south&#44; but from God who judgeth rightly<lb/> and pulleth one down&#44; and setteth another up&#34;  &#34;we must see<lb/> to believe&#34; is the vulgar adage of those whom the Almighty ceaselessly<lb/> favors.  And so rooted is this sense of incredulity in our breasts&#44; that<lb/> although we do see&#44; yet the mind is so obscured by the deformity<lb/> of our  thoughts&#44; that it discovers naught.  Nay even more.  We<lb/> are stricken &#38; heed it not &#34;From the sole of the foot even unto the<lb/> &#34;head there is no soundness&#44; but wounds&#44; and bruises and putrefying sores&#44;<lb/> &#34;that have not been closed&#44; neither bound up&#44; neither mollified with oint&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment.  The country is desolate&#44; cities are burnt with fire&#44; the land is<lb/> as if it were overthrown by strangers&#44;&#34; and nevertheless we cling to the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>same delinquencies.  Israelites of America&#33;  Say&#44; has the visitation<lb/> of an irritated Deity reclaimed you to religion&#63;  Has it convinced you<lb/> of the instability of all human dispositions&#63;  Has it rendered you more<lb/> solicitous of apportioning some of your time and means for the eleva&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion of your race&#44; for the spiritual improvement of your offspring&#44;<lb/> for the glory of your God&#63;  Answer&#44; that I amy be undeceived&#44; for&#44;<lb/> to my vision are yet the former trespasses glaringly exhibited.<lb/>  The same chicanery&#44; the same subtlety in dealing.  The same bare&#45;<lb/>&#45;faced pollution of the sabbath of our Lord and of the festivals&#45;&#45;so in&#45;<lb/>&#45;sulting to a righteous soul&#59; the same license in gratifying human<lb/> appetites&#59; the same apathy for the dissemination of religious knowledge.<lb/>  So true is the axiom of our Rabbins that &#34;when sin becomes rife&#44; it<lb/> ceases to be regarded as such&#34; But neither is its weight lessened there&#45;<lb/>&#45;by&#44; nor does it avert the chastisement it provokes.  It may<lb/> please the Father of mercy to defer its execution&#44; for&#44; &#34;He is slow to<lb/> anger&#34; and taketh delight in repentance&#34; but when man&#39;s obudracy<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>goads him on to openly defy the power of the Most High&#44; then he is<lb/> irretrievably lost.  To the wicked Ahab&#44; who abused his royal autho&#45;<lb/>&#45;rity in order to rob and to murder&#44; was promised nevertheless a reprieve<lb/> of the grievous sentence pronounced against his progeny becuase he<lb/> bowed himself down in contrition&#59; but the refractory relatives of<lb/> Lot&#44; who scoffed at his word of warning and denied God&#44; were consu&#45;<lb/>&#45;med by the fire that rained down upon Sodom.<lb/></p>
            <p>My friends&#33; let us not continue in our supineness.  Let us shake<lb/> off the vestment of infidelity&#44; and don the armour of faithfulness.<lb/>  Surely we have beheld fearful things&#44; we have drained almost to the<lb/> dregs the bitter cup of affliction&#59; but &#34;let us now return unto the<lb/> Lord&#34; peradventure He may look down pitifully on us and restore us to<lb/> our former happiness&#59; &#34;for He hath torn&#44; and He may heal us&#44; He hath<lb/> smitten and He bind us up&#34;.  He alone can cure our lacerated hearts&#44;<lb/> when they appear to be beyond recovery.  But in order to regain the<lb/> health we long for&#44; we must unflinchingly abide by the direction<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>of the heavenly Physician&#59; in other terms&#44; our repentance must<lb/> be sincere.  He who acknowledges his sin&#44; but still has not firmly<lb/> resolved to relinquish it&#44; will die in his iniquity.  Likewise he<lb/> who <sic>wilfully</sic> pursues a froward career trusting to the efficacy of the<lb/> day of atonement for the yearly remission of his backslidings&#44; has sold<lb/> himself to perdition.  He who designedly violates the law of God&#44;<lb/> and defers his repentance to the age when the keenness of the<lb/> passions is blunted&#44; cannot hope for mercy.  Truly penitent&#44;<lb/> say our sages&#44; is he who placed in the exact position&#44; which occa&#45;<lb/>&#45;sioned his trespass&#44; summons moral courage and his aid and with&#45;<lb/>&#45;stands the onslaught of sin&#59; and to an individual so praise&#45;<lb/>&#45;worthy have they promised a beatitude even above that allotted<lb/> to the perfect righteous.  But let us not forget&#44; my Brethren&#44;<lb/> that the great and tremendous day which is fast approaching&#44; will<lb/> atone only for the crimes committed against God.  If we have<lb/> wronged our fellow&#45;man in our daily intercourse&#59; if we have<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>aspersed his character&#44; and a false pride deters us from seeking his pardon&#44;<lb/> or if we have hardened our heart and refused our brother the forgiveness we<lb/> ourselves implore from the Lord&#44; we may fast and weep&#44; we may chastise<lb/> our flesh and offer supplications&#44; but the Father of all mankind will<lb/> turn irefully away from us.  My friends&#33; Remember the fleetness<lb/> of your existence&#44; and strive to forgive and to forget.  Again&#58; if<lb/> we see our offspring prone to sin&#44; and through mistaken affection&#44; we<lb/> fail to exert ourselves that the baneful seeds which contaminate<lb/> them&#44; may be timely eradicated&#44; we can never obtain grace from<lb/> our heavenly Maker.  Alas&#33; that this condemnable recklessness has<lb/> estranged from their ancestral faith many a promising son and daughter<lb/> in Israel.  The seed of Abraham heretofore so prominently free from all<lb/> alloy&#44; has not unfrequently in these degenerate days&#44; polluted itself by<lb/> the blending of a strange admixture.  O ye Parents&#44; who have the happiness of<lb/> your dear ones at heart&#44; think not lightly of the responsibility which<lb/> you have assumed in the face of God and of our nation at large.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>From you&#44; the residue of Judah&#44; expect a race of men&#44; who shall become<lb/> the pillars of our faith&#44; and it is in your power to further the consum&#45;<lb/>&#45;mation of such hopes.  Between every maternal kiss and paternal em&#45;<lb/>&#45;brace&#44; whisper in their tender ears words of pure religion&#44; let the<lb/> spirit of love for all mankind which breathes in the heavenly<lb/> volumes grow with them&#44; let it be entwined in the innermost<lb/> souls.  Speak to them of the beauty of their faith.  Endeavour<lb/> by your own example&#44; that the performance of religious observances&#44;<lb/> so needful to assist and strengthen inward piety&#44; be to them an easy<lb/> and agreeable task.  Reason with them on the statutes of God and<lb/> his law&#44; &#34;teach them diligently to your children &#91;Hebrew&#93; reads the<lb/> Hebrew text&#44; purposing to signify that you must&#44; by constantly<lb/> expounding them&#44; quicken their young mind&#44; rendering it&#44; as it were&#44;<lb/> sharp and clear as a weapon of burnished steel.  In fine&#44; my beloved<lb/> hearers&#33; let each of us in his own sphere&#44; assiduously work henceforth<lb/> for the improvement of himself and his fellow&#45;<lb/>man.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>Let us vigilantly watch over steps&#44; lest we deviate from the path<lb/> which alone leads to salvation&#44; and if the cravings of the flesh&#44;<lb/> impel us at times to sin&#44; let us not delay our repentance till<lb/> the morrow&#44; lest the morrow fails us&#44; but forthwith bend the<lb/> knee before the Dweller in heaven and cry &#34;O Father&#33; for&#45;<lb/>&#45;give us according to Thy abundant mercy&#59; for Thou alone art<lb/> infallible&#44; but we frail&#44; perishable beings are constantly exposed<lb/> to error.  Behold the suffering we endure by reason of our folly&#44;<lb/> and speedily alleviate them.  Draw us nearer to Thee&#59; make us<lb/> more spiritual&#44; suppress our worldly desires&#44; and strengthen us in<lb/> our pious resolves&#44; by offering to our minds a foretaste of the un&#45;<lb/>&#45;speakable bliss&#44; which the righteous will enjoy beyond the grave in the<lb/> contemplation of Thee.  Then He will hearken to and grant our peti&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion&#44; for &#34;the Lord is nigh unto those who call upon Him&#44; unto<lb/> those who call upon Him in truth&#34; So may it be for<lb/> evermore.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
