<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF1_8</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_9_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_9_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_9_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_9_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_9_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_9_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_9_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_9_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_9_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_9_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_9_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_9_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>64</p>
            <p>Faith in God.<lb/>
                It was <sic>remodelled</sic> and delivered on<lb/>
                Sabbath Teshubah 5653<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#34;How great is Thy goodness&#44; which Thou hast laid up<lb/> for those that fear Thee&#44; which Thou hast wrought for<lb/> those that trust in Thee&#44; before the sons of men&#34;.<lb/></p>
            <p>Let us ponder <del>a while</del>&#44; my dear Brethren&#44; on thise devotional<lb/> outpourings of the ancient shepherd of Israel&#44; that we<lb/> may <del>discover the important</del> profit by the lesson <del>with which it is frought</del>. it imparts.<lb/>  The goodness of the Lord&#44; which He has reserved for His righteous<lb/> servants&#44; is as unmeasurable as the extent of His power.<lb/>  They who dwell on earth&#44; cannot&#44; in the highest flight of<lb/> their imaginations reach the knowledge of that heavenly<lb/> happiness.  Their immortal spirit&#44; the spirit which<lb/> animates them&#44; will burst forth from its tenement of clay&#44;<lb/> &#91;On verso of cover&#44; at this line on page 1&#58; Butterly&#45;chrysalis&#93; see and enjoy pleasures set apart by the all&#45;just Creator.<lb/>  But who are they&#44; that shall attain the climax of that<lb/> felicity&#63;  Who are they to whom a wealth of delights<lb/> treasured up by the very hand of the Omnipotent will<lb/> be <sic>proferred</sic>&#63;  Inspiration answers&#44; &#34;<del>to</del> those who trust<lb/> in God before the sons of men &#91;Hebrew&#93; we will search<lb/> together into the meaning of the sacred text.<lb/>  If I do not err in my judgment&#44; one of the motives<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>which makes us swerve from right is a want of moral<lb/> courage&#44; our inability to stand out boldly out and acknowledge<lb/> our governing principles.  <del>Our</del> The sentiments we entertain may be in full<lb/> accord with the law of Truth&#44; but we fear to exhibit them<lb/> in our intercourse with the world.  Doubtless&#44; in most cases<lb/> we are influenced in our actions by greed&#44; or controlled by the passions&#44; but<lb/> in some instances we deviate&#44; because we pander to the whims<lb/> and wishes of a corrupt society&#44; because we dread the derision<lb/> of the ungodly more than we stand in awe of Gods displeasure.  The taunts and jeers<lb/> of those who will call it absurd to sacrifice one&#39;s propen&#45;<lb/>&#45;sities to olden ordinances&#44; exercise a complete sway over<lb/> our feelings.  We might willingly yield temporal<lb/> advantages to faith&#44; but we cannot withstand the arms<lb/> of radicals.  The idea of being mentioned with a<lb/> curl of the lip as one&#44; behind the age&#44; is a terror too<lb/> great to be overcome.  This lack of moral courage&#44;<lb/> to use above temptations&#44; this want of manliness to<lb/> repel the first attack of <del>un</del> wickedness&#44; will draw<lb/> us so tightly into the net spread for our souls&#44; that<lb/> we ultimately lose every power to extricate ourselves<lb/> from its meshes &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  It is as our sages have taught.<lb/>  When we fail to lay hold of at once and enchain <del>the</del><lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>the enemy that conspires against our moral character and<lb/> spiritual elevation&#44; we forge our own fetters &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  If the<lb/> history of some youths who lapsed from vice to crime&#44; could<lb/> be written down&#44; we might be shown that the first step<lb/> to ruin was taken when they lent a willing ear to pleasing<lb/> seductions.  Many&#44; I know&#44; are being reared by<lb/> parents&#44; who ardently hope they have added by precept<lb/> and example to the number of the faithful&#44; and while<lb/> under the parental roof&#44; the children of such will not do<lb/> violence to the feelings of those who tenderly love their offspring.<lb/>  But mingling with the world&#44; the same youths may be<lb/> apt to hear their coevals speak in this wise &#34;How preposterous<lb/> to be fastened down by antiquated rules&#33;  Who can believe<lb/> that the Almighty who created us from love intended to<lb/> withhold from his creatures what lends jest to pleasure&#63;<lb/>  That he would deprive us of what renders existence delight&#45;<lb/>ful&#63;  Will those youths then summon courage and prove them<lb/>&#45;selves hero<del>e</del>s&#39; by asserting fearlessly that they owe allegiance<lb/> to the sovereign Legislator&#44; and consider <del>a</del> pollution whatsoever<lb/> jars with the tenets of Holy Writ&#63;  No&#58;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>scoffing and bantering did their work too effectually.<lb/>  The unwary have fallen into the snare.  Therefore cautions<lb/> the royal Psalmist by saying &#34;Great is Thy goodness<lb/> O Lord&#33; which Thou hast laid up for those who fear Thee&#44;<lb/> for those who trust in Thee before the sons of men&#34;  There<lb/> is a reward vast and unending kept <del>of</del> for our deeds<lb/> upon earth.  It surpasses all human thoughts&#44; as<lb/> the knowledge of the Great Being who set it apart is<lb/> beyond our comprehension.  But they <del>who</del> alone will be entitled<lb/> to it whose fidelity is not shaken by every adverse wind<lb/> <del>raised by</del> which infidelity raises.  They whose senses are not beclouded<lb/> and whose minds are not warped by the specious reasoning<lb/> of mortals&#59; men of brave mettle who stand firm against skepticism like a<lb/> sturdy oak against a hurricane <del>of skepticism</del> &#91;Hebrew&#93; raging<lb/> abroad&#44; men who have a complete mastery over their <del>hearts</del><lb/> understanding&#44; who act as free agents and not as slaves<lb/> to prevailing notions.  And they conduct themselves thus<lb/> not only in private&#44; in their houses&#44; in their secret chambers<lb/> but openly&#44; before society&#44; aye&#58; &#34;before the sons of men&#34;<lb/> To them will be held out the reward reserved by a just God&#44;<lb/> for they postponed all earthly considerations to the glory of<lb/> being called trusty servants of their heavenly Master.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Read and reflect&#44; my Brethren&#33;  Tribal obedience is a duty<lb/> that ranks exceedingly high in our religion.  It is in very<lb/> deed a golden key <del>that</del> which opens the gate of earthly blessings <del>on<lb/> earth</del> and the portals of paradise.  Were the teachings of<lb/> Judaism which prove that verity to be collected together they<lb/> would swell into volumes.  But the circumstances that<lb/> of the commandments of the Decalogue&#44; the fifth is the only one<lb/> to the observance of which a divine promise has been attached<lb/> must be <del>interpreted</del> regarded as significant of its supreme sanctity.  And<lb/> yet we are told &#34;Every man shall fear his mother and his<lb/> father&#44; but keep my Sabbaths&#34; meaning&#44; he shall not<lb/> allow even a feeling of veneration due to the guardians of<lb/> his existence to estrange his heart from the duty he owes to<lb/> God.  How can we then be so senseless as to become guilty<lb/> of desertion&#44; in order to follow the advice of beings to whom<lb/> we are not bound by ties so strong and so sacred&#63;  How<lb/> can we&#44; to please our earthly associates&#44; provoke to anger our<lb/> heavenly Friend&#63;  To avoid the jeers of the impious&#44; esteem<lb/> lightly what the Eternal has declared important&#63;  How<lb/> can we&#44; I say&#44; offend the Creator by a cowardly<lb/> fear of the creatures&#63;  Do we perhaps anticipate<lb/> <del>to advance our interest</del> that by pursuing such a course we<lb/> shall&#44; at all events&#44; advance our material interests&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Vain hopes&#33;  Our allies in sin are may be likened to the<lb/> sky on a sultry summer day.  Clouds mount high&#44; all<lb/> eyes eagerly look for the refreshing rain&#44; but <del>sarcely</del><lb/> scarcely a drop falls to relieve the drought.  They<lb/> will<hi rend="sup">2</hi> flee away and return not again&#44; <del>those</del> when we need them who1 become our com&#45;<lb/>&#45;panions in wantonness and irreligion.<lb/></p>
            <p>But admitting that they will be <del>more</del> generous&#44; that they will<lb/> stand by us&#44; and demand neither servility nor humiliation&#44;<lb/> nor even an acknowledgment of their favors&#44; we still may<lb/> awaken to discover that we leaned upon an arm of flesh<lb/> which was palsied.  Aside from the uncertainty of life&#44;<lb/> and the inconstancy of human fortune&#44; a word incautiously<lb/> uttered&#44; an innocent jest&#44; a false report may tear away<lb/> from us those upon whom we confidently relied.  How<lb/> different with those who &#34;trust in God before the sons of men&#34;&#33;<lb/>  They will not stand in fear that He will cease to love assist them though<lb/> they be faithful.  That he will withdraw His mercy&#44; though<lb/> they be innocent.  For they know that He reads the heart&#44; and that no human<lb/> <del>machinations and evil&#45;purposes th</del> device can alter His love.<lb/>  Nay&#58; we can turn away from Him&#44; while He showers down favors<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>upon ourselves and our households&#44; but He will not deny us<lb/> His support&#44; unless the number of our <del>en</del>iniqueties raises an<lb/> impenetrable mist&#44; preventing the sun of His goodness<lb/> from reaching us&#33;  The mortals may profer what they<lb/> cannot or will not grant&#44; God gives mre than we need&#44;<lb/> even when we ask not.  Seeing then that to many<lb/> causes may rob us of the <del>support</del> friendship of <del>mortal</del> perishable beings&#44; and<lb/> nothing&#44; <del>safe</del> save deliberate sin&#44; can <del>alienate</del> deprive us of the <del>immortal everlasting</del> protection<lb/> <del>Creator from His creatures&#44; how can we cling to</del> of the everlasting Creator&#44; ought we to still harken after the former&#44;<lb/> and <del>desert</del> &#91;&#63;&#93; the latter&#59; <del>how can we</del> ask the loss of that good&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness which He has laid up for those who fear Him&#44; which<lb/> He wrought for those who trust in Him&#44; before the sons of<lb/> men&#63;  Never&#58; my Brethren&#33; To avoid that&#44; the greatest of all evils&#44; we must<lb/> imitate the example of a heathen Sage&#44; whom a worldly<lb/> person would induce to deviate from truth &#34;I will <del>w</del> serve you&#44;&#34;<lb/> he said &#34;only so far as it does not injure the health of my<lb/> soul&#34;.  A similar reply will prove our best safeguard.  It<lb/> will deter any further attempt to tamper with our character.<lb/>  When urged to sully our lips with falsehood&#44; and our souls<lb/> with vice&#44; to resort to chicanery and swerve from honesty.<lb/> When pressed to make all days alike and all food permissible&#44;<lb/> in a word&#44; when advised to break down the dikes set up to<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p><sic>to</sic> shut out the overleaping tide of corruption&#44; we must<lb/> have a ready and emphatic refusal. <del>to the instigation</del><lb/> should they who so instigate us to do wrong be even our nearest<lb/> and dearest we must prepare an unconditional No&#44; that<lb/> we may not be lost.  for if we are in duty to bound to<lb/> live harmoniously with our neighbors&#44; and specially with<lb/> those to whom we are bound by family ties&#44; still we should<lb/> prefer discord to a union of wickedness.  When we there&#45;<lb/>&#45;fore discover by the light received from above&#44; that what the<lb/> world loves is abhorrence to God&#44; that to follow prevailing notions<lb/> is to be guilty of treason against Our heavenly King&#44; we must<lb/> summon moral courage and defy ungodliness by a spirit<lb/> of rectitude which knows no flinching from duty.  We<lb/> must cast off the fetters imposed by the world&#44; fearlessly<lb/> adhere to religion and truth&#44; and strengthening ourselves on<lb/> the infallible promise of the Almighty&#44; <del>the right to the rise above</del> bear scorn<lb/> <del>best of our knowledge&#44; and the highest of our capacities</del> contumely and persecution&#44; glorifying still in our convictions&#44;<lb/> <del>so</del> that <del>we may deserve</del> &#34;great is the goodness reserved by the<lb/> Lord for those who fear Him&#44; laid up for those<lb/> who trust in Him&#44; before the sons of men.&#34;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
