<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF1_3</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_3_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_3_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_3_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_3_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_3_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_3_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_3_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_3_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_3_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_3_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_3_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_3_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>156</p>
            
            <p>A lecture exhorting<lb/>
                Parents to discontinue<lb/>
                the practice of teaching<lb/>
                the Bar Mitzva a single chapter<lb/>
                unaccompanied with any knowledge<lb/>
                of the language and spirit of the Bible<lb/></p>
            
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  Every change in matters connected with<lb/> the public worship&#44; is not a dangerous renovation&#44; still&#44; a<lb/> feeling exists among excellent conscientious men and women in Israel<lb/> hostile to any alteration in customs and practices&#44; which<lb/> they have ever seen or followed.  To rise against that<lb/> feeling in open antagonism would be unwise&#44; for&#44; op&#45;<lb/>&#45;position creates resistance&#44; and this calls forth divisions<lb/> and heartburnings&#44; through which the very object sought<lb/> after is defeated.  To reason dispassionately about regarding<lb/> it the propriety or impropriety of holding to it&#44; is the province of such as aim in earnest to im&#45;<lb/>&#45;prove&#59; and of those who wish that the wheel of progress be set in<lb/> motion without receiving a check from internal causes.<lb/>  Arguments&#44; cannot fail to penetrate the mind&#44; and<lb/> gradually to <sic>dispell</sic> prejudgments.  Now&#58; the in&#45;<lb/>&#45;stances in which changes for the better might be in&#45;<lb/>&#45;troduced even among us&#44; exceptionally conservative&#44;<lb/> are various.  And if I have never ventured to point<lb/> them out&#44; you may attribute the cause motive to a fear<lb/> of doing a permanent injury&#44; while attempting to<lb/> remove what is objectionable&#44; yet harmless.<lb/>  But the instance I am about to cite&#44; does positive mischief&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>hence I make mention of it. submit my thoughts concerning it to your considerations.  Let me preface my<lb/> remarks by saying that Hebrew parents are guilty of<lb/> an injustice towards their children and their people&#44; which the usages of this congregation en&#45;<lb/>&#45;courage and commend.  I appeal to your good<lb/> sense&#44; my hearers.  Can a mason structure be built without materials&#63;<lb/>  Or dares an architect to master mason expect that an edifice having<lb/> but sand for its foundations will stand firm unmoveable&#63;  Cer&#45;<lb/>&#45;tainly not&#44; is the universal answer.  Yet&#44; we act<lb/> as if we believed that impossibility possible.  We<lb/> are in duty bound to construct Judaism in America<lb/> upon solid bases&#44; so strong that the adverse violent winds<lb/> raised by opposite creeds shall not shake it&#59; nor so very staunch<lb/> that the storms of incredulity may not threaten its stability.<lb/>  But I will speak plainly.  Whatever the leaders<lb/> of a schismatic party that style themselves &#34;Reformers&#34;<lb/> may assert to the contrary&#44; the our ancestral religion<lb/> lacks here the elements of self&#45;preservation.  It can&#45;<lb/>&#45;not resist&#44; unless by timely provisions&#44; it cannot long<lb/> resist very long the perils lo which surround it.<lb/>  Idle is the boast of a crowded attendance at the<lb/> Synagogue on New Year and the day of atonement.<lb/>  I tremble at the consequences of a centering Judaism<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>round so narrow a sphere&#44; were it even that in this age of skepticism singleness<lb/> of purpose always prompted the large gathering.  I<lb/> tremble&#44; because the next generation&#44; uninfluenced by<lb/> the associations which make those days dear to our hearts awe&#45;inspiring to our souls&#44;<lb/> will suffer them also to be expunged from their calendar.<lb/>  No O Israelites&#44; the religious training of our youths is<lb/> the barometer indicating the state of the religious atmosphere<lb/> in which we religiously breathe&#59; that alone will determine&#44;<lb/> whether the Jewish horizon is to will be overcast with clouds&#44;<lb/> or to continue bright.  But is what is in very deed that culture&#63;  A<lb/> blank.  And we help to keep it so.  The Bar&#45;<lb/>Mitzvah ceremony as followed among us proceeded&#44; like<lb/> many other practices of old&#44; from a pure and high source&#44; but<lb/> in the course of time it mixed with much that is<lb/> earthy and became turbid and foul.  The object<lb/> it intended to reach has been lost sight of&#44; and the mind<lb/> has gone astray after the gratification of personal vanity.<lb/>  Formerly&#44; the public reading of the a section of the Pentateuch&#45;&#45;<lb/>not unfrequently accompanied with a short lecture&#45;&#45;<lb/> was to denote the auspicious beginning of parental<lb/> education&#44; and a pledge for its continuation.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Parents Our predecessors mindful of the divine command &#34;Thou<lb/> shalt teach &#40;the tenets of thy faith&#41; diligently to thy<lb/> children&#44;&#34; remembered also that according to the counsel<lb/> of a Sage in the Mishnah&#44; a lad ought to be able<lb/> in his thirteenth year to read and measurably to<lb/> understand Holy Writ with its oral meaning in the ori&#45;<lb/>&#45;ginal.  But no steps are steps in that direction taken very rarely The occasion had therefore a deep<lb/> by the coreligionists I minister to&#44; or with whom I am significance&#59; it gave genuine motives<lb/> in contact.  The public celebration was therefore a<lb/> genuine occasion for rejoicing alike to the Hebrews Israelites<lb/> immediately interested&#44; and for to the community<lb/> to which they belonged.  Can it so be viewed at<lb/> present&#44; when very rarely are measures taken to attain the<lb/> same end&#44; either by the coreligionists I minister to&#44; or by<lb/> others with whom I came in contact&#63;  It was a grievous<lb/> revelation to me&#44; when requesting a few days ago some<lb/> of our young&#44; I desired to imitate in the translation of<lb/> the Pentateuch to fetch the book along&#44; that they did not possess a Hebrew<lb/> copy of the Mosaic law.  Nay&#58; I have since been<lb/> assured by a person whose activity in Jewish matters<lb/> affords the capacity of speaking knowingly&#44; that even<lb/> an English copy of the Scriptures is not to be found<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>in houses dwelt in by the divine original guardians of<lb/> the inspired word.  A lad may have been left in utter<lb/> ignorance of his descent&#44; of the obligations it imposes&#44;<lb/> and the doctrines peculiarly our own&#59; he may not have<lb/> learnt a letter of the Hebrew Alphabet before the<lb/> time approaches for his would&#45;be admission into the<lb/> body of an observant community.  But If he can master<lb/> a few sentences by memorizing them&#44; the pleasure<lb/> of his parents is complete.  They receive a round of<lb/> congratulations&#44; and the successful efforts of their<lb/> son is commented on&#44; within his hearing&#44; with in terms<lb/> of approval.  Ought that system to continue&#63;  Is it<lb/> by it&#44; I ask in sorrowful earnestness&#44; is it by it<lb/> that we anticipate to establish Judaism in this land<lb/> on a firm footing&#63;  Or shall we trust its perpetuity<lb/> to chance&#44; imagining that our offspring ignorant unacquainted<lb/> of their mission will still perform it&#44; that they will hear<lb/> the banterings of gentiles&#44; and nevertheless remain unaffected&#44;<lb/> that assailed by the worldly and the unbelievers&#44; they will<lb/> hold fast to that&#44; of the real sanctity of which they<lb/> have no conceptions&#63;  Vain hopes&#44; groundless an&#45;<lb/>&#45;ticipations&#44; my fellow Israelites.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Some may perhaps say&#58; &#34;we are weary of these reflect&#45;<lb/>&#45;ions upon the conduct of men and women who sup&#45;<lb/>&#45;port the worship with their means&#44; at all events&#44; if<lb/> not with their presence.  You disparage what is old&#44;<lb/> condemn what is new&#44; and give us offer us nothing which<lb/> may supersede both.&#34;  Yes&#58; I disapprove of our<lb/> practice&#44; though it has the stamp of antiquity&#44; because<lb/> barren altogether of goodly fruits.  I deprecate the novel<lb/> method borrowed from our gentile neighbors.  I mean<lb/> the confirmation&#44; because it is an exhibition in the house<lb/> of God&#44; attended with surroundings not all at all cal&#45;<lb/>&#45;culated to inspire love for retiring habits and moderation<lb/> in dress on the part of the female&#44; and fondness for sa&#45;<lb/>&#45;cred learning on the part of the male confirmants&#45;&#45;<lb/>to use a newly coined word.  But I am free of the<lb/> charge of not supplying a method condemning<lb/> itself to the understanding of all who believe that<lb/> they are bound to contribute to the permanence of<lb/> Mosaic doctrines and institutions.<lb/></p>
                <p>I reiterate what has has been expressed time and<lb/> again.  Retain the calling of the youth to the Law&#44; with a clear and intelligent recital of the benedictions.  It may awaken hereafter&#44; in the most callous&#44; a reminiscence leading the steps once more to the Synagogue&#44; but let Let your children be taught the language<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>and the precepts spirit of the book of books.  do not&#44;<lb/> I pray&#44; subject them to a procedure which works<lb/> positive evil.  For&#44; often a whole year is devoted to a<lb/> profitless study&#44; often it is attended with a worriment<lb/> and a fatigue which destroys all taste for Hebrew learning&#44;<lb/> and&#44; this is the worst feature&#44; it often impresses the intel&#45;<lb/>&#45;ligent child with the idea that the religion of his fathers<lb/> demands only dead forms&#44; which with the mind empty&#44;<lb/> and the heart unsatisfied.  Demand&#44; for you have the<lb/> right so to do&#44; that the pulpit be devoted with greater<lb/> frequency than&#44; on a Bar Mitzvah occasion&#44; to the in&#45;<lb/>&#45;struction of the young&#44; but principally and mindless<lb/> of the sacrifice&#44; let teachers be engaged&#44; whose knowledge<lb/> and honest convictions will enkindle an undying at&#45;<lb/>&#45;tachment for what is purely Jewish in the breasts of<lb/> your offspring.<lb/></p>
            <p>I have been requested by several of our city Ministers to<lb/> offer their gratuitous tuition twice a week&#44; Wednesday and<lb/> Thursday afternoon from half past four to half past six<lb/> o&#39;clock&#44; to any lad able to read Hebrew with fluency.<lb/>  The meeting place will be in the vestry rooms of<lb/> the Congregation Keneseth Israel&#44; in 6th st above Brown.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>This lecture was considerably altered and<lb/> made more forcible in delivering it&#44; and it was<lb/> followed by an address to a Bar Mitzvah<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
