<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF26_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff26_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff26_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff26_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff26_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff26_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff26_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff26_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff26_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff26_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff26_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff26_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff26_1_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff26_1_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff26_1_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff26_1_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff26_1_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>For Parashat Bemidbar<lb/>
                on the ministerial mission<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;I&#44; behold I have taken the Levites from<lb/> among the children of Israel&#44; instead of every first<lb/> born...of the children of Israel&#44; and the Levites shall<lb/> be mine.&#34;  Brethren.  In early ages&#44; before society<lb/> was had constituted itself into various separate nationalities&#44; the first born male<lb/> child of a family exercised an supreme authority which was<lb/> absolute supreme.  All the rest of the household was bound<lb/> to submit bow to it the rule it&#44; and obey it implicitly submissively.  The effect<lb/> of that primitive&#44; but most unjust institution&#45;&#45;some<lb/> remains of which unfortunately mischievously hurtfully harmfully exists even in our boastful<lb/> age times&#44; was domestic quarrels&#59; family feuds&#44;&#45;&#45;always<lb/> the bitterest&#45;&#45;beginning which began in envy and ill will and ended<lb/> &#45;ing in blood shed.  The holy book&#44; which is<lb/> our guide&#44; forcibly teaches in its almost the very its opening pages thereof that<lb/> not the casualty of birth&#44; but the qualities of heart<lb/> and mind ought to ensure preeminence.  Mark<lb/> it well&#58; Abel was the second son of his parents&#44; never&#45;<lb/>&#45;theless he stood higher than his older brother in<lb/> the sight of God&#44; because his thoughts and feelings<lb/> were purer.  It cannot be denied that the<lb/> right of primogeniture&#44; or superiority by reason of birth&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>was craved for in patriarchal times but judging<lb/> without bias&#44; we must arrive at the conclusion that the<lb/> object was not an increase of temporal power&#44; or per&#45;<lb/>&#45;sonal property.  Jacob&#44; notwithstanding the rude<lb/> charges made against his character&#44; obtained nothing<lb/> of the paternal estate over his brother Esau&#44; when the<lb/> latter parted with his birth right which he despised.<lb/>  All that our patriarch gained was a spiritual benediction&#44; which<lb/> we&#44; his descendants have inherited.  I mean&#44; the knowledge<lb/> of Abraham&#39;s God&#44; and the worship of the understanding of the mission of eternizing it as a world&#45;redeem&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing Unity principle.  Again&#58; of the twelve sons of the aged Israel whom he<lb/> gathered round his dying death bed&#44; the youngest but one Joseph<lb/> was preferred to the oldest&#44; Reubens and he and the seed of Joseph&#44; not of Reuben received a<lb/> twofold portion of in the promised land.  It This was not an<lb/> act of partiality&#44; but a richly deserved reward for due to the<lb/> splendid virtues of a son&#44; a brother and a beneficent<lb/> ruler.  On the night of the great deliver&#45;<lb/>&#45;ance from bondage&#44; the first born males were chosen<lb/> to perpetuate the memory of their miraculous escape<lb/> from death&#44; and to all appearances that end they were granted<lb/> a signal distinction.  They acted&#44; for a time&#44; as officiating<lb/> ministers&#59; so the context shows&#44; and so is asserted in<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>the volumes of our traditions &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Before the Tabernacle was raised&#44; temporary altars were allow&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed&#44; and the service worship was performed by the first born.&#34;  But<lb/> when that provisional service ceased&#44; and a sacred edifice<lb/> was set up&#44; then a distinct special tribe displaced the first born<lb/> in the exercise of religious functions rites.  So Thus we read in to<lb/> day&#39;s portion&#58; &#34;I&#44; behold I have taken the Levites from <lb/>among the children of Israel&#44; instead of every first born...of<lb/> the children of Israel&#44; and the Levites shall be mine.&#34;  Now&#58;<lb/> if we inquire into the reason for that choice&#44; we will<lb/> become convinced still more of the fact that according to the teachings of Holy Writ no precedence<lb/> at birth influenced a promotion&#44; but that&#44; according to the<lb/> teachings of Holy Writ only real&#44; sterling merit.  Levy was<lb/> the third son of Jacob&#44; and Kehath from whom Amram&#44;<lb/> the father of Aaron and Moses the Levite par excellence&#44; issued&#44; was not the first but<lb/> the second son of Levy.  Therefore It cannot then be said those that the Levites attained an<lb/> enduring distinction not because of by a fortuitous precedence mere casualty&#44;<lb/> of birth&#44; but they won it through an action of theirs&#44; which proved a<lb/> how their steadfast was their fidelity to the Law of Sinai.<lb/>  Incited&#44; no doubt&#44; by Egyptians who had joined who<lb/> had joined the Hebrews at the hour of the redemption<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>from slavery&#44; but who could not wean themselves<lb/> away from pagan heathen practices&#44; some of our an&#45;<lb/>&#45;cestors acknowledged a molten calf as a representation<lb/> of the Deity.  Moses horror&#45;struck at a sin&#44; which&#44;<lb/> if left unpunished&#44; would defeat the object of his<lb/> Divine mission&#44; took a summary and severe measure<lb/> to spread terror and prevent a recurrence of the blasphemy heinous offense.<lb/>  He called upon all who loved the Lord more than<lb/> their own flesh and blood&#44; to stand by him and destroy<lb/> the transgressions guilty ones.  At that summons the Levites rallied<lb/> around&#44; and suppressing all feelings&#44; save a wish to<lb/> vindicate their outraged religion&#44; slew those who paid caroused<lb/> homage to and prostituted themselves before a golden idol.  Then were the Levites<lb/> promised the ministerial vocation in these words&#58; &#34;Ye<lb/> are consecrated this day to the Lord&#44; yea&#58; every one though acting &#40;rising&#41;<lb/> against his own child and brother&#44; and this day you have been<lb/> given this day a blessing.&#34;  And when at the last<lb/> hour of his life the archprophet bestowed a benediction<lb/> on his people&#44; he so spoke of the tribe that had<lb/> stood up for the belief of Sinai at a moment when<lb/> it was imperilled endangered&#58; &#34;He sayeth of his father and of his mo&#45;<lb/>&#45;ther&#44; &#39;I kno saw them not&#44;&#39; and of his brothers &#39;I know recognize<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>them not&#44;&#39; and of his children &#39;I know them not&#44;&#39; for yea&#58;<lb/> they would keep Thy ordinance&#44; and preserve Thy covenant there&#45;<lb/>&#45;fore shall they teach Thy judgments to Jacob and Thy Law<lb/> to Israel&#34;.  But if more evidences of the fact which I<lb/> have intended purposed to explain were needed&#44; I could cite the<lb/> instance of Gideon clothed with a spirit of God for<lb/> as a champion of his brethren in Israel through his good ardent zeal&#44; though his family was<lb/> the most least numerous numerous in the tribe of Menesseb&#44;<lb/> and he himself was the youngest of his father&#39;s family.<lb/>  But what brighter illustration can be brought forward<lb/> than that of David set royally apart&#44; not because he could<lb/> claim precedence of birth&#44; for he was the last child<lb/> of Jesse&#44; but because his zeal patriotism and his genius had made proved<lb/> him a hero as he afterwards became the sublime the poet and sweet psalmist of Israel.<lb/>  Clearly then&#44; if we take our scriptures as a standard&#44;<lb/> neither age nor family connection should secure a selection<lb/> to the service of God.  but Virtue&#44; the capacity and<lb/> the endeavours to benefit the community by deeds<lb/> of righteousness&#44; should be the criterion.  &#34;Say not&#44; &#39;I am<lb/> but a lad&#44;&#39; for to whomsoever I shall send thee thou shalt go<lb/> and all which I command thee&#44; There shalt speak&#34; so a Divine<lb/> inspiration told Jeremiah.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>But are they deserving of occupying a holy<lb/> station as chiefs in religion&#44; who claim point to pride themselves on their grey hair<lb/> and or social influence&#44; but who use their position<lb/> to mislead the unwary into an abandonment of an&#45;<lb/>&#45;cestral doctrines&#44; who aim at self&#45;deification and not at the &#91;&#63;&#93; glorification of the olden faith&#63;  I have no desire to meddle<lb/> in matters which specially concern another body of<lb/> Israelites in our city&#44; but as I have been taunted<lb/> even by my gentile neighbors about the want of<lb/> harmony among us&#44; I b must boldly defend the action<lb/> of the Rodef Sholom Congregation.  It was perfectly<lb/> justifiable&#44; though declared by some inconsistent with its name&#44;<lb/> which say denotes a wish to promote peace.  Con&#45;<lb/>&#45;tinuously&#44; persistantly has the man who ministers<lb/> to a large congregation and controls a college in<lb/> the West&#44; obtraded his heretical notions upon the Hebrews<lb/> at large.  Persistently has he attacked the Law and<lb/> traditions.  At one time&#44; ordinances hallowed by dear asso&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciations&#44; are rudely inveigled against with abusive utter&#45;<lb/>&#45;ances&#59; at others&#44; persons who conscientiously adhere<lb/> to ancient precepts&#44; are consigned to public contempt.<lb/>  More recently the laws&#44; which by the confession of<lb/> scientists&#44; have most effectually contributed to the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>physical and mental preservation of our proper&#44;<lb/>&#45;&#45;despite a combination of causes working to our injury&#44;&#45;&#45;have been vulgarly ridiculed by sentences&#44; such as<lb/> these&#58; &#34;stop that noise over the culinary department<lb/> of Judaism.  Nobody has appointed those very or&#45;<lb/>&#45;thodox critics&#44; overseers of the kitchen and taskmasters<lb/> of the stomach.&#34;  The climax was perhaps reached<lb/> last week in a very lengthy article in which the<lb/> following views are categorically set forth&#58; &#34;The cause<lb/> of Jewish vitality&#44; energy&#44; profundity and longevity<lb/> must be sought somewhere outside the Rabbin&#45;<lb/>&#45;ical dietary laws.  The standard and test of orthodoxy<lb/> is not in the kitchen or in the stomach&#44; for Ju&#45;<lb/>&#45;daism is a matter of conscience and intelligence.&#34;  I<lb/> don&#39;t know what the writer understands for con&#45;<lb/>&#45;science&#44; but as to intelligence I am certain that<lb/> the soundness or unsoundness of the body proceeding from the nature of our food does exercise<lb/> vast influence over the mind.  Then with a sweeping<lb/> insult to all who believe the Sages of antiquity to<lb/> have been wiser than modern changelings&#44; he&#44; cast&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing aside every sense of Rabinnical&#44; professional or<lb/> journalistic dignity&#44; concludes&#58; &#34;Let us alone with your<lb/> Kosher and Trepha philosophy.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Yet&#44; one of his pupils&#44; writing immediately after&#44; upon<lb/> another subject&#44; complains that &#34;reformers are reviled<lb/> and cursed.&#34;  No wonder then that a congregation body<lb/> of Philadelphia Israelites&#44; &#91;&#63;&#93; which who had entered the Union of<lb/> American Congregations in the hopes of raising the<lb/> standard of Hebrew literature&#44; and rearing pulpit tea&#45;<lb/>&#45;chers &#34;to the manner born&#34;&#44; severed themselves from an<lb/> institution blighted by the guidance of a coarse adversary<lb/> to undermining the principles he is morally bound to inculcate.<lb/>  No wonder that continental journals on the eastern<lb/> side of the Atlantic&#44; sober and conservative and in<lb/> their tone&#44; denounce proceedings so calculated to bring<lb/> scandal upon the Jewish ministry.  No wonder<lb/> that they predict the final surrender of the ark<lb/> of the covenant by the hands once consecrated hallowed to<lb/> its sacred service.  Brethren.  An evil incalcu&#45;<lb/>&#45;lably serious threatens the American Synagogue.<lb/>  Lie not supinely&#44; for it rests with the people<lb/> to ward it off.  The ease with which the privilege<lb/> to wear sacerdal&#91;sic&#63;&#93; garments can be procured&#44; offers<lb/> a premium to dishonesty.  Making it stringently It behooves you to make it excessively<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>difficult to gain a public hearing by ascending the sacred desk.  You will<lb/> thus have prevented the insidious to undermine our religious<lb/> fabric.  Only a few weeks ago&#44; one whose heart<lb/> had never responded to the duties of the holy priesthood<lb/> in the sanctuary of our God&#44; deliberately cut the threads<lb/> of his own existence.  We may pity him that<lb/> having proved utterly false to his trust&#44; forfeited confi&#45;<lb/>&#45;dence&#44; and sought a refuge in self&#45;destruction.<lb/>  But does it become Rabbis to palliate the deed&#63;<lb/>  Yet&#44; it had been defended on the plea that the suicide<lb/> in his epistolary will wrote&#58; &#34;Though overtures were made<lb/> to me by <sic>Episcolian</sic> and Unitarian authorities&#44; I prefer&#45;<lb/>&#45;red to die&#44; when I found once became convinced that I was not wanted in<lb/> the house of my fathers.&#34;  But could overtures such<lb/> advances overtures be made by Christian churchmen to any except to an individual who had im&#45;<lb/>&#45;piously and treasonably disclosed his disbelief in Judaism&#63;<lb/>  Will Israelites tolerate then the subtle destroyers of<lb/> their creed&#63;  No&#58; frown upon the priests of Baal&#44;<lb/> be they ever so strong in their social connection. so fast on the increase&#63;  The<lb/> first born were at one in olden times the leaders in the wor&#45;<lb/>&#45;ship&#44; but men of tried sincerity and zeal re&#45;<lb/>&#45;placed those who had not stood the test in the face of fallen into vile seductions.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>I repeat it&#44; the people must purify the dwel&#45;<lb/>&#45;ling of our Lord from the pollution of the untrustworthy.<lb/>  In the scales of the Hebrew Scriptures integrity and<lb/> truthfulness outweighs age social connection influence&#44; or even learning.<lb/>  Let such only as their deeds proved them worthy deserving of<lb/> the lofty station to which you will raise them&#44; become<lb/> your spiritual guides&#44; such only as recognize duty<lb/> as their standard.  They shall lay hold of the holy<lb/> ark and guard its vessels&#44; even as those set apart<lb/> by God in the days of antiquity because of their fidelity.<lb/>  &#34;I&#44; behold I have taken the Levites from among the<lb/> children of Israel&#44; instead of every first born...of the<lb/> children of Israel&#44; and the Levites shall be mine&#34;.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
