<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF5_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_2_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Post&#45;Biblical<lb/>
                45<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>There are persons whose individuality is so strongly<lb/> marked&#44; that their history becomes the history of<lb/> a new era.  In the course of my occasional brief lectures<lb/> in the schools of Judea&#44; I have&#44; at times&#44; set to view<lb/> characters that left among us impressions ever enduring.<lb/>  Such were&#44; for instance&#44; Johanan Ben Zaccka&#239;&#44; whose<lb/> escape from Jerusalem when all hopes for political<lb/> safety had died out&#44; was the means of preserving<lb/> Judaism from extinction by the establishment of Rabbin&#45;<lb/>&#45;ical schools beyond the capital.  Such were Akiba<lb/> the martyred Sage and his disciple Meir&#44; who impart&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed a fresh impulse to our national learning&#59; but no<lb/> one created so marked an epoch in our annals like Judah the<lb/> descendant of Hillel the elder&#44; and therefore called Han&#45;<lb/> &#45;nasi &#34;the prince&#34;.  That he grew to be singularly<lb/> famous&#44; it is due to the circumstance which led him<lb/> to commit to writing most of the traditions orally com&#45;<lb/>&#45;municated by the fathers&#44; and known in their codified<lb/> form under the general title of &#34;Mishnah.&#34;  Judah<lb/> son of Simon III&#44; was not the first to make memo&#45;<lb/>&#45;randa of religious rules thus transmitted from age<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>to age.  Others before him had adopted followed the same<lb/> plan to help their memory&#44; for it was naturally<lb/> impossible to store in one&#39;s mind all the teachings&#44;<lb/> which since the days of Ezra had come down to poste&#45;<lb/>&#45;rity&#44; even admitting with the Talmudists that the Sages of antiquity did<lb/> possess extraordinary retentive faculties.  But Ju&#45;<lb/>&#45;dah undertook what none had attempted.  He laid out<lb/> in a somewhat methodical order a voluminous work<lb/> divided into six parts&#44; with holding more than sixty treatises&#44;<lb/> and over five hundred chapters.  It remains yet<lb/> an open question&#44; whether the Mishnah was in<lb/> reality written out by that renowned Rabbi as an authority to posterity&#44; not&#45;<lb/>&#45;withstanding the aversion&#44; and&#44; according to many&#44;<lb/> notwithstanding the actual prohibition to put to writing<lb/> for general use more than the Bible.  Those who<lb/> believe that the illustrious Sage did so&#44; argue that<lb/> he found it necessary&#44; so as to prevent national troubles<lb/> and voluntary or compulsory emigration from wiping<lb/> out the memorial of ordinances which had been kept<lb/> up for centuries.  Others&#44; again&#44; are of opinion that<lb/> Judah the Prince intended the Mishnah for his own<lb/> personal guide in the instruction of scholars&#44; but that<lb/> in the lapse of time what he had meant for private<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>reference&#44; was deemed by his disciples the best arraigned<lb/> codification of oral laws&#44; and it was universally adopted.<lb/>  Whatever judgment be the correct&#44; it is undeniable that<lb/> without the aid of the Mishnah we could not intelligently carry<lb/> out the precepts of Holy Writ.  Thus&#44; we could under&#45;<lb/>&#45;stand neither what constitutes a work prohibited on<lb/> Sabbaths and holidays&#44; nor how to nationally observe<lb/> solemn fasts and festivals.  The service at the Synagogue&#44;<lb/> marriage regulations&#44; dietary prescriptions and a large<lb/> number of ordinances followed adhered to by our people in their<lb/> domestic and communal relations&#44; would be unknown&#44;<lb/> for&#44; about some our Bible is silent the letter of the Bible does not furnish a date&#44; and about others<lb/> it has expressed itself in very general terms and<lb/> concisely&#44; relying undoubtedly on oral instruction for<lb/> a proper application.  Then the Mishnah contains<lb/> a vast deal of an historical and moral character&#44; while<lb/> it is invaluable from a linguistic standpoint.<lb/>  To Judah&#44; deservedly styled by way of eminence &#34;our<lb/> teacher the holy&#34; Rabbiner Ha&#45;Kadosh&#44; belongs the<lb/> merit of having preserved the bulk of ancestral teach&#45;<lb/>&#45;ings&#44; and to of having indirectly originated a new and<lb/></p> 
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>inexhaustible literature&#44; for&#44; as all are aware&#44;<lb/> the Mishnah forms the text of the Gemara&#44;&#45;&#45;<lb/> both being together termed Talmud.&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>The vicissitudes to which our predecessors were ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;posed under Roman rule dominion&#44; necessitated a frequent<lb/> change in our ancient seat of learning.  It was<lb/> at Tiberius in Galilee&#44; which city Herod Antipas&#44;<lb/> son of Herod the great had built&#44; and which he<lb/> called so in honor of the Roman emperor Tiberius&#44;<lb/> that the Mishnah was computed formulated.  In later<lb/> days&#44; Rabbi Judah&#44; whose health&#44; was always deli&#45;<lb/>&#45;cate&#44; removed to Sepohris&#45;&#45;a more mountainous and<lb/> healthful climate.  But wherever he resided&#44;<lb/> men flocked to receive his tuition.  He gave with<lb/> gladness of the immense erudition possessed&#44; for&#44;<lb/> as wisely and as modestly&#44; he confessed that questions<lb/> submitted to us by the inquiring minds of our pupils&#44;<lb/> add incalculably to our stock of knowledge.  He<lb/> was in the habit of saying&#58; &#34;Much I have learned<lb/> from my preceptors&#44; still more from my associates&#44; but<lb/> I owe most to my pupils.&#34;<lb/>  His love for study<lb/> and for students was so deep&#44; that he gave &#91;&#63;&#93; dispensed generously<lb/> of his means for the support of indigent scholars&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>but his fondness of sacred literature led him&#44; on<lb/> one occasion&#44; very nearly to the commission of a<lb/> grievous wrong.  A famine had spread all over<lb/> the country.  Judah the Prince&#44; who was rich&#44; ordered<lb/> the following announcement to be made in his<lb/> name&#44; &#34;Whosoever has become familiar with the Bible<lb/> or with our traditions in their various forms and charact&#45;<lb/>&#45;ers&#44; shall may apply to me&#44; and he will receive assistance.&#34;<lb/>  When a person called for aid&#44; he was asked concerning<lb/> his acquaintance with Hebrew lore.  It fared ill with<lb/> the illiterate.  But the injustice of such a pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;cedure&#44; did not escape the attention of a very learned<lb/> scholar.  He was poor&#44; but at the same time loth to<lb/> make capital of his literary acquirements.  He sought<lb/> relief.  Being questioned about his abilities&#44; he disclaimed<lb/> the possession of any&#44; but insisted upon obtaining help<lb/> as one of God&#39;s creatures.  &#34;Feed me&#34; said he&#44; &#34;as thou<lb/> wouldst feed a hungry dog&#44; or a famished raven.&#34;<lb/>  Rabbi Judah was moved by the appeal and consented&#44; still he regret&#45;<lb/>&#45;ted to have favored a supposed ignorant man.  Soon&#44;<lb/> however&#44; the Sage discovered his error&#44; and profited by the<lb/> lesson which the applicant feigning illiteracy had taught him&#44;<lb/> recalled his first order&#44; and let every one in need be assisted.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Beautiful are the maxims as his life&#44; so was the character of the tuition which the worthy<lb/> descendant of the meek Hillel inculcated.  Most<lb/> significant is the one of his aphorisms&#44; which reads thus&#58;<lb/> &#34;Man&#33; weight in even scales the temporal loss which<lb/> thou mayest bear by the performance of righteousness&#44;<lb/> and the gain which thou mayest enjoy by following<lb/> wickedness&#44; then consider three things and thou wilt<lb/> avoid sin.  Know that there is above thee&#44; an eye ever<lb/> open&#44; an ear ever listening&#44; and a volume ever un&#45;<lb/>&#45;folded to register all thy deeds.&#34;  Of a nature intensely<lb/> devotional&#44; our Judah was in the habit of making<lb/> at the conclusion of his customary prayers an invocation&#44;<lb/> which has been embodied in the ritual still adhered to by con&#45;<lb/>&#45;servative Jews.  It runs so&#58; &#34;May it be Thy will O Lord<lb/> our God&#33; to deliver me this day and always from arro&#45;<lb/>&#45;gance and from the arrogant&#44; from an evil person and<lb/> a malicious opponent&#44; from a severe judgment&#44; and<lb/> a severe judge&#44; whether he be one of Thy covenant peo&#45;<lb/>&#45;ple or a non&#45;Israelite.&#34;  Now&#44; some may consider it<lb/> an exaggeration on the part of the successors of Judah&#44;<lb/> to have written that at his death there died piety<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>piety and humility&#44; but certainly the last words and<lb/> the last will of that great man&#44; who stood up full<lb/> thirty years for his religion and his fellow religionists&#44;<lb/> prove him entitled to high encomium.  Having<lb/> resignedly suffered bodily pains for a long time&#44; when<lb/> he felt that the end was approaching&#44; he sent for<lb/> his children and his colleagues.  Raising Lifting up his<lb/> hands&#44; and stretching out his ten fingers&#44; he exclaimed&#58;<lb/> &#34;Sovereign of the Universe&#33;  Thou&#44; the all&#45;seeing&#44; knowest<lb/> that I have labored with these&#44; and that I have<lb/> not derived the slightest material compensation from<lb/> my endeavours&#59; only for Thy glory have I worked.<lb/>  Grant&#44; I beseech Thee&#44; that spiritual peace be my<lb/> reward.&#34;  Then turning to his sons&#44; he gave them directions<lb/> how to proceed in the government of academical and<lb/> national Synedrial affairs&#44; bid them pay their mother the highest<lb/> respect&#44; and keep the house in the usual order as if<lb/> he were alive.  To the Rabbis whom he had summoned&#44;<lb/> he ordered that his burial and obsequies be inexpensive<lb/> and unostentatious&#44; and that two of his servants&#44; who<lb/> had faithfully waited on him in life&#44; should follow<lb/> his mortal remains to their resting place.  Like<lb/> Gamliel of Jammia his honored grand&#45;sire&#44; and Simon III his father&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>who deprecated under all circumstances extravagance at funerals and the<lb/> waste of gold in the erection of tombstones&#44; so our holy<lb/> teacher Rabbim Hakkadosh&#44; recognized the wisdom<lb/> of living godly and the folly of being entombed interred luxuriou&#45;<lb/>&#45;sly.  If asked&#44; those ancient preceptors of ours would<lb/> have advised the purchase of everlasting merits with<lb/> that gold&#44; by bestowing it on institutions of learning&#44;<lb/> of industry and of charity.  The venera&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion in which the guardian and perpetuator of ancestral<lb/> traditions was held&#44; revealed itself extraordinarily at<lb/> his decease.  Though some of his disciples were informed<lb/> that their Master had gone to heaven&#44; no one ventured<lb/> to spread abroad the report.  At length of one of the<lb/> pupils&#44; noted for his versatile mind cried out&#58; &#34;Archan&#45;<lb/>&#45;gels and their adversaries engaged in a severe combat contest&#44; who<lb/> shall seize lay hold of the holy ark&#63;  Archangels bore bared their<lb/> arms&#44; and won the glorious victory&#44; they laid strong hold of seized<lb/> the ark of God.&#34;  The people understood it&#44; and sobbingly<lb/> lamented exclaimed &#34;He is gone&#44; he is gone&#44; our holy teacher is gone&#34;.<lb/>  With the demise of Rabbi Judah&#44; the period of Mishnic Sages&#44; or Tannaim<lb/> closed&#44; &#38; that of Talmudical sages&#44; or Emoraim&#44; commenced.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>I cannot conclude my remarks&#44; without paying a tribute of respect to the<lb/> memory of a disciple of our Rabbi&#44; the holy.  Jacob Frankel of Philadelphia<lb/> copied the moral standard once set forth by the immortal teacher of sephoris.<lb/>  The Cantor of the Rodef Shalom congregation never laid claims to natural talents<lb/> and scholarly attainments.  He understood the limits of his knowledge&#44;<lb/> and kept within bounds.  Yet&#44; he remarkably illustrated the truth that<lb/> character exceeds learning in value beyond calculation.  Genial in his inter&#45;<lb/>&#45;course&#44; kind in his speech&#44; tender hearted towards the needy&#44; he won the<lb/> esteem of a far more extended circle than that of his own constituents.<lb/>  And how very acceptable the performance the of his offices&#33;  At the sacred<lb/> desk&#44; where he sang the praises of God&#44; his bearing&#44; his mellifluously<lb/> sweet voice inspired reverence.  Out of the Sanctuary&#59; in the usual walks<lb/> of life&#44; his commanding appearance&#44; his friendly smile made him uni&#45;<lb/>&#45;versally welcome.  On occasions of joy&#44; either in a ministerial capa&#45;<lb/>&#45;city&#44; or as an invited guest&#44; he always strove to add pleasure to the pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;vailing pleasure.  In time of affliction&#44; his sterling sympathies acted<lb/> as a balm to the sorrow&#45;stricken.  My intercourse with<lb/> with2 that venerable colleague&#44; existing for1 of nearly thirty six years&#44; has3<lb/> been uninterruptedly agreeable.  I had cause to discover in him an honest<lb/> and truthful man.  Privileged to call on him when he became the recipient<lb/> of congregational tokens of regard &#38; he felt happy&#44; &#38; when sickness &#38; trials depres&#45;<lb/>&#45;sed his spirits&#44; I invariably found Jacob Frankel a meek and God&#45;fearing Israelite.<lb/>  If&#44; as as taught by the Talmudists&#44; the prayer of a whole population will surely<lb/> be heard in heaven &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; the soul of my noble hearted colleague will now rise<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; to the realms where the saints &#38; pure shine like the firmament.<lb/>  May it be so.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
