<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF2_13</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1892" source="" attested="yes">1892</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_13_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_13_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_13_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_13_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_13_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_13_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_13_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_13_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_13_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_13_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_13_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_13_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 3 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English, Hebrew</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

<pb n="1"/>
<p>S. MORAIS,<lb/>
            546 N. FIFTH STREET,<lb/>
            PHILADELPHIA.</p>
            

            <p>66<lb/>
                For the penitential Sabbath<lb/>
            5652<lb/></p>
            
<pb n="2"/>
            <p>A<del>n worthy</del> brother Israelite, young in years, but mentally well<lb/> <sic>developped</sic> called on me last Monday evening for coun-<lb/>-sel and instruction.  He avowed his want of knowledge<lb/> of Jewish theology, hence his mind had been somewhat<lb/> disturbed by a conversation which he had lately held with<lb/> an acquaintance born and <del>educated as</del> reared as a Christian.  The<lb/> latter had pictured his own religion as preeminently spiritual,<lb/> and comforting in the highest degree.  These claims of<lb/> superiority <del>above</del> to Judaism were based upon what was<lb/> set forth as admitted facts, namely; one who follows<lb/> the teaching of the man of Nazareth, will attach no im-<lb/>-portance to this transient world and its fleeting pleasures.  He<lb/> will rather direct his constant thoughts to a hereafter which<lb/> <del>lasts</del> endures everlastingly, and yearn for its joys.  Again; a Christian,<lb/> however sinful, bears within himself the assurance of<lb/> Divine forgiveness, for, a belief in the atoning power of<lb/> the cross instills it.  This last assertion was illustrated by the<lb/> case of a person guilty of a heinous <sic>offence</sic>.  In a fit<lb/> of passion he had thrown at a neighbor's a weapon which<lb/> he had in his hand, and which occasioned instant death.<lb/>  Though acquitted by the courts of justice, the homicide was haunted by the awful deed,<lb/>
            
<pb n="3"/>
            <del>haunted the homicide</del>, until existence became an<lb/> insufferable burden.  Finally, a coreligionist of his, who<lb/> <del>was</del> firmly <del>attached</del> adhered to the doctrines of the Church, aroused<lb/> him from a state of the deepest depression, by pointing to<lb/> the Calvary, where&#8212;as he alleged&#8212;god put on flesh and made himself<lb/> a voluntary sacrifice for all sinners.  The one who<lb/> had committed manslaughter felt then relieved.  My<lb/> visitor said that at this <del>point</del> stage of the narrative his companion turned triumph-<lb/>-antly to him and <del>asked</del> inquired whether the Jewish faith can offer<lb/> its votaries such consolations, and I was asked: "Have you<lb/> any knowledge that might help to prove the creed<lb/> by which <del>you</del> we swear equally grateful to the penitent?"<lb/>  I answered by opening the pages of the book which is our<lb/> sole guide.  First: That the world in which a loving<lb/> <del>Leader</del> Father has placed us <emph rend="underline">must not</emph> be looked upon with indif-<lb/>-ference, was told us by an undisputed authority, even by<lb/> the inspired son of Amoz.  "Thus has said the Lord, the<lb/> Creator of the heavens; He who is the God <del>who</del> that formed<lb/> the earth and made it, He that has established it, <emph rend="underline">not for nothing</emph> He created it,<lb/> to be inhabited He formed it" [Hebrew]<lb/> Are we the dwellers thereof to turn with contempt upon<lb/> what the Wisest Beneficence molded for man's enjoyment?--a terrestrial existence?<lb/>
            
<pb n="4"/>
            Must we declare it valueless, because we should believe<lb/> in another state perfectly spiritual?  To argue so would be like holding that a child may despise and<lb/> cast aside important tokens of his parents' affection,<lb/> because he expects that the future will bring him parental gifts<lb/> of rarer worth [Hebrew] we are taught<lb/> by the prophet.  Far be from us so obvious an ingratitude.  Not in vain, but for a definite be-<lb/>-nign purpose God brought forth the world we live in,<lb/> and all that can render existence pleasurable.  The<lb/> Rabbis who inculcate the doctrine of <del>an existence</del> life beyond<lb/> the grave with great frequency and emphasis do not say<lb/> that we are bound in a prison here below, but they compare<lb/> this world to the porch of a palace [Hebrew]<lb/> Mark it well: a the porch of a magnificent mansion is not a dismal fail, but a<lb/> <del>stately</del> wide and <del>ornamental</del> stately entrance way.  In that ante-<lb/>-chamber, as it were, we must fittingly prepare ourselves, so<lb/> that when the time arrives for being admitted into the<lb/> presence of the King, we shall be found deserving of<lb/> His royal <del>approval</del> <del>accep</del> welcome.  [Hebrew]<lb/>  They who fail to suitably arrange themselves<lb/> in a manner becoming the beneficiaries of the<lb/>
            
         <pb n="5"/>
            <del>the</del> Sovereign Lord, or to say it in plainer words, persons<lb/> who like a shuttlecock are plaid against continually by the<lb/> exactions of a material existence, tormented by their inca-<lb/>-pacity of resistance, may call the habitation in which the<lb/> Almighty put us, sadly probationary, not so men whose cra-<lb/>-vings are under control and who acknowledge a heavenly<lb/> hand that scatters blessings.  A Jew who makes his daily<lb/> devotions, praises <del>H</del> his Maker because of the luminaries<lb/> that gladden a created world [Hebrew]<lb/></p>
           <p> Now, as regard the instance of the homicide, casting his<lb/> burden on the deified being whom the church proclaims co-<lb/>-existent with the Omnipotent, and able to wash away sin,<lb/> I did at once confess to my inquiring visitor that my sym-<lb/>-pathies, are not with creatures possessed of intelligence who<lb/> leave governing reason behind to become slaves <del>of</del> to destructive<lb/> propensities.  The consolation which my religion offers<lb/> is not built upon a barren creed, but on fruitful deeds.<lb/>  At this stage of my conversation with the anxious youth,<lb/> who had called at my house, I laid my finger on the eight-<lb/>-eenth chapter of Ezekiel and read sentences which I will now<lb/> quote in part.  Says the Lord, "Behold, all the souls<lb/> are mine, as the soul of the father, so that of the son;<lb/>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            they are mine, the soul that sins that alone shall die."<lb/>...If a man be just, he exercises justice and righteous-<lb/>-ness....but he begets a dissolute son, who sheds blood...<lb/>...oppresses the poor and needy, is guilty of robbery......<lb/> gives out money upon usury; should he live?  He shall<lb/> not live.  He has done all those abominations, he shall<lb/> surely die; his blood shall be upon him.  Now, if <emph rend="underline">he</emph> begets<lb/> a son, who seeing all the sins which his father com-<lb/>-mitted, considers and does not the like of them.....<lb/> he shall not die for the iniquity of his father; he<lb/> shall surely live" [Hebrew].  Here<lb/> we are given in the clearest and most explicit <del>manner</del> language<lb/> the law of personal accountability, not to be shifted, nor<lb/> transferred to any being <del>supposed</del> either reputed as heavenly or in all<lb/> reality earthly.  The guilty ones themselves must suffer<lb/> for their offences--[Hebrew]  "The soul that sins,<lb/> <del>it</del> that alone shall die."  I looked and saw the face of my<lb/> visitor troubled.  He remembered the Christian who had<lb/> spoken of the <del>comforting healing</del> soothing balm applied to the stricken<lb/> conscience of the repentant; of the joyous feelings derived<lb/> from the dogma of forgiveness through a mediator, and<lb/> he interrogated me as to the end of a Jewish sinner.<lb/>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            Will he be lost for ever?  <del>No</del> Is there no expiation for his back-<lb/>-slidings?  Again the prophet in the river Chebar was<lb/> appealed to in order to tranquillize a disturbed mind.  We<lb/> illumined understanding of Ezekiel had read pity, grace,<lb/> love in the <del>ordinations</del> decrees of the Most High, and he inter-<lb/>-preted the Divine qualities luminously.  "If the wicked will<lb/> turn away from all his sins that he committed, and<lb/> keep all Thy statutes, and do that which is lawful and<lb/> right, in his righteousness that he has done, he shall<lb/> live.  All his transgressions which he committed, shall<lb/> not be remembered against him; by his righteousness<lb/> that he has done, he shall live."  Then <del>in</del> with an outburst of affect-<lb/>-ion for his people, the great Seer so addresses them.<lb/>  "Cast away from you all your transgressions and make<lb/> yourself a new heart and a new spirit.  Why will<lb/> you die, O house of Israel?  For, I have no pleasure in<lb/> the death of him who deserves to die, says the Lord<lb/> God, therefore turn back and live."  What <del>does</del> does then<lb/> purchase our redemption?  Not blood, but actions, not<lb/> the blind acceptance of a mind-perplexing doctrine,<lb/> but an unshaken resolve to reform, and cling to virtue.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>But suppose such a case as that brought forward by<lb/> the Christian interlocutor should happen to a Jew, would<lb/> that unfortunate offender, bent in contri<del>bu</del>tion, find no<lb/> healing to his lacerated soul?  Surely he would, if<lb/> sincerity draws forth tears of repentance [Hebrew]<lb/> [Hebrew]  The suffering of compunction, mental trials,<lb/> bodily chastisements have the power to cleanse away inequi-<lb/>-ties; such is the Rabbinical maxim, and the Talmud<lb/> is replete with <del>app</del> aphorisms which are a refreshing<lb/> dew to the mind withering at the memory of crimes in<lb/> the days that have gone, but and which have called for<lb/> sorrow and remorse.  In the place allotted to the<lb/> penitent, even the perfect righteous will not be given<lb/> room" [Hebrew] and again, penitence<lb/> is the supreme court the acquits the guilty [Hebrew]<lb/> Let none tremble who possess such supporting as-<lb/>-surances when about to cross over to the way of eternity,<lb/> but we must procure them early while we enjoy our full<lb/> faculties, while we have the capacity to do wrong<lb/> and will determinedly abstain to honor truth and glorify<lb/> the Eternal Lord.  So beautifully writes one<lb/> of our greatest ascetic philosophers in the beginning of the 12th century.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
           <p> O my soul, make thy provision ready, while<lb/> <del>full</del> power is given thee to gather it.  Say not<lb/> wait to morrow I shall prepare it, for thou knowest not<lb/> what a day <del>may</del> will bring forth, yesterday will never<lb/> <del>return</del> come again; the looked for tomorrow may <del>not</del> ne'er arrive, for like a <del>bu</del> bird<lb/> flying out of its nest, so man may suddenly<lb/> depart from his abode.  <del>And</del> That <del>he</del> the pious monitor proceeds long, concluding<lb/> with these comforting words.  My [?] seek the Lord thy Master,<lb/> lay hold of righteousness, put on <del>humility</del> meekness like a vesture thou<lb/> wilt rise aloft shining with undiminished bright-<lb/>-ness, <del>even</del> like the hen <del>going</del> that cometh forth in all its<lb/> might, singing the praises of the Most High God.<lb/>  May we all <del>that</del> so act, and receive God's par-<lb/>-don and God's blessings without end.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
