<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF10_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1893" source="" attested="yes">1893</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_1_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>An admonitory lecture<lb/>
                predicated in from Parashat Shemot<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Moses grew up and went<lb/> out to his brethren&#34;.  My hearers.  Without searching<lb/> into legends and tales&#44; excellent in their own way to<lb/> teach a moral&#44; I find that the scriptural text itself<lb/> unvarnished as we have received it&#59; very plainly but touchingly as it is even always set forth in historical narrative points<lb/> to the distinguishing quality which made Moses in from his earliest youth&#44;<lb/> a representative Hebrew.  That quality is&#44; a sympathetic nature.<lb/>  Not a sentimentality&#44; which becomes at times becomes a morbid sen&#45;<lb/>sibility&#44; powerless and inoperative&#44; but an active&#44; intelligent<lb/> fellowship with the lowly&#44; a perfect thorough identification with<lb/> the humblest of mankind&#44; aiming at their elevation.  I see this<lb/> trait more broadly unfolded in the character of the arch&#45;pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;phet than in that of any historical prominent men in our Bible Holy Writ&#59; more<lb/> <sic>developped</sic> than even among the disciples of the schools<lb/> which taught inspired ingenius to speak.  I gratefully admit it.  All who<lb/> were imbued with a divine spirit loved their people<lb/> and worked disinterestedly for its welfare.  Thus&#44; Samuel<lb/> tried his utmost to benefit Israel by gathering around<lb/> him devoted followers whom he trained as preachers of the word of God at Najoth in Rainah&#44; but still the<lb/> sturdy republican could ill disguise a sense of passing resent&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment&#44; of momentary estrangement&#44; when another was asked<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>to take the lead of the naturi.  Elijah&#44; clothed in a<lb/> course garment satisfied with a the scantiest<lb/> meal was fearless&#59; he faced a tyrant again and again in the vindication of the ill used maltreated<lb/> of right and for the sake of right he faced a tyrant again and again.  Yet a degree of leaven mixed in the nature of him the Tishbite<lb/> who declared that he alone had been lefts to serve the Lord<lb/> zealously.  Isaiah&#44; to reform his fallen brethren pleaded<lb/> for righteousness with impassioned eloquence&#44; but his soul<lb/> which revolted at sin&#44; drew from his lips a scathing<lb/> denunciation against those a community whom he likened to the inhabitants<lb/> of Sodom and Gomorrah.  Nor did the successors of the son<lb/> of Amoz remain entirely free from a sense of their supe&#45;<lb/>&#45;riority above the masses.  The bard seer of the florid style by<lb/> the river Chibar&#44; and the &#91;&#63;&#93; of my illusive vision he who beheld an all relieving humanizing vision Maresha of Judah&#59; Jere&#45;<lb/>&#45;miah in his plaintive language and Malachi in the his<lb/> warmth of his glowing enthusiasm for the Law&#59; all exhibited the some<lb/> human weakness of the bibles of the great men&#39;s foibles&#44; all evince a measure&#44; however small light&#44; of self&#45;assertion.<lb/>  Moses alone&#44; Moses the greatest&#44; because the best&#44; of<lb/> Scriptural characters&#44; placed himself on a par with the<lb/> lowly&#44; on a perfect level with the humblest&#44; and seeking their progress&#44; early showed and became<lb/> himself a truly representative Hebrew.  You have read it&#58;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;When Moses grew up&#44; he<lb/> went out to his brethren&#34;.  The son He was a youth<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>He was A youth who breathed a royal atmosphere he was. Who<lb/> can doubt but that Flattery was must have been the daily seasoning<lb/> of his food who can doubt that around him stood courtiers with approving winning&#44;<lb/> radiant smiles&#44; ready to obey at a nod&#44; at a look of the<lb/> princess&#39; adopted son&#63;  But I see&#33; that he has quitted the com&#45;<lb/>&#45;pany of parasites&#59; those surroundings of lackings&#44; to ward his<lb/> steps where sufferings were are endured.  Mark the words narrative<lb/> as they it stands in the original.  &#34;When Moses grew up he went<lb/> out to his brethren &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#34;.  It is not written &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> for it was an no act act of mere idle curiosity which had led him to the<lb/> spot in which a distinct race rigorously works was bent down&#44; while with with work of rigour&#59; but &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> He would look into effects the system of a grinding oppression.  He intently looked then&#44; was his sym&#45;<lb/>&#45;pathetic nature was stirred from its depths&#59; in contemplating injustice then his and revolted at compassionate heart revolted at<lb/> wrong.  Then the persecuted became his near allies&#44; the persecutors his personal<lb/> enemies.  Now my hearers&#58; To imagine that those who worked at labored in the brick<lb/> kiln were the equals in knowledge and social standing of<lb/> to the favorite of a king&#39;s daughter would be folly.  Few Scarcely any<lb/> could have had the opportunity to learn so extensively&#44; and fewer none&#44;<lb/> of any perhaps&#44; could have moved in&#45;so called&#45;high circles.  But all were<lb/> unjustly proscribed&#44; and all had were held up by one traditional belief which<lb/> held them up sufficiently to prevented the total debasement&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>as sought after by a crushing tyranny.  All remembered their Let us reflect a moment upon<lb/> descent from one a righteous lineage&#44; all awaited for the the alternative.  To obey nature&#39;s generous impulse<lb/> fulfilment of a divine promise and follow spare the destiny of the unhappy&#44; or abandon the latter<lb/> to their fate and enjoy a princely station.<lb/>  Say&#58; can any of us claim that he or she has been placed in offered<lb/> the same soul&#45;trying alternative&#63;  Can any of us contend to have occu&#45;<lb/>&#45;pied a rank so eminent as that of Moses&#44; and that<lb/> it became necessary on his or her part to make a great insofar immense sacrifice in so as to and <sic>comeing</sic><lb/> down and mingling with a people of very inferior in condi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion in life&#63;  Most <sic>Assuredly</sic> not&#44; and yet a sense of self&#45;importance&#44;<lb/> of overweening self&#45;esteem is robbing Israel of some&#44; who<lb/> might have worthily acted as our representative men and women.<lb/>  Some of us I&#44; among many had once fondly hoped looked for the growth of a genera&#45; youths<lb/> &#45;tion that who reaching maturity would have cast their lot with the lowly&#44;<lb/> and endeavoured to uplift them&#44; but little by little my<lb/> expectations in that direction are being cut off.  I will not not<lb/> call it cowardly&#44; but it is certainly it is not far from courageous in<lb/> the sons and daughters of Hebrew observant parents&#44; to be ashamed<lb/> of confessing their identity with the unpopular minor&#45;<lb/>&#45;ity&#44; and to deserting it because it does not <sic>weild</sic> the<lb/> social influence&#44; which the majority&#44; by reason of their its<lb/> numerical strength&#44; commands.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>What would have become of us&#59; what would have become<lb/> of civilization&#59; if Moses had deemed it too great a con&#45;<lb/>&#45;denscension to be drawn into contact with less instructed&#44;<lb/> less refined persons individuals&#44; if you wish so to term it&#44; than he himself was&#63;<lb/>  But you have been shown it.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  When the youth grew up&#44; he left behind<lb/> the blandishments of the worldly&#59; the adulation of sordid<lb/> mortals&#59;he tore tore himself from the allurements of<lb/> outward splendour&#44; to follow the inward prompting<lb/> of his sympathetic nature.  Sublime model of<lb/> fraternal affection&#33;  Matchless pattern of a yearning soul&#33;<lb/>  In early life Moses resolved to cling to his suffering proscribed brethren&#44;<lb/> his last days found him still devoted to their cause&#44; and<lb/> when the hour to depart from them struck&#44; he bid the tribes he had<lb/> lifted up from lowliness an eternal farewell with a blessing&#44;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Happy thou O Israel&#33; who is like unto thee&#44; a people<lb/> saved delivered by the Lord&#44; who is thy shield of thy help&#44; helping saving shield&#44; and<lb/> the thy victorious sword&#33;&#34; of thy excellency&#34;.  Oh that a spark of that<lb/> ardent intensity of love would kindle the hearts of all American Hebrews&#63;<lb/>  Our community at large&#44; and this congregation specially<lb/> would cease to lament suffer losses which are irretrievable.  For if<lb/> parents are summoned hence to heaven&#44; we may hope that their<lb/> children will fill up the vacancy gap&#44; but when the offspring<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>sever their connection with the Synagogue&#44; then the<lb/> void stares us in the face&#44; and draws from us all laments.<lb/>  But idle would be your the complaints of the faithful&#44; and useless my<lb/> speaking utterances&#44; were I solely to point out defections.  You parents who believingly love the One God you must prevent backslidings and I I<lb/> must improve every opportunity for in the discharge performance of<lb/> a sacred duty solemn duties must improve every opportunity to admonish.  I must entreat parents fathers and mothers to keep<lb/> double watch for the sake of the faith&#45;&#45;a watch<lb/> over their tongues&#44; lest they inadvertently drop words<lb/> poisoning the minds of their young ones against our<lb/> ancestral belief&#59; a watch at their doors&#44; lest these<lb/> remain wide open for the reception of non&#45;Israelites and<lb/> tight shut against the coheirs of the Sinaic covenant.<lb/>  And I must exhort my youthful brothers and sisters&#44;<lb/> whom my voice can reach&#44; to study&#44; when it is yet<lb/> time&#44; the <sic>woful</sic> consequences of rash acts.  The unhappy results personally as well as<lb/> religiously&#44; of exchanging the simplicity of a Jewish<lb/> home&#44; for the fashionableness of gentile residences.<lb/>  To study the subject most seriously&#44; so that ultimately they<lb/> may not ultimately have occasion to cry in the language of the old<lb/> moralist &#34;How could I have hated instruction&#44; and how could<lb/> my heart have despised correction&#63;&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>The sound of these plaintive words would ring in our<lb/> ears&#44; as they proceed from sad experience&#44; if shame did<lb/> not withhold them from the stranger.  Oh&#33;  May they<lb/> never issue from those the Israelites I now address.  Too many<lb/> that might have reflected lustre on Judaism have<lb/> enriched with their talents the domains of its adver&#45;<lb/>&#45;saries.  In some instances ambition goaded our the<lb/> people waverers on.  Thus in Germany&#44; when the avenues<lb/> to social and political preferments were inaccessible<lb/> to any who wl could not swear by the cross&#44; whole<lb/> families tried to reach their goal by the road that leads<lb/> to the Church.  And thus likewise alliances which<lb/> proved most inauspicious to our interests were contracted.<lb/>  At times vulgar pride thinned our ranks.  They who<lb/> by a stroke of fortune had been made to bask in<lb/> the sun&#45;shine of aristocracy&#44; would not move allow<lb/> that their sons and daughters to any more to acknowledge their identity<lb/> with a race looked upon with disfavor.  A thirst after<lb/> earthly honors&#44; and unmanliness conspired in to deprive<lb/> us of men and women who&#44; we had reasonably<lb/> hoped&#44; might have become representative He&#45;<lb/>&#45;brews.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>But America is not inimical to our race people&#44; if we ourselves<lb/> are not its enemies.  America will learn to appre&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciate the excellencies of our religion and the homely virtues<lb/> of our people race&#44; when those who can enhance their<lb/> prestige thereof shall cleave to both.  Are you ready&#44;<lb/> my aged brethren&#44; to assume the control of your household<lb/> and by precept and example hold your children in the<lb/> faith&#63;  Are you willing&#44; my young brethren&#44; to rule<lb/> your feelings and seek happiness in the ancestral fold&#63;<lb/>  Holy Writ has placed before you this day a most matchless<lb/> perfect model.  Moses reared in a palace&#44; seeking<lb/> the association companionship of the proscribed.  Moses preferring the<lb/> iron chains of the persecuted to the golden sceptre of<lb/> the persecutors.  You are not raised quite so eminently&#44;<lb/> but neither are you asked to make too great a sacrifice.<lb/>  What is demanded of you can be performed with ease&#44; if<lb/> that which is earthly is eliminated from your nature in early<lb/> life&#44; and the genius of spirituality is infused breathed into it.  Remember<lb/> that &#34;better it is to be modest among the humble ones&#44; than to share<lb/> spoil with the proud&#59;&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93; and it is also written&#44; that &#34;he who reflects<lb/> upon the matter will find good&#44; and whosoever trusts in the Lord&#44; is shall finally be happy.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
