<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF9_11</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1890-04" source="" attested="yes">April 1891</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_11_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_11_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_11_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_11_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_11_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_11_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_11_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_11_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_11_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_11_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_11_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_11_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>105<lb/></p>
            
            <p>April&#47;91<lb/></p>
            <p>About the controversy in London<lb/>
                regarding the proposed demolition<lb/>
                of the Bevis Marks Synagogue<lb/></p>
            
            <p>This lecture was lengthened considerably and improved upon<lb/>
                in the course of its delivery.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  The late agitation among our coreligio&#45;<lb/>&#45;nists of London&#44; has excited my interest considerably.<lb/>  The dispute has been set at rest&#44; for a time at least&#44; but<lb/> it presents certain features deserving of attention our reflection.<lb/>  Thus&#44; by way of elucidation&#44; it involves a question<lb/> of some moment from a talmudical Rabbinical stand point.<lb/>  That question I asked myself about thirty one years<lb/> ago&#44; without daring to propound it to others&#44; for&#44; I<lb/> felt sure of a solution adverse to my views.  Is it<lb/> at all permissible to demolish a Synagogue&#44; or to<lb/> dispose of it for any worldly use&#63;  Well guided<lb/> by Talmudical rules&#44; the answer must be in the negative&#44;<lb/> for the Rabbis Sages insist that a place once devoted to God&#39;s<lb/> worship must remain&#44; inasmuch as a degree of<lb/> sanctity clings always to it.  So strong are the feelings<lb/> against surrendering a spot hallowed to Divine ser&#45;<lb/>&#45;vice and particularly against suffering it to become<lb/> a stall or a store&#44; that even after the Roman<lb/> ghetto disappeared by royal order&#44; our people could<lb/> not be induced to tear down the dingy buildings<lb/> in which prayers had been publicly said.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>In that instance&#44; doubtless&#44; other sentiments mingled<lb/> with the religious&#44; as based on talmudical ground.<lb/>  The Synagogues at Rome have a history dating<lb/> many centuries back.  Who can tell&#44; but Sages travel&#45;<lb/>&#45;ling to the seven hilled city&#44; during the period of Roman<lb/> dominion in Judea&#44; may have made their devo&#45;<lb/>&#45;tions there.  Then&#44; again&#44; countless are the<lb/> memories clustering round those worn out spots&#44;<lb/> even if the memorials are apt to draw forth tears<lb/> of sorrow.  To the young&#44; born and reared under<lb/> a constitutional monarchy&#44; better ventilated&#44; more<lb/> imposing edifices in newer localities&#44; would possess<lb/> a readier attraction&#44; but to their parents every stone<lb/> in the Ghetto&#45;synagogues has the charm of an anti&#45;<lb/>&#45;quity fraught with stirring events.  Indeed&#44; now<lb/> that various communities in the peninsula&#44; where<lb/> Judaism <sic>plaid</sic> so important a part&#44; are ransacked<lb/>&#45;ing their ancient archives&#44; and producing separate<lb/> accounts of this thrilling past&#44; a full history of<lb/> the Hebrew Congregation in the capital&#44; would<lb/> prove of exceeding value.  The<lb/> Synagogue at Bevis Marks in London cannot<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>look back on very many centuries.  Still&#44; it<lb/> is dear to our English fellow&#45;believers&#44; and justly<lb/> so in more than one respect.  During three centuries<lb/> and a half&#44; no Jewish step congregation dared touch pray on English soil.<lb/>  Expelled fro ma land that promised commercial<lb/> advantages&#44; a strong wish for readmission had<lb/> long been felt by the exiles tribe of sore wandering foot and weary<lb/> breast.  But not till their champion arose in<lb/> Holland&#44; could they hope for a realization of their<lb/> cravings.  Menasseh Ben Israel&#44; who deserved so<lb/> well of his brethren for literary services rendered&#44; had<lb/> warmly espoused their cause.  He summoned cou&#45;<lb/>&#45;rage to personally petition Cromwell&#44; that he<lb/> might allow his coreligionists to take up their<lb/> homes again in Great Britain.  Some had hazarded<lb/> entering it pending negotiations in 1656&#44; to cele&#45;<lb/>&#45;brate the great festival of Passover&#44; but difficult<lb/> as it is to reconcile conflicting reports&#44; it seems&#44;<lb/> at all events&#44; that the house of worship&#44; whose<lb/> retention or demolition has given rise to a heated controversy&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>was not erected till 1699.  Be that as it may&#44;<lb/> it awakens splendid reminiscences&#45;&#45;the noble<lb/> efforts of the eminent scholar and Jewish advocate<lb/> from Amsterdam&#44; and the first step&#44; however<lb/> feeble&#44; toward the attainment of the height reached<lb/> by the Jews of England.  No doubt&#44; the original<lb/> settlers&#44; who reared the synagogue in Bevis<lb/> Marks&#44; were Portuguese Marranos&#44; who feigned<lb/> Catholicism&#44; to escape the inquisition&#44; till they<lb/> could safely land in Holland&#44; and acknowledge them&#45;<lb/>&#45;selves openly descendants of Abraham and believers<lb/> in the Lord and in Moses His servant.  But in<lb/> the acrimonious dispute which has recently been<lb/> waged&#44; Ashkenazim&#44; so called by way of a senseless<lb/> distinction&#44; took a prominent part&#44; notably editors<lb/> of Jewish periodicals.  They united in crying&#44; &#34;Shame<lb/> upon an attempt to vandalism.&#34;  Why tear down<lb/> a monument making privileges long denied and<lb/> finally granted and the brave efforts of a celebrated<lb/> Jew&#63;  But the party of Sephardim&#44; who combat&#45;<lb/>&#45;ted the scheme of <sic>levelling</sic> to the earth the historic<lb/> building&#44; alleged additional motives.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>The voice of Sasportas&#44; Abendana&#44; Niete&#44; Meldola.<lb/>  All more or less regarded for their high learning and<lb/> piety&#44; had sounded within the walls of that mi&#45;<lb/>&#45;nor sanctuary.  Ought it to be destroyed&#63;  But<lb/> in all truth&#44; the locality has deteriorated too greatly.<lb/>  It was already objectionable in 1845&#44; when I<lb/> resided there&#44; as Hebrew Master in the institution of<lb/> Orphans.  Since then it has grown much worse&#44;<lb/> according to all accounts&#44; and the Hebrew population<lb/> has largely removed to distances&#44; disabling it<lb/> from attending worship in the most olden part<lb/> par of the city.  Consequently&#44; the &#34;demolitionists&#44;&#34;<lb/> as those who favored felling down the venerable<lb/> structure have been ironically called&#44; were not<lb/> wantonly inconsiderate.  They lamented the ever<lb/> decreasing number of worshippers&#44; and proposed<lb/> to build in a spot&#44; where the number of Hebrew<lb/> inhabitants warranted it.  I confess that<lb/> I myself would have deprecated the victory of<lb/> the demolitionists.  Not that I apprehended that<lb/> the noble edifice would have been knocked down<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>by the hammer of the auctioneer.  In London&#44;<lb/> the courts in which the Lord God of Israel was<lb/> congregationally extolled&#44; will never be given out over<lb/> to an unholy usage.  The ground might be<lb/> sold&#59; the edifice which had stood on it&#44; would<lb/> not be disposed of for a purpose conflicting<lb/> with its former sanctity.  Still&#44; I admit it&#44;<lb/> my objection would proceed from sentiment&#44; and&#44;<lb/> say what you will&#44; cold reasoning will not<lb/> silence it.  I surmise that the Haham&#45;<lb/>as the Ecclesiastical chief of the Sephardim<lb/> is titled&#45;&#45;who has been made the butt of sar&#45;<lb/>&#45;casm&#44; was not exactly in sympathy with<lb/> either the Londoners of the Ashkenazic ritual&#44; or<lb/> of the Sephardim&#44; whom he serves.  For he is<lb/> comparatively a new comer&#44; born and raised in<lb/> Roumania.  Dr Gaster argued correctly in the<lb/> abstract from the stand which he took.  A<lb/> deserted synagogue cannot reflect honor upon<lb/> the living nor upon the dead.  So long as the<lb/> Montefiore&#39;s&#44; the Lousadas&#44; the SAmudas&#44; the Lindos&#44;<lb/> the Almosninos visited the Bevis Marks Synagogue<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>the memory of Menasseh Ben Israel was<lb/> revered and the object of his efforts practi&#45;<lb/>&#45;cally carried out&#44; but when time wrought<lb/> soon a change as to compel the hiring of men<lb/> to form the requisite quorum for holding<lb/> public worship&#44; the determined opposition<lb/> against a removal&#44; and the personal ill will<lb/> it created&#44; even not defensible.  Possibly&#44;<lb/> the Rabbi&#39;s language may have been more<lb/> forcible than polished&#44; yet&#44; to me the offensive<lb/> adjectives applied to him&#44; appear <sic>inaccessable</sic>.<lb/>  I have not the least acquaintance with<lb/> the reverend gentleman.  When he was first<lb/> installed&#44; an estimable lady friend of mine&#44;<lb/> knowing that I harbor no prejudice against<lb/> any of my coreligionists from whatever part of<lb/> the globe they hail&#44; wrote to me to the wonder&#45;<lb/>ful departure.&#45;&#45;an askenaz&#44; as Haham<lb/> of Sephardim&#33;  But if our London brethren<lb/> would have preferred an Englishman&#44; and I<lb/> &#91;&#63;&#93; their feelings&#44; they ought to have made<lb/> timely prevision for the choice.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>When fifty or sixty thousand Israelites&#44; in<lb/> in a land conspicuous for commerce and letters&#44;<lb/> cannot raise a number of spiritual leaders<lb/> to guide them&#44; they ought not to slight the<lb/> foreigner&#44; who may hold views not altogether<lb/> in accord with those entertained by the natives.<lb/>  Since Menasseh Ben Israel called forth the his<lb/> best endeavours&#44; the Bevis Marks Synagogue<lb/> has not had an ecclesiastical chief to the manner<lb/> born.  All scholars heard&#44; either at the sacred<lb/> desk or in the pulpit&#44; came from abroad.<lb/>  Now Holland&#44; anon Italy&#44; supplied the demand.<lb/>  At present&#44; when unhappily those two countries<lb/> have also a dearth of students for the Rabbinate&#44;<lb/> lands on the Danube or Volga must be applied<lb/> to.  Let us&#44; Jews of America&#44; who&#44; like<lb/> our brethren in England&#44; hold on to traditional Ju&#45;<lb/>&#45;daism&#44; take the lesson to heart.  Let us smile<lb/> approvingly on the endeavours to train in our<lb/> midst those who will lead hereafter our<lb/> Congregations aright&#44; men familiar with<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>the vernacular language&#44; perfectly identified<lb/> with the habits and aspirations of the freedom<lb/> loving in the Republic&#44; attached to the insti&#45;<lb/>&#45;tutions of the State&#44; and above all&#44; let us promote<lb/> by our material and moral encouragement<lb/> the cultivation of a religious literature&#44; conducive<lb/> to a life of holiness.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
