<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF1_6</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_6_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_6_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_6_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_6_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_6_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_6_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_6_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_6_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_6_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_6_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_6_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_6_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>On the origin of the Kaddish<lb/>
                in connection with the celebration of a Bar Mitzvah<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>The origin of the Kaddish&#44; or&#44; rather of the practice that the children<lb/> of deceased Jewish parents should recite a prayer before<lb/> the Congregation&#44; is quite singular.  Founded upon a legend&#44;<lb/> it has&#44; in common with other Rabbinical tales&#44; the appear&#45;<lb/>&#45;ance of a superstition.  At the first blush&#44; reason rejects it<lb/> it&#59; the sensible believer shrinks from it&#44; as lowering the<lb/> character of the Mosaic religion.  But if an intelligent<lb/> Israelite will take pains&#44; and exercise his reflective powers&#44;<lb/> he will be fully repaid by discovering under a coarse look&#44;<lb/> a vast deal which is exceedingly fine.  Let me relate<lb/> the story.<lb/></p>
            <p>Rabbi Akiba&#45;&#45;as illustrious for his learning&#44; as he is re&#45;<lb/>&#45;nowned for his checkered history and his tragical end&#45;&#45;was is said to have been<lb/> going walking through a burial ground.  Suddenly&#44; a person passed<lb/> by him&#44; carrying a heavy load of wood&#44; and running with<lb/> all speed.  The Sage moved to pity&#44; motioned to the<lb/> man to stop&#44; and calling aloud said cried.  &#34;Friend&#44; why must<lb/> you work so very hard&#63;  Are you perchance a slave&#44; and<lb/> your master compels you to do it&#63;  Tell it to me&#44; and I will<lb/> try to buy your freedom.  Or&#44; has destitution brought you<lb/> to this&#63;  Let me relieve you in a manner&#44; that you shall<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>not need labor any more so painfully.&#34;  The<lb/> man answered&#58; &#34;Kind Sir&#44; do not detain me&#44; for I dare<lb/> not rest a second.  I am from the land of the dead&#44; and my<lb/> punishment is to gather wood and cast it into a fire&#44; which<lb/> will burn me.&#34;  Akiba startled&#44; inquired what sins had<lb/> forced out a sentence so severe&#59; and the other replied<lb/> &#34;I was a public assessor&#44; and I let the rich go off easily&#44;<lb/> but I used to grind down the face of the poor.  Besides&#44; my<lb/> general conduct was immoral.&#34;  The Rabbi then anxiously asked.<lb/>  &#34;Have you heard in the place of your chastisement&#44; that any<lb/> atonement can yet be made for your crimes&#63;&#34;  Oh&#33; do<lb/> not keep me with back to answer your inquiries&#44; that my fate may not<lb/> become worse&#44;&#34; interrupted the apparition.  &#34;But..yes&#44; I over&#45;<lb/>&#45;heard that if I had a son&#44; and he who who could rise before the con&#45;<lb/>&#45;gregation and say&#58; &#39;Bless ye the Eternal Lord&#44; who is worthy<lb/> to be blessed&#44;&#39; I might be released.&#34;  The Rabbi having<lb/> hastily informed himself about the name of the deceased person<lb/> of his wife and of his former place of residence&#44; <sic>travelled</sic><lb/> far in search of the surviving relations.  He reached<lb/> the city&#44; where they lived&#44; and speaking with some of the in&#45;<lb/>&#45;habitants&#44; he endeavoured to get the character of the wife<lb/> of the deceased.  He learnt that so reckless she was&#44; as to<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>bring up her only child in total ignorance of religion.<lb/>  Akiba still persevered in his object&#44; and succeeded in<lb/> having the lad intrusted to his care.  Without losing<lb/> any time&#44; he began to teach him the Hebrew Alphabet.<lb/>  For forty days the teacher fasted and prayed that his<lb/> pupil might make rapid progress.  A voice was heard<lb/> from above to exclaim&#44; &#34;Why so much concern about a<lb/> child of such a parasitage&#63;&#34;  But the Rabbi did not<lb/> relax in his exertions.  Soon the boy was able to read<lb/> grace after meal&#44; and the daily service.  Then then<lb/> instructor took him to the Synagogue&#44; and in the<lb/> presence of the assembled multitude he was made to read<lb/> the prayers and say with a loud voice &#34;Bless ye the Eternal<lb/> Lord&#44; who is worthy to be blessed.&#34;  In the night Akiba<lb/> had a comforting dream.  The man&#44; whose spectre he<lb/> had seen in the burial ground&#44; stood before him and<lb/> said. &#34;May your soul delight in the garden of Eden&#44; as<lb/> mine has your through your goodness been delivered from <lb/>the valley of Hinnom.  Akiba then cried &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;O Lord&#33;  Thy name shall be praised for<lb/> ever.  O Lord&#39; thy memorial&#44; O Lord&#33; on every generation&#33;&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Now&#58; my brethren&#59; taken literally the narrative is an<lb/> absurdity.  But stripped of its rough cover&#44; it re&#45;<lb/>&#45;veals impartings deserving of our deep consideration.<lb/>  I will point out some&#44; and you shall judge whether my<lb/> mind has dived into the purport of the legend.<lb/></p>
            <p>R. Akiba believed in both the attributes of justice and mercy.<lb/>  He held that we ourselves supply the instruments of our<lb/> torment hereafter&#59; namely&#44; that the recollection of our<lb/> misdeeds becomes&#44; as it were&#44; the fuel with which we keep<lb/> consuming remorse ablaze&#59; and that is divine justice.<lb/>  But he held also that the Almighty regards piety with<lb/> favor&#44; and that&#44; when manifested in the conduct of those<lb/> who represent our name and our household&#44; it may<lb/> be received as a propitiatory offering&#44; the savory smell<lb/> of which will prove a restorative to the spirit of the<lb/> departed&#59; and that is divine mercy.  Consistently<lb/> with that idea&#44; the same Rabbi wrote in the Mishna&#44;<lb/> that the sufferings of sinners will not last beyond<lb/> the term of twelve months&#44; and our legend purposes<lb/> to tell&#44; that during that period&#44; the devotional practices<lb/> of the children during that period will have a softening influence on the<lb/> souls of their dead deceased parents.  Hence&#44; the custom of<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>the Kaddish&#44;adopted as a substitute for longer<lb/> prayers&#44; which not every one may be capable of reciting ac&#45;<lb/>&#45;ceptably before the Congregation.  When the Chaldaic was<lb/> the vernacular&#44; it was composed in that language&#44; and<lb/> it served&#44; I think&#44; as an invocation&#44; which the Sages&#44; habi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tually uttered at the conclusion of their daily studies.  I<lb/> In the course of time its use became extended&#44; and its<lb/> wording amplified&#44; specially by Spanish Jews.  and The<lb/> Kaddish was made to in after years to constituted an important essential part of the ritual.<lb/>  But the lesson which I mainly wished to unfold<lb/> from the story cited&#44; is more important than that which I<lb/> have hitherto explained.  It sets forth a principle as<lb/> broad as nature&#44; as comprehensive as humanity.  It teaches<lb/> the <sic>perfectability</sic> of man.  None are born so predisposed<lb/> to evil&#44; that a correct education cannot exercise a control&#45;<lb/>&#45;ling force.  Now ought ever to be cast aside as a<lb/> prospective injury to society&#44; because by reason of a vile extraction.<lb/>  The far&#45;reaching eye of Akiba beheld sin and its<lb/> retribution&#45;&#45;and that of oppressing the poor&#44; he recognizes<lb/> as most hateful to God&#45;&#45;&#44; but his benevolent heart<lb/> felt that to cut short the way of irreligion&#44; and open wide<lb/> a path for morality&#44; as in the power of well&#45;meaning and intelligent<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>beings&#44; and he would not permit hindrances to stop him in the<lb/> pursuit of righteous endeavours.  Our preceptor of old considered<lb/> it a greater merit and a more enduring advantage<lb/> to the world&#44; to rescue from rain a young creature brought<lb/> to its verge by circumstances of birth and surroundings&#44; then<lb/> to watch over the preservation of what is not exposed<lb/> to immediate danger in the body potic.  We leave<lb/> the ninety nine lambs&#59; they are safe in the fold&#44; and<lb/> we go in search of the stray one&#44; to bring it back.<lb/>  Such must have been the sentiments&#44; actuating that<lb/> champion of our faith&#44;and when his efforts met with success&#44; Akiba thanked the Lord because His heavenly<lb/> name would thereby be practised&#59; His memory from gene&#45;<lb/>&#45;raton to generation.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            <p>Pity that the Rabbi has such few disciples among<lb/> men who pride themselves on the title he bore.  Schools<lb/> and Synagogues form&#44; as a general rule&#44; so many aristo&#45;<lb/>&#45;cracies.  A privileged class&#45;&#45;that which pays&#45;&#45;engages<lb/> the attention of the pastor.  Outsiders&#44; so called&#44; are very<lb/> little&#44; if at all&#44; looked after.  But Israel&#39;s houses of learning&#44;<lb/> and houses of prayer&#44; are the common property of all<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>bound by the law of Sinai&#44; and all ought to be<lb/> drawn thereto by every means within reach of the<lb/> minister.  It cannot&#44; naturally&#44; be expected&#44; where<lb/> a large and wide spread population exists&#44; that the<lb/> servant of God can go and find the children of his<lb/> people&#44; that who mostly need his spiritual care.  Indeed<lb/> were he to try it&#44; he would often meet wit ha rebuke<lb/> as being unduly meddlesome and officious&#44; but whenever<lb/> the opportunity presents itself for bringing his influence<lb/> to bear upon youths&#44; who otherwise might be lost to<lb/> Judaism&#44; he ought to remember the glorious lesson con&#45;<lb/>&#45;veyed in Rabbi Akiba&#39;s legend&#44; and act accordingly.<lb/>  I rejoice&#44; my brethren&#44; that the unrestrictive views of this<lb/> congregation have occasionally afforded me that op&#45;<lb/>&#45;portunity.  For any lad of whatever lineage&#44; in<lb/> whatever condition of life&#44; can stand here&#44; and acknow&#45;<lb/>&#45;ledge himself a member of the ancient faith&#44; and be<lb/> as such addressed and exhorted to follow virtue.  Thus&#44; our<lb/> Bar Mitzva is unknown to my hearers&#59; he was entirely<lb/> unknown to me&#59; but I casually learnt that circumstances<lb/> kept him far from the race to which he belongs&#44; and form<lb/> the belief of which is he is the legitimate coheir.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>I approached him&#44; instructed him in the benedictions<lb/> expressive of our choice as witnesses of God&#39;s truths&#44; and<lb/> though by parental confession&#44; he will not be allowed<lb/> the privilege of <sic>worshipping</sic> in our midst but very<lb/> rarely&#44; yet&#44; I resolved that he should receive the im&#45;<lb/>pression&#44; which the occasion must needs create.<lb/>  I brought him before the see oracle of God our Lord&#44; hoping<lb/> that despite drawbacks&#44; this day may cast the<lb/> seeds productive of goodly fruits to the lad and to<lb/> the community in which he lives.<lb/></p>
            <p>&#40;Here follows an address to the Bar Mitzva&#44; in which he<lb/> is encouraged to rise by his own exertions&#44; quoting the history<lb/> of B. Akiba as an illustration of what can be accomplished<lb/> by the power of a well&#45;directed Will.&#41;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
