<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF11_4</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1896-01" source="" attested="yes">1896</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_4_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_4_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_4_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_4_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_4_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_4_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_4_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_4_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_4_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_4_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_4_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_4_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>11</p>
            
            <p>96<lb/></p>
            <p>About the scheme of Christianizing<lb/>
                the Constitution of the U. S.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>At longer or shorter intervals attempts are being<lb/> made to Christianize the constitution of the United<lb/> States of America.  Since my residence here&#44; I could<lb/> reckon scores of time&#44; when fanaticism broke loose and<lb/> attacked the Republic of the North&#44; as a godless union&#59; as detestably altruistic&#44;<lb/> for not having given a conspicuous foremost place in its Magna<lb/> Charta to the man of Nazareth as a the alleged the regent of the all&#45;ruling Divinity.<lb/>  The very circumstance which manifests the profound wisdom<lb/> of the founders creators of the freest nation on earth&#44; has been declared<lb/> a heinous sin.  It matters nothing to the<lb/> clergy&#44; that probably more churches exist and<lb/> flourish under the stars and stripes than in countries<lb/> boasting&#44; in their charters&#44; of great perfect loyalty to the<lb/> Church.  The indisputable fact that in<lb/> every stage of the history of this government&#44; its<lb/> temporal authorities have acknowledged the Providence<lb/> and protection of the Universal Father&#44; has no weight<lb/> on the minds of most ministers of the gospel.<lb/>  No&#59; they must read in capital letters in the pages<lb/> of the statute book this confession&#58; &#34;We&#44; a Christian<lb/> people&#44; acknowledge the trinity as the supremest<lb/> power in earth the universe&#34;.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>There came lately in my possession a pamphlet<lb/> containing some letters of George Washington and<lb/> others among the immortal Sages of the revolution.<lb/>  In that correspondence he that runs may read the<lb/> sentiments of deep rooted belief in the Almighty<lb/> cherished by men at the helm of the ship of state.<lb/>  Washington&#44; writing to answering a Mr Levi Sheftal&#44; who<lb/> had sent tendered the first President of the Republic con&#45;<lb/>&#45;gratulations on behalf of the Savannah Jews&#44; said&#58;<lb/> &#34;May the same wonder&#45;working Deity&#44; who long<lb/> since delivered the Hebrews from their Egyptian<lb/> oppressors&#59; planted them in a promised land&#45;&#45;<lb/>whose providential agency has lately been conspi&#45;<lb/>&#45;cuous in establishing these United States as an<lb/> independent nation&#45;&#45;may He still continue to<lb/> water them with the dews of heaven and make<lb/> the inhabitants of every denomination parti&#45;<lb/>&#45;cipate in the temporal and spiritual blessings<lb/> of that people whose God is the Eternal&#34;.  To<lb/> the Jews of Newport&#44; the great hero and statesman&#44;<lb/> with unmistakable proofs of his appreciation of the<lb/> broad righteous God approving principles upon which this government was<lb/> based founded&#44; writes&#58; &#34;The citizens of the United States of<lb/> America have a right to applaud themselves&#44; for<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>having given to mankind examples of an enlarged<lb/> and liberal policy&#45;&#45;a policy worthy of imitation.<lb/>  All alike possess liberty of conscience and immuni&#45;<lb/>&#45;ties of citizenship.  It is now no more a tole&#45;<lb/>&#45;ration spoken of&#44; as if it were the indulgence of a<lb/> class of people&#44; that another may enjoy the<lb/> exercise of their inherent rights.  For&#44; happily<lb/> the government of the United States&#44; which gives<lb/> to bigotry no factions&#44; to persecution no assistance&#44;<lb/> requires only that they who live under its protect&#45;<lb/>&#45;ion should demean themselves as good citizens in<lb/> giving it on all occasions their effectual support.&#34;<lb/>  To our own Mickv&#232; Israel&#44; Washington emphasized<lb/> his confession of faith&#44; in the following terms&#58; &#34;The<lb/> power and goodness of the Almighty&#44; so strongly<lb/> manifested in the events of the late glorious revo&#45;<lb/>&#45;lution&#44; and His kind interposition in our behalf&#44; have<lb/> been no less visible in the establishment of our<lb/> present equal government.  In war He directed<lb/> the sword and in peace He has ruled in our<lb/> councils&#34;.  But such admissions of an absolute<lb/> reliance in the Sovereign Ruler of the world&#44; count<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>nothing with in the opinion of the white cravatted&#44; who cry down<lb/> the constitution because it fails to declare that<lb/> Washington and his coworkers intended the asylum of the oppressed<lb/> which they built up&#44; to be solely and exclusively Christian.<lb/>  One of the strongest staunchest advocates of a denominational<lb/> constitution&#44; warming up in his subject before the<lb/> Judiciary Committee in the House of Representatives&#44;<lb/> said last week that &#34;the opponents of a Christian<lb/> government&#44; would abolish prayers in the churches&#59;<lb/> the Bible in the schools&#59; chaplains in the<lb/> army and navy.&#34;  No&#44; not quite so.  Churches&#44;<lb/> like Synagogues&#44; are for prayers.  The Bible<lb/> in secular schools&#44; if restricted to sayings teachings and maxims<lb/> unsectarian in character&#44; might not be objectionable&#44;<lb/> though unnecessary.  Years ago when my oldest<lb/> daughter attended the Norman School&#44; I argued<lb/> with Mr Fetter&#44; the then principal in order to show<lb/> the injustice done by the constant preference given<lb/> to the recital of new testament&#44; while the old offers much<lb/> that is not doctrinal&#44; as for instance several of the psalms and the<lb/> entire book of Proverbs.  With regard to chaplains<lb/> in the army and navy&#44; their presence is of a very doubt&#45;<lb/>&#45;ful usefulness&#59; their absence could not possibly be felt&#44;<lb/> missed&#44; where our defenders on sea nad land comprise men<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>of various denominations.  Bearing in mind the<lb/> woeful effects of occasioned by Christianized governments&#44; their<lb/> total secularization&#44; can may indeed be regarded as an<lb/> incalculable blessing.  Thomas Jefferson&#44; who framed<lb/> the declaration of Independence&#44; understood that well&#59;<lb/> for&#44; in a communication to Mordecai M. Noah&#44; a<lb/> prominent Israelite&#44; he wrote&#58; &#34;Your sect by its suf&#45;<lb/>&#45;fering has furnished a remarkable proof of the uni&#45;<lb/>&#45;versal spirit of religious intolerance inherent in every<lb/> sect&#44; disclaimed by all while feeble&#44; and practised<lb/> by all when in power.  Our laws have applied the<lb/> only antidote to this vice&#44; protecting our religious&#44; as<lb/> they do our civil rights&#44; by putting all on an equal<lb/> footing.  But more remains to be done&#44; for although<lb/> we are free by the law&#44; we are not so in practice.<lb/>  Public opinion erects itself into an inquisition&#44;<lb/> and exercises its office with as much fanaticism<lb/> as fanned by an auto de f&#232;&#34;.  And John Adams&#44; ad&#45;<lb/>&#45;dressing the same public spirited Mordecai M. Noah&#44; gave<lb/> utterance to these thoughts&#58; &#34;I wish that your people may<lb/> be admitted to all privileges of citizens in every country of<lb/> the world.  This country has done much.  I wish it may<lb/> do more and annul every narrow idea in religion&#44; in<lb/> government and commerce&#34;.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Brethren.  May the day never arrive dawn when Christianity&#44;<lb/> or any creed shall will have received a public recognition from<lb/> the Constitution of the United States.  For&#44; notwithstanding<lb/> the clause that congress shall make no law respect&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing an establishment of religion&#44; or prohibiting the<lb/> exercise thereof&#44; still&#44; we Jews suffer ostracism<lb/> through local or state laws.  Some years ago&#44; when<lb/> street cars were forbidden to run in Philadelphia on the first day of the week&#44; in deference to by<lb/> the urgent solicitations of would be saints&#44; who did<lb/> not scruple using their own conveyance and hordes on that<lb/> same day&#44; a chief justice the courts decided that Sunday is not<lb/> the Sabbath.  Nevertheless continual arrests have been made<lb/> and are being made in this city almost within a stone&#39;s throw of the Indpendence Hall of Independence&#44; among<lb/> our brethren who as disturbers of public peace for working in their own shops on premises&#44; on<lb/> a Sunday&#44; because as they observe the Sabbath. as disturbers<lb/> of public peace.  Complaints are brought to me&#44; request&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing to take some action&#44; but I realize the inutility of<lb/> it&#59; because if the <sic>the</sic> seventh day <sic>Babtists</sic>&#45;&#45;a large denomination&#45;&#45;cannot<lb/> redress remove a clear wrong injustice&#44; we few cannot hope to rectify<lb/> it.  Injustice Wrong against us&#44; is not easily set righted.  What<lb/> I only could accomplish in Philadelphia was to prevent<lb/> our sons and daughters receiving punishment for<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>non attendance at schools on high holidays&#44; or&#44; as<lb/> expressed in school language&#44; from being demoted&#44;<lb/> a circumstance telling operating working disadvantageously about regarding their<lb/> average at the end of the term.  What stronger proof<lb/> of the arbitrariness which the majority exercises&#44; can<lb/> Philadelphia exhibits than in the case of an insti&#45;<lb/>&#45;tution for the training of fatherless boys in secular<lb/> learning and mechanical skill&#63;  Stephen Girard&#44;<lb/> may have been imbued with the atheistic ideas of<lb/> the France of his time.  Be it so or not&#44; he was so<lb/> determinedly opposed to denominational religions&#44; that<lb/> in bequeathing to their city the magnificent college&#44; which<lb/> bears his name&#44; with the endowment of two million<lb/> dollars&#44; anxious be resolved to prevents the inmates from being<lb/> influenced by Clergymen.  he Accordingly the man left positive orders that<lb/> none of them latter be ever allowed to enter the institution.<lb/>  The thought of imparting Christian doctrines&#44; of<lb/> holding Christian services&#44; of building a Christian chapel<lb/> in those premises&#44; was abhorrent to the testator.  Yet&#44; his<lb/> will is set altogether aside&#44; and I have had obtained in the past&#44;<lb/> the personal knowledge of a Jewish lad admitted there&#44; being tampered with by one of the employe&#233;s to effect<lb/> a so called conversion.  If Christianity acts so clandestinely on<lb/> the Jesuitical plea&#44; that the end justifies the means&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>what could we anticipate&#44; if Congress should have ever de&#45;<lb/>&#45;clared to the world that the cross is the victorious ensign<lb/> of the Republic of the North&#59; that by it every tongue<lb/> must swear&#44; that to it all must pay homage&#63;  But<lb/> that ominous event will not occur.  Too many are the<lb/> interests at stake&#44; clashing among innumerable seats&#44;<lb/> abounding holding together and  jealous of the upper hand gained by any in this land of equality&#44; professedly so at all wants&#44; if<lb/> not in the strictest sense of the word.  That cala&#45;<lb/>&#45;mity&#45;&#45;I may predict&#45;&#45;will not overtake us&#44; but we Jews&#44; without com&#45;<lb/>&#45;mitting ourselves by unwise agitations&#44; must always<lb/> side with the liberals&#44; recognizing that cant is not<lb/> religion&#44; professions are not actions.  At a meeting<lb/> of Philadelphia Episcopalians&#44; ostensibly in the interest<lb/> of Russian Jews&#44; outraged and murdered by the Russian<lb/> government&#44; a clergyman remarked that those who<lb/> do not adhere to the fourth of the majority&#44; must<lb/> expect perse elections.  But that homicidal theory is not<lb/> applied now to the Armenians under a Mohammedan<lb/> government&#44; often provoked incited by the <sic>medlesomeness</sic> of American<lb/> missionaries.  Of course&#44; Turks cannot be placed under in the<lb/> same category as with Christians.  To rebel against them Moslems rule<lb/> is virtue.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>Understand&#44; I lament what happens in the East&#44;<lb/> even if only a part of what have journals here and<lb/> abroad have reported&#44; did come to pass to have be true&#59; and I com&#45;<lb/>&#45;mend the philanthropy of Miss Barton and her mer&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciful coworkers to mitigate the sufferings of human<lb/> creatures&#59; but I cannot help contrasting the uni&#45;<lb/>&#45;versal sympathy now displaced in every city&#44; in every<lb/> town towards the Armenians&#44; and the culpable indif&#45;<lb/>&#45;ference when millions of Jews&#44; were under the lash<lb/> of the brutal Cossacks and then equally brutal<lb/> emperor.  I must fervently pray that in this<lb/> land of the free and home of the brave&#44; the endea&#45;<lb/>&#45;vours of churchmen may prove illusory&#44; shadowy&#44;<lb/> unsubstantial&#44; like specters fleeing phantoms.  In the language of<lb/> Isaiah I exclaim &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;Take counsel together&#44; it will come<lb/> to naught&#44; speak the word&#44; but it will avail<lb/> nothing&#44; for God&#39;s with m us.&#34;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
