<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF2_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_2_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>For Noah<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>From time to time an attempt is being made<lb/> by local authorities to hinder Israelites from following<lb/> the traditional manner of slaughtering their cattle.<lb/>  It may be remembered that owing to the action of some<lb/> of the Swiss cantons&#44; a great deal of controversy was<lb/> carried on ten or twelve years ago in European papers.<lb/>  Societies for the prevention of cruelty to animals began<lb/> then to spread fast&#44; and&#44; as usual&#44; Jews became the<lb/> butt of public censure&#44; because they refused to conform<lb/> with an ordinance which would have made their meats<lb/> unfit for use.  Very recently the same question&#44; embaras&#45;<lb/>&#45;sing to our people&#44; came up in England&#44; where at Man&#45;<lb/>&#45;chester the principal operator&#44; or the Congregationally ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;pointed Shochet and his assistants&#44; were brought before<lb/> court on the charge of inhumanity.  Fortunately&#44; Jewish<lb/> rules resting on Rabbinical ground can stand the brunt of<lb/> the battle. Put to a fiery ordeal&#44; they again came off again<lb/> uninjured.  Science helped them through.  Science&#44;<lb/> called to give an impartial judgment vindicated a<lb/> practice which&#44; notwithstanding the prevailing defection&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>many still hold in reverence.  Physicians who are<lb/> best acquainted with the subject&#44; stated that the least<lb/> painful process&#44; because accompanied with immediate<lb/> fainting and the consequent loss of sensation&#44; and also<lb/> the quickest&#44; because the stroke needs not be repeated&#44;<lb/> is that which the Hebrews adopted in killing their sheep<lb/> and oxen.  Truly&#44; all the humane must admire a<lb/> perseverance aiming to deliver dumb creatures from ill&#45;<lb/>treatment&#59; all whose inborn feelings of goodness are<lb/> not blunted&#44; will argue that since mankind found it<lb/> necessary to feed upon the flesh of beasts&#44; that want<lb/> ought to be gratified with as much regard for the suf&#45;<lb/>&#45;fering of animals&#44; as it is possible under the circumstance<lb/> to exercise.  And to that end have the oral laws of the<lb/> Jews&#44; in connection of with the question at issue been partly<lb/> established.  I have qualified my assertion by saying<lb/> partly&#44; for a well understood reason.  The removing of<lb/> the blood is one and perhaps the leading cause of the<lb/> Shechitab ordinance.  It is foreign to my purpose&#44;<lb/> now to discuss its moral merits phys <sic>psycologically</sic>&#44; but<lb/> I may without digressing too much&#44; mention an<lb/> instance which proved its sanitary tendency.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>The Italian government having discovered that the<lb/> different manners of preserving meats for any length of<lb/> time&#44; to feed with a large moving army&#44; had been a failure&#44;<lb/> proposed that scientists should study how to remedy as<lb/> the evil and report.  Among the competitors to the honor<lb/> of having discovered an effective plan&#44; was the Israelite<lb/> I. Segr&#233;&#44; a physician of refute in the government<lb/> service.  He showed to the satisfaction of even General<lb/> Garibaldi&#44; that the only means to prevent the serious incon&#45;<lb/>&#45;venience spoken of was to slaughter animals in the Jewish<lb/> old fashion.  His arguments I am unable to reproduce&#44;<lb/> through my ignorance of the technical terms employed&#44; but I learnt that<lb/> he pointed to the continuance of the blood in the meat&#44; as<lb/> the main agent of putrefaction.  Of course that coreligionist of ours<lb/> took then merely science as a standard&#44; yet on that very<lb/> account&#44; the triumph is greater.  For we see man&#39;s high<lb/> talents compelled to pay homage to an institution of our<lb/> religion&#44; as two of its essential characters&#44; the sanitary and<lb/> the humanitarian.  Both are recognized therein&#44; and<lb/> both ought to be kept in mind&#44; particularly by those&#44; for<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>whom they have been lad laid down.  That any<lb/> person entrusted with the operation of slaughtering animals<lb/> should neglect to attend the humanitarian rules&#44; with<lb/> due consideration&#44; is a wrong which ought not to be<lb/> overlooked.  And I&#44; on hearing complaints on that score&#44;<lb/> from a member of the society for the prevention of cruelty<lb/> to animals&#44; endeavoured to guard against the repetition<lb/> of the same wrong.  But that the traditional laws them&#45;<lb/>&#45;selves be charged with inhumanity appears strangely<lb/> inconsistent in a people who have derived knowledge<lb/> from the ancient scriptures.  For&#44; clearly clearly&#44;<lb/> our books were the first to circulate sentiments of<lb/> tender compassion towards the brutal creation.  That<lb/> fact is so self&#45;evident&#44; that none need ransack a<lb/> Hebrew&#45;library to discover it.  A glance over the few<lb/> pages read this morning will suffice.<lb/></p>
            <p>To renew the world&#44; after a generation full of violence had<lb/> been swept away&#44; a universal flood came.  And<lb/> here I wish&#44; in passing&#44; to say that the Mosaic account<lb/> is borne out not simply by the vague notions which some&#45;<lb/>how reached the heathens&#44; and took the form of fables&#44; like<lb/> that of Darculion&#91;&#63;&#93; in Greece&#44; and Tohi in China&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>but by the discoveries made by of the late George Smith<lb/> in Assyria&#44; where he found impressed upon bricks&#44;<lb/> which may have had resisted for thirty centuries the erasing hand of time&#44; a history<lb/> of the deluge agreeing in the main with that recorded<lb/> in Genesis.  There we have read this morning&#44; that the<lb/> first commandment Noah received in settling his foot<lb/> again upon dry land was one&#44; condemnatory of a practice<lb/> which may have been rife among those&#44; whom the flood<lb/> destroyed&#44; and of which we still hear among those savages.<lb/>  He was prohibited eating flesh cut from a live animal.<lb/>  And whatever the shortcomings of Israelites may be&#44; I may<lb/> venture to assert that they are not guilty of a violation<lb/> of that Noachete precept.  They do not wantonly so torment<lb/> a creature.  What a contrast with the refined bar&#45;<lb/>&#45;barity of men&#44; who&#44; boasting of a creed instilling softer<lb/> feelings that Judaism does&#44; subject fowls to a most<lb/> cruel treatment to gratify their depraved appetites&#33;<lb/>  I allude to the famous&#44; or rather infamous dish ob&#45;<lb/>&#45;tained by making the liver of a goose swell to an<lb/> unnatural size.  And I can feel yet a thrill through<lb/> my whole being&#44; as I recollect&#44; what I often heard in the<lb/> days of my boyhood.  The piercing cries of animals stabbed<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>to death with a heated steel to prevent the loss of<lb/> blood&#44; considered a delicacy when thickened.<lb/></p>
            <p>No Israelite instructed by their religion that the Lord&#39;s<lb/> tender mercies are towards all his works&#44; never needed<lb/> a society to check them in deeds of ferocity against<lb/> the brute creation.  Exquisitely delicate is the feeling<lb/> which our Bible and its interpreters tried to foster.<lb/>  Thus&#44; we are shown in the section of today&#44; the hand<lb/> of Noah stretched out of the window of the ark&#44; to bring<lb/> in the dove which could not find rest where water<lb/> still remained.  Thus&#44; also we are told that the thoughts<lb/> of all the inmates of the ark&#44; alike of man and beast&#44;<lb/> came up to the mind of God&#44; when he ordered the winds<lb/> to dry the ground.  And to signify to us that animals<lb/> form an important link in nature&#44; and as such ought<lb/> they to be used with kindly consideration&#44; the Almighty<lb/> said that the covenant of which the rainbow would<lb/> be an eternal remembrance&#44; was made with Noah<lb/> and his descendants and with the fowl of the heaven&#44; and<lb/> the beast of the field&#44; with every creature which He<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>has given the breath of life.  The Talmudists on<lb/> their part bestow abundant praise on the deluvian patriarch&#44;<lb/> for the care he took during twelve months of different<lb/> animals&#44; which were to preserve their species.  They<lb/> write that the thoughtfulness of Noah in giving each<lb/> what was needful&#59; his unremitting attention to prevent<lb/> suffering made even the wild tame and affectionate and won for him the name of wise&#44; in addition to<lb/> that of righteous.  And in one of their significant para&#45;<lb/>&#45;bles&#44; these sages of Israel teach us that the cravings<lb/> of animals are heeded above&#44; and fulfilled here below.<lb/>  &#34;Why did the dove pluck off an alive leaf and not a<lb/> fruit or flower&#44;&#34; ask they&#44; and the answer is&#44; &#34;because<lb/> that creature petitioned its Maker that the food received<lb/> might come from His hand though bitter rather than<lb/> from man&#44; though its taste be sweet.  Our religion<lb/> my fellow believers&#44; inculcates principles by heeding which<lb/> we must prove ourselves humane&#44; and considerate&#44; and<lb/> demonstrating that not the fear of being arraigned before a human<lb/> court deters us from ill&#45;using the lower creation&#44; but the love<lb/> of that faith which has infused certain us goodness and<lb/> compassion.  May those virtues be brightly illustrated<lb/> in our dealings with all creatures of the earth.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
