<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF25_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff25_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff25_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff25_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff25_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff25_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff25_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff25_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff25_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff25_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff25_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff25_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff25_1_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>On the sweating system<lb/>
                for Parasha Behar Sina&#239;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>In the first of the two sections of the Law read this<lb/> Sabbath&#45;&#45;a section which suggested the motto engraved upon<lb/> the historic bell so dear to American hearts viz&#58; &#34;Proclaim liberty<lb/> throughout the land unto all the inhabitants thereof&#34;&#44;<lb/> in that section we read a word variously translated.  Noticing the<lb/> scriptural sentences in which it occasionally occurs&#44; I argue that it means a<lb/> caution to every Jew to deal fairly and squarely with<lb/> all human beings&#44; but most scrupulously so with persons<lb/> in a lowly or dependent condition.  Jeremiah&#44; and oftener<lb/> than he Ezekiel&#44; made use of that term&#44; to warn us<lb/> against the heinous sin of taking advantage of the<lb/> weak powerless and poverty stricken &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; I would therefore render thus&#58; &#34;Do not wrong one another&#34;;<lb/> &#34;Do not overreach one another.&#34;  Do not consider it<lb/> harmless to make thy brother pay dearly for your thy<lb/> having prevented his complete ruin.  The Rabbis&#44; how&#45;<lb/>&#45;ever&#44; teach that &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; or wrong doing&#44; can be practised<lb/> in our talk not less than in our traffic.  And they illus&#45;<lb/>&#45;trate their lesson in the following manner.  Suppose<lb/> that a neighbor of mine had committed a sin&#44; but of which he<lb/> has repented&#44; I dare not under any circumstance say to him&#58; &#34;Take a Look back on of<lb/> your past&#34;.  Again&#59; imagine that my neighbor was<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>born a heathen&#44; but that the has studied and learned<lb/> to appreciate the true faith I dare not say to him at any time&#58;<lb/> &#34;Remember your origin.&#34;  And So likewise if my neighbor is suffer&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing domestic afflictions&#44; or temporal losses&#44; I dare not<lb/> say to him set myself up as judge and say to him &#34;Had<lb/> you been always upright&#44; misfortune would not have befallen<lb/> you.&#34;  While on the subject&#44; an eminent Babylonian Sage inquired so put once<lb/> of the following question to a Palestinian colleague&#58; &#34;What do you guard most<lb/> carefully against in your country&#63;&#34; and the answer<lb/> was &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Against bleaching a person&#39;s countenance.&#34;<lb/>  For&#44; he that shames another&#44; forfeits his hereafter.  Brother Israelites.<lb/>  I have quoted Scriptures and Talmud to show that both<lb/> impart a morality not surpassed by religions or systems of ethics which<lb/> claim superiority to ours.  In these days of inhuman sweat&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing shops&#44; when the cry is loud &#38; general and unhappily well founded&#45;&#45;that Jews oppress<lb/> Jews&#44; it is necessary to let all know&#44; beyond peradventure&#44;<lb/> that Hebrew prophets and Sages are a unit in demanding the<lb/> strictest probity&#59; aye nay&#59; the exercise of the most exquisite<lb/> charity towards each other&#45;&#45;a charity which does not con&#45;<lb/>&#45;sist in the distribution of alms to prevent starvation&#44; but in sparing the feelings<lb/> of the very least among God&#39;s creatures.  It is impe&#45;<lb/>&#45;rative&#44; I say to make the whole world understand that he is a Jew<lb/> only by the accident of birth&#44; and not in reality&#44; who treads<lb/> under foot the principles which lie at the basis of<lb/> Judaism.  &#34;That shalt love thy neighbor as thyself&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>&#34;Thou shalt love the stranger.&#34;  &#34;Ye shall not steal&#44; ye &#34;The wages of a hired servant shall<lb/> shall not lie.&#34; not abide with thee all night until the morning.  &#34;Ye shall not vex nor oppress the<lb/> poor&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93; Oppressive words&#44; the Talmudists<lb/> call what occasions heart&#45;burnings&#44; without exposing<lb/> the offender to the charge of having &#91;&#63;&#93; perpetrated a<lb/> crime punishable by the courts.  You may not be indicted for the commission of the crime&#44; therefore we read &#91;Hebrew&#93;   But the Talmudists<lb/> who wrote &#34;Fear thy God&#44;&#34; He knows whether you have hurt a man&#39;s feelings that to wound one&#39;s feelings so cruelly inflict&#44; a wound&#44; that to shame any any<lb/> one is to forfeit a hereafter&#44; would have hurled ana&#45;<lb/>&#45;themas against a Jew who feathers his nest with<lb/> that which he has pitilessly plucked off from the hard<lb/> working&#45;operative.  Faithful representatives of<lb/> their predecessors&#44; our inspired prophets&#44; the Talmud&#45;<lb/>&#45;ists&#44; commenting on a passage in Deuteronomy&#44; which<lb/> commands that enjoins upon the employer shall to give the employ&#39;e<lb/> his daily wages&#44; because his soul craves for it &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; those preceptors of ours they say&#58; &#34;Whosoever defrauds wrongs the laborer<lb/> retaining delaying or denying his due&#44; will receive a chastisement&#44;<lb/> as if he had taken a poor man&#39;s life.  During<lb/> the strike in the summer of 1890&#44; I was given<lb/> ocular proofs that when the unfortunate&#44; unjustly<lb/> treated&#44; cries to heaven&#44; the just God in heaven does<lb/> avenge the cause of the ill&#45;used.  It was<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>at that trying season that I was then forcibly reminded of the denunciation in the<lb/> Haftarah of this Sabbath&#58; &#34;As the partridge that<lb/> gathers hatches young which she has not brought forth&#44;<lb/> &#40;&#45;&#45;namely they will part with it&#45;&#45;&#41; so is he getti that gets riches&#44; but not by night.  In the<lb/> middle of his days he shall leave them&#44; and in his<lb/> end he shall be vile&#34;.  I recalled then also the impre&#45;<lb/>&#45;cation of our shepherd seer who so in his righteous indignation exclaimed&#58; Woe unto<lb/> them who lie upon bedstands of ivory&#44; and stretch themselves<lb/> upon their couches&#44; who eat of the best...drink wine in<lb/> bowls&#44; annoint themselves with the costliest oint&#45;<lb/>&#45;ments&#44; but feel no pain for the affliction of brethren.&#34;<lb/>  Jeremiah doomed to weep over national disasters&#44; be&#45;<lb/>&#45;gotten by fraud&#44; faithlessness&#44; and falsehood&#44; addres&#45;<lb/>&#45;sing the wicked successor son of good Josiah who aspired to the throne spoke thus one upbraided him the ambitious<lb/> &#34;Woe unto him that builds his house by unrighteousness<lb/> and his chambers by injustice&#44; that uses his neigh&#45;<lb/>&#45;bor&#39;s services without wages and gives him not<lb/> his hire&#59; who says &#34;I will build myself a wide<lb/> house and spacious chambers and who designs the<lb/> windows and puts up a cedars ceiling and paints<lb/> it with vermillion&#63;  Shalt thou reign&#44; because thou<lb/> strivest to <sic>excell</sic> in choice buildings&#63;  Behold&#44; thy<lb/> father ate and drank&#44; but he executed justice and<lb/> righteousness&#44; then was it well with him.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>He judged the cause of the poor and needy&#44; then<lb/> was it well.  Yea&#59; that is to know Me&#44; says the<lb/> Lord.&#34;  Not with the boldness which God&#39;s inspiration tends&#44; did I address some in 1890&#44; who<lb/> lived in palatial mansions surrounded by objects en&#45;<lb/>&#45;gendering luxurious ease rich individuals wealthy men but who still and but begrudge the scanty<lb/> loaf ate by men&#44; women and children who herded to&#45;<lb/>&#45;gether in rooms&#44; which hapless brethren could not enter at noon<lb/> time except at the light of a tapir&#44; not boldly but beseechingly for &#91;&#63;&#93; yet at times I failed in voice to no purpose.  Who will No wonder<lb/> that periodical strikes break out&#63;  A thousand pities<lb/> it is that those who stretch themselves on their couch&#44;<lb/> are not made to change situation with fellow beings&#44;<lb/> who lie on straw&#44; or on the bare floor.  For by the<lb/> confession of a heartless employer I derived the blood&#45;curdling<lb/> knowledge that eight cents for a dozen of children&#39;s knee&#45;<lb/>pants were paid a poor woman.  What great wrong&#44;<lb/> except to murder her&#63;  My pleading for the sake<lb/> of the sufferers may even have been regarded as meddlesome&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness.  What business has a &#91;&#63;&#93; Hazan and lecturer<lb/> with worldly affairs&#63;  Let him keep to his trade. attend to his profession.  His duty is to pray and<lb/> explain Jewish creeds.  May the day never dawn&#44;<lb/> when the disciples of prophets and sages&#44; to whose keeping<lb/> practical religion has been entrusted&#44; shall be muzzled&#44;<lb/> that they may not denounce social iniquities.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Meanwhile However&#44; let us be glad that rejoice over the act of our state Legis&#45;<lb/>&#45;lature has enacted according to which&#45;&#45;as reported&#45;&#45;a law which will regulate the<lb/> employment and provide for the safety and interest of persons em&#45;<lb/>&#45;ployed.  May the appointed inspectors and their deputies prove<lb/> incorruptible beyond the reach of the unprincipled mer&#45; in business<lb/> &#45;chants and politics&#59; men may they become public servants determined to deliver the oppressed from the<lb/> hand of their oppressors.  I experienced a melancholy<lb/> satisfaction a few days ago in reading that not all<lb/> who enrich themselves with the earnings robbed from<lb/> the working people&#44; are Jews.  If that statement is<lb/> correct&#44; the request I received from a brother that <sic>If</sic> all<lb/> my colleagues in the pulpit issue a petition to Philadel&#45;<lb/>&#45;phia merchants of the Jewish persuasion&#44; to deal fairly and squarely with their em&#45;<lb/>&#45;ploye&#39;s has become was unnecessary.  It was reported has been asserted in<lb/> the daily papers that an equitable arrangement has<lb/> been entered into between the wage in winners and their<lb/> bosses&#59; that Russian Jews will not be ground down<lb/> by their coreligionists.  May it be so and I respond<lb/> &#34;Amen&#34; most heartily for the honor of our faith&#44; and<lb/> the vindication of righteousness.  The lament comes<lb/> now from other quarters.  Italians and Germans&#45;&#45;it is said&#45;&#45;are<lb/> still compelled forced to work in sweating shops under<lb/> very most distressful hardship conditions.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>The evil is not any the less grievous&#44; because the<lb/> sufferers are born in a belief different from ours.<lb/>  The voice of nature&#44; which is the voice of God&#44; demands<lb/> that we yearn with compassion towards every creature<lb/> bent under bu the burden of oppression.  Edom<lb/> was not Israel&#44; nevertheless yet Amos reproaches<lb/> it because it had cast off all pity.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> But few of us stop to consider that in a measure<lb/> we are responsible for the aggravate of that the existing evil&#44;<lb/> that we&#44; unwittingly perhaps&#44; transgress the commandment in the section<lb/> of this sabbath &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Do not wrong one another&#34;.  Some well meaning<lb/> women&#44; complain that their sisters&#39; vanity compels<lb/> the wanton killing of innocent birds&#44; wherewith to<lb/> bedeck their headgears.  But a much greater wrong it<lb/> is to look for g bargains in our wearing apparel&#44;<lb/> whose cheapness may be the life blood of creatures&#44;<lb/> sickened in unventilated hovels&#44; blinded by the mid night&#39;s<lb/> lamp which may bring on the morrow the bread<lb/> to allay hunger.  Instead of theorizing in econo&#45;<lb/>&#45;mics&#44; let us give a wide scope to the senti&#45;<lb/>&#45;ments of humanity implanted in our breasts by<lb/> the Universal God.  That is religion&#44; that<lb/> is Judaism exemplified&#44; bea faithfully illustrated.<lb/></p> 
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>When enticed by greed to follow crooked<lb/> ways with a view to attain selfish ends&#44; let us be restrained by recalling to<lb/> memory the comforting sentences promise of Jeremiah in<lb/> our Haftarah&#58; &#34;Blessed is the man that trusts<lb/> in the Lord&#44; the Lord will be his sustaining<lb/> hope.  He shall be like a tree planted by the<lb/> water&#44; whose roots extend spread forth near a stream.  It does<lb/> not feel the drought heat when it comes&#44; the leaves thereof<lb/> remain green&#44; it does not fear the year of drought&#59;<lb/> it never ceases from producing fruit.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
