<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF4_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_1_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_1_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_1_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_1_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_1_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Post&#45;biblical lecture<lb/>
                21<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  As the season is fast approaching&#44; in<lb/> which I shall suspend my weekly lectures for a time&#44; and<lb/> will speak from this pulpit only when emergencies<lb/> arise&#44; I wish to stop at such a period of the post&#45;<lb/>biblical series&#44; that I have given at intervals&#44; as will en&#45;<lb/>&#45;able me to resume it hereafter with ease.<lb/></p>
            <p>It will be remembered that I began by tracing the his&#45;<lb/>&#45;tory of our people during the Babylonian captivity&#44;<lb/> and then proceeded to narrate the return of the exiles to the promised land&#44;<lb/> and the difficulties they met in the rebuilding of the Temple&#44;<lb/> through the jealousy of neighboring tribes.  I described<lb/> the final reconstruction of the Sanctuary&#59; the respect<lb/> paid to it by Persian rulers&#59; the comin of Alexander<lb/> the great to Palestine and the division after his death of the vast em&#45;<lb/>pire he founded&#44; leaving Judea to the supervision of<lb/> Laomedon.  I dwelt at some length on the domi&#45; rule<lb/> &#45;nion domination of the Ptolemies&#59; on that of the Syro&#45;Grecian<lb/> dynasty&#44; and on the revolutionary war under the Maccabees.<lb/>  I described portrayed the patriotism of the latter&#44; Mattathias and his five gallant sons&#44; and the unfortu&#45;<lb/>&#45;nate conflict between John Hyrcanus I son of Simon the<lb/> Asmonean&#44; and the Pharisees&#44; and showed also the dire consequences<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>of that rupture down to the time&#44; in which<lb/> Hyrcanus II became a more pliant tool in the hand of<lb/> Antipater&#44; the insidious crafty Idumean.<lb/></p>
            <p>To day my lecture will cover an important period in<lb/> the life of Herod I&#44; the cunning usurper of other men&#39;s power.<lb/></p>
            <p>Julius Caesar had fallen under the daggers of conspirators&#44;<lb/> in the senate chamber at Rome&#44; and Cassius who<lb/> joined in the conspiracy because&#44; forsooth&#33; &#34;Caesar was<lb/> ambitious&#44;&#34; took advantage of the unnatural death of<lb/> that&#44; undoubtedly most illustrious&#44; citizen of the republic&#44;<lb/> to raise an army and vast means in Syria and its vi&#45;<lb/>&#45;cinity.  Antipater and Herod&#44; always ready to<lb/> bow before the rising son&#44; sought the favor of the suc&#45;<lb/>&#45;cessful tribune&#44; and this one demanded as a pledge of<lb/> regard nothing less than 700 talents&#44; or about 700&#44;000<lb/> dollars.  The request was not very modest&#44; but<lb/> to refuse it was would have been to sharpen the all&#45;tearing claws of<lb/> the Roman eagle.  Accordingly&#44; tax gatherers were<lb/> selected to have the amount raised at a given stated time.<lb/>  Herod brought his quota first of all&#44; and gained<lb/> thereby the good will of the unambitious Cassius&#44;<lb/> who&#44; it is said&#44; to promised to make him soon absolute king.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Malichus&#44; one of the appointed collectors&#44; could not&#44;<lb/> or perhaps would not&#44; grind drain the people&#39;s coffers.  As he failed<lb/> to remit the sum promptly&#44; Cassius seized several<lb/> cities&#44; and sold their inhabitants to slavery.  Malichus<lb/> himself would have paid with his life for his tardiness&#44;<lb/> if Hyrcanus&#44; who was his friend&#44; had not turned away<lb/> Roman wealth with Jewish gold.  He drew out of<lb/> his own private coffers treasury one hundred talents&#44; and sent<lb/> them to Cassius with his compliments.  But Ma&#45;<lb/>&#45;lichus looked with well&#45;founded suspicion apprehensions on the pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;ceedings of the Idumean family&#59; on the unscrupulousness<lb/> with which they fleeced ground down all classes of the community<lb/> to ingratiate themselves with the tyrannizing stranger.<lb/>  When Cassius left Palestine to push his conquests further and<lb/> <sic>ammass</sic> more gold&#44; Malichus plotted to put Antipater<lb/> out of the way.  In reality&#44; no positive evidence<lb/> of such an intention exists&#44; th but it is generally<lb/> agreed that Malichus made excited suspicions&#44; which he<lb/> allayed by strong protestations of good faith&#44; and that<lb/> he and Antipater having dined together in company with Hyr&#45;<lb/>&#45;canus&#44; Antipater was suddenly taken ill and died.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>In the course of these short sketchy lectures&#44; enough has<lb/> been said to show in its true light the character of the<lb/> Idumean chief converted to Judaism.  Knowing<lb/> that Antipater was the sole primary cause of the bitter quarrel between<lb/> the two Asmonean brothers&#45;&#45;Hyrcanus and Aristobulus&#59;<lb/> knowing that he alone principally occasioned bloodshed among con&#45;<lb/>&#45;tending parties&#44; and the virtual surrendering of Judea<lb/> to the Roman power under Pompey&#59; knowing that<lb/> he was the main instigator of the heartless and de&#45;<lb/>&#45;fiant conduct of his son Herod&#44; it is painful and<lb/> humiliating to hear a Jewish historian bestow a eu&#45;<lb/>&#45;logy on Antipater in these terms&#58; &#34;Thus died a man<lb/> who had distinguished himself for piety and justice<lb/> and the love of country.&#34;  Josephus besides contradicting<lb/> his own self&#44; who had previously called Antipater &#34;a seditious man&#44;&#34;<lb/> insulted his religion and people&#44; when he penned the<lb/> encomium of the father of Herod.  But that is<lb/> not the only nor the worst offense of which our post&#45;<lb/>biblical historian became guilty.  We shall discover detect<lb/> more blemishes in the life of the very learned&#44; but the<lb/> very servile writer&#44; who basked in the sun&#45;shine<lb/> of rulers and princes.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Herod feigned to believe Malichus in his assurances declarations<lb/> of innocence&#44; but fox&#45;like he watched for the favorable<lb/> opportunity&#44; when he could take revenge.  The occasion<lb/> soon presented itself.  Hyrcanus&#44; accompanied by Ma&#45;<lb/>&#45;lichus and Herod had gone to Laudicea in Phrygia to<lb/> do reverence to Cassius&#44; who had seized captured that city.<lb/>  Herod had notified informed Cassius by letter of the death of<lb/> Antipater&#44; accusing Malichus of treason.  The Roman<lb/> tribune&#44; who had stabbed his benefactor Caesar&#44; had<lb/> no conscientious scruples about ordering some of his officers<lb/> to kill Malicus&#44; as he was on his way to attend a ban&#45;<lb/>&#45;quet artfully prepared by Herod.  Hyrcanus&#44; who<lb/> witnessed the murder&#44; fainted with fright.  When he<lb/> came to and was told that Cassius had ordered<lb/> the deed&#44; the powerless dotard had to approve of and praise<lb/> that which his soul detested.  But no<lb/> sooner had Cassius left Syria to join Brutus and<lb/> fight Octavious their common rival&#44; than Judea<lb/> took up arms against the Romans at Jerusalem.<lb/>  Antigonus&#44; the younger son of Aristobulus II&#44; and nephew<lb/> of Hyrcanus&#44; who had been living under the protection of<lb/> the prince of Chaleis&#44; availed himself of the prevailing spirit of discontent discontent<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>to raise an army among the national party&#44; who<lb/> hated a foreign yoke.  But Herod was equal to<lb/> the emergency.  He fought Antigonus&#44; defeated him&#44; and<lb/> drove him and his allies out of Judea.  He then entered<lb/> the capital&#44; like a triumphant hero to be wreathed<lb/> and garlanded by the representative of the race which<lb/> he was bent to destroy crush.  Hyrcanus gave Herod<lb/> a great royal ovation&#44; and promised him as a wife the<lb/> beautiful but unhappy Marianne&#44; daughter of his<lb/> nephew Alexander&#44; whom Pompey had beheaded&#44; and<lb/> of his only daughter Alexandra.  We are not told<lb/> whether the Idumean divorced the first wife he had<lb/> married among the women of his people&#44; and who had<lb/> born him a son.  But before the wedding<lb/> which would was to blend the blood of the Idumean with that<lb/> of the Maccabean&#44; could take place&#44; stirring events<lb/> rapidly succeeded each other.  Cassius had<lb/> committed suicide at Phillipi in Macedonia&#44; and Mark<lb/> Antony assumed authority in the East.  Herod could<lb/> not foresee the consequences of that sudden change of<lb/> fortune.  Might not Antony turn against the former friend<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>of Cassius and favor the claim s of Antigonus&#44; the<lb/> only survivor of the Asmoneans&#44; who displayed a<lb/> valiant spirit&#63;  But Herod had been a very<lb/> apt scholar under paternal tuition.  He had learnt from<lb/> Antipater the influence effect of gold with upon the Romans&#44; and<lb/> he dexterously employed its influences.  No one<lb/> needed money more than the dissolute Antony&#44; and no<lb/> one was more ready to uphold profitable tyranny than<lb/> the unprincipled Antony.  Herod&#39;s rich gifts<lb/> possessed an eloquence which made all the remon&#45;<lb/>&#45;strances of his opponents fall listless upon the ear.<lb/>  A deputation of Jews who came to complain before<lb/> Antony of the depsotism of Herod and Phasael&#44; were not<lb/> allowed even to speak.  Shortly after another deup&#45;<lb/>&#45;tation of leading citizens&#44; who succeeded in bringing charges against the<lb/> two usurping brothers&#44; would have seen some of the<lb/> most outspoken put to instant death&#44; if Herod him&#45;<lb/>&#45;self to avoid seditions&#44; had not interposed in their behalf.  More<lb/> lately another and still larger deputation&#44; who insisted<lb/> upon being heard&#44; were fallen set upon by Roman soldiers<lb/> and inhumanly slaughtered.  Thus the Idumeans mount&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed high on the corpses of the Judeans&#44; who tried in vain<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>to shake off a foreign hateful yoke.  Thus the insidious<lb/> policy of Antipater&#44; in seeking Rome as a prop to<lb/> his house&#44; fastened ever tighter the bands of that yoke.<lb/>  But Mark Antony who was to have been to Herod<lb/> a tower of strength&#44; forgot friends and foes in the arms<lb/> of the luxurious and wanton Cleopatra&#44; queen of Egypt.<lb/>  Then the Syrians weary of the made oppression of him<lb/> who styled himself &#34;imperartor&#34; <sic>profitted</sic> of his depraved<lb/> lassitude to encourage the invasion of a new power.<lb/>  The Parthians&#44; whose dominions lay in Western Asia&#44; were<lb/> anxious to thrust back to the Tiber the ever encroaching power of Rome.<lb/>  They could shoot the arrow with a deadly aim and break<lb/> the inimical lance at a blow.  They came in large num&#45;<lb/>&#45;bers and spread terror among the legions of the dread<lb/> republic.  Antigonus the Asmonean&#44; thought<lb/> he also could now help in weakening Rome and break&#45;<lb/>ing down the support of Herod.  Before the latter and<lb/> his brother Phasael could assume the offensive prepare for the defensive&#44; Anti&#45;<lb/>&#45;gonus had marched upon Jerusalem.  Blood flowed<lb/> like rivers streams&#44; but neither party gained the victory.<lb/>  Meanwhile the feast of Pentecost arrived&#44; and the vast<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>concourse of people who came to celebrate it&#44; mingling<lb/> in the scuffles according to their political proclivities&#44; made<lb/> the slaughter greater.  At length&#44; Antigonus called in<lb/> the Parthian general&#44; ostensibly as an umpire&#44; but really<lb/> to entrap Hyrcanus and the two Idumean bothers.<lb/>  Herod whose keen penetration enabled him to see<lb/> throught that fraud&#44; left Jerusalem stealthily by night.<lb/>  Denied a place of safety temporary refuge in Syria and in Arabia&#44; he<lb/> set sails for Alexandria&#44; and thence for Rome Italy&#44;<lb/> where Mark Antony had gone&#44; in spite of his debauch&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed self&#44; leaving quitting Cleopatra&#44; to look after his decaying<lb/> interests in the metropolis of the world.  Phasael<lb/> and Hyrcanus were treacherously kept as prisoners by<lb/> the Partheans&#44; and Antigonus was proclaimed king of<lb/> Judea.  Whatever excuse historians may find<lb/> for the double dealings of that Asmonean&#45;&#45;whose reign was<lb/> but of a very short duration&#45;&#45;nothing can be alleged to<lb/> extenuate his barbarous conduct towards his uncle.<lb/>  He To disqualify Hyrcanus from holding any more the<lb/> authority of high priest&#45;&#45;whom the Mosaic laws required<lb/> that he to be without any bodily blemish&#45;&#45;he cut off<lb/> the ears of the aged pontiff&#44; and sent him to Parthia as an exile.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>Phasael enraged with himself at having fallen a<lb/> victim to his credulity&#44; beat his head to death against the<lb/> walls of his prison&#44; rather than be slain by Antigonus.<lb/>  But Herod reached Rome in safety to piteously to tell Mark<lb/> Antony how fortune had turned her back upon him.<lb/>  Language and looks and bearing favored Herod greatly.<lb/>  He created the deepest impression.  Antony who had<lb/> become reconciled&#44; for a time&#44; with Octavious the powerful<lb/> triumvir&#44; commended to the latter the cause of his Idumean<lb/> friend.  Herod&#39;s hopes revived.  Rome would stand by<lb/> him against the Parthians&#44; and Antigonus&#44; brought to<lb/> disgrace&#44; would meet the fate of a traitor.  But<lb/> Herod&#39;s presence at Rome exceeded his achieved what the most sanguine<lb/> expectations could not dream of.  He had gone thither&#44; without intending<lb/> to make lay any &#91;&#63;&#93; claim to the crown.  He would<lb/> have felt satisfied&#44; that the young brother of his betrothed<lb/> Marianne&#44; be clothed by the Roman senate with ro&#45;<lb/>&#45;yalty&#44; for he he believe that he could use him that scion of the Maccabees&#44; as his<lb/> father had used Hyrcanus&#44; but Antony remembered the good<lb/> services Herod had rendered him&#44; and he knew moreover<lb/> how useful an ally the Idumenean would prove to Rome.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>Accordingly&#44; having convened the Senate&#44; he<lb/> had Herod conducted with honors becomingly escorted into its presence.<lb/>  Two accomplished orators extolled his deeds and the exploits<lb/> of Antipater.  A unanimous vote declared Herod<lb/> worthy of the crown&#44; and he was solemnly raised<lb/> to the regal dignity.  Leaving the Senate chamber with<lb/> Octavious and Antony on his right and left&#44; all the dignitaries escorted conducted him<lb/> to the Capitol&#44; where the decree was recorded.  Antony<lb/> made a feast&#44; as a mark of respect to the newly<lb/> chosen King of the Judeans&#44; and he who had come<lb/> to Rome as a suppliant&#44; departed from the eternal<lb/> city covered with honors.  We shall learn<lb/> hereafter&#44; to what account Herod put the sceptre<lb/> and the diadem&#59; how the people over whom he<lb/> reigned&#44; by the grace of heathen Rome&#44; fared under<lb/> his rule.  We shall learn whether we ought to<lb/> reserve to Herod a golden page or a blotched<lb/> and spotted leaf in in the volumes of our post&#45;biblical history.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
