<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF9_5</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1890-11" source="" attested="yes">November 1890</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_5_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_5_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_5_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_5_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_5_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_5_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_5_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_5_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_5_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_5_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_5_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_5_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. Fifth St.<lb/></p>
            <p>Philadelphia&#44; Nov. 90<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>A bit at the opponents of Orientalism<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Brethren.  Among Oriental customs cried down with an astounding<lb/> inconsistency in a spot which strikingly represents Orientalism&#45;&#45;<lb/> namely the Synagogue with all its surroundings&#45;&#45;there is one<lb/> universally and undeviatingly followed in whatever part of<lb/> the world&#44; the descendants of Abraham&#45;&#45;the typically Oriental Hebrew Hebrew&#45;&#45;<lb/>Congregate.  Enter a place of their worship in Paris&#44; or<lb/> in Shang&#45;Ha&#239;&#44; in Corfu or in Sydney&#44; in Teheran or in<lb/> Copenhagen&#59; make the round of the whole globe&#44; and the<lb/> same identical object will meet your vision&#44; a shrine wherein a<lb/> roll of parchment with oriental written characters is deposited.<lb/>  The copy manuscript which you will notice in Rome<lb/> does not vary in the least from another which you will<lb/> hear read in Jerusalem.  Precisely alike are they in words<lb/> and in form&#59; the same rule governs each regarding the<lb/> measurement of space to be left and the arranging of<lb/> poetical passages&#59; the letters of a larger size than ordinary&#44;<lb/> and those of a smaller kind are the same in all copies.<lb/>  How ancient far back those regulations are can be dated from&#44; I will not venture<lb/> to assert say with positiveness.  That if they did not<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>actually emanate from the Archprophet himself&#44; as<lb/> some will contend&#44; they may have issued from the Great<lb/> Synod &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; early presided over by Ezra&#44;<lb/> after our ancestors&#39; restoration to Palestine at the expi&#45;<lb/>&#45;ration of the Babylonian captivity&#44; over upwards of two thousand and<lb/> two hundred years ago&#44; it is reasonable to suppose.  For<lb/> that illustrious priest President of an illustrious body of Sages is called in our Bible &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;A scribe skilled in the Law of Moses&#34; and&#44; beyond<lb/> all doubts&#44; he gave a strong impulse to the school of<lb/> Sepharim that made numerous copies of the Pentateuch<lb/> and taught its contents&#44; or to quote the Rabbis&#44; Ezra that noble priest and his associates&#44; gave our crown again its former brightness &#91;Hebrew&#93; But But now it is seriously pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;posed that the Hebrew Oriental scroll so venerable for its high<lb/> antiquity&#44; and venerated because of the joyous and sad<lb/> memories clustering around it&#44; shall occupy no more<lb/> the its conspicuous spot in the synagogue our minor sanctuaries&#44; but that<lb/> eliminating perhaps whatever clashes with modern<lb/> thought&#44; it shall be exchanged for a printed book volume<lb/> suiting Western taste.  That vandalism is<lb/> advocated on the plea that the five books are not<lb/> better than the rest of the Scriptures&#44; which comes<lb/> from the press continually&#44; and is in use among<lb/> all Israelites in Synagogues as well as in schools.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>So Thus they reason to whom confessedly deem the narratives of Holy Writ of<lb/> have no greater value than the histories of Xenophon<lb/> and Herodotus&#44; and who would fain class our prophets<lb/> and moralists with Sophocles and Epictetus.  But Not so<lb/> Jews who believe in Divine inspiration.  While regarding<lb/> Holy Writ our Bible in its entirety with religious respect&#44; they draw a<lb/> wide line of demarcation between the volumes that tell<lb/> of man&#39;s creation and of the birth&#44; the growth&#44; the training of a nation devoted<lb/> by the God of Sinai to His service and eternized as the<lb/> witnesses of His existence&#44; Unity and almightness&#44; between<lb/> the Pentateuch I mean&#44; and subsequent books which<lb/> are made comprehensible only through the teaching<lb/> of him&#44; in whose soul were reflected the brightest rays<lb/> of the Lord&#39;s glory &#91;&#63;&#93; refulgently shone.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  But is it simply a love for the antique a moment recalling the remotest times.  Or&#44; is it<lb/> superstition&#59; a species of fetish idolatry&#44; as flippantly<lb/> stated declared asserted&#44; with a senseless adherence to Orientalism&#44; that demands the retention of the Sepher<lb/> Torah precisely exactly as traditionally received&#63;  No one<lb/> who claims an acquaintance with the subject&#44; should<lb/> so assert.  Were it not indeed for the extreme<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>scrupulousness observed by the Sages in transcribing<lb/> the five books&#59; had they not laid down exact fixed rules&#44;<lb/> given particulars as to the number of words&#44; to<lb/> those which begin each volume&#44; to those which are<lb/> in the middle and at the end thereof&#59; had they not<lb/> looked to the preservation of the scroll of the Law<lb/> unalterably in the minutest details&#44; who could<lb/> have insured its genuineness&#44; after thirty two centuries<lb/> of countless vicissitudes to Israel&#44; since the man of God &#91;Hebrew&#93; wrote it for the<lb/> instruction of future generations&#63;  As early as Already in<lb/> the reign of Ptolemy Philadelphus&#44; three hundred years<lb/> before the common era&#44; a number of Rabbis charged by<lb/> that King to translate the Pentateuch in Greek&#44;<lb/> introduced their version some changes not borne<lb/> out by the text&#44; but designedly made&#45;&#45;as the story<lb/> goes to avoid controversies. tells&#45;&#45;for political and other purposes.  To those alterations&#44;<lb/> a few of which are now yet perceptible in the Greek<lb/> rendition&#45;&#45;the Septuagint&#45;&#45;&#44; have been added there now from time to time&#44; very many&#44;<lb/> others from time to time&#44; by ignorant writers&#44; who<lb/> either were unable to understand the original well&#44;<lb/> or who fancied that they could improve upon it.<lb/>  But even previous to long before previous that period&#44; the Samaritans<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>a few small remnant of of whose ancient sect still<lb/> lives in Shechem&#44; or Napluse&#44; audaciously transposed<lb/> sentences&#44; and transformed them in the interest of their<lb/> belief&#44; according to which Moses should have ordered<lb/> that a temple be erected on Mount Gerizim&#44; and<lb/> sacrifices be offered only there.  Imagine now that<lb/> the roll of parchment on which are traced letters&#44; wi&#45;<lb/>&#45;thout any division of words or verses&#44; without vowel points&#44;<lb/> or singing accents&#44; without the least sign to guide to the<lb/> reader&#44; but save the traditions tenaciously kept in the memory<lb/> of olden preceptors and orally transmitted to their disci&#45;<lb/>&#45;ples with the strictest jealousy fidelity&#59; imagine&#44; I say&#44; that four<lb/> hundred years ago&#44; when the art of printing was disco&#45; invented&#44;<lb/> &#45;vered&#44; our Sepher Torah was had been put away as orientally antiquated<lb/> and finally lost&#44; and a printed copy of the Pentateuch furnished with<lb/> the separation of paragraphs&#44; of periods&#44; and all dia&#45;<lb/>&#45;critical points had taken its place supplanted it&#44; how easy for the<lb/> Chruch to surreptitiously introduce into the press<lb/> a phrase&#44; a term&#44; a letter&#44; a mark here and there&#44; fa&#45;<lb/>&#45;voring its belles creed&#33; dogmas&#33;  Instead of using events and<lb/> ordinances&#44;&#45;&#45;as it is wont to do as far&#45;fetched has always used absurdly used&#45;&#45;in the nature of veiled allu&#45;<lb/>&#45;sions to the man&#45;god&#44; and his advent&#44; it would have<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>foisted in into the Pentateuch Mosaic writings&#44; deliberate corruptions&#44; in<lb/> the original&#44; and I need not tell how typographical<lb/> blenders intentionally or unintentionally made&#44; are transferred from copy to copy&#44; until they<lb/> become irremediable errors&#44; engrafted on the people&#39;s minds.<lb/>  That I am not maligning my neighbors of another<lb/> persuasion creed&#44; I can prove by merely two illustrations.  Thus&#44;<lb/> in one of their books entitled &#34;The epistle of Paul&#44; the<lb/> apostle&#44; to the Hebrews&#44;&#34; in Chapter XI. v. 21&#44; an<lb/> event in our Bible is distorted&#44; to make it tally with that it may give a colour to<lb/> Christian ideas.  It reads so as follows&#58; &#34;By faith Jacob&#44;<lb/> when he was dying&#44; blessed both the sons of Joseph&#44; and<lb/> <sic>worshipped</sic>&#44; leaning upon the top of his staff&#34;&#45;&#45;a state&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment equally untrue both from an historically and philologically stand point&#59; for it was<lb/> after Joseph had promised by a solemn oath to have his<lb/> father buried in Canaan&#44; that Jacob bowed at the head of<lb/> the bed&#44; whereon he was lying&#44; sick but it suited the vulgate&#44;<lb/> or Latin translation sanctioned by Catholicism&#44; to alter facts and substitute Mattea<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; stick for &#34;Mittah&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93; bed&#44; availing itself of the<lb/> want of vowels in the text&#44; to intimate that on the<lb/> staff the cross was engraved and to it and which our patriarch anticipatedly paid homage.  Another instance of<lb/> <sic>wilful</sic> perversion of the original is found in Deuteronomy the King James authorized version<lb/> of the 26th verse of chap XXVII<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>chapter XXVII v 26 in Deuteronomy&#44; where by the insertion interpolation of the<lb/> word all&#44; which is not in the Hebrew&#44; the Church<lb/> declared us accursed under a curse from God because we cannot <sic>fulfil</sic> all every<lb/> the word of the His Law&#44;&#45;&#45;and as falsely stated for so it is declared accursed we are pronounced by reason of that in the<lb/> &#34;Epistle of Paul&#44; the Apostle to the Galatians&#34; Chap.<lb/> III v. 10.  &#40;I think that both errors are in the Septuagint&#41;  Now&#44; could Romanism or<lb/> Protestantism&#44; have suppressed our Sephar Torah&#45;&#45;hap&#45;Providen&#45;<lb/> &#45;pily &#45;tially left intact as the inheritance of the Congregation of<lb/> Jacob&#45;&#45;and substituted a printed and punctuated<lb/> copy&#44; or a translation&#59; depend upon it&#44; a flood of<lb/> &#34;pious frauds&#34;&#45;&#45;as they are termed styled&#45;&#45;would have flowed<lb/> in to give glory to Jesus glory and to Moses the lie.<lb/>  Call that not superstition&#44; but loving wisdom&#44; which prevented such a profanation.<lb/>  Never shall our heirloom be alienated&#59; never shall<lb/> it be defaced&#44; changing its venerable aspect into<lb/> a modernism ill&#45;comforting with its high antiquity.<lb/>  Let the despisers of Orientalism destroy in their &#34;Temples&#34;<lb/> every trace of the spot in which the Torah is enshrined&#59;<lb/> let them occidentalize the worship as they will&#44; we<lb/> who are not ready to sunder apart the bond<lb/> of union in Israel&#44; we&#44; who owe allegiance to<lb/> the Sages&#45;&#45;those restless watchers over the preser&#45;<lb/>&#45;vation of the five holy books&#45;&#45;will revere their<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>memory by holding maintaining unalterably for over the Sepher<lb/> Ha Torah.  Suffer me to quote&#45;&#45;however though<lb/> in imperfectly prose&#45;&#45;from a Hebrew transale metrical translation in Hebrew&#45;&#45;a few<lb/> lines of Gabriel Reisser&#39;s touching poem on the elevation of<lb/> the sacred scroll at the Synagogue.<lb/></p>
            <p>&#34;This is the Law&#44; this the word that God has given&#44;<lb/> as for His people&#39;s heritage.  Keep it&#44; guard it well Hold it dear&#44; keep it safely unchanged&#44;<lb/> while a breath stirs up your thy soul.  Raise it<lb/> af aloft&#44; O Israel it is thy boast&#44; O Israel&#33;<lb/> show it to all&#44; thou mayest&#44; you thou gavest a price thy all for it a price which<lb/> exceeds all value Liberty&#44; and peace&#44; fortune and fame was the<lb/> price.&#34;  One word more&#44; my brethren&#44; it will not be to<lb/> lament a sad defection&#44; where devotion to duty ought to rule&#44;<lb/> but rather to give offer thanks that faith is met&#44; where it can pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;mote its glory.  The youth whom his country has commissioned<lb/> with a high trust was cradled in ancestral Judaism doctrines.  In this<lb/> house of our God he learned to worship&#59; in Philadelphia was he<lb/> reared and taught&#44; therefore we share with him the honor he received.<lb/>  That he may fully realize the confidence reposed in his early<lb/> matured judgment&#44; I eagerly wish&#44; but that in his career&#44; so<lb/> creditably begun and so hopeful&#44; he may shed lustre on Judaism&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>is my ardent prayer.  In the native land of Moses and<lb/> in that where Cyrus reigned&#44; may he discover what will<lb/> associate his name with a national celebration destined<lb/> to form an epoch in the annals of America.  May he<lb/> live and a prosperous life&#44; as a Hebrew without guile.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
