<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF11_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1896-01" source="" attested="yes">1896</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_2_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>96<lb/></p>
            <p>About Mission schools<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Two articles in a New York Jewish Weekly and one a lengthy<lb/> communication in our Philadelphia Organ&#44; have affected<lb/> me very painfully.  They showed that the exertions of<lb/> well meaning brothers and sisters in faith of mine striving to<lb/> prevent the young in Israel from being caught in the<lb/> nets which Christian conversion&#45;mongers are spreading out abroad&#44;<lb/> have been altogether inadequate.  Perhaps&#44; the num&#45;<lb/>&#45;ber of boys and girls of Hebrew parentage reported to<lb/> attend mission schools&#44; is exaggerated&#44; but&#44; beyond all<lb/> doubts&#44; many can be found there regularly.<lb/></p>
            <p>It had been earnestly hoped that the afternoon Sun&#45;<lb/>&#45;day school&#44; opened last winter a year in a locality&#44;<lb/> round which propagandists&#45;&#45;mostly hired recreants renegades former<lb/> &#45;ly of to formerly connected with our faith&#45;&#45;ply their trade&#44; would counteract<lb/> what we must deplore as an unmitigated evil&#59;<lb/> but that school did not prove sufficient.  At the<lb/> outset&#44; a multitude which the hall could not pos&#45;<lb/>&#45;sibly hold&#44; thronged it&#44; but soon the crowd soon thinned<lb/> off.  The reason is obvious.  We would not&#44; we<lb/> dared not demoralize our children&#44; in obedience to the<lb/> Jesuitical maxim&#58; &#34;the end justifies the means.&#34;<lb/>  Occasionally&#44; we might recognize reward punctuality and good<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>behaviour by a present&#59; particularly so&#44; when<lb/> our own festivities are celebrated&#44; but we made<lb/> it universally understood that we do not intend to<lb/> enter into competition with apostatising shops.  Our<lb/> dealings are not like their dealings we do not bribe any into religion.  In the<lb/> language of our prophets we say&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;yes&#44; let all peoples walk&#44; each one in the name<lb/> of his own god&#44; but we will walk in the name of<lb/> the Lord Eternal our God for ever and <sic>and</sic> ever.&#34;  We do<lb/> not go in quest of proselytes.  If millions of our<lb/> fellow&#45;creatures are happy in the belief that the<lb/> Almighty begot a son&#44; and in order to deliver<lb/> all born of woman from the torments of a life here&#45;<lb/>&#45;after&#44; made that son die as a vicarious sacrifice&#59;<lb/> if a creed dogma against which every sentiment dictate of ours na&#45; reasoning<lb/> &#45;tive mind protests&#44; appeals to the feelings of non&#45;Israelites&#44;<lb/> and affords them comfort&#44; surely the Synagogue<lb/> will not send to the Church messengers&#44; to the Church&#44; commision&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed to disturb the public mind.  Tolerance is the<lb/> Jewish motto.  But we insist upon the right of receiving<lb/> the same degree of consideration.  We decidedly<lb/> object the measure to measures&#44; which falsehood<lb/> alone can suggest.  We object to the opening of schools&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>ostensibly for Hebrew teaching&#44; but really for the hidden pur&#45;<lb/>&#45;pose of distorting the understanding of our little ones.<lb/>  We object to the luring of such into the acceptance<lb/> of a religion creed which we&#44; their parents&#44; discard reject alto&#45;<lb/>&#45;gether&#44; by the allurements&#44; I say&#44; in the shape of gifts of different<lb/> kinds at all times&#44; and notably when the alleged natal<lb/> day of the man of Nazareth&#44; is kept amidst high<lb/> festivities.  Enough that we are constrained compelled to act un&#45;<lb/>&#45;Jewishly&#44; just as our Rabbis feared we would so under foresaw and deprecated.<lb/> compulsion. &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Enough that we must suffer in do violence to our convictions&#44; because<lb/> we form only a small minority in the community.  I know that<lb/> not alone at that period of the winter season&#44; which<lb/> recalls the sore trials of our martyred people during eighteen cen&#45;<lb/>&#45;turies&#44; but every day&#44; educational institutions in Ameri&#45;<lb/>&#45;ca expect all pupils to sing hymns and listen to<lb/> invocations of a character&#44; hostile to Judaism.  Re&#45;<lb/>&#45;monstrances repeatedly made availed nothing.  We<lb/> succumb to the idea that the majority rules&#44; al&#45;<lb/>&#45;though in matters of religion the Constitution of<lb/> the United States does not acknowledge that<lb/> idea as an axiomatic truth.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>But if we submit to a great wrong&#44; in order not<lb/> to deny our sons and daughters the advantage of<lb/> secular earning&#44; we will not tacitly submit to<lb/> a provocation deliberately devised to the advantage<lb/> of the Church.  The mission schools in the<lb/> southern section of our city&#45;&#45;now spreading extending still<lb/> further&#45;&#45;are an open insult to every Philadelphia Jew<lb/> and Jewess&#44; who has not sold delivered heart and soul to<lb/> sinful indifference.  We have read in the<lb/> issue of last week&#39;s Exponent&#44; the assertion made<lb/> by a teacher of the gospel&#44; that parents as a whole do not at all find<lb/> fault with their children for attending the<lb/> mission school in St Mary Street&#44; held at the<lb/> building of the College settlement intimating a parental approval.  For the honor<lb/> of the name which those parents bear&#44; I trust<lb/> that the assertion is false groundless&#59; I hope that&#44; knowingly&#44;<lb/> fathers and mothers in Israel do not permit<lb/> a heinous sin to be recorded to the perdition of<lb/> their own households.  Still&#44; I would act with<lb/> deception&#44; if I did not admit that&#44; in some a few more than one in&#45;<lb/>&#45;stances&#44; avarice does overcome a sense of duty to<lb/> God and our people.  I met once a parent&#44;<lb/> whose children frequented a mission school&#44; then<lb/> on 9th near Lombard street.  I administered<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>a reproof.  The saucy answer retort was&#44; that no<lb/> harm would result&#44; while the good derived in<lb/> the shape of presents&#44; was felt.  Very<lb/> recently&#44; addressing a large meeting in the inte&#45;<lb/>&#45;rest of a down town Hebrew school&#44; I cautioned&#44; with all<lb/> the power of speech&#44; Jews within hearing of my<lb/> voice against the wily schemes of missionaries.<lb/>  I have at times faced the unscrupulous and pictured<lb/> to them the effect of their shocking heedlessness&#44;<lb/> but more than words&#44; actions are needed&#44; concerted actions.<lb/>  Say brethren&#59; what tangible benefit to our religion<lb/> are Synagogues or Temples of a superb architecture&#44;<lb/> luxuriously tapestried&#44; fashionably cushioned and<lb/> electrically lighted&#44; while the lurid darkness of<lb/> ignorance&#44; the unrelieved poverty of intellect con&#45;<lb/>&#45;tinue to reign among masses&#44; who can reckon<lb/> an ancestry of prophets and Sages&#63;  But another<lb/> reflection presents itself in connection with Syna&#45;<lb/>&#45;gogues and temples.  I am thoroughly nauseated<lb/> with lessons emanating from such monuments<lb/> of wealth.  Almost weekly the man&#44; whom<lb/> the Churches invoke and extol and bless&#44; is pic&#45; depicted<lb/> &#45;tured there as the typical Jew.  What reply answer<lb/> could I give to some reckless parents&#44; whom the love<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>of unlawful gain induces to wink at or to<lb/> permit in their young sons and daughters the<lb/> singing of the doxology&#44; or other hymns by their young sons and daughters to<lb/> the glory of Jesus&#44; if I were shown that Rabbis<lb/> always pronounce his name with profound<lb/> reverence&#63;  Now&#59;  I will be asked&#58; If&#44; as our preachers believe&#44; the<lb/> founder of Christianity is on a par with Moses&#44;<lb/> greatly superior to Ezra&#44; surpassing in purity<lb/> our olden preceptors&#44; what harm impropriety can there be<lb/> in sounding his praises&#63;  I am not drawing on<lb/> the imagination.  I could prove that scores of<lb/> times have pulpits&#44; spuriously reputed Jewish&#44; have pictured portrayed<lb/> that man in such high colours.  Brethren.  One<lb/> tenth of the thousands spent for the payment<lb/> of rhetorical gymnastics in stately edifices&#44; would<lb/> give us many a college settlement to initiate our<lb/> children in accomplishments&#44; within the pale of<lb/> unexceptional Jewish circles.  We do need it.<lb/>  The best armor with which we can panoply clothe<lb/> the young among the Jews against the barbed ar&#45;<lb/>&#45;rows of a Christian propaganda&#44; is sound know&#45;<lb/>&#45;ledge and broad culture.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Last week a coreligionist called on me.  He<lb/> was accompanied by His wife who accompanied him was in tears.<lb/>  Both seemed deeply distressed.  Inquiring about into the<lb/> cause&#44; I was handed a letter.  It had been written<lb/> by their son&#44; who is yet still a lad.  Misconduct had brought<lb/> him to a reformatory.  In his letter&#44; the youth<lb/> confessed that he deserved the punishment under&#45;<lb/>&#45;gone&#44; but&#44; as the time for his release was ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;proaching&#44; he would tell his parents that since<lb/> he left his home&#44; his mind had changed greatly radically.<lb/>  He became convinced that Jesus is the promised<lb/> Messiah&#44; and consequently he had become a Christ&#45;<lb/>&#45;ian.  Mark it well.  That is the reformation which<lb/> a nationally American Institution has brought about.<lb/>  The betterment of a lad&#39;s morals&#44; was the alienation estrangement<lb/> of his heart from the hearts of his parents.  Brethren&#58; The<lb/> opponents of Judaism are everywhere at work&#44;<lb/> and they do not stop short&#44; should all the ten<lb/> commandments be set at <sic>nought</sic>&#44; provided that<lb/> they bring one&#44; whose belief in the indivisible Unity they hate&#44; to the foot of<lb/> the cross.  Likely&#44; the Jewish boy with whose feel&#45;<lb/>&#45;ings soul&#45;catchers tampered&#44; had never learnt the prin&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciples on which the Israel&#39;s faith stand for support.<lb/>  He may have seen outward practices mechanically<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>performed &#91;Hebrew&#93;; he may have<lb/> heard mutterings&#44; interpreted as prayers&#44; but not<lb/> solemn invocations.  The spirit of Judaism had<lb/> never penetrated his heart.  I pitied his<lb/> parents&#44; &#38; wrote to their son a letter of gentle advice<lb/> and friendly admonition&#59; the effect of which I have<lb/> not yet learned&#59; but in all candor I declare riches that abundant silver &#38;<lb/> gold are ill bestowed on music and sermons lectures.  The great<lb/> desideratum in a community of Hebrews&#44; that has in&#45;<lb/>&#45;creased unprecedentedly within the last decade and a<lb/> half&#44; is Jewish institutions amidst surroundings per&#45;<lb/>&#45;fectly Jewish&#59; instruction calculated to breathe a<lb/> sense of noble pride for the religion that never bent<lb/> to man&#39;s worship&#44; that proclaimed a code of ethics<lb/> in which the love of God&#44; as the archetype of spi&#45;<lb/>&#45;ritual perfection and love of our neighbors&#44; is<lb/> inculcated.  Admit&#58; We have not been inactive&#44;<lb/> and I took occasion to tell editors so&#44; in Justice to<lb/> our people in Philadelphia&#44; but we have not done more than a<lb/> fraction of what it behooves us to do.  Who will stir up<lb/> to largely increase the number of our schools&#44; widen the sphere of<lb/> pure learning&#44; waken devotion to the cause of Israel&#63;  God&#39;s blessings will<lb/> accompany them&#44; here and beatitude hereafter.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
