<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF5_3</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_3_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_3_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_3_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_3_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_3_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_3_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_3_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_3_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_3_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_3_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_3_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_3_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Post&#45;Biblical<lb/>
                46<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>The history of &#34;Judah the Prince&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; offered<lb/> abundant opportunities for saying what might be<lb/> of general interest.  When&#44; a short time ago&#44; I<lb/> made it that history the subject of one of my occasional lectures of the series<lb/> on the schools of Judea&#44; I tried to show that the<lb/> man known by who bore the appellation of &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Our holy<lb/> Rabbi the holy&#34; justified the title given him by a<lb/> grateful posterity.  For he had dispensed his large riches<lb/> in a manner that <sic>benefitted</sic> many&#44; while his lite&#45;<lb/>&#45;rary labors saved our national traditions from oblivion through our in the accepted compilation of the his Mishna.<lb/>  One of the Hebrew Sages who appears to have<lb/> lived about the time of Judah the Prince&#44; wrote that<lb/> the splendid qualities and natural endowments of which distinguished our<lb/> illustrious Rabbi&#44; were noticeable also in his children.<lb/></p>
            <p>But I have searched in vain to find how the his&#45;<lb/>&#45;tory of the sons of our Rabbi the holy&#44; bears out confirming that<lb/> assertion.  The oldest child who succeeded his father<lb/> as President of the college at Tiberius&#44; or Patriarch<lb/> &#40;and first in order of the &#34;Emoriam&#34;&#44; or interpreters<lb/> of the Mishnah&#41; has not left behind traces of a<lb/> great remarkable strongly marked individuality.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>With the exception of some excellent maxims with which he is credited&#44; and&#44; which<lb/> are interspersed through the Talmud&#44; little is told<lb/> which that may prove the activity and direct influence<lb/> of Gamliel III.  Those maxims&#44; however show reveal<lb/> a man possessed of a well balanced mind and a<lb/> tender heart.  He used to say&#58; The following<lb/> of a trade joint to the study of the Law is high&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly to be praised&#59; for&#44; occupations will drive away<lb/> evil inclinations.  A mere knowledge of sacred<lb/> literature is insufficient to keep us from sin&#44;<lb/> active Work must e associated with &#91;&#63;&#93; learning.  To his<lb/> pupils&#44; the Sage recommended self&#45;dependence&#44; rather<lb/> than a reliance on the patronage of men in social or political<lb/> heights&#44; and he laid great stress on the necessity<lb/> of extending kindness towards persons of in every<lb/> condition of life.  Commenting on a Biblical passage<lb/> which promises God&#39;s mercy as a reward to the<lb/> observance of the precepts&#44; Gamliel said&#58; The<lb/> living goodness of the Creator will only be exhi&#45;<lb/>&#45;bited towards such as show loving&#45;kindness to<lb/> all their fellow&#45;creatures.  That religion is best&#44;<lb/> which copies the ways of the Lord by deeds<lb/> of benevolence&#44; mercy forbearance and human forgiveness.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>But if historical accounts of the life of Gamliel<lb/> III are very meagre&#44; those about his son give ample<lb/> scope to lecture thereon.  However&#44; <sic>Before</sic> I allude to them&#44;<lb/> I deem it necessary essential to say that modern critics<lb/> are greatly widely at variance concerning dates and events in<lb/> the period of which I intend to speak and I candidly admit that the Talmud<lb/> cannot be followed altogether as a guide in matters pertaining to chronology and genealogy.  A large<lb/> number of writers contend that the illustrious grand<lb/> father Judah the Prince viz&#44; our Rabbi the Holy&#44; and not his grand&#45;child is the man<lb/> to whom certain incidents recorded in Rabbinical works<lb/> have reference.  I have adopted the contrary opinion&#44;<lb/> as entertained by Professors Graetz and Luzzatto&#44; for reasons which<lb/> seem to me forcible.  The difference of views<lb/> among historians arose from a confusion of names and<lb/> from circumstances which I could not present here con&#45;<lb/>&#45;sistently with the customary brevity of my sketches.  Let<lb/> me simply tell&#44; that the son of Gamliel II went<lb/> also by the appellation of &#34;Judah the Prince&#44;&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93; and that<lb/> the name of Antoninus&#44; who is reported to have<lb/> been on intimate terms with the Jewish Rabbi&#44; was a<lb/> name borne by several Roman emperors in succession.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>With the short prefatory explanation I will proceed.<lb/>  During the period that pagan Rome was pro&#45; display&#45;<lb/>&#45;ducing the soul&#45;revolting sight of rival emperors<lb/> murdering one another&#44; and of a people brutalized<lb/> by the indulgence of vice&#44; the unhappy country of our fathers<lb/> felt the ill&#45;effects of quarrels and dissolution depravity among<lb/> her masters.  To add to her misery&#44; the religion of<lb/> Christianity which had begun to assert itself and<lb/> which the ruling heathens could not distinguish<lb/> from Judaism&#44; gave cause to internal wranglings<lb/> and abuses&#44; and served as a cause pretext for increasing<lb/> taxation and multiplying vexations.<lb/></p>
            <p>finally&#44; one of the several called Antoninus princes &#40;I will let the<lb/> savants decide which it was&#41; being enlightened<lb/> and humane understood the value of the religion&#44;<lb/> whose renowned Sage&#44; Hillel&#44; had taught the golden rule &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Do not unto others&#44; what is displea&#45;<lb/>&#45;sing to thee.&#34;  Accordingly&#44; he showed its adherents<lb/> particular favors&#44; and even made a present of a costly chan&#45;<lb/>&#45;delier to a <sic>Palestenian</sic> Synagogue.  But because that Ro&#45;<lb/>man emperor was unprejudiced and willing to learn&#44;<lb/> he sought did not disdain to seek the intimacy of Judah II&#44; the<lb/> Jewish patriarch.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>The Talmudists assert that he ate and drank<lb/> with the Sage&#44; advised with him on important<lb/> matters&#44; and in several instances various important cases closely followed<lb/> his counsel.  The Rabbi cherished greatly knew how to appreciate a friend&#45;<lb/>&#45;ship that enabled him to improve the sorrowful<lb/> condition of his brethren&#44; and advance forward their inte&#45;<lb/>&#45;rest.  He knew felt that his belief did not put lay any<lb/> obstacle in the way of an alliance of goodwill and<lb/> amity between a Jew and a non&#45;Israelite.  The<lb/> father of our people&#44; Abraham&#44; had set a bright<lb/> example of tolerance&#44; when he took into his con&#45;<lb/>&#45;fidence Aner&#44; Eshcol and Mamr&#233;&#44; three Emorite<lb/> brothers&#44; and while among the custodians of our the traditions&#44;<lb/> Meir&#44; a splendid luminary &#40;as the name denotes&#41; in our literary horizon&#44; had<lb/> cultivated the acquaintance of Nimos or Euonymous&#44;<lb/> a heathen philosopher.<lb/></p>
            <p>I will now quote a few instances illustrating the fa&#45;<lb/>&#45;miliar intercourse and mutual trust between the<lb/> emperor and the sage.  Antoninus being wor engaged in let<lb/> Judah know&#44; at one time expensive foreign wars&#44; and became alarmed at noticing that his finances fell short of the expenditure.  He informed Judah through a trusty messenger that the national<lb/> treasury was being very nigh emptied out&#44; while the wants<lb/> of the country were increasing.  Judah gave no<lb/> answer&#44; but took the messenger who brought word<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>to a garden connected with his house&#44; and<lb/> pulled off some of the old plants and set others in<lb/> their stead&#44; then said he to the messenger to the man who brought him word&#58; &#34;Go and<lb/> report what you have seen.&#34;  Antoninus immediately<lb/> caught the sense of the Rabbi&#39;s action&#44; and he remo&#45;<lb/>&#45;ved a number of incompetent and dishonest officials&#44;<lb/> and supplied their vacant places with efficient and<lb/> reliable men.  In the course of conversation&#44;<lb/> Antonius said once to Judah.  I think that when<lb/> we are called to judgment after death&#44; both our<lb/> body and soul can manage to escape punishment.  The body<lb/> may plead in this manner.  I did not sin&#44; for<lb/> flesh has no sense&#44; the soul which possesses wis&#45;<lb/>&#45;dom and power did all the wrong.  But the soul<lb/> on in its part turn may exonerate itself by saying&#58; why&#44; I am<lb/> only a spirit an ethereal substance&#44; I have no means to act&#44; the body which<lb/> has limbs did all the mischief.  Rabbi Judah<lb/> replied.  I will tell you Listen to a story.  A king had a<lb/> beautiful garden&#44; in which a tree of delicious<lb/> fruits had grown.  He set there as guardians<lb/> two men&#59; one of them was lame&#44; the other blind.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>One day the lame one said to the blind&#44; I long<lb/> to have my fill of the sweet fruits I see.  Do&#44;<lb/> let me stand on your shoulders&#44; and I shall steal<lb/> them at pleasure and we two shall have enjoyment.  As said so it was done.  But the king noticed the<lb/> theft&#44; and took the guardians to task.  The blind<lb/> man denied the charge in toto&#44; bringing forward alleging his want<lb/> of sight as his defence&#44; the lame alleged on his part brought forward his<lb/> inability to climb up as his justification advocate.  The<lb/> king placed one on the top of the other&#44; and in that<lb/> position had them both scourged.  The Rabbi then continued<lb/> so likewise it will happen&#44; that the punishment<lb/> which the soul receives&#44; will &#40;in some manner unknown inexplicable to us&#41; sorely affect the body&#44;<lb/> whose receptacle and medium it was.<lb/></p>
            <p>On another occasion Antoninus asked&#58; Is it right<lb/> to be praying all the time&#63;  The Rabbi answered.<lb/>  It is wrong for what you call for prayer necessarily becomes then through that usage&#44; The emperor did not agree a mere re&#45;<lb/>&#45;hersal of empty words.  The emperor did not agree to<lb/> that opinion.  One morning Rabbi Judah rose up<lb/> early and presenting himself to the King&#39;s mansion&#44; greet&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed the ruler thus&#58; &#34;Peace be with you good dear Sovereign&#34;.<lb/>  Shortly after he returned and said&#58; &#34;I hail your ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;pearance O monarch.&#34;  Many minutes had not passed&#44;<lb/> when he came back and exclaimed&#58; &#34;May you enjoy good health<lb/> O King&#33;&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Antoninus objected to that behaviour seemed annoyed and told<lb/> the Sage&#58; &#34;I think that you are treating me with<lb/> levity&#34;.  Well then&#44; rejoined Rabbi Judah&#44; if you<lb/> who are a mortal consider such a conduct as mine<lb/> undue familiarity&#44; or an unbecoming jest&#44; how can<lb/> you recommend it with regard to the Almighty&#44; whom<lb/> we must approach with a mind devotionally prepared&#63;<lb/>  Now&#44; the anecdotes which I have narrated will<lb/> furnish an idea of the Character of Judah II and<lb/> of his intellectual calibre.  Clearly&#44; he was wise<lb/> and pious.  The Jewish historian Hirsch<lb/> Graetz intimates&#44; however&#44; that the Rabbi&#44;<lb/> presuming on the privileges granted him by his imperial friend&#44; did not always use them wisely<lb/> and piously&#59; that he sometime treated his colleagues<lb/> with harshness arbitrariness&#44; and exacted fees and services un&#45;<lb/>&#45;becoming of a religious teacher.  I concede that<lb/> the certain occurrences recorded in the Talmud leads us to infer that&#44; inference&#44; but inas&#45;<lb/>&#45;much as to look for perfect consistency&#44; is to go<lb/> in search of a very rare Jewel&#44; we should pass<lb/> lightly over the short comings and of a distinguished man&#44; solely to remember his sterling merits.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Let us remember recall the fact that during a number of years&#44;<lb/> our some ancestors&#44; harassed by the wickedness of Rome<lb/> enjoyed some respite only through the esteem and af&#45;<lb/>fection which an emperor entertained for our Rabbi.  We<lb/> we should not forget that Judah II promoted by<lb/> his influence national learning&#59; and that though sur&#45;<lb/>&#45;rounded by luxuries&#44; he retained simple habits to the<lb/> last.  It is those virtues highly commendable that won for the Sage the reverence<lb/> of his contemporaries&#44; and handed down his name<lb/> to posterity encircled with a halo of sanctity.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
