<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF8_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff8_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff8_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff8_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff8_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff8_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff8_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff8_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff8_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff8_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff8_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff8_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff8_1_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff8_1_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff8_1_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff8_1_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff8_1_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>14 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>On the character of Joseph<lb/> For Parashat Vayeggash<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  To form a correct opinion of our neighbor&#39;s<lb/> character&#44; we must attentively mark the thoughts and<lb/> wishes to which he unguardedly gives expression.  For&#44;<lb/> what our minds mostly dwell upon&#44; will instinctively force<lb/> itself out&#44; whether in private our domestic or social intercourse.<lb/>  Thus&#44; for instance&#44; the egotist whom an overweening<lb/> love of self&#44; prompts to thrust quote his own &#91;&#63;&#93; forward authority&#44;<lb/> on all occasions&#44; will be easily discovered.  So the votary<lb/> to sensuality&#44; will be readily detected&#59; and so the envious&#44;<lb/> the avaricious&#44; the proud will betray their ruling passions.<lb/>  And what is true of men&#39;s vices&#44; can be applied to their virtues.<lb/>  These will be reflected as in a mirror&#44; in utterances unstu&#45;<lb/>&#45;died and ingenious.  Now&#44; such a standard by<lb/> which we may be safely guided in forming a conception<lb/> of the characters of the living&#44; may serve likewise as a<lb/> criterion to judge thereby of those who have long since&#44;<lb/> ceased to exist here below.  The distance of time&#44; which<lb/> separates us from Our olden predecessors&#44; may prevent our<lb/> thoroughly understanding the motives of their actions.  Causes<lb/> now unfathomable to the minds of our generations&#44; or unto which&#44; we of the present age&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>cannot appreciate&#44; may have given rise to<lb/> certain deeds startling and perplexing.  But we will<lb/> be competent now as always rightly to estimate the<lb/> moral worth of the ancients&#44; using as a test their<lb/> words <sic>unpremeditately</sic> spoken.  For&#44; nature does not<lb/> follow the course of earthly events.  It remains unchanged.<lb/>  The principles which the Almighty Creator has implanted<lb/> into within our breasts&#44; have exorcised the same power in the<lb/> primeval days of the world as they would in our own<lb/> days.  Revealed religion has added sanctity to those<lb/> principles by affixing thereunto a divine seal&#44; but a<lb/> noble sentiment nobly spoken&#44; will ever thrill the<lb/> heart&#44; independent of the stage of civilization&#44; or of religious<lb/> culture attained by him that gave it utterance.<lb/></p>
            <p>Dear hearers&#33;  The lesson we have just read&#44; gives us an<lb/> insight into the character of an individual&#44; with whose<lb/> history we have become acquainted through the records<lb/> left in the oldest of all books&#59; yet&#44; his loveliness and<lb/> genuine greatness admit of no superior&#44; among the illu&#45;<lb/>&#45;strious personages who have since trod the path<lb/> of life.  Neeed I say&#44; who amidst the glorious dead<lb/> so charms and still interests posterity&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>You know&#44; the exemplary son&#44; the forgiving brother&#44;<lb/> the honest and high&#45;minded statesman of yore&#44; Joseph<lb/> the son of our sainted patriarch&#44; Jacob.  I will He had<lb/> not repeat myself by portraying fully what I was<lb/> privileged on two former occasions to present to your un&#45;<lb/>&#45;derstanding&#44; but I will simply point out some salient<lb/> traits which the section of this sabbath sets conspicuously<lb/> forth.  The viceroy of Egypt had recognized his<lb/> brothers&#44; but he carefully avoided being recognized by them&#44;<lb/> ere his object had been compassed.  Therefore he spoke<lb/> in the Egyptian language&#44; and not in the Hebrew tongue&#44;<lb/> and through an interpreter he addressed them in terms harsh<lb/> and threatening.  But under the guise of austerity&#44; the<lb/> heart still beat high with generous emotions.  It yearned throbbed<lb/> with fraternal love.  He that wore the insignia of<lb/> power&#44; had not forgotten that they who stood in his pre before him<lb/> sence self&#45;condemned&#44; intensely distressed at the thought<lb/> of meeting again their disconsolate parent with the tidings<lb/> of Simeon&#39;s imprisonment&#44; and of the stern necessity of<lb/> parting with Benjamin&#44; were the natural companions<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>of his childhood&#44; creatures equally dear to that<lb/> father&#44; at whose table all had been fed&#44; and by whose<lb/> fond care all had grown to manhood.  Not a spout<lb/> of nurtured malevolence&#44; not a desire for revenge&#44; which<lb/> the ungodly alone call sweet&#44; had suggested the severity<lb/> of manners assumed&#44; but a resolve to probe the heart&#44;<lb/> to learn with certainty that time and reflection had<lb/> erased every vestige of a passion which had goaded<lb/> on to crime&#59; that none of the lurking jealousy harbored<lb/> against the first child of the beloved Rachel was en&#45;<lb/>&#45;tertained towards the surviving and younger brother&#59;<lb/> hence the imperative demand for having the latter brought<lb/> away from home&#59; hence the stratagem of the silver&#45;cup<lb/> and the accusation that followed.  But now all<lb/> misgivings had vanished.  Judah himself a husband and<lb/> a father entreated that he might put on the shackles<lb/> of servitude&#44; that H he might be allowed to relinquish<lb/> man&#39;s dearest right&#45;freedom&#45;&#45;&#44; to rescue his father&#39;s<lb/> darling&#44; Benjamin&#44; from bondage.  What could more<lb/> strongly prove the happy change which twenty years<lb/> of repentance had wrought&#63;  And then that<lb/> soul&#45;stirring picture of Jacob&#39;s terrible suspense&#44; drawn<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>with colours&#44; which nature alone can lend&#59; that of his an&#45;<lb/>&#45;guish at the detention of the lad with whose fate his<lb/> own seemed interwoven&#59; the narrative of the <sic>woful</sic> res&#45;<lb/>&#45;ponsibility resting on the suppliant&#44; of the description<lb/> of the horror felt at the bare idea of plunging an<lb/> already bereaved parent into a state of utter misery&#44; of<lb/> the dread of calling down a curse for having failed to perform<lb/> a solemn promise&#44; all that pathetic address&#44; with which<lb/> our section opens&#44; brought home to the gentle heart of<lb/> Joseph the conviction that the past had been lamented and<lb/> atoned for.  Their pent up feelings could no longer be<lb/> stifled.  Nature <sic>yeilded</sic>&#44; and kisses and tears became<lb/> witnesses of a scene sublime and thrilling and sublime.<lb/>  But&#44; Oh human greatness&#33;  None was suffered to look<lb/> upon that scene&#44; at which angels must have wept for joy.<lb/>  None saw it on earth&#44; because if it supremely elevated the forgiver&#44;<lb/> it awakened a sense of unconcealable humiliation in the<lb/> forgiven.  &#34;Joseph could no more refrain himself before<lb/> all who stood by him&#44; and he cried &#34;Let every man go out<lb/> from before me.&#34;  It should not be known that the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>magnanimity of a brother had raised his kindred<lb/> from self&#45;debasement.  All who issued from the loins<lb/> of Jacob should stand exalted in the eyes of the stranger&#44;<lb/> all should be welcome&#44; and respected in the land where<lb/> Joseph wielded sway.  Oh&#33; that our own sons and daughters<lb/> acted always so considerately&#44; so benignantly towards one each<lb/> another&#44; screening from shame&#44; covering up sin&#59; listening<lb/> to the voice of nature&#44; which appeals to our best instincts&#44; and<lb/> letting it not be drowned in the din of unruly passions.<lb/>  Would that like the righteous Joseph they ingeniously<lb/> exclaimed &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Do not fall out by the way&#34;.<lb/>  &#34;We are the same flesh and blood&#59; let us lay hold of one<lb/> another&#44; let the weak in virtue be sustained by the strong&#44;<lb/> let him that toils for a subsistence find a powerful<lb/> support in him that commands wealth&#44; easing the passage<lb/> that leads us all to our Father.&#34;  How happier would<lb/> our communities be&#44; how when our children go for the hand<lb/> in hand through the journey of life&#63;............<lb/>  But behold again the loveliness of a true man&#39;s character&#33;<lb/>  Joseph had repeatedly obtained assurances that his father<lb/> still lived.  He had inquired with solicitude concerning his<lb/> health&#44; when his brothers returned from Canaan to buy corn.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>He had just heard the affecting address of Judah&#44;<lb/> which mainly tended to spare his aged parent greater<lb/> sorrows.  And yet no sooner did he reveal his own name&#44;<lb/> than he instinctively asked for that which he already knew.<lb/>  Does it surprise you&#44; my hearers&#33; that he should be so<lb/> eager to learn t what he had been of repeatedly told&#63;<lb/>  I have said it&#44; whi that upon which our minds mostly dwell&#44;<lb/> will spontaneously force itself out&#44; and give tone to our speech<lb/> and our manners.  The memory of Jacob was ever pre&#45;<lb/>sent to Joseph.  It had accompanied him&#44; through the<lb/> checkered events of undergone.  It had clung to his very soul.<lb/>  The Rabbis relate&#44; in one of their allegories&#44; that when the<lb/> trusty steward of Poliphats house&#44; was tempted to swerve<lb/> from the fidelity due to his master and to his God&#44; the<lb/> image of his parent stood before his vision&#44; and prevented<lb/> wickedness.  And now feelings long cherished&#44; but<lb/> denied expression&#44; burst impulsively forth &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> What a volume of affection those three Hebrew words<lb/> do reveal&#33;  They signify a longing to see&#44; to embrace<lb/> the father so <sic>transcendently</sic> loved&#44; to declare the joy of a<lb/> reunion.  Look well on the picture&#44; my youthful auditors&#33;<lb/>  The rich&#44; and powerful Joseph&#44; he before whom a whole<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>nation bent the knee&#44; does not only merely thinks of his aged pa&#45;<lb/>rent&#44; and forward the means that which may sustain his life&#44;<lb/> but craving to clasp him that dear being into his arms&#44;<lb/> <sic>preceeds</sic> him on his arrival&#44; bedews his wrinkled visage<lb/> with his tears&#44; promises to comfort&#44; to solace&#44; to<lb/> highly honor the author of his existence.  Where<lb/> are they who blush if their parents cannot bow as<lb/> gracefully as they have learnt to bow&#59; who style feel<lb/> scandalized if their mother cannot shine in fashionable<lb/> circles&#44; if their father lacks the high polish they<lb/> profess to have acquired.  Let them such contemplate the<lb/> portrait Holy Writ has drawn.  Jacob&#44; an humble<lb/> shepherd&#44; ignorant of the manners and language of<lb/> the Egyptians&#44; stands before the in the courts of a dreaded monarch of<lb/> who brought him there&#63;  His son&#44; his son who prized his<lb/> father&#39;s hoary&#45;head above all greatness.  Contrast<lb/> now the demeanour Joselph with that of some of<lb/> our gaily&#45;attired young men and women&#44; who not<lb/> only suffer their aged parents to remain unnoticed&#44; but<lb/> who deliberately avoid that their associates may see them&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>lest their peculiar habits may excite derision.  But<lb/> let me tell those youths in the name of our religion&#44; that<lb/> if it is base ingratitude to forsake the guardians of<lb/> our early days&#44; when they need our aid&#44; it is not less<lb/> shocking and contrary to all laws to withhold from them<lb/> those the tokens of deference as implied by the Hebrew term &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Honor&#34;&#44; and which they may claim by reason of as co&#45;<lb/>workers of the Almighty in the running and preserving<lb/> of our lives.  For it is not the simple act of sup&#45;<lb/>&#45;plying food and raiment that partly repays long trials&#44; and greatly our greatest gratifies our real gratifies our early benefactors&#44;<lb/> but rather the demonstration of affection which accompanies<lb/> the act.  Justly have our Sages written&#44; that some children<lb/> feed their parents on dainties&#44; and still g grieve them even<lb/> unto death&#44; while others make suffer them to toil&#44; and<lb/> nevertheless afford them ineffable pleasures.  Look<lb/> again upon Joseph.  Unspeakably anxious to show<lb/> Jacob tokens of filial devotion&#44; he sends this message.<lb/>  &#34;Come down to me&#44; tarry not&#34;....&#34;thou shalt be near to<lb/> me&#34;.  Nothing of that cold manner&#44; with which some<lb/> of our world would be enlightened children&#44; disp treat their parents<lb/> is then in can be detected in those words.  They are brimful of glowing<lb/> love&#59; of that love which knows no disparity of conditions&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>which levels down all inequalities.  &#34;Near unto me<lb/> shalt thou dwell&#44;&#34; so must we cheer the winter of<lb/> our parent&#39;s existence&#44; if we wish to do our full duty.<lb/>  So must we prove ourselves the worthy recipients of<lb/> that law&#44; which places filial reverence next to Divine<lb/> obedience&#44; and which is in very deed the primary<lb/> element of all human greatness.  May the<lb/> Almighty grant that the dwelling&#45;places in<lb/> which our sons and daughters are brought up&#44; may<lb/> be exactly what the English word &#34;home&#34; implies&#44; redo&#45;<lb/>&#45;lent of the joys which a respectful demeanour towards<lb/> superiors&#44; is always evinced a harmonious consonance of feelings among<lb/> equals&#44; and a considerate and benevolent disposition<lb/> shown to inferiors&#44; secure and continually enhanced.<lb/>  May in each and all of us be fulfilled the sentence<lb/> of the Scriptures&#44; in which the righteous man is<lb/> promised &#34;Thou shalt know that peace is in<lb/> thy tent&#44; and when thou shalt look over thy<lb/> habitation&#44; shal thou shalt miss nothing.&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>So may it be.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>Addition<lb/></p>
            <p>It may not have escaped your attention&#44; dear hearers&#44;<lb/> that holy writ while impressing upon children with great fre&#45;<lb/>&#45;quency&#44; the duty of serving and honoring their parents&#44;<lb/> it does not define the obligations which the latter must exer&#45;<lb/>&#45;cise towards their offspring.  Beside the command of im&#45;<lb/>&#45;parting to them the knowledge of the Law&#44; no ordinance<lb/> has been imposed upon those who are privileged to be called<lb/> fathers and mothers.  Have they then none other to per&#45;<lb/>&#45;form&#63;  Nature&#44; which is the messenger of God&#44; invested<lb/> with functions no less holy sacred than the revealed Word&#44;<lb/> emphatically answers &#34;Yes.&#34;  &#34;Numerous are the duties<lb/> devolving upon parents&#44; and they who fail to <sic>fulfil</sic> them<lb/> with exactness&#44; offend the Deity&#44; by doing violence<lb/> to the principles He has implanted with&#44; the human<lb/> breast.&#34;  Fortunately the occasions are very rare&#44;<lb/> when a Jewish father or a Jewish mother stifles in&#45;<lb/>&#45;nate sentiments&#44; and lets egotism assume a despotic<lb/> sway.  Exceedingly rare are the occasions&#44; when<lb/> men and women in whose view the blood of Abra&#45;<lb/>ham courses&#44; deny their sons and daughters food and<lb/> raiment&#44; a home and a screen from the evil of an<lb/> early exposure to the world&#39;s seductions.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p>I know parents who extended their protecting arm<lb/> beyond the limits which nature and the revealed<lb/> word have set.  I have heard of some who forgiving<lb/> and forgetting filial ingratitude&#44; melted with com&#45;<lb/>&#45;passion for their suffering progeny&#44; and drew them<lb/> to a throbbing breast bosom&#44; most gently and tenderly.<lb/>  No&#58; the Rabbinical denunciation against pitiless parents<lb/> does not apply to Israelites &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; cannot be said of any of us&#44; my fellow&#45;believers.<lb/>  But gladly admitting that a cruel father is a<lb/> monstrosity in our midst&#44; and a ruthless mother<lb/> almost an impossibility&#44; I nevertheless fear that<lb/> through want of thought we&#44; at times&#44; sin and as our<lb/> sages term it we put a stumbling block in the<lb/> way of our dear ones.  We are apt that to check with severity our children&#39;s buoyancy of spirits when young&#44; &#38; demand too much at their hands when advanced in years.  We are liable to If we become partial in our<lb/> conduct even perhaps inadvertently&#44; we and thus sow the choke weeds tha<lb/> in the field of domestic tranquility.  A renowned author<lb/> of our people&#44; recommends exceeding consideration lest<lb/> we ask of our son what is contrary to his inclination&#44;<lb/> and force out thereby a refusal&#44; attended with ill&#45;results.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="14"/>
            <p>Or we offer a provocation too great to be borne with<lb/> humility.  How beautiful&#44; again&#44; is the example<lb/> which the Hebrew Scriptures set upon this score.  Jacob<lb/> sees death approaching.  He sends for his Joseph&#59; and<lb/> entreats that he may not be suffered to lie after his demise<lb/> among idolaters.  The son swears that the paternal will<lb/> shall be religiously carried out&#44; despite any labor or fa&#45;<lb/>&#45;tigue connected with its performance.  The father recognizing<lb/> as a father favor what he might have expected claimed as an act<lb/> of obedience&#44; bows his feeble head before him who made the<lb/> solemn promise.  Again&#58; The viceroy of Egypt receives<lb/> the distressing tidings that his father&#39;s life is drawing to<lb/> its dissolution.  He hastens to Goshen.  Israel hears of his<lb/> coming&#59; he makes a strong effort and sets himself in bed.<lb/> as the Talmud pithily tells it to honor him who wore the<lb/> insignia of power.  Oh&#33; let us O parents learn wisdom.<lb/>  Let our sons and daughters behold in us not their masters<lb/> and mistresses but their friends&#44; their companions&#44; those in<lb/> whose association we delight above all others.  Let us<lb/> be considerate as we are affectionate&#44; and our offspring<lb/> may be our stay&#44; our joy and solace&#44; till the sweet ties that<lb/> bind us with what is mortal shall will be severed&#44; and we shall<lb/> join those who enjoy immortality in the presence of our Great Father.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
