<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF10_9</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_9_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_9_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_9_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_9_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_9_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_9_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_9_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_9_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_9_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_9_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_9_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_9_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_9_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_9_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_9_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_9_8v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_9_9r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_9_9v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_9_10r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_9_10v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_9_11r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_9_11v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_9_12r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_9_12v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_9_13r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_9_13v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_9_14r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_9_14v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_9_15r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_9_15v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_9_16r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_9_16v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_9_17r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_9_17v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>31 pages on 11 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>A few remarks on the duties incumbent on Israel<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>With trepidation I ascend this pulpit to address you<lb/> my Dear Brethren on this sacred day&#45;&#45;with excessive<lb/> fear I approach a place from which men distinguished<lb/> by talent and wisdoms have often imparted to you the<lb/> truths of our holy religion&#45;&#45;with dread I am seized&#44; when<lb/> I consider that I&#44; inexperienced as I am&#44; have undertaken<lb/> a task&#44; which requires deeper knowledge&#44; greater<lb/> eloquence and purer lips than I possess.<lb/></p>
            <p>But amidst all these uncertainties one idea encourages&#45;&#45;<lb/> yea&#45;&#45;animates me to proceed&#45;&#45;that if I lack talent&#44;<lb/> eloquence and erdut erudition&#44; the deep love which<lb/> I feel for you&#44; will supply me with words&#45;&#45;that<lb/> if I am&#44; through ignorance&#44; incapacitated from<lb/> <sic>equalling</sic> others in the choice of terms adapted to<lb/> the subject&#44; those will issue out of my mouth<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>will most sincerely represent the inmost sentiments<lb/> of my heart&#44; and above all convince you that in<lb/> venturing upon so arduous a matter as this&#44; no<lb/> other incentive guides me than to consecrate my<lb/> feeble understanding to the glory of the Lord God of Israel<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            <p>And He &#40;the Lord&#41; said to Abram&#44; know thou that thy<lb/> seed shall be strange in a land which is not theirs&#44; and<lb/> there they will be afflicted and subjugated four hundred<lb/> years&#45;&#45;but the nation whom they shall serve I will<lb/> Judge and afterwards shall come out with much property<lb/>  Is there any human creature who feels not touched at<lb/> the misery of his fellow&#45;being when fatal destiny levels<lb/> his condition with that of the brute&#63;  Is there<lb/> any human creature&#44; who seeing the sublimest work<lb/> of the Lord depressed and trampled upon&#44; has not been<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>moved with commiseration towards that unfortunate&#44;<lb/> and has not strongly desired to break asunder the fetters<lb/> which bound him&#63;  Oh&#33; how wretched and degrading<lb/> is it&#44; to that being created in the image of God&#44; to<lb/> bow that front on which is written in indelible characters<lb/> Thou shalt rule over all which is under heaven&#33;<lb/>  How ignoble for that mind&#44; which can&#44; as it were&#44; traverse<lb/> the boundless realms of space and fathom the depths<lb/> of science&#44; to sink under material labour&#33;<lb/></p>
            <p>When this noble work of the Lord loses the precious gift<lb/> of liberty&#44; when his neighbour bids him &#34;Bow down<lb/> at thy soul&#44; that we may go over it&#44;&#34; when man<lb/> from a free agent is turned into a mere machine&#44;<lb/> he descends from the rank in which nature had<lb/> stationed him&#44; he ceases from looking upon himself<lb/> as a part of that whole&#44; which constitutes<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Mankind&#44; all his efforts tend&#44; not to please his Maker<lb/> but him who can dispose of his life.  The yoke<lb/> bows his head&#44; he cannot raise his eyes above&#44; he<lb/> only sees objects whom he has learnt to deem the<lb/> issue of a different nature&#44; he no longer adores God&#44;<lb/> he only fears man.<lb/></p>
            <p>In this abject condition were our ancestors under<lb/> the scourge of Egypt&#44; when the Lord heard their<lb/> cries&#44; and their groans form under the rod of tyranny<lb/> reached his throne.  He remembered the covenant made with<lb/> Abraham&#44; and from the waters of the Nile he<lb/> drew forth their predestined liberator.  The daughter<lb/> of <sic>Pharow</sic> saw him exposed on the banks of the<lb/> river&#44; and in spite of the iniquitous order promulgated<lb/> by her father &#40;that all male children of the Hebrew<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>should be given a prey to the waves&#41; she could<lb/> not resist the inward voice which powerfully enjoined<lb/> her to save his life.  Moses bred up in<lb/> the court of <sic>Pharow</sic> did not imbibe the pernicious<lb/> maxims which prevailed there.  Although he did<lb/> not share the burdens of his brethren&#44; he beheld with<lb/> noble indignation their bondage&#44; and his love for the<lb/> sons of his people&#44; soon caused him to be exiled from<lb/> that court&#44; in which he had hitherto mixed with the<lb/> princes of Mizraim and her sages&#44; to become a servant<lb/> to Jethro the Medianite.<lb/></p>
            <p>But the hour for the emancipation of the Hebrews was<lb/> near at hand&#44; and Moses was the man to whom<lb/> the great mission was entrusted.<lb/></p>
            <p>The impure lips of the Monarch of Egypt blasphemed<lb/> &#34;he lifted up his eyes on high against the holy One<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>of Israel&#34; he <sic>rivetted</sic> still more strongly the chains<lb/> which bound the afflicted seed of Abraham&#44; he subjected<lb/> them to harder labour and more cruel inflictions&#44; saying<lb/> in his heart&#44; who shall wrest them from my hand&#63;<lb/>  &#34;But Egypt is man and not God&#34; says the prophet<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#45;&#45;The fetters of iron became like<lb/> stubble at the rebuke of God and that hand which<lb/> held them so tightly&#44; was compelled to <sic>forego</sic> its hold&#44;<lb/> when the arrows of the Almighty struck it.<lb/></p>
            <p>Ten times did the wondrous deeds of Heaven make<lb/> havoc in the land of Ham&#44; and ten times its<lb/> sovereign and its inhabitants refused to sh submit.<lb/>  &#34;Come no more into my presence&#44; for the day<lb/> that thou comest before me&#44; thou shalt die&#34; such<lb/> were the words of the tyrant to the man of God&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>unaware of the dreadful punishment which<lb/> impended over his doomed empire.  The same<lb/> might&#44; death&#44; which without discrimination multiplied<lb/> its victims among them Egyptians&#44; recalled <sic>Pharow</sic><lb/> to his senses.  The mandate which he had years before&#44;<lb/> so cruelly issued&#44; recoiled upon himself.  He saw babes<lb/> even of his people dy perish by thousands and by<lb/> tens of thousands in a single night&#44; and had no<lb/> other resort than to send for him&#44; whom he had<lb/> so lately and with so much contumely driven out<lb/> of his palace.  It was that very night that<lb/> the pillar of fire showed Israel the way out of<lb/> slavery and guided them on the path of freedom&#44;<lb/> leaving their inveterate foes mourning and awailing.<lb/>  But death could only for a moment abate the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>stubbornness of Mizraim.  As soon as its terrifying<lb/> scythe had ceased to reap its harvest among them&#44;<lb/> they saw with envy and anger a people whom<lb/> for centuries they had held in subjection&#44; marching<lb/> with rapid strides under the banner of liberty.<lb/>  &#34;Let us pursue them&#44; they said&#44; &#34;we will overtake<lb/> them&#44; and share the booty.&#34;  On the shore of<lb/> the Red&#45;Sea&#44; they found a power more formi&#45;<lb/>&#45;dable than any earthly army they had ever encountered<lb/>&#45;&#45;of the Lord of hosts who fought for his people&#45;&#45;<lb/> <sic>Pharow</sic> and his subjects had inhumanly<lb/> drowned the innocent sucklings of Israel&#44; and<lb/> <sic>Pharow</sic> and his vassals were engrafted <sic>engulphed</sic> in the<lb/> watery abyss.  The offspring of Abraham<lb/> saw the waters divide at their approach&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>and as suddenly close over the bodies of their<lb/> pursuing enemies.<lb/></p>
            <p>Thus&#44; was completed that glorious salvation&#44; predicted<lb/> to him who first adored the true God&#44; four hundred<lb/> years before it was fulfilled.<lb/></p>
            <p>With the circumstances which I have just narrated<lb/> you are all familiar&#44; I have only briefly alluded<lb/> to them&#44; in order to humbly draw some deductions<lb/> which naturally arise therefrom.<lb/></p>
            <p>Now&#44; were we while pondering on these supernatural<lb/> events which marked our enfranchisement from<lb/> Egyptian thraldom&#44; to ask ourselves&#44; why has Israel<lb/> been denominated the chosen people&#44; why to them<lb/> alone has the Deity vouchsafed to evince so many<lb/> irrefragable proofs of his love&#45;&#45;we would find<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>an explicit answer in the words of the Prophet<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;I have declared<lb/> and saved&#44; I have shown it&#44; when no strange God was<lb/> among you&#44; therefore ye are my witnesses&#44; says the<lb/> Lord&#44; that I am God.  In these concise but forcible words<lb/> of Isaiah we find the solution of all our queries.&#45;&#45;<lb/>  Whether in the East&#44; or in the West&#44; in the North or in<lb/> the South&#44; we are the witnesses of God&#39;s immeasurable<lb/> power.  In what places soever it may please Him<lb/> that we be sojourners&#44; we are &#91;Hebrew&#93; the work<lb/> of his hands which attests his glory.<lb/></p>
            <p>And indeed&#44; what nation of the earth can than<lb/> Israel better testify the magnificence of the Lord&#63;<lb/>  What people can than Israel better attest the<lb/> glory of the Creator&#63;  While obscurity covered<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>the earth&#44; and the people were involved in thick<lb/> darkness&#44; the Sun of truth shone brightly before the<lb/> eyes of our ancestors.&#45;&#45;while nations that had<lb/> attained the highest degree of knowledge&#44; remained<lb/> fettered in the chains of error&#44; our fore&#45;fathers acquired<lb/> at once physical and moral emancipation&#45;&#45;<lb/> while they suffered their sons and their daughters to<lb/> be immolated as victims to Molock and Milcow&#44;<lb/> Israel had learnt to adore the One only God&#44; father<lb/> of all created.<lb/></p>
            <p>And when we recall to our memory&#44; the words of<lb/> our sages&#44; can we any longer entertain doubts<lb/> touching the mission intrusted to us by the Almighty&#63;<lb/>  &#34;Beloved are Israel&#44; they say&#44; to whom was given<lb/> a valuable instrument&#44; but that love was<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p>surpassing&#44; which made it known that to them<lb/> had been given this valuable instrument&#44; wherewith<lb/> the world was created &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>&#45;&#45;&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Yes&#44; my brethren&#44; to us was this valuable instrument<lb/> &#40;the law&#41; intrusted&#44; to us that we might use it<lb/> for the benefit&#44; for the enlightenment&#44; for the consolation<lb/> of all mankind.  This precious instrument which<lb/> is the means of attaining temporal and spiritual<lb/> felicity&#44; the Almighty has deigned to commit<lb/> to our guardianship.  To maintain the promise<lb/> made to the patriarch Abraham&#44; he selected us<lb/> to be the depository of that knowledge&#44; which<lb/> diffused throughout the world will incontestably<lb/> one day produce its beneficial effects over<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="14"/>
            <p>the whole human race.<lb/></p>
            <p>For happiness&#44; in adversity&#44; in exile&#44; in martyrdom<lb/> we have a noble a sacred office to discharge.<lb/>  In happiness we will <sic>fulfil</sic> the office intrusted to<lb/> us&#44; by jealously preserving the treasure confided to<lb/> our vigilance&#44; by keeping it unaltered as He is<lb/> unalterable from whom it emanates.  Our praise&#45;worthy<lb/> conduct will be emulated by all nations&#44; who shall<lb/> say&#45;&#45;&#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Certainly this<lb/> great nation is a wise and an understanding people&#34;<lb/> In adversity&#44; we will <sic>fulfil</sic> it&#44; by enduring with<lb/> resignation the inflictions of the Almighty&#44; by<lb/> blessing that hand&#44; which even like the hand of<lb/> the father&#44; who chastises his sons&#44; punishes to correct.<lb/>  In exile&#44; our submission to the will of our Celestial<lb/> Father&#44; our unflinching adherence to his blessed laws&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="15"/>
            <p>our unshaken fidelity to those precepts that&#44; in the<lb/> midst of all our vicissitudes are a real comfort to our<lb/> hearts&#44; the memory of that lofty mission which we<lb/> are bound to accomplish in every climate in every<lb/> region&#44; the consciousness that although derided&#44;<lb/> scorned&#44; trampled on&#44; we are yet those in whom<lb/> eventually &#34;all the nations of the earth shall be blessed&#44;&#34;<lb/> will infuse in us so much fortitude&#44; so much<lb/> energy&#44; to convince all our brethren the offspring<lb/> of Adam&#44; of the truth which we profess&#44; of the<lb/> principles that are our sole guide and standard<lb/> wherever wer sojourn.<lb/></p>
            <p>In martyrdom&#44; we will perform the design with<lb/> which we were selected from all people&#44; we will<lb/> be the witnesses of our God and Father&#44; by meeting<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="16"/>
            <p>death with cheerfulness&#44; to sanctify his holy name<lb/> &#34;All nations shall understand&#44; that I am God&#44; says<lb/> the Lord&#44; when I shall be sanctified by you in their<lb/> eyes&#34;&#45;&#45;The greatest token of gratitude that<lb/> we can evince towards the Almighty&#44; for the<lb/> glorious and beneficent purpose to which he has<lb/> destined our lives&#44; is&#44; when required by his inscrutable<lb/> orders&#44; to sacrifice&#44; with serenity of mind&#44; with unmoved<lb/> resignation&#44; our bodies to the development of that<lb/> sublimest knowledge confided to our care.  Yes&#44; to become<lb/> martyrs for the noblest of all causes&#45;&#45;for the triumph<lb/> of truth over falsehood.&#45;&#45;The pages which<lb/> narrates the history of our nation teem with the<lb/> blood of those illustrious martyrs&#44; who inspired by<lb/> these same feelings&#44; when put to the terrible alternative<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="17"/>
            <p>of choosing between the most cruel torments&#44; and the<lb/> denial of their faith&#44; when placed between glorious death<lb/> and ignominious life&#44; did not hesitate to embrace<lb/> the former&#44; thus teaching man&#44; with what a superna&#45;<lb/>&#45;tural power the Almighty can endue his creature&#44;<lb/> who promptly offers himself to his sacred service<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; We read in the talmud treatise Berachat &#34;When the hour<lb/> arrived for <sic>Rabby</sic> Hackib&#224;&#44; to perish&#44; amongst others&#44; as<lb/> a victim of his attachment to the law of god&#44; it was<lb/> the time of for reading the &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#45;&#45;The instruments of<lb/> iron which tore his flesh&#44; were incapable of diverting<lb/> his mind from his God.&#45;&#45;He read the &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#45;&#45;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="18"/>
            <p>His disciples astounded at so much fortitude and<lb/> religious perseverance&#44; evinced <sic>supprise</sic>.  The <sic>Rabby</sic> said<lb/> unto them.  I have all my days longed to prove that I<lb/> do love God more than I love life&#44; now that the moment<lb/> of trial is arrived shall I not prove my faith by dying<lb/> for it&#63;  He continued the recital of &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#45;&#45;with his last<lb/> breath avouching the unity of God.&#45;&#45;But history<lb/> teaches us also that<lb/> that martyrdom has never proved sterile&#45;&#45;men die&#44;<lb/> but ideas are eternal&#44; as eternal is He who endowed his<lb/> creatures with the faculty of conceiving them.  On the<lb/> soil washed by the blood of martyrs&#44; they fructify&#44; they<lb/> grow fast&#44; and like the fabulous <sic>poenix</sic> pass through<lb/> the fire unscathed&#44; receiving new vigour and new youth.<lb/>  Truth may be persecuted&#44; anathematized&#44; but if upheld<lb/> with heroic efforts&#44; it cannot fail to irradiate the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="19"/>
            <p>whole human race.<lb/></p> 
            <p>It is incumbent on us then to uphold the truth<lb/> of which we are the heirs and trustees.  Like the apple<lb/> of the eye&#44; it <sic>behoves</sic> us&#44; O congregation of Jacob&#33; to<lb/> keep the heritage of our fathers&#44; that we may transmit<lb/> it in its integrity&#44; when they happy day predicted by the<lb/> prophet shall come to pass &#34;that the earth shall be<lb/> full of the knowledge of the Lord&#44; as the waters cover<lb/> the sea &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#45;&#45;<lb/></p>
            <p>We are then the basis of that broad edifice&#44; under<lb/> the roof of which&#44; all mankind will resort and find a<lb/> shelter&#59; and as such ought we not to join hand<lb/> in hand in brotherly love&#63;  Ought we not convinced as<lb/> we are of the truth of God&#39;s holy law imparted to<lb/> us&#44; and to us solely&#44; devoutly to consecrate our lives<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="20"/>
            <p>to the <sic>practise</sic> of the duties contained therein&#63;  We &#40;if<lb/> I be allowed this trivial comparison&#41; like the miser<lb/> who assiduously watches over the heap of gold&#44; that<lb/> he has accumulated&#44; and who he is never fatigued by<lb/> reckoning it lest it be lessened&#44; must unremittingly<lb/> watch over this treasure &#40;the holy law&#41; confided to us&#44; and<lb/> <sic>indefetegably</sic> attend to the various rites that it prescribes.<lb/>  These rites&#44; which were enacted with the view of diverting<lb/> our minds from sin&#44; while occupied in the worship of<lb/> God Almighty&#44; these rites instituted to perpetuate in<lb/> every breast a feeling of reverence and awe towards<lb/> our Divine Protector&#44; if we were to minutely consider<lb/> we would also discover in them the source of every domestic<lb/></p> <p>enjoyment.&#45;&#45;Let us for a moment&#44;<lb/> dwell upon those which are observed in the present<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="21"/>
            <p>festival.&#45;&#45;Every head of a family in his respective<lb/> house&#44; surrounded by objects dear to his soul&#44; sits<lb/> at table&#44; to be not to gratify his appetites&#44; but<lb/> to recall to the minds of them around him&#44; by the<lb/> very eatables&#44; which his fatherly hand distributes among<lb/> them&#44; the manifold favours of the Deity in behalf<lb/> of his chosen people.&#45;&#45;All which he sees<lb/> bears testimony of the Lord&#39;s imperishable decree that<lb/> the offspring of Abraham should keep these holy days&#44;<lb/> throughout their generation for an everlasting statute.<lb/>  The belief that he professes&#44; he inculcates on his children<lb/> He expounds to them the wondrous circumstances which<lb/> occasioned the observance of these rites&#59; he explains<lb/> to them their own origin&#44; their eventful history and<lb/> the mission they have to <sic>fulfil</sic>.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="22"/>
            <p>He makes his children partakers of the Divine Grace&#44;<lb/> by initiating them in his holy service.<lb/></p>
            <p>Thus they early learn to regard him as the author of their<lb/> temporal spiritual as well as temporal felicity.  Betimes&#44; they<lb/> are impressed with a sense of love mixed with fear&#44;<lb/> of esteem and gratitude for him&#44; who nourishes both their<lb/> bodies and souls.&#45;&#45;for him whose anxious cares tend to<lb/> conciliate in their favor the affection of God and men<lb/> Their demeanour towards their parent&#44; is not a blind<lb/> submission to his orders&#44; which decreases with years&#44; and<lb/> sometimes becomes a real apathy&#44; but it is an eagerness<lb/> in fulfilling his desires&#44; in evincing with <sic>anabated</sic><lb/> exertion their thankfulness to him.  Hence an intercourse<lb/> of reciprocal friendship&#44; if I may call it so&#44; is formed<lb/> between father and son&#44; each vying with the other<lb/> in the discharge of his duties.&#45;&#45;Union and concord<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="23"/>
            <p>Vice are promoted among the various members of<lb/> the family.  Vice cannot display its heinous sway<lb/> over them&#44; for they have fenced themselves with a<lb/> powerful buckler&#45;&#45;religion and virtue.<lb/></p>
            <p>Thus&#44; my dear brethren&#44; does the strict performance of<lb/> those external forms&#44; which may apparently be deemed<lb/> of minor importance&#44; contribute in a very efficacious<lb/> mode to the internal happiness of families.<lb/></p>
            <p>To them also we are indebted for our unchanged national&#45;<lb/>&#45;ity throughout a long series of dreadful persecutions&#59; and<lb/> they moreover remind us of that most essential object<lb/> which we ought constantly to keep in mind while<lb/> performing them any action&#45;&#45;namely love and gratitude<lb/> towards our Creator and Father.&#45;&#45;So long<lb/> as this feeling swells our breasts&#44; so long as it<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="24"/>
            <p>governs our actions&#44; we cannot sin&#44; we cannot do<lb/> wrong&#44; it infallibly leads to righteousness and conse&#45;<lb/>&#45;quently to real happiness.  For who is truly happy<lb/> but he who in investigating the inmost recesses of his<lb/> hearts&#44; discovers that all his actions have been directed<lb/> by the love of God.&#34;  It is to foster this divine love&#44;<lb/> which is conducive to our temporal and eternal felicity<lb/> that most of the commandments of the law are intend&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed&#45;&#45;and gratitude which is but a step to love is<lb/> obviously and explicitly declared to be the object of all<lb/> the sacred rites attached to the present festivals.<lb/></p>
                <p>And by our sincerely acting in accordance with them&#44; we will<lb/> surely hasten the glorious moment vaticinated by the prophet<lb/> Zechariah &#34;When many people and mighty nations<lb/> &#40;recognizing the truth of our holy religion&#41; shall come to seek the<lb/> Lord of hosts in Jerusalem&#44; and to address to<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="25"/>
                <p>Him their prayers and supplications.&#45;&#45;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="26"/>
                <p>Dear Children<lb/></p>
                <p>I cannot allow this day of recreation to elapse without<lb/> addressing to you a few words which I trust you will listen to with<lb/> an attentive ear&#44; in order that on quitting this spot&#44; you<lb/> may be impressed with a higher notion touching your day&#39;s<lb/> diversion than that you had when you repaired to it&#59;<lb/> in order that amidst your amusements you may not forget<lb/> your duties towards God and men&#44; the performance of which<lb/> must be as it were the hinge on which all human actions<lb/> must turn.&#45;&#45;I read on your countenances the<lb/> pleasure that this day has afforded you&#44; whilst indulging<lb/> in innocent sports and honest pastime&#45;&#45;I rejoice at it.<lb/>  But do you know to whom you are indebted for it&#44; what<lb/> is the object of it&#44; and what it <sic>behoves</sic> you to do after<lb/> it&#63;  These three points on which I purpose to detain you<lb/> a few moments&#44; will form the theme of my short address.<lb/>  I need it <sic>unecessary</sic> to dwell at length on the first&#44;<lb/> your own eyes see here&#44; witnessing your sports some of<lb/> those generous individuals&#44; who with <sic>indefetigable</sic> exterior<lb/> continue to procure you not only a religious and civil education<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="27"/>
                <p>not only a supply for your wants by stretching forth their chari&#45;<lb/>&#45;table hand to the appeal of your parents when in need&#44; but they<lb/> moreover grant you occasionally a holiday&#44; which you may entirely<lb/> devote to the refreshment of your minds and bodies.&#45;&#45;It is to them&#44;<lb/> it is to their liberality then that you owe the relaxation which<lb/> you have enjoyed this day.  The second point&#44; that is the know&#45;<lb/>&#45;ledge of the object which this holiday has&#44; I will briefly ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;pound to you.  Two principal faculties distinguish man<lb/> from irrational animals&#45;&#45;speech and reason.  These<lb/> two gifts with which the Almighty endued the first Man&#44;<lb/> and which have reverted to his offspring&#44; are the source of all<lb/> noble enjoyments.  They place us in the loftiest rank of<lb/> the creation&#44;&#45;&#45;through the former &#40;speech&#41; we communi&#45;<lb/>&#45;cate with our fellow&#45;beings&#44; open with them an intercourse<lb/> of mutual love&#44; understand their griefs griefs and endeavour<lb/> to sooth them.  The latter &#40;reason&#41; is&#44; if I be allowed<lb/> this comparison&#44; the pillar of fire which must enlighten us<lb/> in obscurity and lead us securely through the vicissitudes that<lb/> we may undergo during our life time.  It is a <sic>counsellor</sic><lb/> that the Deity has infused within us&#44; that it may<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="28"/>
                <p>advise us&#44; and curb the impetuous emotions of the heart&#44; which<lb/> is sometimes liable to lead us astray.  It hence we<lb/> infer the necessity of consulting it incessantly&#44; and again to let<lb/> all our doings proceed from an accurate examination of it.<lb/>  Our food&#44; our sleep&#44; our work&#44; our sports&#44; yes&#44; even our sports<lb/> must be directed by reason.  It will teach us that these<lb/> actions which alternately perform&#44; must tend to a sole purpose&#44;<lb/> that their drift must be a but a compact one&#44;&#45;&#45;that of<lb/> preserving a sound body and mind to be able to serve our<lb/> Celestial father by a continual practice of his dictates.<lb/>  It is this idea which I desire to inculcate in your minds&#44; so<lb/> that amidst your amusements you should never forget<lb/> the object of them&#44; which is the same that those generous<lb/> persons who have afford them to you&#44; have in view.<lb/>  Let the day of rest be followed by many days of unremit&#45;<lb/>&#45;ting study&#44; strive with the best means with which the<lb/> Almighty has gifted you to advance in your learning&#44; earnestly<lb/> endeavour to become a useful members of society at large&#44;<lb/> and you will be worthy of the care spent upon you.<lb/>  The third and last point which remains to be discussed&#44;<lb/> concerns the obligations incumbent on you towards your<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="29"/>
                <p>superiors and benefactors.  A long discourse&#44; would not<lb/> suffice to acquainted you to with them&#44; for they are sundry<lb/> and diverse in nature&#44; but as I lack time&#44; because I promised I would not<lb/> detain you long&#44; to dilate on every one of them&#44; I will<lb/> remind you of one&#44; of the most essential&#44; of that which I repute<lb/> as the key that opens the door to the <sic>fulfilment</sic> of all others.<lb/>  I mean gratitude.  Just consider an instant what<lb/> would have befallen you&#44; when you first saw the light&#44;<lb/> if your parents had abandoned you&#44; if at your first cries<lb/> your mother had not eagerly opened her breast to satisfy<lb/> your wants.  Death would have been the sure conse&#45;<lb/>&#45;quence&#44; yet that death&#44; believe me&#44; were preferable<lb/> to a life dragged on as irrational beings&#44; devoted devoid<lb/> of any rudiment of knowledge&#44; and consequently incapable<lb/> of elevating itself above the sensual habits which we<lb/> in common in other animals.  Greatly is to be pitied<lb/> that unhappy man who has not received education&#44;<lb/> but on the other hand he is extremely to be blamed&#44; who<lb/> has slighted it when he had opportunity to attain<lb/> it.<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="30"/>
                <p>He renounces the endowments of nature&#44; degrades himself<lb/> in the presence of his fellow&#45;creatures&#44; and above all insults<lb/> with so disgraceful a demeanour that beneficent Being&#44;<lb/> who has so liberally conferred on him the blessing of<lb/> intellect.  I doubt not but you will admit as well<lb/> as I&#44; that such a conduct would justly draw upon us<lb/> general contempt&#44; and that whoever should refractorily<lb/> pursue this untoward course&#44; would deserve severe punishments&#44;<lb/> but it is not sufficient to discern the evil&#44; we must<lb/> be continually on our guard to eschew it lest once insinuated into<lb/> our mind it lead us into a way of error and vice.<lb/></p>
                <p>And how can you avoid it&#44; but through a sound edu&#45;<lb/>&#45;cation&#44; such as you receive in your respective schools&#63;<lb/>  Sublime is then&#44; my dear children&#44; the charity bestowed<lb/> upon you&#44; for it averts sin from you&#44; it affords you the<lb/> means of honestly earning your daily maintenance&#44; and it<lb/> makes of you useful members of society.  And ought you<lb/> not to acknowledge this benefit&#44; ought you not in<lb/> fervent prayer to beseech Almighty God to pour over<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="31"/>
                <p>your superiors a shower of &#91;&#63;&#93; an everlasting bliss happiness.<lb/>  Oh yes&#44; I will join you&#44; in this over&#45;flowing of you sincere<lb/> feelings&#44; and in our sacred tongue crave the aid of God<lb/> over you and over your benefactors.<lb/></p>
                
                <p>The hebrew prayer follows<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
