<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF4_6</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1893" source="" attested="yes">1893</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_6_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_6_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_6_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_6_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_6_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_6_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_6_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_6_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_6_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_6_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_6_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_6_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET.<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;1893<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>The character of the Shunammite<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>A typical Jewess stood before my mind&#39;s eye this<lb/> morning.  I looked&#44; perhaps I might discover<lb/> a genius&#44; a new Deborah invoking God&#39;s<lb/> salvation in poetic strains&#59; a Huldale chas&#45;<lb/>&#45;tising sin with a prophetic rod.  The woman<lb/> I saw was neither.  Nor did she speak in<lb/> such accents as the woman her predecessor of Tekoa&#45;styled &#44;dulled in<lb/> our Scriptures &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;a wise woman&#44;&#34; spoke&#59;<lb/> nor even in the manner as that a Beruriah of the<lb/> Talmud would have made herself heard.  Yet&#44; the<lb/> Shunammite was great&#44;&#95;so are we assured by<lb/> the sacred historian &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Have you<lb/> traced the lives of that greatness&#63;  Follow me and you will<lb/> be shown them.  There stands her house.  The<lb/> front door twins upon its hinges. and It frequently opens to<lb/> welcome the stranger&#44; who need rest and food &#38; rest.<lb/>  A worthy descendant of Sarah&#44; who encouraged<lb/> and helped her husband in the exercise of kindly<lb/> hospitality&#44; the mistress of that house governed it<lb/> her home by the rules of unstinted generosity.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>We would certainly consider her an &#91;Hebrew&#93; and praise her as such if she only<lb/> responded to the appeal of creatures who begged stood asked felt<lb/> the want of for a meal&#44; because for kindness is nobleness <sic>enobles</sic> human nature&#44; but our<lb/> commendation must increase proportionately to<lb/> the higher degree of largeheartedness that she<lb/> manifested.  Let us look again&#58; you we are placed face<lb/> to face with an exceptional character&#44; one in whose veins the blood of the<lb/> righteous founder of our people copiously flowed.  Like<lb/> Abraham&#44; who begged pilgrims to be allowed<lb/> to entertain them &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44;<lb/> so that &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;the great woman&#34; of Shunem&#44;<lb/> urged Elisha never to pass by her dwelling place&#44;<lb/> without entering to be greeted as a most honored<lb/> quest.  The prophet accepted  &#91;Hebrew&#93; That is a patriarchal trait of which we of the God of Abraham&#44; may rightly boast&#44; &#91;Hebrew&#93; the imitation of which by &#91;&#63;&#93; may well be our boast made by us&#44; I say<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; the seed of Abraham the friend of God.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  But work<lb/> ye now the influence of a wife&#44; whose sentiments are<lb/> thoroughly Jewish Abrahamic.  It is agreed on all hands that<lb/> the Shunammite was not distinguished for the<lb/> possession of qualities&#44; which lifted her far<lb/> intellectually far above her sisters in faith.<lb/>  Judging her fro by the record lelf left in Holy Writ&#44;<lb/> I would not belittle her&#44; if I said that she was<lb/> simply a modest&#44; an exceedingly retiring woman&#59;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>She made making no <sic>pretention</sic> to learning&#59; she had having<lb/> no ambition to shine in society.  Her fire side set the<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; all aglow with love for domestic virtues.  In her<lb/> habitation she the Shunammite did <sic>exall</sic> many&#45;&#45;not in fashionable soir&#233;es&#44; but acts of practical goodness.  Her woman&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly intuition discovered that Elisha was more than<lb/> any ordinary guest upon whom she bestowed kind<lb/> attention.  &#34;Better than a man&#44; a woman can dis&#45;<lb/>tinguish the character of those who deserve to be treated<lb/> most hospitably&#44;&#34; write the Rabbis &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Som She had soon learnt that the spirit of God rested<lb/> upon Elijah&#39;s faithful attendant&#59; that&#44; like the<lb/> master he whose mantle had fallen upon his shoulder&#44; the disciple journeyed from city to city<lb/> in the interest of Israel&#39;s belief.  That woman &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> whose greatness consisted in the practice exercise of broad wide<lb/> beneficence&#44; had a request to make of her husband.<lb/>  We are not told of the man&#39;s circumstances.  Indirectly we<lb/> can infer that he was a prosperous farmer&#44; tilling<lb/> the ground and hiring others to help him in his work.<lb/>  Still&#44; what his wife asked may have appeared<lb/> in his sight to his mind novel and extraordinary.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>He should have a room built in his own premises<lb/> and furnished with the necessary objects of comfort<lb/> for the exclusive use of Elisha.  His holy vocation&#44;<lb/> his trials in the prosecution of his arduous duties&#44; de&#45;<lb/>&#45;manded that token of deep signal appreciation.  Now&#44;<lb/> I gladly confess that even in our matter of fact<lb/> generation times&#44; the number of Jewesses who devote their<lb/> thoughts to charitable endeavours is con beyond<lb/> calculation.  I shall not be guilty of the offence<lb/> which some occupants of the pulpit commit&#44;<lb/> when&#44; similarly to Isaiah&#44; who denounced the<lb/> luxurious extravagance of the female sex of his<lb/> own days&#44; depict our maidens and matrons in<lb/> repulsive colors as being solely as wedded to corruptive fashion&#44; to<lb/> seductive self&#45;admiration&#44; to outdoors diversions with at the neglect of home &#91;&#63;&#93;.<lb/>  Too unjustly &#91;&#63;&#93; is the condemnation.  Not because<lb/> wrong does exist in that direction&#44; and many not a few follow<lb/> it to the rain of families and the ultimate<lb/> sinking of healt hand reputation&#44; ought we to<lb/> deny that a vast amount of what is sequally unusually supremely<lb/> laudable&#44; is accomplished by self&#45;denying<lb/> daughters of the Hebrew race.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Nevertheless&#44; I could scarcely assert that the<lb/> Shunammite of that unsophisticated age&#44; could<lb/> vastly very largely find now counterparts of her disposition.  I<lb/> mean Jewesses who honor piety and sacred learning to<lb/> the point of giving offering the possessor thereof a home and<lb/> every mark of unstinted generosity.  As a reason<lb/> for the absence of the genuine veneration formerly<lb/> evinced towards the representatives and custodians<lb/> of religion&#44; it was lately declared that modern<lb/> rabbis are unworthy of it&#44; that they were too self&#45;important&#59; that they do not fail to<lb/> open a current of mutual sympathy&#44; which<lb/> ought to flow from the pulpit to the pews&#44; no&#45;<lb/>&#45;tably among those who constitute the main<lb/> factors in the upbuilding of our <sic>hoseholds</sic>&#45;&#45;our<lb/> wives and mothers.  There may be some grain of truth<lb/> in the assertion charge&#44; but at all events our Haftorah clearly demonstrates<lb/> that the Shunemmite did not anticipate any<lb/> reciprocation to her exceeding benevolence.  She<lb/> was generous in obedience to her Jewish instincts&#59;<lb/> she was respectful because sacred knowledge<lb/> must elicit reverence&#44; or&#44; to say it with the Talmud&#44;<lb/> because such reverence&#44; such respect is offered to the Bestower of Wisdom is equivalent to the adoration of Him who is the Fountain Head of Knowledge.  &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Brethren.  I began my remarks by extolling the<lb/> Shunammite as a typical Jewess and her own<lb/> ingenerous words prove my description unmistakably<lb/> correct.  Elisha was alive to a sense of<lb/> deep gratitude.  Now could he make his generous<lb/> hostess understand realize that he did feel under great<lb/> obligation&#63;  That he was anxious to prove it his sentiments<lb/> by some personal exertions&#63;  He sent for the mistress<lb/> of the house&#44; in which he was so nobly welcomed&#44; and inquired whether his influence in high places could<lb/> be to her of some service.  He said &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> He said&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Behold thou has been careful for us with all this<lb/> care&#44; what can be done for thee&#63;  Wouldst thou be spoken<lb/> for to the king&#44; or to the captain of the army&#63;&#34;  You<lb/> have heard her answer&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;I dwell<lb/> among my own people&#34;.  Exemplary Jewess&#33;<lb/>  Thy retiring modesty&#44; is thy handsomest adornament.<lb/>  Thou cravest for nothing more beautiful.  My peo&#45;<lb/>&#45;ple are those in whose circle thou delightest preferest to move.<lb/>  That is the humble sphere thou hast chosen&#44; because it does not excite<lb/> against the petty jealousies and envy.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>To bask in the sunshine of political or social<lb/> greatness will not bring thee healthful warmth&#44;<lb/> but consuming heat.  Yes&#44; the Shunammite moved<lb/> within among her own however lowly their position circle.  To help the poor and the<lb/> stranger&#44; to make her husband the participant of her<lb/> goodly work&#44; to become the exponent of the virtues<lb/> of her race&#44; of the religion of her ancestors&#44; was her<lb/> ambition.  Her week&#91;sic&#63;&#93; days she sanctified by<lb/> deeds of active kindness&#59; the sabbath and festivals<lb/> she honored by imbibing pious instruction from the<lb/> lips of men fit to give instruction.  Look once more the child<lb/> so longed for&#44; so fondly loved&#44; has been taken home<lb/> to his mother to drop lifeless on her knees.  She must see the prophet<lb/> who had foretold her the happiness of which she<lb/> is suddenly deprived bereft.  She will not sadden grieve her<lb/> husband&#39;s heart by the grievous sorrowful tidings&#44; but requests<lb/> to leave him a short brief while&#44; that she may visit Elisha<lb/> at mount Carmel&#45;&#45;the famous spot where the trial<lb/> between false polytheism and the truth of the Unity&#44;<lb/> was made by Elijah&#44; and were where the disciples of the Tishbite met for holy<lb/> purposes.<lb/>  &#34;Wherefore art will thou going to him to say&#63;  It is can neither new<lb/> moon nor Sabbath&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>the husband inquired.  he knew that his wife devoted those days the Shunammite consecrated to her creed&#44;<lb/> days set apart by the Divine Legislator Moses and thy prophets for national &#91;&#63;&#93; &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#91;Hebrew&#93;.<lb/>  Never would she dare to be seen abroad on Sabbath and festivals unnecessarily&#44; never could she be met then in market places to making<lb/> purchases&#44; nor to driving abroad for recreation and thoughtlessly then flippantly riding in her carriage for<lb/> sport.  The association of those qualified to add<lb/> strength to her devotional nature she ther then sought&#44; their<lb/> advice she consulted in order to be confirmed in habits<lb/> of practical goodness&#44; which were for her the title&#44;<lb/> wherewith the Biblical historian has ennobled her&#44;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;A great woman&#34; Brethren.  Disclaiming<lb/> any approach to the character of the exalted being<lb/> whom the Shunammite generously entertained&#44; ex&#45;<lb/>pecting in no way services in the same direction at the<lb/> hands of Philadelphia Jewesses&#44; I nevertheless ardently<lb/> wish that my well meant counsel may secure to<lb/> many a one the title of &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;A great woman.&#34;<lb/>  I shall not urge just now a redoubling of unabated ef&#45;<lb/>&#45;forts in behalf of charity.  That essential pleading I may reserve for another<lb/> occasion.  But I would beg of my sisters in faith to hal&#45;<lb/>&#45;low Sabbaths and festivals&#44; never scandalizing God&#45;fear&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing Israelites by a demeanour that ill agrees with the<lb/> sanctity thereof&#44; but to set our men an example of right&#45;<lb/>&#45;eousness and make our homes a temple of religion&#44;<lb/> a seat of spirituality&#44; even the like that of the great<lb/> woman of Shuman.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
