<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Piza, D.; Piza, M.</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx5FF6_15</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Piza, D.; Piza, M.</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes">K. K. Sheerit Israel</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet></placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1890" source="" attested="yes">1890</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx5ff6_16_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx5ff6_16_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx5ff6_16_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx5ff6_16_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx5ff6_16_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx5ff6_16_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx5ff6_16_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx5ff6_16_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx5ff6_16_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx5ff6_16_5v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>5 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Gentlemen.	Sheerit Israel<lb/></p>
            <p>I regret that owing to ill health&#44; I<lb/> was unable to attend the last two meetings of<lb/> your Board&#59; and as I shall yet for some time be<lb/> thereby prevented from going out in the evening&#44; I<lb/> take the liberty of hereby calling your attention to a<lb/> few remarks&#44; which I otherwise intended to place<lb/> before you verbally&#44; &#38; which I consider particularly<lb/> needed at this juncture&#44; when a new election is<lb/> about to take place.<lb/></p>
            <p>Reviewing my connection with your honorable Board<lb/> for the last two years&#44; I regret to find that while<lb/> we have doubtless been working with the same end<lb/> in view&#44; the policy of the majority and mine have<lb/> been diametrically opposite.  Orthodoxy being our common<lb/> object&#44; I believe that the best method of attaining it<lb/> would be by the building up of our congregation<lb/> by attracting <sic>worshippers</sic> to its shrine by every lawful<lb/> means&#59; rather than by being guided by the fear that<lb/> by interesting our members in the synagogue services&#44;<lb/> we might induce them to introduce the so&#45;called<lb/> &#34;reform&#34; which undoubtedly has wrought so much<lb/> mischief in other congregations.  I would therefore here<lb/> indicate what I consider the actual essentials for<lb/> the promotion of spiritual life in ours&#45;&#45;One of the<lb/> most urgent needs of the moment is a competent<lb/> assistant <hi rend="underline">Hazan</hi> who would command the respect<lb/> and esteem of the congregation because he could<lb/> be relied upon to fulfill conscientiously his duties<lb/> as such&#44; and give his active attention to our<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Hebrew and religious school.  One at the<lb/> same time qualified to superintend a choir<lb/> which would lead congregational singing&#44; and<lb/> thus give dignity to the service of the synagogue.<lb/>  Another important consideration is the removal<lb/> of our synagogue to a location more conveniently<lb/> situated for the majority of our congregants.<lb/>  In my humble opinion it appears to be no correct<lb/> argument that the most of them ride on Sabbath<lb/> our duty as leaders of an orthodox congregation&#44; is<lb/> to discourage this habit.  Nor does it seem any any<lb/> more correct one&#44; that a few who do not ride on<lb/> that holy day&#44; are living in the vicinity of nine&#45;<lb/>teenth st&#59; for a pious minority are always expected<lb/> to make willing sacrifices for the general welfare.<lb/>  Neither can it be denied&#44; against these arguments&#44; for<lb/> non&#45;removal&#44; that in the several years in which our present<lb/> location has gradually become too distant for the young<lb/> and the aged&#44; not to mention those who may not be<lb/> in the most robust health&#44; they have had no alternative<lb/> but to ride&#44; or absent themselves from&#44; the house of God<lb/> if&#44; as staunch followers of our sublime liturgy they<lb/> cannot enjoy the same spirit of devotion among<lb/> <sic>brethern</sic> of another <hi rend="underline">minhag</hi>.  But another momentous<lb/> point that cannot be overlooked in this connection is&#44;<lb/> that there being no orthodox congregation centrally<lb/> located&#44; many of our members&#44; consulting their<lb/> convenience&#44; are induced to attend places of worship<lb/> whose forms and innovations we are endeavoring<lb/> to keep out of our own&#59; and that we are thus weaken&#45;<lb/>ing orthodoxy&#44; to the manifest advantage of &#34;reform.&#34;<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="3"/>
            <p>With regard to matters affecting the welfare of<lb/> Judaism in general&#44; it is not to be lost sight of<lb/> that&#44; occupying the highest standing among orthodox<lb/> congregations in America&#44; we are placed in a<lb/> responsible position.  Conservative congregations in<lb/> all parts of the country&#44; in search of <sic>ledarship</sic><lb/> out of the entanglement of &#34;reform&#34; naturally look<lb/> to us for such guidance.  Therefore whether or not<lb/> orthodoxy in this hemisphere is to rear its head in<lb/> the near future&#44; will depend a great deal on the<lb/> action we take in <sic>fulfilment</sic> of our duty.<lb/></p>
            <p>This congregation has the means to make its influence<lb/> felt&#59; and if by using a part of its finances&#44; we<lb/> should later be unable to show as much material<lb/> wealth as at present&#44; we would doubtless be in a<lb/> position to enjoy more spiritual prosperity.<lb/></p>
            <p>But even from a material point of view I am<lb/> sure we would not be the losers&#59; for whose piety<lb/> exits&#44; voluntary offerings are readily made for the<lb/> service of the Lord&#59; and the increased membership<lb/> which our congregation would attract by its honored<lb/> position as consistent Israelites&#44; would bring<lb/> abundant resources to its coffers&#59; and thus also<lb/> would God reward our good deeds.  I would have<lb/> been most happy&#44; gentlemen&#44; if I could have hoped<lb/> to be so fortunate as to enlist your sympathy and<lb/> support for my views of our congregational requirements&#44;<lb/> as above expressed.  In that case it would have<lb/> been my duty no less than my pleasure to make<lb/> diligent use of my very humble abilities&#44; in <sic>fulfilment</sic><lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="4"/>
            <p>of the responsibilities of the past which&#44; by a<lb/> very large vote&#44; I was called to feel&#44; two years ago.<lb/>  And I hope I have succeeded in attaining your<lb/> acknowledgment of having done my work conscientiously<lb/> while&#44; as already intimated&#44; I trust also to receive<lb/> your approval of the policy which I think ought<lb/> to be made the basis of activity in the incoming<lb/> administrative year.<lb/></p>
            <p>But having unfortunately had an adverse majority<lb/> against me in the past&#44; in what I consider such<lb/> essential matters&#44; I have much to my regret to<lb/> resign the office I now hold on your honorable Board.<lb/>  It has been a struggle with me to decide where my<lb/> duty lies&#59; for the resignation of a position so full<lb/> of honor in God&#39;s service&#44; might unwittingly indicate<lb/> a want of appreciation of His grace in calling me to<lb/> do His work in so important a congregation.<lb/>  And if I could have entertained any hope that by<lb/> perseverance I might later be able to win your<lb/> concurrence&#44; I would yet have hesitated before<lb/> expressing my <sic>determation</sic>.  But the fear that by<lb/> further debate on this and kindred subjects while<lb/> our views are in such opposite directions&#44; the<lb/> difference between us might on the contrary&#44; be<lb/> intensified&#45;&#45;which is a contingency carefully to be<lb/> avoided&#45;&#45;leads me to the decision that there is no<lb/> alternative.  Respectfully yours<lb/> &#40;signed&#41; D and M. Piza<lb/></p>
            <p>To the President and<lb/> Trustees of <hi rend="underline">K. K. Sheerit Israel</hi><lb/> New York.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Rev. Dr. S. Morais&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. 5th St.<lb/>
                Philadelphia.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
