<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF12</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1886-01" source="" attested="yes">4 January 1886</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff12_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff12_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff12_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff12_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff12_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff12_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff12_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff12_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff12_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff12_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff12_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff12_1_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>77</p>
            
            <p>On Moses Mendelssohn &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  At the ministerial conference held in<lb/> Baltimore towards the end of last October&#44; it was<lb/> proposed resolved that on the fourth of January&#44; a me&#45;<lb/>&#45;morial service be held in honor of Moses Men&#45;<lb/>&#45;delssohn&#44; for on that day&#44; the one hundred years<lb/> ago&#44; the revered Sage departed this life.  At a re&#45;<lb/>&#45;cent meeting of several of our city ministers&#44; I<lb/> moved that instead of the proposed united service&#45;<lb/>&#45;impracticable for various a number of cogent reasons&#45;&#45;each Jewish<lb/> pulpit should choose as a subject of discussion<lb/> on the Sabbath preceding the fourth&#44; the character<lb/> and works of the celebrated philosopher of Dessau.<lb/>  Now&#44; if I had never been offered before opportu&#45;<lb/>&#45;nities to speak in your presence of the German Isra&#45;<lb/>&#45;elite whom the literary world honors generates&#44; or if I believed<lb/> that to some of you his name is entirely new&#44;<lb/> I would tell of his humble parentage&#44; of his<lb/> poverty&#44; of his feeble body&#44; and of his mighty<lb/> struggle withal to gain knowledge.  But all know are aware<lb/> that Mendelssohn&#39;s father was only a writer and<lb/> vender of <sic>philacteries</sic>&#44; or Tephillin and similar objects&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>that his son could find scarcely enough<lb/> to eat procure a meal&#44; that at ten years of age he<lb/> became sickly and deformed&#44; that at fourteen he<lb/> left his native city in his eagerness to follow<lb/> his Hebrew Rabbinical teachers David Frankel to Berlin.  It is not<lb/> to the severe privations he bore&#44; that I wish to refer.<lb/>  Others have&#44; like Mendelssohn&#44; endured trying want and<lb/> a voluntary parting with home and its early<lb/> associations for the sake of learning.  But his&#45;<lb/>&#45;tory has rarely recorded instances of a lad who<lb/> studied in the face of popular frowning &#38; ridicule&#44; in the<lb/> certainty of never rising nationally or commu&#45;<lb/>&#45;nally.  For the Germany of the days of Men&#45;<lb/>&#45;delssohn was an engine of torture to the Jews.<lb/>  All combined to their injury.  The commonalty<lb/> hated men considered by declared held registered in their statute book as aliens&#44;<lb/> the socially elevated despised men who spoke a<lb/> language which was no language unintelligible beyond the ghettos.  An emperor<lb/> who made <sic>pretentions</sic> to lore and erudtion mental enlightenment&#59; and who<lb/> felt proud at being called &#34;the Great&#44;&#34; showed him&#45;<lb/>&#45;self contemptibly benefited and small in his dealings towards<lb/> his Hebrew subjects.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>When Frederick II of Prussia&#44; struck off the<lb/> name of Mendelssohn from among those the candidates who had<lb/> earned by a scientific writing a title to a mem&#45;<lb/>&#45;bership in the Berlin Academy&#44; the ruler proved<lb/> that he was overruled by vulgar prejudices.<lb/>  Worthy of remembrance is Mendelssohn&#39;s answer remark<lb/> on hearing of that injustice.  He said&#58; &#34;I have would<lb/> have been grieved if the Academy had refused me<lb/> admission.&#34;  Still&#44; it would be unfar I should commit a great wrong<lb/> to in condemning all Germans because of the narrow&#45; vile<lb/> mindedness bigotry and proscriptive laws of their country.<lb/>  Christians like Lessing&#44; Nicola&#239;&#44; Sulzer&#44; Dohm&#44;<lb/> who recognized merit where it existed are always<lb/> a glory to mankind in whatever nation they are met.  Through the broad mindedness &#38; noble hearted&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness of such Mendelssohn overcame the obstacles<lb/> which his religion unhappily placed against<lb/> the practical application of his wonderful powers&#44; and<lb/> the recognition of his genius.  Some of his<lb/> productions were borrowed in the manuscripts&#44; and<lb/> published&#44; without his knowledge&#44; by his admirer&#45;&#45;<lb/> the philosopher&#45;poet Ephraim Lessing.</p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Some were put in print because<lb/> circumstances forced them out.  When Lavater&#45;&#45;<lb/> the renowned Swiss Physiognomist&#45;&#45;who &#45;&#45;but a fanatic&#45;&#45;believing in<lb/> Mendelssohn&#39;s honesty incapable of evasions&#44; dared publicly to ask him<lb/> to prove Judaism true&#44; or become a Christian&#44; the<lb/> Hebrew Sage must unavoidably have replied<lb/> through the press to let all understand why he remained a Jew.  When the name of his dead<lb/> friend and benefactor&#44; the good Lessing&#44; was blackened<lb/> by with the accusation of atheism of or Spinosism&#44; he must<lb/> have penned a defence and spread it far and<lb/> wide.  When the question of his people&#39;s eman&#45;<lb/>&#45;cipation was began to be agitated and the laws of Moses were<lb/> cited as precluding the consummation of the devoutly<lb/> wished for object&#44; Mendelssohn&#39;s devotion attachment to the<lb/> Torah demanded that he should compose his famous<lb/> double treatise called &#34;Jerusalem&#34;.  When the would be libe&#45;<lb/>&#45;rals of his days&#44; aping voltairianism denied God and immortality&#44;<lb/> one profoundly sincere in his creed&#44; could not hold<lb/> back the sentiments&#44; which have deservedly<lb/> won for him the name of modern Plato&#45;&#45;I<lb/> mean the publication of his Phaedon&#44; the most lurid<lb/> and comforting exponent of a life hereafter in the realms of<lb/> spirituality.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>His &#34;morgenstunden&#44;&#34; or morning hours&#44; written<lb/> specially for the education training of his son Joseph&#44;<lb/> was&#44; like his Phaedon&#44; intended to bring <sic>thoughful</sic><lb/> youths&#44; humbly to the footstool of an omni&#45;<lb/>&#45;potent Creator.  In none of his philosophical<lb/> productions&#44; the great Jew of Dessau aimed at no&#45;<lb/>&#45;toriety.  He was lifted up to fame by the lever<lb/> of his sterling merits&#44; despite a natural disposition<lb/> to retiredness&#44; which circumstances had intensified.<lb/>  But if Mendelssohn&#39;s had simply labors<lb/> to had simply enriched secular literature and purified and beautified<lb/> the German language&#44; this pulpit would not<lb/> resound with his praises at the centennial<lb/> period anniversary of his death.  A pardonable racial pride might<lb/> cause us individually to point to the Sage of Dessau&#44;<lb/> as to a luminous star in the world&#39;s literary horizon.  We might boast<lb/> that the despised Jew became the restorer of learning<lb/> and philosophy&#44; in the country even now shaming<lb/> itself by antisemitism.  Still Congregationally we<lb/> could not feel gratitude.  What claims had<lb/> then that Moses to our veneration&#63;  Have his exer&#45;<lb/>&#45;tions <sic>benefitted</sic> his people&#44; glorified his religion&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>I answer &#34;Yes&#44;&#34; even while &#34;Reformers&#34; set up Men&#45;<lb/>&#45;delssohn as their leaders in the march of Synagogual<lb/> devastation.  For it is absolutely false that the<lb/> philosopher was guilty of duplicity&#44; that he out&#45;<lb/>&#45;wardly conformed with the rules of his faith&#44; but<lb/> secretly taught to despise them.  This charge in&#45;<lb/>&#45;sinuated by the soi&#45;distant progressive Jews&#44; and<lb/> brought boldly forth by Christian authors&#44; I de&#45;<lb/>&#45;clare unfounded&#44; and &#91;&#63;&#93; unpardonably offensive to the<lb/> memory of a noble Jew.  What could have<lb/> deterred Mendelssohn&#44; who never exercised Rabbinical ecclesiastical<lb/> functions&#44; who never acted as Reader or Preacher to any congregation&#44; who never denied derived pecuniary advantages<lb/> from his coreligionists&#44; who lived in extreme poverty to the<lb/> age of his manhood&#44; and afterwards finally in comparative<lb/> ease as partner of a Jewish silk manufacturing Jew in Berlin&#44;<lb/> what could have deterred a man sought after by the<lb/> greatest celebrities of his time&#44; from acting with per&#45;<lb/>&#45;fect independence&#44; and severing his connection with<lb/> the Synagogue&#44; even if he disdained to openly accept bap&#45;<lb/>&#45;tism&#63;  Hypocrisy may be the cloak which they<lb/> put on&#44; who expect that the disguise will procure gain<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>or fame&#44; but it is utterly absurd to suppose that<lb/> a person who needs neither at the hands of his brothers<lb/> in faith&#44; will clothe himself in that fictitious garment.<lb/>  Upon this day of his memorial&#44; I pronounce Moses<lb/> Mendelssohn a typical Jew&#44; who loved all his fellow&#45;<lb/>&#45;mortals&#44; but clung to his oppressed race and to Israel&#39;s God.<lb/>  His translation of the Pentateuch&#44; and the his comment to several portions of<lb/> it&#44; he commented&#44; his poetical rhythmical version of the five books<lb/> of psalms&#44; his preface to Menasseh Ben Israel&#39;s &#34;Vin&#45;<lb/> dicae Judaeorum&#34;&#44; or &#34;Vindication of the Jews&#44;&#34; and the<lb/> rendition of the &#91;&#63;&#93; same volume in German&#44; his introduction to Ecclesiastes&#44; his contribu&#45;<lb/>&#45;tions to Hebrew periodicals&#44; were all inspired by his<lb/> attachment to his fellow believers and to the Sinaic<lb/> legislation.  That a people unused<lb/> to a language which the Christian community<lb/> spoke&#44; should interpret Mendelssohn&#39;s productions<lb/> as an approximation to gentilism&#44; we can scar&#45;<lb/>&#45;cely wonder&#59; that his association with the poets<lb/> and thinkers of Germany&#44; should have aroused<lb/> suspicion among his ostracised coreligionists&#44; can&#45;<lb/>&#45;not occasion a surprise&#44; but none of his multifarious<lb/> writings betray a devotion departure from the Law and traditions.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>All his actions evince a spirit of humility which<lb/> finds its outflow in the education of the untutored and<lb/> the social amelioration of the lowly.  I shall<lb/> not allow the apostasy of his descendants to asperse tarnish<lb/> the character of their glorious sire.  Exceedingly pain&#45;<lb/>&#45;ful to me is the thought that the children and<lb/> grand&#45;children of Moses Mendelssohn swerved from<lb/> the path which he undeviatingly followed&#59; molli&#45;<lb/>&#45;fying it is to me as well as sorrowful that ambition to shine within<lb/> a circle unopen to the Jew&#44; robbed us of men and<lb/> women who would have shed lustre upon the Syna&#45;<lb/>&#45;gogue.  Still I will always emphatically repel with force<lb/> the accusation that the in his teachings and example&#44; of the<lb/> most honored Jew of the eighteenth century&#44; had been<lb/> false to Israel&#39;s God.<lb/></p>
            <p>Mirabeau&#44; the world renowned French orator and revolutio&#45;<lb/> &#45;nist&#44; who made the personal acquaintance of<lb/> the Sage of Dessau wrote that a superior being towering intellect&#45;<lb/>&#45;ually to use superior above his contemporaries&#44; cast among born in a race un&#45;<lb/>&#45;justly kept in degradation&#44; without means&#44; sickly&#44;<lb/> timid&#44; compelled to engage in commercial pursuits&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>but who de in spite of all impediments became<lb/> a factor in the creation of a lan style lucid&#44; graceful<lb/> and energetic&#44; a being more noted for his virtues<lb/> than even for his learning&#44; who influenced his<lb/> fellow&#45;religionists for good&#44; and whom neither<lb/> bigotry nor calumny could reach injure&#44; deserves to<lb/> be known and honored.  Brethren.  In a Jewish free<lb/> school at Berlin a bust of the Sage of Dessau is set conspicuously.  Upon it the poet Ramler inscribed these<lb/> words on a bust of the Sage of Dessau&#58; this memorable motto&#58; &#34;Moses<lb/> Mendelssohn&#44; wise like as Socrates&#45;&#45;yet faithful<lb/> to the religion of his fathers&#45;&#45;as Socrates taught immortality<lb/> like Socrates&#44; and like him Socrates became immortal&#34;<lb/>  Let us then&#44; O children of the Lord he adored&#44; bear<lb/> this day his name on our lips with a blessing<lb/> and a prayer.  Let us beseech the Lord&#44; whose<lb/> word he expounded&#44; whose commands he observed&#44;<lb/> that the life of eternity which he made us deeply<lb/> to believe in&#44; may <sic>yeild</sic> for his soul ever renewed<lb/> delights among the saints and the pure&#44; who<lb/> contemplate the glories of the Universal Creator.<lb/>  &#40;Here follows the long Hashcabah&#41;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
