<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Voorsanger, Jacob</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx2FF8_39</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Voorsanger, Jacob</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Morais, Sabato</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Houston, TX</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1879-11" source="" attested="yes">17 November 1879</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx2ff8_39_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx2ff8_39_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx2ff8_39_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx2ff8_39_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx2ff8_39_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx2ff8_39_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx2ff8_39_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx2ff8_39_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx2ff8_39_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx2ff8_39_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx2ff8_39_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx2ff8_39_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 6 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>JACOB VOORSANGER&#44;<lb/>
                HOUSTON&#44;<lb/>
                TEXAS.<lb/></p>
            <p>November 17 1879<lb/></p>
            <p>Rev. S. Morais<lb/>
                Rev &#38; Dear Sir<lb/></p>
            <p>&#33;&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> What must you think of me&#63;  Two years have actually<lb/> passed over our heads without I have written to you.<lb/>  To defend the reasons&#44; why I have omitted to do so<lb/> would be utterly impossible simply because there<lb/> exists no reason.  I have not even the patent &#34;no<lb/> time&#34; excuse simply because I have had plenty of<lb/> time at my disposal.  What was the cause&#63;  Careless&#44;<lb/>ness&#44; culpable neglect of my best &#38; oldest friend in<lb/> this country.  I am prompted to make this candid<lb/> &#38; straightforward confession because I am convinced<lb/> that you rather have me tell the real truth than<lb/> to exculpate myself by paltry excuses.  And I<lb/> know your generous disposition so well&#44; that even<lb/> while writing this I feel confident that you<lb/> will pardon my neglect &#38; reinstate me in<lb/> <del>your</del> my place as one of your &#91;Hebrew&#93; for I<lb/></p> 
                
                <pb n="2"/>
            <p>JACOB VOORSANGER&#44;<lb/>
                HOUSTON&#44;<lb/>
                TEXAS.</p>										
            <p>2&#47;<lb/>
                187<lb/></p>
            <p>never forget &#91;Hebrew&#93; etc.  I will promise<lb/> that if you should forgive me&#44; I shall never<lb/> give you any cause to strike me off the list of<lb/> your friends &#38; correspondents &#91;Hebrew&#93;.<lb/>  Allow me to make one more confession.  Whilst my pen<lb/> was silent and I gave you cause to believe that I<lb/> had forgotten you&#44; you were never out of my thoughts.<lb/>  Not one act of my busy life was performed without<lb/> the consciousness that it would please you to hear that<lb/> I am benefitting my people.  Newspaper praise has no<lb/> weight with me.  And yet sometimes I was grateful<lb/> to <del>so</del> anyone who publicly praised my efforts&#44; for<lb/> I knew that you would be pleased to learn I pass<lb/> not my days in idleness.  My literary work&#44; when<lb/> published&#44; possessed for me double attraction for<lb/> I knew that it would pass your view &#38; you<lb/> would pass judgment upon it.  And I beg you to<lb/> believe that this is not a complimentary effusion<lb/> for the purpose of pleasing you&#44; but the honest ex&#44;<lb/>pression of a young man&#44; who will never forget<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="3"/>
            <p>JACOB VOORSANGER&#44;<lb/>
                HOUSTON&#44;<lb/>
                TEXAS.</p>
            <p>3&#47;<lb/>
                187<lb/></p>
            <p>that the first words of encouragement he ever heard<lb/> in this country were spoken by you And now let<lb/> me pass on to other matters.<lb/></p>
            <p>My life is a different one from what it has been.<lb/>  You have known me as the struggling &#91;Hebrew&#93; of a broken<lb/> down congregation&#44; as a youngster with some know&#44;<lb/>ledge &#38; no experience whatever.  Since that time four<lb/> years have passed.  It seems to me as if in these latter<lb/> years I have really become a man&#44; for I look upon<lb/> the world with entirely different eyes&#44; &#38; whilst<lb/> I cannot presume to yet possess all the requisite<lb/> experience I yet have learned a great deal of worldly<lb/> wisdom&#44; which enables me to better understand my<lb/> relations to the world &#38; my congregation than before.<lb/>  I have not neglected any opportunity to enrich my<lb/> mind &#38; cultivate my English.  I have become more<lb/> enthusiastic in our holy cause now that by care&#44;<lb/>ful study I better understand its tenets&#44; I know<lb/> it will please you when I assure you that not<lb/> a day passes by that I do not devote some time<lb/> to the study of Talmud&#44; Midrash &#38; the philoso&#44;<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="4"/>
            <p>JACOB VOORSANGER&#44;<lb/>
                HOUSTON&#44;<lb/>
                TEXAS.</p>
            <p>4&#47;<lb/>
                187<lb/></p>
            <p>phical authors.  After many months of application<lb/> to modern philosophy I have&#44; tried a confounded&#44; come<lb/> back to the &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#38; please God I will never<lb/> abandon them again.<lb/></p>
            <p>This leads me to a statement of my convictions.  It<lb/> is necessary&#44; imperatively so&#44; for I owe you an expla&#44;<lb/>nation of my conduct in abandoning time&#45;honored cus&#44;<lb/>toms for the new &#38; gaudy attire that has been re&#44;<lb/>commended as the &#34;latest style&#34; of worship.  I suffe&#44;<lb/>red in Washington from too much piety.  Every one of<lb/> my steps was watched&#44; the natural buoyancy of my<lb/> temperament was taken for wildness and my repen&#44;<lb/>ted expressions of tolerating innocent innovations as<lb/> a hankering after reform.  Hence my congregation&#44; com<lb/>posed as it was of Poles &#38; Russians of the blackest<lb/> type&#44; did not appreciate my efforts&#44; inasmuch<lb/> as we did not harmonize in matters of decorum<lb/> &#38; worship.  I soon grew tired of this constant watching<lb/> &#38; compulsory attendance at every occasion&#44; where<lb/> my services as minister were not required&#44; of the<lb/> cant &#38; hypocrisy&#44; which I perceived all around<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="5"/>
            <p>5&#41;<lb/></p>
            <p>me&#44; of the eternal quarrels about &#91;Hebrew&#93; etc.&#44; <del>which</del><lb/> <del>men</del> The latter <del>wer</del> especially were disgraceful<lb/> and so against every conception of &#91;Hebrew&#93; that<lb/> I did not hesitate to publicly express my disgust.<lb/>  Accordingly I hailed the opportunity of severing<lb/> my relations with them when the Providence com&#44;<lb/>munity just organized extended me a call which<lb/> I immediately accepted.  Yet I departed from W.<lb/> with a great deal of reluctance &#38; regret The splendid<lb/> congressional library&#44; the intercourse with such<lb/> men as Wolf&#44; Abrahams &#38; Solomons&#44; and the singu&#44;<lb/>larly courteous treatment of my congregation apart<lb/> of their bigoted &#38; intolerant conception of religion<lb/> are not to be found everywhere.  I left upon the advice<lb/> of my friends above mentioned who assured me<lb/> that the field in W. was too limited &#38; narrow &#38; that<lb/> my abilities &#91;&#63;&#93; deserved a better &#38; wider scope of<lb/> usefulness.  When arrived at Providence I found&#44; that<lb/> the congregation&#44; just organized&#44; had adopted Dr. Jas&#44;<lb/>trows Minhag.  I was not displeased with the change&#44;<lb/> especially as I had learned to believe that one may<lb/> affiliate with the reform wing of our denomination<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="6"/>
            <p>6&#41;<lb/></p>
            <p>without doing violence to his convictions.  I spent in<lb/> Providence  a year of blessing &#38; usefulness.  I became<lb/> the means of creating a good&#44; strong&#44; congregation out<lb/> of three or four independent Minyanim&#91;&#63;&#93; and infusing<lb/> in them some of the spirit of Judaism.  Not once during<lb/> the year had I been at variance with any one.  This re&#44;<lb/>quires some explanation.  I have been <sic>a</sic> guilty of a<lb/> great fault&#44; namely over&#91;&#63;&#93; finding so much the<lb/> &#91;&#63;&#93; culpable as it did not &#91;&#63;&#93; itself against<lb/> my superiors but against those whom I considered<lb/> my inferiors.  I candidly confess that much of the<lb/> unpleasantness between myself &#38; my congregations<lb/> in Philadelphia &#38; Washington was due to my selfish<lb/> determination to be right always and never to defer<lb/> to another&#39;s or let me say to a layman&#39;s opinion.<lb/>  And now&#44; that I am enabled to dispassionately<lb/> review my part career I know that very often<lb/> I have been lamentably in the wrong in many in&#44;<lb/>stances and opposed measures taken for my own<lb/> welfare from mere conceit &#38; <sic>stubborness</sic>.  When<lb/> I assumed charge of the Providence congregation<lb/> I resolved&#44; that&#44; God helping&#44; I should <del>be a</del><lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="7"/>
            <p>7&#41;<lb/></p>
            <p>endeavor to merit everybody&#39;s goodwill &#38; comport<lb/> myself with good&#45;will towards the rich &#38; the<lb/> lowly&#44; the learned &#38; the ignorant equally.  God<lb/> has blessed that resolution&#44; for I have left Providence<lb/> with all my people bidding me God speed at the<lb/> depot and an honest tear in many an eye because<lb/> I left.  I am honestly proud of the record I have<lb/> left in that city.  And now why did I again change<lb/> my position&#63;  Because I could not withstand<lb/> the temptation of becoming the minister of a large&#44;<lb/> influential congregation.  The Houston people had<lb/> been in correspondence with me for a long time &#38;<lb/> without an application on my part&#44; without a<lb/> trial&#44; without ever having seen me&#44; upon the re&#44;<lb/>ports of many prominent clergymen&#44; who had sug&#44;<lb/>gested my name to them&#44; they elected me their<lb/> minister.  I am too young <del>to</del> not to listen to the<lb/> voice of ambition.  Financially &#38; socially my pre&#44;<lb/>sent position is all my limited abilities deserve<lb/> &#38; I have every reason to thank God for the happy<lb/> change in my lot.  As to my labor here I cannot<lb/> refer to it without feeling profoundly moved that<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="8"/>
            <p>8&#41;<lb/></p>
            <p>I should have become the instrument of so much<lb/> good.  I shall upon another occasion tell you of the<lb/> work I have done here.  Suffice for the moment that<lb/> I am proud of my people.  I live in peace with every<lb/> one and I enjoy the confidence and esteem of my<lb/> constituents.  Unwittingly I have strayed from the<lb/> subject.  I was to tell you of my convictions &#38; I told<lb/> you of myself.  Careful study has confirmed my<lb/> convictions above mentioned that a reformer is a<lb/> Jew to all intents &#38; purposes.  The ceremonial law<lb/> is subject to eternal changes.  But whilst at present<lb/> I am officiating according to new rituals I am<lb/> by no means contented.  Reform has desported&#91;sic&#63;&#93; Judaism<lb/> of spirituality.  That is a crime&#44; <del>which</del> the penalty<lb/> of which is death.  Reform will die.  That means<lb/> the present wishy&#45;washy unmeaning substitute<lb/> for the grand ceremonies of by&#45;gone days has<lb/> to make place for &#91;crossed&#45;out&#93; something more sub&#44;<lb/>stantial&#44; something&#44; <del>in which</del> which will tend<lb/> to revive the spirituality in Judaism.  We are<lb/> drifting towards materialism&#44; not because we<lb/> disagree with our masters in their conception<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="9"/>
            <p>JACOB VOORSANER&#44;<lb/>
                HOUSTON&#44;
                TEXAS.</p>
            <p>9&#41;<lb/>
                187<lb/></p>
            <p>of the Deity but because we have desported&#91;sic&#63;&#93; our<lb/> worship from all the elements of spirituality.<lb/>  We must return to a form of worship that satis&#44;<lb/>fies the cravings of the heart&#44; whilst doing no<lb/> violence to the tenets of our faith.  Whatever that<lb/> form may be&#44; it shall have my entire <sic>adhaesion</sic><lb/> and I shall advocate it with all the strength<lb/> &#38; enthusiasm of which I am capable.  It stands<lb/> to reason that many of the old forms are obsolete&#44;<lb/> have died of actual old age&#44; but we will always<lb/> need an historical&#45;conservative form of worship.<lb/>  Nothing else will arouse and keep alive the dorm&#44;<lb/>ant piety of our people.<lb/></p>
            <p>I wish I could as conclusively speak of my<lb/> convictions upon purely <del>religious</del> theological matters.  Like<lb/> all young men who have a mind of their own<lb/> and a turn for investigation I have been swayed<lb/> by various opinions &#38; systems.  The longer I thought<lb/> the more I became confused.  Sometimes I would<lb/> deny one thing&#44; again another until I sadly<lb/> felt the need of some experienced mind to<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="10"/>
            <p>JACOB VOORSANGER&#44;<lb/>
                HOUSTON&#44;<lb/>
                TEXAS.</p>
            <p>10&#41;<lb/>
                187<lb/></p>
            <p>lead me back from the labyrinth of my &#91;crossed&#45;out&#93;<lb/> own creation.  I cannot say that all my doubts<lb/> are settled&#44; but I have so far become convinced<lb/> of all the grand &#91;crossed&#45;out&#93; truths of Judaism that I<lb/> say with Job &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  My speculations rested<lb/> mainly on &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Alb. And<lb/> the More&#39; have been of great help to me.  I can<lb/> now preach these doctrines without a single doubt.<lb/>  Upon minor matters I am not settled.  For instance<lb/> I have a strong tendency to believe with the Gnostics<lb/> that matter is eternal.  I cannot conceive that the<lb/> Deity&#44; eternal &#38; infinite&#44; should have been inactive<lb/> at any period of His existence.  The latter being<lb/> eternal&#44; his activity must have been the same<lb/> hence the emanations of His mind &#38; hands&#44; figu&#44;<lb/>ratively spoken&#44; are co&#45;existent with Himself.<lb/>  I have found in none of the Jewish authors any<lb/> allusion to this idea&#44; and I am lamentably<lb/> in doubt whether the doctrine is compatible<lb/> with Judaism.  I am not afraid&#44; that it will<lb/> interfere with my other settled convictions&#44; but<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="11"/>
            <p>11&#41;<lb/></p>
            <p>I am deeply anxious to remove from my mind eve&#44;<lb/>rything that tends to making me anything but<lb/> a real&#44; good Jehuda&#58; Will you keep me&#63;  By<lb/> setting my <del>a</del> doubts at rest you will but add<lb/> to the many obligations under which I am<lb/> placed by yourself.<lb/></p>
            <p>I must conclude now.  Were it not that I know<lb/> you to take a deep interest in all young men&#44;<lb/> who are willing to devote themselves to the cause<lb/> of which you are so faithful a servant I<lb/> would not have written so much.  As it is&#44; only<lb/> the fear of tiring you restrains me from writing<lb/> much more More than ever I feel the necessity<lb/> of consulting men&#44; my superiors in age and<lb/> wisdom&#44; and much will depend upon the result<lb/> of these consultations.  Last Thursday I was<lb/> twenty seven years of age&#44; and please God&#44;<lb/> a long life of usefulness is before me Thus far<lb/> all has been well.  My daily prayer is &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  With His aid all my doubts will be<lb/> finally set at rest &#38; there is a growing conviction<lb/> within me&#44; that <del>I we will</del> my name will yet<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="12"/>
            <p>12&#41;<lb/></p>
            <p>be on the great list of those who have deserved<lb/> well of their people because of eminent services<lb/> rendered.  I ask you to forget my past neglect.<lb/>  Send me again some of the golden words I have<lb/> been wont to receive from your honored pen.  I<lb/> assure you that words are inadequate to describe<lb/> my regard for yourself.<lb/></p>
            <p>A few lines about domestic affairs.  I am now the<lb/> happy father of those children.  A fourth one is coming<lb/> and when a son I shall ask you the honor of allowing<lb/> me to give him your name.  I am doing well financially<lb/> saving a little and making no debts.  Please ask<lb/> Henry to send me his book as soon as published.<lb/>  A friend of mine&#44; who rejoices in the rather odd<lb/> name of Koppel von Vloomberg&#44; desires to know<lb/> whether you think he is improving in style &#38; language.<lb/>  He says&#44; your opinion will have much weight with<lb/> him.  And now &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            <p>Jacob Voorsanger<lb/></p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
