<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF9_3</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_3_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_3_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_3_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_3_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_3_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_3_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_3_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_3_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_3_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_3_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_3_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_3_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>An address on the Parashat Vaihi<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Dear Brethren&#33;  In pondering on the section of this sabbath&#44; I am<lb/> reminded of a maxim of our sages in the Mishn&#225;.  It is the<lb/> following &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Know what to answer the unbe&#45;<lb/>liever&#34;.  The application of this Rabbinical apothegm on the<lb/> subject of my meditation&#44; will become apparent to those&#44; who have<lb/> read the productions of modern critics on our Bible&#59; for&#44; among<lb/> the passages&#44; which they pitilessly dissect in quest of imperfection blemishes&#44;<lb/> the prophetic benediction of Jacob has not escaped the poignancy<lb/> of their skeptical analysis.  They who carp at seeming in&#45;<lb/>&#45;congruities&#44; in order to disprove the authenticity of Holy Writ&#44;<lb/> could not concede the genuineness of the 49th Chapter of the book<lb/> of Genesis.  Guided by human criticism&#44; they not alone<lb/> deny the sainted patriarch the knowledge of future events&#44; but<lb/> likewise the ability of couching his words in a poetical strain.<lb/>  They cannot conceive how at an advanced age&#44; when the men&#45;<lb/>&#45;tal faculties are impaired&#44; and at a moment when every<lb/> thought should be centred in that of approaching death&#44;<lb/> an effusion so sublime could have been poured forth.<lb/>  Yet&#44; their reasoning is futile&#44; so futile that it does not require<lb/> much acumen&#44; to demonstrate it such.  We will not&#45;&#45;as upon<lb/> a former occasion&#45;&#45;descant on every historical incident<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>prognosticated in the blessing that Jacob bestowed on his children&#44;<lb/> conformably with their various aptitudes&#44; but not satisfied with a<lb/> mere cursory view of the context&#44; in order to discover whether it bears<lb/> indications of its authenticity.  And as we begin our research&#44;<lb/> the truth opens itself to our intellects in all its brightness <sic>radiancy</sic>; for&#44;<lb/> if the presumption of the hyper&#45;critics be admitted&#44; that the<lb/> chapter in question under consideration&#45;&#45;having emanated from the pen of an unknown<lb/> writer&#44; is of less antiquity than that universally credited&#44; a grave<lb/> question will suggest itself to our mind.  We would ask&#58; who&#44; at any<lb/> period subsequent to the selection of the twelve Israelitish tribes at<lb/> the fort of Sinai&#44; could have ventured to asperse the character of sundry<lb/> of the ancient fathers&#63;  Would Moses&#44; for instance&#44; have per&#45;<lb/>&#45;petuated the memory of the incestuous act committed by Reuben&#44;<lb/> which divested him of the right of primogeniture&#44; unless the right&#45;<lb/>&#45;eous patriarch had thus spoken and decreed &#34;Unstable as water thou<lb/> shalt not <sic>excell</sic>&#44; because thou wenttest up to thy father&#39;s couch&#63;&#34;...<lb/>  Would the divine legislator have imprecated the violence of Simeon&#44;<lb/>&#45;&#45;exhibited in vindication of his sister&#39;s outraged honor&#44;&#45;&#45;and more espe&#45;<lb/>&#45;cially that of Levy&#44; whose progeny had been constituted ministers<lb/> of the sanctuary&#44; if the hoary&#45;headed parent had not reverted<lb/> in terms of abhorrence to the demeanour of his two sons<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>towards the inhabitants of Shechem&#33;  O my soul come not unto their<lb/> secret&#44; O my honor&#44; be not united in their assemblage&#44; for in their<lb/> anger they slew man&#34;.  Is it not more probable&#44; on the con&#45;<lb/>&#45;trary&#44; that the tribe hallowed by the Lord&#44; would have erased a pas&#45;<lb/>&#45;sage unauthoritatively added in the law committed to their vigi&#45;<lb/>&#45;lance&#44; and which moreover cast obloquy on their progenitor&#63;<lb/>  And the later we date the origin of that beautiful episode&#44; which<lb/> adorns the last pages of Genesis&#44; the greater would be the diffi&#45;<lb/>&#45;culties to be encountered in reconciling it with any hypothesis of ours for&#44;<lb/> if on account of the poetical excellencies wherewith it abounds&#44; it<lb/> be transferred to the age of David and Solomon&#44; when the Hebrew<lb/> language had reached its apex&#44; we cannot fail to perceive that<lb/> the lofty and momentous position assigned to the Levites by those<lb/> two monarchs&#44; would have&#44; even more successfully&#44; guarded against<lb/> the interpolation.  The first book of Chronicles relates&#44; that<lb/> twenty four thousand of the descendants of Levy&#44; were to oversee<lb/> the work of the house of the Eternal&#44; that six thousand were<lb/> appointed officers and judges&#44; and many others had become guardians<lb/> and singers in the newly erected Temple.  And if we reflect that<lb/> also that vast number of individuals invested with sacerdotal func&#45;<lb/>&#45;tions&#44; derived their extraction from the same lineal stock&#44; we<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>cannot but acknowledge the impracticability of wedding spuriously engrafting aught<lb/> into the Pentateuch derogatory of their parentage.<lb/></p>
            <p>Should&#44; however&#44; the chapter at issue be ascribed to Helkiah the<lb/> priest&#44; whom many an infidel &#40;without a shadow of argument&#41;<lb/> charges with having concocted the entire law&#44; then the outpouring<lb/> of so much tenderness coined towards Joseph&#44; would indeed be alike<lb/> preposterous and ill&#45;timed.  How could the blessings intended<lb/> to have surpassed all those granted by Jacob&#39;s ancestors to their<lb/> progeny&#44; even &#91;Hebrew&#93; as highly &#34;as the utmost bounds of the<lb/> everlasting hills&#34;&#44; be applicable to a tribe&#44; whose glory the armies<lb/> of Assyria had&#44; a century before&#44; <sic>levelled</sic> with the earth&#63;  If an<lb/> augury expressed with so much fervour had been directed to Judah&#44;<lb/> that still <sic>weilded</sic> weilded a mighty power&#44; the suspicion wrongfully<lb/> attached to the high&#45;priest aforenamed&#44; might possess some plau&#45;<lb/>sibleness&#44; but when the wishes of for an incessant happiness are tendered to<lb/> a race already extinct in those his days&#44; it would be impious folly<lb/> to persist in &#91;&#63;&#93; imputing to Helkiah the invention of that passage.<lb/>  I am also fully aware that some among modern critics have<lb/> been so far misled in their skepticism&#44; as to call Ezra&#44; who restored<lb/> the captives of Chaldea to the promised land&#44; the sole author of<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>the Scriptures&#44; but without even pausing to refute an assertion un&#45;<lb/>&#45;tenable in every respect&#44; I would simply observe&#44; touching the subject<lb/> of our inquiry&#44; that the total dissimilarity of style and language be&#45;<lb/>&#45;tween the book named after that benefactor of our nation&#44; and the<lb/> patriarchal benediction&#44; would be superadded to the difficulties advan&#45;<lb/>&#45;ced above&#44; by a concurrence in the opinion just&#45;cited.  While the<lb/> 49th Chapter of Genesis&#45;&#45;irrespective of the prophetic verities it contains&#44;&#45;&#45;<lb/>is an admirable memento of terseness and elegance of diction&#44; the<lb/> writings of Ezra unmistakably display a decline of Hebrew literature<lb/> verily&#44; my friends&#33; that chapter placed but where it now stands&#44; would<lb/> be a plant which evinces its exotic nature by refusing to reward with<lb/> its blossoms our incessant cares.  No&#44; all the strenuous efforts of criticism<lb/> to stamp it as an interpolation&#44; have been abortive&#44; for&#44; if removed<lb/> to a period posterior to the demise of the righteous Jacob&#44; it loses its<lb/> significance and import.  Nor should our belief in its au&#45;<lb/>&#45;thenticity flag under the thought of the critical situation and decre&#45;<lb/>&#45;pitude of the speaker.  On the contrary&#44; that consideration ought to<lb/> lend new force unto it&#44; for&#44; doubtless&#44; the future of the twelve tribes his children and<lb/> their return to Canaan&#44; was not a transitory reflection&#44; but an idea<lb/> he cherished during the seventeen years of foreign sojourn&#44; by him<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>who had been promised &#34;to spread abroad to the west and to the east&#44; to<lb/> the north and to the south&#34;.  And the glorious <sic>imageries</sic> which had<lb/> so long enlivened his spirit&#44; when kindled by a divine afflatus&#44;<lb/> assumed at the solemn hour of death a prophetic vision&#44; and a lan&#45;<lb/>&#45;guage of superhuman ardour.<lb/></p>
            <p>This much have I deemed proper to say&#44; not because I fear that any<lb/> among my hearers may be tainted with the errors which the works<lb/> of modern critics have striven to disseminate&#44; but to warn my youth&#45;<lb/>ful junior brethren&#44; who may be induced to scan those pages&#44; not<lb/> to receive as a dictum their specious arguing&#44; for&#44; it is even as our<lb/> sages have told us&#44; that in the very biblical passage at which infidels cavil&#44;<lb/> a strong refutation can be found against them.  Yet&#44; it will not be by listening<lb/> to a weekly recital of the Pentateuch&#44; or to occasional strictures thereon&#44; that<lb/> will be discerned we shall detect the falsity of doctrines which have unhappily obtained in<lb/> our days many disciples&#44; it is by dint of serious studies.  Wherefore the<lb/> maxim of our Rabbins that I chose for my text is preceded by another<lb/> which recommends to ponder sedulously on the law of God &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; that is&#44; if it be thy wish to learn how to answer<lb/> the unbeliever&#44; thou must seek that knowledge in the volumes of<lb/> truth.  Oh&#33; that such desire were experienced by our youths&#44; for&#44; while<lb/> engaged to strengthen themselves in their ancestral faith&#44; they would<lb/> also grow wisely beneficent and spiritually religious&#33;&#33;&#33;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Beneficent Lord&#33;  On this Sabbath&#44; that we complete the perusal of that<lb/> heavenly volume&#44; wherein the lives of sainted men are truthfully recorded&#44;<lb/> we beseech thy mercy&#44; that the noble example they exhibit they become<lb/> the polar&#45;star&#44; by which we may be guided on earth.  May we&#44; when<lb/> reflecting on the godliness of Abraham our father&#44; on the &#91;&#63;&#93; of Isaac&#44;<lb/> and the pious fortitude of Jacob&#44; feel that we also are deeply imbued with<lb/> love for Thee&#44; with kindliness towards all thy creatures&#44; and with submission<lb/> to thy inscrutable will.  Grant O Lord&#33; that the virtues&#44; which<lb/> pre&#45;eminently adorned the character of Rachel&#39;s first darling son&#44; may<lb/> be engrafted in the breasts of our cherished offspring.  May they&#44; like<lb/> Joseph&#44; resist the allurements of the impious&#44; solely to follow integrity<lb/> and righteousness.  May his forgiving spirit&#44; and his profound<lb/> reverence be copied by our children.  Oh&#33; may the exquisite<lb/> feelings of filial attachment which that doting son of Jacob evinced<lb/> towards his aged parent&#44; sweeten also the winter of our years.<lb/>  His eagerness in anticipating the desires and wants of the <sic>decrepid</sic><lb/> patriarch&#44; his devotion in executing his last bidding&#44; the tokens of<lb/> homage which he paid to his memory&#44; may be the model&#44; on which<lb/> our sons and daughters&#44; will shape their demeanour towards the<lb/> authors of their life&#44; and the guardians of their tender age&#44; for&#44; then<lb/> shall we acknowledge ourselves happy&#44; when &#34;our seed shall be known<lb/> among the gentiles&#44; &#38; our offspring arming the people&#44; &#38; all that see them<lb/> shall proclaim that they are the progeny whom the Lord hath blessed&#34; Amen.<lb/></p>
            
            <p>May this be thy gracious will.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
