<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF15_3</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_3_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_3_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_3_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_3_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_3_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_3_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_3_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_3_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_3_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_3_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_3_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_3_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 3 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>For Sabbath Terumah<lb/>
                on the two&#45;fold object<lb/>
                of the Synagogue.<lb/>
                Prayer &#38; instruction.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  While striving searching for a text to a discourse&#44;<lb/> I met&#44; in a Rabbinical work&#44; with a singular anecdote.<lb/>  I will relate it.  A ship was sailing fast towards<lb/> the shores.  The foreign traders who had taken passage in it&#44;<lb/> discussed the quality of the goods&#44; from which they expected<lb/> to derive great profit.  Among the motley company&#44; one<lb/> person evinced no interest in the topic which elicited<lb/> general attention.  Questioned about the articles he had<lb/> brought from abroad&#44; he answered.  &#34;I have them with<lb/> me&#44; but they are hidden away&#34;  The incredulous querists<lb/> expressed then the wish to be shown the trunks which con&#45;<lb/>&#45;tained his <sic>merchandize</sic>. but He said. &#34;When we land&#44; I will<lb/> gratify your curiousity.&#34;  But his fellow&#45;passengers having<lb/> discovered that nothing belonging to that individual had been<lb/> stored away in the vessel&#44; made very merry over the<lb/> circumstance.  Their jesting&#44; however&#44; soon turned<lb/> into sorrow.  For&#44; having cast <sic>anckor</sic>; the officers of<lb/> the custom&#45;house&#44; seized all the goods&#44; and held them<lb/> on the plea of some irregularity in the dealing of<lb/> the owners.  Meanwhile&#44; he whom they had<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>considered a braggart&#44; had gone his way.  We meet him<lb/> again at a public assemblage.  It is in a Synagogue.<lb/>  A lectures he has delivered&#44; revealed the vast amount<lb/> of learning he possessed.  His hearers greatly edified&#44; offered<lb/> him tokens of respect&#44; and insured his future subsistence.<lb/>  The foreign traders&#44; being Jews&#44; repaired also to that Synagogue.<lb/>  Recognizing at what they saw&#44; the moral taught by the<lb/> man who said that what he owned was hidden away&#44; they<lb/> begged that he would exercise his influence in their behalf.<lb/>  for&#44; they acknowledged that what he claimed as his own&#44;<lb/> was so valuable that it could purchase again what<lb/> they had lost.<lb/></p>
            <p>Y It will surprise you&#44; dear Brethren&#44; that an anecdote<lb/> so curious should preface the section of this Sabbath.<lb/>  And I confess&#44; that I also&#44; perusing it in the Medrash&#44;<lb/> had to think long&#44; before I could discover that its bearing it<lb/> has thereupon.  But I believe I have succeeded.  Attend.<lb/>  Moses was commanded to bid our ancestors bring a tribute to<lb/> God.  The following is the wording of the sentence.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93; sp which literally rendered means&#44;<lb/> &#34;Speak to the children of Israel&#44; that they may fetch for<lb/> me a leave&#45;offering.&#34;  We will pause to reflect<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>The gift presented to the Deity must be a Terum&#224;&#44; that<lb/> is&#44; it must accomplish an object of a two&#45;fold character.<lb/>  It must honor God&#44; while debating the mind of the Donor&#58;<lb/> the Divine request had not been simply for a Nedabah&#44; but<lb/> for a Jeremah&#44; a term implying the idea of uplifting and exalting.<lb/>  But surely the glory of the Omnipotent cannot be inhanced&#44;<lb/> though we were to lay at the foot of His altar all the gold<lb/> of Ophar&#44; all the exhaustless treasures imbedded in the sea.<lb/>  For as He has declared by the mouth of the Psalmist &#34;The uni&#45;<lb/>&#45;verse and the fulness thereof are mine&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>  What was then the precious metal poured out into the crucible<lb/> intended to effect&#63;  What the cloth of the finest texture&#44; what<lb/> the rare timber&#44; the purest oil and the various other materials<lb/> beautifully proferred&#63;  We are told in the first part<lb/> of this week&#39;s lesson &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;They shall make<lb/> for me a sanctuary&#44; and I will dwell among them.&#34;  Whatever man gives freely and willingly must be appropriated<lb/> for the erection of a building dedicated entirely to the Lord.  Un&#45;<lb/>&#45;derstand &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Not to pander to man&#39;s<lb/> vanity.  Not for our material gratification&#59; but to sanctify<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>the Sovereign Creator&#44; by the spiritualizing of his creatures.<lb/>  That was the Teramah sought for.  The rearing of a Tabernacle&#44;<lb/> inspiring reverential awe&#44; and hence best calculated as a school<lb/> for the intellect and the soul.  The presence of the Monarch<lb/> in his palace&#44; must prepare the mind of the subjects<lb/> for the instruction therein imparted.<lb/></p>
            <p>Now&#44; precisely the same idea the Rabbinical parable I have<lb/> narrated means to convey.  Listen.  The value of earthly<lb/> goods is only imaginary. Today the anticipated gain may<lb/> be in within gra reach&#44; to morrow it will elude our Torah.<lb/>  For&#44; as the moralist exclaims &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;Wilt thou set thine eyes upon that which<lb/> is not&#63;  For verily&#44; riches will make themselves wings and fly<lb/> as an eagle toward heaven.&#34;  Yet&#44; it lies in our power to<lb/> give stability to that which is naturally fluctuating.<lb/>  The wealth employed to further our spiritual improvement&#44;<lb/> will be uplifted from a acquire permanency.  IT will be uplifted from a<lb/> fleeting and perishable state&#44; to a durable and indes&#45;<lb/>&#45;tructible condition.  It will be in very deed&#45;&#45;when so appropriated&#45;&#45;a &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;a leave&#45;offering&#44;&#34; exalting our soul to God. when it is so<lb/> appropriated.  But lest we be uncertain how to<lb/> bring that noble end about&#59; the allegory of the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Medrash points to the place where we should wend<lb/> our steps in order effectively to reach our goal&#59; even<lb/> to the dwelling of the Most High.  The construction of<lb/> an edifice in honor to the Lord must command our ample<lb/> means&#44; but our attendance must promote the object it<lb/> shall accomplish&#44; to really be what its name denotes.<lb/>  Let us fully comprehend the moral communicated  by the<lb/> teaching of our Bible and our Sages.  The sanctuary<lb/> must be a spot&#44; all the surroundings of which call forth<lb/> feelings of reverence&#44; and therefore most adapted for man<lb/> there to commune with his Maker&#59; but it must prove<lb/> likewise a sacred lever&#44; an impelling force urging<lb/> our spirit upward to the source of perfection.  The worship<lb/> must prepare the mind for the instruction&#44; the latter must<lb/> render the former practically useful.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;Happy the king&#44; who is extolled in his own<lb/> house&#44;&#34; say our Rabbins.  But empty would be that praise<lb/> bestowed on celestial attributes&#44; which we do not at all endeavour<lb/> to copy.  Observe well.  It is not stated in the Talmudical<lb/> tale&#44; that the scholarly <sic>traveller</sic> betook himself to the<lb/> Synagogue&#44; only to pray&#59; but to preach so that we might<lb/> infer therefrom the two&#45;fold object of which that habitation must<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>must attain in order to <sic>fulfil</sic> its high mission.<lb/></p>
                <p>Supplications and instruction must combine in order to achieve<lb/> the two double purposes it is intended to subserve.<lb/>  But&#44; has it ever occurred to you&#44; my Brethren&#33; that our Sy&#45;<lb/>&#45;nagogue has should have fallen short of the happy results it ought<lb/> to have <sic>yeilded</sic>&#63;  Were the preacher of the Talmudical<lb/> tale present&#44; with when many come in&#44; and others go out&#44;<lb/> methinks it would tax his abilities to the utmost&#44; to<lb/> speak in a manner acceptable to his hearers.  For&#44;<lb/> they would not&#44; most assuredly&#44; pass a vote of thanks<lb/> for his having alluded to their backslidings&#44; though ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;parent to a casual observer.  They would not make<lb/> him the recipient of munificent gifts for having<lb/> deprecated their tardiness&#44; their unnecessary converse&#44; or<lb/> the undisguised distaste they evince for the sermons.<lb/>  Still&#44; if he were true to his calling&#44; he would brave a<lb/> general displeasure&#44; to perform a sacred duty.<lb/>  He might perchance resort to the gentlest expressions&#59;<lb/> but he could not forbear censuring the joining of the worship<lb/> when half of the ritual has been rehearsed&#59; that degree<lb/> of restlessness&#44; which induces some to absent themselves<lb/> from these holy courts at a certain part of the service.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>and the presumption that causes some to think them&#45;<lb/>&#45;selves so perfect&#44; as to need neither instruction nor exhortations.<lb/>  Yet&#44; were that preacher with us&#44; I would gladly draw<lb/> his attention to that which Augurs will for the future of<lb/> our Synagogue.  I would especially point out a father<lb/> with his three sons&#44; whom I invariably count among the<lb/> earliest attendants&#44; and whose decorous demeanour during<lb/> the whole of the service may serve as a model&#44; which others<lb/> will strive to imitate.  Were that distinguished visitor<lb/> in our midst on this sabbath&#44; I would show the spiritual<lb/> joy pictured on that father&#39;s countenance&#44; whose eldest son<lb/> has been summoned to this sacred desk&#44; there to read the<lb/> word of God.  He would then agree with me in opinion<lb/> that&#44; when parents act consistently with their professions&#44;<lb/> and set an enforce by their example a respectful attitude in the dwelling<lb/> of the Almighty&#44; the synagogue which they frequent&#44;<lb/> bids fair to <sic>fulfil</sic> its noble aim.<lb/></p>
                <p>Y As to myself&#44; I cannot conceal that I deem the<lb/> application of the family of our Bar Mitzvah to this sy&#45;<lb/>&#45;nagogue an auspicious occurrence.  And I congratulate myself therein.<lb/>  Yes&#44; my dear young brother.  Your conduct has not<lb/> remained unnoticed.  I have seen and rejoiced that<lb/> you know&#44; when here&#44; before whom you stand&#44; even<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;before the King of Kings&#44; the Holy<lb/> one&#44; blessed be He.&#34;  Continue in the career you have<lb/> hitherto pursued.  Let no outside pressure cause you<lb/> to swerve.  I hail you the occasion which qualifies you to<lb/> be reckoned among the number with whom we may hold pu&#45;<lb/>&#45;blic worship.  You are doubly welcome&#44; because the paucity<lb/> of the members of your privileged tirbe&#44; denies us at times the<lb/> satisfaction of conforming to the ancient custom of calling first<lb/> to the Law&#44; a descendant of Aaron.  But your constant attend&#45;<lb/>&#45;ance will remove that difficulty.  Remember then your<lb/> noble extraction&#44; and let it keep you in the path of righteous&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness.  In the days of old&#59; you would have been entitled<lb/> to a daily support from the offerings which the faithful<lb/> brought to the Temple.  Seek now in the minor sanctuary<lb/> we have dedicated to Israel&#39;s God&#44; food for the mind&#44; aliment for<lb/> the soul.  Let your demeanour be an impetus to<lb/> your coevals to imitate it&#44; let it be a cause for admiration<lb/> among your seniors&#44; and let it be instrumental in render&#45;<lb/>ing this spot a true habitation of the Lord&#44; irradiated by<lb/> His divine presence&#44; as it is written&#44; &#34;They shall make&#44; for me a sanctuary&#44; and I will dwell among them.&#34;<lb/> Amen.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
