<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF15_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_1_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>On the existence of God.<lb/>
                1t<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#34;Be not rash with thy mouth&#44; and let not thy heart<lb/> be hasty to utter any thing before God&#44; for God is<lb/> in heaven&#44; and thou art upon earth&#44; therefore let thy<lb/> words be few.&#34;  Brethren&#33;  This advice of the oldest preacher<lb/> has sounded to me like a threat&#44; since my heart impelled<lb/> my lips to make a promise.  For to <sic>fulfil</sic> it worthily<lb/> of the object&#44; I must exercise more than ordinary care.<lb/>  I must weigh every sentence&#44; avoid a single utterance apt<lb/> to leave behind a doubt behind&#44; and choose only such expressions<lb/> as may briefly&#44; yet plainly and clearly explain the<lb/> point at issue.<lb/></p>
            <p>Am I equal to the undertaking&#63;  Have I not rather over&#45;<lb/>&#45;rated my powers&#44; and in my eagerness to serve the cause of<lb/> truth&#44; rendered myself liable to the charge of having tres&#45;<lb/>&#45;passed against the counsel of Ecclesiastes&#44; which I have<lb/> just cited&#63;  Yes&#58; I acknowledge it at the outset.  The<lb/> subject which you have a right to expect I shall now<lb/> argue lucidly and convincingly&#44; ill&#45;agrees with my na&#45;<lb/>&#45;ture.  Its discussion belongs to a man less open to out&#45;<lb/>&#45;ward impressions&#44; and more given to deep meditations.  To<lb/> reason on God&#44; to prove His existence by a line of logical<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>premises and conclusions is a trial&#44; aye&#44; a torture<lb/> to my soul.  &#34;I know that my Redeemer liveth&#34;.  I feel<lb/> His hand in each throbbing of my heart breast&#59; I hear His voice<lb/> in every sentiment that leads me to goodness&#44; but when<lb/> I attempting to point to the uncreated Spirit that fills<lb/> all space&#44; I experience a strength&#45;withering sensation seized my whole being.<lb/>  I have passed through that ordeal&#44; which you&#44; dear<lb/> young friends&#44; undergo.  There has been a time when I<lb/> also looked for palpable evidences&#44; which might support<lb/> my belief in God.  Then I would read with avidity all written reach of my intellect&#44; while<lb/> in quest of my object&#59; while expecting to satisfy my<lb/> thirst after a knowledge of the unknowable&#44; but years<lb/> and vicissitudes have made me understand better than<lb/> I could have learnt from finely constructed syllogisms<lb/> how closely interwoven is the idea of God with the idea<lb/> of personal and social virtue&#44; and hence of human happi&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness.  Judaism&#44; the religion which we profess&#44;<lb/> places this verity constantly before our eyes&#44; not by<lb/> philosophical dissertations&#44; but by historical lessons in their ingenuousness&#44; and<lb/> by maxims drawn form the fountain of experience.<lb/></p>
            <p>It is an error of Jewish writers&#44; who lived in the middle&#45;<lb/>ages among the Arabs&#44; to teach that the Scriptures com&#45;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>command a searching into metaphysics&#44; and that our<lb/> perfectibility depends on our overcoming difficulties<lb/> which stand in the way of a comprehension of the<lb/> essence of God and His government of the universe.<lb/>  I avow myself in this respect&#44; a the disciple of a thinker<lb/> of great originality&#44; who fought that error in the course<lb/> of his multifarious writings.  Samuel David Luzzatto&#44;<lb/> the unexcelled Hebraist&#44; and unbiased critic&#44; exposes the<lb/> wrong done by our philosophers to the multitudes&#44; who<lb/> are incapable of those profound investigations and who&#44; as<lb/> a consequence&#44; are put almost on a par with the beasts<lb/> that perish.  A great grievous wrong it is&#44; fro ma Jewish stand<lb/> point&#44; because it breeds contempt for the simple&#45;hearted<lb/> who correctly hold with the Bible that &#34;the beginning of<lb/> wisdom is to fear the Lord&#44;&#34; and with the Rabbis that &#34;the<lb/> completion of wisdom is to mend our evil doings and act practice<lb/> beneficence.&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>Till about the tenth century of the common era that<lb/> humanising imparting of the written and oral Law chiefly<lb/> occupied the thoughts of Israelites.  Speculative learning<lb/> scarcely entered into their studies.  I will not deny<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>that the teachings of Greek schools exercised<lb/> from time to time&#44; a powerful influence over some<lb/> Jewish minds.  But a system of philosophy among<lb/> our people did not exist before that period.  The<lb/> first to borrow it from the Arabs&#44; who in their<lb/> turn&#44; had mainly derived it from the Hellenists&#44;<lb/> was Seadyah&#44; a Jew born in native of Egypt and chosen<lb/> as President of a college in Persia&#44; where sacred li&#45;<lb/>terature greatly flourished.  That extraordinary<lb/> man who wrote extensively on various topics&#44; left in<lb/> the Arabic language a work&#44; which we know through<lb/> its Hebrew translation to have have born the title of &#34;Creeds and opinions.&#34;<lb/>  With that Sage&#44; however&#44; philosophy was never allowed to<lb/> usurp the highest authority.  She was never set up as clad with the apparel of<lb/> the mistress.  The Philosophy was employed merely to convey to men the mes&#45;<lb/>&#45;sages of religion&#44; in a manner which might find meet with<lb/> a ready acceptance among deep thinkers.  Unlike<lb/> many of his successors&#44; notably Gersonides in his<lb/> book called &#34;battles of the Lord&#44;&#34; our author did not ven&#45;<lb/>&#45;ture to prove too much.  In an introduction to<lb/> the first of his ten treatises&#44; he sensibly remarks that<lb/> they who read the principles he laid down&#44; must not look<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>for evidences which fall immediately under our<lb/> senses&#59; that he would simply give the result of his own<lb/> investigations meditations and that of others&#44; and appeal to reason<lb/> for an assent to his arguments.<lb/></p>
            <p>But since Seadyah penned his famous work&#44; which alone<lb/> of all his productions has found its way to the printing<lb/> press in its entirety&#44; the human mind has pressed forced itself for&#45;<lb/>&#45;ward and more forward still in its researches.  It has built<lb/> theories and overthrown them.  Again reared it has set up reared hypotheses &#38; theses which others which<lb/> seemed to defy attacks&#44; and afterwards cast them down as groundless.<lb/>  In its illimitable inquisitiveness&#44; the human mind has<lb/> pushed its inquiries beyond all bounds&#44; and because it<lb/> could not enter the Holy of Holies &#38; tear the veil&#44; which hides the infinite Crea&#45;<lb/>&#45;tor from the finite creature&#44; it has&#44; at times&#44; set up a divine<lb/> throne to Materialism.  Accordingly&#44; the world&#44; that<lb/> magnificent scene exhibited to all eyes in its vast pro magnitude<lb/> portions&#44; its order and beauty&#44; is the effect production of atoms<lb/> or invisible particles of matter which have existed eter&#45;<lb/>&#45;nally&#44; and which&#44; through the lapse of ages chance has<lb/> in the lapse of ages grouped together.  From that casual combination of<lb/> atoms or molecules&#44; sun and moon and stars and air<lb/> and water and the vegetable and the animal kingdoms<lb/> have emanated.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Let us ponder.  We are <sic>travelling</sic>.  Suddenly an edifice<lb/> of admirable architecture meets our vision.  We inspect<lb/> its interior&#44; and notice that its halls&#44; and drawing&#45;rooms&#44;<lb/> and chambers and kitchens answer exactly to the wants<lb/> of the inmates and are calculated to afford much comfort.<lb/>  What is the thought which first strikes the beholder&#63;<lb/>  I unhesitatingly say the thought which points to the<lb/> existence of a mind that designed and arranged the structure<lb/> suitably to the necessities of its occupants.  Should<lb/> one suggest then that perhaps some minute fragments<lb/> of a rock had fallen below&#44; and the small tiny stones stri&#45;<lb/>&#45;king against each other by some inexplicably inherent<lb/> force finally raised themselves into walls&#44; stretched themselves<lb/> down into floors&#44; and that by an equally fortunate com&#45;<lb/>&#45;bination some small fragments of a tree shaped themselves into ceilings<lb/> and doors and windows&#44; I could not consider such a one a philosopher<lb/> nor a free deep thinker&#44; but a middle brained fellow&#44; a fit object maniac&#44; whose intellect was shattered<lb/> for a mad house. in fighting against Reason.  Yet that is the theory which<lb/> several philosophers in ancient and modern times<lb/> have advanced concerning the noblest buildings of structures&#45;&#45;the universe&#45;&#45;&#44; and which they fain would that we <sic>perfer</sic><lb/> to the idea of a Supreme Intelligence reflected in nature&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>and the contemplation of which drew from a<lb/> prince of poetry and thought this soul&#45;elevating invo&#45;<lb/>&#45;cation &#34;How manifold are Thy works&#44; O Lord&#33; with wisdom<lb/> has Thou wrought them all&#44; the earth is full of Thy<lb/> riches.&#34;  To the belief which associates creation in its<lb/> symmetrical grandeur with the idea of an all&#45;directing God&#44;<lb/> we are given as a substitute the hypothesis of atoms as a substitute&#44; that<lb/> is&#44; the irrational supposition of particles of matter mo&#45; floating<lb/>&#45;ving in the immensity of space without any rule or guidance&#44;<lb/> but coming always together in a manner which their<lb/> contact might produce the object best suiting the<lb/> requirements of living beings.  Reason is lost wrecked in a<lb/> sea of bewilderment at the consideration of molecules<lb/> which by chance brought forth a countless variety<lb/> of things&#44; different in size&#44; in shape&#44; in quality&#44; in<lb/> appearance and purpose.  Senseless as was<lb/> the polytheism of the heathens&#44; who deified natural<lb/> forces&#44; and peopled the heavens with beings at variance<lb/> with each other&#44; and inciting their votaries by their<lb/> example to immorality and blood&#45;shed&#44; it was wisdom<lb/> itself when compared with the disbelief in the existence of a<lb/> Sovereign Mind&#44; and a belief in the <sic>marvellous</sic> action of<lb/> minute particles of matter.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>A French author who cannot be suspected of<lb/> orthodoxy has declared that without having absolutely<lb/> surrendered our reasoning mental faculties&#44; it is impossible to<lb/> become Atheists or deniers of a First Cause.  Beautifully have the Sages of<lb/> Israel illustrated this point&#44; when alluding to the mis&#45;<lb/>&#45;sion of our father Abraham.  In one of their legends&#44; they represent the faithful Hebrew in the guise of a<lb/> <sic>traveller</sic>.  He sees at a distance a palace splendidly<lb/> illuminated.  &#34;Can it be&#44;&#34; the asks pilgrims the wayfarer of himself&#44; &#34;that no power<lb/> has kindled those shining lights&#63;  It may remain concealed<lb/> to my vision&#44; but its existence cannot be doubted&#34;  Then<lb/> the owner owner of the palace disclosed appeared to stood before the seek&#45;<lb/>&#45;er of truth&#44; and bid him spread abroad the world&#45;redeeming<lb/> truth knowledge he had discovered possessed.<lb/></p>
            <p>This physical proof of the existence of God&#44; first dissemi&#45;<lb/>&#45;nated by the founder of our people&#44; and which scien&#45;<lb/>tists have termed &#34;teleology&#34;&#44; or argument from the ef&#45;<lb/>&#45;fect to the primary Cause&#44; will be further discussed in<lb/> my next lecture.  When announcing my intention<lb/> to deliver a series of discourses on the subject of which I<lb/> began to speak today and on kindred topics&#44; I promised<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>to be brief&#44; in order not to fatigue my hearers.<lb/>  That promise I now perform&#44; closing my remarks<lb/> with the words of the matchless orator of antiquity to his<lb/> contemporaries.  &#34;Lift up your eyes on high and behold<lb/> who has created those things&#44; who it is that brings them<lb/> out in order like a host&#44; who calls them all by name&#44;<lb/> &#38; through whose great power and infinite strength&#44; none<lb/> stands backward.&#34;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
