<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF5_18</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_18_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_18_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_18_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_18_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_18_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_18_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_18_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_18_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_18_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_18_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_18_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_18_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>June 94<lb/>
                Post&#45;Biblical<lb/>
                61<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Before the hottest part of the season sets in&#44; when I shall<lb/> suspend as usual my weekly addresses for a time&#45;&#45;as usual&#45;&#45;I wish<lb/> to conclude the sketch of the lifework of Joseph Albo&#44;<lb/> which I began to draw some several weeks ago.  In my<lb/> preceding lecture upon that illustrious sage of the fifteenth<lb/> cnetury&#44; I stated that after his having held a contro&#45;<lb/>&#45;versy at Tortosa&#44; in Spain&#44; in defence of our religion a&#45;<lb/>&#45;gainst with the apostate Joshua Larocca&#44; known as Jerome<lb/> of de Santa F&#233;&#44; Albo&#44; fearing the ill will formented by his op&#45;<lb/>&#45;ponent and being mentally exhausted&#44; chose to settle in Soria&#44; rather<lb/> than return to his native home at Monreal.  With a Later on&#44; when his<lb/> mind was more at ease&#44; he betook himself to the task of writ&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing his famous book&#44; which he called &#34;Sepher &#91;&#63;&#93;&#34;<lb/> or&#44; the book of creeds.  Now&#58; whenever it occurs to us to<lb/> speak of Jewish creeds&#44; we are unavoidably compelled<lb/> to allude to the great Maimonides&#44; for&#44; it was he who<lb/> first assumed to define what Jews must believe in&#44;<lb/> so that we may be saved.  He formulated the thirteen<lb/> creeds&#44; universally accepted by the Synagogue. for ages<lb/> But in the same manner as the literary productions of<lb/> that greatest among the great of our medieval Rabbis&#44;<lb/> occasioned long and severe disputations&#44; so his thirteen<lb/> creeds found in the middle ages controversialists strong and determined.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>I will mention&#44; in passing&#44; that Maimonides appears<lb/> to have wished desired to conform to the system of other religions&#44;<lb/> which profess articles of faith&#44; varying in number.  He<lb/> conceived&#44; that it would be an reflect honor to show that on Judaism&#44;<lb/> also to show that it is based upon certain cardinal doctrines.  The num&#45;<lb/>&#45;ber thirteen may have suggested itself to his mind by the<lb/> cer thirteen attributes of God&#44; which the Rabbis have<lb/> derived form that sentence in Exodus heard by Moses as a vision passed before him&#44; while<lb/> he stooding in the cleft of a rock at Sinai. as a vision passed<lb/> before him But the common notion that the hymn Igdal&#44;<lb/> embodying those thirteen creeds&#44; emanated from Maimonides<lb/> himself&#44; is evidently an error.  The author of that rhyth&#45;<lb/>&#45;mical composition was an Italian Jew of the fifteenth<lb/> century&#44; called Daniel Dayan.  Joseph Albo<lb/> arose to forcibly controvert the opinion of Maimonides.  He denied<lb/> the authority of the Sage of Cordova in declaring that who&#45;<lb/>&#45;soever does not subscribe to the dogmas which he laid<lb/> down&#44; as essential principles in Judaism&#44; is a heretic<lb/> and forfeits every right to a brotherly recognition among<lb/> the people of Israel.  Albo admits that<lb/> religion in general must have some fundamental doctrines<lb/> to stand upon&#59; but he insists that those doctrines are only<lb/> very few&#44; such as man&#39;s reason&#44; will accept at once&#44;<lb/> as indispensable to the maintenance of any persuasion and denomination.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>According to his judgment&#44; which he fortifies by<lb/> solid arguments&#44; every religion depends upon the belief<lb/> of in the existence of God a creative Power&#44; called God&#59;<lb/> upon the belief that God manifested His will through<lb/> nature and inspiration&#44; and upon the belief that God<lb/> commensurately rewards or punishes our actions.  Those<lb/> three principles our philosopher considers the foundation<lb/> stones upon which the fabric of religion is built.<lb/>  Nevertheless&#44; he concedes that from those three cardinal<lb/> points certain truths are evolved which have a claim to our credence.  For instance&#44; once<lb/> that we agree upon the existence of a Creator&#44; we virtually<lb/> agree that He is eternal&#44; having neither beginning nor<lb/> end&#59; that He is incorporeal&#44; for what is bodily&#44; must<lb/> necessarily decay and perish&#59; that He is a spiritual&#44; and<lb/> <sic>and</sic> and as a spirit He is invisible&#44; but fills all space<lb/> and sees us all&#59; that He is an absolute Unity&#44; for&#44; a<lb/> division of powers would imply weakness in Him who<lb/> must be Omnipotent&#44; in order to perform His sovereign<lb/> will on nations and individuals.  Joseph Albo&#39;s phi&#45;<lb/>&#45;losophy is free from the intricacies&#44; of characterizing that of several some of<lb/> his predecessors.  He does not attempt what Gersonides<lb/> notably ventured to do&#44; that is&#44; to forcibly drag the Scriptures<lb/> after his fanciful notions.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Albo was fearlessly orthodox&#44; respecting paying obeisance during paying deference neither<lb/> to Aristotle nor to Avicenna nor Averroes&#44; where Judaism<lb/> is concerned.  Clearly reasoning upon the second<lb/> principle which he enunciated&#44; namely&#44; God&#39;s<lb/> manifestation through nature and inspiration&#44; he<lb/> shows that the Revelation at Sinai was indispen&#45;<lb/>&#45;sable as a sanction to principles what is implanted in the<lb/> human breast&#45;&#45;love of virtue and abhorrence of vice.  The weakness of our nature sensations so apt<lb/> to leading us astray&#44; needed a mighty support&#44; and<lb/> Albo justly proves that none could be more power&#45;<lb/>&#45;ful than that the support which Moses and the prophets<lb/> have offered the world to check wrong&#44; uphold<lb/> right and promote the welfare of the social family.<lb/>  He contends that the son of Amram was endowed<lb/> with a knowledge of the Supreme above that of all<lb/> mortal beings&#44; and therefore what he proclaimed<lb/> in the name of his heavenly Master&#44; must be held<lb/> as an emanation divine.  Still&#44; Albo hazards the<lb/> opinion against Maimonides&#44; that it may please<lb/> the Author of the Torah to change His ordinances in<lb/> the same extraordinary manner as delivered in the<lb/> wilderness of Sinai.  To that idea&#44; the immortal<lb/> Mendelssohn gave his full assent in the course<lb/> of his famous treatise&#44; which he entitled Jerusalem&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Arguing on the third principle enunciated which he advanced&#44; Albo<lb/> tells us his conviction&#44; that God assigns to Jew and Gentile their<lb/> deserts&#44; with this distinction&#44; that whereas the Jew<lb/> is amenable for his obedience or disobedience of the affirm&#45;<lb/>&#45;ative and negative precepts of the Torah&#44; as far as compatible with<lb/> his residence beyond the limits of the Holy Land&#44; the<lb/> gentile is bound only by the moral code of the Pen&#45;<lb/>&#45;tateuch.  Albo makes the belief in a Messiah<lb/> and in the resurrection&#44; on the part of the Jew&#44;<lb/> as being connected with the third principle which he deems<lb/> an essential.  He sensibly argues that inas&#45;<lb/>&#45;much as the prophets foretold the permanence<lb/> of the Jewish people&#59; as a separate people&#44; it<lb/> obviously follows that their dispersion is only tem&#45;<lb/>&#45;porary and the fulfilment of the predictions concerning a return to<lb/> a national unification and a commanding posi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion among the families of nations&#44; must be waited<lb/> for religiously.  Our author scouts the idea<lb/> that the promise concerning our perpetuity&#44; means<lb/> simply our continuance as a religious distinct denomination<lb/> among many different denominations.  He<lb/> quotes extensively to fortify his views&#44; and among<lb/> other scriptural passages&#44; he cites Jeremiah in who re&#45;<lb/>&#45;says tells &#45;assures us so in the name of the infallible Lord&#58;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>&#34;Thus saith the Eternal&#44; that giveth the sun for a light<lb/> by day and the ordinances of the moon and of the stars<lb/> for a light by night&#44; who stirreth up the sea<lb/> that the waves thereof roar&#44; whose name is &#39;the Lord of hosts.&#39; is His<lb/> name  If those ordinances shall depart from before Me&#44;<lb/> then the seed of Israel also shall cease from being a<lb/> nation before Me for ever.&#34;  With regard to the<lb/> resurrection&#44; Albo is not quite so decidedly emphatic.  He admits<lb/> the power of God to rekindle life after it has become<lb/> extinct.  He refers to that effect to Holy Writ<lb/> and Talmud&#59; advances ideas pro and con&#44; and states that<lb/> in like manner as he could not explain the attractive properties<lb/> of the loadstone&#44; and many other phenomena&#44; he could not define the process of a bodily resur&#45;<lb/>rection obviously to our limited understanding.<lb/>  From the little which I have told&#44; it will be perceived<lb/> that the disagreement between Albo and Maimonides<lb/> consists mainly in the definition of what is a dogma&#44;<lb/> the denial of which should deserve public condemnation<lb/> as a heresy&#44; and expose the sinner to excommunication.<lb/>  Albo&#44; with a sense of justice&#44; that does his heart and<lb/> mind honor&#44; would not anathematize a Jew&#44; whose<lb/> ideas of God are not in full accord with the belief that<lb/> He is a perfect spirit&#44; or that He is an ever ex&#45;<lb/>isting Power that brought forth out of nothing the world in which<lb/> we live out of nothing&#44; solely by His infinite will.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>He would consider such one short sighted&#44; faulty&#44; misguided by his mind.<lb/>  Albo would not say that a Jew who refuses<lb/> to believe in our restoration to Zion&#44; or in a bodily corporeal<lb/> return of the departed upon earth&#44; ought to be<lb/> hated and chased away from the Congregation.  In<lb/> his judgment&#44; Maimonides committed a grievous<lb/> error in giving expression to such thoughts&#44; and we&#44;<lb/> with the profoundest veneration for the Sage of<lb/> Cordova&#44; we must side with the Sage of Monreal.<lb/>  God&#44; inspiration&#44; and a retribution to our deeds are&#44;<lb/> in all truth&#44; the cardinal doctrines derived from the<lb/> teaching of the Chief of all prophets&#44; who stood<lb/> with his soul in the closest communion with the<lb/> soul of the Universe.  Albo&#39;s work is<lb/> divided into four large treatises.  The first&#44; hinging<lb/> upon the signification of the word Ikhar&#44; or &#34;dogma&#34;<lb/> contains twenty six chapters.  The second&#44; explaining<lb/> how we should understand the ex self existence<lb/> of God has thirty one chapters.  The third&#44; discussing<lb/> Revelation consists of thirty seven chapters and the<lb/> fourth&#44; referring to reward and punishment is the<lb/> largest of all&#44; having fifty four chapters&#44; all of them the treatises<lb/> being written in an easy style as plain and intelligible as<lb/> the character of that philosophical&#45;Hebraic compo&#45;<lb/>&#45;sition would possibly allow.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>I cannot part with that deservedly celebrated<lb/> teacher in Israel&#44; without quoting the closing remarks<lb/> of his Sepher Ikkarin&#44; or &#34;book of creeds.&#34;<lb/>  According to Joseph Albo&#44; the threefold priestly<lb/> benediction is to be so understood interpreted &#34;The Lord bless<lb/> thee and preserve thee&#44;&#34; is a prayer for temporal<lb/> happiness&#45;&#45;health and prosperity.  &#34;The Lord make<lb/> His face shine upon thee and be gracious unto thee&#34; is<lb/> a petition for mental acquirements&#45;&#45;a knowledge&#44;<lb/> useful to ourselves and our neighbors.  &#34;The Lord lift<lb/> up His countenance towards thee and grant thee peace&#34;<lb/> is a supplication for spiritual gifts&#45;&#45;contentment<lb/> and tranquility sweetening this life and procuring the<lb/> enjoyments of a life to come.  May all the three<lb/> be our allotment.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
