<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF5_8</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1895" source="" attested="yes">1895</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_8_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_8_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_8_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_8_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_8_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_8_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_8_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_8_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_8_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_8_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_8_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_8_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_8_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_8_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_8_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_8_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>95<lb/>
                On Parashat Chay&#233; Sarah<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Brethren.  Let no one imagine that my utter&#45;<lb/>&#45;ances proceed from ill&#45;will or prejudice.  I declare that<lb/> I entertain no unkind feelings towards the rest of<lb/> the world&#44; who differs from my people on doctrin&#45;<lb/>&#45;al points.  Views which I may&#44; at times&#44; have<lb/> advanced during my ministration in the present capa&#45;<lb/>&#45;city&#44; may have seemed to some a contradiction of the<lb/> assertion which I make this moment&#44; but I say it<lb/> in all sincerity&#59; I am fraternally disposed to&#45;<lb/>&#45;wards every creature&#44; who bears the impress of the<lb/> One Sovereign Creator.  It should be re&#45;<lb/>&#45;membered&#44; however&#44; that I have a mission to per&#45;<lb/>form&#44; and I understand that mission to be the<lb/> elevation of Judaism.  Hear me then.  An<lb/> error is held among all classes&#44; which&#44; like many errors<lb/> that have become inveterate&#44; it is extremely difficult to<lb/> root out.  If the error existed only among non&#45;<lb/>Israelites&#44; I might abstain altogether from attending<lb/> to it&#44; for my voice does not reach further than the<lb/> Synagogue.  It is universally known that Christ&#45;<lb/>&#45;ians imbibe very early in life the idea that the creed by<lb/> which they swear is spiritually superior to any other.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>To convince them against a notion&#44; grown with their<lb/> growth would be more than an Israelite can anticipate.<lb/>  But the error is held by some who share with me<lb/> descent and we would suppose principles also.<lb/>  The error is discussed by them with the confidence ari&#45;<lb/>&#45;sing from a full persuasion that it is not a mis&#45;<lb/>&#45;apprehension but a fact.  Now in reading the<lb/> section of this Sabbath&#44; I was forcibly reminded of the<lb/> injustice done to Judaism&#44; even by persons who ought<lb/> to understand it rightly and be ready to rebut argu&#45;<lb/>&#45;ments prejudicial to it.  Yet&#44; it is not unusual<lb/> to hear Jews&#44; and especially Jewesses&#44; assert that the<lb/> laws which govern us tend to lower the standing of<lb/> women born in Israel&#59; that&#44; according to our books&#44; wo&#45;<lb/>&#45;man has no value save as a kitchen drudge or a parlor<lb/> sport.  In contrast with that&#44; the praises of the re&#45;<lb/>&#45;ligion of the man of Nazareth are sounded&#44; for having<lb/> liberated woman&#59; for having delivered her from a moral<lb/> bondage and raised her to equality in every respect<lb/> with man.  No clearer wrong can be committed<lb/> than that of identifying Judaism with woman&#39;s<lb/> enslavement&#44; and crediting Christianity with woman&#39;s<lb/> emancipation.  I am perfectly aware that current<lb/> literature has contributed immeasurably to the spreading<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>of that huge blunder&#44; so that few stop to con&#45;<lb/>&#45;sider&#44; whether an idea so very general is a reality&#44;<lb/> or a mere fiction.  I was cut to the quick&#59; deeply<lb/> mortified by a recent criticism&#44; which would create<lb/> the impression that Jewish women in Mendelssohn&#39;s<lb/> time embraced the dominant belief because our belief<lb/> ostracized them.  &#34;Shades of our Moses IIi&#59; our philoso&#45;<lb/>&#45;pher&#44; our expositor&#44; our defender&#33;  Rise not enwrapped<lb/> in shame but clothed in honor.  Silence the detractors.  Tell<lb/> that neither thy example&#44; nor the teachings which thou didst<lb/> promulgate led Henrietta Herz&#44; Rachel Levin&#44; and also thy<lb/> own Henrietta and Dorethea and Recha away from the<lb/> synagogue which thy life and writings have illustrated.&#34;<lb/>  No&#44; my brethren&#44; it was an irresistible ambition to shine&#44;<lb/> while oppression kept the Jew and Jewess forcibly in<lb/> obscurity&#44; that <sic>counselled</sic> the awful sin.  It was a<lb/> spirit of worldliness that prompted Abraham Men&#45;<lb/>&#45;delssohn to encourage his children to join the reli&#45;<lb/>&#45;gion of the majority&#44; which he described as that repre&#45;<lb/>senting modern civilization.  I open Moses<lb/> Mendelssohn&#39;s most erudite introduction to his famous<lb/> Pentateuch and read the following&#58;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>&#34;The Lord brought to my acquaintance Solomon &#91;&#63;&#93;.<lb/>  Him I charged to instruct one hour every day in<lb/> the construction of the Hebrew language the only son<lb/> I had then been left.  May God strengthen that child<lb/> that he may fear and worship his holy name.&#34;  No&#44;<lb/> it was not Mendelssohn&#39;s surroundings and the religion<lb/> he represented and sought to eternize&#44; that robbed us<lb/> of many.  Antisemitism&#44; which like the hydra has<lb/> raised its monstrous head again and again in Germany&#44;<lb/> was the foul seducer.  Now&#44; I will not dispute<lb/> that peoples who are positively or nominally Christ&#45;<lb/>&#45;ians have a right to claim a large share in modern<lb/> civilization&#44; but I deny that it is due to the faith&#44; in<lb/> which they were born.  History protests against that<lb/> untenable assertion.  Civilization&#44; as far as it goes&#44;<lb/> is the product of the press&#44; the steam engine&#44; the<lb/> telegraph&#59; it is the result of a closer intercourse among the<lb/> nations of the earth.  Practical science is a true civilizer.<lb/>  Edison is a promoter of civilization.  Not Popes&#44; not<lb/> cardinals and bishops.  Confining myself to the<lb/> point from which I started&#44; I insist that the<lb/> New Testament&#44; instead of improving upon the old&#44; has<lb/> lowered woman from the height in which our Bible has placed her.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Read what Saul of Tarsus&#44; called St Paul&#44; writes&#44; and<lb/> if you find me at fault&#44; I shall publicly retract.<lb/>  That apostle&#44; who enjoys unlimited authority in the<lb/> church&#44; who is indeed the real builder of the Church&#44;<lb/> in the course of his first letter to the <sic>Corintheans</sic>&#44; asks<lb/> that woman should always appear with her head<lb/> covered&#44; or&#44; as the newly revised version puts it&#44; veiled&#44;<lb/> in acknowledgment of her humbleness and her subordinate<lb/> position to man.  He further demands of woman<lb/> not to be heard in the worship&#44; resting satisfied to<lb/> listen and seeking instruction at home from her hus&#45;<lb/>&#45;band.  Addressing Timothy&#44; <sic>on</sic> of his disciples&#44; Paul&#44;<lb/> after having given some sensible directions to the women<lb/> of his age how to dress when in a house of prayer&#44;<lb/> he repeats the same rule&#44; as above&#44; more emphatically<lb/> and recommends that women should remain silent in the<lb/> service and never be allowed to teach.  My hearers<lb/> know that owing to those rules&#44; showing man&#39;s superiority&#44;<lb/> a maiden in the hour of marriage promises &#34;to honor and<lb/> obey&#34; her husband.  Contrast now Paul with<lb/> Moses and the prophets.  Notice the privileges which the<lb/> women of Israel enjoyed&#44; not alone to sing loudly and <sic>unin&#45;<lb/>&#45;cumbered</sic> by veils as our Miriam did on the safe shore of the<lb/> Red Sea&#44; and to pray like our Hannah before Eli the priest in the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Tabernacle at Shiloh&#44; but to judge and poetize like<lb/> our Deborah&#44; to admonish and advise a crowned head&#44;<lb/> like our Huldah&#44; and then say which of the two<lb/> religions elevated and which lowered woman.  I will<lb/> grant that the first pages of the Pentateuch&#44; in pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;dicting the effects of Adam and Eve&#39;s expulsion from Eden&#44;<lb/> intimate the dependence of the wife on her husband&#44; but in<lb/> doing so&#44; Holy Writ simply defines the mutual relations<lb/> resulting from a marriage state.  It does not mean<lb/> to command obedience&#45;&#45;a pledge which a woman in Israel<lb/> never gives to the man of her preference.  For&#44; with us the<lb/> matrimonial bond is not a bondage&#44; but a Kiddushin&#44;<lb/> &#34;a sanctification&#44;&#34; the hallowing of the lies of those who<lb/> contract it&#59; or&#44; as the Talmud more expressively terms<lb/> it&#44; Yoma de Hillula &#34;a day of thanksgiving&#34;&#44; when<lb/> two beings will jointly endeavour to further the design<lb/> of the Creator&#44; building up homes on virtue&#44; so that the<lb/> aggregate of such homes may render society morally<lb/> sound.  To learn how beautifully this principle<lb/> is illustrated in the Old Testament&#44; one needs only open<lb/> the book of Proverbs.  For&#44; there wisdom&#44; industry&#44; chastity&#44;<lb/> are invariably typified by the female sex.  I may be<lb/> told that though I should be able to defend the Hebrew<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Scriptures from the charge of having degraded woman&#44; I would<lb/> find myself at a loss to free the Rabbis from that accusa&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion.  Accordingly&#44; I might be compelled to face scattered<lb/> sentences in the Jerusalem and Babylonian Talmud&#44; reflecting<lb/> on woman.  A benediction&#44; embodied in our ritual&#44; might<lb/> be cast into my teeth&#44; and&#44; heaven knows&#44; what more might<lb/> be quoted to terrify me into a detraction.  Yet&#44; I am bold<lb/> enough to declare that I could cite from the same volumes<lb/> as many sentences to the exaltation of woman&#59; utterances<lb/> describing her origin of domestic prosperity and of com&#45;<lb/>&#45;munal success.  And I could moreover prove that the<lb/> benediction so greatly condemned for thanking the Lord<lb/> at not having been created a woman&#44; does not imply<lb/> the least disparagement&#59; that it is simply and exclu&#45;<lb/>&#45;sively an acknowledgment of man&#39;s capacities to per&#45;<lb/>form more and heavier duties than the weaker sex.  England<lb/> which is no more what it was&#44; regarding her Jewish inhabit&#45;<lb/>&#45;ants&#44; in the days of my youth&#44; when I sojourned there for<lb/> a time&#44; tried in vain to compel the Chief Rabbi to declare<lb/> that benediction an insult&#44; by erasing it from the liturgy.<lb/>  He resisted the pressure asserting with positiveness that<lb/> no offence to the Jewess was intended by Rabbi Meir&#44; the<lb/> author thereof&#44; the husband of the good and learned Beruria.<lb/>  But not to engage in a lengthy discussion&#44; I shall submit<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>to the attention of my hearers simply a few remarks<lb/> connected with incidents in our Parashah&#44; elucidating the<lb/> point which I have advanced.  Sarah had died&#44; whether<lb/> from the shock of having suddenly received the news of<lb/> the thrilling scene on mount Moriah&#44; as some of the Sages<lb/> allege&#44; or from other causes&#44; it is immaterial.  What interests<lb/> me now is the deep affection of the patriarch&#44; exhibited<lb/> alike in words and actions.  He mourned for the wife<lb/> who had followed him&#44; when he had quitted home and kind&#45;<lb/>&#45;red&#44; bent upon a heavenly mission.  He wept over the<lb/> devoted mother of his Isaac&#44; but controlling his grief with<lb/> mealiness&#44; he looked for such a burial of Sarah&#44; as might afford<lb/> him a melancholy satisfaction.  He would buy at whatever cost<lb/> a separate spot&#44; which he might visit and bedew with his<lb/> tears.  He could have accepted a generous offer and have<lb/> had Sarah interred inexpensively among the Hittites&#44; but he<lb/> declined that token of respect.  Of what value were his<lb/> shekels of silvers or gold&#44; in comparison with the woman<lb/> he had now lost&#63;  His own dead one&#44; as he repeatedly called<lb/> her&#44; her whom he longed to honor in her grave&#59; the che&#45;<lb/>&#45;rished one he had loved and esteemed in his home&#63;<lb/></p>
            <p>Let us now change scene.  Eliezer the unselfish servant&#44;<lb/> the noble steward&#44; has succeed in his errand.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>Rebecca is to become the wife of his master&#39;s son.  The<lb/> bride elect and the expectant groom meet.  He takes<lb/> her to his mother&#39;s tent&#44; weds her&#44; loves her and the<lb/> sorrow stricken son finds in conjugal devotion&#44; com&#45;<lb/>&#45;fort for the irreparable loss of her that gave him<lb/> birth.  How expressive the Hebrew sentence in its<lb/> simplicity&#44; how true to nature&#44; and how illustrative<lb/> of the religion that teaches its votaries to respect value<lb/> woman as man&#39;s equal&#44; to pay her respect above<lb/> man&#39;s self.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  A wide spread<lb/> dispersion&#59; a long residence among innumerable nationalities of<lb/> different grades of civilization may have given rise in our<lb/> midst to feelings and practices that ill&#45;accord with the his&#45;<lb/>&#45;tory of our Bible&#44; but such usages&#44; where they exist&#44; are<lb/> of foreign origin&#45;&#45;unJewish.  Laws which the legis<lb/>&#45;lation of peoples&#44; among the most enlightened of our<lb/> days still retain&#44; never stained our statute book.  The<lb/> whipping post was not resorted to in Judea even against<lb/> a scold&#44; and a shrew&#44; as in Great Britain not many centuries<lb/> ago.  I cannot dismiss a subject interesting<lb/> to me&#44; without relating a significant legend.  Says the<lb/> Midrash.  While Sarah lived a celestial shade overspread<lb/> her tent&#59; the bread she prepared for the family table never grew<lb/> sour&#59; the doors of her dwelling remained widely open&#44; and<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p><sic>and</sic> a light kept perpetually bright.  After<lb/> Sarah departed&#44; all had altered.  For three years<lb/> Isaac lamented the change in the parental home.<lb/>  But soon did things resume their former aspects.<lb/>  Rebecca came&#59; her husband beheld again what he was<lb/> wont to see in Sarah&#39;s time &#34;And Isaac was comforted<lb/> after his mother&#39;s death.&#34;  You understand it.<lb/>  Woman&#39;s blessed influence was felt.  Industry and con&#45;<lb/>&#45;tentment met&#44; charity and pleasure kissed one another<lb/> in the home of the righteous.  Let those who charge<lb/> the Hebrew scriptures with the sin of woman&#39;s enslave&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment and who rail at the Rabbis&#44; ponder on what<lb/> I have said&#44; and judge between the laws of my people<lb/> and the Testament of our detractors.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
