<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF32_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1894" source="" attested="yes">1894</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_1_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>G<lb/>
                94	<lb/>
                On the main virtue<lb/>
                in the character of Abraham<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>It is not a new revelation to say that the<lb/> Hebrew Bible represents men as they actually were&#44;<lb/> that it offers no apology for their shortcomings&#44;<lb/> however surpassing their merits may otherwise have<lb/> been.  During the last three consecutive Sabbaths&#44; the<lb/> same character has passed in review before our mental<lb/> vision.  Was its possessor all&#45;perfect&#63;  Nearly so<lb/> as a mortals creature can possibly be&#44; barring some weaknesses&#44;<lb/> impartially recorded&#44; which&#44; upon the minds of the<lb/> ancients&#44; did not leave the unpleasant impression which<lb/> they create in ours.  Still&#44; people&#39;s views vary<lb/> as to the most prominent feature&#44; distinguishing in the cha&#45;<lb/>&#45;racter of the founder of our nation.  Some will point<lb/> to the benevolence shown towards his fatherless nephew&#59;<lb/> will admire also his pacific disposition in his intercourse with<lb/> Lot.  That demeanour they will deem a noble example set to<lb/> posterity&#44; which the moralist expressed in the maxim&#58;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;A brother is born to aid in distress&#34;.<lb/></p>
            <p>Others will prefer to direct attention to Abraham&#39;s<lb/> generous hospitality&#44; and they will enlarge upon that merit of<lb/> our patriarch.  In fact&#44; the entertaining of strangers<lb/> is a trait highly eulogized by Talmudists.  It is related<lb/> that on one occasion a number of our older preceptors<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>met at an Academy of learning in Jamnia.  They<lb/> opened the discussion by alluding to the quality&#44; which<lb/> they greatly valued.  Unanimously they extolled hospit&#45;<lb/>&#45;ality as an glory to shedding honor upon those who practice it &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;  Some&#44; again&#44; will consider<lb/> the magnanimity which prompted our patriarch&#44; after<lb/> having risked his life and delivered a city from its<lb/> invaders&#44; to restore to all every one the property he revered&#44;<lb/> and to refuse the least gift for himself&#44; the noblest<lb/> of all virtues.  And that also received at the hands of<lb/> the Talmudists a profound acknowledgment &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> very many will agree that Abraham&#39;s willingness to<lb/> part with the dearest treasure in his possession&#59;<lb/> with the son of promise&#44; through whom his name<lb/> would remain a blessing upon earth to the end of<lb/> time &#91;Hebrew&#93;; his readiness I say to tear from<lb/> his heart the child so eagerly&#44; so yearningly ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;pected&#44; so fondly loved&#44; in order to prove his fidelity<lb/> to God&#44; was the crowning merit of Abraham&#39;s the patriarch&#39;s life.<lb/>  And really it is in that light that his descendants<lb/> have regarded the trial borne during the three days&#39;<lb/> journey to the mountain&#44; where devotion to religion<lb/> struggled for victory over paternal affection.<lb/>  The authors of the Hebrew ritual&#44; observing the halo<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>with which prophets and sages surrounded the<lb/> sainted brow of the patriarch Hebrew of Ur Chasdim&#44; as<lb/> a reward of his heroic faith&#44; filled our formulary<lb/> of prayers with striking references to the his binding<lb/> of Isaac upon the altar &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            <p>Not a few will be drawn closer to Abraham<lb/> by reason of that melting tenderness which bedewed<lb/> with tears what was mortal of his Sarah&#59; by reason<lb/> of his affectionate anxiety to sure secure for her&#44;<lb/> who had shared his joys and sorrows&#44; an honorable<lb/> burial. at any cost regardless of Yet&#44; admitting that each of those<lb/> qualities was lovely&#44; were I asked of what we&#44; the<lb/> progeny of Abraham&#44; should notably boast&#44; rather than<lb/> cite his kindness to Lot&#45;&#45;great as it was&#59; his hospital&#45;<lb/>&#45;ity far reaching unlimited as it showed itself&#59; his unsel&#45;<lb/>&#45;fishness&#44; so very truly admirable&#59; his having show proved<lb/> to the world that if&#44; like the brutal deities of pagan&#45;<lb/>&#45;ism&#44; the God he discovered in nature demanded<lb/> human sacrifices&#44; the great believer would have<lb/> obeyed&#59; or his devoted care of the body which had en&#45;<lb/>&#45;shrined the immortal soul of his wife&#44; rather than all I would point<lb/> to Abraham&#39;s intercession ever for irreclaimable unfortunate sinners.  That I<lb/> would call the loftiest virtue in the character of our patriarch.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>I will explain my sentiment.  It is not unusual<lb/> with our Christian neighbors to draw a contrast<lb/> prejudicial to Judaism.  Often I am pained by<lb/> the charge that the religion of the Synagogue<lb/> loses much in comparison with the religion of the<lb/> Church&#59; that ours is an austere religion&#44; a re&#45;<lb/>&#45;ligion of unbending rigor&#44; while through that the religion of<lb/> our neighbors a current of gentle love and humans soft<lb/> forgiveness compassion runs freely with limpid clearness.<lb/></p>
            <p>Literature&#44; whether light or serious harps upon<lb/> that subject with so much such assurance&#44; that even<lb/> Israelites learn to  chime in&#44; encouraged by their<lb/> own pulpits which place the Galilean&#44; whose<lb/> supposed alleged mission heaped upon Israel mountains of<lb/> sorrow&#44; on a par with Moses and Isaiah and<lb/> Micah&#45;&#45;the glory of our race.  The man of Naza&#45;<lb/>&#45;reth is eulogized as a friend of the abandoned<lb/> and the fallen.  The new Testament represents him<lb/> as a seeker of publicans and outlaws for a good pur&#45;<lb/>pose.  But while I would always upraise and never<lb/> cast down my fellow&#45;creature&#59; while I would never counsel the rejection<lb/> of even the lowest among backsliders&#44; I hold nevertheless<lb/> that the demeanour of the founder of our people<lb/> and belief&#44; rises infinitely higher than that of the Nazarene&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>It was certainly more honorable in keeping with the dicate dictates of honor and dignity.  Abraham did not<lb/> sit with the degraded&#45;&#45;an association of doubtful ad&#45;<lb/>&#45;vantage&#59; He nor did not he say that he who has never<lb/> committed a sin&#44; should cast the first stone upon the<lb/> adulteress&#45;&#45;intimating that no punishment be meted<lb/> out and that all wrongs be overlooked.  No&#58; he<lb/> would not preach justice out of the world&#44; but his<lb/> humanity was so all embracing that he could not contem&#45;<lb/>&#45;plate even at a distance in his mind thought the sufferings that follow close<lb/> at the heels of crime.  A graphic illustration of that<lb/> trait in Abraham&#39;s character is the entreaty which he poured<lb/> forth.  The inhabitants of Sodom or Gomorrah were<lb/> atrociously wicked.  Ezekiel so speaks of them in the<lb/> name of his heavenly Master.  &#34;This was the iniquity<lb/> of Sodom and her daughters&#44; pride of abundance and of<lb/> prosperous ease &#91;Hebrew&#93;...nor would she<lb/> strengthen the hand of the poor and helpless &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#40;Sodom and Gomorrah&#41; were haughty they committed<lb/> abominations&#44; therefore &#40;says the Lord&#41; I took them away&#44;<lb/> as I saw fit&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;  Among the<lb/> legendary tales of the Talmud we read the following&#58;<lb/> Two young women met at a fountain&#44; where they<lb/> had gone to drink and fetch water.  One looked very<lb/> sickly.  The other asked what ailed her.  She answered<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>that she was nearly dying with with hunger.  Upon<lb/> that&#44; she who had spoken first quickly went<lb/> and filled the empty pitcher with flour and sent<lb/> the starving girl home.  The generous donor was<lb/> cruelly treated because of that by her brutal country&#45;<lb/>&#45;men&#44; as a recompense for her goodness.  Now&#44; Abraham must have known and how pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;fligate and inhuman were the people in whose<lb/> midst his nephew Lot had settled.  Still&#44; when<lb/> the vision vouchsafed to him exhibited to view the<lb/> impending doom with which Sodom and her sur&#45;<lb/>&#45;rounding towns were threatened&#44; he prayed&#44; ardently<lb/> prayed&#44; most humbly prayed &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; perseve&#45;<lb/>&#45;ringly prayed for Divine mercy.  He did not simply<lb/> petition that his brother&#39;s son and his relatives<lb/> be might&#44; for his virtues&#39; sake&#44; be delivered from the univer&#45;<lb/>&#45;sal catastrophe&#44; but he implored of the Lord that<lb/> all might would be shielded under the wings of Divine heavenly<lb/> graciousness.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  Have the<lb/> progeny of the patriarch inherited the quality<lb/> of sweet mercy which is nobility&#39;s true badge&#63;<lb/>  Most assuredly they have &#91;Hebrew&#93; is the little they bear.  They<lb/> gained it because the blood of Abraham courses through<lb/> their veins&#59; they gained it because his example and precept<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>gave them lasting instruction.  To bring forth into<lb/> action the noblest trait of Abraham&#39;s character&#44; God<lb/> revealed His purpose to the ancient patriarch &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;I have known him&#45;&#45;meaning I have distinctly set him<lb/> apart&#45;&#45;to the end that he may command his child&#45;<lb/>&#45;ren and his household after him and they shall keep<lb/> the way of the Lord&#44; to do righteousness and justice&#34;.<lb/>  In the word Zedakah translated &#34;righteousness&#44;&#34; gene&#45;<lb/>&#45;rous beneficence&#44; deep compassion&#44; absolute forgiveness<lb/> are comprehended&#44; so ar our Bible proclaims&#44; and all<lb/> can hear that declaration who study to learn the prin&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciples on which their religion stands &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Zedakah exalts a nation&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;The promotion of peace and the exercise of commiseration<lb/> are Zedakah&#34;.  In the word Mishpat or &#34;Justice&#34; Jews<lb/> who understand their creed&#44; perceive the golden rule&#44;<lb/> which is not Christian&#44; for Hillel and the Babylonian<lb/> anticipated Jesus the Galilean when he said &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Do not unto others what would be unpleasant<lb/> to thyself.&#34;  That rule&#44; as inculcated by prophets and<lb/> Sages&#44; means an honesty of thought so perfect that<lb/> will not allow an single action which has not been weighed<lb/> in the scales of truthfulness.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Holy Writ calls a conduct measured by the<lb/> line of St Zedakah and Mishpat godliness&#44;<lb/> or keeping the way of the Lord &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Thus preached Jeremiah by divine inspiration &#34;Let not the wise man glory in his<lb/> wisdom&#44; neither let the mighty man glory in his might&#44;<lb/> let not the rich man glory in his riches&#44; but let him<lb/> that glories glory in this&#44; that he understands and knows<lb/> Me that I am the Lord that who exercises loving kindness&#44; justice<lb/> and righteousness Misp Mishpat Uzdakah in the<lb/> earth&#44; for in those things I delight&#44; says the Lord&#34;.<lb/>  Brethren.  Why search out goodness through<lb/> other channels&#44; when it strains forth perennially<lb/> in our own midst&#63;  Why ungratefully b turn our<lb/> back on our own preceptors&#44; to seek instruction at<lb/> the hands of the stranger&#63;  It has been very re&#45;<lb/>&#45;cently preached&#44; in a spot ostensibly dedicated devoted to<lb/> the interests of Judaism&#44; that a more sublime teach&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing than the sermon on the Mount&#44; would be very<lb/> difficult to imagine.  Well&#44; beleve believe me<lb/> Israelites&#44; what is acceptable there&#44; is a facsimile&#59;<lb/> the original is ours&#59; what clashes there with rea&#45;<lb/>&#45;son is a new testament.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
