<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF4_4</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_4_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_4_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_4_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_4_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_4_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_4_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_4_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_4_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_4_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_4_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_4_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_4_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Post&#45;Biblical Lecture<lb/>
                24th<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Several weeks ago in looking back to the state of our<lb/> forefathers in Judea&#44; we saw Herod their King in high<lb/> spirits.  The rebuilding of the Temple had been finished<lb/> with a magnificence surpassing even that of Solomon&#39;s.<lb/>  Herod thought that the dazzling splendor of such an edifice de&#45;<lb/>&#45;dicated to Israel&#39;s God&#44; had blinded our people to the<lb/> unpardonable faults vice of his character&#59; that the ineffaceable<lb/> crimes he had committed against the house of the<lb/> Asmoneans&#44; had been washed away by the blood of<lb/> burnt&#45;offerings.  In that hope&#44; he left for Rome&#44;<lb/> where his two sons Alexander and Aristobulus Aristobulus were being<lb/> educated&#44; and brought the youths along to Jerusalem.<lb/>  The reception which those children of the unhappy<lb/> Marianne met was an outburst of popular affection.<lb/>  Their father noticed the welcome&#44; but did not appear<lb/> jealous&#59; his sister Salome noted it down&#44; but with<lb/> a pen dipped in gall.  That wretched vile woman cared<lb/> nothing that her own daughter Berenice had been given<lb/> in marriage to Aristobulus.  The same hatred which<lb/> she had shown to Marianne and which had unjustly<lb/> consigned the latter to the death of a criminal&#44; she<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>nurtured against her two sons.  It was a<lb/> fear that if f either got rose into power&#44; she would be<lb/> made to suffer for her past offences&#44; which stirred her up<lb/> to plan conspiracies.  She took into her secrets&#44; her wicked<lb/> brother Pheroras&#44; and both succeeded in persuading Herod<lb/> that his two sons bore him grudge because of the execution<lb/> of their mother.  That the youths may not have<lb/> forgotten the sad fate of their maternal parent and that<lb/> of her unfortunate relatives&#44; is scarcely to be wondered<lb/> at&#44; but that because of it they designed to kill their<lb/> father was rank falsehood.  Herod believed credited it&#44; for&#44;<lb/> &#34;conscience does make cowards of us all&#34; of us&#34;&#44; wrote the greatest<lb/> of English poets.  To spite his two sons of Maccabean<lb/> blood&#44; he recalled to the royal courts&#44; an older son whom<lb/> he had by an Idumean wife before he married Marianne.<lb/>  Antipater was his name&#44; and like his name&#39;s sake&#45;&#45;Herod&#39;s<lb/> father&#45;&#45;he was an adept in cunning and knavery.<lb/>  Him Herod declared his successor to the throne&#44; and sent to Rome The two sons of Marianne could not to have him instructed<lb/> in all branches of learning.  The two sons of Marianne<lb/> could not look upon such partiality with unconcern.  They<lb/> complained of it among supposed friends&#44; and there by exag&#45;<lb/>&#45;gerations and untruths made Herod believe that his life was<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>in imminent danger.  Upon that&#44; he set off for<lb/> Italy&#44; and summoned Alexander and Aristobulus before Au&#45;<lb/>&#45;gustus Caesar.  The Roman emperor discovered that the sons<lb/> of Marianne had been indiscreet in their talk speaking&#44; but not guilty<lb/> of attempting a parricide.  A reconciliation took place&#44; and<lb/> the king of the Jews&#44; who was always tossed on a sea of<lb/> uncertainties&#44; promised that at the death of Antipater&#44; Alex&#45;<lb/>&#45;sander and Aristobulus should share the kingdom between<lb/> them&#45;&#45;a resolution not at all calculated to promote<lb/> peace.  Herod finding his home a prey to bitter<lb/> quarrels&#44; tried to divert his mind by indulging in public<lb/> amusements.  Having built a city which he called Cesarea&#44;<lb/> with great magnificence&#44; he introduced there Greek and<lb/> Roman games&#45;&#45;circuses for gladiators&#44; theatres for Athletes<lb/> and for dancers.  He also married Jewish and foreign women<lb/> to the number of eight&#44; and it is told that being unable<lb/> to meet the extravagant expenses caused he by his mania<lb/> for building&#44; and for entertaining his most sumptuously strangers<lb/> visiting Judea and bestowing costly gifts on Romans&#44; he<lb/> ransacked tried to impiously tried to open the grave of King David&#44; which was reported to<lb/> <sic>to</sic> contain treasures of silver and gold&#44; and ransack it &#38; rob it.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>But to Herod Herod&#39;s house was still a guilded grave.  To him might be applied the sentence<lb/> of Micah&#58; &#34;Trust not in a friend&#44; rely not on a con&#45;<lb/>&#45;fidant&#44; keep the doors of thy mouth from her that lies<lb/> in thy bosom&#44; for the son dishonors the father&#44; the daughter<lb/> rises against her mother&#44; the daughter in law against her<lb/> mother in law&#44; a man&#39;s enemies are the men of his own<lb/> house.&#34;  Salome Pheroras&#44; Antipater and other members<lb/> of that iniquitous family never ceased to poison the mind of the<lb/> king by letters if not they could not reach him by words.  And they succeeded in<lb/> weaving a net into which the two sons of Marianne<lb/> were inextricably caught.  The unnatural Herod having<lb/> extolled false confessions by means of tortures&#44; convened a<lb/> mock tribunal&#44; and had Alexander and Aristobulus condemned<lb/> to be strangled.  Thus a last remnant of the illustrious<lb/> Asmoneans was rooted out&#44; and its destroyer was a parent<lb/> who tore out of his breast every human instinct&#44; to let ferocity<lb/> lodge therein.  Marianne&#39;s children may<lb/> have lacked prudence&#59; they may have spoken too candidly<lb/> to their grievances&#44; but was it an actual crime to complain<lb/> that their ever suspecting father had raised above them<lb/> the son of an Idumean woman&#63;  Was it a sin to be loved by<lb/> a people who remembered their noble birth and extraction&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Or should the beauty of their persons have been<lb/> accounted an offence&#63;  Had they deceived their father&#44; as<lb/> the infamous Antipater deceived him&#63;  Alexander and Aris&#45;<lb/>&#45;tobulus died the victims of an irreconcilable hatred&#44; but their<lb/> blood and vengeance from out of the ground which opened to receive<lb/> their corpse.  Wherever Herod turned he saw treason and or<lb/> sedition.  He detected discovered it in his people and in one of his wif<lb/> wives&#44; in his brother&#44; in his sister&#44; in his favorite son.  For Antipater<lb/> grew impatient of waiting to mount up the throne for his father&#39;s natural death.<lb/>  to mount the throne and By a combination of plots&#44; which<lb/> he thought could never be unravelled&#44; he prepared had a poison<lb/> prepared to be mixed in Herod&#39;s food.  The traitor imagined&#44; perhaps&#44;<lb/> that he was beyond detection for being in Rome at the time&#44; but<lb/> the book of truth has taught that &#34;there is no darkness nor shad&#45;<lb/>&#45;ow of death wherein the workers of iniquity can hide them&#45;<lb/>&#45;selves.&#34;  Antipater was sent for&#44; and to throw him off his<lb/> guard&#44; Herod pretended that his services were greatly needed at home.<lb/>  On his arrival at Jerusalem&#44; he perce read his doom in the<lb/> ominous silence which attended his entry.  The vile f hypocrite<lb/> attempting to kiss his father was motioned back&#44; and<lb/> charged with having occasioned the condemnation of his brothers&#44;<lb/> and with stealthily endeavouring to become a parricide.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Summoned before a tribunal&#44; he made protestations of love<lb/> and loyalty&#44; called God as a witness&#44; of his innocence&#44; struck<lb/> his breast and wept aloud&#44; but the proofs of his contemplated<lb/> crime were too strong and too numerous.  Having deprived<lb/> him of his right of succession to the kingdom&#44; Herod had him<lb/> enchained in a tower&#44; awaiting for a letter of Augustus Caesar&#44;<lb/> sanctioning the execution of the rebellious son.<lb/></p>
            <p>Meanwhile grief&#44; vexation&#44; debauch and old age told severely<lb/> on the wretched king.  He brew hopelessly ill&#44; and as his scik&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness was of a nature insufferably virulent he would have committed<lb/> suicide&#44; if not prevented by a relative.  Antipater ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;pecting to hear every moment of his father&#39;s death&#44; entreated<lb/> the prison&#39;s guard keeper to set him to liberty&#44; promising a large<lb/> reward&#44; but the man reported the proposition and the offer&#44;<lb/> and Herod ordered his son&#39;s instant decapitation.  Nor was<lb/> only the atrociously wicked Antipater that lost forfeited his life towards<lb/> the end of the king&#39;s career.  A number of Pharisees&#44; and among<lb/> them two distinguished and revered Sages Judah &#38; Matthias who&#44; <sic>profitting</sic><lb/> of the desperate condition of Herod tore down the Roman<lb/> Eagle which he had placed on the top of one of the Temple&#39;s<lb/> gates&#44; were burnt alive.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Knowing moreover that his demise would be a<lb/> source of joy to the nation when he had tyrannized over and<lb/> outraged&#44; he ordered that the most noted among his<lb/> subjects should be shut up in a circus&#44; and he bid Salome<lb/> and his sister and her third husband Alexis&#44; to have them<lb/> slaughtered as soon as he expired.  In that manner<lb/> Jews would be compelled to mourn and lament&#44; whereas they<lb/> might otherwise have felt happy.  After having made<lb/> new dispositions about succession&#44; dividing the country<lb/> among three sons&#44; Archela&#252;s and Herod Antipas of a<lb/> Samaritan woman&#44; and Phillip of another&#44; he died in<lb/> the seventieth year of his age&#44; and the thirty seventh&#44; since<lb/> he had been chosen king of Judea by the grace of the Roman<lb/> senate.<lb/></p>
            <p>It is has been my painful task to dwell somewhat on the character<lb/> of a man deserving of the detestation of all good people&#44; and<lb/> specially of every Jew.  A proper understanding of post&#45;<lb/>&#45;biblical events&#44; demanded at my hands to that I should follow that course.<lb/>  Still I make cannot dismiss the unpleasant subject&#44; without<lb/> making adding a few observations.  If we measure one&#39;s<lb/> greatness by the number of battles successfully fought&#44;<lb/> of the splendid cities he built&#44; of the rich treasures he <sic>ammassed</sic><lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>of the treaties he concluded with dreaded republics and empires&#44;<lb/> then Herod the Idumean can claim the title of &#34;great&#34; by<lb/> which he is designated.  For few potentates excelled him<lb/> in military bravery&#59; in the ability to plan the extension<lb/> of territories and the erection of temples&#59; in the art of<lb/> <sic>of</sic> filling his royal treasury with countless gold&#44; and<lb/> in the munificence of presents to his allies friends and allies.<lb/>  But if a king&#39;s greatness is gauged by the his capacity of to<lb/> rendering the country happy through the prevalence of peace&#44;<lb/> through internal improvements conducive to the comfort<lb/> of the masses&#44; through a limitation of taxes&#44; making the laborer<lb/> enjoy his earnings&#44; and through the preservation of national<lb/> laws and customs&#44; then Herod is little and meanly low indeed.<lb/>  For he began his career by waging war against all who<lb/> opposed his arbitrary schemes&#44; he proceeded by defying the authority of the<lb/> Sanhedrin&#44; by scandalising our fathers with his learning to<lb/> heathen habits and practices&#44; by extorting money to gratify his<lb/> mania for enlarging his dominions&#44; and because he knew<lb/> that his descent from a people&#44; always inimical to the<lb/> Jews&#44; and his having supplanted the offspring of a family<lb/> whom the Jews fondly loved and venerated&#44; rendered him an object<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>of abhorrence&#44; he killed one by one the members of<lb/> that illustrious household.  He turned his home into a<lb/> chamber of horrors&#44; his metropolis into a vast dungeon&#44; and<lb/> too wicked or too weak to shake off a hateful yoke&#44;<lb/> he tied Judaism to the conquering chariot of pagan<lb/> Rome.  Herod was not altogether destitute<lb/> of generous impulses&#45;&#45;for the worst of beings have been<lb/> supplied by nature with kindly sentiments&#45;&#45;but an am&#45;<lb/>&#45;bition which knew no bounds stifled all other feelings&#44; and con&#45;<lb/>&#45;verted him into a monster.  I cannot conclude<lb/> my narrative of the life of that detestable ruler of our people<lb/> more fittingly than with the words of a distinguished French writer<lb/> of our own faith.&#34;  &#34;The epithet of great which history<lb/> has given him&#44; is a bitter sarcasm.  His greatness consisted<lb/> in being a magnificent slave dragging golden cha fetters&#44;<lb/> and that greatness culminated in delivering his people to despair<lb/> for which issue he himself dug opened an abyss that swallowed<lb/> it up completely.&#34;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
