<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF9_4</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1893" source="" attested="yes">1893</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_4_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_4_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_4_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_4_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_4_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_4_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_4_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_4_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_4_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_4_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_4_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff9_4_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>93<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>
                On David&#44; his last will and his deeds<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Had not my feelings&#59;dictated Had not certain events by which wrought up my compelled my feelings were wrought up&#44; compelled the remarks which that<lb/> I made last Sabbath&#44; my discourse would have<lb/> been then of an entirely different character.  The<lb/> Haftorah chosen from the second chapter of the first<lb/> book of Kings had suggested a subject which&#44;<lb/> to me&#44; is of some interest.  I shall present it this<lb/> morning.  Among the illustrious personages who<lb/> figure in Holy Writ&#44; David undoubtedly occupies a<lb/> front rank in various capacities.  Nevertheless&#44; the impertent unprejudiced reader<lb/> cannot avoid detecting glaring faults among the<lb/> shining virtues of that famous king.  In my<lb/> judgment&#44; those faults are particularly repre&#45;<lb/>&#45;hensible&#44; when committed towards the close of<lb/> an exceptionally checkered career.  We may over&#45;<lb/>look mans natural frailty the effects of an impetuous human nature&#44; which offending morality&#44;<lb/> in man&#39;s early years&#44; or long before old age has crept on.<lb/>  We may forgive the excessive order which in fighting championing<lb/> for a cause&#44; disregards&#44; for a time&#44; the demands dictates of human&#45;<lb/>&#45;ity.  The sacred historian&#44; who chronicled seven wrongs<lb/> in David&#44; recorded also his utter humiliation that at the &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Thou<lb/> art the man&#44;&#34; pronounced by the fearless prophet.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>And so He recorded He likewise the restraining of sounded that told us how the hands which had shed reddened<lb/> human &#91;&#63;&#93; the battle field with blood were restrained held back restrained from building a Temple in honor of the Universal Lord.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93; We&#44; who are ourselves cannot trust not always to rise above<lb/> the meeting of low low appetites and vicious &#91;&#63;&#93; unrighteous desires&#44; may pass over transgres&#45;<lb/>sions fallen into which others have fallen under exciting circumstances&#44; but we shrink<lb/> from contemplating a coldly premeditated act of cruelty&#44;<lb/> done when about to leave this earth and all its associations.<lb/>  Admit&#58; Joab the general in Chief of David&#39;s army&#44; was fierce<lb/> and unrelenting in his hatred.  Shimei the Benajmite&#44;<lb/> was villainous and contemptible&#44; hypocritical&#44; but neither ought<lb/> to have been implacably remembered in David&#39;s last<lb/> will and testament.  The military services which<lb/> the first had rendered&#44; should have forced back into<lb/> its scabbard the avenging sword of vengeance.  To the other&#44;<lb/> amnesty royal pardon has been promised.  He ought to have<lb/> been spared.  Why then the terrible legacy&#63;  Why<lb/> was Solomon commanded not to allow Joab and<lb/> Shimei to end their days naturally&#63;  Whoever<lb/> has studied David&#39;s character well carefully&#44; must have<lb/> discovered a failing&#44; not singular to be sure&#44; but<lb/> attended with the saddest consequences&#44; when it ex&#45;<lb/>ists in crowned heads.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>He that by his an indomitable courage and by surpassing<lb/> abilities had knit together into a compact nation&#44;<lb/> twelve tribes not always formerly harmonious&#59; he whom his<lb/> contemporary Asaph so graphically described &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; God &#34;made choice of David His servant<lb/> and took him from the sheepfolds.  From following suckling<lb/> lambs He brought him up to feed Jacob His people and<lb/> Israel His inheritance.  And he did feed them according to<lb/> the integrity of his heart and guided them by his skilful<lb/> hands&#34;; even the same mighty leader was unconquerably<lb/> weak in dealing with his own household.  That<lb/> infirmity of purpose which had caused a murder&#44; sedition&#44; &#38; rebellion<lb/> among his offspring&#44; and finally left a stain upon<lb/> a document that the latest posterity ought to might otherwise have read<lb/> with unction admiration &#38; profit.  For&#44; we all approve of David&#39;s injunction<lb/> to his royal successor&#44; to walk in the ways of God&#44; as<lb/> commanded prescribed in the Law of Moses &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> We all delight in David&#39;s recommendation to Solomon to show unwavering<lb/> gratitude to a family&#44; whose father had been to him a friend in need.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> But we instinctively recoil at the thought that the same document&#44;<lb/> demanded two deeds of blood.  Was there for it any<lb/> justification&#63;  None&#44; unless we choose so to so term a parental<lb/> moral blindness.  David who had shed bitter a flood of tears<lb/> over the well merited ignominious death end of wicked<lb/> Absalom&#59; oblivious of his obligations to the people at<lb/> large&#44; who had encouraged by his overindulgence Ado&#45;<lb/>&#45;nijah&#39;s plotting to reach seize the throne&#44; who had suffered<lb/> the outrageous conduct of Ammon to go unpunished&#44;<lb/> yearning now towards Solomon with an unwise love&#44; beyond religious<lb/> wisdom asked of him to rid himself of two malcontents<lb/> among his subjects.  That dying request&#44; is to the<lb/> deced descendants of the Judaean king&#44; even to oursel&#45;<lb/>&#45;ves&#44; a thrust in our hearts and a pang I feel then&#44; and<lb/> yet who dares withal deny David&#39;s greatness&#63;  Let a<lb/> brilliant but not unveracious Renan&#44; rail and belittle<lb/> and traduce.  He who searches through the pages<lb/> of &#34;the history of the people of Israel&#34; with eyes unblurred by prejudice&#59; with eyes open<lb/> to truth&#44; and not closed deliberately shut against taminous<lb/> evidences proofs&#44; will discover the youngest son of Jesse&#44;<lb/> a consummate warrior&#44; a statesman&#44; a poet&#44; a Hebrew<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>of Hebrews.  Perfect&#63;  No&#44; by no means&#59; still<lb/> endowed with qualities that outshone the bright&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness of the crown which he wore.  Firm in his resolve<lb/> to humble the enemies of his race&#44; but constant in<lb/> his friendship to the defenders of Israel&#39;s honor and to their progeny.<lb/>  Loyal to the core to the his native country&#44; but gently considerate in his pa&#45;<lb/>&#45;triotism.  To me&#44; an episode in David&#39;s life&#44; per&#45;<lb/>&#45;haps scarcely noticed&#44; is a full glorious revelation of his the<lb/> mobility of his sentiments.  An exile from home and wanderer&#44; forced to en&#45;<lb/>&#45;trust his parents to the treacherous Moabites&#44; in<lb/> the hope of screening them from the implacable wroth<lb/> of envious Saul&#44; he had remained kept hidden in a<lb/> fortress with the companions of &#91;&#63;&#93; his sad lot.  A garrison<lb/> of Philistines was stationed in the sweet home dear spot<lb/> from which hatred had banished him.  &#34;Oh that<lb/> I could sip a draught out of the well of Bethlehem&#44; which<lb/> is by the gate&#34;&#44; he cried out in an out a burst of affection for<lb/> the dear place sweet home of his birth.  Three <sic>heros</sic> broke<lb/> through the inimical host&#44; drew the water so long&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed for and brought it to their adored beloved chief.  &#34;God forbid&#44;&#34; said<lb/> David.  &#34;I will not drink the blood of men who stalked their<lb/> existence to do me pleasure.  This water I offer<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>to the Most High&#44;&#34; and he poured it to<lb/> the ground&#44; as a libation upon the altar&#45;&#45;a<lb/> veritable sacrifice of self&#44; in obedience to a sense of<lb/> duty right.  And who more generous than David<lb/> in offering of parting with that which was his won to do his<lb/> living Redeemer honor&#63;  Vast riches he had gathered<lb/> by his conquests over Edom and Philistia&#44; over Amon<lb/> and Syria&#45;&#45;the arch foes of Israel&#45;&#45;but unlike royalty in his days and in<lb/> ours&#44; he did not hoard it the up wealth to luxuriate in kingly<lb/> extravagances magnificence.  Hark&#58; I hear him the ruler speak to an assembled<lb/> multitude of his subjects&#44; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;with all my power I have set apart for the house of my<lb/> God&#44; gold&#44; and silver&#44; and copper and iron and timber&#44; pre&#45;<lb/>cious stones and marble stones in abundance.&#34;  Then turning towards facing<lb/> his hearers listeners&#44; he thus publicly blessed the uathor of all good.  &#34;Riches<lb/> and glory proceeds from Thee...  But who am I&#44; and<lb/> who is my people that we should possess the power<lb/> to offer after this manner&#63;  but from Thee is every<lb/> thing &#91;Hebrew&#93; O Lord our God&#33;  All this abundant store<lb/> which we have prepared to build for Thee a house&#44;<lb/> for devoted to Thy holy name&#44; is out of Thy hand and thine is all &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Brethren&#44; much that belonged to our sacred literature<lb/> we have lost&#44; but very deeply thankful we must be feel for<lb/> the precious appendix to the history of God&#39;s people.<lb/>  I mean&#44; for the two books of Chronicles.  They<lb/> sent set forth in all its preeminence the great&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness of David&#39;s greatness&#44; they relate his prowess&#44; his His munificence&#44; the deep<lb/> sagacity of displayed in his administration&#44; but notably&#44; and at length&#44; his foresight which<lb/> dictated the splendid management of the ministrytion<lb/> of priests and levites directed destined to officiate at the<lb/> Temple&#44; that he was not permitted to rear and tell together with his exhort&#45;<lb/>&#45;ations to the nation&#44; that he had almost recreated&#44;<lb/> to rejoice in their success but with reverential awe<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> And yet&#44; had even those two precious volumes sunk into<lb/> the oceans of time&#44; and the psalter alone floated across it<lb/> in safety&#44; David&#39;s real genius greatness would become manifest&#44; and<lb/> hundreds of millions would turn with glowing glowing<lb/> affection towards the bard&#44; who thus sung to the Lord&#58;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Yea&#44; though I should walk through the valley of the<lb/> shadow of death&#44; I will fear no evil&#44; for Thou art with<lb/> me&#34;.  The psalms of David are the imperishable legacy<lb/> which we hold next to our hearts.  Not every one opens<lb/> to us a source of spiritual comfort&#59; not every one uplifts<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>our souls to the Eternal&#44; heavenward&#44; but many direct our spiritual devotional<lb/> vision to the mountains&#44; of the Lord whence our help cometh.<lb/>  Rightly have our Sages declared that David exceeded surpassed all<lb/> in the glorification of our Maker&#44; and &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#38; let us add&#44; also in the beatification of mortals&#44; while yet clothed<lb/> in flesh.  Could If creatures in sorrow&#44; solaced by David&#39;s<lb/> psalter&#44; if repentant sinners brought by it to the foot&#45;<lb/>&#45;stool of forgiveness&#44; if men in danger given reassurance by obtained reassured by it as that God is nigh&#44;<lb/> it if women in mental agitation calmed by it&#44; the prisoner<lb/> in his fear tranquillized gloomy dungeon brightened by it&#44; the sick upon his bed&#44; as&#45;<lb/>&#45;suaged by it&#59; could&#44; I say&#44; all be wanted if all of them could whom received<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;the <sic>annointed</sic> of the God of Jacob<lb/> and the sweet pa pslamist of Israel&#34; gladdened and<lb/> inspired be reckoned&#44; could be counted&#44; only the sand of the sea might<lb/> equal exceed them in number.  Let us be grateful that David is ours&#44; is<lb/> David&#44; with his human imperfections which at times that darkened his career&#44; yet with also redeemed also but still radiant with the glorious <sic>marvellous</sic><lb/> deeds which he accomplished for us&#44; and his people&#44; in<lb/> ages past&#59; for mankind at large&#44; interminably.  Aye for time<lb/> will be no mercy ere the effusions of the minstrels royal minstrel be forgotten&#44; who<lb/> sang &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Awake up my glory&#59; awake&#44; psalters and harp.  I will<lb/> awake up the morning dawn.&#34;  We forgotten by the race of man<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
