<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF11_5</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1896-01" source="" attested="yes">1896</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_5_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_5_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_5_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_5_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_5_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_5_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_5_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_5_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_5_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_5_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_5_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_5_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>100<lb/></p>
            <p>96<lb/></p>
            <p>Did Jews practice human sacrifices&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>A sentence towards the end of Leviticus&#44; the<lb/> third book of the Torah&#44; whose perusal we have<lb/> just concluded&#44; has given me of late considerable concern.<lb/>  Nearly the whole chapter in which that sentence occurs&#44;<lb/> treats of the valuation of persons&#44; or property de&#45;<lb/>&#45;voted to the sanctuary&#44; or becoming&#44; by reason<lb/> of a vow&#44; the possession of the ministering priests.<lb/>  The twenty ninth verse however&#44; reads thus&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  The revised ver&#45;<lb/>&#45;sion&#44; varying very little from the so called author&#45;<lb/>&#45;ized one&#44; translates literally as follows&#58; &#34;None devoted&#44;<lb/> which shall be devoted of men&#44; shall be ran&#45;<lb/>&#45;somed&#44; he shall surely be put to death&#34;.  The<lb/> school of higher criticism&#44; undeterred by the<lb/> repeated denunciations in the Law and the pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;phets against human sacrifices&#44; has dared to<lb/> cite that verse as a proof that among<lb/> ancient Israelites such brutalities were<lb/> practised.  And as novelties in literature&#44; as like<lb/> in all things&#44; find easy acceptance&#44; so in this<lb/> instance&#44; an idea destitute of foundation has<lb/> been accepted received and approved by the credulous because supposed to emanate from deep thinkers profound scholarship.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>It is said&#59; the Pentateuch declares the first<lb/> born of man&#44; like the first ling of an animal<lb/> hallowed to the Lord&#44; therefore hence both are were to be<lb/> placed in the same category&#59; both are were to be con&#45;<lb/>&#45;sumed on the altar&#44; in honor of the Lord.<lb/>  But in deference to an indisputable truth&#44; I<lb/> must recall to the memory of my hearers the<lb/> fact that the Pentateuch has also shown<lb/> the difference in the treatment of the human<lb/> first born among males among human beings and the firstling of<lb/> animals.  In language which cannot be<lb/> possibly misunderstood&#44; we are told that the<lb/> former was to have been ransomed by five shekels<lb/> of the Sanctuary......&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; whereas the latter<lb/> was immolated &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Naturally&#44; I will be asked&#44; what means then<lb/> the sentence in which I quoted from to day&#39;s section&#63;  Well&#44; the<lb/> Leeser Bible&#44; following agreeably to the traditional rendering&#44;<lb/> reads as follows&#58; &#34;Any one condemned to death<lb/> among men&#44; shall not be redeemed&#59; he<lb/> shall be put to death&#34;.  Is that correct&#63;<lb/>  Yes&#44; substantially so&#59; and the reason must be<lb/> apparent to all unprejudiced minds.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>For&#44; the preceding sentence speaks of an object<lb/> of whatever character devoted to the Lord&#44;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; while in our sentence<lb/> no mention at all is made of a consecration<lb/> to the Lord.  It has reference therefore decidedly<lb/> to a totally different case&#59; I mean to that in which<lb/> the judicial courts&#44; or the ruling authorities have<lb/> condemned a person&#45;&#45;for a crime committed&#44; as it was&#44; for instance&#44; in<lb/> the case of Achan&#44; during Joshua&#39;s administra<lb/>&#45;tion.  That person could be not be ransomed.  The<lb/> sentence must be carried out&#44; as we read else&#45;<lb/>&#45;where&#44; that a guilty being may be dragged away<lb/> from the very sanctuary to to which he too refuge&#44; in order that he shall pay the penalty<lb/> of his crime transgression offence.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            <p>But who can harbor the thought that human<lb/> sacrifices were sanctioned by our Legislator&#44; seeing<lb/> that mere ill usage towards a slave&#44; such as<lb/> blinding him of one eye&#44; or even knocking out one<lb/> of his teeth&#44; compelled the owner to send his servant bondman<lb/> free&#33;  Seeing also that parents could not exercise<lb/> irresponsible power towards their own children&#44; when<lb/> these were dissolute and rebellious&#44; but must apply<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>to the courts for a condign sentence&#63;  Does<lb/> it stand to reason that a legislator so considerate<lb/> and humane&#44; would favor killing as a savory oblation to God&#63;<lb/>  Far be it such iniquity from our Lawgiver&#44; who in incisive lan&#45;<lb/>&#45;guage prohibits copying the atrocious and hein&#45;<lb/>&#45;tious habits of Egypt and Canaan&#44; far be it from him to wink<lb/> at and much less to approve of those very abo&#45;<lb/>&#45;minable customs.  But higher criticism<lb/> is not given to acknowledging itself vanquished.<lb/>  So also in the question at issue&#44; it tries to prove<lb/> from the act of Abraham&#44; what that act positively<lb/> disproves.  Criticism argues thus.  Unless hu&#45;<lb/>&#45;man sacrifices were had been common&#44; the patriarch would<lb/> never have thought of offering his son to God the Lord.<lb/>  And I&#44; copying the critics and leaving aside for the &#91;&#63;&#93; what Holy Writ sets down as a heavenly trial&#44; argue thus.  Yes&#44; human sacrifices<lb/> doubtless formed part of the shocking worship of hea&#45;<lb/>&#45;thens&#44; but Abraham&#44; who had discovered the way<lb/> of God&#44; which was to do righteousness and justice<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; instructed by inspiration his conscience&#44; felt<lb/> showed that such cruelties are an abomination in the<lb/> sight of the Creator.  So certain was he of that it&#44; that<lb/> he desisted from carrying out his intention original intention.  And what the founder of our people&#44;<lb/> was Divinely <sic>whithheld</sic> from doing&#44; his descendants learnt<lb/> to avoid as a most heinous offence to nature and to nature&#39;s God.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>But Bible readers&#44; have sought to silence me by<lb/> directing my attention to Jephtha&#39;s vow.  I did not&#44;<lb/> however&#44; flinch.  I stood my ground.  Let us cast<lb/> a glance on the history of the Hebrew warrior&#45;&#45;I<lb/> prefer that appellation to the title of Judge&#45;&#45;.<lb/>  He was a natural son of Gilead.  The unkindness<lb/> of relatives drove him early away form home and<lb/> he&#44; with a party of wild companions&#44; made his home settled<lb/> among strangers to his people and religion&#59; very<lb/> probably heathen Syrians&#44; for the land of Job was<lb/> in Amram near Mesopotamia.  How long Jephtha led there a roving life&#44; it is<lb/> not stated.  History simply says &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; mean&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing some years later&#44; when the Ammonites had at&#45;<lb/>&#45;tacked the Israelites&#44; the chiefs of Gilead&#44; asked<lb/> Jephtha to place himself at their head and<lb/> fight the enemy.  He consented and routed the<lb/> invaders.  But his sojourn among idolators&#44; had<lb/> exercised a woeful influence.  Jephtha in his eager&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness to prove himself worthy of the generalship<lb/> entrusted to his valor&#44; vowed to that in the went of his victory&#44; he would offer on the altar<lb/> whatever being met him first&#44; when he returned hailed<lb/> home victorious a conqueror.  To his horror&#44; the only child he<lb/> had&#45;&#45;a young girl&#45;&#45;had hastened to welcome back<lb/> her father&#44; dancing at the sound of timbrels which she played upon.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>At that sight&#44; the reckless parent who had become half paganised&#44;<lb/> was terror struck&#44; but though heart broken&#44; he insisted<lb/> upon performing his rash vow and the filially<lb/> devoted&#44; but misled child&#44; agreed to become the willing<lb/> victim of that horrible promise.  I know that<lb/> not all Bible expositors have explained alike the fate<lb/> of Jephtha&#39;s daughter.  Some are of opinion that<lb/> her having remained unmarried was then regarded<lb/> as being deprived of life.  But if it were so&#44; what<lb/> occasion had the girl to ask of her father two<lb/> months time&#44; during which she might weep<lb/> on the mountains over her remaining being doomed to continue a virgin since she was to<lb/> keep so always Besides nunneries never existed in Israel.  Then&#44; again&#44; what did the<lb/> daughters of Israel yearly lament about the daughter of Jephtha&#44; as stated &#91;&#63;&#93; &#91;Hebrew&#93;  In reading the sad event incident with<lb/> an unbiased judgment&#44; I perceive that the<lb/> historian&#44; unwilling to dwell on the shocking epi&#45;<lb/>&#45;sode&#44; limits himself simply to write&#44; &#34;he did with her accord&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing to the vow which he had vowed.&#34;  I hold<lb/> that Jephtha did not alone sin&#44; for acting con<lb/>&#45;trarily to what Roheleth recommended centuries after later<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Be not rash with thy mouth&#44;&#34; but<lb/> also against the other injunction by the same author &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Be not hasty in thy spirit to get angry.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>We notice that while Gideon instead of fighting<lb/> the quarrelsome tribe of Ephraimites&#44; pacified them.<lb/>  Jephtha made a desperate war against them and per&#45;<lb/>&#45;petrated a slaughter.  The Talmudists not<lb/> wishing to cast odium on one who had bravely<lb/> entered the lists to deliver Israel our people in the hour of danger&#44; say that Jephtha<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#45;&#45;of light value&#45;&#45;deserved nevertheless the<lb/> esteem of his contemporaries &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> but they do not scruple to add that he had he<lb/> studied his religion&#44; he would not have lost his daughter &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;  I candidly admit that human<lb/> sacrifices were offered by corrupt Kings of our nation<lb/> and by then imitative subjects&#44; for the impartial scriptures<lb/> record that melancholy fact&#44; but never never were they made by the<lb/> sanction or connivance of our faith.  In the<lb/> third chapter of the second book of Kings&#44; we<lb/> read of a league between Jehoshaphat King of Judah&#44;<lb/> Jehoram King of Israel&#44; and the King of Edom to de&#45;<lb/>&#45;feat the army of Moab.  The battle was fierce.<lb/>  When the ruler of Moab felt that the fate seemed<lb/> conspired determined to destroy his host&#44; he took his oldest<lb/> son&#44; the heir apparent to the throne&#44; and butchered<lb/> him as an offering to his false gods&#59; but he was<lb/> a heathen&#44; not a Jew&#44; and Amos reproaches Moab<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>for his brutality.  If we except the incident<lb/> of Jephtha&#44; which cannot be sufficiently repre&#45;<lb/>&#45;hended&#44; no instance similar to it is met&#44; during<lb/> the lapse of so very many centuries&#44; from the days that<lb/> Moses our inspired legislator gave us his solemn charge&#44; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;There shall not be found among<lb/> thee&#44; one that causes his son&#44; or his daughter to<lb/> pass through the fire&#44;&#34; and again&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Thou shalt not do so to the Lord thy God &#40;viz&#44; like<lb/> the heathens&#41; for even their sons and their daughters<lb/> they burnt on fire to their gods&#59;&#34; during so many cen&#45;<lb/>&#45;turies&#44; I say&#44; a crime unreproved&#44; like that of Jephtha&#44;<lb/> never occurred.  I leave it to the higher criticism to show<lb/> the contrary beyond peradventure.  I rest satisfied<lb/> with having intimated that to blindly accept what<lb/> a school&#44; now a days greatly extolled lays down its axioms&#44; is not wisdom&#44;<lb/> but credulity.  The duty bounden obligation of every Jew and every Jewess<lb/> who wishes to hold correct views touching the religion<lb/> of Moses and the Prophets&#44; is to search&#44; without bias&#44;<lb/> into the writings of Moses and the Prophets.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
