<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF15_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_2_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>A continuation of the subject<lb/>
                on the existence of God.<lb/></p>
            
            <p>2d lecture<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  My last lecture ended where that which I The lecture which I purpose to deliver this morning&#44; will begin<lb/> purpose to deliver this morning will being  The where my last one ended.  Its closing<lb/> sentence was an appeal from by the grandest grandest of inspired speakers orators<lb/> to the minds of his people.  Isaiah knew that he could<lb/> not mathematically prove the existence of a Being who designed the fabric structure of<lb/> the universe and who governs it the world with wisdom&#44; any more than<lb/> the existence of our thinking faculties can be proved by the<lb/> sense of touch.  Yet&#44; the prophet felt that unless man will determinedly<lb/> shut his eyes against the light of reason&#44; he must<lb/> see and confess an Almighty Creator.  He would there&#45;<lb/>&#45;fore lead us form nature up to nature&#39;s God.<lb/></p>
            <p>The shepherd bard&#44; who became Israel&#39;s king&#44; had already described<lb/> the language of the sky&#44; which as it daily declares the glory of<lb/> its Maker&#44; and the son of Amoz&#44; his successful disciple in the<lb/> graphic delineation of truth&#44; pointed to the same fir&#45;<lb/>&#45;mament studded with bright stars&#44; which&#44; like an army<lb/> set in faultless array by the skillful skilful Chief&#44; come<lb/> forth in the order primordially established primordially by the Most High.<lb/>  That contemplation was to dethrone the imaginary deities of<lb/> heathenism&#44; to confound Atheism&#44; and to vindicate the<lb/> belief in One supremely good and watchful God.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Dear young friends.  I remember to have read<lb/> once&#45;&#45;I think it was in in a work of Philo Judeo&#45;&#45;a remark which im&#45;<lb/>&#45;pressed me forcibly.  That author&#44; who lived in<lb/> Alexandria about the commencement of the vulgar era&#44;<lb/> wrote in Greek a number of books&#44; deservedly appre&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciated by those who wish to understand the philosophy<lb/> prevailing at that time.  But the volume which<lb/> he devoted to &#34;the life of Moses&#34; commends itself principally possesses the greatest interest<lb/> to for us his coreligionists.  In it the thoughtful scholar<lb/> argues contends that the miracles which worked out effected the deli&#45;<lb/>&#45;verance of the Hebrews from Egypt are not more<lb/> as prodigious than these signs of Divine &#91;&#63;&#93; goodness omnipotence which mankind at large witness<lb/> every day.  Only because these latter signs are performed with<lb/> uninterrupted great frequency&#44; they have ceased to call forth even<lb/> a passing notice.  Philo instances in support of his<lb/> reasoning argument the rising of the sun with its unfailing<lb/> precision&#44; and he describes pictures the thrilling sensation<lb/> which its first appearance would produce in those among human beings whose<lb/> horizon had never before been lighted by the mighty<lb/> luminary&#59; the joy at being rescued from darkness&#44; the<lb/> gratitude for a gift so incalculably valuable obtained<lb/> at the hands of a an invisible&#44; but most beneficent Lord.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>We&#44; of modern times&#44; are taught that the turning of the earth<lb/> upon itself is what causes the change of night and day.<lb/>  But the wonder of God is just as clearly perceptible by the<lb/> motion of our globe&#44; which brings us regularly every morn&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing the life&#45;restoring and heart&#45;cheering sun&#44; as if the latter<lb/> were the main actor.  Well there is my reflecting friends&#44; what power gives the planet which<lb/> man dwells upon that motion most exact and continuous&#44; and<lb/> the suspension of which&#44; for a second&#44; would might be attended with<lb/> a universal catastrophe&#63;  Atheists answer&#58; Necessity gives<lb/> it&#44; for motion is a property inseparable from matter&#59; it this<lb/> moves involuntarily&#44; mechanically.  I shall not make the<lb/> question more intricate&#44; by asking&#44; in return&#44; what does the word<lb/> Necessity mean in connection with inanimate objects&#45;&#45;for I<lb/> could never agree with Maimonides who states after Aristotle&#44; that the<lb/> planets and stars are so many living creatures endowed with<lb/> understanding&#45;&#45;&#44; but I will simply observe that a thing ne&#45;<lb/>&#45;cessary to an object signifies a property of its nature&#44; without deprived of<lb/> which it cannot exist.  Now&#44; we all can form an idea of the<lb/> earth matter in a quiescent state&#44; or perfectly still&#44; and as to the theory of involuntary or me&#45;<lb/>&#45;chanical action&#44; experience assures us that nothing can move with&#45;<lb/>&#45;out the power of the will&#44; or of an outside pressure brought to bear on it.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Thus our minds compel the belief that the earth<lb/> receives its impulse from a power which is not not in<lb/> itself&#44; but which is was miraculously imparted at the beginning.<lb/>  But why&#44; my dear hearers&#44; stop to speak of the earth<lb/> revolving on its axis and thus supplying us&#44; its inhabi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tants&#44; with light and refreshing shades&#44; with rest warmth and renewed strength&#44;<lb/> as a if that were the greatest marvel in creation&#44; when the earth is a mere<lb/> speck in the immensity of the universe&#63;  You know it.  Astronomers have dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;covered&#44; by means of their hugely magnifying instruments&#44;<lb/> that what we see above us is a boundless space&#44; in the<lb/> center of which&#45;&#45;to borrow a term&#45;&#45;the sun has been stationed.<lb/>  Round that centre or rather in its direction move&#44; not alone our globe&#44; but planets&#44;<lb/> some of which are hundreds of thousands times larger than our<lb/> own and round these again&#44; secondary planets or satellites&#44;<lb/> &#45;&#45;possibly&#44; all inhabited by sentient beings&#45;&#45;and all of them rolling in various ways&#44; with a different degree<lb/> of rapidity&#44; but always keeping their paths&#44; or orbits&#44; with<lb/> a wonderful exactness regularity&#44; ever preserving the order&#44; the harmony<lb/> the symmetrical beauty&#44; the majestic grandeur of the universe who can reflect ponder on that and be not struck with unspeakable unutterable awe&#63;  But whence&#44; I in&#45;<lb/>&#45;quire again&#44; whence did all those celestial bodies&#44; whirling round through<lb/> the measureless space&#44; derive the impelling force which leads<lb/> them towards the sun to receive from it light and heat<lb/> and animation&#63; vitality&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Even if the inexplicable imaginary law of Necessity could be<lb/> account for that forward impulsion tendency of the planets&#44; what<lb/> cause could we assign set forth for the opposite motion&#63;  You&#44;<lb/> my young friends&#44; are aware that according to astronomical discoveries researches&#44; the heavenly spheres<lb/> possess two forces&#44; one which draws them in the direction<lb/> of the sun&#44; or the centripetal&#44; and th another which holds<lb/> them back in a curve in within their own lines&#44; so that they mayght not fall into approach draw too closely to near the sun&#59; or the and a force which is called cen&#45;<lb/>&#45;trifugal.  Will atheists assert that both those two contrary<lb/> forces are the property of matter&#63;  Fancy to yourselves a<lb/> cannon ball discharged against a certain point.  It keeps<lb/> on a track towards that point same spot&#44; but it somehow it is kept checked and held<lb/> always at a given distance from it.  Will it be insisted&#44; with any<lb/> show of reasonableness&#44; that the nature of the projectile<lb/> is to have in itself two mechanical properties of an opposite<lb/> character&#63;  I may not have presented an apt very striking illus&#45;<lb/>tration to my argument&#44; but it will give na idea however faint&#44; of the absurdities in which<lb/> the deniers of a Supreme Artificer are involved.  With them lies<lb/> the burden of proof that the whole planetary system is blindly<lb/> following a law of necessity&#44; that a mechanical motion&#44; inherent in<lb/> t matter had assigned to each of the stars its size&#44; and station<lb/> and power&#59; that it has also furnished comets with a capacity<lb/> to roll about the space in an eccentrical way&#44; but still<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>in obedience to the two forces of attraction and gravitation&#44;<lb/> so as not to fall into the sun and that its encounter with another planet or with the sun<lb/> might not overthrow the work of creation.<lb/></p>  
            <p>Until they Atheists Atheists have accomplished that stupendous undertaking&#59; until they have convinced all by logical arguments rational persons by logical arguments that the Deity whom hundred of millions did and will ever adore is a fiction&#44; and lifeless matter is the real divinity&#44; until then have we<lb/> will continue to believe in a Creator what the shepherd of old believed believed&#44; who<lb/> heard the melody of the firmament as it daily rehearsesing the praises<lb/> of its Maker&#59; believed and what the prophet believed believed&#44; who saw the<lb/> host of heaven <sic>marshalled</sic> out by the Omnipotent Chief. beloved.<lb/>  the will even believes  Nor will the Bible alone strengthen our faith&#44; for we shall be aided and confirmed therein by that which a mind&#45;&#45;if not inspired<lb/> gigantic certainly wonderful&#45;&#45;&#44; beheld&#44; when surveying the illimitable space<lb/> with be in its gigantic flights.  Great among the greatest among the great<lb/> of modern Astronomers was Sir Isaac Newton.  And this Listen to<lb/> is his declaration&#58; &#34;The planets and the comets remain<lb/> in their ob orbits by the laws of gravitation&#44; but the re&#45;<lb/>gular position they hold in those orbits could not originally<lb/> have been received by those such laws....That grand system of<lb/> the sun&#44; the planets and the comets&#44; could not have been<lb/> produced except by the will of a Being most intelligent<lb/> and powerful&#34; &#43;  Not without profound wisdom investigations have the<lb/> Rabbis laid down the maxim&#44; that whosoever wishes to know<lb/> the wisdom of His Creator&#44; must make himself acquainted with astronomy.<lb/></p>
            <p>&#43; Translated from Luzzatto&#39;s &#34;Teologia Dogmatica.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>And yet notwithstanding the startling discoveries of our<lb/> age&#44; how exceedingly slow is human progress in that particular science&#44; which<lb/> our Sages rightly considered a key to the understanding of<lb/> the Lord&#39;s Omnipotence of the Lord&#33; of the omnipotence of the Lord&#33;  I speak with a hesitation arising<lb/> from an intense consciousness of my ignorance&#44; but I can recall the<lb/> circumstance that a Talmudist who boasted of a familiarity<lb/> with the course of the stars through the sky as with the streets of his city&#44; confessed himself<lb/> at a loss to explain the erratic revolution of the comets&#59; and<lb/> now after sixteen centuries comes one to whom the world bows as<lb/> to an unsurpassed master and says&#58; to his admirers &#34;To myself I seem I have<lb/> been a child playing on the sea&#45;shore&#44; while the immense ocean<lb/> lay unexplored before me.&#34;  It is <sic>Neuton</sic> that I have again quoted&#44;<lb/> my young friends&#44; and I cite his words because I eagerly wish<lb/> to infuse into your hearts a sense of humility&#44; which leads to<lb/> Godliness.  When a man so preeminent for his achievements in<lb/> the realms of thought&#44; acknowledges that his efforts&#45;&#45;&#40;and how<lb/> prodigious they were&#33;&#41;&#45;&#45;that his efforts have brought him but<lb/> a grain of what is left still to be learnt&#59; when he who has created<lb/> a new era in science bends low and owns that the spring whence<lb/> all knowledge flows and out of which mortals can but sip a few drops at a time intervals&#44; is the Almighty&#44; how extremely careful cautious<lb/> ought we to be in expressing an opinion breathing a doubt as to the existence<lb/> and government of the Prime Mover of heaven and earth&#33;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>The more will science will advance develop in all its branches&#44; the more<lb/> will&#45;&#45;no doubt&#45;&#45;the saving truth of God&#39;s essence and infinite wisdom be felt.  Would it were in my power<lb/> to work in the vast field of science&#59; but may I not hope measurably to serve the cause of truth<lb/> by a timely caution a friendly warning to those who are apt to become tinctured with pre&#45;<lb/>vailing ideas&#59; liable to imbibe and practically carry out prin&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciples subversive or morality and religion&#44; and fatally mischie&#45;<lb/>vous&#63;  It is that hope which has inspired the humble labor<lb/> in which I am at present engaged.  I shall proceed with it we to the<lb/> utmost limits of my capacity&#59; but I think judge I cannot close this lec&#45;<lb/>&#45;ture more appropriately than by reproducing the advice of a fa&#45;<lb/>&#45;ther more appropriately than by reproducing the advice of a fa&#45;<lb/>&#45;ther to his inquiring child&#44; and which I read once with interest.<lb/>  My son &#34;My son don&#39;t be in too great a hurry to accept &#34;advanced opinions&#34;.  It is &#34;the thing&#34;<lb/> &#34;to be &#34;advanced&#34; in this progressive day &#38; generation&#44; but there is a heap of shallowness in it.<lb/>.......I don&#39;t want to suppress any inclination you may have<lb/> towards genuine free thought and careful&#44; honest investigation.<lb/>  I only want you to avoid the great fault of Atheism in this<lb/> day and generation.  I don&#39;t want to see you try to build a<lb/> six story house or one story foundation.  Before you criticise&#44; condemn<lb/> and finally reverse the work of creation&#44; be pretty confident&#44; my<lb/> son&#44; that you know something about as it is&#44; and don&#39;t&#44; I implore<lb/> you&#44; don&#39;t turn this world upside down&#44; and flatten sit on it&#44; and flatten<lb/> it entirely out&#44; until you have made&#44; or secured&#44; another for the<lb/> rest of us to live in&#44; while you demolish the old.&#34;  An excellent<lb/> advice&#44; my young friends&#44; take it to heart.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
