<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF4_7</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_7_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_7_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_7_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_7_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_7_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_7_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_7_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_7_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_7_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_7_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_7_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_7_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_7_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_7_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_7_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_7_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Post Biblical lecture<lb/>
                27<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  In the general view which I<lb/> have asked you to take of the annals of our<lb/> ancestors during the existence of the second Temple Sanctuary&#44;<lb/> your minds have mostly been directed to men<lb/> and events in Palestine.  To day you are requested to<lb/> turn away your looks awhile from Jerusalem and notice<lb/> the checkered life of a Jew in Rome.  The Hebrew lad<lb/> to whom I allude had lived there long from his boyhood and was raised<lb/> among the <sic>childrens</sic> and relatives of the emperor Tibe&#45;<lb/>&#45;rius.  Asmonean blood ran in his veins&#44; but all<lb/> that was left in him to recall his noble descent<lb/> was a disposition to associate with the great&#44; and<lb/> to give largely of his means to show a generous<lb/> spirit.  His father was Aristobulus&#44; the son<lb/> of the unhappy Marianne&#44; and whom the unnatural<lb/> Herod had executed on suspicion of treason.  His mo&#45;<lb/>&#45;ther was Berenice daughter of the wicked Salome&#44; the<lb/> sister of Herod.  The latter had called his grand child<lb/> Agrippa&#44; in honor of a relative and general of<lb/> Augustus Caesar&#44; who bore that name.  Owing<lb/> to political agitations in the capital of Judea&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Berenice had emigrated to Rome and<lb/> taken there her young son Agrippa and her<lb/> daughter Herodias.  Their income derived from<lb/> family bequests&#45;&#45;was not sufficient to enable<lb/> Agrippa to vie in splendor with patricians and<lb/> princes.  So long as his mother lived&#44; he was<lb/> somewhat checked in his extravagance&#44; but after her<lb/> death he indulged in it beyond measure.  His<lb/> wife Cyprus&#44; who was his first cousin&#44; and whom he married early seems to have<lb/> been an estimable person&#44; and moderate in her<lb/> wishes&#44; but Agrippa could not be restrained by good wise<lb/> counsel.  He spent both what belonged to him&#45;<lb/>&#45;self and what was the property of relatives and<lb/> friends.  His ambition to shine among the mag&#45;<lb/>&#45;nates of the land became uncontrollable&#44; and he con&#45;<lb/>&#45;tracted debts&#44; which he could not possibly discharge.<lb/>  Hunted Harassed by creditors&#44; and ashamed of his poverty&#44;<lb/> he stealthily left Rome Italy and journeyed to Judea.<lb/>  It will be remembered that his sister Herodias<lb/> had gone there before&#44; when she shamefully deserted<lb/> her husband in Rome to marry Herod Antipas<lb/> ruler of Galilee.  At her request&#44; Agrippa<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>received the nominal office of governor of Tiberias&#45;&#45;the newly built city&#45;&#45;&#44;<lb/> with a modest pay&#44; but he was by nature too<lb/> proud to remain there long and his brother in law was too mean.  This one<lb/> did not let let an occasion pass by&#44; when he<lb/> could make Agrippa feel little&#44; throwing into<lb/> his teeth the mo favors gained by relatives&#44; and<lb/> without which the high spirited Maccabee would be<lb/> in a miserable condition plight.  To a man like Agrippa<lb/> such reproaches were deep wounds.  He could not<lb/> endure them&#44; and he soon left departed from Galilee to go to<lb/> Syria&#44; where he hoped to find help in the Roman<lb/> governor&#44; with whom he had been on familiar terms<lb/> at Rome.  But even there political intrigues com&#45;<lb/>&#45;pelled him to wander further in search of means to<lb/> keep life.  Through a freed slave of his mother&#44;<lb/> he obtained a loan on usurious interest.  With it that money<lb/> he had determined to return to Italy&#44; but he had<lb/> not <sic>travelled</sic> far&#44; when a previous creditor stopped<lb/> him short and demanded his money due.  Agrippa<lb/> promised it&#44; but knowing that to pay up would be<lb/> to remain penniless&#44; escaped at night and reached<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Rome&#44; where he met with a hearty welcome<lb/> from at the hands of the emperor Tiberius.  Scarcely had he the<lb/> time to congratulate himself on that reception&#44;<lb/> when a letter arrived from the creditor who had<lb/> overtaken him been baffled in Syria&#44; explaining to Tiberius<lb/> the <sic>uggly</sic> conduct of Aggrippa.  The emperor<lb/> peremptorily ordered that the debt be discharged<lb/> according to promise.  Agrippa had again<lb/> recourse to some of his mother&#39;s friends for a<lb/> loan.  and He would have thus continued to drag an existence&#44; making<lb/> debts to pay up debts&#44; and would have died poor obscure<lb/> and unhonored&#44; but for his intimacy with Cassus<lb/> Caligula&#44; grand nephew of Tiberius.  Yet&#44; over<lb/> this close friendship came very near to sending him<lb/> to the scaffold.  One day the two were riding<lb/> out and talking louder than discretion would suggested&#44;<lb/> Agrippa expressed the wish that Tiberius might<lb/> soon die and Cass Caligula mount up the throne.<lb/>  by the driver was overheard  The conversation was overheard by the driver&#44; and the impru&#45;<lb/>&#45;dent Agrippa was cast into a prison and heavily<lb/> laden with chains.  For six months he lay<lb/> there uncertain of the sentence which might be<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>passed on upon him.  One day morning Unexpectedly a freed slave<lb/> who had been in the service of the Asmonean family<lb/> called at the prison and cried in Hebrew &#34;the lion<lb/> is dead.&#34;  Agrippa understood it and broke out<lb/> in exclamations of joy at his forthcoming deliver&#45;<lb/>&#45;ance.  The prison&#39;s keeper believing that Tiberius<lb/> had really died&#44; congratulated Agrippa and invited<lb/> him to a rich dinner.  But while eating&#44; the news<lb/> came that the emperor had only fainted.  and He had revived and would be up again.<lb/>  Terror stricken&#44; the host and his guest imagined already<lb/> that their doomed had been sealed.  Consternation seized<lb/> every body&#44; for all Rome had thought hoped that the tyrant<lb/> had passed away&#44; but what nature failed to do&#44;<lb/> foul play did accomplished.  Tiberius was suffocated smothered under<lb/> bolsters and pillows.  Caligula having been pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;claimed emperor&#44; exchanged the Agrippa&#39;s iron chains into for golden<lb/> ones of the same weight&#44; and gave presented them to Agrippa him.<lb/>  As Phillip his uncle&#44; son of Herod I&#44; who had ruled<lb/> over a third part of Judea with wisdom and kindness&#44;<lb/> had died without children&#44; Caligula gave that bestowed the same pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;vince to on Agrippa and added to it other principalities.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Thus Agrippa actually stepped from a<lb/> jail to a throne.  But Herodias&#44; wife of<lb/> Herod Antipas felt jealous of her brother&#39;s good<lb/> fortune.  The worthy daughter descendant of her grand&#45;mother Salome&#44;<lb/> began to devise new schemes for her husband&#39;s further aggrandi&#45;<lb/>&#45;sing request to go to Rome&#44; but finally was in&#45;<lb/>&#45;duced to accompany her and represent matters<lb/> in a way which might prove useful to them&#45;<lb/>&#45;selves and hurtful to Agrippa.  But It hap&#45;<lb/>&#45;ened precisely as predicted by the psalmist&#58;<lb/> &#34;the wicked are ensnared in the work of their own<lb/> hands.&#34;  Agrippa prevented anticipated the evil designs<lb/> of his unkind relatives&#44; and Caligula detecting a<lb/> conspiracy&#44; allowed him the country of which he<lb/> had dispossessed Antipas entirely.  This prince was<lb/> banished to Lyons in France and her as his brother Archelaus had been transported to Vienne.  It must be<lb/> recorded to the credit of his wife Herodias&#44; that<lb/> although Caligula&#44; gave her leave to choose her<lb/> residence and enjoy some of the revenue of her for&#45;<lb/>&#45;mer dominions&#44; she preferred to share her hus&#45;<lb/>&#45;band&#39;s exile and lowly condition.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>But Cassus Caligula&#44; who began his reign<lb/> as a mild and upright ruler&#44; soon turned to be<lb/> a fiercely brutal and impious.  He had sent issued<lb/> orders that wherever Rome&#39;s supreme power was acknowledged&#44; su&#45;<lb/>&#45;preme in power&#44; his likeness should be set up in<lb/> temples and adored as a divinity.  To any other<lb/> people but the Jews&#44; the demand was of no con&#45;<lb/>&#45;cern.  One god more or less seemed perfectly<lb/> immaterial.  But to our fathers&#44; the command<lb/> occasioned anguish of spirit.  The Greeks of Alex&#45;<lb/>&#45;andria were the first to insist on declaring Cali&#45;<lb/>&#45;gula a god and compelling all to worship him.<lb/>  Their object was to stir up hatred strife against the<lb/> Hebrew race&#44; and they succeeded but too well.<lb/>  The hatred they bore our people was deep inveterate and undisguised.<lb/>  Already when Agrippa passed through Alexandria<lb/> on his way to his dominions&#44; they had offered him<lb/> a gross insult&#44; by dressing a beggar as a king and in tatters of different kinds giving him a stick to hold&#44; pretending he was a king&#44;<lb/> and calling after him Mari&#44; which in Aramaic language<lb/> means&#44; &#34;my lord&#34;&#44; and now they accused the Hebrews all Israelites<lb/> of treason against Rome for refusing to pay divine<lb/> honors to its head.  Matters took assumed a very serious<lb/> turn aspect&#44; when synagogues were attacked and the attempt<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>was made to forcibly place idols therein.  Alexandria<lb/> looked like a battle ground&#44; our ancestors stoutly fought<lb/> back their assailants&#44; and scenes of carnage<lb/> were perpetrated.  At last a deputation was sent<lb/> to Rome to seek redress and protection.  The<lb/> most famous among the Jews who undertook<lb/> to plead for our people was Philo.  His copious<lb/> writings in the Greek language on religion and<lb/> philosophy have given him a name which<lb/> will never die.  He Philo Judge&#45;&#45;or Philon or Jedidiah Alechsandri&#45;&#45;has left an account of<lb/> his mission and a description of the madman Ca&#45;<lb/>&#45;ligula&#44; running as he ran from room to room&#44; stopping a<lb/> moment to rail at the Jews&#44; because they sacri&#45;<lb/>&#45;ficed to a God they did not know&#44; and denied homage<lb/> to a god whom they could see&#44; and then going<lb/> off in a rage&#44; and turning again to the embassy<lb/> to ask why Jews did not eat pork.  Philo The illustrious Alex<lb/>&#45;andrian Jew&#44; was not successful in his mission&#44; but he and<lb/> his colleagues must have considered themselves for&#45;<lb/>&#45;tunate to be dismissed by the despot with only the<lb/> following remarks&#58; &#34;these people are less wicked than<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>they are unlucky and stupid in not believing<lb/> in my divine nature.&#34;  At Jerusalem<lb/> the resistance to the emperor&#39;s will was so deter&#45;<lb/>&#45;mined that Petronius the governor of Judea dared not<lb/> enforce it&#44; lest rivers rivers of blood flow through<lb/> the land.  He agreed to write to Caligula and tell<lb/> him the state of feelings existing&#44; though he was<lb/> sure that his letter would cost him his life.  but<lb/> before that missive arrived&#44; Agrippa had found<lb/> the way to gain a point which no other man<lb/> in the world could attain.  Informed of<lb/> what transpired in Asia and Africa among his<lb/> coreligionists&#44; and being then at the time in Rome&#44; he invited<lb/> Cassus Caligula to a supper.  The food and the art<lb/> with which it was served surpassed the most ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;travagant expectations.  The would&#45;be god<lb/> drank freely&#44; and appeared was put in so good a humor&#44;<lb/> that he pressed Agrippa to ask any favor&#44; giving<lb/> his royal assurance that&#44; however great&#44; it would still be granted.<lb/>  Agrippa very adroitly answered that what he<lb/> had already received&#44; was suffer abundant proof of<lb/> the goodwill of the Roman emperor towards his vassal.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>He would ask nothing more for himself.<lb/>  But Caligula still urging him on to try the<lb/> extent of his friendship&#44; Agrippa said&#58; &#34;I do not<lb/> crave for riches&#59; you have honored me enough with<lb/> them&#44; but I crave for a favor which will give<lb/> you the name of an upright man&#44; and me<lb/> the great honor high distinction of knowing that I have never<lb/> petitioned you in vain.  Pray&#44; let the statue<lb/> which you wish to have placed in Jewish temples&#44;<lb/> be not set up there.&#34;  Caligula was thunder&#45;<lb/>struck.  He never anticipated such a request&#44;<lb/> but he had pledged his word in the presence<lb/> of all the Roman quests to grant any favor&#44; and<lb/> a retraction would have brought contempt and self<lb/> humiliation.  He wrote to Petronius that if his<lb/> statue had already been set up&#44; it should not<lb/> be taken down&#44; if otherwise it should not be<lb/> forcibly placed in Jewish temples.  But when<lb/> the letter of Petronius came to hand&#44; and showed<lb/> the resolve of our people to fight to the bitter end<lb/> rather than submit&#44; Caligula grew furious and<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>and wrote immediately back to the govern&#45;<lb/>&#45;or to choose of what death he wished to die.<lb/>  Providentially the horrid message was detained&#59;<lb/> it did not reach its destination till after the<lb/> news of the assassination of the tyrant had restored<lb/> tranquility.  Agrippa was still in Rome<lb/> when the emperor was dispatched by conspirators.<lb/>  Being an adept in politics&#44;&#45;&#45;a thorough diplomatist&#45;&#45;he induced his friend<lb/> Clad Claudius&#44; uncle of Caligula&#44; whom the army<lb/> saluted king to accept the crown and the Senate to agree to the selection.  The reward<lb/> he obtained for that service surpassed his most sanguine anticipa&#45;<lb/>&#45;tions.  Claudius exalted him to the rank enjoyed<lb/> by his grand father Herod I.  Once again and<lb/> for the last time&#44; the lands of Israel was recon&#45;<lb/>&#45;structed and placed under one head.  Agrippa be&#45;<lb/>came its sovereign.  In another lecture&#44; I shall<lb/> speak of his short rule and of the manner in which<lb/> it was exercised.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
