<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Henry, H. S.</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx3FF7_33</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Henry, H. S.</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Morais, Sabato</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>New York, NY</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1884-08" source="" attested="yes">22 August 1884</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx3ff7_33_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx3ff7_33_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx3ff7_33_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx3ff7_33_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx3ff7_33_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx3ff7_33_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx3ff7_33_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx3ff7_33_4v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 2 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>H.S. Henry&#44;<lb/>
                Box 3144&#44; P.O.<lb/>
                CABLE ADDRESS&#45;&#45;KENRY&#44; NEW YORK.<lb/></p>
                
            <p>48 Exchange Place&#44;<lb/>
                New York&#44; 22 Aug 1884<lb/></p>
                
            <p>Rev<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. S. Morais<lb/>
                Philadelphia<lb/></p>
            <p>Dear Sir<lb/></p>
            <p>Some ten days ago when I happened to<lb/> see Judge Isaacs &#44; he asked me if I would reply to a<lb/> letter he had received from you &#40;dated 27 July last&#41;<lb/> as the subject of the Colony at Vineland. I told him<lb/>that I would read the letter&#44; he would not promise to<lb/> reply to it. I have to day received a note from him<lb/> enclosing yours to him of 16 Inst.&#44; and urging me to<lb/> reply to you at once on the subjects touched on.<lb/></p>
            <p>The sudden awakening of our brethren in Philadelphia<lb/> after a two years&#39; sleep&#44; to the existence of the Jewish<lb/> Colony at Alliance &#40;within 30 miles of this City&#41;<lb/> appears to have left them much in the condition<lb/> of Rip Van Winkle on his return to the village after<lb/> his memorable slumber on the Katskills. They do<lb/> not appear to know how and by whom the Colony<lb/> was established&#44; or how it has been kept alive and<lb/> few did &#91;&#63;&#93; since.  They apply to Judge Isaacs for<lb/> information which they should know that it is impos&#45;<lb/>sible for him to impart&#44; considering that except inci&#45;<lb/>dentally as the trusted agent of the Paris &#34;Alliance<lb/> Israelite&#34; he has had personally very little to do with<lb/> the Colony&#44; which was established by the Hebrew Emigrant<lb/> Aid Society of which I am a Resident and which has<lb/> been cared for since that Society&#44; practically<lb/> ceased to exist by a Committee consisting of myself as<lb/>  Chairman &#38; Treasurer&#44; Messrs. Gershel&#44; Eppinger &#38; Rosenfeld&#44;<lb/> aided by funds raised here under the supervision of<lb/> the Rev<hi rend="sup">d</hi> D<hi rend="sup">rs</hi> Gottheill &#38; Heubsch and some remittances<lb/> for agricultural purposes from the Paris &#34;Alliance Israelite.&#34;<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="2"/>
            <p>They appear to be ignorant of the fact that about<lb/> a year ago&#44; Drs Gottheil &#38; Heubsch visited the<lb/> Colony and were so impressed with the necessity of its<lb/> usefulness that on their return to New York they made<lb/> a collection among their parishioners of over &#36;5000<lb/> which was handed to this Committee and used by<lb/> them to help the Colonists through the winter&#45;&#45;that a<lb/> further sum of <hi rend="underline">&#36;3500</hi> was accepted&#91;&#63;&#93; by Judge Isaacs<lb/> as the agent of the &#34;Alliance&#34;&#44; for Agricultural work<lb/> expanded this Spring pro rata among the Colonists.<lb/>  Finally they do not seem to be aware <del>that</del> when Passover<lb/> of this year came along and Matsoth were required<lb/> for gratuitous distribution&#44; that an application made<lb/> by Dr. Gottheil and others to charitable people in<lb/> Philadelphia be a contribution of sufficient <hi rend="underline">Bread</hi><lb/> of this description known so well to Israelites and<lb/> refered&#91;&#63;&#93; there and that I had to purchase of<lb/> Hammerslag &#38; Amram&#44; to the extent of &#36;219 with<lb/> out of the funds in hand&#44; necessary for more important<lb/> purposes.<lb/></p>
            <p>I go with these details to show you what has happened<lb/> during the Philadelphia slumber&#45;&#45; as you may seem<lb/> to be awake and desirous of helping with good work<lb/> it will afford me much pleasure to advise as to how<lb/> your Society can be best bestowed. We have practically<lb/> no funds in hand &#40;barely &#36;200&#41; and having done all<lb/> that we think necessary to aid these people in their<lb/> battle for life&#44; we have concluded henceforth merely<lb/> to protest them in their proprietary rights&#44; and help to <lb/> keep alive the Segar industry which furnishes some<lb/> wages to those not otherwise employed. I am aware&#44;<lb/> however&#44; that some individuals require special<lb/> temporary assistance and much good could be done by<lb/> a visiting Committee possessed of some means &#40;&#36;1000 is<lb/>all would probably be sufficient&#41; to bridge over the<lb/> approaching winter. As a rule the 50 families who<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="3"/>
            <p>H.S. Henry&#44;<lb/>
                Box 3144&#44; P.O.<lb/>
                CABLE ADDRESS&#45;&#45;KENRY&#44; NEW YORK.<lb/></p>
            
            <p>48 Exchange Place&#44;<lb/>
                New York&#44; 22 Aug 1884<lb/></p>
                
            <p>now comprise the Colony&#44; are good people&#44; anxious<lb/> to work and desirous of making homes for themselves.<lb/>  They have had a hard fight to subdue the land and<lb/> to make it yield ultimately something wherefrom to live.<lb/> The cost of this establishment has been very heavy<lb/> as irrespective of the land we have expended over &#36;25&#44;000<lb/>  in houses&#91;&#44;&#93; seeding&#44; fertilizing and support during<lb/> the past two years. We have weeded out now the inef&#45;<lb/>ficient &#40;about 17 families&#41; so that the 50 remaining are<lb/> likely to be henceforth less of a burden. The first cost<lb/> of the houses you complain of as &#34;mere sheds&#34; &#38;c cost&#91;&#63;&#93; &#36;125<lb/> each to which in most cases have since been added<lb/> kitchens&#44; cellars &#38; outhouses&#44; then stoves &#38; furniture&#44; so<lb/> that the total cost is no less than &#36;200 each. There are<lb/> 67  houses representing therefore <hi rend="underline">&#36;13&#44;400</hi>&#8212;no inconsiderable<lb/> an outlay to start upon.  That these houses are not<lb/> altogether weather tight is quite possible&#45;&#45;but we do not<lb/> propose to go any further expecting that in many cases<lb/> the people themselves can help to keep their places in order<lb/> and that where they are not able to do so&#44; an occasional<lb/>  assistance in money would straighten things out&#8212;our<lb/> observations tending to show us that the more that is<lb/> &#91;&#63;&#93;&#44; the more is required.<lb/></p>
            <p>I have the utmost confidence in the &#91;&#63;&#93;<lb/> They own one half of the property absolutely&#8212;the Hebrew<lb/> Em. Aid Society the other half. Settlers were put on<lb/> their land and in &#91;&#63;&#93; indiscriminately&#8212;contracts<lb/> for the sale of the land to the Colonists were given to all<lb/> holders identical in character&#44; and it was understood<lb/> that  no discrimination should be made in any way.<lb/> They of course cannot afford to donate the land&#44; but are<lb/> willing to wait for payment until the same can be made<lb/> by the holders&#44; pending which interest &#38; taxes must be<lb/> met.  I will enquire with the case of the man<lb/> <hi rend="underline">Yassem</hi> to which you refer&#44; and will inform you in a<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="4"/>
                
            <p>few days how the matter stands. These people sell out&#91;&#63;&#93;<lb/> to one another without regard to the debt contracted by<lb/> them at Messr Leach&#39;s store or the improvements that<lb/> have been made as their places and of course they cannot<lb/> move in any other direction until the indebtedness<lb/> is covered. By right&#44; the first man cannot sell out<lb/> until he has paid what he owes in this respect.<lb/> The report I have on record of this man &#34;Yasem&#34; is<lb/> that his family consists of wife&#44; mother&#44; mother in law<lb/> 5 children 3&#91;&#63;&#93; 16 years&#44; of age. Shoemaker by trade.&#34; He<lb/> has done much towards cultivating his land&#8212;but<lb/> has a sewing machine. He asks &#64;40&#58;pdz&#91;&#63;&#93; for shirts to<lb/> Johnson 41 Walker St NYork&#44; where he has a son.<lb/></p>
            <p>I have not time to enlarge any further on matters<lb/> which it doubtless might be interesting for you to <lb/> know&#44; but to show you that I am thoroughly desirous<lb/> of co&#45;operating with you and the other Gentn. of your<lb/> &#91;&#63;&#93;&#44; I shall be happy if you will name a day when<lb/> it will be convenient for you to meet me and any other<lb/>Gent&#91;lema&#93;n &#91;&#63;&#93; who may be desiring &#91;&#63;&#93;to go down<lb/> to Vineland. We will sleep in Philadelphia&#44; and take<lb/> the 8 o&#39;clock train returning the same evening &#40;West Jersey<lb/> road&#41;. We can then discuss all matters of interest&#44; and<lb/> I can give you personally the information necessary for<lb/> you to form a proper judgment of what should be done<lb/> further to help these people&#8212;in whom I need not<lb/> say that I take a deep interest&#44; and with all of<lb/> when I am more or less acquainted&#44; having a<lb/> written record of all their personal peculiarities.<lb/> Hoping to get a favorable response to this request&#44;<lb/></p>
            <p>I am Dear Sir<lb/>
                Yours &#91;&#63;&#93;
                H S Henry<lb/></p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
