<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF4_11</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_11_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_11_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_11_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_11_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_11_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_11_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_11_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_11_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_11_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_11_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_11_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_11_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_11_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_11_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_11_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_11_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>13 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Post Biblical lecture<lb/>
                31.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>In a previous the preceding lecture&#44; I f expressed my opinion&#44;<lb/> that the choice of Josephus as military commander of<lb/> Galilee&#44; was a misfortune.  Had It is believed that had he gathered<lb/> in that mountainous region&#44; all whose hearts<lb/> beat for country religion and country&#44; and by a<lb/> resolute effort held Rome in check&#44; a painful redoutable<lb/> ally might have arisen to thrust back a<lb/> common foe.  The Parthians in Western Asia<lb/> were the sworn enemies of that empire Power on the Tiber whose<lb/> vaulting ambition led it to meddle in the af&#45;<lb/>&#45;fairs of other nations&#44; and then to domineer<lb/> over them by with insolence with and brutal force.  But Josephus<lb/> frittered away a most precious time in fighting&#44;<lb/> by tactics in which he was a perfect master&#44;<lb/> those whom he feared as his personal own personal opponents.<lb/>  Johanan&#44; or John son of Levy&#44; was the man<lb/> with whom our Jewish historian entered into a bit&#45;<lb/>&#45;ter contest.  John belonged to a wealthy<lb/> family of Giskala&#45;&#45;a city in the Western<lb/> part of Galilee.  Being a personal on friendly<lb/> of relations with Simon son of Rabbi Gamliel I&#44; President of<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>the Sanhedrin under whom St Paul boasted to have studied&#44; he enjoyed <sic>weilded</sic> considerable<lb/> influence.  Of that he took advantage&#44; to<lb/> put himself at the head of a number of Jews&#44;<lb/> who were determined to resist Roman aggression.<lb/>  Still&#44; John of Giskala acted cautiously at the<lb/> outset.  He knew that the Roman eagle was<lb/> ever wakeful and ready to fly upon its prey.  He therefore<lb/> <sic>counselled</sic> prudence&#59; but when his native city<lb/> rashly attempted what it could not accom&#45;<lb/>&#45;plish&#44; and suffered as a penalty the burning<lb/> of its houses and the destruction of its inhabitants&#44;<lb/> then John arose stirred like a lyon lion&#44; and the report<lb/> of his deeds of valor spread throughout Galilee.<lb/>  Josephus acknowledges that his adversary had<lb/> language at his command&#44; bright intelligence<lb/> and large capacities&#44; but he charges him with an<lb/> inordinate thirst for power.  Judging dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;passionately&#44; one might infer that John of Giskala<lb/> would have acted in concert with the newly appointed<lb/> Governor of Galilee&#44; if he had not detected in Josephus<lb/> a wavering mind&#44; disinclined to openly declare himself openly<lb/> hostile to Rome.  However&#44; an enmity arose ensued&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>which became irreconcilable.  John had on his<lb/> side the Zealots&#44; and all who would not bend the neck to a<lb/> foreign yoke.  Josephus had the advantage of being<lb/> the recognized commander chief&#44; and the favorite of Agrippa<lb/> II and of the Peace party.  The man of Giskala<lb/> and his followers seeing that Josephus was temporizing&#44;<lb/> instead of using vigorous measures to put the country<lb/> in the requisite state of defense&#44; accused him of<lb/> treachery before the Sanhedrin.  The ways by<lb/> which the Governor of Galilee eluded evaded the order<lb/> of the higher authorities at Jerusalem that summoned<lb/> him to the captial to justify his conduct&#59; how he<lb/> defiantly remained in office and overreached his op&#45;<lb/>&#45;ponents&#44; all of that forms a record of artfulness cunning un&#45;<lb/>&#45;surpassed&#44; of a an artful diplomacy not met among the shrew&#45;<lb/>&#45;dest politicians.  Josephus despite his superlative<lb/> abilities to put the best face on his worst actions&#44;<lb/> cannot <sic>decieve</sic> his readers who follow him closely<lb/> in the narrative of that transaction.  I have<lb/> no wish to report in detail what he tells us in<lb/> his history and in his biography&#44; not unfrequently<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>falling into contradictions&#44; his own statements&#44; in<lb/> his anxiety to appear pure hearted.  Intending<lb/> to give only a summary of accounts which others<lb/> have related at great length&#44; I pass on to the<lb/> most stirring event in the public life of Josephus.<lb/></p>
            <p>Nero was in &#91;&#63;&#93; abroad&#44; when the news of the<lb/> revolutionary in war in Palestine reached his ears.<lb/>  That mad&#44; not less than wicked&#44; emperor had gone to<lb/> Greece to display his pretended talents as a comedy<lb/> player&#44; a poet&#44; a musician and a singer.  Among<lb/> the retinue that had accompanied him there&#44; was Flavius<lb/> Vespasian.  This general was did not particularly liked enjoy the<lb/> by good will of his sovereign.  He had the misfortune of having<lb/> been seen asleep at the theatre&#44; while Nero was<lb/> on the stage reciting some insipid a piece of his own compo&#45;<lb/>&#45;sition.  His Vespasian&#39;s drawniness might have cost him<lb/> his life&#44; if the turn of affairs in the East had<lb/> not made his services indispensable very desirable.<lb/>  Vespasian was of humble parentage&#44; and Nero<lb/> did not fear that his ambition would rise too<lb/> high above his lowly station.  As a soldier&#44; he had<lb/> shown consummate skill in fighting Germans&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>British&#44; and Gauls&#44; and all acknowledged in recognized conceded to him<lb/> the virtues of perseverance &#38; prudence&#44; and the knowledge of military<lb/> discipline.  When As soon as he was entrusted with the general&#45;<lb/>&#45;ship of the army destined to overthrow Judea&#44; Vespa&#45;<lb/>&#45;sion ordered his son Titus to precede him by the way<lb/> of the Mediterannean sea to Alexandria&#44; while he would<lb/> go travel by land through Asia Minor.  Arrived at Saint<lb/> John D &#39;Acre&#44; then called Ptolema&#239;s&#44; and in Biblical<lb/> times Acco&#44; Vespasian prepared his plans for an inva&#45;<lb/>sion of the land of our fathers.  He had with him under his com&#45;<lb/>&#45;mand&#44; a force amounting to nearly a hundred thousand men&#44; besides aside<lb/> having from the reliance he could place in the active sympathy of he resigned from of the Peace party in<lb/> Judea.  A description of those troops&#59; of their looks&#44;<lb/> of their movements&#44; of their discipline&#44; and of their fear&#45;<lb/>&#45;lessness&#44; is drawn by Josephus with a masterly<lb/> pen.  It That delineation has been considered superior to the finest<lb/> chapters in Greek and Roman histories.  We&#44; as<lb/> Jews&#44; can take no delight in fixing our mental vision<lb/> on a picture which recalls our national suffering<lb/> and sorrow&#44; however we may admire the literary<lb/> eminence of a man of our faith.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>What we do gaze upon with melancholy<lb/> pleasure is the delineation portrait description of the unexcelled bravery<lb/> of those among our ancestors&#44; who made rendered the<lb/> siege and capture of Jotapata famous in the<lb/> annals of the world.  And here I must award<lb/> to a Christian clergyman the honor of having<lb/> left the most thrilling and withal the most just<lb/> narrative of that episode&#44; so sublime in its unut&#45;<lb/>&#45;terable sadness.  Dean Milman had no occasion<lb/> to apologize in a measure&#44; for having dwelt long<lb/> on that subject.  It deserved a lengthy record&#59; for<lb/> at Jotapata our people strikingly showed that the noble<lb/> blood of the Maccabees flowed in their veins.<lb/>  It was in that city surrounded by mountains and ravines&#44; and<lb/> accessible only on the from its Northern side&#44; that the de&#45;<lb/>&#45;fenders of Galilee gathered banded together to hul hurl back the hea&#45;<lb/>&#45;then&#44; or to die sword in hand.  If They felt that if Rome planted<lb/> her banner on the heights of Jotapata&#44; the ensign<lb/> of Israel would be made to trail the dust everywhere.<lb/>  Josephus commanded the patriots&#44; who had shut them&#45;<lb/>&#45;selves in that town&#44; from which to they would dare Vespasian&#39;s<lb/> redoutable army.  In the absence of any<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>other history save that which he wrote&#44; we<lb/> must allow that the son of Matthias the priest<lb/> was the man who in Jotapata exhibited a<lb/> generalship wonderful in genius&#44; most stupendous<lb/> in its appliances.  Was it compulsion that stirred<lb/> up Josephus&#59; was it compunction&#63;  None will ever<lb/> tell be able to tell.  The Romans had<lb/> placed themselves in battle array&#44; on a distant hill.<lb/>  They would thus strike terror among the defenders&#44;<lb/> and they succeeded in their object&#44; but for a mo&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment.  Dread of such a formidable army&#44; so<lb/> splendidly equipped soon gave room to stubborn<lb/> resistance.  The Latin soldiers mounted up walls<lb/> which they raised&#44; to throw in dart off their javelins&#44; but<lb/> often they met a grave into the precipices below&#44;<lb/> wherein the Jews of Jotapata cast them headlong.  Forty<lb/> seven summer days the siege continued.  The want<lb/> of water was distressing&#44; yet the besieged&#44; hung their<lb/> garments from the battlements&#44; steeped in water&#44;<lb/> to mock the enemy&#44; who thought hoped that thirst would<lb/> effect more than the sword.  The Romans built<lb/> up battlements&#44; the Galileans reared still higher ones&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>from which to harass their foes.  To prevent<lb/> the latter striking at the workmen&#44; Josephus<lb/> ordered poles to be nailed round the walls&#44; on which<lb/> were suspended hides of oxen freshly killed.  Against<lb/> those curiously contrived curtains&#44; the arrows shot<lb/> by the Romans glided off without doing the least injury.<lb/>  Vespasian saw himself baffled&#44; and changed tactics con&#45;<lb/>&#45;tinually&#44; but the Jews watched him by the courage<lb/> of desperation.  The battering ram&#44; the most<lb/> tremendous piece of artillery in ancient warfare had<lb/> been resorted to.  It was consisted of an immense beam headed with<lb/> iron&#44; in the shape of a ram&#39;s head.  It was drawn<lb/> back by a great number of men&#44; and then driven forward<lb/> by cables with a push&#44; at which towers would sometime crumble break<lb/> into fragments.  At the first shock the all&#44; behind<lb/> which the defenders of Jotapata stood fought&#44; quaked&#44; and<lb/> a wild cry pierced the sky&#44; but Josephus ordered that<lb/> bags fell full of straw&#44; be let down from the walls<lb/> to catch the hard blows of the battering rams&#44; and<lb/> make them ineffectual.  The Romans were astound&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed at the <sic>unequalled</sic> daring of those who kept<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>at bay the invincible legions that had conquered<lb/> mighty nations.  They <sic>marvelled</sic> when they witnessed<lb/> instances of a valor never surpassed.  A Galilean<lb/> called Eleazar Ben Sameas&#44; seeing the battering ram<lb/> approach&#44; stood up on the top of the wall&#44; and<lb/> holding a huge stone struck off with a steady aim struck off the iron head of the<lb/> ram.  He then leaped down below&#44; secured his prize&#44;<lb/> and was bearing it back to his <sic>follow</sic> combat&#45;<lb/>&#45;ants&#44; while arrows and javelins whizzed around him.<lb/>  He was pierced through&#44; but he succeeded to reach<lb/> again the top of the wall&#44; display his trophy the ram&#39;s head with<lb/> an air of defiance&#44; before1 the Roman army&#44; and then<lb/> fall dead&#44; while clinching his trophy in his convulsive<lb/> hand.  The future emperor of Rome was per&#45;<lb/>&#45;sonally directing the assault by with that appalling engine<lb/> of destruction&#44; when a javelin from a Jewish archer<lb/> wounded his heel.  At the sight of Vespasian&#39;s<lb/> wound blood&#44; the Romans became frantic with wroth.<lb/>  They rushed furiously on against the defenders&#44; who<lb/> met them with drawn swords&#44; with fire&#44; with<lb/> streaming oil&#44; which they poured upon the assailants.<lb/>  I shall not venture on a description far by beyond<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>my capacities and too harrowing in its nature.<lb/>  Suffice to say that Jotapata has left on our<lb/> people the indelible impress of a heroism&#44; which<lb/> must claim the respect of mankind to the end<lb/> of time.  For our defenders showed that they knew<lb/> not alone how to steel their hearts for the battle&#44;<lb/> but also how to suffer long and terribly fearfully rather<lb/> than abandon the cause of country and religion.<lb/>  The blockade would would have lasted until every<lb/> man that could carry a weapon had died from<lb/> sheer exhaustion.  Josephus who&#44; at one time&#44; would<lb/> have fled &#91;&#63;&#93; surrendered to save his life&#44; was made to stand<lb/> at his post&#44; and lead on to a combat&#44; which<lb/> promised but death&#44; though yet glorious.  Thus<lb/> for forty seven days the gallant inhabitants<lb/> of Jotapata braved the dreaded cohorts of Rome&#44;<lb/> heeding neither fatigue nor wounds nor thirst&#44;<lb/> solely intent upon meeting strategy with stra&#45;<lb/>&#45;tegy&#44; assaults with counter assaults&#44; intrepidity with a tenacity<lb/> of will with equal interepidity But a deserter<lb/> found his way to the tent of Vespasian.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>He told of the enfeebled condition of those<lb/> who still resisted the Romans&#44; he related how the same<lb/> people who fought by day were obliged to watch<lb/> at night&#44; how reduced were their ranks by through a super&#45;<lb/>human efforts strain of body and mind.  Vespasian<lb/> was inclined at first to suspect treachery&#44; for not<lb/> long before&#44; a Jew taken prisoner bore tortures and<lb/> finally crucifixion rather than betray the state<lb/> of his countrymen be<sic>seiged</sic> in Jotapata.  Still&#44;<lb/> after mature deliberation&#44; the Roman general decided upon making a<lb/> sudden attack before sun rise. at early dawn.  Titus was the<lb/> first to scale the walls.  The sentinels jaded<lb/> and weary&#44; had fallen asleep.  They were pierced<lb/> through&#44; and under the cover of a thick mist<lb/> which unfortunately overspread the sky the<lb/> enemy advanced.  The people awoke to see<lb/> the sword hanging over their heads.  Terrific was<lb/> the struggle&#44; horrid the carnage.  None by women<lb/> and children were spared.  Forty thousand perished<lb/> and only twelve hundred&#45;&#45;unable by age or sex to bear arms&#45;&#45; were made captives out of that band of heros were seized as captives.<lb/>  The noble city was made became a heap of ruin&#44; and its fortifications<lb/> were burnt by order of Flavious Vespasian.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p>The scene is too unspeakably distressing.<lb/>  Our historian could picture it with the pencil<lb/> of a literary genius&#44; but not with the a pen dip&#45;<lb/>&#45;ped in the tears of a soul crushed patriot.<lb/>  We will cast a veil over it&#44; and turning<lb/> our looks away from it&#44; we shall meet Jo&#45;<lb/>&#45;sephus again seeking to preserve his own<lb/> life after the fall of all the heroic defend&#45;<lb/>&#45;ers of Jotapata.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
