<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF3_12</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_12_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_12_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_12_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_12_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_12_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_12_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_12_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_12_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_12_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_12_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_12_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_12_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_12_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_12_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_12_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_12_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>An address for the sabbath before<lb/>
                Purim<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Dear Brethren&#33;  The history of the period&#44; which we are about to<lb/> celebrate&#44; is evidently held by our Sages in the highest estimation.<lb/>  Those zealous teachers have been scrupulous in transmitting every<lb/> portion of Holy Writ intact&#44; still&#44; in none&#44; except in the whole<lb/> Pentateuch&#44; and the fragments thereof&#44; have they enjoined such pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;cision in the mode of writing&#44; such accuracy in preparing the vellum<lb/> to be employed by the scribes&#44; as in the transcription of the book of<lb/> Esther.  And they&#44; who have given the study of the law precedence<lb/> to the performance of other important duties&#44; allow even the temporary<lb/> neglect of the former&#44; in order that we may attend to the recital<lb/> of the Meguil&#224;h.  Were we now to enquire into the motives<lb/> that actuated them&#44; we would learn that they are principally to<lb/> be ascribed to homage for the illustrious Jewess&#44; who became at this<lb/> season&#44; an instrument of salvation.  The exactitude&#44; they say&#44; which<lb/> the daughter of Abihail&#44; must have practised in promulgating<lb/> her edict among all her dispersed brethren&#44; shall be employed<lb/> by her descendants in copying &#38; perusing the events connected with her life.<lb/>  My friends&#33;  A tribute of so much honor could h not have been<lb/> more deservedly bestowed&#59; for&#44; Esther the queen was severely<lb/> tried&#44; and proved true to her faith and true to her people.<lb/>  The annals of modern times&#44; as well as those of antiquity&#44; afford<lb/> instances of women&#44; who staked their lives and reputations&#44;<lb/> when inflamed by patriotism&#44; and who through their<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>heroic deeds&#44; either won freedom for their country&#44; or purged the<lb/> earth of a ruthless tyrant&#59; but the combination of sterling<lb/> virtue&#44; and heartfelt religion&#44; such abnegation of oneself&#44; such<lb/> sagacity in thwarting the devices of the wicked&#44; such moderation<lb/> in enjoying success&#44; have no parallel.  The inspired<lb/> writer with a forcible simplicity peculiar to the narratives of<lb/> the Scriptures&#44; represents to our mind the winning qualities of<lb/> that orphan maid&#44; whilst under the tutelage of her cousin.<lb/>  &#34;It was not only commiseration for her forlorn condition&#44; that<lb/> prompted Mordecai to offer her his protection&#44; but&#44; as we sub&#45;<lb/>&#45;sequently learn&#44; her unbounded affection and obedience engen&#45;<lb/>&#45;dered in his bosom&#44; feelings of parental tenderness.  And we<lb/> may even be allowed to infer that had it depended upon<lb/> her own will&#44; she would have preferred lowness beneath the<lb/> roof of her generous kinsman&#44; to the pomp of the royal<lb/> court.  But her desire was not consulted.  The officers<lb/> of King Ahasueros had been deputed to convey to his palace<lb/> all the comely damsels&#44; dwelling within his dominion&#44; and she<lb/> could not elude their watchfulness.  The hebrew text renders gives us<lb/> testimony scope to imply that she was constrained to repair thither.  &#34;And it<lb/> came to pass&#44; when the king&#39;s commandment and his decree were<lb/> heard&#44; and when many maidens had gathered together into Shushan<lb/> the palace&#59; then Esther was taken into the king&#39;s house&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Others may have appeared eager to obtain that which was<lb/> deemed the highest honor&#44; but she must have loathed a union with an<lb/> idolater&#44; and fain would have clung to her home and to her faith relative.  Yet&#44; if com&#45;<lb/>&#45;pulsion placed her in a sphere&#44; where her inherent virtues were<lb/> in jeopardy&#44; we perceive that throughout her vicissitudes&#44; she<lb/> maintained the excellencies that had distinguished her youth.<lb/>  And this must chiefly elicit our admiration&#59; for&#44; it is comparatively<lb/> easy in a mediocre condition to resist vice&#44; but to stand proof<lb/> against corruption&#44; when we inhale its very atmosphere&#44;<lb/> it is almost superhuman.  As we see how&#44; individuals<lb/> who pursued religion and truth in humble circumstances will<lb/> evince a totally different demeanour&#44; when raised to affluence<lb/> and power&#59; how&#44; elated by their success&#44; they will consider it vulgar<lb/> to adhere to their former religious habits&#59; how&#44; the seductive voice of<lb/> sycophants will inflate their minds with the conception of a<lb/> superiority they do not possess&#44; we must indeed award infinite<lb/> praise to that queen of whom we read &#34;that she performed the<lb/> command of Mordecai&#44; as when she was brought up with him&#34;<lb/> secluded from the rest of her brethren&#44; separated from him who<lb/> had been her guide and tutor&#59; surrounded&#44; on the contrary&#44;<lb/> by heathens and by courtiers&#44; Esther did not nevertheless forget the lessons<lb/> she had early imbibed.  &#34;The sabbath and the festivals&#44; and<lb/> all the ceremonial tenets of the law&#44; she observed with the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>with the same rigidness as when with her cousin&#34; Such is<lb/> the chaldaic paraphrase upon of the sentence above quoted&#44; and<lb/> although the remark may be regarded as a simple conjecture&#44;<lb/> still&#44; the character of that illustrious Jewess fully justifies it&#44;<lb/> for&#44; nothing save the constant exercise of religious duties could<lb/> have inspired her with the courage of <sic>imperilling</sic> her own existence&#44;<lb/> for the sake of her people&#44; by confronting her dreaded lord without<lb/> his summons.  And verily my friend was not that hazardous<lb/> undertaking&#44; <sic>preceeded</sic> by an act of humiliation to her heavenly<lb/> Protector&#63;  Did she perchance rely for the success of her <sic>appaling</sic><lb/> mission&#44; on her comeliness&#44; on her charms&#63;  No&#44; during three<lb/> consecutive days she poured forth her soul unto Him &#34;who can<lb/> turn the hearts of kings whithersoever he will&#34; And as the right&#45;<lb/>&#45;eous by Babylonian captives&#59; as Daniel&#44; Hyra and Nehemiah<lb/> had propitiated the help of God by fast and prayer&#44; so did<lb/> she deny herself every ailment&#44; solely intent to elevate her pure<lb/> spirit to the omnipotent Lord.  And even subsequently<lb/> to her success after she had by a wisely concocted plan&#44; crushed<lb/> the wicked Haman wily minister to the earth&#44; at a moment he deemed himself<lb/> in the full enjoyment of her favor&#44; still piety and virtue brightly shone in her<lb/> character.  The wife of a Potentate&#44; who had proffered her<lb/> half of his vast realm&#44; she could have demanded the exter&#45;<lb/>&#45;mination of those&#44; who were ready to imbue their hands<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>in guiltless blood&#59; she could have sought posts of distinction<lb/> for the exiles who had been iniquitously traduced&#44; but whilst<lb/> queen Esther yearned towards her brethren and knew how to brave<lb/> death for their sake&#44; yet&#44; her noble heart harbored no revenge&#44; and desired<lb/> no boon.  With tearful eyes therefore she implored her husband and<lb/> King&#44; as an act of justice&#44; to repeal the sanguinary mandate<lb/> he had issued&#44; not&#44; as some have <sic>wofully</sic> misunderstood it&#44; in order<lb/> that the Jews might gratify their vengeance&#44; but that they might<lb/> not be deliberately slaughtered.  &#34;For&#44; how could I&#44; she lamented&#44; how could<lb/> I witness the extinction of my race&#34;&#63;  And in truth&#44; had not<lb/> the laws of Persia&#44; forbid the recantation of a royal edict&#44; tran&#45;<lb/>&#45;quillity and security might have immediately followed the exe&#45;<lb/>&#45;cution of Haman&#44; but in consequence of that prevention&#44; it<lb/> became needful to empower the hebrew subjects of Ahasueros&#44;<lb/> to defend themselves against repel their aggressors.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> is the original text &#34;to gather themselves and stand for their lives&#44;&#34;<lb/> and the event proved the efficacy of such a measure&#44; for&#44; despite<lb/> the posterior rescript&#44; they who had looked forward to the day&#44; when<lb/> they could with impunity&#44; massacre and plunder&#44; were not deter&#45;<lb/>&#45;red from their purpose.  But they encountered a staunch<lb/> resistance.  The Jews strengthened by the justice of their cause&#44;<lb/> supported by royal authority&#44; manly gallantly opposed that irruption<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>ready to overwhelm them.  To defend their hearths and their<lb/> children&#44; they slew their fierce oppressors&#59; still&#44; the pages<lb/> wherein their victory is registered&#44; record also that they forbare<lb/> laying their hands upon the spoil of their enemies.  And&#44;<lb/> what furthermore reflects honor upon their memory is the<lb/> fact&#44; that whilst the term &#34;&#91;&#63;&#93; man&#34; occurs twice in the<lb/> enumeration of their victims&#44; the word &#34;woman&#34; or &#34;infant&#44;&#34; is<lb/> not to be found.  A moderation is1 that2 greatly to be<lb/> commended&#44; inasmuch as the decree of Haman spared neither<lb/> female nor suckling.  And if we bear in mind withal the<lb/> state of warfare among the ancients&#44; when the belligerents allow&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed themselves the most flagitious acts&#44; we&#44; the descendants<lb/> of those outcasts of Judea&#44; may glory in our predecessors.<lb/>  Their names have perished with their bodies&#44; but the virtuous<lb/> deed they accomplished&#44; history has penned with indelible cha&#45;<lb/>&#45;racters&#44; as a pattern worthy of imitation.<lb/></p>
            <p>But if the demeanour of our progenitors&#44; at those stirring times&#44;<lb/> justly deserves encomium&#44; that of their righteous pious queen&#44; claims<lb/> all the honor which our Sages have bestowed&#44; and their adherents<lb/> publicly exhibit every revolving year&#59; for&#44; alike upon the<lb/> throne as in obscurity&#44; in the days of triumph as in those of<lb/> calamity&#44; Esther never forswore her faith&#44; nor abjured her<lb/> lowly extraction.  The virtues which formed the brightest<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>ornament of her crown&#44; were based on the religion she was<lb/> taught to revere&#44; and consequently they never flagged.  Her<lb/> implicit obedience to the protector of her youth&#44; the intense love<lb/> she bore her despised brethren&#44; the absence of rancorous feelings<lb/> even against their feel persecutors&#44; sprung from a mind accustomed<lb/> to the constant exercise of those practices which uplift the spirit<lb/> and chasten the passions.  To them did Esther resort for consolation&#44;<lb/> and they sustained her checkered life.  She felt that she was<lb/> the humble handmaid by whose instrumentality the Lord had<lb/> chosen to operate miracles&#44; and became not elated on beholding<lb/> a dreaded monarch enchained by her graces.  When he in the<lb/> fulness of admiration&#44; repeatedly asked her to tax his bounty&#44; she<lb/> with sobbing accents petitioned&#44; but for the deliverance of them&#44; who<lb/> like her&#44; adored the God of Jacob.  And that all&#45;absorbing design&#44;<lb/> is&#44; according to my judgment&#44; the motive that prompted her to<lb/> request that the children of Haman might be suspended upon<lb/> the gallows.  They had already been slain in the conflict&#44; on<lb/> the thirteenth of Adar.  Upon the following day&#44; the meeting was<lb/> generally quelled&#44; and the Hebrew denizens of Persia and Media<lb/> rested&#59; but in the Metropolis&#44; where the partizans of the impious<lb/> Agaguite were more numerous&#44; the sedition was still formented<lb/> by the ring&#45;leaders.  The queen therefore imagined that when the<lb/> knowledge that the principal actors in that tragedy&#44; had succumbed&#44;<lb/> spread abroad<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>might stop the shedding of blood might cease and restore peace be restored to her<lb/> nation.  That her suggestion proved abortive&#44; ought not to<lb/> be assigned to her indiscretion&#44; for&#44; often the noblest and most<lb/> magnanimous schemes fail in their intended effect.<lb/></p>
            <p>And now that I have cursorily delineated the traits of the Jewess<lb/> who instituted the festivity of Purim&#44; let us draw the conclusion<lb/> at which I meant to arrive.  The Rabbies have instructed us<lb/> to pay annually a tribute of veneration to that illustrious woman<lb/> of our race.  Their appreciation of her relig piety and virtue induced them<lb/> to enact the strictest accuracy in transcribing the history of<lb/> the time&#44; where she played so important a part.  To perpetuate<lb/> the memory of her excellent deeds&#44; they enjoined the public recital<lb/> of the Meguil&#225;h&#59; and in obedience to her behests&#44; they recom&#45;<lb/>&#45;mended&#44; on this joyous occasion&#44; the reciprocity of gifts and<lb/> the succour of the indigent.  I believe that your instincts<lb/> as men and as Israelites&#44; will impel you to discharge the two<lb/> last obligations.  You will enliven your circle by tokens<lb/> of amity&#44; and gladden by your generosity the heart of the poor.<lb/>  But&#44; take heed not to disregard the other precept&#44; because it seems<lb/> of minor importance&#59; for&#44; your attending the Synagogue on the<lb/> eve of Purim and on the morrow&#44; will be an open avowal of<lb/> your adherence to the practices of our religion&#44; on which greatly<lb/> depend the preservation of our nationality and the happiness of<lb/> our homes.  It will prove&#44; moreover&#44; that you cherish the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>memory of her who jeopardized her existence&#44; to avert from us a<lb/> certain death&#44; and it will also imbue your children&#39;s mind with<lb/> the respect due to the counsel of the sages of Israel.<lb/></p>
            
            <p>Omnipotent Lord&#33;  Upon they mercy we have ever relied&#44; and<lb/> Thou hast not shamed us in our trust.  When Thou hadst led thy<lb/> people into the heritage&#44; which thy hands had established&#44; thy<lb/> divine presence dwelt among them&#44; and was their guide.  The<lb/> high priest by his sacred oracles&#44; and the prophet by his inspiration<lb/> interpreted thy will&#44; and imparted it to the faithful.  But our fathers<lb/> sinned&#44; and Thou didst hide thy face from them.  Men&#44; hordes of bar&#45;<lb/>&#45;barous nations trampled upon the land of promise&#44; and sorely grieved<lb/> the seed of Abraham&#59; but yet Thou hadst not abandoned them.<lb/>  Thou wouldst not&#44; whilst in captivity&#44; visibly interpose in their fa&#45;<lb/>&#45;vour as heretofore&#44; but Thou <sic>dist</sic> raise for them redeemers and they<lb/> were liberated.  Even the most tenuous beings&#44; summoned the courage<lb/> of a lion to execute thy fiat&#44; for&#44; Thou dost not take delight in the<lb/> might of man&#44; but in the fear which he harbors for Thee.  And<lb/> because she feared thy name&#44; Thou didst choose the foster&#45;child<lb/> of the righteous Mordecai as the arm of thy vengeance.<lb/></p>
            <p>One of the iniquitous progeny of Amalek spurred by wounded in his ambition&#44; and<lb/> goaded by an hereditary hatred against thy people&#44; devised their<lb/> annihilation.  A That profane unbeliever&#44; he wished to uproot what<lb/> Thou O God&#33; hast planted for all ages&#44; but through the feeble means<lb/> of a hebrew woman&#44; Thou didst cause his iniquity to recoil upon<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>his head.  The day which he superstitiously had set apart<lb/> to execute his impious scheme&#44; Thou didst signally prove to him<lb/> and to the world&#44; that he who offendeth Israel&#44; offendeth God<lb/> their protector.  Lord&#33;  To maintain vivid in our minds that<lb/> token of thy fatherly love&#44; we at this season&#44; yearly assemble at<lb/> thy holy courts O Lord&#33; and whilst we rejoice at thy salvation&#44; we<lb/> render our necessitous brethren participants <sic>als</sic> of our festivity.<lb/>  Grant O Shield of our lives existence that they who thus celebrate thy<lb/> miracles&#44; may be satisfied with the blessings which thy hand alone<lb/> can bestow&#59; with life&#44; with wealth&#44; and with happiness&#44; for&#44;<lb/> fulness of joy is in thy presence&#44; and precious delights are at thy<lb/> right hand&#44; forevermore.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
