<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF1_8</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_8_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_8_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_8_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_8_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_8_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_8_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_8_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_8_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_8_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_8_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_8_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_8_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>7 pages on 3 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For a Sabbath before Rosh Hashanah<lb/>
                of &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  Three points I am obliged to explain before<lb/> the holy days fast approaching will have arrived.  One is<lb/> not new to my congregation&#59; for&#44; if I remember correctly<lb/> I presented it in former years at the recurrence of this<lb/> same season.  It concerns our dearest interests as a religious body&#44; those of <del>public</del> Divine<lb/> worship.  We destroy the effect which the beautiful<lb/> prayers and chanting of our sacred convocations would<lb/> produce&#44; by the discordance of our voices.  Fatiguing in<lb/> the extreme as the services of the coming solemnities are&#44;<lb/> I would prefer to going through them myself alone rather<lb/> than to hear the noisy and jarring sounds of untrained readers<lb/> of Hebrew.  You see&#58; I speak more plainly than I<lb/> would wish&#44; because I think it an injustice to my<lb/> brothers and sisters in faith who visit this Sanctuary<lb/> to be upraised to God&#59; that instead of <del>obtaining</del> deriving spiritual<lb/> gratification they should receive disagreeable impressions&#59;<lb/> and that simply by reason of some who <del>led</del> persist in<lb/> leading and not being led in the singing. <del>of the ritual</del><lb/>  Must I offend by telling this attendant&#58; &#34;Lower your<lb/> notes&#59; <del>or be silent</del> you cause annoyance&#34;&#63;  By saying to that &#34;You are not<lb/> acquainted with the words and the tunes&#59; listen <del>and be not heard</del> and cease disturbing&#34;&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>I believe<hi rend="sup">2</hi> and hope<hi rend="sup">1</hi> that I shall not find it<lb/> necessary to go to such an extreme.  My few <del>words</del> well&#45;meant utterances<lb/> this morning will serve as a healthful check&#44; and our<lb/> assemblies of Rosh Hashana and Yom Kippur will<lb/> be distinguished for the devotion which the rendering<lb/> of the ritual ought ever to inspire.<lb/></p>
            <p>The second point relates to an experiment tried last year<lb/> and which I do not desire to see repeated.  My judg&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment has always been against using the Synagogue<lb/> as the medium to gain obtain immediately within its walls<lb/> subscriptions and donations for any society.  Invited to<lb/> attend meetings for the purpose of <del>sanctioning the</del> cooperating in a measure&#44;<lb/> adopted by other congregations&#44; I invariably opposed its<lb/> being carried out in our midst.  But twelve months<lb/> ago&#44; the yellow&#45;fever raged through the South.<lb/>  Already the <del>consequent</del> evils consequent upon it were visible in Philadelphia&#44;<lb/> and it was expected that during the winter the <del>demands</del> calls<lb/> upon the United Charities would be so numerous&#44; so<lb/> urgent and distressing&#44; that additional efforts must<lb/> be absolutely made to meet them.  Our lamented<lb/> President yielded to the pressure brought upon him&#44;<lb/> and I&#44; following his direction&#44; made an appeal on the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>eves of the day of atonement.  Neither the amount<lb/> then realized&#44; according to the schedules&#44; serving as a<lb/> promissory notes&#44; nor the general look of the congre&#45;<lb/>&#45;gation altered my conviction that the w plan was<lb/> unsatisfactory.  And now I have a positive assur&#45;<lb/>&#45;ance&#44; that it proved very objectionable to several<lb/> who might be induced to absent themselves from the<lb/> worship&#44; if it should be annually practised.  I<lb/> entertain no doubt that when the temporal officers<lb/> of the congregation will have exercised their personal<lb/> influence&#44; our Jewish Charities will gain rather than<lb/> lose for our having set aside the experiment ineffectually tried<lb/> <del>last year</del> once.<lb/></p>
            <p>The third point is perhaps somewhat startling&#59;<lb/> but unfortunately I can no longer prevent its being<lb/> brought forth.  A custom which I think is very <lb/>general in Portuguese Congregations requires that two<lb/> persons shall stand by the Hazan on Rosh Hashanah<lb/> and Yom Kippur.  The origin of that usage may<lb/> be traced to a sentence in the writings of a very<lb/> ancient commentator.  Alluding to the battle<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>against Amalek at Rehidim&#44; the Rabbi remarks<lb/> that as Moses when raising up his hands heavenward<lb/> had Aaron and Hur beside him&#44; so must the Minister<lb/> have two supporters when he offers prayers.  This<lb/> recommendation has been very partially observed.<lb/>  Our brethren of the Ashkenz ritual conform with it<lb/> only on the eve of Kippur and only to form a Beth&#45;Din while <hi rend="underline">Kal Nidre</hi>&#44; or the<lb/> petition for the absolution of promises forgotten and<lb/> unperformed is being <del>made</del> recited.  The Sephardim act up<lb/> to it merely on the days I have mentioned.  And<lb/> in Europe they habitually appoint to that office in&#45;<lb/>individuals invested with religious authority&#44; or laymen<lb/> noted for their piety.  Now&#44; my feelings and<lb/> early associations would urge me to continue the custom&#44;<lb/> but my knowledge of altered circumstances forces me<lb/> to abandon it&#44; with a single exception.  I will be<lb/> explicit.  During the first two decades of my<lb/> ministration&#44; persons adhering to Jewish rules&#44; and<lb/> <del>who considering it regarding</del> esteeming it an honor to attend the Reader&#44; could<lb/> easily be chosen.  But within late years some among<lb/> those I would prefer&#44; have directly or indirectly requested<lb/> that owing to advanced age or infirmities&#44; or the<lb/> </p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>distance they have to walk to return home&#44; I<lb/> would spare them the fatigue of standing.  And<lb/> <del>inasmuch</del> as many I considered eligible to the holy position have died or<lb/> removed to other cities&#44; the selection would have necessarily<lb/> to fall upon very few.  These might deem it a burthen<lb/> rather than a gratification to be repeatedly called upon<lb/> to remain <del>long</del> for hours at this sacred desk.  Hence <del>my</del> the unpleasant resolve I have taken.<lb/>  But I may be met with a constitutional objection.<lb/>  I may be told that among the honors which the statute<lb/> book of our congregation confers upon two individuals<lb/> during the ensuing Hebrew month&#44; that of accompanying the<lb/> Hazan in the <hi rend="underline">Musaph</hi> of the first day of Rosh Ha&#45;<lb/>&#45;shanah is specially provided for.  But need I re&#45;<lb/>&#45;mind my Brethren of the humiliating fact that&#44; like<lb/> other by laws&#44; that provision has for years remained a dead<lb/> letter&#44; because no two persons will act the whole term<lb/> <del>in the capacity of</del> as Hatan Torah and Hatan Beresheet&#63;  Nay&#44;<lb/> it is known to all&#44; that even on the concluding day of <del>our</del> the<lb/> festivals of Tishri&#44; the presiding officer has been <del>put to</del> at<lb/> his wits end to find men willing to serve in that capacity&#44; though not<lb/> expected to make rich offerings.  It may be painful to<lb/> those of my hearers&#44; who have experienced a different state of<lb/> affairs&#44; to notice the changes which time has wrought but they do exist&#44; and it is<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>useless to close our eyes against them.  Happily&#44; the<lb/> matter under discussion is of minor importance.<lb/>  And where I <del>consider</del> look at the agitation <del>of</del> in clerical circles<lb/> which threatens to overthrow the entire fabric of histo&#45;<lb/>&#45;rical Judaism&#44; I congratulate myself <del>on</del> notwithstanding shortcomings&#44; or our present condition.  I rejoice over our escape from<lb/> the rude &#91;&#63;&#93; of a coercive liberalism.  The government<lb/> of our Synagogue has not suffered in its dignity un&#45;<lb/>der ancient rules&#44; and I <del>feel</del> believe that a willing attendance to the hints<lb/> <del>hints suggestions</del> I have thrown out this morning will enhance its<lb/> reputation still more.  But I would not that my suggestions<lb/> be interpreted as an encroachment upon the rights of<lb/> two officials in the congregation.  A time&#45;honored <del>custom</del> usage<lb/> among us has made it requisite that the President and<lb/> Treasurer shall stand by the Minister at the <del>concluding</del> closing service<lb/> of the day of atonement.  That I desire <del>may be construed</del> ever to retain<lb/> I could not part wit hit&#44; and not feel that I tear my&#45;<lb/>&#45;self from a long and cherished past.  Let the Parnass and<lb/> Gabba&#239;&#44; still add by their presence at this desk to the im&#45;<lb/>&#45;posingness of the soul&#45;stirring Negnilah.  And may they&#44;<lb/> <del>Almighty&#45;grant that before the hour</del> deserving the honor&#44; always esteem it such.  Oh may the God of Israel grant that next year and <del>every after</del> for many successive years before that solemn hour arrives&#44; we all<lb/> may be inscribed in the book of life and domestic happiness.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
