<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF4_8</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_8_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_8_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_8_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_8_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_8_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_8_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_8_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_8_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_8_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_8_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_8_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_8_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For the Sabbath before Passover<lb/>
                on education &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Rejoice and be exceedingly glad&#44; ye who believe in<lb/> the word of God&#44; for as He ordained&#44; so has even come<lb/> to pass &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Thou shalt<lb/> keep this statute at its season&#44; from year to year&#34;.<lb/>  Aye&#44; we will ever proclaim that season holy&#44; wherein<lb/> the stretched&#45;out arm of the Omnipotent took a nation<lb/> from amidst another nation by memorable deeds.<lb/>  We will call that day blessed&#44; whereon the Creator<lb/> announced to the world&#44; that He would be our protecting<lb/> God&#44; and we His people and the flock of His pasture.<lb/>  Thrice blessed that day which saw our fathers advance&#44;<lb/> under the banner of freedom&#44; towards that mountain<lb/> whence a life eternal was to be granted unto man.<lb/>  Long centuries have rolled away since that matchless<lb/> day dawned upon redeemed Israel&#44; but the hand of<lb/> time has not obliterated its memory.  As in the<lb/> days of yore&#44; the statute is kept at its season from<lb/> year to year.  Wheresoever be our sojourn&#44; whether<lb/> breathing the exhilarating air of liberty&#44; or enduring<lb/> ruthless persecution.  In whatever condition of life we be<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>whether in affluence or in want&#44; the fifteenth<lb/> day of Nissan is hailed with devotional delight.<lb/>  Alike in the palatial mansion and in the humble<lb/> dwelling&#44; the cup of salvation is raised brimful to<lb/> sing praises to the God of truth&#44; who has performed<lb/> His covenant with Abraham&#44; and shown mercy to<lb/> a thousand generations.  So also we&#44; my beloved<lb/> hearers&#33; we&#44; a clustering branch of that vine&#44; which<lb/> God brought out of Egypt and transplanted in this genial soil&#44; we believing Hebrews will uplift our voice<lb/> around the family board hearth with hymns and psalmody.<lb/>  We will again assemble in this house dedicated to<lb/> our living Saviour&#44; and celebrate together the festival<lb/> He has appointed as an everlasting ordinance.<lb/>  But need I say to you that those acts&#44; however<lb/> meritorious&#44; do not constitute the main duties con&#45;<lb/>&#45;nected with and flowing from the institution of the<lb/> Passover&#63;...Behold&#33; the heavenly volumes<lb/> are open to all for our instruction.  From thence you<lb/> must draw divine knowledge.<lb/></p>
            <p>But as I examined the passage&#44; from which I quoted<lb/> a sentence&#44; my attention was directed to the circumstance&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>that two commands of a different character follow<lb/> each other immediately.  One is negative &#91;Hebrew&#93; and to<lb/> our praise be it said&#44; scrupulously observed in Israel&#44;<lb/> the other is positive &#91;Hebrew&#93; but I have reason to believe &#91;inserted above&#58; few&#93;&#44; not so<lb/> rigidly fulfilled.  In compliance with the first&#44; we<lb/> cleanse our habitations from all leaven&#44; and provide<lb/> ourselves with the bread emblematic of our deliverance<lb/> from bondage&#59; un in obedience to the second&#44; we<lb/> should tell our children the origin and object of our<lb/> precepts&#44; keep them fresh into their minds by tangible<lb/> signs&#44; and bear them constantly on our lips&#44; that<lb/> our offspring may&#44; as it were&#44; inhale from our breath<lb/> piety and virtue &#91;Hebrew&#93;.<lb/>
                Now&#44; that we bestow exceeding care upon the preservation of our children&#39;s<lb/> bodily health&#44; no one will deny&#44; for Hebrew men<lb/> are proverbially attached to their domestic fire&#45;side&#44;<lb/> and the comfort of home and its inmates is their<lb/> constant solicitude.  That to render our children accom&#45;<lb/>&#45;plished we spare no effort&#44; that to open for them the<lb/> avenues to opulence&#44; we labor unremittingly&#44; admits of no question<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>but that we experience the same anxiety touching<lb/> their spiritual health that we strive with all might<lb/> that they may grow learned in the obligations to<lb/> God&#44; and rich in virtues&#44; cannot as well be asserted.<lb/>  The chilling apathy of our youths regarding religion&#44;<lb/> and the rampant changes introduced in it to gra&#45;<lb/>&#45;tify the senses&#44; are to my judgment&#44; the legitimate<lb/> offspring of parental heedlessness.  I will prove it.<lb/>  Some will exact from their children&#44; while under their<lb/> control&#44; the exercise of numerous religious practices&#44; yet<lb/> they will utterly fail to invest the same with a halo<lb/> of sanctity&#44; for they will neglect the point most essential.<lb/>  They will not disclose their purport&#44; the noble object<lb/> they are intended to subserve.  They will not&#44; as<lb/> our heavenly Legislator has recommended&#44; explain at<lb/> large that the behests of our God aim at securing our<lb/> happiness here and hereafter&#44; for it is written &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;The<lb/> Lord hath commanded us to do all these statutes&#44; for<lb/> our own good always&#44; to keep us alive as at this day.<lb/>  And it will moreover be counted to our righteousness before<lb/> the Lord our God&#44; when we observe to do all this commandment.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Rather than win them to religion by describing the<lb/> loveliness of a godly existence&#44; by pointing out the<lb/> actions that most ennoble human nature&#44; by speaking<lb/> of the satisfaction we derive from the <sic>fulfilment</sic> of<lb/> our duties&#44; though unrequited and misapprehended by<lb/> man&#44; they will insist upon the execution of ceremonial<lb/> ordinances&#44; only as &#91;Hebrew&#93; as &#34;an habitual task&#34;.<lb/>  Others again imagine that to procure their children&#45;&#45;<lb/>during a certain period at least&#45;&#45;a religious instructor&#44; is<lb/> all that can be required of them at their hands&#59; for upon<lb/> the man of their choice they have will cast their <sic>burthen</sic> of<lb/> their obligations.  He must shape the hearts of their young<lb/> offspring.  He must leach them to distinguish between the<lb/> holy and the unholy&#44; He must fit them to solve all<lb/> queries when <sic>catechised</sic> about the ancestral religion.<lb/>  The parents need not devote a time which may <sic>yeild</sic><lb/> them great many advantages in their various callings&#44; to impart<lb/> religious knowledge.  Grievous errors are these&#44;<lb/> my friends&#33; pregnant with laf baleful results.<lb/>  I do not&#44; by any means&#44; hold it as necessary or judicious<lb/> to discuss with our children the nature of every command<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>we desire to enforce&#44; nor do I deprecate the system<lb/> of employing a tutor to aid us in training our children&#44;<lb/> provided we know that his moral standing and<lb/> piety&#44; keep pace with his learning&#59; but I contend<lb/> that upon the parents most especially has the Almighty<lb/> imposed the duty of giving exercising their best abilities to give the mind and heart of<lb/> their offspring a right tendency &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Thou shalt teach them diligently to thy children&#44; and<lb/> speak of them&#44;&#34; exclaims Holy Writ&#59; and our Rabbins<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;It is the bounden duty of every man<lb/> to teach his son religion&#34;.  Those whom we have<lb/> voluntarily given existence&#44; we must show&#44; under our own<lb/> guidance&#44; the way of salvation.  This is a law stamped<lb/> by nature upon our breast&#44; and to which nature&#39;s God<lb/> demands our implicit obedience.  None dares with<lb/> impunity refuse it&#44; or transfer it unto others.<lb/></p>
            <p>The Great Master who fashioned our being&#44; has designedly<lb/> infused into our tender offspring a feeling which prompts<lb/> them to regard their parents&#44; as the best interpreters of the<lb/> word of God&#44; as the wisest and most virtuous among<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>all mortal creatures.  It behooves us therefore to improve<lb/> that great divine boon&#44; by inculcating such lessons<lb/> as calculated to inspire love for God&#44; and reverence for<lb/> His revealed word.  It is not sufficient that we<lb/> say to our children&#44; this is right and that is wrong&#44;<lb/> we must cast around their path a flood of religious<lb/> light.  We must by precept and example endear to<lb/> them the faith in which they were born&#44; and the people<lb/> with whom they have community of history and hopes.<lb/>  Vain will indeed be the imparting of their preceptors&#44;<lb/> if not preceded&#44; accompanied&#44; and followed by our own<lb/> tuition.  Besides&#44; we are not always able or willing<lb/> to ascertain what principles govern the life of<lb/> him who is to influence hereafter the character<lb/> of our progeny&#44; that we may fully entrust them<lb/> to his charge.  It is a remark&#44; my friends&#33; often times<lb/> repeated&#44; that the children of apparently pious parents&#44;<lb/> are in general among the foremost to disregard religion.<lb/>  But if the early history of such could&#44; in all cases&#44; be<lb/> unfolded&#44; it would reveal&#44; in the majority of<lb/> instance&#44; the working of one of the two radical errors<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>I have described above.  Either was parental<lb/> instruction devoid of spirituality&#44; or it was entirely<lb/> committed to unqualified and incompetent teachers.<lb/>  But when religious imparting is so given that it<lb/> illumines the intellect&#44; and appeals to our finer<lb/> feelings&#44; it will&#44; it must fructify and produce<lb/> an exuberant harvest of goodness and righteousness.<lb/>  Were it not even so&#44; the education of the heart so<lb/> emphatically recommended in the volumes of inspiration&#44;<lb/> would be an unmeaning word&#44; a shadow without<lb/> reality&#44; a phantom without substance.  Forbid<lb/> it God&#33;...That wickedness will grow where righteous&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness had been sown&#44; is not never to be ascribed to<lb/> the inefficacy of home&#45;culture&#59; but to the mildew<lb/> which a corrupt association will raise on our<lb/> tender plants.  Against it&#44; must we industriously<lb/> guard&#59; we must never abandon our offspring<lb/> to themselves&#44; until we are confident that the<lb/> light they have received&#44; enables them to proceed<lb/> alone.  We should remember that &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;He that goeth with wise men&#44; will grow wise&#59;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>but he who goeth in company with the reckless will<lb/> do ev be destroyed.&#34;  To avert this fatal issue&#44; our<lb/> Almighty Deliverer has conjointly established the<lb/> Passover and the duty of parental education.<lb/>  It does not become the free&#45;man to grope in<lb/> darkness.  He must know his obligations&#44; and follow<lb/> them with moral courage.  Freedom and duty<lb/> are <sic>inseperably</sic> connected.  Such is our motto&#59; and<lb/> upon this broad principle stands the memorable<lb/> me festival now fast approaching.  Let us solemnize it<lb/> in accordance with its spirit&#59; O my beloved hearers&#33;<lb/>  Let us by precept and example draw our children nearer<lb/> to their protecting God&#44; who is the fountain of human<lb/> salvation.  We know not how long we shall be<lb/> permitted to labor in His holy cause&#44; let us then not<lb/> tarry be slothful&#44; and if we have sinned of neglect permitted ourselves to suffered ourselves to be found slumbering over our task&#44; let us re&#45;<lb/>&#45;double our efforts&#44; and never grow weary in teaching<lb/> our children what they owe to their Creator&#44; to them&#45;<lb/>&#45;selves and to their fellow&#45;mortals&#59; then will we<lb/> have performed what is demanded of us&#44; and have rightly kept<lb/> this statute at its season from year to year&#44; as it written<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
