<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF10_3</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_3_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_3_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_3_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_3_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_3_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_3_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_3_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_3_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_3_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_3_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_3_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_3_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_3_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_3_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_3_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_3_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>14 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>131</p>
            
            <p>Is the sacrificial rite or prayer<lb/></p>
            <p>the most acceptable service&#63;<lb/>&#63;&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  A question which may have often arisen in<lb/> your minds&#44; and which the section of this Sabbath suggests&#44;<lb/> was lately put to me for solution.  I will set it forth&#44;<lb/> and discuss it before you&#44; in as simple and brief a manner<lb/> as the subject will allow.<lb/></p>
            <p>&#34;Do the Israelites believe that when restored to their land&#44; the<lb/> sacrificial service will be reinstated&#44; or that it will be super&#45;<lb/>&#45;seded by prayer&#63;&#34;  To the first part of this query&#44; I<lb/> replied&#44; unhesitatingly&#44; in the affirmative&#44; and for the following<lb/> reason&#58; Firstly&#59; because in several instances when the prophets<lb/> foretell a gathering of our people from their dispersion&#44; allu&#45;<lb/>&#45;sions are made to the offerings that shall again be laid<lb/> upon the altar.  Secondly&#59; because our ritual&#44; composed by men<lb/> thoroughly acquainted with our traditions&#44; teem with entreaties<lb/> for a return of the time&#44; in which we may present to the Lord<lb/> the choice of our flock and herd.  Thus&#44; by way of illustra&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion&#44; Isaiah in the 56th chapter of the book bearing his name&#44;<lb/> declares that at the restoration from our captivity even<lb/> the oblations of the strangers&#44; who serve God faithfully&#44;<lb/> will be accepted with favor.  &#34;&#91;Hebrew&#93;  I will bring them unto my<lb/> holy mountain&#44; and make them joyful in my house of prayer&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>their burnt&#45;offerings and their sacrifices shall be accepted<lb/> on my altar and immediately follows&#58; So saith the Lord God&#44; that gathereth the<lb/> outcasts of Israel&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  And in our daily prayers<lb/> we so petition the Lord &#34;Restore the service to the oracle of thy<lb/> house&#44; and receive speedily with loving&#45;kindness the burnt&#45;offerings<lb/> and orisons of Israel &#91;Hebrew&#93; But notwithstanding all this&#44; I<lb/> was bold enough to assert that the sacrificial service<lb/> may be modified or totally abolished in the Messianic era.<lb/>  Men dare not alter what God has established&#44; but the<lb/> heavenly Legislator can&#44; if He so wills&#44; change the laws He<lb/> enacted.  The command not to add or diminish therefrom&#44;<lb/> is evidently intended as a restraint upon our inclinations<lb/> to make the Mosaic ordinances subserve <sic>wordly</sic> purposes.<lb/>  For example&#44; to permit ourselves&#44; when among gentiles&#44; the<lb/> adoration of being besides the Creator&#44; or to lay in abeyance<lb/> the observance of the Sabbath&#44; but it cannot be construed<lb/> into the absolute perpetuity of every precept of the<lb/> Torah.  These veins as held by Albo in his book of<lb/> creeds&#44; I deem admissible and perfectly orthodox.<lb/>  The Almighty who thought it necessary to instruct us by<lb/> means of revelation&#44; can&#44; in the same manner&#44; as publicly<lb/> and as effectually communicate to us the alterations He<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>may desire that the external form of Jewish worship<lb/> undergo.  Might He not indeed consider that the<lb/> object to be attained by the sacrificial rite&#44; could be<lb/> reached through some other agency&#63;  For nearly twenty<lb/> centuries Judaism has existed without priesthood&#44; without<lb/> altar&#44; and without the blood of atonement&#59; hence the<lb/> Temple service cannot be essential to the preservation of<lb/> our religion.  Nay&#44; its having been confined within narrow<lb/> limits goes far to prove that its absence is not detrimen&#45;<lb/>&#45;tal to the principles of which we were made the depo&#45;<lb/>&#45;sitaries.  For&#44; whereas the dietary laws and many<lb/> other prescriptions are not depending for their observance<lb/> on any locality&#59; concerning about the sacrifices we read in Deuteronomy&#44;<lb/> &#34;only in the place that the Lord shall choose&#44; out of one of<lb/> thy tribes&#44; there shalt thou make thy burnt&#45;offerings&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>  In fact&#44; Maimonides&#44; who in his ritual work writes&#44; at the<lb/> end of treatise &#34;Kings&#44;&#34; that in the days of the Messiah all<lb/> the institutions of the Pentateuch will be reestablished&#44; and<lb/> among others that of the sacrifices&#44; does not scruple to lay<lb/> it down as his opinion&#44; in the third discourse of his philosophical<lb/> book&#44; that the injunction to slaughter animals as a sign<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>of admiration to the Deity&#44; was a mere concession to the time&#59;<lb/> that the universality of that custom induced the divine heavenly Legis&#45;<lb/>&#45;lator to retain it in His code&#44; under such restrictions&#44; as<lb/> would prevent Israelites from copying their heathen neighbors.<lb/>  Thus we see that celebrated author representing in one<lb/> case our people&#39;s tradition&#59; and endeavouring in the other<lb/> to show that the sacrificial service had nothing in itself<lb/> to recommend it&#59; but that it owes its origin to extraneous<lb/> causes.  As a theologian&#44; he could but say that the im&#45;<lb/>&#45;molation of victims upon the altar would be resumed&#44; for&#44;<lb/> so prophecy and the oral law seem to teach&#59; as a deep<lb/> thinker&#44; he imagined ot have discovered that that usage&#44;<lb/> though hallowed by the Divinity&#44; was only borrowed.<lb/></p>
            <p>This opinion&#44; however&#44; has been disputed&#59; and on strong grounds.<lb/>  Its opponents contend&#44; that the wish to return&#44; as it were&#44;<lb/> a portion of our substance unto God&#44; as a token of gratitude&#44;<lb/> is inborn in man&#45;&#45;for Abel could not have been in&#45;<lb/>&#45;fluenced by idolatrous practices to offer the firstlings of<lb/> his flock and the fat thereof&#45;&#45;but as riches among<lb/> the ancients&#44; consisted principally in the possession of<lb/> cattle and in the produce of the ground&#44; it was natural<lb/> that their gifts should be choice fruits&#44; and unblemished animals.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>That practice God deigned to sanction and even to encourage&#44;<lb/> because it served a righteous purpose&#44; because it bound<lb/> the creature to his Creator&#59; and as a mere feeling of compunc&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion appeared to man insufficient to blot out sin&#44; our ancestors<lb/> were ordered to let the blood of animals&#44; poured on the<lb/> altar&#44; typify their willingness to spill their own blood&#44;<lb/> if it were demanded as an expiration.  But with that<lb/> practice another&#44; equally inherent in man&#44; and more<lb/> acceptable to the Lord was found.  It was the offering<lb/> of the heart&#58; prayer.  It co&#45;existed with the sacrificial<lb/> rite.  It did and will survive it under whatever circum&#45;<lb/>&#45;stances Israel be placed.  No one can positively assert<lb/> that stated prayers were recited during the first stages<lb/> of our national history.  But what we can gather<lb/> from Holy Writ leads us to believe that entreaties to the<lb/> Lord were made as they occasion would call for.<lb/></p>
            <p>Moses invoked a blessing upon Israel on the day that the<lb/> Tabernac work of for the Tabernacle was completed&#44; and when<lb/> Aaron was first invested with authority to minister therein.<lb/>  The latter pronounced a benediction with uplifted hands<lb/> after he had been inducted into his sacred office.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Our progenitors often when they suffered in the wilderness by reason of their<lb/> trespasses&#45;&#45;knowing the efficacy of prayer&#45;&#45;asked their<lb/> inspired leader to implore the mercy of god for their sake.<lb/>  And we read in Deuteronomy that the Israelite who confesses to have given all the tithes<lb/> prescribed by the law&#44; added to his acknowledgment the<lb/> following supplication.  &#34;Oh&#33;  Look down from Thy holy habitation&#44;<lb/> from heaven&#44; and bless Thy people Israel&#44; and the land which<lb/> thou hast given us.&#34;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  It would<lb/> be superfluous that I should cite biblical passages&#44; in order<lb/> to prove that as we come down to later times the<lb/> exercise of prayer is exhibited with still more frequency.<lb/>  Hannah is said to have been praying long&#44; while Eli obser&#45;<lb/>&#45;ved the motions of her lips.  Samuel gathered the<lb/> people of Israel at Mizpah to hold a solemn<lb/> convocation with fasting and prayer.  Shall<lb/> I mention David whose petitions to God are numerous and<lb/> soul&#45;stirring&#44; and who established a daily service with<lb/> hymns and psalmody both for the moveable sanctuary<lb/> and for that he contemplated building at Jerusalem&#63;<lb/>  But a striking evidence of the regard in which prayer was<lb/> held by the Hebrews&#59; nay&#44; of the superiority assigned thereto<lb/> over the rite of sacrifice&#44; is to me the petition of King<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Solomon at the dedication of the Temple.<lb/></p>
            <p>That sublime testimony of religious fervor&#45;&#45;so comprehensive<lb/> but withal so lengthy&#45;&#45;does not contain a single allusion<lb/> to animal sacrifices&#44; but only&#44; and in almost every line&#44;<lb/> to man&#39;s spiritual offering&#59; even to prayer.<lb/></p>
            <p>God is ardently invoked and His hearing is implored to<lb/> all human supplications&#59; whether they be for the remission<lb/> of sin&#44; or the bestowal of grace&#44; in seasons of peace&#44; or<lb/> in time of war&#59; whether they be prompted by the want<lb/> of rain&#59; by national calamities&#44; or by private sufferings&#59;<lb/> whether they be powered forth at the devoted shrine<lb/> in the promised land&#44; or in exile&#59; whether they be<lb/> the utterance of a son of the covenant&#44; or of a stranger<lb/> to the Hebrew family.  Notwithstanding<lb/> that the occasion which elicited that entreaty&#44; saw<lb/> numberless victims immolated upon the altar&#44; the sup&#45;<lb/>&#45;pliant Monarch asked to obtain a Divine blessing&#44; not<lb/> through them&#44; but through the out pouring of a soul&#44; that<lb/> yearnsng after the great and beneficent God.  Now&#44;<lb/> Having adduced this&#45;&#45;to me conclusive proof&#45;&#45;of<lb/> the powerful hold which prayer had taken on the mind<lb/> of our ancestors&#44; and of the high position it occupied.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>I shall forego an inclination to quote other passages&#44;<lb/> in order to substantiate the same idea.  I will<lb/> rather request that you follow me in a hasty review<lb/> of the Jewish worship after the return from the<lb/> Babylonish captivity.  When the corner stone<lb/> of the second Temple was laid&#44; Levites accompanied<lb/> by instrumental music&#44; sang to the Lord&#44; in the lan&#45;<lb/>&#45;guage of King David&#44; and all the people transported<lb/> with joy at the happy occurrence&#44; unanimously joined<lb/> in the divine praise.  Later&#44; at the consecration of<lb/> the capital of Judea&#44; Levites were urged to come thither&#44;<lb/> to celebrated the occasion with hymns and psalmody&#44;<lb/> and two companies thereof were stationed in the house of<lb/> God for that special purpose.  From that time&#44; writes<lb/> the inspired historian&#44; men were appointed to officiate<lb/> as choristers&#44; for&#44; &#34;since the days of David and Asaph<lb/>&#45;&#45;the chiefs of singers&#45;&#45;songs of praise and thanks&#45;<lb/>&#45;givings were given to God&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Thus far&#44; my dear Brethren&#33;  I have<lb/> endeavoured to draw from the Bible itself corroborative<lb/> proofs to my assertion.  I have shown that<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>even without our accepting tradition&#44; which makes public<lb/> thanksgivings &#38; supplications an institution coexistent with the sacrificial<lb/> service&#44; we may readily admit that prayers were offered<lb/> by our ancient fathers&#44; and their efficacy was greatly relied upon.<lb/>  But what light can guide us in our researches&#44; after<lb/> the closing of the sacred canon&#44; if we do not follow<lb/> the Mishn&#225;h and Gem&#225;ra&#63;  It is those books<lb/> that have treasured up all that comes within the range<lb/> of Jewish history and literature&#44; and then we must<lb/> consult when we seek information.  Well&#44; from their<lb/> pages we learn that besides the customary j hymns<lb/> sang daily by the Levites&#44; whilst the libations were made&#44;<lb/> <sic>&#44;</sic> some prayers identical with those we now recite&#44; were<lb/> read by the priests early every morning.  We are<lb/> likewise told that whosoever presented a sin offering&#44;<lb/> pronounced a confession&#44; while laying his hand on the<lb/> head of the animal&#44; and that each sacrifice called forth<lb/> some expression of grateful acknowledgment or <sic>intreaty</sic>.<lb/></p>
            <p>But what specially demonstrates the value<lb/> in which prayer was held&#44; is a regulation&#44; which tradition<lb/> dates from a very remote period&#44; but which&#44; beyond all<lb/> doubt&#44; existed during the second sanctuary.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>I have reference to the Ma&#228;madot.  A few words<lb/> will explain its object.  The impossibility of detaining<lb/> the people of Israel constantly at the Temple&#44; to<lb/> witness the worship&#44; induced our Sages to establish<lb/> that certain individuals of noted for their piety&#44; should<lb/> be selected out of every section of the country&#44; as repre&#45;<lb/>&#45;sentatives of the whole nation.  Those among them<lb/> who dwelt at Jerusalem&#44; or in a neighboring city&#44; should<lb/> personally attend the service&#59; others who resided at a<lb/> distance should meet in their respective Synagogues&#44;<lb/> and by fasting and prayer draw the blessing of God<lb/> over their brethren.  Here we clearly perceive&#44;<lb/> that the offering of piety &#91;&#63;&#93; stood&#44; to say the least&#44;<lb/> parallell with the offering of the choicest steers.<lb/>  But the Rabbis go further and declare&#44; that the existence<lb/> of the world depended mainly upon those assemblies<lb/> of the godly &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; for when all would might fail<lb/> to propitiate the grace of the Almighty&#44; sincere<lb/> prayers will appease His wrath.  &#34;The gates<lb/> of prayer&#44;&#34; write some of those teachers of Israel&#44; &#34;are<lb/> never closed&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  What means<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>Holy Writ&#44; when it bids us serve God&#44; they ask<lb/> each other&#44; and the answer is&#59; &#34;it recommends prayer.&#34;<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  And in drawing a comparison between<lb/> the two kinds of worship&#45;&#45;the immolation of victims<lb/> and supplications&#45;&#45;&#44; they ascribe to the latter &#91;&#63;&#93; a decided superiority.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  In like manner commenting upon the<lb/> sentence passage of Isaiah&#44; which I quoted above&#44; they discover the<lb/> unsurpassed value of prayer&#44; in the fact that the prophet<lb/> ends it his sentence thus &#34;My house shall be a house of prayer for all<lb/> people.&#34;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  But I promised at<lb/> the outset to be brief&#44; and I will not trespass any longer.<lb/>  If I have succeeded to prove that prayer has always<lb/> claimed and received in Israel a high position&#59; that<lb/> it was always regarded as a link between the creature<lb/> and his Creator&#44; that time further <sic>developped</sic> and inten&#45;<lb/>&#45;sified those feelings&#59; that prayer coexisted with the<lb/> sacrifices&#44; and as they ceased&#44; it became more generalized<lb/> and heightened in value through the maxims of our<lb/> Sages&#44; I have reached the goal I desired to attain.<lb/>  For&#44; what we have so long been taught to believe the<lb/> most acceptable offering to the Lord&#44; you will own that<lb/> it cannot be displaced by another object.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p>The slaughtering of animals upon the altar may be<lb/> reinstated&#44; if God so wills&#59; but prayer must rank<lb/> foremost in the worship&#44; prayer must to the end<lb/> of time continue to be our refuge&#44; our comfort<lb/> and delight.  It may be that in the Messianic era<lb/> our obedience to both institutions will be required&#44;<lb/> therefore do we in our ignorance of God&#39;s purposes&#44; beseech<lb/> Him to hasten the time&#44; in which we may be enabled<lb/> to perform those commands of His law&#44; now suspended<lb/> because of our dispersion.  Heedful of prophetic teaching<lb/> and tradition&#44; we exclaim &#34;O Lord our God&#33; bring us back to Zion thy city<lb/> with joy&#44; and there will we in thy presence&#44; make the<lb/> offerings obligatory upon us &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  And<lb/> on the day of atonement&#44; to which special allusion is<lb/> made in the lesson of this Sabbath&#44; we repeatedly express<lb/> the same wish&#59; yet I most humbly &#38; reverently&#44; say that the sacrificial<lb/> rite may be abolished by Divine direction&#44; but prayer will<lb/> eternally remain the service in which the Almighty takes<lb/> pleasure.  When we shall have washed our hands in innocence&#44; we<lb/> shall again be permitted to surround the altar to be reared<lb/> in Judah&#39;s land&#59; but the outpouring of our hearts<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="14"/>
            <p>will best evince our thankfulness to the Great<lb/> Redeemer&#59; the thrilling sound of our united orisons<lb/> shall manifest the love of Israel for their living<lb/> Saviour&#59; joyous songs and ardent praise&#44; will<lb/> call down from heaven the fire&#44; symbol of God&#39;s<lb/> acceptance and blessing.  May this be speedily<lb/> verified.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
