<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF3_19</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_19_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_19_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_19_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_19_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_19_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_19_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_19_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_19_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_19_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_19_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_19_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_19_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_19_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_19_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_19_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_19_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Post Biblical Lecture<lb/>
                19<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  Israelites of the present age&#44; and in particular<lb/> those in particular of North America&#44; will scarcely appreciate the cause which hasten&#45;<lb/>&#45;ned the capture of the Temple by the army of Pompey.<lb/>  Our ancestors progenitors would not engage in manual labor upon the<lb/> Sabbath of the decalogue.  During the war of independence&#44; Mattathias and<lb/> his wise&#45;hearted associates had exercised their authority also on matters<lb/> of conscience with a to a good purpose.  They had induced their coreligionists<lb/> to set aside&#44; for the time being&#44; the holiness of the seventh day&#44;<lb/> when the law of self&#45;preservation imperatively demanded it.<lb/>  That measure was sensible and in perfect harmony with the<lb/> leading principles of the Pharisees&#44; thus expressed in the Talmud&#58;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Nothing must stand in the way of<lb/> <sic>sheilding</sic> one&#39;s own person from immediate danger.&#34;  But in after<lb/> years a distinction appears to have been made between bearing<lb/> arms and fighting on the defensive&#44; and raising fortifications&#44; or<lb/> throwing down embankments upon the Sabbath.  Specially<lb/> the Sadducees&#44; who&#44; like the Caraites of later ages&#44; closely ad&#45;<lb/>&#45;hered to the letter of the Hebrew Scriptures&#44; considered such<lb/> undertakings on that day unwarrantable in any event.<lb/>  The <sic>seige</sic> which the Roman general had laid against the Sanctuary<lb/> was proceeding slowly&#44; for the be<sic>seiged</sic> kept the enemy at bay.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Our ancestors were quick in sending off their arrows<lb/> with a deadly aim&#44; and in demolishing engines of destruction.<lb/>  Finally&#44; a curious circumstance was brought to the notice of the<lb/> foreign enemy.  Every seventh day&#44; the Jews would look on<lb/> inactively&#44; see and only fire back when attacked.  Had<lb/> the perfidious Antipater directed attention to that&#63;  The sur&#45;<lb/>&#45;mise is not at all ill&#45;founded.  But Pompey however was but too glad<lb/> to avail himself of the information.  He ordered that not a<lb/> bow&#45;shot be discharged on that day&#59; the time should be em&#45;<lb/>&#45;ployed in filling up the ditches&#44; in undermining the<lb/> towers&#59; in drawing the battering&#45;rams near the walls.<lb/>  At the expiration of three months a terrible gap breach was<lb/> made on the north eastern side of the Temple.  That ill&#45;<lb/>fated space opening gap invited the heathens to rush on to the<lb/> slaughter.  A massacre followed in which twelve thou&#45;<lb/>&#45;sand of our people perished.  But not all of them were<lb/> pierced through by the Roman javelin.  Some having dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;puted in vain every inch of ground&#44; in vain&#44; fell by the sword in they grasped with<lb/> their own hands&#59; others cast themselves headlong over the<lb/> embankments ramparts&#44; rather than be cut down by the heathens pagans.<lb/>  A majestically <sic>appaling</sic> sight met the Romans.  The<lb/> priests had heard the crash which foretold their sure death.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>They had heard the approach footsteps of their slayers&#44; but did<lb/> not stir.  It was the great day of atonement&#44; some<lb/> historians have said.  The servants of Israel&#39;s God continued<lb/> in the performance of their Sacerdotal functions&#44; till their<lb/> blood crimsoned the floor of the hallowed edifice.  Even a<lb/> the soldier&#44; inured to hardened in cruelty&#44; was struck with awe admi&#45;<lb/>&#45;ration at such intrepidity.  IT was natural for arbiters who have narrated dwelt on Ro&#45;<lb/>&#45;man exploits&#44; naturally to have deemed that which a sense of deep<lb/> piety and resignation dictated&#44; the mere effect of superstition&#44; but<lb/> they themselves could not nevertheless withhold a meed of praise.<lb/></p>
            <p>Josephus refers to Greek and Latin authors in support of<lb/> his assertion narrative of that sublime episode.  But Pompey having set foot on the<lb/> spot so renowned through the known world&#44; would see<lb/> all which it contained.  He even presumed to fling aside<lb/> the veil which hid the holy of holies&#44; and crossed<lb/> its sh threshhold.  Great was the astonishment in<lb/> discovering there nothing but an empty space.  No<lb/> earthly&#44; no heavenly representation arrested his attention.<lb/>  That&#44; was incomprehensible to a polytheistic race.  A<lb/> service tendered to an invisible spirit could not be under&#45;<lb/>&#45;stood by men&#44; whose folly had peopled the sky with mutually<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>loving and mutually hating gods and goddesses&#44; and<lb/> whose fancy <sic>chiselled</sic> them in marble&#44; and moulded<lb/> them in bronze&#44; or drew <sic>pencilled</sic> them upon canvas.<lb/></p>  
            <p>A distinguished Jewish French author remarks that<lb/> this very absence of images may have given rise to<lb/> the charge of Atheism brought against us by the an&#45;<lb/>&#45;cients.  As the adoration of false divination is a vi&#45;<lb/>&#45;sible shape&#44; was then universally paid and deeply rooted into the minds&#44; the<lb/> report that Jews would not allow the representation<lb/> of any likeness in their worship&#44; forced the con&#45;<lb/>&#45;clusion that Jews must be the haters of religion&#59;<lb/> confirmed atheists.  Whatever opinion Pompey<lb/> may have formed&#44; he certainly showed a consideration<lb/> which neither his predecessors nor his successors evinced.<lb/>  He restrained his cupidity and that of his army.  He<lb/> did not rob the Temple.  He commanded that it<lb/> be cleansed of the human blood which had flowed within its<lb/> precincts&#44; and the usual rites be resumed.  But<lb/> the foreign chief was by no means so considerate<lb/> throughout.  Many a head which carried itself<lb/> high was he cut off&#59; many a possession which had<lb/> dearly been purchased he seized&#59; many a heavy tax he imposed.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>The Roman general who pretended to have come to<lb/> Judea to Jerusalem as a mediator and to settle a quarrel between two<lb/> contending parties&#44; acted with the merciless policy<lb/> of his government.  He divided to conquer.  Hyr&#45;<lb/>&#45;canus&#44; whose cause he prte pretended to warmly<lb/> advocate&#44; was ridiculously left a crownless king.<lb/>  Judea became a virtual dependency of Rome&#44; under<lb/> the vigilance of its cringing hierling&#45;&#45;Antipater the<lb/> Idumean.  The warlike Aristobulus&#44; with his two<lb/> sons and two daughters were taken prisoners to Rome&#44;<lb/> as a trophy&#44; to grace the triumphal entry of the victor into the<lb/> eternal city.  Queit was restored&#45;&#45;the<lb/> quiet of the grave&#59; for how could peace be enjoyed with<lb/> the loss of all that Maccabean valor had gained&#63;<lb/></p>
            <p>Suddenly the prevailing calm was disturbed.  Alexan&#45;<lb/>&#45;der&#44; the older son of Aristobulus had escaped from the<lb/> hands of his captors.  Round him rallied several thou&#45;<lb/>&#45;sands who had battled under his father.  With them<lb/> the dashing fiery youth made inroads into the country and<lb/> harassed the Hyrcanus&#45;party.  Antipater who had<lb/> done Rome service at various times&#44; asked for assistance<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>to repel Alexander and his dashing &#91;&#63;&#93;<lb/> followers.  Gabrini Scaurus&#44; Antipater&#39;s friend<lb/> had gone back to Italy&#44; but Garinius who had suc&#45;<lb/>&#45;ceeded him as governor of Syria did not delay to<lb/> comply with the request.  He <sic>despatched</sic> an army<lb/> <sic>marshalled</sic> by a captain famous in history&#59; famous<lb/> in among English speaking peoples through the creation of<lb/> their immortal <sic>Shakespear</sic>.  Mark Antony chal&#45;<lb/>&#45;lenged the young Jewish leader to the fight.  The<lb/> impetuous Alexander accepted&#44; but he was overpowered<lb/> and routed and compelled to rela retire into a fortress.<lb/>  There he would have sustained a long <sic>seige</sic>&#44; and finally<lb/> died of starvation&#44; had not his mother&#39;s eloquence<lb/> and personal bearing come to his rescue.  That<lb/> Jewess has been described by historians as one who<lb/> favouring the the idolatrous overbearing Romans.  I prefer to believe that she<lb/> was loyal to her husband&#44; the Asmonean&#59; that only<lb/> to save him and her children from an ignominious death<lb/> she had not shared their captivity dissembled.  Fearing that if Alexander defied the<lb/> Roman power still longer&#44; those dear to her in Rome would<lb/> have been exacted&#44; she presented herself before Gabrinius.<lb/>  Her address made a profound impression.  Alexander<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>was allowed to leave the fortress unmolested&#44;<lb/> disband his troops and live in privacy.  Gabrinius<lb/> then dismantled the principal strongholds&#44; and to<lb/> further dismember Judea divided it into five districts&#44;<lb/> appointing a separate council over each of them.<lb/>  This arrangement&#44; which ignored the claims of Hyrca&#45;<lb/>&#45;nus did not suit the latter&#44; nor did it agree with the am&#45;<lb/>&#45;bitious plans of Antipater&#44; who was in reality master<lb/> of the impotent high&#45;priest.  But before any action<lb/> had could been taken upon it&#44; Aristobulus and his second<lb/> son Antigonus had fled from Italy&#44; and reached<lb/> Palestine.  The appearance of the two descendants<lb/> of Mattathias was hailed by the patriots&#44; who<lb/> hated Rome and its mercenary vassal&#44; Antipater.<lb/>  A vast multitude offered to stand by their former<lb/> King and recover for him the royal diadem.  Aris&#45;<lb/>&#45;tobulus accepted only some eight thousand picked men soldiers<lb/> inured to the hardships of the field&#44; and possessed<lb/> of military knowledge.  A rash attempt to break<lb/> up the serried legions of Rome with a few com&#45;<lb/>&#45;battants&#33;  Prodigious acts of valor were displayed&#44; the<lb/> father and his son fought desperately&#44; till covered with wounds<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>they fell into the en hands of the enemy.  They<lb/> were put in fetters and sent back to a Roman<lb/> prison.  It was due to a promise given<lb/> by Gabrinius to the mother of Alexander&#44; that<lb/> the captives were not sentenced by the Senate to<lb/> pay with their lives for their foolhardiness.<lb/></p>
            <p>But the complete defeat and its sad consequences&#44;<lb/> did not calm the agitated spirits.  Alexander<lb/> tried again to accomplish with thirty thousand<lb/> what he failed to attain with one third of that<lb/> number.  The result proved equally disastrous.<lb/>  Judea seemed fated never again to rise from<lb/> a state of lowliness abject galling dependence.  The<lb/> last stages of her history are so closely con&#45;<lb/>&#45;nected with the events in Rome&#44; that to explain the<lb/> former&#44; a reference to the latter is unavoidable&#91;&#63;&#93;.  My<lb/> reference will be very slight.<lb/></p>
            <p>The triumvirate of Crassus&#44; Pompey and Julius Caesar<lb/> had been formed.  The three were to divide among them&#45;<lb/>&#45;selves the world and its riches.  Crassus chose<lb/> Syria&#44; and superseded Gabrinius in Palestine.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>All will remember the unenviable character<lb/> of Crassus.  He was said to be the wealthiest Ro&#45;<lb/>&#45;man and the most avaricious of men.  Our people had<lb/> suffered much by the greed of former consuls and governors.<lb/>  Judea had been plundered by those of the Greek and Latin<lb/> race&#44; yet&#44; the conduct of such was generosity itself<lb/> in when compared with the demeanour of Crassus.  He<lb/> entered Jerusalem as a friend of Hyrcanus&#44; but more<lb/> than for the priest&#44; he cared for the Temple.  He had The greed The covetous<lb/> triumvir had learnt that to it the faithful&#44; then scattered into different countries&#44;<lb/> sent precious offerings&#44; and he determined to &#91;&#63;&#93; make them<lb/> his own.  The guardians of the treasury would willingly<lb/> had yielded much&#44; if the rapacious Roman would only have<lb/> respect consecrated vessels.  One Eleazar&#44; the chief super&#45;<lb/>&#45;intendent&#44; after having received a solemn oath that<lb/> nothing more would be asked&#44; delivered to the thieving<lb/> chief general a wedge of solid massive gold in the shape of a beam<lb/> enclosed encased in another of made of wood&#44; but Cressus va&#45;<lb/>&#45;lued oaths as much as he cared for the lives of his soldiers.<lb/>  He robbed&#44; pillaged&#44; profaned and outraged.  Then leaving<lb/> the Judeans to lament their impotency he turned his marched on to<lb/> cohort to the country spread havoc in ruin in the land of the Parthians.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>But there Nemesis awaited him.  Treachery had<lb/> been his companion through life&#44; and by treachery he was<lb/> caught into the snares of death.  Pompey&#44; the other<lb/> member of the triumvirate&#44; having grown jealous beyond<lb/> bounds of Ceasar&#39;s popularity&#44; resolved to rid him&#45;<lb/>&#45;self of an associate who was by far his superior in<lb/> talents and resources and talents.  The two rivals turned their country<lb/> into the battle ground field of their bloody disputes.  But<lb/> before the decisive battle had been fought on the plains of Pharsalia&#44; had<lb/> been fought&#44; Casar Caesar sought of bringing Asia<lb/> under his control.  He knew that Antipater favored<lb/> Pompey&#44; and he would therefore create a counteracting<lb/> force.  With that object in view&#44; he set Aris&#45;<lb/>&#45;tobulus free&#44; and gave him command over two legions.<lb/>  But the Asmonean King did not enjoy the opportunity&#44;<lb/> which he so fondly craved for.  He was poisoned by<lb/> men who sided with Pompey&#44; and his body was preserved<lb/> in honey till it could be carried to the ancestral burial<lb/> place.  Alexander met with a severer sadder end.  At the<lb/> instance if the same partizans of Pompey&#44; he was beheaded<lb/> in at Antioch&#44; after a mock trial for treason.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>As we mentally accompany those two brave<lb/> Maccabeans to their untimely grave&#44; we can almost<lb/> see the shadow of the iniquitous Idumean pass before<lb/> us with a joyful smile.  For who but he could<lb/> have brought about the fatal issue&#63;  Who but he<lb/> was vitally interested in the extinction of the family&#44;<lb/> that gave us heroes&#44; statesmen and sages&#63;  The race<lb/> of the upstart could not rise but upon the ruins<lb/> of the illustrious.  As we proceed&#44; we will be shown<lb/> the waving of the chords of unrighteousness by<lb/> which Antipater dragged us down to the lowest ebb of degradation and forced his<lb/> own children up to the summit of power.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
