<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF4_13</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1869-01" source="" attested="yes">1869</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_13_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_13_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_13_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_13_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_13_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_13_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_13_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_13_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_13_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_13_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_13_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_13_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_13_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_13_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_13_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_13_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>A sermon for the Sabbath<lb/>
                before Passover  1869<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  Various are the reasons given for the name by<lb/> which this Sabbath is designated.  I have read&#44; among others&#44;<lb/> that it has also derived its origin from a practice prevalent<lb/> in former ages.  Our fathers thronged the Synagogue&#44; and<lb/> remained therein longer than customarily ordinarily&#44; to be instructed<lb/> in the rules attending the observance of the approaching<lb/> festival.  That circumstance&#44; added solemnity to the day&#59;<lb/> and therefore it was distinguished by the appellation of<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;the great Sabbath.&#34;  That epithet is retained<lb/> even at the present time.  But scarcely for the motive<lb/> just assigned.  The preacher who should imagine to be<lb/> able to detain his congregation&#44; and command attention by<lb/> descanting on the importance of removing every trace of leaven<lb/> from our dwelling places homesteads&#44; or on the nature of the food and the<lb/> utensils permitted to be used during the Passover&#44; would soon discover<lb/> that his words fell upon listless ears.  Are we then<lb/> better informed on the subject&#63;  Or&#44; is the interest&#44; which our<lb/> predecessors evinced in whatever concerns the anniversary of our<lb/> freedom from bondage&#44; greatly lessened&#63;  Daily occurrences tend to corroborate the latter of my 2 suppositions.  Yet&#59; If we credit that<lb/> which the self&#45;styled progressive press circulates&#44; our antipathy<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>to against the observances of old&#44; arises from a higher conception of<lb/> our religious mission.  If Whereas&#44; on the other hand if the assertions<lb/> publicly made by the followers of the man of Nazareth&#44; are<lb/> to be believed&#44; it is the sure index of our gradual adoption lapsing<lb/> of into the doctrines they profess.  I however&#44; judge both to<lb/> be wrong.  The prevailing indifference for the rites<lb/> of our faith&#44; does by no means prove denote a due appreciation of<lb/> its spirit.  To argue thus&#44; would be to declare that<lb/> those sentiments of the heart are the strongest&#44; which are<lb/> never revealed by external evidences.  No&#58; love is<lb/> demonstrative.  The object of our affection&#44; is not only<lb/> the burden of our thoughts&#44; but the being upon whom we<lb/> delight to bestow the tokens of our sentiments inward feelings.  Just because<lb/> our progenitors did honor the principles of Judaism&#44; they<lb/> practically showed the feelings by sentiments regarding it with which they were imbued.<lb/>  And So that when the season arrived which &#91;&#63;&#93; calls to memory the most<lb/> important event in the history of our people&#44; everything<lb/> attested their desire of to celebrateing it in the signal most remarkable manner.<lb/>  Their unsophisticated minds could not understand&#44; how a<lb/> Hebrew might perform his mission negatively.<lb/></p>
            <p>I use the term advisedly&#59; for&#44; it is so that many of<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>my brethren &#40;and they are the loudest in professing reverence for<lb/> the ancestral creed&#41; imagine they can discharge their religious duty.<lb/>  The ritual law is regarded by them as antiquated&#44; and he who<lb/> observes it as a benighted being.  Their religion resolves itself into a<lb/> denial of a plurality of gods triune god&#59; and that they dignify with<lb/> the title of &#34;the&#34; Messiaship of Israel.&#34;  Let those who<lb/> have a mind to reflect&#44; determine&#44; whether such is the<lb/> Judaism&#44; the adherence to which is destined to dispell the<lb/> errors of gentilism.  I walk in the light&#44; shed around<lb/> me by history&#44; and see&#44; as clearly as at noon&#45;day&#44; that a<lb/> course like that pursued by the so called reformed Jews of<lb/> this age&#44; would&#44; in less than a century&#44; obliterate even the memory<lb/> of the truths&#44; we were commissioned to perpetuate.<lb/>  None of us can resist surrounding influences.  Unless our<lb/> attention is drawn therefrom by some powerful agencies&#44; we<lb/> must finally <sic>yeild</sic>.  Those agencies&#44; my dear hearers&#33;<lb/> are the statutes of the Pentateuch&#44; guarded by Rabbinical<lb/> enactments.  Let your sons grow with the<lb/> mere knowledge of the existence of God&#44; and if they will not<lb/> embrace the belief of the majority&#44; their offspring will surely<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>become identified with it.  The Sages of our nation have<lb/> said &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;He who rejects false deities&#44; gives<lb/> his assent to the teachings of the whole law.&#34;  And again&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;He who discards Whosoever abjures idolatry&#44; is called a Jew.&#34;<lb/>  But those pithy sentences have evidently reference to non&#45;<lb/>Israelites.  They antonomastically allude to to the gentiles&#44; from whose eyes the veil which<lb/> conceals the truth&#44; has been lifted up.  But those The men who<lb/> are born of the Hebrew race have positive obligations<lb/> to perform&#44; by which they will prove their fidelity to the<lb/> Lord&#44; and propagate the knowledge of his Unity.<lb/>  Of them did the greatest of all mortals speak in his parting<lb/> address.&#34;  Set your hearts unto all the words which I testify<lb/> among you this day&#59; so that you may command them to your children&#44;<lb/> and they will observe to do all the words of this law&#34;.<lb/>  And that saying of the arch&#45;prophet is reechoed by the<lb/> inspired Asaph.  &#34;He established a testimony in Jacob&#44; and<lb/> instituted a law in Israel&#44; which he commanded our fathers&#44;<lb/> that they should make them known to their children.<lb/>  In order that the latest generation might know them&#44; even<lb/> the children that are to be born&#44; that they may arise and again relate<lb/> them to their own children.  So&#44; that they place their hope in God&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>and do not forget the doings of the Almighty&#59; but observe<lb/> his commandments.&#34;  What means then the<lb/> doctrine now preached&#44; that ceremonial precepts may<lb/> be kept at bay a distance&#44; provided the idea of One God is kept<lb/> in sight&#63;  Must we believe&#44; that the punish&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment of &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;excision&#34; pronounced against the Israelite<lb/> who eats aught which is leavened on Passover&#44; will not<lb/> be inflicted&#63;  Or&#44; that by placing upon our table an<lb/> unleavened cake&#44; as a memorial of the past&#44; we have duly<lb/> solemnized the great season of our redemption from Egypt&#63;<lb/>  For&#44; you will be no more surprised to learn&#44; that such a course<lb/> has been advocated&#44; than I was to bear the assertion that<lb/> Passover may be postponed to the fourteenth of the following<lb/> month&#44; if it be inconvenient to observe it&#44; an entire week<lb/> in Nissan.  No theory&#44; however untenable&#44; can now&#45;a&#45;days<lb/> be startling&#44; since an Israelite strove recently to show in his<lb/> writing&#44; that only obstinacy&#44; ignorance and bigotry prevent a<lb/> universal celebration of the Sabbath upon Sunday.<lb/></p>
            <p>Nevertheless&#44; lest some of my hearers may be induced to<lb/> think that a passage in the book of Numbers&#44; supports<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>the opinion advanced about differing the feast of un&#45;<lb/>&#45;leavened bread&#44; I will briefly remark&#59; that the Scripture speaks<lb/> there exclusively of the paschal lamb.  It prescribes that he<lb/> who through some impurity or by reason of the distance&#44; could<lb/> not be present in the court of the Sanctuary at the time ordained by the law&#44; should<lb/> bring his offering at a later period.  But that rule can&#45;<lb/>&#45;not in any manner be applicable to us.  For&#44; with the<lb/> destruction of the Temple&#44; the rite of sacrifice entirely ceased&#44;<lb/> whereas concerning the festival itself&#44; we are repeatedly com&#45;<lb/>&#45;manded&#44; irrespective of place or climate&#44; to hold it for seven consecutive<lb/> days&#59; and it is explicitly written in the holy volumes &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;In all your habitations&#44; ye shall eat unleavened bread.&#34;<lb/>  Nothing short of infidelity can therefore occasion a disregard for<lb/> that or of other biblical ceremonial injunctions of the Bible.<lb/></p>
            <p>Our neighbours who closely watch us&#44; interpret a perceptible<lb/> general defection perceptible in our ranks&#59; as a wish to merge into their religious com&#45;<lb/>munities.  But they also are greatly at fault.  The Hebrews<lb/> are a new school&#44; do not contemn the ordinances of their faith&#44;<lb/> because they prefer those of the imposed by the Nazarene church&#59;<lb/> but because the skepticism of Northern Europe&#44; has seized<lb/> their minds&#44; and rendered them audacious.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Being ill&#45;at&#45;ease under a law which lays restrictions<lb/> on its votaries&#44; they reason themselves into the belief that<lb/> their fathers were unnecessarily burdened.  That while the found&#45;<lb/>&#45;ations of Judaism are to stand immoveably&#44; the fabric raised<lb/> upon it&#44; maybe pulled down at pleasure.  And those individuals<lb/> they call friends of enlightenment&#44; who bring all their<lb/> strength to bear on the demolition of that venerable structure.<lb/>  But to accept any other dogma than that of one indivisible<lb/> God&#44; is as remote from their thoughts as it is form mine.<lb/>  They would resent it as an offense&#44; if told that their general<lb/> conduct gives room to the supposition.  In short&#58; they<lb/> are wiling to remain Jews&#44; and be free to set at <sic>nought</sic><lb/> the laws of Judaism.  Alas&#33; that it was my fate<lb/> lately&#44; to witness how far that disregard for the time&#45;honored<lb/> prescriptions of our religion&#44; will be carried out.  And the<lb/> deeper is my sorrow&#44; because I tacitly sanctioned what I<lb/> should have openly reprehended&#59; because&#45;&#45;heedless of the<lb/> duty I owe myself and my God&#44; I lent my countenance<lb/> to sin.  But the very incident which saw me thus<lb/> disgraced&#44; revealed also how widely spread in Israel is the<lb/> contagion of incredulity.  It has infected every grade<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>of Jewish society&#44; so that the fear of contamination debars<lb/> a residue that are still faithful&#44; from joining their own<lb/> brethren at convivial gatherings.  Oh Malachi&#33; Oh<lb/> sainted precept Seer&#33;  Thou didst reprove the boldness of thy<lb/> contemporaries.  But what did they speak against the<lb/> Most High&#44; which is not exceeded in acrimony by certain Israelites of<lb/> this age&#63;  They said &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;It is in vain<lb/> to serve God&#44; and what profit is it that we keep his<lb/> ordinances charge&#63;&#34;  But now the pulpit declares the prophets<lb/> false.  The robed ministers of the Hebrew church berate<lb/> Moses and decry his laws.  Therefore is impiety rampant&#44;<lb/> and those who cling to the statutes &#38; ordinances of Horeb&#44; deeply lament.<lb/>  But....they shall rejoice&#44; for each of their godly thoughts<lb/> is already registered as a merit in the book of memorials<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Upon that dreadful day which the Lord creates&#44;<lb/> they shall be proclaimed His peculiar treasure.  Then will be<lb/> seen a palpable distraction between him that worships God<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; for God&#39;s sake &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; and him who worships<lb/> God not&#44; safe for his own gain. &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Dear Brethren&#33;  The consolatory<lb/> promises chronicled in the Haftorah of this great Sabbath&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>should be our stay through life.  God broke asunder<lb/> the chains that shackled our bodies&#44; in order to bind us to his<lb/> holy service&#59; as it is written ye have seen what I did unto the Egyptians&#44; &#38; &#34;how I carried you upon eagles wings&#44;<lb/> and brought to bring you unto myself.&#34;  And the approaching festival<lb/> is designed to awaken the memory of that assumed mission.<lb/>  We may meet with obstacles in the performance thereof.  We<lb/> may perchance consider our labor <sic>unrequitted</sic>&#59; but you have<lb/> heard the infallible sentence.  To falter is to purchase ever&#45;<lb/>&#45;lasting sorrow&#59; to persevere despite difficulties is to gain earn<lb/> a reward which lasts eternally.  Who among you&#44; O<lb/> believing Israelites who will hesitate to choose&#63;  I feel&#44;<lb/> I can safely count upon some&#44; who will stand firm&#44; and I turn<lb/> with an abiding confidence towards our young brother&#44; the &#34;Bar Mitzvah.&#34;<lb/>  None will more steadily hold up the standard of Sinai.  Precept<lb/> and example will combine in strengthening his hands.<lb/>  My friend&#33;  You are being fashioned in a mould&#44; out of<lb/> which your heart and soul will come forth beautifully<lb/> shapen.  It is home instruction.  Your parents doubtless<lb/> value the education of the mind and will afford you the<lb/> teaching capable of <sic>developping</sic> your natural capacities.<lb/>  But their main endeavours have been&#44; and will continue to be&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>the preservation of your soul.  They love you bodily&#59;<lb/> but they are sensible of their responsibility before God&#44;<lb/> and therefore they will avoid the sin of which many<lb/> a father and mother in Israel are now gently&#44; even&#44; of<lb/> promoting the material interests of their sons&#44; to the detri&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment of their spiritual weal.  To add another<lb/> word in praise of your natural guardians&#44; would ill become comfort<lb/> this place&#59; with the dignity of the house of prayer&#59; but to you&#44; I must&#44; by virtue of my calling&#44;<lb/> picture the blessings you enjoy&#59; that you may appreciate<lb/> and improve them.  You are raised above want&#59;<lb/> hence you are shielded against  the moral evils to which the<lb/> children of the needy are often exposed.  For&#44; they must<lb/> necessarily be sent out into the world early in life to plod for their subsistence&#44; and<lb/> there thus they frequently meet with corrupt associates.  You can&#44; under<lb/> parental supervision&#44; choose as companions those that<lb/> are good and well&#45;bred.  You are likewise supplied with<lb/> preceptors&#44; who impart the knowledge of the law&#44; conformably<lb/> with the manner approved by our Sages&#44; and you will<lb/> not consequently imbibe any of the new&#45;fangled notions&#44; subversive<lb/> of the revealed will of God.  So&#44; the instruments<lb/> are at work&#44; to keep you in the path of righteousness<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>should you abandon it&#44; to follow that of vice and irreligion&#44;<lb/> you would at the latter end be stung by self&#45;reproach and<lb/> exclaim &#34;How have I hated instruction&#44; and how my heart despised<lb/> correction&#44; and I have not obeyed the voice of my superiors&#44;<lb/> and inclined not mine ears to my teachers.&#34;  But you<lb/> will&#44; under God&#44; remain steadfast&#44; and I shall joyfully<lb/> number you among the residue of the faithful.<lb/></p>
            <p>May it be so&#44; and may I glory with you over the increase<lb/> of godliness in the community of whom you will&#44; from this<lb/> day be counted reckoned a member.  Grant Thy heavenly support&#44;<lb/> O Lord&#33; to this son of Thy people&#44; who has promised to walk<lb/> in Thy statutes.  Grant that he may ever obtain in this<lb/> sacred dwelling a fresh incentive to do what is right in Thy sight.<lb/>  May the demeanour of its attendants exalt him in spirit&#59;<lb/> the conduct of its officers inspire him with humility and<lb/> goodness.  May he be hereafter instrumental in perpe&#45;<lb/>&#45;trating this congregation&#44; in maintaining its high standing&#44; &#38; pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;moting its temporal and spiritual welfare.  For&#44; this is the<lb/> supplication which we all unitedly offer&#44; and the accomplishing<lb/> thereof will exalt Thy name&#44; O Redeemer and everlasting<lb/> Protector of Thy people Israel&#33;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
