<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF12_5</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1894" source="" attested="yes">1894</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_5_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_5_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_5_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_5_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_5_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_5_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_5_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_5_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_5_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_5_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_5_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_5_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET.<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;1894<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Personal pity&#44; national patriotism<lb/>
                For Beshalach<lb/></p>
            
            <p>96</p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>The columns of the Philadelphia Ledger&#44; devoted<lb/> on Saturdays to &#34;Religious thoughts&#44; which by the editors of that Journal gathered from<lb/> various sources&#44; offer&#44; at times&#44; occasion for sober reflect&#45;<lb/>&#45;ions.  Among the sentiments most frequently quoted&#44;<lb/> the reader will find those expressed by the late Episcop&#45;<lb/>&#45;al Bishop of <sic>Massachussets</sic>&#45;&#45;the Rev. Dr. Phillips<lb/> Brooks.  Earnestness and broad humanity won for<lb/> the gifted preacher an enviable reputation&#44; both in<lb/> American where he in whose cities he regularly officiated and in England&#44; where his<lb/> voice was publicly heard.  As Jews&#44; we cannot<lb/> agree with him regarding to the supremacy given to claimed for Christian&#45;<lb/>&#45;ity and its alleged founder&#44; but we must approve of<lb/> the charity taught in the pulpit and practised by<lb/> a sincere teacher in the daily walks of life.<lb/>  The Haftorah of this morning&#44; has recalled to my<lb/> mind an idea quoted from Phillips Brooks&#44; which<lb/> I read once in the a Saturday&#39;s Ledger but disapprovingly.  The lecturer&#44; had al&#45;<lb/>&#45;luded to the concluding sentence of the impassioned<lb/> song of Deborah&#44; and had contrasted it pointedly with the<lb/> saying of the man of Nazareth&#44; who is reported to<lb/> have thus prayed in his last moments&#58; &#34;Father&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>forgive them&#44; for they know not what they do.&#34;<lb/>  &#34;Barbaric&#34; was declared by Phillips Brooks&#44; the<lb/> triumphal cry of the Hebrew woman&#44; brimfull of ten&#45;<lb/>&#45;der compassion&#44; on the contrary he proclaimed the utterance of the<lb/> Jewish man dying on the cross.  Now&#58;<lb/> I am none of those who look far and wide to<lb/> find discover extenuating causes to actions&#44; which our hearts<lb/> or our minds repel.  With all the deference<lb/> due to our Talmudists&#44; I could never&#44; by way of example&#44; accept their<lb/> their opinion of some of them&#44; that to condemn Reuben as a sin&#45;<lb/>&#45;ner&#44; is to commit an error&#59; or that to attri&#45;<lb/>&#45;bute to David <sic>wilful</sic> misdeeds&#44; is a mistake &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> The canonizing of Biblical characters as saints&#44;<lb/> simply because they figure prominently in sacred<lb/> pages&#44; will never under no circumstance&#44; meet my approval.  The<lb/> views held by some Rabbis in that respect&#44; I reject&#44;<lb/> as unscriptural and misleading.  If asked&#44; I would<lb/> not hesitate to answer that the brotherly consideration<lb/> of the oldest of Jacob&#39;s sons&#44; cannot excuse his<lb/> filial offence&#44; nor the immense services of the youngest son<lb/> of Jesse to Israel and mankind&#44; can cover over<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>the wrongs of which he became guilty.<lb/>  Still&#44; I draw a sharp line of demarcation be&#45;<lb/>&#45;tween defending the indefensible and justifying<lb/> what the love of country and independence dictates.  A<lb/> cardinal fault in with in the Christian religion is its<lb/> confounding national with personal feelings.<lb/>  Judaism&#44; which goes hand in hand&#44; as it were&#44; with<lb/> reason&#44; marks out well the distinction between<lb/> what we owe one another as individuals&#44; and<lb/> what we owe ourselves as integral parts of the people to<lb/> which we belong and of the land in whose happiness<lb/> ours is immediately connected directly involved.  Let an unpre&#45;<lb/>&#45;judiced judge&#44; search through the pages of Biblical<lb/> and post&#45;biblical writings&#44; and he will discover find<lb/> rules directing commanding each person to act in his relations<lb/> to his fellow man with a thoughtfulness&#44; loving<lb/> kindness and forbearance unsurpassed.  &#34;Thou shalt<lb/> not hate thy brother in thy heart&#34;.  &#34;Thou shalt<lb/> love thy neighbor as thyself&#34;.  &#34;Ye shall love the stran&#45;<lb/>&#45;ger&#34; are maxims most assuredly&#44; Mosaic.  maxims  &#34;There<lb/> rises unto the upright&#44; light in the darkness&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>to the gracious&#44; the compassionate and righteous.&#34;<lb/>  &#34;It is well with the man that deals mercifully&#44;<lb/> and who leads&#59; who governs his affairs with justice.&#34;<lb/>  &#34;A kind man does good to his own soul&#34;.  By kind&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness and truth sin will be forgiven&#34;&#44; are undoubted&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly sentences emanating from our psalmist and our<lb/> moralist.  And even more forcible than Holy Writ are the Sages&#44; in<lb/> demanding the exercise of humane qualities.  Be of the disciples of Aaron &#38;c  &#34;Who&#45;<lb/>&#45;ever shows no pity for his fellow&#45;being dares not<lb/> claim a descent from Abraham.&#34;  &#34;Whoever causes<lb/> another being to suffer punishment through his<lb/> instrumentality&#44; will never enter the presence<lb/> of the Most High&#34;.  &#34;To be Godlike is to copy<lb/> the divine attributes of unrestricted goodness&#34;.<lb/>  Those are some of the innumerable sayings of equal<lb/> import&#44; scattered among the volumes of the Talmud&#44;<lb/> and there we meet also incidents illustrating<lb/> the truth that to forgive man is to draw down<lb/> God&#39;s infinite blessings.  And all Israelites know<lb/> the night prayer embodied in the Jewish liturgy.<lb/>  &#34;Sovereign of the world&#33;  Behold&#44; I fully pardon<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>every one who has angered or offended me&#44; in any<lb/> manner&#44; whether personally&#44; financially&#44; or in<lb/> whatever is mine whether the deed was done<lb/> by instigation&#44; or <sic>wilfully</sic>&#44; or by mistake&#44; or pre&#45;<lb/>meditately.  May no Israelite be punished on my<lb/> account&#44; nor any human creature &#91;Hebrew&#93; Yet&#44; I<lb/> admit it without reservation&#44; those teachings in<lb/> which we Jews may justly glory&#44; apply to each of us in<lb/> our conduct towards our neighbors&#44; as our neighbors&#44;<lb/> not towards the united oppressors of our country&#44;<lb/> the combined robbers of our national property&#44; the<lb/> allied persecutors of our belief.  The failure to make<lb/> that discrimination is the cause of Phillips Brooks&#39; censure&#44; of rather of our Deborah&#44; or rather of the impossible<lb/> theoretical Christianity which the good Bishop of <sic>Massa&#45;<lb/>&#45;chussets</sic> wished to inculcate.  For practically Christ&#45;<lb/>&#45;ians and Jews are of one and the same mind in draw&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing the distinction.  Now&#58; who were the enemies<lb/> that Deborah prayed against and whose destruction<lb/> she desired&#63;  Her personal opponents&#44; or the adversaries<lb/> merely of her household&#63;  Not at all History tells it.  For twenty<lb/> years Jabin King of Canaan&#44; who reigned in Chazor&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>asked by heathen princes&#44; bent upon the extermin&#45;<lb/>&#45;ation of our people&#44; had held a crushing hood over<lb/> Israel.  The invincible general who mar&#45;<lb/>shalled a large cavalry and infantry was the invincible Sisera.<lb/>  He spread terror reigned abroad.  Husbandry and commerce languished.  Hemmed&#44; in around and harassed on all sides&#44; our<lb/> villagers feared to venture out&#59; the high ways<lb/> of our cities remained deserted.  The fate of our<lb/> ancestors seemed to tremble in the balance&#44; when<lb/> patriotism fired the heart of a woman.  Debo&#45;<lb/>&#45;rah could not have listened unconcerned to<lb/> the lament of sufferers who came to counsel<lb/> with her as her simple the female Judge bench of Mount Eph&#45;<lb/>&#45;raim sitting under beneath the shades of a her palm tree.  Her<lb/> ardent spirit is aroused awakened.  She can will endure no longer the<lb/> vile servitude under the foreigner.  She must<lb/> cast off the <sic>femminine</sic> garb and rise to the<lb/> deliverance of her nation.  Stirred up in her<lb/> every fibre&#44; the wife of Lapidoth&#44; summons<lb/> Barak quickly to master together the fearless valiant<lb/> among his tribe&#44; arouse Naftati and Zebulon<lb/> ready for the fray&#44; gather an army of ten thou&#45;<lb/>sand soldierly Hebrews&#44; and let them bleed for their country and their God.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>She also will stand at Mount Tabor&#44; and<lb/> and strengthen with her martial presence the <sic>combattants</sic>.<lb/>  Short and decisive was the battle.  The heavens<lb/> fought against Sisera.  A terrific storm which<lb/> arose hastened the routing and discomfitting of<lb/> the dreaded enemy.  We may pardon a heroine<lb/> and poetess who&#44; upon hearing that the terrible Si&#45;<lb/>&#45;sera has fallen slain under the blows of one of<lb/> her sex&#44; friendly to the cause of Israel&#44; forgets the<lb/> treachery only to remember the conquest and its<lb/> completeness through Jael&#39;s hammer.  We<lb/> may forgive the patriotic daughter of our race&#44;<lb/> who&#44; in a flight of her genius&#44; pictures the<lb/> alternating of feelings of in a proud mother&#44; accustom&#45;<lb/>ed to embrace her victorious son&#44; trembling<lb/> at one moment because of his delay&#44; leaping with<lb/> joy at another the next moment&#44; at the prospect of his return<lb/> enriched with inimical  the rarest spoil.  We may condone<lb/> in Deborah the outburst of feelings which found<lb/> vent in her last utterance &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  But who were then the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>foes that God might destroy&#44; while His<lb/> friends shall shine as brilliantly as the son<lb/> at its meridian&#63;  They were the persecutors and<lb/> plunderers of Deborah&#39;s nation and of the<lb/> country of her birth.  Would Christians&#44; on<lb/> a like occasion&#44; have folded their arms and inactive&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly following falling on their knees&#44; inactively have prayed &#34;Father<lb/> forgive them&#44; for they know not what they<lb/> do&#34;&#63;  So long as every spark of love of<lb/> her one&#39;s native hearth&#44; is not extinct&#44; not a we shall find<lb/> people none be they of whatever religion or region who will so<lb/> act.  But to refuse to do as Deborah and her<lb/> faithful followers instinctively did&#44; is called by enthusiasts&#45;&#45;<lb/>I will not style them visionaries&#45;&#45;is called&#44; I say&#44;<lb/> &#34;refined Christianity.&#34;  I have read a French<lb/> author who wrote thus&#58; &#34;Patriotism is a sen&#45;<lb/>&#45;timent belonging to the old Law&#44; theoretically&#44;<lb/> it has no place in the new.  The day on<lb/> which the new was preached to gentiles&#44; was&#44;<lb/> on principle virtually&#44; the last day of nationality.&#34;<lb/>  And continuing in that strain&#44; the author added&#58;<lb/> &#34;The sentiment of nationality&#44; as the English<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>understand it&#44; is a sentiment essentially Jewish.<lb/>  One would believe that an English community is a<lb/> community of the circumcised.&#34;  Well&#58; Be that as it<lb/> may&#44; the world at large does not blame the En&#45;<lb/>glish born&#44; wherever dwelling&#44; through voluntary<lb/> or fortuitous circumstances&#44; for referring to Great<lb/> Britain as his &#34;Home&#34;.  Bishop Brooks&#44; who bore<lb/> the reputation of having the courage of his convictions&#44;<lb/> would have us denounce the magnificent woman of whom we are<lb/> proud.  He says&#58; &#34;we must entertain no sentiment<lb/> but that of pity and a desire to help even the worst<lb/> of men&#34;.  I unite in share that sentiment.  So does my<lb/> Bible and my Talmud.  &#34;If thou canst draw out of what<lb/> is vile&#44; something precious&#44; thou shalt be My ins mouthpiece&#34;<lb/> said the Lord to Jeremiah&#44; and a sage advised his son so&#58;<lb/> &#34;If a corrupt one meets thee&#44; lead him gently where he<lb/> may learn to do right.&#34;  Such should be our conduct<lb/> towards every human being in our walks of life&#44; but toward<lb/> the enemy of our country and the faith we cherish&#44; we and all the world all over will imitate<lb/> Deborah&#44; until the Hebrew prophecies are fulfilled and<lb/> the reign of universal peace is proclaimed on earth&#44; that<lb/> is&#44; when the fatherhood of God&#44; enunciated by our Lord&#44; will be acknowledged by all mankind&#44;<lb/> through the length &#38; breadth of the habitable globe.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
