<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF5_16</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_16_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_16_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_16_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_16_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_16_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_16_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_16_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_16_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_16_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_16_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_16_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_16_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_16_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_16_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_16_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_16_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET.<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44;  189<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Post Biblical<lb/>
                59<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>When I undertook to offer to view sketch out line the<lb/> writings of Levi son of Gerson&#44; or Gersonides&#44;<lb/> my intention was to be as brief about them&#44;<lb/> as I usually am&#44; when treating post&#45;Biblical<lb/> subjects&#44; but the darigngness displayed by<lb/> that French Israelite in his principal work&#44;<lb/> prevented my dismissing him with merely a few words.<lb/>  I have already explained how irreconcilable<lb/> with our accepted belief in immortality are his<lb/> philosophical notions&#59; how absurd is his credulity<lb/> in dreams and divinations&#59; how falsely the<lb/> author argues to prove that God possesses a<lb/> general and not a specific knowledge of<lb/> what happens in the world which He created.<lb/>  Now&#58; the fourth treatise of Michamoth Ha shem<lb/> &#34;the battles of the Lord&#44;&#34; consisting of seven chapters&#44;<lb/> may be regarded as a sequel to the third treatise&#44; for&#44;<lb/> if it be true&#44; that only national and communal<lb/> affairs fall under the consideration of the Most<lb/> High&#44; it logically follows that special Providence<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>does not exist.  And such is in fact&#44; the opinion<lb/> which Gersonides entertains.  According to him&#44; He contends that<lb/> man is too insignificant that the Omnipotent<lb/> Lord should deign to mark out notice his good or<lb/> evil doings.  But our writer forgot that<lb/> society is simply a collective body of separate persons&#44;<lb/> just as a single family is an aggregate of<lb/> a few individuals.  As in other in&#45;<lb/>&#45;stances&#44; so here the writer appeals to the Bible<lb/> for support&#44; but his quotations openly refutes<lb/> him.  In imitation of Maimonides who&#44; in<lb/> his More Nebuchim&#45;&#45;&#34;A guide to the perplexed&#34;<lb/> devoted some thoughts to the book of Job&#44; pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;senting the various theories&#44; which&#44; according<lb/> to his judgment&#44; were discussed by the per&#45;<lb/>&#45;sonages figuring in its pages&#44; Gersonides dwells<lb/> at some length on that splendid didactic<lb/> poem.  Referring to a commentary which he<lb/> had written upon it&#44; he pretends reasserts that Job<lb/> denied God&#39;s inspection of every man&#39;s con&#45;<lb/>duct&#44; while the very contrary is the truth.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>In that grand volume&#44; which adorns our Bible&#44; the principal actor&#44;<lb/> smarting under dire sufferings&#44; complains that<lb/> God has made him the incessant target aim of<lb/> Divine arrows&#44; as we read&#58; &#34;If I have sinned&#44;<lb/> what harm have  Idone unto Thee&#44; O Keeper of<lb/> man&#44; why hast Thou set me a mark for Thee&#44;<lb/> so that I am a burden to myself&#63;&#34;  And not<lb/> once&#44; but often the same idea of God&#39;s watch&#45;<lb/>&#45;fulness over each individual is brought forward.<lb/>  For example&#58; &#34;Life and favor Thou hadst granted<lb/> me and Thy care preserved my spirit.&#34;  And again as a rebuttal to the accusations of incredulity by one of his visitors&#44; Job said&#58;<lb/> &#34;Ask now the beasts and they will teach thee&#44; the<lb/> fishes of the sea and they will tell thee.  Who does<lb/> not know among through those things&#44; that the hand of<lb/> the Lord has wrought this.  In whose hand is the<lb/> soul of all living&#44; and the spirit of every human<lb/> creature&#63;&#34;  No&#58; Job&#39;s lament was not that<lb/> God is mindless of man&#39;s doings&#44; but that the<lb/> good actions virtues which he had performed were<lb/> insufficient to declare him pure in the sight of the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>all perfect God&#44; who counted his every step.<lb/>  On the other hand But Job&#39;s interlocutors in order to defend the Lord&#44;<lb/> charged the sufferer with sins and crimes&#44; which<lb/> he knew not to have committed.  But<lb/> Gersonides was too on his part&#44; misrepresented Job.  As an expert in misapplying<lb/> Bible and Talmud&#44; and he made a liberal<lb/> use of both to carry out his preconceived<lb/> notions.  To us however&#44; who discard a medieval<lb/> philosophy&#44; built upon rickety foundations&#44;<lb/> which time has overthrown&#44; Scriptures and<lb/> traditions read just precisely as the context shows.<lb/>  We believe with the inspired moralist that<lb/> &#34;the upright man&#34; is requited on earth and more so the<lb/> wicked and sinner&#44;&#34; and we agree with Rabbi<lb/> Akiba&#44; that we possess freedom of will and the<lb/> larger or smaller extent of our deeds is impart&#45;<lb/>&#45;ially weighted.  Were it otherwise&#44; prayers and<lb/> penance and penitence&#44; recommended as our atone&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment&#44; would be futile and absurd.  We let<lb/> Gersonides and the speculative philosophers of<lb/> the Middle ages fancy that only by means of an<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>&#34;active intelligence&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; man may forcibly draw<lb/> down upon him God&#39;s speciall Providence.  We<lb/> reject that doctrine as unscriptural&#44; unrabbinical<lb/> and unjust&#44; and we hold that &#34;from heaven the<lb/> Lord looks&#59; He beholds all the children of man.  From <lb/>the place of His habitation he watches all the inhabitants<lb/> of the earth.  He that fashions the hearts of them all&#44;<lb/> considers all their works&#34;.  The<lb/> fifth treatise of Milhamoth Ha&#45;shem&#45;&#45;and the most<lb/> important&#45;&#45;has not come down to posterity&#44; in its print&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed form&#44; entirely as originally composed.  We may regret that what<lb/> has deservedly won for the author an imperishable<lb/> renown among real scholars&#44; the editor saw fit<lb/> to omit.  Gersonides was confessedly an astronomer.<lb/>  He is credited with having invented a magnifying<lb/> instrument of exceeding value.  The famous<lb/> Reuchlin&#44; the friend of Hebrew literature&#44; the ency&#45;<lb/>&#45;clopedic Pico della Mrandola&#44; Pope Clemens VI&#44; even<lb/> the great Kepler studied what the French Jew<lb/> of in the XIV century wrote on about the starry sky.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>The very meritorious Solomon Munk assures<lb/> us that in the royal library at Paris&#44; ma&#45;<lb/>&#45;nuscript copies of the missing section of the<lb/> work exist&#45;&#45;probably with a Latin translation&#45;&#45;but<lb/> Jacob Mercaria&#44; who first published the book<lb/> at Riva di Frento in 1560&#44; left out a prominent<lb/> part of the fifth treatise&#44; considering it foreign<lb/> to the main subject.  That treatise&#44; as<lb/> now in our possession&#44; is divided into three sections.<lb/>  They speak of the planets and their influence on<lb/> human affairs&#44; as believed in his according to the universal belief of the time.  But recog&#45;<lb/>&#45;nizing that Gersonides did not rise above the errors<lb/> of the age in which he lived&#44; we cannot deny<lb/> him a <sic>marvellous</sic> knowledge of science.  In his<lb/> fifth treatise he exhibits it stupendously&#44; when treat&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing of the causes which produce the sun&#39;s heat&#44; of<lb/> those which keeps the moon cold&#44; though<lb/> reflecting its light&#59; when describing the fixed<lb/> stars&#44; and the planets celestial bodies&#44; moving in their orbits through<lb/> the measureless space.  And he rises aloft<lb/> when from the wonders of creation&#44; he turns<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>his thoughts to the Almighty Creator.<lb/>  With a depth and erudition simply amazing<lb/> he sets to view what Greek and Arabian thinkers<lb/> have written in their attempt to define the Prime<lb/> Mover of the boundless Universe worlds&#44; and he arrives<lb/> at the conclusion that God is the source of unalloyed glad&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness&#44; to worlds even as the psalmist declares it.  &#34;In<lb/> Thy presence there is fullness of joy.  At Thy right hand<lb/> then are pleasures for evermore&#44;&#34; and as the Sages<lb/> say &#34;Joy abides in His habitation.&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>The sixth and last treatise of Milhamoth Ha&#45;shem<lb/> divided in two parts&#45;&#45;the first containing twenty<lb/> nine chapters and the second fourteen&#45;&#45;is a<lb/> most profound disquisition on the creation of<lb/> heaven and earth&#44; and on the duration of time.<lb/>  The boldness of the author surpasses all limits&#44;<lb/> when judged from a Jewish stand&#45;point.  Mai&#45;<lb/>monides who in his undue deference to Aristotle&#44;<lb/> declared the Greek philosopher second to none&#44;<lb/> except our inspired prophets&#44; still opposed the<lb/> Stagirite in the idea that the world had existed<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>always&#44; and he reasoned against it logically<lb/> and religiously with more than usual force<lb/> and acuteness acumen.  Gersonides&#44; servile to the opinion<lb/> of Averr&#246;es&#44; could not summon the courage to rise<lb/> against the Arabian philosopher.  Unable<lb/> to explain away what is as clear as noon&#45;day&#44;<lb/> namely&#44; that Judaism points to a sovereign<lb/> wisdom whence all above and around us emanated&#44;<lb/> as we read &#34;For He spoke&#44; and it was&#44; He com&#45;<lb/>&#45;manded and it stood fast&#44;&#34; the French Jew ad&#45;<lb/>&#45;vances this preposterous notion.  Eternal mat&#45;<lb/>&#45;ter&#44; out of which the universe was moulded&#44; did<lb/> exist&#44; but it was so very imperceptibly thin&#44; that<lb/> we may consider it as if not existing.  And actuated&#44; by that unscripturial impression&#44;<lb/> he undertakes to dissect the first chapter<lb/> of Genesis with a scalpel so sharp edged&#44; that&#44;<lb/> a physician as he was&#44; he never could have<lb/> handled in his anatomical operations.  Not<lb/> content with wresting Biblical passages<lb/> from their true meaning&#44; he strains Rab&#45;<lb/>&#45;binical sayings into an impossible con&#45;<lb/>&#45;struction.  Then&#44; nothing daunted&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>he proceeds to define prophetism&#44; and<lb/> ventures so far as to surmise that some con&#45;<lb/>&#45;trivance&#44; like modern spiritualism&#44; may have<lb/> been applied to in certain miraculous events nar&#45;<lb/>&#45;rated in Holy Writ.  Indeed&#44; when we read<lb/> the principal work of Gersonides&#44; we<lb/> have just cause to lament the waste of time of<lb/> which the author&#44; and a number of his Hebrew<lb/> predecessors and contemporaries were guilty.<lb/>  In their endeavour to reconcile Mosaism with<lb/> a current philosophy which cameleon&#45;like has<lb/> changed its colours in every age&#44; they wrote<lb/> what has largely served to confuse the simple&#45;<lb/>&#45;hearted and lead the waverers away from the Law<lb/> and traditions.  If Gersonides&#44; who had commented<lb/> and philosophised on the book of Job&#44; had in&#45;<lb/>&#45;terpreted it correctly&#44; he would <sic>agreed</sic> with the<lb/> last conclusion of the great Eastern patriarch&#58;<lb/> &#34;Behold the fear of the Lord&#44; that is wisdom&#44;<lb/> and to depart from evil&#44; that is understand&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing.&#34;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
