<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF20_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff20_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff20_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff20_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff20_1_2v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>3 pages on 1 sheet<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>39</p>
            
            <p>For Sabbath Zav<lb/></p>
            
            <p>Sovereign of the world&#33;  To withdraw ancient Israel from the<lb/> inhuman worship of the heathens&#44; and inspire their hearts with<lb/> sentiments of parity&#44; thou didst vouchsafe to deal with them<lb/> after the manner of earthly kings.  Thou didst promise to<lb/> hallow honor with Thy Divine presence the dwelling they would build<lb/> in honor reverence to Thy name&#44; and accept with favor their voluntary<lb/> sacrifices.  Thou&#44; to whom all appertains&#44; and whose glory can&#45;<lb/>&#45;not be heightened by man&#39;s gifts&#44; didst nevertheless command that a continual perpetual<lb/> fire burn upon Thy a consecrated altar&#44; and thereon daily offerings be laid<lb/> as savory meat.  It was so that Thou wouldst impress<lb/> our fathers predecessors with the thought of the close connexion existing between<lb/> themselves a redeemed people and their Lord of truths heavenly Deliverer.  To strengthen that health&#45; salutary<lb/> &#45;ful idea&#44; were the ordinances of which we have read in the lesson section of this<lb/> Sabbath likewise mainly enacted.  They whom Thou hadst chosen to mini&#45;<lb/>&#45;ster at a house dedicated to Thy service&#44; should be inducted into<lb/> their office by rites&#44; symbolical typical of their high mission.  Their<lb/> minds must be lives were to be wholly devoted to spiritual objects.  Hence&#44; the<lb/> provision that the officiating priests should share anticipate in many<lb/> of the oblations brought to the sanctuary&#44; and obtain from<lb/> the a faithful a constant subsistence.  But because in the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>lapse of ages&#44; our ancestors mistook the means for the end&#44; and<lb/> learnt to look upon the immolation of oxen&#44; as an exemption<lb/> from moral duties&#44; therefore did Jeremiah Thy prophet upbraid<lb/> them in the language with which wherein the haptar&#225;h of this<lb/> Sabbath commences.  He declared that the sacrificial &#91;&#63;&#93;<lb/> had ceased to be accepted&#44; by reason of the foul thought baneful belief which<lb/> prompted its performance.  But that to know Thy holy attributes&#44;<lb/> O God&#33; and copy them in our intercourse with human our fellow beings&#44; is ever<lb/> pleasing in Thy sight&#44; ever propitiatory&#44; and ever profitable to<lb/> the souls.  Father of the fatherless&#33;  That offering is now<lb/> presented unto Thee by the sundry women of Thy people.  They have laid stretched<lb/> hold of forth their hands to save a child bereft of parental support&#44; and taught him to<lb/> walk in Thy statutes.  Under their fostering care he was has hitherto<lb/> been nurtured&#44; and through their well&#45;designed charity he will still be<lb/> directed until ripe age&#44; when capable of becoming self&#45;dependent.<lb/>  Thankful are the benefactors unto the Lord and joyful is the beneficiary&#44; that<lb/> he has been permitted to approach Thee&#44; and avow in this habita&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion of holiness&#44; intentions consistent with his birth and education.<lb/>  God of Righteousness&#33;  Receive favorably the fruit of a noble<lb/> institution in Israel our community.  Bless the zealous laborers&#44; and cast<lb/> around the objects of their generous endeavours&#44; a shield that<lb/> may avert from them all influences of destruction.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Our hearts are stirred up yearn at this hour for innocent orphans and we jointly<lb/> pray for the happiness of the Hebrew lad&#44; that has rehearsed<lb/> within our hearing the word of inspiration.  May he become grow<lb/> its defenders vigorous&#44; and be in turn endowed with powers to further<lb/> the cause of humanity&#44; the religion which is the cause of civilization humanity.  As upon over<lb/> his cradle hung affliction&#44; and his infancy was ushered in<lb/> by bereavement&#44; so may that painful past contrast greatly with his predestined<lb/> future&#44; when Thy merciful hand will guide his manhood to<lb/> gladness&#44; and his lengthened existence to comfort and peace.<lb/>  Grant O God that those the parents who contemplate in spirit the<lb/> welcome reception among the community of their son amid a congregation of his brethren&#44; may<lb/> obtain for us who gave it&#44; the fruition of health and abundance<lb/> of terrestrial goods as a celestial ray reward for our actions.  May this be<lb/> Thy gracious will&#44; and voices from above respond thereto&#44; Amen &#38; Amen.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
