<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF2_10</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1875" source="" attested="yes">1875</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_10_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_10_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_10_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_10_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_10_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_10_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_10_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_10_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_10_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_10_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_10_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_10_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For the 15th anniversary of the<lb/>
                7th st Synagogue.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>On the 15th anniversary of this Synagogue&#44; and at the<lb/> approaching of the season&#44; in which I shall tempo&#45;<lb/>&#45;rarily cease to address the Congregation&#44; a few out&#45; unre&#45;<lb/>&#45;spoken &#45;served words on relative to the worship we hold may<lb/> not be inopportune.  It is said that comparisons are<lb/> odious&#44; but through them we can alone judge of our<lb/> progress or retrogression.  If When we perceive that others<lb/> similarly situated to ourselves&#44; have gained a point&#44; which<lb/> we have not attained&#44; we ought to seek into the cause<lb/> and redouble our efforts in the future.  Looking on our<lb/> status from an orthodox stand&#45;point&#44; it will appear<lb/> that we have fallen short of our duty.  I have just<lb/> personally ascertained that in a neighbouring city&#44; a<lb/> congregation of kindred ritual to ours&#44; and conducted on<lb/> the same principles&#44; have made previsions for keeping<lb/> their house of prayer opened each morning and evening in<lb/> the year&#44; at least during the period when the inclemency<lb/> of the weather&#44; will not prevent the carrying out of the plan&#44;<lb/> through the distance to be reached by the attendants.<lb/>  That I consider that a movement in the right direction&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>because consistent with established rules in<lb/> Judaism&#44; and because calculated to popularize<lb/> the Congregation religious body adopting it.  I remember that<lb/> the proposition to follow a practice which our brethren<lb/> adhere to in all the countries of their dispersion&#44; once was<lb/> once made a a public meeting of this congregation&#44; but<lb/> it was declared incompatible with the usages prevailing in<lb/> our midst.  I acknowledge with unfeigned satisfaction<lb/> that at certain seasons&#44; daily service is held also in<lb/> this consecrated building&#44; but the largest majority of Israelites<lb/> connected with us in the manner of <sic>worshipping</sic> do<lb/> not even know perhaps of even the existence of that circumstance.<lb/>  At all events they are of opinion that to assemble over<lb/> on the Sabbath morning for divine service&#44; is all that<lb/> ought to be demanded or expected of Israelites.  Nay&#44;<lb/> they charge the officiating minister with want of<lb/> consideration.  Now&#59; a clerical failing of that nature&#44;<lb/> if proved by facts&#44; holds the accused to reprobation.<lb/>  The Sages have written &#34;Whosoever fatigues the Congre&#45;<lb/>&#45;gation by a prolongued singing of the prayers&#44; de&#45;<lb/>serves censure.&#34;  But I feel perfectly at east on that<lb/> score.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>I feel sure that I have not fallen under Rabbinical dispen&#45;<lb/>&#45;sure because by reason of that fault.  On the contrary&#44; my anxiety<lb/> to avoid it&#44; has laid me open at times to the imputation<lb/> of reading with unbecoming rapidity.  No&#44; the com&#45;<lb/>&#45;plaint of being unduly detained&#44; each Sabbath morning<lb/> has not its origin in my self&#45;complacency&#44; or in a fondness<lb/> for display&#59; but in two circumstances&#44; which I cannot<lb/> remedy alter.  IN the form of our ritual&#44; and in the practice<lb/> of lecturing.  I neither instituted the first&#44; nor introduced<lb/> the last.  Were it in my power to offer one hour of<lb/> diversion instead of two and a half of prayer&#45;singing and<lb/> pulpit&#45;preaching&#44; none should leave this spot dissatisfied.<lb/>  A feeling inborn with me to favor the wishes of my<lb/> coreligionists would suggest the adoption of a system&#44; af&#45;<lb/>&#45;fording recreation&#44; if not edification.  And as the number<lb/> of Israelites&#44; who&#44; like myself&#44; prefer the old beaten way<lb/> to the newly opened path&#44; is not extinct&#44; I would<lb/> set apart for them also the time needed to pursue it.<lb/>  But I cannot arrogate to myself an authority with<lb/> which I have not been invested.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Others may deem it permissible to alter at will<lb/> to expunge&#44; to condense&#44; to refashion any part of<lb/> the accepted prayer liturgy.  I cannot so construe the<lb/> leave I received from my superiors to pray and preach<lb/> in the house of our God.<lb/></p>
            <p>But this fact may be pointed out as note&#45;worthy.<lb/>  The complaint to which I have alluded&#44; emanates mostly<lb/> from my brethren who are tardy in arriving at the Sy&#45;<lb/>nagogue.  They rarely hear more than the latter half<lb/> of the ritual&#44; and as to the lecture&#44; if does not<lb/> act as a soporific&#44; it engages their attention but for<lb/> a very short time.  I cannot say&#44; with certainty&#44; that<lb/> the dilatoriness of the <sic>worshippers</sic> is due to their expecting<lb/> a delay of several minutes each Sabbath&#45;morning towards the conclusion of<lb/> the service&#44; but it has been so general during the<lb/> present year&#44; that the suspicion rises involuntarily.<lb/>  And with respect to the number of attendants&#44; I may&#44;<lb/> and I do ardently&#44; pray Almighty God to grant parents<lb/> a lengthened existence&#44; for experience has shown me&#44;<lb/> that in many instances the nails which press down<lb/> the lid of their coffins&#44; became the bolts with which their<lb/> children fasten against themselves the doors of the Synagogue.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Possibly&#44; the inducements which other shrines offer<lb/> to youths unacquainted with the language of the Bible&#44;<lb/> and averse to learn it&#44; the attractions of a service closely<lb/> imitative of that which gentilism of presents&#44; might<lb/> draw here also those among our rising generation&#44; who<lb/> are co not compelled to desecrate the Sabbath&#59; but even<lb/> the charms of music&#44; of eloquence&#44; &#38; of the setting of<lb/> both sexes together upon damask cushions&#44; will be resisted<lb/> by the all&#45;absorbing thought&#45;business.  Unless<lb/> it is boldly proclaimed and firmly believed in&#44; that Isra&#45;<lb/>&#45;elites have performed the fourth commandment of the<lb/> Decalogue in full&#44; when they have remained a short hour<lb/> in the temple of song&#44; even the latter will be re continue<lb/> unfrequented.  I am not ready to impart that<lb/> instruction&#44; and none of you&#44; my hearers&#44; have become grown<lb/> so degenerate&#44; to heed it and be guided thereby.<lb/>  But you wish for the swelling of our diminishing number&#44;<lb/> for a worship dignified by a crowded assembly&#59; you<lb/> wish for the temporal and spiritual welfare of this ancient<lb/> body of Hebrews.  And so eager you are to compass it&#44;<lb/> that you have at times planned a measure&#44; which you<lb/> conceived to be directly leading to that end.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Yet&#44; I would act falsely&#44; were I to say that a contem&#45;<lb/>&#45;plated amalgamation&#44; would&#44; under existing circumstances&#44;<lb/> be effect the good intended.  Materially it could not<lb/> prove of advantage&#44; and that for reasons obvious to every<lb/> thinking mind&#59; morally&#44; I am bold to assert&#44; it<lb/> would be far from profitable&#44; as it mighty naturally<lb/> provoke a constant contrast&#44; and with it a feelings<lb/> of partiality <sic>yeilding</sic> aught but peace.  We would<lb/> procure a number at the cost of mental sufferings<lb/> under which other Congregations smart.<lb/></p>
            <p>Let us then seek in our own immediate selves the means<lb/> of securing our permanence.  Let us search for them in<lb/> the hearts of our children.  They will still prize highly<lb/> this monument which we raised fifteen years ago<lb/> to historic Judaism&#44; if we&#44; their parents&#44; show a<lb/> sincerity of attachment to it.  Let them under&#45;<lb/>&#45;stand that the fidelity with which we adhere to<lb/> our ancient ritual is not bigotry&#59; that it is not even<lb/> a believe in its inviolability&#44; but that we cling to<lb/> it&#44; because it is a national bridge connecting<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>the present with the eventful past.  That<lb/> we look with fond affection upon that which prove<lb/> the source of comfort and of union to our predecessors&#44;<lb/> and the abolishing of which has divided their successors<lb/> into hostile camps.  Let them be shown how un&#45;<lb/>&#45;authorized changes have brought a strange fire to<lb/> the altar in the form of hired Nazarenes&#44; invoking with<lb/> feigned lips the One God of Israel&#44; while the believers<lb/> in the Unity are forbid to utter &#91;&#63;&#93; pronounce aloud the declara&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion of their faith.  Let them see the anomaly&#44; which<lb/> some of our edifices ostensibly dedicated to the Lord of<lb/> Abraham present&#44; and your sons and daughters inspired<lb/> by your example&#44; animated by your earnest precepts<lb/> carefully trained in the language and in the traditions<lb/> of antiquity the ancients&#44; will look upon this dwelling&#44; as true<lb/> representative of Judaism.  Fathers and mothers&#33;<lb/>  Will you not lend me your assistance that I may<lb/> give it perpetuity as such.  Oh&#33; let your powerful<lb/> influence supply my deficiencies&#44; your efficacious<lb/> word at home&#44; supplement my feeble teaching<lb/> in the Synagogue.  Let us join in hands in a<lb/> holy work&#44; in preserving Judaism from the inroads<lb/> of skepticism &#38;c.  &#40;This exhortation was continued<lb/> at some length&#41;</p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
