<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF3_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1888" source="" attested="yes">1888</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_2_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>On the 26th anniversary<lb/>
                of the 7th st Synagogue<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren<lb/> B An estimable lady&#45;friend said to me last year<lb/> about this season&#44; that I committed a grievous error.<lb/>  &#40;It was not the first&#44; nor can I hope it will be the last&#41;<lb/> She believed that had I followed then an almost uni&#45;<lb/>&#45;versal practice&#44; a great end would have been accom&#45;<lb/>&#45;plished.  It was then the 25th anniversary of<lb/> the dedication of this Synagogue.  Its celebration with<lb/> festive ceremonies on a week day&#44; would have drawn<lb/> here a throng&#44; and free&#45;will offerings would have poured<lb/> in sufficient to redeem&#44; partly at least&#44; our congre&#45;<lb/>&#45;gational indebtedness.  So my friend believed.<lb/>  I confess that the idea of holding a celebration did oc&#45;<lb/>&#45;cur to me.  But after having revolved in my mind<lb/> the pros and cons I dismissed it.  Not that my in&#45;<lb/>&#45;terest in the welfare of this sacred building had at all<lb/> lessened.  Nay&#58; to have been able to tell&#44; as a sister<lb/> congregation in New York told last week to an editor<lb/> of a city paper &#34;Our Synagogue is entirely unencumbered&#44;&#34;<lb/> would have afforded me veritable pleasure.  But I<lb/> asked myself&#58; ought I to use a means&#45;legitimate enough<lb/> yet intended as a subterfuge&#44; in order to induce the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>wealthy among my constituents&#44; to perform<lb/> a duty which I have set before them with repeated<lb/> emphasis countless times&#63;  And if I fail&#44; even despite<lb/> the addition of that means&#44; adopted&#44; will I not suffer the deepest<lb/> mortification&#63;  These reflections disturbed me&#44; and<lb/> I let the occasion pass by unnoticed.  But the<lb/> During twenty sixth year has arrived&#44; and with it an&#45;<lb/>&#45;xious thoughts have crowded my mind.  You<lb/> will pardon me for making allusions to events which<lb/> occasion will cause pains.  During the last twelve months<lb/> we have met with irreparable losses&#44; more numerous&#44;<lb/> I judge&#44; than we have sustained in the same space of<lb/> time&#44; since the erection of this minor sanctuary.<lb/>  I call those losses &#34;irreparable&#44;&#34; because in too many<lb/> instances the absence of the departed has not been<lb/> replaced supplied by their survivors&#44; and because some of<lb/> the survivors Is after having joined us&#44; withdrew<lb/> for having grown indifferent to the religion of<lb/> their deceased fathers.  We should fervently<lb/> pray that the coming fiscal year may prove<lb/> more prosperous&#44; but our supplications must be<lb/> supported by personal and most earnest efforts.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>In proportion as the difficulties to obtain success increase&#44;<lb/> so must our exertions become stronger.  When Israelites&#44;<lb/> married ones&#44; at all events&#44; would never have conceived the idea<lb/> of remaining unconnected with a congregation&#44; it might have<lb/> been comparatively easy to obtain secure an accession to our number.<lb/>  But now sentiments have undergone a lamentable stupendous change.<lb/>  With the creation of pseudo Jewish orders&#59; of independent<lb/> burial grounds cemeteries&#59; of public hall worship at the lowest<lb/> rate twice a year&#44; and kindred indecorous institutions&#44; the<lb/> impediments to our material progress augments constantly.<lb/>  I will illustrate my point.  Not long ago&#44; I was prompt&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed by sympathy to attend a funeral.  While at the house<lb/> of the bereaved&#44; I looked but saw no one who was likely<lb/> to officiate and either a word of consolation or supplication of prayer.  I made inquires&#44; about it&#44; and learnt<lb/> that the head of the family belonged to a wide&#45;extended<lb/> society which&#44; by the payment of a small quarterly assess&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment&#44; furnishes money relief in case of sickness&#44; hearse and<lb/> carriages at death&#44; ground for burial&#44; and a stipulated sum&#44;<lb/> if the seven days of mourning are rigidly kept.  Of course&#44; the<lb/> services of a minister are not engaged&#44; that part is left<lb/> to every one&#39;s free will and option.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>In the case which I have quoted cited&#44; the action might<lb/> have had extenuating causes circumstances in the humble position of the<lb/> party&#44; but how many who allow some of their earnings<lb/> to vanish into smoke with great ease&#44; as if they money were<lb/> valueless&#44; prefer that cheap society method of showing their<lb/> Judaism&#44; to contributing to the maintenance of a house<lb/> of God&#63;  It is owing to that fact that our Rab&#45;<lb/>&#45;bis in America have seriously discussed the question&#44; whe&#45;<lb/>&#45;ther measures should not be taken&#44; with the view<lb/> to protect the interest of established places of worship.<lb/>  It was proposed that an agreement be entered into<lb/> among ministerial officials to refuse any religious ceremony to<lb/> persons of our faith unattached to a Synagogue.  I thought<lb/> the proposition irreligious&#44; and dissented.  But I do<lb/> recognize the hardship.  I cannot deny that the pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;sent state of affairs militates against the welfare<lb/> of congregations.  And ours more than others is<lb/> exposed to dangers&#44; which we must avert by strenuously<lb/> strenuously endeavouring to fill our seats with occupants&#44;<lb/> even by waving rules&#44; and welcoming him that can give<lb/> only little&#44; as him who is able to give much<lb/> I will explain.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>We have never had a school directly connected<lb/> with our congregation.  Though the Education Society ema&#45;<lb/>&#45;nated from our midst&#44; was largely supported by our<lb/> members&#44; and to this day its leading spral spirit proceeds<lb/> from among us&#59; though the same may be precisely<lb/> be said of the Sunday Schools&#44; still we do not offer the<lb/> supporters of attendants at this sanctuary the inducement&#44; real or ima&#45;<lb/>ginary&#44; of having their children taught Hebrew and the<lb/> Bible gratuitously.  This festive is circumstance acts greatly to our injury.<lb/>  It is not enough that&#45;&#45;without daring to make a boast<lb/> of it&#45;&#45;I have personally contributed to the spread&#44; or&#44; rather if you will&#44;<lb/> to the preservation of a little knowledge of Hebrew in Phi&#45;<lb/>&#45;ladelphia&#44; more than all my colleagues.  It is not enough<lb/> that I have always placed my time at the disposal<lb/> of young and old&#44; who chose to learn our sacred literature&#44;<lb/> and have supplied schools with teachers of my own train&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing.  It is not enough that I have invited to my<lb/> Sunday and other days class all&#44; irrespective of congregational bias ties and af&#45;<lb/> &#45;forded asked no question ritual question in affording general instruction.  It is not enough that noise&#45;<lb/>&#45;lessly I have facilitated the acquirement of a familiarity<lb/> with Holy Writ in its ethical as well as well as its historical<lb/> contents&#44; by explanations conversationally given&#44; by lectures &#38; exhortations and in no instance with the expectation or desire for a compensation.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>No&#58; people must be assured that their sons and daugh&#45;<lb/>&#45;ters will gain such proficiency as it will enable<lb/> them to be confirmed with high honors.  For that<lb/> is the sum and substance of the instruction imparted<lb/> in most of the congregational schools.  Hebrew is not<lb/> the main object&#44; so true it is that its total abolition<lb/> in Temples is urgently advocated in the pulpit &#38; the press&#44; by reason of the dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;qualification of the young to join in the prayers re&#45;<lb/>&#45;cited in the language of the scriptures.  Ought we<lb/> then to try a new similar plan&#44; in order to draw adherents&#44; ought<lb/> we to open a daily school that we may rival sister con&#45;<lb/>&#45;gregations&#63;  Let me predict the effect of such a<lb/> resolve.  We would centralize an existing good&#44; for<lb/> fewer children would be likely to attend our classes&#44; after public<lb/> school hours in this locality&#44; than those who frequent<lb/> those in the afternoon the town <sic>town</sic> Hebrew free school.  I say nothing of<lb/> the expenditure that resolve determination would entail&#44; and which<lb/> we are ill&#45;prepared to assume.  But in my mind the<lb/> adoption of such a system would prove damaging to ano&#45;<lb/>&#45;ther institution.  Now under the influence&#44; which this<lb/> congregation has actively or indirectly exercised&#44; the Sunday<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Schools have grown immensely.  I am not given<lb/> to flattery&#44; but my hearers will bear me out&#44; when I<lb/> assert that the prestige lent by the women of this religious body and<lb/> of an similar religious body offshoot of our thereof&#44; has been largely effectively at work in<lb/> widening the sphere of our weekly institution.  Should<lb/> it be proclaimed that we have set up a separate one<lb/> on Sunday morning&#44; the continuance of that which has<lb/> remained very nigh a half a century&#44; would be <sic>imperilled</sic>&#44; it<lb/> would perhaps cease altogether.  But then it is con&#45;<lb/>&#45;tended that such an event would be is rather desirable.  Boys<lb/> and girls whose parents belong are affiliated to a congregation would be<lb/> sent there for a better instruction.  Admit it for the sake<lb/> of argument.  Yet&#44; I appeal to persons within reach of<lb/> my voice&#44; who are better qualified to answer the question.<lb/>  They must honestly say&#44; whether even in the up town<lb/> Sunday School&#44; a large number of the attendants are not<lb/> the offspring of coreligionists&#44; attached to no Jewish congre&#45;<lb/>&#45;gation&#44; whose homes have no distinguishing Jewish features&#44;<lb/> whose outdoor example is not calculated to benefit advance the<lb/> Jewish cause&#63;  You cry &#34;shame&#34; and so do I&#44; but will<lb/> you deprive those little ones of the benefit they derive from<lb/> some wholesome impressions in early life at a school&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>where Biblical history is taught impartially and<lb/> the Mosaic ordinances are expounded and recommended&#63;<lb/>  Have I ever asserted that the course of studies is comprehensive&#44; or that the present system is faultless&#63;  No&#58;<lb/> I would that the living word&#44; more than the catechism<lb/> should in every instance be the medium of religious<lb/> tuition.  I would that all who sit at the head of<lb/> the classes be conscientious followers of the tenets they<lb/> impart.  I would that we had fewer instructors and<lb/> better capacity employed in the working of the institution&#44;<lb/> so as to secure ensure progress&#44; punctuality and perfect disci&#45;<lb/>&#45;pline.  But happy as I shall be to devote<lb/> hereafter the whole morning of Sunday to either of<lb/> the two schools&#44; or to both as formerly&#44; aiding&#44; advising&#44;<lb/> lecturing&#44; I will never so offend the belief in which<lb/> I was raised&#44; and which I am bound to preach&#44;<lb/> never will I consent to limit my instruction to the<lb/> ethics of Holy Writ&#44; excluding the ceremonial<lb/> precepts and the testimonies of the Lord.  Do not<lb/> rail at mock me by saying that any how those precepts<lb/> and testimonies will go unheeded in the turmoil of a<lb/> busy life&#44; or through the ruling spirit of the time.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Shall I forswear my trust&#44; or counsel my colabours to disgrace<lb/> the memory of the pious ones who have directed the Sunday School&#44; by turning<lb/> it into an ethical culture&#44; or an agnostic school&#63;  The though is im&#45;<lb/>&#45;piety.  Let Radicalism or materialism do their worst.  We shall<lb/> instill obedience to the Lord and to Moses His servant agreeably to conservatism.  Understand&#44;<lb/> not once have I so demeaned myself as to ask any of the Sunday School my pupils<lb/> to attend worship here rather than elsewhere&#44; but if poor parents re&#45;<lb/>&#45;quested that their children who go there be privileged to be first called to the Law in<lb/> our Synagogue&#44; I have unhesitatingly consented.  Would that all<lb/> who received that favor had remembered it.  We might now<lb/> be stronger numerically and financially.  But it behooves<lb/> all who belong to it us&#44; to seek our increase by pleading in behalf of<lb/> this holy house with friend and acquaintances.  I beg<lb/> for it in the name of conservatism&#44; on this twenty sixth anniversary.  I hopefully<lb/> look to the directors of this ancient and respectable<lb/> congregation in Israel to infuse into it a fresher life&#44; energy<lb/> and consistency.  Oh may it last for ever&#33;  May it show<lb/> stand high as a beacon to the erring&#44; rescuing many from<lb/> sin&#44; causing multitudes to find the path of salvation<lb/> and eternal joy &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Those who are wise shall shine like the brightness<lb/> of the firmament&#44; and they who bring &#91;&#63;&#93; bring many to righteousness like the stars for ever &#38; ever<lb/> Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
