<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF3_10</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_10_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_10_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_10_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_10_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_10_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_10_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_10_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_10_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_10_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_10_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_10_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_10_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Lecture on Post&#45;biblical history<lb/>
                No. 10.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.<lb/></p>
            <p>In my last lecture on post&#45;Biblical history&#44; I made<lb/> you mentally witness the changes which took place<lb/> after the division of the empire left by Alexander&#44; as<lb/> those changes affected our people.  I did not say<lb/> then that persons who believe in prophecy read in the<lb/> book of Daniel the rise of the great Macedonian King&#44;<lb/> and the bloody wars among his lieutenants consequent upon<lb/> his untimely death.  I am well aware that a<lb/> prevailing disposition exists to discredit whatever<lb/> savors of the supernatural.  Accordingly&#44; with the usual<lb/> assurance of modern critics&#44; the visions of the righteous<lb/> exile in Chaldea are put down as declared pious frauds perpe&#45;<lb/>&#45;trated in later times to encourage Jews to fight a foreign power enemy.<lb/>  I scarcely need tell that I do not belong to the school which denies inspiration&#59; the capacity power to flig<lb/> fling aside the veil which that hides the future&#44; or which<lb/> allows it&#44; at best&#44; the ability to conceive lofty ideals<lb/> which that may or may not have a final realization.<lb/>  But though I reject as false the notion that scriptural<lb/> predictions are writings posterior to the events&#44; when they<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>claim to foreshow&#44; I refrained from quoting<lb/> Daniel&#44; because my present object is not to explain<lb/> prophecies&#44; but to acquaint my brethren with some of<lb/> the leading occurrences in the annals of their people.<lb/>  I may nevertheless&#44; with all propriety&#44; refer those who<lb/> share my views&#44; to the eleventh chapter of the book<lb/> of Daniel.  There they will see the inspired heaven&#45;drawn delineation<lb/> of what I have set forth in my former preceding lecture and of<lb/> what I shall further narrate.<lb/></p>
            <p>Ptolemy Soter&#44; in during whose reign Jews had pe settled<lb/> extensively in Egypt the country of the ancient Pharaohs&#44; left as his successor Ptolemy<lb/> Philadelphus.  The latter ruler showed always mani&#45;<lb/>&#45;fested a friendly spirit towards those whom his<lb/> father had entrusted with responsible positions.<lb/>  And Indeed if a legend which has enjoyed general crd cre&#45;<lb/>&#45;dence may be relied upon&#44; it is from his time that<lb/> the Greek translation of the Hebrew Bible dates.<lb/>  At his instance&#44; it was undertaken&#44; completed and<lb/> given a post of honor in the famous Alexandrias library.<lb/>  Be that so or not&#44; Philadelphus found in our<lb/> progenitors faithful and valuable subjects in Egypt&#44;<lb/> and wiling tributaries in Palestine.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>He needed both&#44; for he sustained a tremendous war<lb/> with Antiochus Theos&#44; who had possessed himself<lb/> of Syria.  After many a hard&#45;fought battle&#44; in which<lb/> Hebrews doubtless participated&#44; peace was concluded by<lb/> a wretched compromise.  Antiochus divorced his wife&#44;<lb/> to marry the daughter of Philadelphus.  But&#44; as it<lb/> mostly happens&#44; the vile expediency compromise resorted to proved of<lb/> no advantage benefit to either party.  For no sooner had<lb/> the last named King died&#44; than Antiochus chased away<lb/> the woman he had taken for expedience&#45;sake&#44; and reins&#45;<lb/>&#45;stated the one he had dismissed.  He fancied by<lb/> that to have made amends for past injuries.  Too late&#44; for<lb/> the rehabilitated wife fearing her husband&#39;s want of<lb/> character firmness&#44; poisoned him and set the crown on his oldest son. upon<lb/> the throne  Then with dire revengefulness&#44; fiendish vindictiveness&#44; she<lb/> caused her rival&#44; her infant child al and all the<lb/> Egyptians in her retinue to be strangled.<lb/></p>
            <p>Ptolemy Evergetes who mounted the throne after the<lb/> decease of Philadelphus&#44; was not long in avenging<lb/> the cruel death of his sister.  He rushed upon<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Syria with a formidable army&#44; killed the murderous<lb/> queen&#44; and&#44; had not a sedition in Egypt compelled<lb/> him to suspend his campaign&#44; he would have become<lb/> complete master of all the Syrian provinces.  He<lb/> carried away&#44; however&#44; an immense booty&#44; among which<lb/> there was two thousand and five hundred statues&#44; com&#45;<lb/>&#45;prising idols&#44; that belongeding originally to Egypt&#44; but were stolen<lb/> away by Cambyses when he conquered that country.<lb/></p>
            <p>Passing through Palestine&#44; the victor stopped halted at<lb/> Jerusalem&#44; and presented rich munificent gifts to the Temple.<lb/>  The high priest was then a man ill&#45;calculated to command<lb/> respect and to dignify his station.  Onias II&#44; being of<lb/> a grasping disposition&#44; thought that since Evergetes<lb/> had appeared favorable to the Jews&#44; he might take<lb/> advantage of the circumstance to enrich himself.  Accordingly&#58; For many years<lb/> he subtracted out of from the stipulated tribute&#44; a annual sum of<lb/> about twenty thousand Dollars. annually.  At last the king of<lb/> Egypt noticed a falling off in the amount due&#44; and<lb/> having learnt the cause&#44; sent a message to Jerusalem that<lb/> unless the deficit was made good&#44; he would proceed to<lb/> harsh measures.  And as an evidence of his earnest&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness&#44; he dispatched on of his trusty officers to enforce the<lb/> rule.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>All felt the seriousness of the position situation&#44; except<lb/> Onias.  He had no wish to disgorge the ill&#45;gotten<lb/> treasures.  His greediness would have exposed the<lb/> country to a fearful danger&#44; but for the promptness<lb/> and sagacity of one of his sister&#39;s sons&#44; called Joseph.<lb/>  This succeeded in well wonderfully in gaining the good&#45;will of the king&#39;s<lb/> officers.  Having sumptuously entertained him for some a<lb/> time&#44; Joseph promised that he would himself come personally<lb/> before Evergetes&#44; and assure the Sovereign of the honest<lb/> intentions of his countrymen.  Having He then collected<lb/> the necessary sums&#44; he departed for Egypt&#44; presented<lb/> his credentials as the ambassador of the Jewish nation&#44;<lb/> and met with a most gratifying reception.  Not<lb/> only did he appease anger and ward off hostilities&#44; but<lb/> he was chosen&#44; in preference to many competitors&#44; as royal<lb/> collector of tributes throughout a number of Eastern<lb/> provinces&#44; besides Palestine.<lb/></p>
            <p>Our ancestors under the domination of the Ptolemies&#44; might<lb/> have always longer enjoyed a degree of independence&#44; and the perfect<lb/> entire religious freedom&#44; of their if all the progeny of Lagus the founder of the dynasty had acted with uniform sentiments demeanour tolerance and kindly consideration.  We have seen that Soter had<lb/> atoned&#44; by exceptional kindness&#44; for the hard treatment<lb/> displayed he had practised at the outset.  His son Philadelphus<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>is said to represented described as having reverenced our books and honored our<lb/> sages&#44; and Evergetes allowed the Jews to follow un&#45;<lb/>&#45;molested their own laws&#44; and develop their own resources.<lb/>   But a change greatly to our injury was the ascension<lb/> of Ptolemy Philopater to the throne.  Whether<lb/> the name he bore was given him as a satire&#44; I am<lb/> unable to tell.  Certain it is that Philopater&#44; or<lb/> &#34;a lover of his father&#34; was a title unmerited by a son<lb/> whom historians charge with having seized the crown&#44;<lb/> by putting the parent who wore it to a sleep that<lb/> knows no waking.  That unnatural son who<lb/> joined to his heinous crime the sin of drunkenness and debauchery&#44; and<lb/> drunkenness&#44; shook off for once his usual unmanly indolence<lb/> on hearing that Palestine&#44; which had all along recognized his sovereign&#45;<lb/>&#45;ty was the <sic>covetted</sic> by a Antigonus&#44; a rival king of<lb/> Syria.  To prevent the invasion&#44; he mastered a<lb/> courage of which he was not deemed capable&#44; and<lb/> repelled the aggressor.  Our people&#44; obedient to their<lb/> oath&#44; remained loyal to the unworthy scion of the<lb/> Ptolemean stock.  Philopater remembered noted that&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>and when at Jerusalem&#44; he visited the Temple evinced his admiration of<lb/> its stateliness and grandeur and offered oblations and<lb/> donations.  But Philopater was irrepressibly as he was irrepressibly haughty as he was irremediably vicious.<lb/>  He would not suffer the keenest of men&#39;s religious feelings<lb/> to interpose obstacles to his will.  He insisted upon entering demanded to go into that<lb/> the Holy of Holies be opened for his inspection.  In vain was he told that even the high&#45;<lb/>priest was not allowed&#44; but on the day of atonement&#44; to<lb/> tread that sacred ground.  Entreaties availed nothing.  He ordered<lb/> his attendants to to open for him a way among the priests who<lb/> prayfully tried to prevent an hinder a sacrilegious entrance.  He had not set his<lb/> foot on the threshhold&#44; when he fell to the earth down prostrate as if<lb/> str struck by a lightning.  Very possibly&#44; the cries of<lb/> the people&#44; and the laments which resounded through the<lb/> awe&#45;inspiring edifice&#44; filled the parricide with an inde&#45;<lb/>&#45;finable terror&#44; and he was carried away as like a corpse.<lb/></p>
            <p>Philopater did not continue long make any stay in the city which had<lb/> witnessed his humiliation&#44; but neither did he forget<lb/> what had happened there.  He nurtured his resentment&#44;<lb/> and when once again in the capital of his kingdom&#44; he vented<lb/> the fulness of his anger on the Jews of Alexandria.<lb/>  It will be remembered that these were very numerous and<lb/> esteemed highly for their varied industries and learning.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>To cut them off and degrade them&#44; the wicked ruler<lb/> issued a decree that none who did not sacrifice to his<lb/> gods deities should be permitted to enter the royal palace.<lb/>  The edict meant more than it would now appear to us.  It implied<lb/> the disfranchising of Hebrews&#44; their disqualification to hold<lb/> public offices&#59; so that whereas they had been heretofore<lb/> ranked in among the first class of subjects&#44; like the Macedonians&#44; now<lb/> they were compelled to register their names as members of the<lb/> lowest grade of society.  To add injury to insult&#44; it<lb/> was ordered that those so enrolled&#44; should have bear an<lb/> ivy&#45;leaf stamped on their flesh with a hot iron&#44; as a<lb/> sign of their having been consecrated to Bacchus&#44; the god<lb/> which the dissolute king so greatly fondly loved.  A refusal<lb/> to submit would be punished with slavery and or death.<lb/>  The only means of safety was to voluntarily repudiate<lb/> the Mosaic code&#44; and become Grecianized altogether.<lb/>  The Jews so sorely pressed&#44; gave largely of their wealth<lb/> to bribe the corrupt officials of the corrupt monarch&#44;<lb/> and evade the infamous law&#44; The poorest had inevitably<lb/> to suffered degradation and the humiliating brand on their bodies.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>But to the honor of our ancestors the narrative<lb/> records&#44; that only three hundred out of three millions<lb/> were found to accept embrace <sic>apostacy</sic> as the condition for in order to<lb/> escapeing persecution.  And those three hundred dared not<lb/> come nigh their former coreligionists&#44; for a contact with<lb/> the renegades was shunned by the Jewish population like<lb/> pestilence.<lb/></p>
            <p>In my next lecture I will tell shall speak of the evils which the righteous threatened against our forefathers by<lb/> indignation of our forefathers against their reason of their righteous indignation towards recreant bre&#45; Jews<lb/> &#45;thren&#44; threatened&#44; and and I will tell also how by a divine interposition they<lb/> escaped an appalling misfortune.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
