<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF5_7</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_7_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_7_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_7_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_7_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_7_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_7_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_7_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_7_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_7_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_7_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_7_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_7_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Post Biblical<lb/>
                Babylonian Schools<lb/>
                50<lb/></p>
            
            <p>The Gaonic period is yet to come<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>The Jewish people have been unavoidably affected<lb/> by the social and political affairs of centuries in which<lb/> they have severally lived dwelt lived.  From the days that Babylon&#44;<lb/> which had conquered Assyria&#44; was in turn subjugated by<lb/> Persia&#44; till&#44; after having experienced many changes&#44; it came<lb/> again under the rule of a bold soldier&#44; who claimed descent<lb/> from Cyrus&#44; and established in Neo&#45;Persian empire&#44; up&#45;<lb/>wards of six centuries had glided away.  We have<lb/> seen how our religion was kept alive in those Eastern<lb/> regions&#44; during all such vicissitudes&#44; principally through the means<lb/> of our schools of learning.  We have also seen that the<lb/> degree of tolerance shown to practised towards our belief and its adherents&#44;<lb/> was proportionate to the liberality or illiberality of the<lb/> existing governments.  But aside from external &#38; internal wars that hurt us much&#44; a most decided opposition<lb/> to our faith and its followers was met in the part<lb/> of the Magi&#44; or priests of the Neo&#45;Persians&#44; called in<lb/> history &#34;Ghebers&#44;&#34; and in the Talmud Chelorin.  So<lb/> greatly was that hostility felt&#44; that a proverb ran<lb/> this&#58; &#34;Better be under any of the gentiles&#44; than under the Ghebers&#34;.<lb/>  Still&#44; the two immortal pupils of Judah the Prince had infused<lb/> the power to stand antagonism.  They tried that<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>that to kindle a love for the traditions of the<lb/> fathers&#44; and make render a diligent study thereof a the source<lb/> of Israel&#39;s inextinguishable existence.  Thus&#44; if unfavor&#45;<lb/>&#45;able circumstances caused the closing of a college<lb/> in one place&#44; another soon arose elsewhere.  During<lb/> the two centuries which succeeded the age of Rab<lb/> and Samuel&#44; Presidents of various Academies made their<lb/> seats of learning notable.  It would not accord<lb/> with my plan to speak of even some of the most<lb/> illustrious&#44; such as Abbay&#233; and Raba&#44; whose pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;cocious minds drew from their teacher this significant<lb/> remark&#58; &#34;from their first budding&#44; one can tell how<lb/> plants will grow&#34;.  My lectures of the series are<lb/> merely short sketches of the most striking events<lb/> in the history of our people and our literature.  I<lb/> am compelled therefore to suppress check a strong inclination<lb/> to refer to what was accomplished by a large number<lb/> of Babylonian expounders of the Mishna&#44; or Emoraim&#44;<lb/> and I pass on to dwell awhile on the life&#45;work<lb/> of one&#44; who is entitled&#44; above all others&#44; to our<lb/> consideration.  Ashi or Ash&#233; was his<lb/> name.  Providence raised him in time to save<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>a vast deal of learning which was threatened with might have to fallen into<lb/> is oblivion.  The same reason which had induced<lb/> Judah the Prince in Palestine to formulate and arrange<lb/> the text of the Mishnah&#44; led Ash&#233; to compile in<lb/> Babylon the discussions of the Ghemara.  He fore&#45;<lb/>&#45;saw two things&#44; namely&#44; the effect upon our people<lb/> of bloody wars disputes among Eastern and Western nations&#44;<lb/> and the result of a probable closing of colleges after<lb/> centuries of existence.  Already the difficulty of<lb/> keeping in mind Rabbinical teachings and scholastic debates<lb/> had become apparent&#44; even admitting that extensive<lb/> memoranda were taken down and privately preserved.  Persons justly<lb/> said&#58; &#34;As a generation goes&#44; it leaves to the next the legacy<lb/> of a decline of memory.&#34;  This inconvenience which could<lb/> scarcely be avoided&#44; since the accumulation of learning<lb/> made its retention very hard if not impossible&#44; would<lb/> certainly have increased with the sufferings attending a further<lb/> dispersion and persecution.  Ash&#233; concluded<lb/> to remedy the evil by putting to writing all that<lb/> could be collected gathered of the debates discussions and talks which had taken place<lb/> among the Sages&#44; even their legendary tales and their suggestive talks&#44;<lb/> from the time of Rab and Samuel to his own days.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Fortunately&#44; he was the fittest man to accomplish<lb/> that most difficult arduous task.  He had wealth and<lb/> therefore leisure&#59; he had a well cultured and clear<lb/> understanding and therefore method.  He had a<lb/> burning zeal and therefore determination.  Through<lb/> his powerful connections&#44; he could also command the<lb/> cooperation of many.  Besides his own high parent&#45;<lb/>&#45;age and riches which went very far to gain win adherents&#44; he enjoyed the acquaintance of<lb/> Yezdegerd&#44; one of the late kings of the Neo&#45;<lb/>Persians who reigned during the fifth century and who favored Hebrew knowledge.<lb/>  Ash&#233; found that the two main centres of learning&#45;&#45;<lb/>Sura and Nahardea&#45;&#45;had fallen into decay&#44; after<lb/> the death of their illustrious chiefs&#45;&#45;Rab and Samuel.<lb/>  Very possibly Sura was possibly his native city&#44; and therefore he resolved<lb/> that it should regain the literary elevation which<lb/> it had once reached.  The Talmud relates that<lb/> to carry out his object&#44; he himself superintended the<lb/> rebuilding of the college.  By day and night he<lb/> watched&#44; sleeping close by&#44; till the edifice tower&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed o above all others.  The glory which<lb/> Ash&#233; cast upon Sura was unprecedented.  Its Academy<lb/> was sought after by the most distinguished Israelites.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>There they congregated whenever a meeting of na&#45;<lb/>&#45;tional importance was called for&#44; and to honor<lb/> him who had spent his large means&#59; bestowed his best had devoted his<lb/> and most earnest thoughts&#44; and had devoted his best energies<lb/> on the revival of the place&#44; immortalized by Rab&#44; all the<lb/> chiefs of other schools gathered there once a year on<lb/> the occasion of the Exilarch&#45;festivities.  These were<lb/> held with great splendor in the month of Heshvan&#44;<lb/> after all the Fall Holidays&#44; out of respect for the<lb/> appointed Hebrew&#45;Governor of all Jews living<lb/> in We Eastern Asia.  I have&#44; once before alluded<lb/> to the office of Exilarch or Rosh Galutha&#44; and<lb/> I may have occasion hereafter to explain at some<lb/> length the history connected with that important responsible office.<lb/>  Now I simply wish to illustrate the influence<lb/> which a very eminent Rabbi deservedly rightly exercised.<lb/>  My purpose is not to glorify extoll Ash&#233; to the sky&#44; the detriment of any of our<lb/> Sages but to show the unremitting exertions of that one man on behalf<lb/> of our people and our literature.  The<lb/> Babylonian Talmud&#44; so termed to distinguish it<lb/> from the Palestinian&#44; or Jerusalem Talmud&#44; as it is this has been<lb/> inappropriately called&#44; is the result of that one mans scholar&#39;s<lb/> firm resolution.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>His decided will to prevent the loss of a learning<lb/> vast and unique&#44; gave us the colossal work<lb/> which has played a most important part in the<lb/> destiny of the outcasts of Judea.  Ash&#233; took<lb/> the text of the sixty treatises of the Mishnah&#44; as<lb/> formulated by Judah the Prince&#44; and&#44; aided no<lb/> doubt&#44; by very many associates and disciples&#44;<lb/> collected with religious scrupulousness every thing remark&#44;<lb/> that each section and each paragraph of those<lb/> treatises drew from the lips of different sages<lb/> at different times.  The task seems almost an<lb/> impossible one.  It surpassed beyond comparison that<lb/> of Judah the Prince&#44; for the Mishnah is represents merely<lb/> the dry law&#59; seldom relieved by does it chronicle keen remarks observations&#44; sharp<lb/> questioning&#44; lively answers&#59; &#91;&#63;&#93; those mental gymans&#45;<lb/>&#45;tics&#44; we so to say&#44; that which characterizes the Ghemara.<lb/>  Besides&#44; the Mishnah&#44; well written as it is&#44; invaluable<lb/> as it is&#44; was left incomplete by the exclusion of a<lb/> number of traditional rules&#44; embodied in what is known<lb/> as Baraittia&#44; or esoteric learning.  Ashe&#39;s under&#45;<lb/>&#45;taking was indeed herculean&#44; but then we must<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>consider that he gave to it nearly sixty<lb/> years of his life.  He had moreover furthermore at his dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;posal all the private records of former scholars&#59;<lb/> he went over his compilation a number of times&#59;<lb/> during two months in each year he submitted the extent of<lb/> his labors to an assembly of the learned&#44; and<lb/> notwithstanding all that&#44; he did not finish what<lb/> he had assumed.  It was concluded by his pupils and<lb/> successors in the course of seventy years after his the master&#39;s<lb/> death.  In order to form an idea of<lb/> the Babylonian Talmud&#44; the book must be studied<lb/> in the original&#44; whose general language is the populace Eastern Ara&#45;<lb/>language &#45;maic or Chaldaic&#44; mixed with a large number quantity<lb/> of Greek&#44; Latin and Persian words Hebraized Chaldaized in a<lb/> manner too provoking quite perplexing and often baffling recognition.<lb/>  No translation can convey an adequate notion of<lb/> that peculiar production of thousands of minds.  To<lb/> attempt a version is to fail&#44; nor is that all its &#91;&#63;&#93; preservation in a modern tongue&#44;<lb/> desirable&#59; for candor compels the confession<lb/> that matters not at all at all to our taste have been<lb/> na&#239;vely introduced&#44; and others unsuitable and<lb/> repulsive have also crept in.  The poet&#45;philosopher<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Judah Ha&#45;Levi&#44; acknowledges nearly as much about this regrettable<lb/> fact&#44; and writes that what is objectctionable<lb/> in the Talmud was introduced &#91;&#63;&#93; added in later times by pu&#45;<lb/>&#45;pils who&#44; perhaps did not weigh well what too zealous &#40;surely not too considerate&#41;<lb/> they admitted into the work and that what might should have been left out omitted but after all&#44;<lb/> it that does not affect the authority of the traditional<lb/> teachings it &#91;&#63;&#93; imparts.  To this opinion of the<lb/> immortal Spanish Jew&#44; we may agree&#44; and I add say with<lb/> justice&#44; that whosoever can enter into the laboratory&#44; as<lb/> it were&#44; of the Gemara&#44; will discover gems of the highest<lb/> value&#44; and will&#44; as he proceeds&#44; find that his intel&#45;<lb/>&#45;lect gains in keenness and in depth.  Whether<lb/> to all the 60 treatises of the Mishna&#44; a Gemara&#44; or<lb/> commentary&#44; was originally appended&#44; we do not know.<lb/>  While the Jerusalem Talmud has 40 treatises so ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;pounded&#44; the Babylonian has only 36; nevertheless<lb/> the latter forms a voluminous work four times&#44; at<lb/> least&#44; larger than the former.  It is more&#45;<lb/>&#45;over richer in legendary&#44; more readable and more<lb/> diversified&#44; even if&#44; at times&#44; its stalemates are<lb/> more startling.  But I shall not venture<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>upon any definition&#44; and I will content myself with<lb/> quoting one among the various anecdotes pointing<lb/> a moral&#44; as related of Rabbi Ashe&#39;s life.<lb/>  It was the day of his son&#39;s marriage.  A company<lb/> of friends and well wishers had come called to offer con&#45;<lb/>&#45;gratulations.  Merriment prevailed&#44; and it looked&#44;<lb/> at a one stage of the celebration&#44; as if the assembled<lb/> scholars were about to forget the dignity of their<lb/> characters.  At that Ash&#232; took a valuable cup and<lb/> broke it.  Laughter and jollity soon changed into<lb/> seriousness.  The host had put a check on that<lb/> high glee&#44; which not infrequently degenerates into<lb/> debasing intoxication.  Thus the illustrious<lb/> Sage of Sura meant to tell emphatically told his disciples that<lb/> moderation in pleasures becomes all&#44; but that it<lb/> is a virtue most needed to be cherished most by such as are looked<lb/> upon as spiritual guides of Congregations in Israel&#44;<lb/> in what country soever they may live.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
