<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF2_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1861" source="" attested="yes">1861</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_2_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For the 1st anniversary of the 7th st Synagogue<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>My Brethren&#33;  An idea which now&#45;a&#45;days prevails the human mind&#44;<lb/> but to which I shall never pay deference&#44; is&#44; that a minister of religion&#44;<lb/> must narrow down the range of his pulpit instruction&#44; within the<lb/> compass of doctrinal argumentations&#44; or of general remarks touching<lb/> ceremonial observances.  The tide of public vice&#44; may fearfully swell<lb/> around him&#59; dishonesty may sap the very existence of social relations&#44;<lb/> falsehood may disguise itself under the garb of truth&#44; besides under<lb/> that of bravery&#44; oppression under that of progress&#59; all the elements<lb/> of corruption may be at work to shelter the foundations of morality<lb/>&#45;&#45;which is God&#39;s holy law&#45;&#45;&#44; but the minister of religion must dare<lb/> not raise his voice to upbraid and to condemn.  If&#44; like an<lb/> Elijah or a Jeremiah&#44; he directs the shafts of his zealous indignation<lb/> against the powerful and the opulent&#44; he is decried&#44; as a zealot who<lb/> mistakes his vocation&#59; who abuses his mission.  So degenerate is the age<lb/> in which we live&#44; that it will tolerate the delivery of only that part of<lb/> Divine imparting&#44; which may not probably thoroughly expose to view the hollowness<lb/> of its ruling propensities.  He that should undauntedly strike with the<lb/> rod of his tongue the wicked&#45;&#45;be they highly or lowly stationed&#45;&#45;who violate<lb/> the eternal principles of justice&#44; is told in the language of the rebellious<lb/> people of yore &#34;Cease&#44; speak to us smooth things&#34;.  This I heard&#44; and<lb/> was abashed &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;for the word of the Lord&#44; against<lb/> violence and spoil&#44; hath become a reproach and a derision&#34;  Yet&#44; I<lb/> shall not forbear.  Obedient solely to the dictates of duty&#44; I will<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>continue to denounce sin&#44; wherever it exists.  And this day&#44; even this day&#44;<lb/> the anniversary of an occasion that might be deemed joyful&#44; calls upon will I<lb/> men to utter loud reprobations.  For&#44; how often shall I reiterate it&#59; that<lb/> God is not exalted by polished stones and carved timber&#63;  Are we to rejoice<lb/> over the rearing of a gorgeous structure&#44; which has failed to effect its object&#63;<lb/>  Did we not promise ourselves that its dedication to prayer&#44; would invite<lb/> thereto&#44; a numerous hosts of devoted hearts&#63;  Was it not generally hoped and<lb/> believed that to give the house of our Lord an independent stability&#44; the day<lb/> of Moses and David would be renewed&#44; when both men and women gloried to<lb/> munificently endow the contemplated Sanctuary&#63;  But how have those<lb/> reasonable expectations been verified&#63;  Hearken&#44; my Brethren&#44; and be<lb/> astounded.  It is the time in which&#44; Israel reckon the days that have<lb/> elapsed between their deliverance from physical thraldom&#44; and their<lb/> moral enfranchisement at Sinai.  At dusk a few individuals might<lb/> be seen wending their steps towards the consecrated spot.  They desire<lb/> to hold religious service as prescribed by their revered Sages&#44; but though<lb/> they tarry hither&#44; the legal number appears not.  Many Hebrews&#44;<lb/> whose mind has been engrossed in <sic>harrassing</sic> affairs&#44; are seeking<lb/> diversion at that hour&#44; not in a filial communion with their<lb/> Maker&#44; but at the gaming board&#44; or at some futile representations.<lb/>  You will then concur in my opinion&#44; that so far there is no cause<lb/> for gratulation.  But&#44; what&#63; of I say&#44; that possibly the<lb/></p> 
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>identical motive renders our convening within these courts at the entrance<lb/> of the Sabbath&#44; and at its conclusion exceedingly sparse&#63;  That in the<lb/> afternoon of the same hallowed day and of the festivals&#44; scarcely an<lb/> attendance equally slender can be commanded&#63;  What&#44; if I disclose<lb/> the fact&#44; that all efforts and contrivances to evoke a spirit of liberality<lb/> have proved utterly abortive&#59; that this edifice&#44; which should have been<lb/> enriched by unsolicited gifts&#44; and placed beyond eventualities&#44; is yet&#44; and may<lb/> well long remain&#44; the virtual possession of a few individuals&#63;  It<lb/> would be vain to attempt palliating the last glaring defeat on the<lb/> score of the deplorable events which have clogged the wheels of commerce<lb/> and dried up the springs of wealth&#59; for&#44; our temporal decline&#44;<lb/>&#45;&#45;unwarrantable as it may seem&#45;&#45;dates is coeval with the erection of this<lb/> Synagogue.  Would you then still consider its first anniversary<lb/> an occurrence which elicits exaltation&#63;  No &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> I will exclaim in the words of Scripture &#34;The thing I greatly feared hath<lb/> actually happened.&#34;  Arguing from the past I intimated in my dedicatory<lb/> sermon&#44; that the feelings of devotion then evinced for the progress of our<lb/> community&#44; would be evanescent&#44; that many of the Israelites who had<lb/> thronged those sacred walls to witness a stirring ceremony&#44; would<lb/> scarce revisit them.  My remarks were then animadverted on&#44; as<lb/> an ill&#45;timed rebuke&#44; but judge ye now&#44; my hearers&#44; whether it was<lb/> unjustifiable.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Short&#45;lived has indeed been the period&#44; during which&#44; the Sabbath&#45;morn&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing service was joined in by some infrequent <sic>worshippers</sic>.  It expired<lb/> almost at its birth&#59; hence has arisen our gradual decay.  They whose<lb/> affluence enabled them to strengthen the work of the Lord&#44; they who might<lb/> have been exhorted in the name of religion&#44; to exercise &#91;&#63;&#93; generosity&#44;<lb/> that this new undertaking might be becomingly sustained&#44; remained aloof.<lb/>  But why&#63;  Did they oppose the change&#44; which others had considered advisable&#63;<lb/>  Would they evince their disapproval&#44; by becoming affiliated to another of<lb/> our too numerous Synagogues&#63;  Not so.....They were earnestly engaged in<lb/> disobeying the will of their heavenly Father.  Alas&#33; that so <sic>wilful</sic> a<lb/> dereliction has at length kindled his wrath.  I see&#44; but to weep over&#44;<lb/> the chastisement it has provoked.  Much of the gold <sic>ammassed</sic> by<lb/> trampling on the laws of God&#44; a sudden fire has consumed.  Like the<lb/> Philestian Dagon&#44; the idolized Mammon has been felled by an<lb/> invisible hand.  At the uprising of an avenging Deity&#44; a train of ills has<lb/> passed over the land in which both righteous and wicked were involved.<lb/>  And shall I rejoice&#63;  Brethren&#33;  This&#44; our first anniversary&#44; would<lb/> have occasioned me sincere delight&#44; if it proclaimed our advancement<lb/> towards what is good and true.  If it pointed out new votaries<lb/> who have sworn allegiance to Judaism&#44; and abjured their imaginary<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>gods.  If it recorded that since this structure has been consecrated&#44;<lb/> the number of its <sic>worshippers</sic> has increased&#44; that its requirements<lb/> have been liberally supplied&#59; that a desire to uphold and exalt<lb/> the house of our God in the sight of the world is has been generally experienced&#44;<lb/> that the Congregation Mickve Israel&#44; gave the first impetus<lb/> to all righteous designs&#44; that their members have become conspicuous<lb/> for virtue&#44; for religious knowledge and piety&#44; but inasmuch as this day<lb/> instead of marking progression&#44; shows a retrogression&#44; I cannot be<lb/> induced to celebrate its recurrence with any degree of delight.<lb/>  Let those triumph who pride themselves in the attainment of a<lb/> fictitious aggrandizement&#44; I will rather lament a prevailing apathy<lb/> for real grandeur.  I will ask the delinquents to reflect on current<lb/> events&#44; and see their folly&#44; in being parsimonious with Almighty God.<lb/>  I will ask repeat to them&#44; what Haggim preached to his contemporaries.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Consider your ways&#34; Ye have sown much&#44; but<lb/> gathered little&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; &#34;and he that earneth&#44; hath earned<lb/> to put it into a bag full of holes &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Ye have<lb/> lived neither in accordance with the dictates of God&#44; nor with those of<lb/> reason.  Ye have sacrificed your best years&#44; your noblest instincts&#44;<lb/> prob perhaps your physical as well as spiritual health&#44; to<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p><sic>to</sic> the compassing of one sole object&#44; but when your imagined to have<lb/> laid a firm hold thereon&#44; it released itself from your grasp.  Such<lb/> is the result of avarice.  Verily your demeanour was irrational.  But unto the<lb/> faithful few&#44; who have so apportioned their time&#44; that their worldly<lb/> pursuits might not encroach on their duties to the Eternal&#44;<lb/> to those who have ever responded to the calls of religion and humanity<lb/> I will say&#44; &#34;despond not&#34; you are rich&#44; even if adverse circumstances<lb/> have deprived you of all your honest earnings&#59; for&#44; you bear the<lb/> conscience that the gold you have lost was not the wages of sin.<lb/>  You are rich&#44; because you have laid up treasures&#44; of which none can<lb/> rob you.  Like King Mumbaz&#44; so extolled by the Sages of the Talmud&#44;<lb/> you have scattered abroad&#44; whilst others gathered in&#44; yet you shall<lb/> reap the most copious harvest&#44; for thus&#44; it is written in the volumes<lb/> of heaven &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Say ye to the righteous&#44; that it will<lb/> be will well with them&#44; for they shall enjoy the fruit of their<lb/> deeds&#34;.  Let then all my hearers learn wisdom.  They have felt<lb/> the insecurity of terrestrial gain&#44; let them strive to obtain that which<lb/> can never fail them.  Let them employ their families and means to<lb/> benefit their soul&#59; let them store up the provision which will keep<lb/> it alive everlastingly.  Let them spurn self&#45;interest&#44; when<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>summoned to your stability to a sacred undertaking.  Let them give to<lb/> God what belongs to God&#44; the Sabbath&#45;day and the festivals.  Let them<lb/> seek recreation in assiduously watching at the portals of this minor Sanctuary&#44;<lb/> let them aspire to eminence by virtuous acts.  In fine let them<lb/> prove themselves sincere <sic>worshippers</sic> of their Creator&#44; for He alone<lb/> &#34;maketh poor&#44; and maketh rich&#44; bringeth low and lifteth up&#34;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; By such a<lb/> deportment the Synagogue we solemnly dedicated a year since&#44;<lb/> will assume the position which it ought originally to have received.<lb/>  The Omnipotent Being whose presence we have at that period invoked&#44; will<lb/> be praised therein by a multitude of devout hearts.  The<lb/> Congregation Mikve Israel will rank foremost among those<lb/> which amazingly increase throughout this country&#44; and at each<lb/> revolving mouth of Sivan&#44; we will glory together over our religious<lb/> advancement.  So may it henceforth2 be1 and ever more.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
