<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF7_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff7_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff7_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff7_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff7_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff7_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff7_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff7_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff7_2_4v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>5 pages on 2 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Funeral oration<lb/></p>
            <p>Did I believe that the eighteen years devoted to the development of the noblest<lb/> traits of human character&#44; were spent in vain&#44; I would now boldly<lb/> preach infidelity.  Did I believe that when the eyes of this<lb/> lovely maiden closed in death&#44; the shining virtues they reflected&#44;<lb/> were quenched forevermore&#44; I would hurl imprecations towards<lb/> the vaults of heaven.  But because I feel&#59; because I<lb/> know that death has no steel so sharp that can pierce<lb/> the soul&#44; that the sword it unsheathes sunders a bond of union&#44;<lb/> but destroys naught&#59; because reason and revelation point<lb/> alike to a life immortal&#44; therefore do I ask of you&#44;<lb/> parents of this goodly being that has left the earth&#44; to rise<lb/> above your poignant grief&#44; to reflect and be comforted.<lb/>  The excellencies which formed the chief adornments of your<lb/> dear Cornelia&#44; and wherein you so much delighted&#44; are<lb/> the results emanations of a righteous training.  Yours is the<lb/> merit of having amply supplied her with the means<lb/> of earning beatitude.  Those sentiments of earnest piety&#44;<lb/> those feelings of exquisite kindliness&#44; which lead the spirit<lb/> upwards&#59; those acquirements&#44; which befit the mind for<lb/> the contemplation of Truth&#44; she drew from the sources&#44; which<lb/> you lay open in her terrestrial path.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Could the mist veil which the body raises between us and the<lb/> domains of heavenly intelligences&#44; be flung aside&#44; you would rejoice&#44;<lb/> even now at this hour&#44; over the scene you beheld.  A daughter<lb/> seated in glory&#44; upon a throne which her parents prepared.<lb/>  To it a slight comfort to be certain that we have purchased<lb/> bliss for those we love&#63;&#44; that we ourselves have arrayed them in spotless<lb/> garments&#44; as ministering angels&#63;  Oh&#33; that this knowledge<lb/> would reanimate your drooping spirits.  Oh&#33; that you could<lb/> look upon the separation with serenity&#44; sustained by<lb/> the conviction that the better have our feelings been culti&#45;<lb/>&#45;vated&#44; and our minds instructed&#44; the greater will be<lb/> the enjoyments of our existence beyond the grave.<lb/>  But while the dead lie unburied&#44; the hearts of the bereaved<lb/> are closed against the consolatory words of friends&#58; so have<lb/> our Sages suggested in one of their pity sentences.  And I do<lb/> feel how inadequate <sic>our</sic> my appliances to heal a<lb/> wound so deep as that through which you bleed.<lb/>  Verily&#44; I have schooled myself to look upon death without<lb/> dismay&#44; to recognize in it simply a mere transition from the<lb/> perishable to the imperishable.  I have striven to gain a<lb/> steadfast belief that through it alone will the noblest aspi&#45;<lb/>&#45;rings of our souls find a realization.  Yet&#44; death&#44; presented<lb/> in this form fills me with anguish.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Many and frequent had been the premonitions that the<lb/> spirit of Cornelia Hart sought to become disenthralled from the<lb/> body.  But she was so going&#45;&#45;blooming with grace&#45;&#45;so<lb/> filially good&#45;&#45;the joy of her home&#45;&#45;so profoundly religious the<lb/> model of her coevals&#45;&#45;.  To lose her was to create a void in a<lb/> vast social circle&#44; and the prayers of a whole community held<lb/> back for a time the steps of the dreaded messenger.  How<lb/> fervent the invocations supplications for her recovery in the house of God&#44;<lb/> she delighted to visit&#33;  When her lips offered poured forth praises&#44; that<lb/> she had once more been&#44; apparently&#44; restored to health&#44; our silent<lb/> but deep&#45;felt thanks mingled with those utterances.  The<lb/> The anxious watching which knew no rest&#44; while she struggled with<lb/> a treacherous illness&#44; had at length ceased.  This house&#44; over&#45;<lb/>&#45;spread with gloom&#44; because she was on the eve of departure&#44;<lb/> shone again with the radiance of happiness&#44; at their continued<lb/> presence.  The misgivings of the past&#44; had given room to the<lb/> bright glowing prospects of the future.  Last Thursday night&#44; I<lb/> saw her.  She whirled around at the blithesome sound of &#91;&#63;&#93; music&#44;<lb/> with all the buoyancy of her nature.  I saw her again<lb/> upon the Sabbath.  She offered her devotions to God.  On<lb/> the third day she had left us never to return.  Sudden&#44; stunning&#44; was the blow.  We all were shocked.<lb/>  But you loving parents&#44; you cannot reason yourselves yet into<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>a tranquil acceptance of a divine ordination.  The<lb/> thought that the head which bent to receive your blessing&#44;<lb/> lies motionless in this coffin&#59; that the eyes which spark&#45;<lb/>&#45;led with pleasure at the tokens of your affection have sunken<lb/> in their ob orbits&#59; the thought that you will look for Cornelia&#44;<lb/> and her place will be vacant&#44; harrows up your feelings&#44; particularly<lb/> your minds.  But you possess an inherent power which<lb/> will uplift you above despondency.  Faith the sacred faith of Israel&#44; stirring in your breasts<lb/> will prove a soothing balm.  You will still discover cause for<lb/> thanks even in this sad trial you we all deplore.  You will rejoice that<lb/> for eighteen years&#44; you sowed the seeds of goodness&#44; and this lovely child<lb/> reaped happiness&#59; that while qualifying her for heaven&#44; by teaching precept<lb/> and example&#44; you chose her walks on earth in pleasant places&#59;<lb/> that when the hour struck which was destined to changed the mortal into<lb/> the immortal struck she leaped from your fond arms embraces to the bosom<lb/> of eternity&#44; without suffering the pangs of the separation.<lb/>  Comfort ye&#44; comfort ye thus&#44; my friends&#44; O son and daughters<lb/> who have outlived their dear Cornelia.  Speak of her as of<lb/> a Cherub&#44; hovering round the throne of God.  Say that as harmony<lb/> is not destroyed&#44; because the instrument through which it reached<lb/> us has been broken&#44; nor are symmetry and order obliterated from the<lb/> soul&#44; because the edifice which represented them has been demolished&#44; so<lb/> the grave will not consume the precious traits of her character will not&#44; cannot be but that<lb/> effaced&#44; because the body moulders in the grave.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>those ripe the virtues she practised<lb/> they now form&#44; her reward&#44; her crown&#44; her bliss.  Dear<lb/> relatives of a sainted daughter&#33;  Picture her that died in the liveliest delineaments&#44; but supply<lb/> the void which her celestial heavenly transformation has occasioned.<lb/>  They will not long refuse to be comforted&#44; whose children<lb/> and grand&#45;children entwine themselves around their hearts<lb/> with exquisite tenderness&#59; yes&#58; they in whose surviving progeny<lb/> religion and morality find a bright illustration&#44; will<lb/> cast off sorrow&#44; and grow peacefully calm.<lb/></p>
            <p>Almighty God&#33; stay and support of the afflicted&#33;<lb/>  <sic>Dipell</sic> grief from these mourners.  Restore gladness to<lb/> this habitation of kindness.  Let the memory of her<lb/> who enhanced its joys&#44; remain within it fresh and redolent as an<lb/> ever green&#44; breathing around a celestial perfume&#44; celestial the fragrances of Eden.<lb/>  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
