<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF2_7</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_7_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_7_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_7_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_7_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_7_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_7_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_7_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_7_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_7_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_7_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_7_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_7_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_7_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_7_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_7_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_7_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>18</p>
            
            <p>An explanatory lecture on Ki Tab&#243;h<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Cursed be he that confirmeth not the words of this<lb/> law to do them&#34;  My Brethren&#33;  It is not<lb/> improbable that in your intercourse with your fel&#45;<lb/>&#45;low&#45;men of a different creed&#44; you may have heard<lb/> it declared asserted&#44; that the followers of the Mosaic code<lb/> incessantly expose themselves to a curse pronounced<lb/> therein.  Misconstruing the passage from2<lb/> the section of the day&#44; which1 I have just quoted&#44;<lb/> they argue that as human nature is fallible&#44; no<lb/> one&#44; however heedful of his duties he may be&#44; can<lb/> execute carry out all the numerous injunctions which the<lb/> religion of Israel prescribes&#59; and that the result of<lb/> his neglect&#44; while he still adheres to the Sinaic<lb/> law&#44; will be visited upon him by a divine imprecation.<lb/>  But two cogent reasons gainsay refute their position.<lb/>  The first must be obvious to whomsoever will com&#45;<lb/>&#45;pare the original with the authorized version in the<lb/> vernacular&#44; for&#44; not the discharge of all the be&#45;<lb/>&#45;hests of God&#44; has been demanded in that sentence<lb/> of Holy Writ&#44; in order to avert the celestial denun&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciation.  It may have served the purpose<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>of the English translators to surreptitiously insert<lb/> the word &#34;All&#34;&#44; but the text does not warrant<lb/> the license &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Cursed be he who<lb/> confimreth not the word of this law&#44; and not all<lb/> the words&#44; we find written by the inspired messenger<lb/> of the Eternal making special reference to what has been spoken of in that chapter&#44; as I will hereafter explain.  Besides&#44; how absurd it is to<lb/> harbour the idea that according to the Jewish faith&#44;<lb/> temporal &#38; spiritual happiness depends upon the performance<lb/> of every enactment of the Mosaic legislation&#33;<lb/>
                Who knows not that the sacred volumes contain<lb/> many directions&#44; which an individual may never have<lb/> occasion to <sic>fulfil</sic>&#63;  As for instance&#59; the raising of<lb/> a battlement in the roof of a new dwelling.<lb/>  The assistance which must be tendered to save one&#39;s<lb/> neighbour&#39;s property.  The freedom to be granted<lb/> to the dam&#44; that is stirring on her unfledged young.<lb/>  The offering of a sacrifice at the expiration of the<lb/> term of a Nazarite.  The presentation of five shekels<lb/> of silver to the priest for the redemption of a first&#45;<lb/>born son&#59; and various others&#44; especially such that as<lb/> are connected with the possession of an estate in the<lb/> land of the patriarchs.  Would it not there&#45;<lb/>&#45;fore be exceedingly preposterous nay insulting to Divine justice to assume that<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>the non&#45;performance of duties consequent on for&#45;<lb/>&#45;tuious circumstances&#44; are is accounted a sin&#44; and<lb/> threatened with a malediction&#63;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Far be wickedness from God&#44; and iniquity from the<lb/> Almighty&#34;&#33;  But the second<lb/> reason which we may advance to overthrow the<lb/> argument of our religious opponents&#44; though it<lb/> does not suggest itself at the first blush to the mind<lb/> of every reader&#44; is nevertheless very forcible and conclusive.<lb/>  However&#44; in order To render it clear to your under&#45;<lb/>&#45;standing&#44; my beloved hearers&#33; I need premise sending a few<lb/> remarks.  Whenever the Scriptures prescribes<lb/> certain rules&#59; likewise&#44; whenever they exhort to<lb/> goodly actions&#44; or denounce evil doings&#44; they do not speak<lb/> not in the abstract&#44; but almost invariably they address<lb/> the nation at large.  At times in the plural<lb/> termination&#44; but oftener in the singular&#44; either<lb/> in the masculine or <sic>femminine</sic> gender.  This<lb/> fast scarcely requires any proof&#44; for almost nearly<lb/> every page of the Bible teems with corroborative<lb/> examples&#59; but in order to be perfectly explicit&#44;<lb/>
                
                <pb n="5"/>
                I will say&#44; by way of elucidation&#44; that when we read<lb/> in the lesson of this Sabbath the following words of<lb/> Moses &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Thou hast avouched<lb/> the Eternal this day&#44; to be thy God&#44;&#34; no one could have<lb/> construed interpreted them as if applying directed to a single individual&#44;<lb/> because the grammatical construction would denote it&#44;<lb/> but as an address to the collective body of the Hebrews.<lb/>  And verily True&#58; this is not a distinctive feature in<lb/> the sacred pages volumes tongue&#59; but it is a form adopted as<lb/> well in other languages.  Yet But what in the<lb/> latter is simply a conventional expression&#44; carries<lb/> therewith it in Holy Writ a weighty import recall signification.  The<lb/> Rabbins have signified pointed it out unto us by their well<lb/> known maxim &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Israel are a<lb/> guarantee one for the other&#44;&#34; that is&#44; they consti&#45;<lb/>&#45;tute an association community of divinely favored beings&#44; whose<lb/> singleness of purpose must characterize all their<lb/> actions.  Hence it behooves every member thereof<lb/> to watch over the intact preservation of the standard<lb/> given for their guide&#44; and to adjudge decree by judicial sentence a commensu&#45;<lb/>&#45;rate punishment for any decoration from the same.<lb/>  The omission of this duty would entail upon the<lb/> nation a calamity&#44; called forth by the perpetrator<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>of the same offense.  Thus it is frequently recorded in<lb/> the book of Judges&#44; that the relapse of some<lb/> among our ancestors to idolatrous practices&#44; con&#45;<lb/>&#45;signed whole tribes to foreign subjugation.<lb/></p>
            <p>And in the twenty second chapter of Joshua&#44; we are<lb/> unequivocally taught by a peculiar event narrated<lb/> there&#44; that the dereliction misdoing of few&#44; when left un&#45;<lb/>&#45;rebuked&#44; is visited upon the many who have heed&#45;<lb/>&#45;lessly suffered it to be committed.  The<lb/> Israelites who dwelt on the eastern side of the Jordan<lb/> had erected a very lofty altar&#44; as a token of<lb/> their alliance with the rest of their distant bre&#45;<lb/>&#45;thren.  This act of national fidelity was mis&#45;<lb/>&#45;construed into an unwarrantable separation from the<lb/> common faith&#44; and a delegation&#44; headed by the<lb/> righteous Phineas was commissioned to remonstrate.<lb/>  To eschew the civil war which was impending&#44; the<lb/> deputation sent&#44; held the following language &#34;What<lb/> is this trespass that ye have committed against<lb/> the God of Israel&#63;  Is the iniquity of Peor too<lb/> little for us&#44; from which we are not cleansed even<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>to this day&#44; and for which on whose account there was a plague in<lb/> the Congregation of the Lord&#63;  That ye must turn away<lb/> this day from following the Lord&#44; seeing that ye re&#45;<lb/>&#45;bel to day against the Lord&#44; and to morrow He will<lb/> be wroth with the whole Congregation of Israel&#33;  &#34;And<lb/> in the same strain they continued to speak&#44; evincing<lb/> by their eg eager appeal that they sought to<lb/> aver celestial <sic>chastiment</sic> not alone from the<lb/> supposed transgressors but from the entire people<lb/> of the Hebrews.  But though the<lb/> axiom aphorism of our sages above cited&#44; is very evidently<lb/> founded upon biblical ground&#44; still it cannot always<lb/> be carried into effect&#44; for however watchful vigilant watchful a<lb/> nation may be over for the maintenance of its laws&#44; ne&#45; still<lb/> &#45;vertheless its eyes are its judicial vigilance justice is is not ubiquitous.  It cannot&#44;<lb/> indeed it should not spy what individuals may<lb/> secretly do in contravention with opposition to the dictates of God&#59;<lb/>  consequently it cannot be accountable for hidden<lb/> crimes.  Wherefore it is written &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;The secret things belong<lb/> to the Eternal our God&#44; but those things which<lb/> are revealed belong unto us and to our children for<lb/> ever&#44; that we may execute all the words of this law&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>And this is precisely what the passage by our<lb/> which our opponents would fain misrepresent Judaism us&#44; tends aims<lb/> to communicate impart.  The whole paragraph in<lb/> which it occurs alludes solely to the committal of sins backslidings<lb/> that might easily evade detection&#44; and consequent&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly elude human justice.  He for instance&#44; who<lb/> conceals in his bosom the idol to which he has<lb/> become a votary&#59; he who in the administration of<lb/> his office&#44; stealthily receives the corruptive gift&#44;<lb/> might perchance deem themselves beyond divine<lb/> retribution&#44; as they are without the beyond out of reach of a tem&#45;<lb/>&#45;poral chastisement.  Because they form an<lb/> integral part of a community&#44; in whose weal they<lb/> participate&#44; they might be hardened in delinquency crime&#44;<lb/> so long as it their culpable act can remain concealed beneath an<lb/> impenetrable veil.  Therefore has the word of<lb/> God come to warn the hypocritical sinner.<lb/>  Think not&#44; it tells him&#44; think not that thou wilt<lb/> conjointly share in the <sic>welbeing</sic> of the nation&#44; for&#44;<lb/> if thy inequities are such that they cannot exclude thee<lb/> from its fruition&#44; He that scrutinizes searches even the inmost re&#45; of human<lb/> &#45;condite deeds thoughts&#44; will cut thee off from the partici&#45;<lb/>&#45;pation of the blessings He grants vouchsafes grants unto his people.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Then And as it is even more lucidly expressed&#44; in the<lb/> next Parasha&#59; &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;the anger of the Lord and his<lb/> jealousy shall kindle against thee&#44; and He shall<lb/> blot out thy name from under the heavens.&#34;<lb/>  Thou alone shalt suffer the penalty of thy trespasses&#44;<lb/> and the house of Israel shall be declared innocent<lb/> in the presence of their God.  Ponder&#44; my dear<lb/> Brethren&#44; on the whole context&#44; and judge for your&#45;<lb/>&#45;selves.  It is written  You have read that the Levites were en&#45; bid<lb/> &#45;joined to turn their faces towards mount Ebal&#44;<lb/> and loudly imprecate call down evil on the individual who<lb/> became guilty of certain nefarious wicked deeds.  But<lb/> at this&#44; a question must naturally suggest itself to your minds<lb/> why have those crimes been made a special object<lb/> of execration&#44; while immediately after&#44; curses are<lb/> pronounced against the general abandonment of<lb/> religion&#63;...Because&#44; I answer&#44; the latter concern<lb/> the whole nation&#44; whereas the former affect the<lb/> single individual&#44; hence the people gave their<lb/> full assent&#44; by saying&#59; Amen&#44; purposing to signify&#44;<lb/> that as it was not in their power to bring hidden<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>sins before a terrestrial tribunal&#44; they committed<lb/> to God the inflicting of a condign punishment.<lb/>  This reply&#44; which I consider correct&#44; will&#44; my dear Bre&#45;<lb/>&#45;thren&#33; will unfold the exact meaning of the sentence<lb/> under discussion.  The inspired legislator in&#45;<lb/>&#45;structed the family of Levy who had become the de&#45;<lb/>&#45;positaries and tutors instructors of the law of God&#44; that their<lb/> entrance into the land of promise should be signa&#45;<lb/>&#45;lized by an act of inspiring impressive solemnity.  They<lb/> should gather the tribes around the ark of the<lb/> testimony&#44; and with their countenances upturned<lb/> towards a stony rock&#44; the emblem of aridity and<lb/> waste&#44; they should utter a malediction against<lb/> the false and the unfaithful&#44; who covertly<lb/> violated the national constitution&#44; and yet claimed<lb/> the immunities and the protection it granted.  and its protection.<lb/>  Those servants of the Almighty were directed to threaten<lb/> with the inexorable sentence of an Omniscient Judge&#44;<lb/> the man&#44; who conceived to that they might evade His searching<lb/> eye&#44; as he had eluded human justice&#59; therefore<lb/> after having enumerated certain heinous crimes&#44;<lb/> that might remain for ever enshrouded in dark&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness&#44; they were ordered thus to conclude &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>&#34;Cursed be he that comfirmeth not the words<lb/> of this law&#34; not the entire law promulgated by<lb/> the son of Amram&#44; but in a more respect restricted<lb/> sense&#44; the ordinances to which the preceding<lb/> eleven verses have special reference.<lb/></p>
            <p>I could&#44; my dear Brethren&#33; further demonstrate that<lb/> my interpretation is authorized both by the genius<lb/> of the Hebrew language&#44; and by the commentaries<lb/> of learned authors&#44; but the reasons I have advanced&#44;<lb/> will at all events suffice to convince an Israelite&#44;<lb/> that the adversaries of Judaism have failed to<lb/> comprehend the text&#44; that they have tampered with<lb/> it by their <sic>wilful</sic> interpolation&#44; and that&#44; as<lb/> they are wont&#44; they have taken a detached pas&#45;<lb/>sage and grounded thereon argumentations void of<lb/> strength and truth.  But you my fellow&#45;<lb/>believers&#44; neither need nor demand any proof of<lb/> the abiding love of God for the progeny of Jacob.<lb/>  You remember that the heathen sorcerer&#44; who was<lb/> commissioned to harm Israel our progenitors&#44; was bid not to curse<lb/> the people whom the Most High has blessed.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>You will ever bear in mind that like a father<lb/> who corrects the son he cherishes&#44; so does the<lb/> Lord rebuke those whom He desires to improve&#44;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> May He grant that by the strokes of his chasten&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing rod we may be restored to religion&#44; to virtue&#44;<lb/> and thence to temporal and spiritual happiness.<lb/>  Amen<lb/></p>
            
            <p>This lecture was corrected&#44; and altered in the course<lb/> of being delivered&#44; and and address was added<lb/> at the end to a Bar Mitzvah.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
