<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF19_7</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_7_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_7_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_7_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_7_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_7_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_7_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_7_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_7_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_7_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_7_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_7_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_7_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>An appeal on behalf<lb/>
                of the Hebrew School<lb/>
                &#38; the Sunday School<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  The Hebrew word &#34;Nefesh&#44;&#34; which in its primitive<lb/> sense means breath&#44; has received in the Bible a more extended<lb/> signification.  We find it variously used for the words&#44; persons&#44;<lb/> disposition&#44; life&#44; and very often for the immortal spirit<lb/> breathed within us.  Now&#58; I need scarcely remark that<lb/> when we are told&#44; &#34;Abram took &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> we are to understand by it that he brought along with him<lb/> to Canaan&#44; the persons procured for servants in the city of Haran.<lb/>  But the Rabbis&#44; availing themselves of the circumstance that the<lb/> term &#34;Nefesh&#34; has been used to mean the soul&#44; employ it here<lb/> in that sense.  They say&#58; The parents of our race&#44; when in&#45;<lb/>&#45;creasing the number of their attendants&#44; increased also that<lb/> of believers in the One God.  Abraham made proselytes among<lb/> the men&#59; Sarah among the women.  Hence the Hebrew<lb/> text writes that they took with them &#34;the souls they had made<lb/> in Haran&#34; For&#44; a human being to whom the knowledge of<lb/> religion has been imparted&#44; may be considered as if newly<lb/> created.<lb/></p>
            <p>Dear hearers&#33;  The lesson which our Sages intended to convey&#44; needs requires<lb/> some explanation&#44; for&#44; it is not exactly what would at first<lb/> appear.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>We might be led to infer from it the obligation of making<lb/> converts to our belief&#59; of persuading gentiles to embrace Judaism<lb/> that they may be saved.  Such a construction conclusion&#44; would&#44; however&#44;<lb/> be faulty&#59; for&#44; we have been advised to follow an entirely<lb/> different course.  The righteous son of Terah felt inspired<lb/> to wean away from idolatry many who became brutalized<lb/> through its worship.  We&#44; have been recommended to dissuade<lb/> the adherents of creeds which are not demoralising from adopt&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing that which is binding alone upon the seed of Abraham.<lb/>  All can be saved&#44; who act honestly&#44; according to the light<lb/> received&#59; but the salvation of Israel proceeds solely from<lb/> their obedience to the ordinances of Sinai.  This is the ruling<lb/> principle by which we must be guided.  What rule lesson<lb/> did then our teachers of old wish to inculcate by their fi&#45;<lb/>&#45;gurative application of the sentence above quoted&#63;  I will<lb/> let them answer &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Whoever trains his neighbor&#39;s offspring in the law&#44; acts as<lb/> meritoriously as if had given them existence.&#34;  All&#44; my dear<lb/> brethren&#33; are disciples of Abraham who&#44; by personal exertions<lb/> or by material aid endeavour that our children be religiously<lb/> educated.  The founder of our people&#44; disseminated truth among<lb/> those who had no knowledge of a universal God&#59;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>We must prevent the law which has established to preserve that truth&#44; from<lb/> being lost among the chosen of God.  Without repelling the<lb/> gentile&#44; whom from a deep sincerity conviction seeks admission into the<lb/> household of Israel&#44; we should bend all our energies our activity energies towards<lb/> keeping in the fold&#44; the members of our national family.<lb/>  This stringent duty&#44; we can accomplish by the supporting of<lb/> two institutions in our midst.  One I call Judaism&#39;s vitalizing<lb/> blood&#59; the other its sinewy strength.  Where our children<lb/> daily learn the language&#44; which serves as a mystic bond<lb/> among our scattered race&#44; there I recognize a leading power&#59;<lb/> where they are infused with love for their people by a weekly<lb/> reunion&#44; by oral instruction and hymns breathing faith&#44; there<lb/> I acknowledge a cooperative agency in the performance of a<lb/> holy undertaking.<lb/></p>
            <p>The Hebrew School under the auspices of the Hebrew Education<lb/> Society has been resuscitated.  Not long since its staunchest<lb/> advocates feared it was sinking beyond recovery.  From an<lb/> attendance of pupils ranging about the a hundred&#44; scarcely<lb/> two scores could be reckoned.  But this circumstance&#44;<lb/> which for a time dampened the hopes of its unwavering friends&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>soon stirred up their minds to the devising of a plan&#44; that<lb/> would deliver our Hebrew School from extinction.  Wisely<lb/> it was concocted&#44; and successfully it has been brought<lb/> to completion.  No more does the list of scholars con&#45;<lb/>&#45;tain some too poor to pay for tuition&#44; and others whose<lb/> parents are taxed for their instruction.  Each of the<lb/> numerous attendants acquires the learning essential to<lb/> our national interest&#44; non receives it for a stipulated<lb/> sum.  All&#45;praise to the indefatigable few&#44; whose unflagging energies zeal<lb/> restored to us a decaying movement&#44; unimpaired.  They<lb/> signally deserve the blessing of Abraham&#39;s God.  Like<lb/> our fathers they endeavoured to went about fearless of obstacles strove to gaining adherents to a soul&#45;sa&#45;<lb/>&#45;ving principle.  But their co&#45;workers who pledged their<lb/> Jewish feelings for its perpetuation&#44; are likewise entitled to<lb/> the heartfelt thanks of every reflecting Israelite.  Yes&#58; grate&#45;<lb/>&#45;fully we confess that your contributions&#44; my fellow believers&#33; the to uphold the<lb/> knowledge of the Hebrew language&#44; are streams of<lb/> fresh life to our religion.  Never must we be made<lb/> again to contemplate despondingly the future of the<lb/> institution which a Judah Touro philanthropically endowed&#44;<lb/> and God&#45;fearing men established&#44; and upheld cherished with<lb/> fostering care.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>But in order to provide against the recurrence of any such an<lb/> exigency emergency&#44; you must go about <sic>proselytising</sic>; not among<lb/> our Nazarene neighbors&#44; but among our own brethren&#44; con&#45;<lb/>&#45;verting them to the belief that on the cultivation of the sacred<lb/> tongue&#44; mainly depends the stability of the faith of our<lb/> patriarch in the land&#44; and that the organization which&#44;<lb/> during a quarter of a century&#44; has promoted that study<lb/> must be popularized&#59; that it is but an act of justice<lb/> may&#44; of self&#45;preservation to give it aid and countenance&#44; se&#45;<lb/>&#45;curity and enlargement.<lb/></p>
            <p>But if I assign to the school of Hebrew learning the <sic>fore</sic> fore&#45;<lb/> rank&#44; I do not undervalue the importance of its adjunct&#45;&#45;<lb/>the Hebrew Sunday School.  This institution has also ob&#45;<lb/>&#45;viously improved through the manifestation of a lively<lb/> interest manifested on the part of our community.  Some who<lb/> either allowed their little ones to idle away the first morning<lb/> of the week&#44; or suffered them to go where their hearts became<lb/> imbued with a strange creed&#44; appreciating the efforts of<lb/> our sisters&#44;&#45;&#45;the directresses&#45;&#45;reward them by the presence of with<lb/> their children&#39;s attendance presence presence.  And they do consider it an ample compensa&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion&#59; for&#44; they aspire to nothing higher than to be instrumental<lb/> in <sic>rivetting</sic> the chain of our national union by a frequent gathering<lb/> of our youths.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>But the self&#45;imposed duty grows more onerous in pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;portion to its extension.  When all the attendants at<lb/> the Sunday&#45;school could be comfortably held in a single<lb/> room&#44; it was comparatively easy to supervise their instruction&#59;<lb/> now that they occupy three spacious rooms&#59; and might<lb/> readily fill up a <sic>forth</sic> one&#44; difficulties present themselves<lb/> constantly.  The number of teachers falls short of is very unequal to<lb/> the demand&#44; while the irregularity of some&#44; and the oc&#45;<lb/>&#45;casional withdrawing of others by causes beyond their control&#44;<lb/> add to the <sic>embarassment</sic> of the superintendents.  And<lb/> yet&#44; I verily think that the task could be rendered easy&#44;<lb/> as it certainly is most praise&#45;worthy.  Many among<lb/> those within hearing of my voice&#44; gladly cooperate in carrying<lb/> out the pious intention of Rebecca Gratz&#44; the founder<lb/> of that institution.  But I presume venture to conceive more that zealous colaborers<lb/> might still more be raised in this audience by making an<lb/> appeal.  I have&#44; of my own accord&#44; assumed<lb/> to be the mouth piece of the <sic>superintendants</sic> of our Sunday<lb/> school.<lb/></p>
            <p>Brothers and sisters&#44; descendants of Abraham and Sarah&#33;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>It is in your power also to win precious souls.<lb/>  None who can in the least contribute towards compassing<lb/> that object ought to hold back.  None should argue that<lb/> the instruction you can impart is of little account&#59; or the time<lb/> devoted to it is too short.  Small is the seed imbedded<lb/> in the earth&#59; who does not hope it will <sic>yeild</sic> exuberantly&#63;<lb/>  Can you&#44; can I any of us foresee what beneficial effect a question<lb/> fittingly answered&#44; or a gentle advise may produce in a<lb/> tender mind&#63;  You may never become aware of the power<lb/> you exercised&#44; nevertheless you may have implanted the germ<lb/> of righteousness&#44; which will bear fruit through life&#59; and the all&#45;seeing God&#44; will accept your endeavour as an offering of sweet savor.<lb/>  All can be useful&#44; who determine to serve the Lord with the<lb/> faculties and material means He has granted.  But another<lb/> evident advantage will flow from teaching at the Sunday School.<lb/>  It will benefit The instructors will profit not less than the instructed&#59;<lb/> for&#44; we can best sharpen our intellects against the rough<lb/> minds of our untutored pupils.  A Rabbi has stated&#44; that<lb/> what he had learnt through his scholars&#44; surpassed what<lb/> had been communicated to him by his preceptors and by<lb/> his erudite companions associates&#59; and our own experience agrees bears out<lb/> with that assertion.  We Being compelled to explain a<lb/> lesson&#44; we will be set thinking on points which had never<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>before attracted our attention.  We will search &#38; strive to solve dif&#45;<lb/>ficulties&#44; and thus gain a knowledge of which we might<lb/> otherwise have remained in ignorance.  And now&#44;<lb/> on behalf of the directresses and their coadjutors&#44; who weekly<lb/> labor to retain in the sacred fold the offspring of Abraham&#44;<lb/> I request my hearers to join in the national cause&#59; to see<lb/> that the Hebrew Sunday School of Philadelphia supplied<lb/> with a sufficient number of intelligent teachers&#44; regularly devoting their<lb/> time&#44; and &#91;&#63;&#93; entering coming in to the in the places to which hundreds of our dear ones flock<lb/> to hear words of truth religion and truth.<lb/></p>
            <p>And may heavenly blessings rest upon all who con&#45;<lb/>&#45;tribute to effect the design of god&#44; as expressed to His prophet.<lb/>  &#34;As for me this is my covenant with them saith the Lord&#58; my spirit<lb/> which is I put upon thee&#44; and my words which I put<lb/> in thy mouth&#44; shall not depart from thy mouth&#44; nor<lb/> from the mouth of thy children&#44; nor from the mouth<lb/> of thy children&#39;s children from henceforth and for<lb/> ever&#34; Amen<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
