<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF8_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1888-01" source="" attested="yes">1888</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_1_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>About the proposed Publication Society&#47;88<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>No sensible person who has given the subject a thought&#44;<lb/> will <del>doubt</del> undervalue the importance of books.  They are&#44; to a great<lb/> extent&#44; the mould in which the minds are fashioned.<lb/> <del>with a sense of humiliation I acknowledge that we Israeli&#45;</del> Let us exercise exceeding care in thy selection of those which such as combine<lb/> <del>&#45;tes</del> instruction with diversion looking for their them in a pure channel.  With a sense of humiliation I<lb/> acknowledge that we Israelites do not <del>have</del> possess&#44; by any means&#44;<lb/> a supply equal to the want.  Only last Sunday morn&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing&#44; speaking to some interesting girls and boys in<lb/> the our Southern Sunday School&#44; I felt how very much<lb/> simply written volumes&#44; concisely and attractively prepared volumes on topics<lb/> on ancient relative to post&#45;biblical history&#44; on to ancient Rabbinical<lb/> schools in Palestine and Babylon&#44; or in Europe during<lb/> the middle ages&#44; and even on works of fiction from a<lb/> Jewish stand point would improve the young&#44; whom<lb/> we are eager to retain in our fold.  We must<lb/> widely unavoidably differ widely from our Christian neighbors on doctrinal<lb/> points&#44; but we cannot withhold the merit due to<lb/> their restless activity.  They do make ample provisions for<lb/> facilitating an understanding among youths a comprehension of the history and<lb/> tenets of the Church.  Their societies issue tracts&#44; pam&#45;<lb/>&#45;phlets and books innumerable&#44; and at a figure<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>so low as to be within reach of the humblest.  We&#44; on the contrary&#44; seem<lb/> to have intended even our Bible and prayer books simply for<lb/> the rich&#44; and as regard other words&#44; so defficient we<lb/> are of them that obliged to unavoidably forced to fall back on those which ema&#45;<lb/>&#45;nate from non&#45;Israelites we frequently find ourselves the we are considerably perplexed.  The directors of our schools<lb/> find deem it essential to examine in advance what is hand&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed for a perusal to our pupils for perusal&#44; lest in reading&#44; the<lb/> minds be poisoned against the ancestral faith.<lb/>  Mr Notwithstanding this careful needful revision&#44; more than once an intelligent child called my attention<lb/> to some passage in books borrowed from our libraries&#44;<lb/> whose anti Jewish character had been a inadvertently<lb/> passed over by the superintendent.  A Hebrew<lb/> Publication Society of our men&#44; is therefore a great desideratum.<lb/>  In 1845 one was started in Philadelphia&#44; and<lb/> it reproduced some excellent little volumes.  Among<lb/> others Caleb4 Asher&#44; the 3Perez Family&#44; Hebrew2 tales<lb/> from the writings of our Sages&#44; the Path of Israel&#44;<lb/> or Scriptural stories.  Only one dollar was the yearly<lb/> subscription&#44; but my people always sympa&#45;<lb/>&#45;thetic when the claims of the needy and the sick<lb/> are brought to their notice&#44; do not show&#45;&#45;as a rule&#45;&#45;the same<lb/> readiness to help when whatever food for to healthily nourish the mind is asked.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>So&#44; like the Maimonides college in later years&#44; so our<lb/> publication society came to an untimely end.  It was<lb/> resurrected in New York in 1873 and it gave the English<lb/> speaking Israelites of America&#44; at a higher rate than<lb/> that of Philadelphia&#44; translations of German writings<lb/> on history&#44; theology and philosophy&#44; all good productions&#44; in the<lb/> main&#59; but perhaps too scholarly for the general<lb/> lay reader.  Whether that circumstance hastened<lb/> its the extinction of that society&#44; or whether the same lamentable lukewarm&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness about the mental culture of our youths&#44; chilled it<lb/> to death&#44; I am not prepared to say.  Now a<lb/> fresh attempt is made to breathe into a new existence<lb/> an organization&#44; the need of which I unequivocally admit.<lb/>  A few weeks ago&#44; I officially received information of to<lb/> that project effect&#44; and was requested to state the time which<lb/> I deemed most opportune for holding a general meet&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing to that effect in the interest of the project.  I answered forthwith that I would attend<lb/> it on any day that which the committee determined upon.<lb/>  For though the complexion of that said committee was not<lb/> altogether to my liking&#44; I have made it a rule of<lb/> life to suppress my inclinations to the advantage<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>of Israel&#44; and the promotion of peace.  It is<lb/> scarcely becoming in me to speak so&#44; but as was probably the<lb/> question of a contemplated publication society and its utility now announced in our Jewish organs&#44; will<lb/> be discussed was probably raise discussions in pulpit and press&#44; and as I may<lb/> possibly be quoted as having tacitly promised the scheme<lb/> my cooperation&#44; I may explain be allowed to &#91;&#63;&#93; define my position.  I may tell why this week&#44; when<lb/> asked to take an active part towards its furtherance&#44;<lb/> I refused.  The reason is identical to that which<lb/> led me to oppose at a conference&#44; and this Synagogue two years since the acceptance of a plan for a Union<lb/> of all Sabbaths and Sunday Schools in America.  The<lb/> projector had expressed opinions hostile to Judaism&#44;<lb/> as transmitted by our prophets and Sages.  He wished<lb/> for a union&#44; but only for such as might &#34;command<lb/> the support of all parties &#40;Alas&#33; for the name&#41; among Jews&#44;&#34; by eliminating<lb/> from our text books every vestige of the practices that<lb/> have vitalized our belief.  Passover to be descanted upon&#44;<lb/> minus the obligation of the unleavened bread&#59; Pente&#45;<lb/>&#45;cost without the admission of a Divine revelation&#44; confirmation of a well authenticated tradition&#44;<lb/> a feast of Tabernacles&#44; destitute of the ignoring its symbolic books objects at<lb/> Synagogue and beyond its ever hallowed sacred courts.<lb/>  Never could I become a party to such a Union.<lb/>  An abstract Judaism&#45;&#45;call it an ethical Judaism&#45;&#45;pure and<lb/> simple &#40;&#45;&#45;so goes the cant of the day&#45;&#45;&#41;&#44; is in my mind unhalf Jewish&#59; at no time&#44; under no<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>circumstance will I subscribe to it.  Early<lb/> education training&#44; deep convictions&#44; and an all conquer&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing sense of the duties attending my vocation&#44; impel<lb/> me to discountenance whatever I deem hurtful however remotely to<lb/> the cause which I am bound to advance.  So unalterable<lb/> are my views in that respect&#44; that a few days ago I<lb/> regretfully denied my assistance to a literary under&#45;<lb/>&#45;taking of my colleagues among the &#34;Jewish Minister&#39;s<lb/> Association&#44; of which I am a member.  &#34;The Jewish Home Prayer Book&#44;&#34; which<lb/> they have published&#44; presents no objection in itself.  The pur&#45;<lb/>&#45;pose of its compilation is laudable&#44; and it may<lb/> serve a blissful end.  Israelites in whose home<lb/> the voice of prayer was never raised&#44; may&#44; through<lb/> that varied English formulary&#44; hallow their family hearth<lb/> by hymns and supplications to God.  But as the<lb/> book is intended to substitute take the place of time&#45;honored prayers<lb/> in the accepted ritual&#44; and to let the vernacular supplant<lb/> the national Hebrew&#44; which I love&#44; I declined to<lb/> publicly recommend it to my brethren by a<lb/> written approval.  Now could I&#44; influenced<lb/> by the sentiments which have become my second<lb/> nature&#44; work&#44; as requested&#44; for a literary scheme<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>which has an unholy origin&#44; and a profane tendency&#63;<lb/>  It was so represented as follows recently by the lecturer on an<lb/> anti&#45;Jewish pulpit in Philadelphia &#34;The American Jewish<lb/> Publication Society&#44; about to be organized in this<lb/> city has emanated from the Sunday&#45;service&#44; and<lb/> it is the Sunday service that has supplied us<lb/> with the manuscript for a Sunday service ritual<lb/> and which will give us a ritual next season.&#34;<lb/>  Such is then to be the first ripe fruit of a poison&#45;<lb/>&#45;ous branch engrafted on our soil from the West.<lb/>  Such is the outcome of an unrighteous resolve to<lb/> uproot the tree of life that God has planted.<lb/>  May my hand wither&#44; and my tongue cleave to the<lb/> roof of my mouth&#44; ere I shall write or speak<lb/> on behalf of that scheme.  He that boasted of<lb/> unprecedented achievements from his Sunday&#39;s under&#45;<lb/>&#45;taking&#44; may have been rewarded with an ap&#45;<lb/>proving smile when he said that he would not<lb/> go now and &#34;matriculate in Sims Orthodox Theologic&#45;<lb/>&#45;al Seminary&#34; but neither will one who hopefully<lb/> looks for the overthrow of an audacious reform to the future graduates of scholars who will matriculate in a theological<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>seminary for the overthrow of audacious re&#45;<lb/>&#45;form cast his influence&#45;&#45;however slight&#45;&#45;on<lb/> the side of the new dispensation hatched in Cincin&#45;<lb/>&#45;nati and called &#34;American Judaism.&#34;  I do recognize<lb/> the importance of books of a literature specifically ours&#44; and deprecate a severity great &#91;&#63;&#93; dearth<lb/> of them it in the interest of our youths&#44; but the very thought<lb/> of my unintentionally encouraging the producing or<lb/> the sale of such books as will injure conservatism&#44; is ab&#45;<lb/>&#45;horrent.  Doubtless&#44; some who figure upon the<lb/> committee which that I have replied to enter&#44; will<lb/> watch against the artfulness of the anti&#45;Jewish and<lb/> egotists&#44; but their vigilance will avail little against in the face of<lb/> the artfulness of the a majority bent on carrying out<lb/> their purposes.  Was it not declared unequivocally in an<lb/> official report just published in the American Israelite that the<lb/> champion of Radical Reform in the pulpit of<lb/> the R. I. Cong. will be in the van to attack fossil<lb/> orthodoxy&#63;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;I am for peace&#44; and but when I speak for it<lb/> they are for war&#34;  My answer this week concluded thus&#58;<lb/> I have arrived at an age a stage of life&#44; unfit disqualifying me perhaps from deliberately<lb/> measuring swords with youths&#44; but while the capacity to bear literary<lb/> arms is left me&#44; I will stand up in the defense of what I consider true.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Will you aid me O Bar Mitzvah<lb/> &#40;Here follows an address to two B. M.&#41;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
