<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF2_8</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_8_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_8_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_8_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_8_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_8_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_8_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_8_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_8_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_8_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_8_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_8_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_8_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_8_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_8_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_8_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_8_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>On Penitence<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>In the year that King Uzziah died&#44; a<lb/> vision of <sic>unequalled</sic> grandeur opened before<lb/> the mind of a prophet.  Isaiah saw<lb/> the Almighty Being&#44; whose word quickened<lb/> the world into existence&#44; enthroned upon<lb/> high.  Angels hovered around and above.  With<lb/> faces veiled&#44; with outstretched wings soaring<lb/> aloft&#44; they invited one another to sing the<lb/> praises of their Omnipotent Maker.  The<lb/> vaults of heaven rung again with the voices<lb/> of Sef Seraphim.  They cried &#34;Holy&#44; holy&#44;<lb/> holy is the Lord of hosts&#44; the whole earth<lb/> is full of His glory&#34;.  We&#44; my<lb/> Brethren&#44; often repeat that sublime praise hymn.<lb/>  We even signify by the upraisinglifting of our body&#44;<lb/> that if we could join cast off what is ma&#45;<lb/>&#45;terial in our nature&#44; we would join the saintly<lb/> chorus.  Yet&#44; I feel I will not be charged<lb/> with arrogance&#44; when I say&#44; that we do not<lb/> quite understand what we utter.  Its meaning&#44;<lb/> simple as it may seem&#44; remained unknown to me<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>also till the approaching of this great season&#44;<lb/> when I remembered that the object of the peni&#45;<lb/>&#45;tential days is to draw every one born in Israel<lb/> nearer to God by a life of righteousness.  I<lb/> asked myself&#58; &#34;How can unrighteousness offend<lb/> God&#44; since He is infinite in power.&#34;&#63;  But I dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;covered the answer in that sentence&#44; which<lb/> the son of Amoz heard from the unstained lips<lb/> of archangels.  &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;The whole earth<lb/> is full of His glory&#34;.  In the Temple above<lb/> where sainted creatures tender Him worship&#44; all<lb/> speaks of the Majesty of the Universal King&#44;<lb/> but upon earth God&#39;s glory is manifested in<lb/> the impress of His boundless goodness.  Where&#45;<lb/>&#45;ver we turn&#44; evidences are given that a spirit<lb/> all&#45;mighty and beneficent dwells among us.<lb/>  Every blade of grass announces that truth.  Every<lb/> ripple mark tells that the Eternal cares for the<lb/> world in which mortal beings we move.  But for<lb/> whom did the earth&#44; abounding replete with blessings&#44;<lb/> issue from the plastic hand of God&#63;  For whom&#44;<lb/> but for man&#63;&#45;&#45;the crowning work of creation.<lb/>  Of him it may correctly be said &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>&#34;the last brought forth&#44; but the first in<lb/> thought&#63;  In man&#44; gifted with reason&#44; is<lb/> therefore the glory of the Lord to be most bril&#45;<lb/>&#45;liantly manifested&#59; in man made only &#34;a little<lb/> lower than angels&#34; would the Source of all per&#45;<lb/>&#45;fection be mirrored.  Man&#39;s heart is a<lb/> throne and veritable sanctuary to the Supreme.<lb/>  There an altar can be raised with an unquench&#45;<lb/>&#45;able fire&#45;&#45;the fire of love for whatever is en&#45;<lb/>&#45;nobling of human nature.  But the heart<lb/> tainted with wickedness dishonors God.  The<lb/> man habitually corrupt&#44; insults offends his Maker.<lb/>  He is guilty of ingratitude&#44; for he perverts<lb/> the splendid faculties which the Creator im&#45;<lb/>&#45;planted within into our minds&#44; and by the exercise<lb/> of which He would be sanctified on earth as<lb/> He is in heaven.  Whereas the Deity wished to<lb/> abide within us&#44; as in a Tabernacle&#44; the impious<lb/> reject the association of the best of Friends&#44; to by following<lb/> destructive sin causes the departure of the best of friends.  It is a maxim of our<lb/> Sages&#44; that human arrogance forces the Lord to<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>to abandon the earth &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> and commenting on the passage of Isaiah&#44; that<lb/> I chose for my text&#44; they Rabbis write &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Man should not dare to tread the<lb/> ground with a proud gait&#44;&#34; for the whole earth is<lb/> full of the Glory of God.  But&#44; while admit&#45;<lb/>&#45;ting&#44; my brethren&#44; that pride is despicable&#44; even<lb/> when engendered by the possession of rare qualities<lb/> of the mind&#45;&#45;though in reality the wise will<lb/> always be humble&#45;&#45;&#44; agreeing with the moralist<lb/> of old that haughtiness is one of the seven abo&#45;<lb/>&#45;minations of God&#44; still&#44; indulgence in it may<lb/> prove comparatively harmless.  But false&#45;<lb/>hood&#44; dishonesty&#44; practices debasing to degrading our<lb/> nature&#44; are crimes that grievously offend our<lb/> beneficent Maker.  Picture to yourself&#44; one<lb/> who makes profession of friendship.  He vows declares<lb/> that he is ready to serve you disinterestedly.<lb/>  He pledges his word that no circumstance will<lb/> alter the feelings he pretends to entertain.<lb/>  He thus succeeds in gaining your confidence&#44;<lb/> only to abuse it&#44; and deliver you to sorrowful<lb/> disappointments.  Should he be ever so bright<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>and intelligent&#44; ought he to be considered an<lb/> object through whose agency the Creator of<lb/> intellectual man will receive glorification&#63;<lb/>  And what sanctification can the Almighty derive<lb/> from him who is smart&#44; in holding unjust<lb/> balances&#44; and fraudulent weights&#63;  From the<lb/> vile vulgars who assert that all is allowed in<lb/> business&#44; from him who looks upon his fellow&#45;mor&#45;<lb/>tals not as the means by which legitimately to<lb/> earn a mutual subsistence&#44; but as the unsuspecting<lb/> dolts&#44; through whose credulity he may fill his cof&#45;<lb/>&#45;fers&#63; with gold&#63;  And the dissolute&#44; who rake their<lb/> brains to discover whom they may corrupt&#44; in order to<lb/> effect their wanton purposes&#59; they who study not<lb/> the elevation of God&#39;s creatures but their degradation&#59;<lb/> those who insinuate themselves into your favor&#44; to<lb/> steal a treasure you value most&#45;&#45;the spotless<lb/> character of the inmates of your household&#44; are<lb/> they the fitting representatives of God&#39;s glory which<lb/> fills the earth&#63;  No&#58; as well might we say that<lb/> the drunkard&#44; who issues forth at midnight from the den of vice&#44; reeling and staggering as he attempts<lb/> to walk&#44; is the right exponent of man&#39;s dignity&#59;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>or that the gambler and the idler who waste<lb/> away their means and their energies are types of human industry.<lb/>  The spirit that pervades the Universe can be<lb/> hallowed only by virtue.  The sons of Eli stood<lb/> the highest among the Hebrew nation.  They were<lb/> judges and priests.  But of them the Scriptures<lb/> narrate that they sin they committed was exceed&#45;<lb/>&#45;ingly great before the Lord&#44; because their immoral<lb/> conduct brought God into contempt.  Therefore<lb/> the heavenly messenger who foretold the too indulg&#45;<lb/>&#45;ent father the doom of his family&#44; said in the name<lb/> of the Omnipotent Master &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Those who honor me&#44; will I honor&#44; but those who<lb/> despise me&#44; shall be treated as vile&#34;.  The man<lb/> polluted with social vices may offer at the altar&#59; may linger in the house where<lb/> the Law is expounded&#44; but as he profanes that altar and that<lb/> Law by his demeanour in the outer world&#44; he will<lb/> have injured most seriously the belief he claims<lb/> to profess.  They who watch him closely&#44; will<lb/> be apt to make religion a synonym with hypocrisy&#44;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;; and the name of God will be continued.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>An inconsistency so <sic>frought</sic> with mischief&#44; but occasionally<lb/> met in every age&#44; is denounced in a withering reproach<lb/> by the inspired Asaph.  The Psalmist ironically<lb/> styles Israelites who <sic>practise</sic> it &#34;the saints who have<lb/> made a covenant with the Lord by a bloody sacrifice&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#45;&#45;as if the external observances of the faith&#44; were<lb/> a license for the commission of social wrongs.  And<lb/> after having condemned the culpable acts of which<lb/> the false are guilty&#44; the writer concludes &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;Whosoever offers thanks giving<lb/> glorifies Me&#44; and to him that sets his way<lb/> aright&#44; will I show the salvation of God.&#34;<lb/>  That sentence&#44; I am impelled by a sense of duty<lb/> to quote for your edification&#44; fellow Israelites&#44; at<lb/> this most solemn period of our year.  Virtue<lb/> is the ladder through which we may scale<lb/> the heavens and be eternized&#44; for its exercise<lb/> is a hymn to the God whose glory fills the<lb/> earth.  And what is obligatory on all<lb/> intelligent beings is doubly incumbent on ourselves&#44;<lb/> the people of God&#44; for us the prophet addressed<lb/> when he said &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;I have told it&#44; I have said saved&#44; I have proclaimed<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>it when there was no stranger among you&#59; and<lb/> ye are my witnesses that I am God.&#34;  The<lb/> same voice that thundered at Sinai &#34;Remember the<lb/> Sabbath&#45;day to keep it holy&#34; commanded never to<lb/> steal&#44; never to swear falsely&#44; never to do our<lb/> neighbor harm with our hands or with our tongue.<lb/>  Whether it be Moses&#44; urging us to be holy&#44; as the<lb/> Lord is holy&#44; whether it be latter prophets&#44; declar&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing that we have been chosen as heralds of<lb/> God&#39;s goodness&#44; or whether the uninspired but<lb/> wise teachers of old instruct us&#44; the object is<lb/> one and the same &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Virtue must be joined with<lb/> piety&#44; but religion is an empty word&#44; where mo&#45;<lb/>&#45;rality is left in abeyance.&#34;  We who have been<lb/> thus early taught&#44; must exercise exceeding<lb/> caution&#44; lest any of our actions occasion &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>  I need not mention a fact widely known<lb/> a derivative from rectitude by any of our race&#44;<lb/> is visited upon the whole Jewish community.<lb/>  Unjust as this may appear&#44; it is nevertheless<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>a heavenly ordination.  We were brought nearer<lb/> to the source of truth&#59; we should exhibit a vaster<lb/> amount of godliness.  But while I rejoice that<lb/> as a body we compare favorably with our gentile<lb/> neighbors&#45;&#45;certainly so as a rule in our domestic relations&#45;&#45;&#44;<lb/> candor impels me to add that&#44; at times&#44; events<lb/> are chronicled to the dishonor of Him whose<lb/> glory fills the earth.  Brethren.  If a<lb/> Jew ever declares within your hearing that deception<lb/> <sic>practised</sic> upon non&#45;Israelites is no <sic>offence</sic> against<lb/> God&#44; correct the fatal heresy &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  He who lowers the name the Almighty&#44;<lb/> will not enjoy felicity hereafter.  He has tried<lb/> to show the inefficacy of the heavenly Law&#44; and<lb/> He will be rejected by Him who promulgated the Law.<lb/>  But&#44; my dear companions in this journey of life&#44;<lb/> you all know well how liable we all are to swerve from the<lb/> path of righteousness&#44; how&#44; swayed by circumstances&#44;<lb/> we are carried away into a whirlpool of sin.<lb/>  God in His infinite mercy has therefore set<lb/> apart the present season&#44; for the revision of<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>the past.  He desired that Israel&#44; in whom<lb/> we would be signally glorified&#44; &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44;<lb/> examine at stated periods&#44; whether the charge<lb/> entrusted at Horeb has been faithfully carried out.  To<lb/> prevent a complete corruption of the people designed<lb/> to perpetuate eternal truths&#44; God annually pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;pares for them waters of purification.  Let us&#44;<lb/> my brethren&#44; hail the Divine fountain&#44; which<lb/> flows for our sake&#44; and seek there our spiritual<lb/> regeneration.  Weak are we in purpose&#44; but the<lb/> Omnipotent will strengthen our righteous resolves&#44; if we<lb/> lean upon Him.  Let us beseech our Father that our<lb/> sense of right may be henceforth keenly felt&#59; that<lb/> it may be unmistakably visible in our intercourse<lb/> with all mortals&#44; and that a reward of a pure life<lb/> be blessings sweet and lasting upon our families&#44;<lb/> our Congregation and upon the house of Israel&#44;<lb/> even until all of us after a long series of nobly<lb/> spent years here below&#44; may join above the<lb/> heavenly chorus of Seraphim that sing&#58;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Holy&#44; holy&#44; holy is the Lord of hosts&#44;<lb/> the whole earth is full of His glory&#34;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
