<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF3_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_1_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Historical lecture<lb/>
                1st<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  A well&#45;founded boast of the age in which<lb/> we live is that the history of olden times&#44; has claimed<lb/> the serious attention of scholars.  Jews and Christians have go alike<lb/> gone deeply searched dived into that subject&#44; and they have laid before the<lb/> reading public&#44; in a larger or smaller size&#44; and in a more or<lb/> less attractive form&#44; volumes recalling events which affected<lb/> the religious&#44; social and political condition of once famous na&#45;<lb/>&#45;tions.  It cannot be a cause therefore a matter of surprise to find that<lb/> the past of our people should have drawn to it the minds of the thought&#45;<lb/>&#45;ful&#59; for&#44; Israel <sic>preceeded</sic> some of those nations of antiquity&#44; it met<lb/> others as contemporaries face to face&#44; and it has outlived<lb/> many to this day.  The writers who<lb/> have taken up discussed Biblical and post&#45;Biblical subjects topics are very nu&#45;<lb/>&#45;merous but and not at all confined to any nationality.  English &#38; French&#44; Italians and Dutch&#44; Swede and Poles have contributed to swell up that stream of learning.  But without intending it as a detraction of the merits<lb/> of any&#44; I must do the Germans the justice to say that<lb/> they have shown an unsurpassed activity in that line of study.<lb/>  I am free though to admit that <sic>Judging</sic> of their labors&#44; as far as I can gather from extracts<lb/> and quotations in various translations&#44; I must disapprove of the spirit of<lb/> daring criticism generally prevailing&#44; but I cannot help<lb/> admiring a a most patient researching&#44; and an untiring industry.<lb/>  No one has labored more worked with greater diligencely than our coreligionist&#44;<lb/> Hirsch Graetz.  His success is a history in eleven volumes&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>&#45;&#45;to which&#44; I think&#44; he has lately is adding a twelfth&#44; ranging<lb/> from the birth of our nationality to the present time. century.  An<lb/> abridgment of that colossal work has been promised in English<lb/> and French&#44; but neither has yet appeared.  When Mr Magnus the Revd Mr Magnus<lb/> of London and Rabbi Wogue of Editor of the Univers Israelite at Paris shall have completed<lb/> their undertakings&#44; they will have greatly invaluably <sic>benefitted</sic> those who<lb/> cannot understand the original.<lb/></p>
            <p>Now&#58; with regard to what happened to events which befell our ancestors from<lb/> the period time that Abram the Hebrew left home and kindred&#44;<lb/> and travelled abroad&#44; where he might spread out wile &#45;&#45;to spread abroad his reli&#45;<lb/>&#45;gious views connection sentiments&#45;&#45;to the period of the Babylonian captivity&#44;<lb/> we all may consult the books&#44; commonly called &#34;the Bible.&#34;<lb/>  All men Every person can read them&#44; for because there is scarcely a language&#44;<lb/> or a dialect spoken throughout the world&#44; into which the our Scriptures<lb/> have not been rendered.  I do not assert that the contents<lb/> is always clear to our intelligence.  Such a declaration would<lb/> be worse than folly.  It would betray the shame of having<lb/> never given the writings which should serve us as a have treasured up the learning of over a<lb/> standard of duty thousand years and of scores of minds&#44; a careful perusal.  I&#44; for my part&#44;<lb/> confess that my long studies have been insufficient to explain<lb/> to me innumerable passages in Holy Writ.  But what I<lb/> meant to say is&#44; that&#44; while the history and literature of our<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>people in early times are comprised in very widely universally<lb/> known volumes&#45;&#45;the Bible&#45;&#45;&#44; our history and literature<lb/> in the ages succeeding the exiles into Chaldea&#44; have to be<lb/> looked for in a quantity of varied and scattered writings.  These are<lb/> now a days studied sought after by only a few&#44; and fewer still possess<lb/> the ability to lay out their contents systematically.<lb/>  Hirsch Graetz has accomplished that herculean stupendous task.<lb/>  I myself am not so bold to attempt anything above my mental<lb/> strength&#44; but guided by the faint light I have received&#44;<lb/> I shall try to present to view some points of interest and<lb/> instruction&#44; which are may not be within reach of all my hearers.<lb/>  When Zedekiah&#44; the last king of Judah&#44; had his eyes cruelly<lb/> put out by order of Nebuchadnezzar and was carried in fetters&#44; to Ba&#45;<lb/>&#45;bylon to die in a dungeon&#44; the Hebrew nationality was virtually broken<lb/> up.  Jeremiah did his utmost to prevent avert that calamity sad end.<lb/>  He used the power of inspiration&#44; and his ardent zeal to beg of a<lb/> small number of the poorer classes who had been allowed by<lb/> the conqueror to stay in Palestine&#44; that they would settle down<lb/> peacefully at home and trust in God for a brighter future.<lb/>  But his endeavours availed nothing.  The prophet himself<lb/> who had wished to die in the country of his birth and of his<lb/> love&#44; was forcibly dragged by a party of misguided zealots malcontents<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>to Daphne&#44; in Egypt.  From that moment to<lb/> the restoration of the exiles under Cyrus the Great&#44; history is entirely<lb/> silent about the state of our people.  We are not told<lb/> anywhere explicitly how our predecessors were governed&#44; in the country of stood<lb/> their capture&#44; in their social&#44; religious and political relations to&#44; the country of their captors.<lb/>  A Psalm which must certainly have been composed by a<lb/> patriot who grieved over the fall of Judah&#44; and the Baby&#45;<lb/>&#45;lonian bondage&#45;&#45;the 137th Psalm&#45;&#45;goes for to show a<lb/> keen feeling of deep humiliation&#44; and bitter resentment against<lb/> the victors.  But no scribe was found&#44; as formerly&#44; to<lb/> chronicle facts incidents of weighty importance.  We possess&#44; <sic>how&#45;<lb/>&#45;ver</sic>&#44; two books which indirectly furnish us with consider&#45;<lb/>&#45;able historical information&#45;&#45;the books of Daniel and Ezekiel.<lb/>  From the first we may justly argue that Jews though aliens were not<lb/> regarded as an lower inferior caste&#44; but that&#44; on the contrary&#44; their<lb/> natural talents were recognized and made use of by<lb/> royalty.  For we notice perceive that four noted lads of our belief<lb/> &#45;&#45;and there may have been many more besides&#45;&#45;were supported by the government&#44; and taught trained at<lb/> its expense in the language and learning of the Chaldeans.<lb/>  We may also infer that&#45;&#45;comparatively speaking&#45;&#45;freedom of worship was<lb/> granted&#44; for when the enemies of Daniel determined to<lb/> destroy that pious Jew&#44; they had to play upon the vanity<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>of Darius&#44; or Cyaxeres II&#44; and urge him to pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;claim himself a divinity deity&#44; demanding exclusively divine honors for thirty days&#45;&#45;nothing unusual among kings of<lb/> antiquity&#45;&#45;in order that the man they hated should be put<lb/> to death for offering them prayers to his own God.  Of course&#44; worship<lb/> consisted&#44; then&#44; as now with us&#44; in praises and entreaties &#91;&#63;&#93; entreaties to the Al&#45;<lb/>&#45;mighty and not in burnt&#45;sacrifices&#44; which had must have immediately ceased at the<lb/> destruction of the Temple.  Whether our ancestors<lb/> in Babylon possessed had&#44; like ourselves&#44; Synagogues to hold together<lb/> holy convocations and some uniform prayers&#44; cannot be positively ascertained with positiveness.  A<lb/> legend which may have some foundation&#44; relates that<lb/> the ten thousands transported to Chaldea in the days of Jehoja&#45;<lb/>&#45;chin&#44; before the final overthrow&#44; and among whom the<lb/> Bible reckons craftsmen and locksmiths of different kinds&#44; built up in the<lb/> city of Nehardea a synagogue&#44; using in its construction<lb/> stones and earth brought over form the Holy Land.  Possi&#45;<lb/>&#45;bly those outcasts had&#44; as a common ritual&#44; a number of ancient psalms of a supplicatory character.  For the strokes of misfortune may have softened the<lb/> hearts once hardened in idolatry&#44; so that the Lord&#44; forgotten<lb/> in the land of the fathers&#44; was remembered in the land of the<lb/> foes.  But the reformation could not have been very<lb/> general&#44; for Ezekiel&#44; who doubtless was taken to Chaldea<lb/> among the very earliest prisoners&#44; though addressing his<lb/> inspired word from afar mostly to the Jews who still<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>lived in Palestine&#44; reproved nevertheless<lb/> occasionally his brother&#45;exiles for their neglect of<lb/> moral and ceremonial precepts.  It is clear that the social and<lb/> religious toleration freedom comparatively liberty measurably enjoyed was not taken advantage of<lb/> by all as means to a noble righteous end.  The crying sin of our<lb/> people in every age&#59; the sin of copying gentilism in man&#45; habits<lb/> &#45;ners and practices&#44; had hold of a large portion of our<lb/> ancestors exiled from their homes.  Hence&#44; we hear Ezekiel<lb/> so rebuke them&#58; &#34;What comes up into your mind shall<lb/> not be at all&#59; when you say &#39;we will be like other nations&#44;<lb/> like other families of different lands&#44; <sic>worshipping</sic> wood<lb/> and stones.&#39;&#34;  It was not the fear of persecution being denied rights<lb/> which begot that impious thought wish thought&#44; for the political<lb/> condition of the captives would seem to have been more<lb/> than tolerable.  We may deduce from several passages of<lb/> the prophet whom I have just quoted&#44; that the Judeans<lb/> were allowed to administer their own affairs&#44; through their elders&#44; and were assigned certain sections of the country to dwell in<lb/> unmolested. and were governed by their own princes and elders  But it was the same proclivities&#44; against<lb/> which the luckless unhappy Jeremiah preached to no purpose in<lb/> the streets of Jerusalem&#44; that called forth the denunciation<lb/> of Ezekiel by the waters of Chebar.<lb/></p>
            <p>I do not put any faith&#44; however&#44; in the legend of some<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>fathers of the Christian of the primitive ancient Christian Church&#44; that the prophet<lb/> of the exile was killed by the people it he admonished.<lb/>  They tell us the same fathers of the Christian creed that church&#44; accuse us&#44; without the least authority&#44; about of having<lb/> caused also the death of other inspired teachers of Israel&#44; with the view in order&#44; I imagine&#44;<lb/> to paint us in the blackest colours.  But neither<lb/> do I credit all that Benjamin of Tudela of the twelfth<lb/> century and his contemporary Petachyah of Ratisbon&#44; or<lb/> Regensburg&#44; relate.  According to them the grave of<lb/> Ezekiel&#44; which had a magnificent edifice on the top mausoleum&#44; &#91;&#63;&#93; and other stately edifices around&#44; pos&#45;<lb/>&#45;sessed vi miraculous powers.  And both of them would regale<lb/> us with astounding startling stories.  Later <sic>travellers</sic> agree that<lb/> the spot near the river Euphrates&#44; called now Cabor Rephil&#44; and<lb/> pointed out as the tomb of Ezekiel is considered genuine by<lb/> Arabs Mohammedans as well as Jews&#44; and it is has become an object<lb/> of superstitious reverence.  We&#44; my brethren&#44; should pity<lb/> the aberrations of mind which lead men to pay homage to the<lb/> dust of prophets man.  We love and honor the not the dry bones&#44; but spiritual the ever fresh memory of the illus&#45;<lb/>&#45;trious preceptors of our race&#44; as we see it embalmed in the<lb/> effusions of their illumined intellects.  The history in<lb/> which we may be engaged for some time&#44; will offer for our<lb/> admiration&#44; individuals&#44; who&#44; without claiming a prophetic superhuman vi&#45;<lb/>&#45;sion&#44; became proved by their saintly wisdom a safe guide and light to the house<lb/> of Israel.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
