<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF13_8</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_10_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_10_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_10_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_10_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_10_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_10_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_10_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_10_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_10_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_10_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_10_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_10_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>A lecture for Vaihi<lb/>
                containing some laudatory<lb/>
                remarks on the life of Numa Edward Hartog.<lb/></p>
            
            <p>It was partly published in the Association Review<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>On a certain occasion&#44; two Rabbis of olden times took a<lb/> meal together.  When they had finished eating&#44; one<lb/> asked the other&#44; whether he could tell anything instructive.<lb/>  The question elicited this answer &#34;Our patriarch Jacob is not<lb/> dead.&#34;  Startled at the singular association&#44; the Rabbi<lb/> who possessed an inquiring mind&#44; said&#44; &#34;How can you so<lb/> state&#44; when it is within that a great lamentation was made<lb/> at his demise&#44; and that the physicians opened and<lb/> embalmed his body.&#34;  &#34;I mean&#44;&#34; rejoined his companion&#44;<lb/> &#34;that Jacob lives yet in us&#44; his descendants&#44; the undying<lb/> people of Israel.&#34;  Yes&#44; my dear hearers&#33;  Flesh and bones<lb/> wear away&#59; principles are everlasting.  Suppressed in<lb/> one place&#44; proscribed in another&#44; they exist still in<lb/> regions inaccessible to fire and sword.  They hold their<lb/> secret habitation in the recesses of the human mind.<lb/>  Jacob has&#44; through his family&#44; eternized a principle&#44; which<lb/> has given him an eternity of name.  We are peculiarly<lb/> called his children&#44; because that which Abraham first<lb/> taught&#44; and Isaac imbibed&#44; struck deep root mainly by<lb/> through means of the seed of Jacob&#44; significantly surnamed Israel.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>This truth may be father illustrated  by one of those<lb/> beautiful legends that enrich the pages of the Talmud.<lb/>  Let me relate it.  The patriarch was lying on his<lb/> death&#45;bed.  His twelve sons stood around&#44; to receive<lb/> his last command and his last blessing.  He sees them&#44; and<lb/> bids them draw nearer.  He is in the act of speaking&#59;<lb/> when lo&#33; his thoughts become perplexed.  Disconcerted at<lb/> the occurrence&#44; he cries in a sad tone.  &#34;Are they who have<lb/> issued from my loins unworthy of a father&#39;s parents benediction&#63;<lb/>  Have I begotten Ishmael&#44; whose belief is not like that<lb/> of his sainted father.  Or have I reared an Esaw&#44; whose de&#45;<lb/>&#45;scendants bow to the idol&#63;  Why has inspiration deserted<lb/> me at this hour&#63;  &#34;Then twelve voices burst forth in one<lb/> sweet accord &#34;Hear O Israel&#44; Adona&#239; is our God&#44; Adona&#239; is<lb/> One.&#34;  The troubled countenance of Jacob is overspread<lb/> with serenity at the sound of those words.  He raises his<lb/> hoary head&#44; and devotionally exclaims &#34;Blessed be the name<lb/> of His glorious kingdom for ever and ever.&#34;  Hence on the<lb/> holiest day of the year&#44; when the seed of Israel cleanse<lb/> themselves in the waters of purification&#44; they loudly<lb/> repeat the sentence with which their progenitor responded<lb/> to the declaration of the true faith.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>You understand&#44; my Brethren&#44; the drift of our Rabbin&#39;s<lb/> figurative instruction.  A knowledge all important was<lb/> effectually preserved from extinction by its having been confided<lb/> to the guardianship of an entire household&#58; To the twelve<lb/> sons of one man&#44; united in keeping the parental charge.<lb/>  The same feelings&#44; the same interest urged them to hand<lb/> it down to their lineal descendants as an &#91;&#63;&#93;<lb/> heirloom.  And so long as there will remain any to whom<lb/> that inheritance is of value&#44; Jacob may be said to exist&#44;<lb/> to live in spirit among those who watch vigilantly that<lb/> his belief may never die.<lb/></p>
            <p>But who are the faithful children of Israel&#44; giving an<lb/> eternity of name to their ancestor and to their creed&#63;<lb/>  They whose ever action bears the impress of the religious<lb/> feelings they entertain.  They&#44; I say&#44; for whom the world<lb/> has no honor equal to that which Judaism bestows.  The<lb/> honor of having been chosen the repository of God&#39;s eternal<lb/> truths.  Happily&#44; notwithstanding an increasing defection&#44;<lb/> we are not destitute even in our days if such characters&#44; and it were well&#44;<lb/> my friends&#44; that we searched for them&#44; and exhibited them<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>to view.  It were well useful that we drew our children&#39;s<lb/> attention thereto&#59; especially so&#44; if youths offer example<lb/> of a noble bearing&#44; illustrative of their avowed professing.<lb/>  That model would be the fittest to place before their<lb/> vision&#44; because our sons would might imagine to see in it<lb/> their own reflections illuminated by deeds of commanding<lb/> worth.  In an age of glowing enthusiasm&#44; the<lb/> sight of one walking to manhood under the guidance<lb/> of unflinching principles&#44; will create influences of a<lb/> nature most holy and beneficial.  Now&#44; I bethought<lb/> myself this morning of a life&#44; by whose narrative&#44; our<lb/> brother the Bar Mitzvah and others of the older growth&#44;<lb/> may greatly profit.  Alas&#33; that a life holding forth<lb/> glorious promises&#44; should have so soon come to a close.<lb/>  Still&#44; Numa Edward Hartog lived sufficiently long to<lb/> serve as a bright exemplar to his fellow&#45;believers.<lb/>  An ardent tone for a learning&#44; joint with natural abilities<lb/> he had inherited from his parents&#44; won for him high<lb/> distinctions in the London schools.  So remarkable<lb/> were his talents&#44; and so extraordinary his acquirements&#44;<lb/> that he could not be denied admission into the<lb/> famous university of Cambridge.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Rapidly he passed through the various colleges of that<lb/> extensive institution&#44; till he attained a height never<lb/> before approached by a member of our race.  Then was<lb/> his love for religion put to a severe test.  His profi&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciency in every branch of the sciences he had been taught&#44;<lb/> entitled him to honors <sic>covetted</sic> by many&#44; but which<lb/> few can receive.  They were offered to his acceptance&#44;<lb/> he was pressingly urged by his professors to adorn him&#45;<lb/>&#45;self with what he had nobly earned.  But Judaism<lb/> interposed itself as an insurmountable obstacle.<lb/>  He either must prove false to it&#44; or relinquish that which<lb/> will signally advance his social position.  The choice<lb/> did not occasion a moment&#39;s hesitation.  He refused<lb/> a preferments which a proscriptive law placed within<lb/> reach of those only who can swear by the faith of the found&#45;<lb/>&#45;er of Christianity&#44; and his mission.  On all sides men<lb/> <sic>counselled</sic> compliance with a rule they termed unmeaning<lb/> and futile irrelevant.  The senate of the university conceded even this<lb/> much&#44; that he might omit that portion of the oath conflicting<lb/> with his feelings.  He remained immoveable.  The remains citadel<lb/> of bigotry and intolerance must be thrown down.  A clause offensive<lb/> to his religion&#44; must be expunged from the Statute&#45;book<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>ere he binds himself to obedience.  A conduct so digni&#45;<lb/>&#45;fied&#44; challenged universal admiration.  Both Jews<lb/> and non&#45;Israelites&#44; labored strenuously to remove the<lb/> impediment which militated against the interests of<lb/> young Argot.  The former because they looked f upon him<lb/> as a shining light&#44; shedding lustre on the religion of Jacob.<lb/>  The latter because by reason of his great popularity.<lb/>  While petitions were being circulated for the repealing of<lb/> a law hostile to the believers in the Unity&#44; our exem&#45;<lb/>&#45;plary coreligionist was quietly pursuing his studies in<lb/> the city of London&#44; to become a barrister.  The minister<lb/> of finances having learnt of his sterling abilities&#44; felt<lb/> desirous of securing his services.  Numa Edward Artog<lb/> presented himself and said &#34;I am at the disposal of your<lb/> Highness&#44; provided that you will not require of me to be<lb/> in attendance of my Sabbaths and festivals.&#34;  The<lb/> minister consented.  You will&#44; my Brethren&#44; readily<lb/> perceive that the influence of one so well known and<lb/> respected could not but prove of incalculable advantage&#44;<lb/> if righteously exercised.  Our young fellow&#45;believer<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>sought every opportunity by which the powers he possessed<lb/> might benefit mankind.  With a profound knowledge<lb/> of science&#44; he combined that of in warming the heart<lb/> by persuasive eloquence&#44; and that he f employed specially<lb/> to the elevation of his race.  Every scheme tending to<lb/> ameliorate the condition of his brethren&#44; met with his hearty<lb/> support&#59; every place devised to enhance the welfare of Israel<lb/> found in him an active laborer contributor.  One thought<lb/> seemed to direct and uphold his steps&#44; the thought that<lb/> the talents with which he had been endowed were so<lb/> many of messengers of God&#39;s loving kindness&#44; by which<lb/> the oppressed might be relieved.  That through them<lb/> he might reanimate&#44; encourage&#44; defend the down&#45;trodden.<lb/>  Memorable are his words in a letter sent to a friend.  He writes<lb/> thus.  &#34;Because I am a Jew it is doubly incumbent upon me<lb/> to act in a manner follow a course acceptable to my Maker and my<lb/> fellow&#45;creatures.  For were I to deviate from right&#44; the people<lb/> to whom I belong&#44; would&#44; as usual&#44; be involved in my<lb/> disgrace.  I therefore ponder before I act&#44; studiously<lb/> avoiding what might bring shame upon me and my<lb/> coreligionists&#44; I conceive that I am providentially instru&#45;<lb/>&#45;mental in preserving their honor&#44; and I can accomplish that<lb/> best my by standing spotless before the world.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Alas&#33; that a heart swelling with sentiments so pure<lb/> should have ceased to beat.  To the deep sorrow of<lb/> the community of British Jews&#44; Numa Edward Hartog<lb/> died of the disease&#44; which has&#44; among us also&#44; rendered many<lb/> parents disconsolate.  His labors yielded the fruits he had<lb/> craved for&#44; but he repead reaped them not.  The university of<lb/> Cambridge&#44; will no more exact an oath doing violence<lb/> to the adherents of the ancient faith&#44; but he through<lb/> whose stanch principles the obnoxious rule was rescinded&#44;<lb/> will rejoice only in spirit over that moral victory.<lb/>  A lamenting multitude have laid his body in the cold<lb/> grave.  But if he died young&#44; he lived longer than a host<lb/> of men who outlive the allotted three score years and ten.<lb/>  For&#44; they not unfrequently waste the best portion of their<lb/> existence&#59; he employed every hour of his own to some goodly pur&#45;<lb/>&#45;pose.  He rejected distinctions&#44; that the lowly might be<lb/> exalted.  He won general esteem by the irresistible<lb/> force of a demeanour full of dignity and nobleness.  A<lb/> faithful exponent of the religion of Jacob&#44; he gave an immor&#45;<lb/>tality of fame to his progenitor&#44; to his belief&#44; and<lb/> to his sainted memory &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;The memory of the righteous<lb/> calls us forth a blessing.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Who&#44; among my hearers&#44; can imitate that noble pattern&#63;<lb/>  Will you&#44; my young brother&#44; Bar Mitzvah&#44; strive to copy<lb/> the picture I have set f before your vision&#63;  You will<lb/> not encounter the obstacles he young Artog met in the<lb/> path of worldly preferments.  But an appalling difficulty<lb/> presents itself in your way.  The general desecration of<lb/> the Sabbath&#44; is a formidable enemy ready to fight for mastery.<lb/>  That is the stumbling&#45;block against which many have<lb/> fallen&#44; and been injured everlastingly.  Fortunately for<lb/> you&#44; the parents&#44; who resolved at all hazards to keep<lb/> the fourth commandment of the <sic>Decologue</sic>&#44; will watch that<lb/> you do not infringe on its sanctity.  But in the course<lb/> of time&#44; new associations&#44; the lust for gold&#44; the example of<lb/> the ungodly may lure your heart to sin.  When so tempted&#44; look<lb/> upon the picture I have delineated.  Endeavour to copy all<lb/> its features.  Call to mind the self&#45;denial practiced by<lb/> Numa Edward Artog for the sake of principles&#44; and let<lb/> that be your guide.  May you exceed that youth in the<lb/> number of years you will live.  May you see old age&#44; and<lb/> enjoy temporal happiness.  But oh&#33; employ your existence<lb/> profitably to the race of which you are a member.  Give<lb/> an eternity of name to your creed and to your progenitor&#44; and glory<lb/> to Israel&#39;s God.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
