<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF11_3</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_3_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_3_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_3_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_3_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_3_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_3_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_3_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_3_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_3_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_3_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_3_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_3_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_3_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_3_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_3_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_3_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>An explanatory lecture<lb/>
                on<lb/>
                Parashat Bo<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  The age in which we live&#44; is in a super&#45;<lb/>&#45;lative degree an age of inquiry.  Child&#45;like faith&#45;&#45;<lb/>said to accomplish marvels&#45;&#45;cannot be met&#44; with any<lb/> more frequency among our neighbors&#44; whose religious dogmas<lb/> rest entirely for support upon it&#44; than among Israelites&#44;<lb/> who are free to exercise their reasoning faculties touching their<lb/> belief.  It would be idle to argue whether that<lb/> circumstance works advantageously or prejudicially to<lb/> society at large.  We have to deal with facts&#44; as they stare<lb/> us in the face&#44; and be equal to the exigencies of the time.<lb/>  Many preachers may pine for a return of the days&#44; when<lb/> an occasional exhortation respecting the observance of ritual<lb/> or moral behests&#44; formed the extent of their successful<lb/> efforts.  The days in which a willful audience felt<lb/> edified by the mere recital of their obligations&#44; remain<lb/> in the memory of some&#44; only as a reminiscence of the<lb/> past.  The present generation demands more&#44; and<lb/> that minister might as well be set aside as super&#45;<lb/>&#45;annuated&#44; who is unable to satisfy the claims<lb/> of a religious community.  So much<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>aiming to undermine Holy Writ is heard everywhere&#59;<lb/> so widely spread are the writings antagonistic to it&#44;<lb/> that people&#39;s eyes seem turned to the pulpit&#59; as to the a<lb/> repelling force against the inroad of skepticism.<lb/> Its unwillingness&#44; or incapacity to enter the lists&#44; will<lb/> be interpreted as a virtual surrendering of all points&#44;<lb/> damaging to the cause it must uphold&#44; while strength&#45;<lb/>&#45;ening its opponents.  It behooves then the pulpit to<lb/> accept the position in which the times have placed<lb/> it&#44; and come up vigorously to the task.  When<lb/> human reason raises aggressive arms against reve&#45;<lb/>&#45;lation&#44; it should be fought against with the same<lb/> weapons.  And those I have just made ready in<lb/> vindication of a truth&#44; we share in common with all<lb/> who put faith in the good book.<lb/></p>
            <p>We learnt that the deliverance of Israel from bondage<lb/> was miraculous&#59; that is&#44; Moses directed by God&#44;<lb/> terrified Pharaoh&#44; by means of unsufferable plagues&#44;<lb/> into a final relinquishing of his tyrannic hold.<lb/>  Some modern historians&#44; unable to disprove the fact that the<lb/> descendants of Jacob&#44; were enslaved by the rulers<lb/> of a certain Egyptian dynasty&#44; and that their<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>release from thraldom&#44; and their crossing over to Aka&#44;<lb/> could not be effected without a powerful agency&#44; strive<lb/> to give a natural aspect to that which the world<lb/> has ever regarded as preternatural.  They do not deny<lb/> that repeated strokes humbled the oppressors of the<lb/> Hebrews&#44; but they contend that the land of Mizraim was<lb/> ordinarily subject to the same inflictions.  According<lb/> to the theory they advance&#44; Moses the exceptional<lb/> education which Moses had received&#44; afforded him a<lb/> profound knowledge of the peculiarities of the country<lb/> of his birth&#44; and he availed himself thereof&#44; to predict<lb/> the evils which were to happen.  And as the populace<lb/> are generally credulous&#44; he could with facility inf inspire<lb/> them with awe&#44; and accomplish his high <sic>purpous</sic>.<lb/>  I think&#44; that one needs not be covered with an<lb/> armour of steel to break through such an array<lb/> of arguments.  I would say to those who so<lb/> reason&#58; Deny altogether scriptural narratives&#44; and invent<lb/> what best accords with your prejudgments&#44; to account<lb/> for the existence of the Hebrew race in Palestine&#59;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>but if you follow at all what has been registered<lb/> in the Pentateuch&#44; and what is corroborated by sub&#45;<lb/>&#45;sequent writings&#44; you will find no support&#44; but<lb/> open&#44; unanswerable refutations.  Who will&#44; for<lb/> a moment&#44; entertain the thought that the<lb/> messenger of the Lord anticipated to bend the king&#39;s<lb/> will to his designs through events of common occu&#45;<lb/>&#45;rence&#63;  Imagine Moses foretelling Pharaoh that<lb/> the frogs would leave the river&#44; which at times be<lb/> breeds them&#44; and enter his habitation&#44; his bed&#45;cham&#45;<lb/>&#45;ber&#44; his kneading&#45;troughs&#44; even his oven&#45;&#45;the mo&#45;<lb/>&#45;narch knowing full well&#44; that such was the sequence<lb/> of the reflux of the Nile&#45;&#45;how ludicrous must<lb/> that &#91;&#63;&#93; have appeared&#44; and how unapt there&#45;<lb/>&#45;fore to effect the object in view&#33;  Again&#58;<lb/> If a hail&#45;storm&#44; such as that which swept along<lb/> the territories of the land of Ham was a periodical<lb/> visitation&#44; would not every one have attended to the<lb/> warning of the prophet&#44; when he said &#34;Now go gather<lb/> in thy cattle&#44; and all thou hast in the field&#44; for....<lb/> upon whatever the hail shall fall&#44; will die&#34;.  Would<lb/> not all have evinced anxiety to seek shelter for<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p><sic>for</sic> themselves&#44; and their animals in houses and fold&#44;<lb/> rather than be found exposed to the destructive consequences<lb/> of that scourge&#63;  It has been confidently asserted&#44;<lb/> to explain perhaps such recklessness in the multitude&#44;<lb/> that what the incidents we have perused in th our two last sections<lb/> of Exodus&#44; did not come to pass in so rapid a suc&#45;<lb/>&#45;cession as it might seem form the text&#44; but that<lb/> years elapsed between each of the ten plagues&#59; hence<lb/> people had grown heedless.  The plain records of<lb/> <sic>of</sic> the Bible shows that assertion to be totally unfounded.<lb/>  We read&#58; &#34;Moses was eighty years old.....when he spoke<lb/> unto Pharaoh.&#34;  And in Deuteronomy&#58; &#34;Moses was one<lb/> hundred and twenty years old&#44; when he died.&#34;&#44; while we<lb/> are cont repeatedly told&#44; that the forty years intervening&#44;<lb/> were spent by the son of Amram as the leader of the tribes in their perigri&#45;<lb/>&#45;nations through the wilderness.  We must either<lb/> reject absolutely the words of Holy Writ&#44; or admit that<lb/> only within the space of a few months took place the<lb/> wondrous events&#44; which wrought Israel&#39;s liberation from<lb/> slavery.  But it is truly surprising<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>how a determined wish to divest of the miraculous&#44; what<lb/> bears on its face the unmistakeable &#91;&#63;&#93; of a<lb/> supernatural emanation&#44; will so obscure the mind&#39;s<lb/> eyes&#44; that they cannot any longer see.  The lesson<lb/> of this Sabbath&#44; lays great emphasis upon the cir&#45;<lb/>&#45;cumstance that the swarm of locusts when the east wind<lb/> carried over all Egypt&#44; was a calamity unprecedented<lb/> in the its annals.  For so was the divine messenger<lb/> commanded to address the refractory king.  &#34;Behold I bring<lb/> to&#45;morrow locusts in thy borders.....and they shall<lb/> fill thy houses&#44; and the houses of all thy servants&#44; and<lb/> the houses of Egyptians&#44; what neither thy fathers<lb/> nor thy father&#39;s fathers have ever seen to this day.&#34;  Yet&#44;<lb/> skeptical writers hold tenaciously to their opinion&#44; and<lb/> insists that nothing befell Mezraim to which its geogra&#45;<lb/>&#45;phical position did not render it liable&#33;  But we our<lb/> will cease to surprise at the extravagances of those who urge their<lb/> own untenable notions&#44; rather than concede to the<lb/> Almighty a power ever the &#91;&#63;&#93; alter the laws He has made&#44; over His handiwork<lb/> will increase ten fold&#44; when we learn that how a learned critic<lb/> gives us his assurance that all the first born of Egypt<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>perished by the raging of the small&#45;pox; just as<lb/> if that virulent pestilence could select its victims with<lb/> unfailing precision both among men and among beasts.<lb/>  That novel idea&#44; however&#44; did not meet with general<lb/> favor among rationalists&#44; and some of them have<lb/> endeavoured to improve on it.  Their audacity<lb/> went so far&#44; as to intimate that an army<lb/> secretly organized by Moses&#44; made a fell suddenly on on&#45;<lb/>&#45;slaught the first&#45;born&#44;&#45;&#45;who constituted the<lb/> defenders of the throne&#45;&#45;and made havoc in their<lb/> midst.  A theory so absurd might excite laughter&#44;<lb/> were it not that it has unhappily found advocates among in&#45;<lb/>&#45;dividuals&#44; who pride themselves on exercising the fun&#45;<lb/>&#45;ctions of Rabbis in Amonea.  Good heavens&#33;  What<lb/> teaching can the present generation imbibe from<lb/> such preceptors&#33;  The most glorious event in the<lb/> history of our people.  That event which foreovershadows<lb/> all others&#44; by reason of its ultimate results to the whole hu&#45;<lb/>&#45;man race.  The event stamped with the signet of<lb/> God on all our religious observances.  That event<lb/> ever upon our lips &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;in memory of the<lb/> coming out of Egypt&#44;&#34; that stupendous event&#44; I say&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>is reduced by Rabbinical Neologists into a suc&#45;<lb/>&#45;cessful revolt from among a handful of slaves.<lb/>  Preposterous it is indeed in the highest degree to believe<lb/> that any could penetrate the pls palace and the prison&#44;<lb/> the stable and the barn&#44; and&#44; as by intuition&#44; slay all<lb/> the first&#45;lings&#44; and those who claimed seniority of by<lb/> birth to their mother&#39;s children.  It is preposterous&#44;<lb/> because reason <sic>repells</sic> it.  It is preposterous&#44; be&#45;<lb/>cause the people&#44; who dared not lay hand on their<lb/> oppressors&#44; during a period of impervious darkness&#59;<lb/> the people who were appalled at the sight of their<lb/> former masters&#44; while marching to victory under<lb/> the guidance of the Most High&#44; cannot be supposed to<lb/> have deliberately attacked the Egyptians in their private<lb/> domiciles.  It is preposterous because because such an<lb/> insurrection would have met with resistance&#44; and Israel<lb/> instead of being hastened away from the land of their<lb/> thraldom loaded with silver and gold&#44; would have<lb/> been thrust back to eternal servitude&#44; loaded with fetters<lb/> and heavy burdens.  But it is more than preposterous&#58;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>it is blasphemous.  On the fourteenth of Nissan&#44;<lb/> Moses issued this proclamation &#34;None of you shall<lb/> come out of the door of his house&#44; till the morning.&#34;<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>  Who were they then who made the attack&#44; and before<lb/> whom the portals of all dwellings flew open&#44; that<lb/> they might pierce with the sword young and old&#44; the rational and the irrational among created beings&#63;.....<lb/></p>
            <p>Dear Brethren&#33;  I sincerely hope that none among<lb/> my audience have been tainted with the imparting of<lb/> a new school&#44; whose analysis of the Bible is<lb/> the subversion of revealed religion.  But how<lb/> needful nevertheless it is that you will strengthen<lb/> the citadel of your heart&#45;faith&#45;&#45;with sound<lb/> reasonings.  Unless you abide segregated from<lb/> the rest of the community&#44; you must hear the<lb/> cavils of prejudice and unbelief.  To give credence<lb/> to miracles&#44; means to possess a mind obtuse&#44; dwarfed.<lb/>  Hence&#44; whatever partakes of the <sic>marvellous</sic> in the<lb/> annals of the Jews&#44; must be so construed as to give<lb/> it a more sensible form.  I have offered this morn&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing some illustrations of the sagacious method of<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>transforming the preternatural into natural.<lb/>  So great is the antipathy of the skeptics against what&#45;<lb/>&#45;soever their intellects cannot grasp&#44; that they will<lb/> go in quest of every species of subtlety rather than bow<lb/> the head&#44; and acknowledge that there are things which<lb/> baffle their comprehension.  Man&#33;  Worm&#91;&#63;&#93;&#33;<lb/>  Thou wilt dispute Holy Writ because it gives admission<lb/> to miracles.  But is thy bodily construction&#44; or are<lb/> thy mental faculties less wonderful and incomprehensible<lb/> than the deeds by which the Almighty saw fit to<lb/> chastise tyranny&#44; and deliver a world&#45;enlightening and<lb/> <sic>humanising</sic> nation&#63;  Fain would I&#44; my friends&#33;<lb/> that they who boast of understanding all which comes under<lb/> the head of so termed natural laws&#44; explained to me<lb/> the properties of light&#44; the power of the magnetic needle&#44;<lb/> steadily pointing to the poles&#59; the all lunar attraction<lb/> of the oceans&#44; and seas&#44; and rivers.  I am so ignorant&#44;<lb/> that I by myself cannot discover the power which<lb/> causes me to think&#44; nay&#44; not even that which<lb/> closes my eye&#45;lids&#44; so that I fall into a slumber.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>Dear Brethren&#33;  Listen to a word of friendly<lb/> instruction.  Neither our Bible&#44; nor our Sages<lb/> point to miracles&#44; as the basis of the Jewish religion&#44;<lb/> but to deny them altogether&#44; and thus circumscribe<lb/> the powers of the Omnipotent&#44; is arrogant in man&#44;<lb/> is audacious&#44; is impious.  Let not a son&#44; or a<lb/> daughter of Israel be guilt of that sin.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
