<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF8_14</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1889-01" source="" attested="yes">1889</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_14_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_14_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_14_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_14_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_14_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_14_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_14_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_14_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_14_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_14_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_14_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_14_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>On the rationalists<lb/>
                a sequel to that on the Galician Hassidism&#47;89<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>The excitement caused by the last of its thy its frequent<lb/> sensations in the New York Herald&#44; announcing in capitally<lb/> huge letters about the Jews disappearance from the<lb/> world&#44; may prove a blessing in disguise as it re&#45;<lb/>&#45;gards &#34;American Judaism&#34;&#45;&#45;to use a favorite but inap&#45;<lb/>&#45;propriate phrase.  It Perhaps it may have aroused to a<lb/> sense of danger the camp of miscalled &#34;rationalists&#44;&#34;<lb/> of whom I had intended to speak last Sabbath&#44;<lb/> to follow up my some previous remarks predicated on a Rabbinical<lb/> legend.  They are The Hebrews lauded as entitled rationalists are those who plunge into<lb/> a sea of novel theories ever surging up anew and dragging<lb/> them into circling&#45;eddies and whirlpools.  I observed with ack&#45; verit&#45;<lb/>knowledged &#45;able satisfaction that a loud protest echoed<lb/> forth from pulpits&#44; ministers&#39; libraries&#44; lay lawyers&#39;<lb/> offices&#44; merchants&#39; desks at the announcement tidings of<lb/> a prearranged plan for our final extirpation.<lb/>  Of the many who were interrogated&#44; or who vo&#45;<lb/>&#45;luntarily offered their opinions&#44; only one born in our<lb/> fold audaciously advocated the loss of our identity<lb/> to the advantage of the Church.  With that un&#45;<lb/>&#45;blushing exception&#44; the idea of our children being<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>no more distinguished hereafter as Israelites&#44; the adorers<lb/> of the God&#39;s Unity&#44; appeared horrifying even to men<lb/> who boast of their religious liberality.  If the regrettable<lb/> circumstance trumped up or exaggerated by the Herald were then to occasion a healthful provi&#45;<lb/>&#45;sion against the remotest possibility of our extinct&#45;<lb/>&#45;ion from the Congregation of Jacob&#44; much as<lb/> I deprecate the late alarm&#44; which I consider<lb/> false and deliberately mischievous&#44; I might still be recon&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciled to it by reason of the revival it created.<lb/>  For to a thoughtless merging of our families into<lb/> some larger bodies holding out promises of apparent ma&#45;<lb/> &#45;terial seeming advantages&#63;  Why&#44; with the abolition of<lb/> the precepts discarded as hindrances to our imaginary pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;gress&#44; the amalgamation becomes almost a certainty.<lb/>  Its consummation is only a question of time.<lb/>  Like a solidly impregnably built wall&#44; the ordinances stood to<lb/> prevent that fusion&#44; but one by one have the<lb/> tightly fitting bricks been rudely pulled out&#44; each<lb/> leaving a wide gap&#44; a wide breach facilitating the<lb/> demolition of the whole strong bulwark.  Rationalists is the<lb/> title given to Israelites who have helped in that<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>work of destruction&#44; and their instigators and abet&#45;<lb/>&#45;tors have been lifted high as the wisest preceptors.<lb/>  Whence have then drawn the lessons which with so much self assurance they<lb/> impart&#63;  Not from the Hebrew Bible&#44; where<lb/> the Psalmist first begins his hymns with the declaration of God&#39;s bles&#45;<lb/>&#45;sing to him the man whose delight in is the Law&#44; and makes its<lb/> it his constant meditation &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; not from the Hebrew Bible&#44; whose last<lb/> inspired breathing is a solemn recommendation to keep<lb/> alive the Law of Moses&#44; containing as it treasures statutes and jud&#45;<lb/>&#45;gments from Horeb &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Not from thence&#44; alas because<lb/> in the estimation of the new teachers solons the behests of Sinai<lb/> are obsolete&#44; they became suited olden centuries long gone by.<lb/>  Now a days&#44; the criticism which tries to prove in our Scriptures<lb/> different elements&#44; jarring with each other&#44; some favor&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing sacerdotalism&#44; or the interest of a caste others<lb/> prophetism&#44; or the interest of the people&#59; a Jehovistic &#38; Heloistic system&#44; mind perplexing&#45;&#45;that must<lb/> form the burden of pulpit tuition.  But when youths<lb/> who have not the preparatory training and in<lb/> most instance not neither the mind to judge impartially&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>hear that our history is mythical&#44; that it was<lb/> concocted or made up of some ancient legends&#44; ages<lb/> after its suppositious events&#44; out of some floating legends&#44; that what time<lb/> has hallowed in Israel has no greater sanctity than what<lb/> the heathen Egyptians&#44; Assyrians&#44; Chaldeans and Persians believed<lb/> in and followed&#59; when that becomes the staple foodstuff nourishment which the pulpit dispenses&#44; can we reasonably expect the<lb/> continued existence of Judaism in its distinct ideality&#63;<lb/>  As well might we fancy that to feed nouris feed our sons and<lb/> daughters with noxious victuals&#44; will insure their<lb/> wholesome growth.  For what is Judaism<lb/> in all truth&#63;  This question was asked not long<lb/> ago by a brother in the South&#44; and volumes might<lb/> be written out of the numerous answers variously<lb/> given.  To me there can be but one reply.  Ju&#45;<lb/>diasm is the aggregate body of observing Jews.  When<lb/> the Pentateuchal tenets moral and ceremonial&#44; of the Pentateuch&#44; whose performance<lb/> does not depend on our people&#39;s residence in Palestine&#44;<lb/> are discharged by our offspring everywhere&#44; Judaism<lb/> lives&#59; when those statutes are <sic>wilfully</sic> cast thrown aside&#44;<lb/> Judaism is dying off by inches.  I have said <sic>wilfully</sic>&#44; be&#45;<lb/>&#45;cause young and old may be very apt to trespass &#38; let those who are sinless cast the first stone.  It is<lb/> when we reason ourselves into the rejection of the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Torah&#44; when we join the camp of the rationalists&#44;<lb/> that Judaism is undermined by our own instruments which we ourselves have forged.<lb/>  Having arrived at the conclusion that not till<lb/> seven or eight hundred years after the incidents<lb/> credited to have happened under Moses&#44; our ancestors<lb/> had gained any idea of the a distinct religion as we practice it that till then they were &#91;&#63;&#93; prayers&#44; there<lb/> follows a logical sequence the abandonment<lb/> of rules and behests prescriptions attributed heretofore to the son<lb/> of Amram through a heavenly inspiration.  Aye that is the<lb/> running sore of our time&#45;&#45;a study leading to the<lb/> subversion of all faith.  They who possess influence<lb/> and could build up a strong Judaism with the in&#45;<lb/>&#45;tellects of our youths&#44; shatter it by the dyna&#45;<lb/>&#45;mic forces brought which Biblical critics bring to bear thereon.  by Biblical<lb/> critics  To be well versed in a literature which<lb/> explains Holy Writ and strengthens the ancestral<lb/> belief&#44; is of little account&#59; to be familiar with that<lb/> which explains away Holy Writ and strengthens our doubts&#44;<lb/> is valuable learning.  And how many prattle<lb/> loquaciously on things which they can never un&#45;<lb/>&#45;derstand&#44; but which they repent from having heard<lb/> persons speak who are reputed scholars&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>The Jewish pulpit must be purged&#44; that wholesome<lb/> breath be inhaled by those within its reach.  When<lb/> two years ago the Theological Seminary to which<lb/> I gave origin and in New York was opened and I<lb/> promised in my speech that I would guard it against<lb/> the destructive theories of the German and Dutch<lb/> school of Biblical overthrowers.  I was taken severely<lb/> to task&#44; in the daily certain papers of our neighboring city&#44;<lb/> by colleagues who are wedded to that school.<lb/>  I was depicted as a leader who keeps his follor fol&#45;<lb/>&#45;lowers in fetters swaddles lest they walk too move fast in the path<lb/> of progress.  Never was a charge more groundless.<lb/>  I profoundly felt the importance of my undertaking&#44;<lb/> and I would guard against ward off the danger of a failure.<lb/>  I wished that the youths whom I intend to raise<lb/> as servants of Israel&#39;s God in His holy house&#44; first<lb/> receive such spiritual impressions as may strike deep root<lb/> into their hearts and minds.  After they shall<lb/> have become familiar conversant with He the Hebrew scriptures<lb/> as expounded by tradition&#44; they may read the theorists<lb/> who wage war against the Bible.  They may have<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>then gained acquired the capacity to discover the weakness<lb/> of their arms the weapons.  To ask them alternately to<lb/> study Rashi&#39;s commentaries and Ewald&#39;s&#44; Josephus<lb/> and Rucnin&#91;&#63;&#93; would be to perplex and destroy every<lb/> hope of future usefulness in the field of conservativism.<lb/>  Look around and observe well judge whether my plan<lb/> deserved reprobation.  The disciples of a collegiate<lb/> liberalism&#44; are unfledged philosophers and socialists&#44;<lb/> the masters of rationalism.  I am sworn by every<lb/> thing sacred to strive and prevent the seminary from rearing<lb/> such.  &#34;Are you so very sure of success&#63;&#34;  I<lb/> hear many inquire.  I am not.  Who that sets<lb/> out on a voyage will venture to predict a safe arrival&#63;<lb/>  The perils of the sea may be encountered&#44; but the<lb/> <sic>traveller</sic> trusts that the ship is strongly ribbed&#44;<lb/> well manned&#44; and that the captain at the helm&#44;<lb/> watchful.  In like manner it is with myself.<lb/>  I do not underrate the difficulties of attaining<lb/> my end designed goal.  Surrounded as we are by all phases<lb/> of reform more or less objectionable&#44; the institution<lb/> under my supervision&#45;&#45;which unfortunately is ina&#45;<lb/>&#45;dequate by reason of my residence and multifarious<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>duties in Philadelphia&#45;&#45;may not carry out<lb/> altogether my expectations.  But should not every therefore my<lb/> efforts slack&#63;  Ought they not to be directed towards a happ favorable issue&#63;<lb/>  F To that end I labor&#44; and seek the moral and<lb/> material temporal assistance of my brothers and sisters in<lb/> faith.  If out of the twenty and the ever increasing<lb/> number&#44; a portion will rise having animated with zeal for<lb/> the pers preservation of the history and literature of<lb/> Israel and create a revival&#44; and brighten up our<lb/> horizon with luminous knowledge&#44; quickening our<lb/> dormant souls&#59; if caring for the future of Israel<lb/> in America more than for material gain&#44; or eva&#45;<lb/>&#45;nescent popularity they will read the Torah with<lb/> pure lips&#44; and preach the Torah with sincere hearts&#44;<lb/> I shall receive my reward on this side of the grave&#44;<lb/> and my cooperators will obtain grace in the<lb/> sight of Him whose inspired psalmist wrote &#91;Hebrew&#93; Abundant<lb/> place will be apportioned unto them that love<lb/> Thy Law&#44; and no injury shall befall them.&#34;<lb/>  And so may it be.  Amen.<lb/>  &#40;Here follows an address to a Bar Mitzvah<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
