<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF17_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff17_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff17_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff17_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff17_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff17_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff17_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff17_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff17_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff17_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff17_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff17_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff17_2_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>For Vayakel<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Dear hearers&#33;  In no instance&#44; except in the section of<lb/> this sabbath&#44; does a chapter of the Pentateuch commence<lb/> with the account of a large gathering of people&#44; convened<lb/> by Moses.  And as the opening of the address by the arch&#45;prophet<lb/> on that occasion&#44; relates to the various ordinances of the Sabbath&#44; the<lb/> sages of Israel took the opportunity to offer as thereby useful<lb/> instruction.  They imparted it by the following sentence.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;God bid Moses to assemble a vast multitude &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> and explain to them the laws of the Sabbath&#44; so that posterity<lb/> might learn feel impelled by the example to do likewise&#34;.  But figuring that the afore&#45;<lb/>&#45;said might be interpreted simply as a recommendation<lb/> of to repeating each time the same lesson&#44; they added &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;Future generations must learn understand the imp<lb/> importance of bringing Hebrew communities together every Sabbath&#44; inviting<lb/> them to be present&#44; wherever the law is taught according<lb/> to its various different commands.&#34;  My friends&#33;  The principal&#44;<lb/> if not the sole&#44; object of the seventh day&#39;s observance&#44; is thus revealed<lb/> to us.  Instruction&#59; a thorough knowledge of our duties<lb/> as men and Jews must be obtained thereon.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>We should endeavour to learn on the day&#44; which God<lb/> declared sacred to Himself&#44; the lessons that are to be put<lb/> into practice&#44; during the six days He has given for our own<lb/> use.  Oh&#33; how fruitful of blessings would be the sabbath<lb/> so spent.  Every human being with whom we associate<lb/> would experience its benefits.  Parents would see their children<lb/> draw closer to them&#44; in fastening the natural bonds of affection&#59; while children<lb/> would secure the joint efforts of their parents for their temporal<lb/> and spiritual progress.  Husbands and their wives would vie<lb/> with each other in promoting the comforts of their home&#59; and<lb/> kindly kindness towards our equals would be uniformly manifested&#44; consideration and forbearance would also prevail towards in our actions<lb/> to our dependents.  The precepts of God expounded with much<lb/> frequency and listened to with reverence for their own sake&#44; would be exempli&#45;<lb/>&#45;fied in all our relations of life&#44; and the great goal for<lb/> the sake of which the Sabbath gatherings were mainly instituted would<lb/> be reached&#59; that is&#44; the name of the Almighty Creator would be<lb/> exalted through our agency &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> worship alone cannot effect that holy purpose.  For external<lb/> observances are only one the means conducive to righteousness.<lb/>  I am far from undervaluing the object of our sacred<lb/> ceremonies&#91;&#63;&#93;.  I know that they keep alive national<lb/> sentiments&#59; prevent the law and the prophets from<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>being forgotten&#44; and they are calculated to uplift our souls to<lb/> their Maker and thus withhold us from sin.  But unaccompanied with instruction&#44;<lb/> prayers and thanksgivings may degenerate into a habit that<lb/> cannot profit&#44; because the thoughts they should awaken<lb/> lie dormant.  In fact&#58; Has it not been said&#44; and<lb/> with some degree of truth&#44; that they who are most noted<lb/> for the attendance to devotional exercises&#44; are not always so&#45;<lb/>&#45;cially&#44; the best of men&#63;  It is a common adage among Rab&#45;<lb/>&#45;binical writers that no one ignorant of his duties&#44; can be<lb/> pious &#91;Hebrew&#93; and our daily experience shows that<lb/> the mere act of repairing often to the synagogue&#44; is<lb/> insufficient to uphold retain us in the path of virtue.  For&#44;<lb/> there are some who practice religion in the house of<lb/> God&#44; but fail to carry it with them along&#44; when mingling<lb/> with the outward world.  &#34;What connection can there<lb/> be between religion and trade&#44;&#34;&#63; they are apt to ask.  &#34;How<lb/> can religion blend with the pursuit of my vocation&#34;&#63; will the<lb/> merchant or the practitioner inquire.  And I answer.  Brethren&#33;<lb/>  If you believe that religion consists in the recital of a certain<lb/> amount number of prayers&#44; in doing penance on a certain day&#44; and<lb/> enjoying a sumptuous repast or another&#59; you have mistaken<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>a shadow for a reality&#44; you have the shell but to not the<lb/> kernel of the fruit.  For religion is in very deed connected with all<lb/> your walks of life.  Like wisdom&#44; personified by Solomon in<lb/> his book of proverbs&#44; religion stands in the high places ways roads&#44; and<lb/> in the gates of the city&#44; wherever man is found&#44; there it<lb/> stands and cries aloud.  &#34;Listen&#44; for of noble things I speak&#34;....To fear<lb/> the Lord is to hate wrong&#44; pride&#44; insolence&#44; waywardness&#44; and a<lb/> foul mouth.&#34;  ItClearly then&#44; the synagogue is only one of<lb/> the aids&#45;&#45;confessedly valuable essential&#45;&#45;which religion sends forth<lb/> to assist in a godly work&#59; but it is&#44; by no means&#44; Religion<lb/> itself.  So well our Rabbis understood this fact&#44; that they<lb/> accorded a greater degree of sanctity to school&#45;houses than to<lb/> houses of prayer.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  They knew that in the latter former latter our growing<lb/> sons and daughters cannot receive altogether a learning which<lb/> will qualify them to represent Judaism intelligently and<lb/> becomingly.  For&#44; aside from any rudimental or linguistic<lb/> instruction&#44; the manner of addressing children must necessa&#45;<lb/>&#45;rily differ from that followed in lecturing to their elders.<lb/>  Were it even that the Sanctuary had in view the teaching of<lb/> the young in their tender years&#44; its practice would have to be<lb/> limited to distant intervals&#44; else injustice might be done<lb/> to the majority of the attendants.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>We should therefore hail every effort to combine plain<lb/> and persuasive instruction with a simplified worship&#44; beyond<lb/> these precincts&#44; and give it pecuniary and moral support.<lb/>  I cannot disguise my surprise at hearing that such exertions<lb/> meet with a disapproval among some of my brethren&#44; and that the unavoidable dissolution<lb/> of the Education society school&#44; and its transformation into<lb/> a Sabbath&#45;afternoon Bible&#45;teaching and prayer&#44; and week days&#39;<lb/> Hebrew classes&#44; is made a cause for the withdrawal of a patron&#45;<lb/>&#45;age still essentially greatly needed.  Yet&#44; the change can effectually<lb/> serve the purpose for which&#44; according to the Talmudists whom I have<lb/> quoted&#44; Moses gathered a large multitude&#44; as told in the opening<lb/> sentence of our Parasha.  But while I regret the difficulties<lb/> which undertakings that principally aim to the cultivation of the<lb/> Hebrew language encounter among Philadelphia Hebrews&#44; I<lb/> congratulate myself on the popularity of an institution in<lb/> our midst&#44; heretofore <sic>combatted</sic> against as useless and effete.<lb/>  Our two Sunday&#45;Schools are a valuable an important adjunct to the Syna&#45;<lb/>&#45;gogue.  They do not set forth pretentious claims.  Modestly<lb/> and unobtrusively they carry out a plan whereby our<lb/> children acquire what&#44; lamentable circumstances&#44; often<lb/> debar the rising generation from learning anywhere else.<lb/>  Portions of our people&#39;s history read&#44; and explained in conversational<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>style&#44; the pointing of morals principles to be drawn from the<lb/> events narrated&#44; the origin and object of the holidays&#44; the<lb/> passages of the Scriptures which have reference to the<lb/> Unity of God and to the divine promises of reward and<lb/> punishment&#59; these&#44; together with a little memorizing of ca&#45;<lb/>&#45;techisms&#44; constitute the instruction there imparted.  Admit<lb/> it.  The range of religious knowledge compassed is very limited&#44;<lb/> but how many might have grown in total ignorance of sa&#45;<lb/>&#45;cred duties except for the hour spent on the first day of<lb/> the week in the association of their coevals and fellow core&#45;<lb/>&#45;ligionists&#33;  How many might have deserted our fold&#44; but<lb/> for the memory of childhood&#44; when the belief in One indivisible<lb/> Creator&#44; the Provident Father and Saviour of all mankind&#44; had been rooted<lb/> into their nature&#33;  Certain it is&#44; that our Sunday&#45;School<lb/> does not come under the charge lately brought against<lb/> the Episcopal institution of the same name&#44; and publicly<lb/> made by prominent ministers of that denomination&#59; namely&#44;<lb/> that &#34;it drives children away form the Church&#44; instead of<lb/> drawing them thereto.&#34;  The speakers attribute the fault to<lb/> the church itself&#44; to the contrast between the democratic ben&#45;<lb/>&#45;ches and the aristocratic pews&#59; to the noted facts the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>places of worship are overburdened with debt&#44; and they<lb/> cannot afford to reserve free seats for the children of the<lb/> destitute.  But it is not so with our Sunday&#45;school.  Knowing that all<lb/> can find a place ample room in the Synagogue&#44; it strenuously urges attendance<lb/> to the service.  It even offers accords tokens of distinction to the young<lb/> who behave well during the sacred devotional exercises.<lb/>  
                A case in point&#44; is that of the lad&#44; who attained this Sab&#45;<lb/>&#45;bath his thirteenth year.  The Sunday&#45;school gave him an<lb/> idea&#44; however faint&#44; of Jewish doctrines.  The Sunday&#45;school<lb/> surroundings aroused the thought of being thus congregational<lb/>&#45;ly recognized as a Hebrew&#44; and it will be due to the<lb/> Sunday&#45;school&#44; if the lad youth will hereafter be seen with<lb/> frequency in the dwelling of Israel&#39;s God.  For&#44; in the<lb/> Sunday&#45;school the kindest influence has been exercised<lb/> to that effect.  More would be unseemly for me to<lb/> say&#44; as I must spare the feelings of parents&#44; and&#44; on<lb/> the other hand&#44; avoid words of praise&#44; though richly<lb/> deserved&#44; which might be sound as studied designed flattery.<lb/>  With regard to myself&#44; I may add&#44; that through the<lb/> Sunday&#45;school I became acquainted with our young brother&#44;<lb/> and I could therefore gratify the wish expressed&#44; that he be<lb/> made to stand in this holy spot&#44; on the day of his becoming Bar<lb/> Mitzvah.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Dear lad.  I have reason to think that you feel much<lb/> pleased at having been called to the Law in this Synagogue.<lb/>  And it would also be a afford me pleasure to me to make a few<lb/> remarks which might increase your gratification for<lb/> the event celebrated&#44; and your love for this hallowed place.<lb/>  Specially I would like to keep you awhile to recommend<lb/> your studying every Sunday&#44; how best to prove yourself<lb/> in future worthy of the name of Jew&#44; and of citizen of the<lb/> goodly land in which your lots has been cast.  But the<lb/> Sabbath which comes before the month of Nissan&#44; lengthens<lb/> the service&#44; and I have&#44; accordingly&#44; detained the congregation<lb/> beyond the usual time.  Therefore&#44; I must bring my re&#45; obser<lb/>&#45;marks to you vations abruptly&#44; to a close.  May But not without praying that the God whose miraculous<lb/> deeds in Egypt we are about to commemorate may bless and<lb/> preserve you&#44; as He watched over and rescued from death the<lb/> first&#45;born of Israel on the night of our father&#39;s deliverance from<lb/> slavery.  Oh&#33; Lord of wonders&#33;  I petition Thee to<lb/> prepare for every family of the men and women I have addressed&#44; a festival<lb/> as joyful as at the birth of our nationality&#44; when freedom from the burden of<lb/> affliction was experienced.  May the lightheartedness with which the redeemed<lb/> left the country of oppression&#44; be felt by those whom reverses have depressed.<lb/>  May all have cause to sing the inspired psalm uniting the sick and the prisoner&#44;<lb/> him that fears danger and those exposed to ills to thank the Lord for His salvation&#44; and for His<lb/> mercy which endureth for ever.  May such be Thy gracious will.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
