<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF2_7</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_7_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_7_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_7_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_7_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_7_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_7_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_7_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_7_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_7_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_7_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_7_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_7_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>On Penitence<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>When Adam saw that days were fast growing<lb/> shorter&#44; and darkness displaced light&#44; terror seized<lb/> him.  &#34;Alas&#44;&#34; he exclaimed &#34;that because of my dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;obedience this lively world will be enshrouded in eter&#45;<lb/>&#45;nal gloom.&#34;  But a voice from on high reassured<lb/> the penitent sinner.  He was promised a return of<lb/> the days&#44; on which the majestic and soul&#45;enliven&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing luminary lingers in the sky.  Then man who<lb/> labored usefully while the long evenings prevailed&#44; would<lb/> enjoy the fruits of his endeavours&#44; when the sun abides<lb/> in the horizon with prolonged brightness.  Such<lb/> is the substance of a legend which I once read in Rab&#45;<lb/>&#45;binical writings.  The season of the year&#44; and<lb/> that which Israelites now keep in deep solemnity&#44; bring<lb/> that legend back to the mind.  The period during which<lb/> night shrinks&#44; as it were&#44; within narrow limits&#44; and<lb/> allows the day to wield an almost absolute domi&#45;<lb/>&#45;nion&#44; is fading away.  We do not fear&#44; like our first<lb/> parent who had been chased from paradise&#44; fear that<lb/> nature will be overthrown by reason of our transgressions.<lb/>  We have learned to know the cause of the various changes<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>which the globe we inhabit successively under&#45;<lb/>&#45;goes.  But though we need not entertain any fore&#45;<lb/>&#45;boding&#44; for &#91;Hebrew&#93; the universe follows the course<lb/> assigned to it by its Maker&#59; though it were fully in<lb/> any of us to be disconcerted&#44; because autumn is far<lb/> advanced&#44; and the state of the atmosphere heralds the<lb/> approaching winter&#44; we may nevertheless fittingly ask ourselves&#44; without<lb/> terror undismayed&#44; but in anxious thought&#44; whether the present time<lb/> should not recall shortcomings.  Thus we may labor work<lb/> sensibly for our improvement&#44; while the sun is down&#44; and enjoy the yieldings<lb/> of our exertions wisely&#44; when it will long shine again<lb/> with brilliancy in the heavens above.<lb/></p>
            <p>Very many whose absence form the habitation of prayer<lb/> continued without intermission&#44; have at length entered<lb/> its portals.  They feel that to approach stand before the Bestower<lb/> of all good with entreaties when a year has come to its<lb/> close&#44; and another whose embosomed events are veiled from our vision<lb/> has been ushered in&#44; is beseeming&#59; that when the heart<lb/> eagerly wishes yearns for joys domestic and social&#44; it becomes<lb/> believers to approach the One God with petitions.  But<lb/> it behooves me to say&#44; as the a messenger of that perfect<lb/> Being crowned in with purity&#44; that unless we Israelites in crossing<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>the threshhold of the Sanctuary&#44; leave behind the burden<lb/> of former errors&#44; the Tishri communions with the Almighty<lb/> will effect nothing &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;I will wash my hands in sincerity&#44; and then will I<lb/> compass Thy altar&#44; O Lord&#33;&#34; exclaimed the conscience&#45;stri&#45;<lb/>&#45;cken ruler of old.  He meant&#44; I will remove the stains<lb/> which misdeeds left stamped on my character as a man and a<lb/> Jew&#44; before I seek the presence of Him who is enthroned<lb/> in righteousness.  Now&#58; it is not unlikely<lb/> that both the quotation just made&#44; and the legend<lb/> cited before above&#44; may seem inappropriate.  For to charge<lb/> my coreligionists with David&#39;s great sin&#44; or compare my<lb/> brethren&#39;s disobedience to that of which the parent of<lb/> the human race became guilty&#44; would be an abuse<lb/> of the pulpit.  Still&#44; I conceive that I do<lb/> not offend truth by asserting that when we appear<lb/> before the Lord of life with supplications&#44; we are<lb/> neither in the same frame of mind as the shepherd<lb/> King&#44; nor as the first created man.  Some<lb/> Hebrews have spent the long days which are fast<lb/> passing away&#44; in a manner totally at variance with<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>proprieity&#44; or positively sinful.  I know<lb/> of youths of both sexes who on the plea of recruiting strength&#44;<lb/> trespassed against the rules of that refined chastity&#44; whose rigid<lb/> preservation was formerly the pride of our people.<lb/>  They do not feel abashed deem it wrong&#44; because a corrupt practice<lb/> sanctions what an uncompromising Jewish morality frowns upon&#44; but were<lb/> they to turn aside from the exciting fascination&#44; and<lb/> soberly think&#44; surely their checks would colour&#44;<lb/> because of that which under ordinary circumstances must be<lb/> declared highly reprehensible.  Yet&#44; matronly<lb/> mothers and staid fathers look on unconcerned&#44; if they do<lb/> not smilingly approve.  &#34;No harm in that&#59; it is<lb/> innocent past time&#34;; and so is the promiscuous gather&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing and the late dance&#44; which defeat the alleged object<lb/> of a temporary absence from home and its healthful sur&#45;<lb/>&#45;roundings.  But is that youth who risks at the<lb/> gaming board the hard&#45;earned substance of his father&#44;<lb/> indulging also in innocent past time&#63;  How much god that might promote the cause of education and of humanity&#44; is culpably wasted&#44; and how many characters are<lb/> sunk in places ostensibly sought for recreation&#63;<lb/>  Allurements beset our offspring everywhere&#44; for like<lb/> the wisdom described in the book of Proverbs&#44; so does<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>folly cry out on public thoroughfares&#58; &#34;Come&#44; eat enjoy<lb/> of the food I have prepared&#44; and drink of quaff the wine which<lb/> I poured out&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; but the unwary fails<lb/> to notice the pit that yawns under their steps.  Yes&#58;<lb/> everywhere seductions beset hedge around their children&#39;s path&#44; but<lb/> there where the long days of a summer season attract<lb/> them&#44; there at every corner sin lies in ambush and many<lb/> are caught in its meshes.  Yet those who became its prey so entangled&#44; regardless of irregularities committed against the code of ethics &#38; ceremonial religion&#44; appear<lb/> at the Tabernacle of the Lord uncontrite&#44; as if they had<lb/> never swerved from rectitude.  It is this heedless&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness that drew from Jeremiah&#44; who speaking in the name of his<lb/> Heavenly Master&#44; the sentence &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Behold&#44; I enter into judgment with thee&#44; because thou<lb/> sayest &#39;I have not sinned&#39;.&#34;  Mark it&#44; my brethren&#44;<lb/> Adam rebelled against the expressed command of his Maker&#59;<lb/> David offended the Law of Sinai heinously&#44; but both met<lb/> with temptations difficult to overcome&#44; and both acknow&#45;<lb/>&#45;ledged the justice of the suffering which their misdeed<lb/> brought on.  The former terror&#45;stricken&#44; na&#239;vely believed<lb/> that nature that nature would be overturned by reason<lb/> of his disobedience&#44; the latter in deep compunction exclaimed<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; and again &#34;I will wash my hands in innocence&#44; and then<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>will I compass Thy altar&#44; O Lord.&#34;  We go deliberate&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly in search of seductions&#44; and as if perfectly<lb/> spotless&#44; as if always loyal to the Torah&#44; we ask for life<lb/> and health&#44; and prosperity and honors.  Fellow<lb/> Israelites.  It is a source of unfeigned rejoicing satisfaction to see<lb/> the edifice hallowed to prayer&#44; thronged with attend&#45;<lb/>&#45;ants at the solemn season of memorial and of atonement&#59;<lb/> and As to our immediate selves since we offer our orisons jointly and not by means<lb/> of hirelings&#44; it is indeed exceedingly gratifying to feel that<lb/> it lies in our power to illustrate the Biblical sen&#45;<lb/>&#45;tence&#44; figuratively and by the Sages in connection with<lb/> the worship.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  &#34;The King &#40;of the universe world&#41;<lb/> is honored extolled by a multitude of people.&#34;  But not<lb/> in the vastness of the assemblage ought we to pride<lb/> ourselves&#44; but rather in a congregation humbled beofre<lb/> the majesty of the Lord&#59; ready to acknowledge horrors faults&#44;<lb/> whether committed towards man or towards the heavenly Universal<lb/> Father&#44; and disposed to lead a life consistent with<lb/> the tenets and statutes of religion revelation.<lb/>
                I heard once a Rabbi of the modern school&#44; make<lb/> public boast of the largeness of the body of Hebrews<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>to whom he ministered&#44; and of their controlling<lb/> influence.  But as it happens that the influence<lb/> exercised emanated simply from riches and not from<lb/> piety&#44; and the largeness of the body had its origin in<lb/> the facility offered to cast aside without compunction<lb/> law and traditions&#44; and make to let Judaism to bear very lightly<lb/> upon the Jew&#44; we none need not crave for the ability to<lb/> indulge in that price of self&#45;glorification.  What<lb/> God&#45;fearing minister will joy over members who with<lb/> shameless ostentation drive their own carriage to the<lb/> Temple on the day of atonement&#44; and having eaten their<lb/> fill&#44; condescend to sit our damasked easy chairs&#44; and<lb/> listen to the <sic>warbling&#39;s</sic> of non&#45;Jewish songstresses.  No&#59; rather<lb/> pray with and address the thinnest assemblage&#44; but<lb/> one impressed with the sanctity of the spot and of the<lb/> occasion&#44; one who does not point to the gorgeousness of<lb/> of a stately structure as a criterion of its devotion to the<lb/> faith&#44; but to its exemplification illustration of ancestral virtues and<lb/> its confiding trust in the Lord.  Dear brothers and<lb/> sisters in faith.  The time of the year&#44; and the season<lb/> which we celebrate&#44; demand that we shall pause<lb/> and reflect.  I long to render this congregation exemplary&#59;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>You must aid my endeavours.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;.<lb/>  &#34;Some will gain eternity in one hour&#34; write the Sages.<lb/>  None more propitious than the present on this penitential<lb/> Sabbath.  The shades of night gather now quickly<lb/> around&#44; as a message from above.  Let us seize<lb/> the inextinguishable lamp given granted us by God&#45;&#45;our luminous light&#45;giving<lb/> intellect&#45;&#45;and examine the course we have pursued<lb/> Let us We all level here what was uneven&#44; according to the<lb/> standard of justice&#59; raise there what was low&#44; and<lb/> steep according to the measure of rectitude&#44; amplify amend every&#45;<lb/>where what was unrighteous.  Let us make our future<lb/> way so correctly straight&#44; that it may be like that<lb/> pictured by the moralist of yore it may lead us and others upward&#44; as by a star&#44; ever resplendent&#44; with<lb/> lightly shining on unto the perfect day &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  When that day arrives&#44;<lb/> we shall behold the record due to our actions.  We<lb/> shall feel that to adhere&#44; despite all allurements&#44; at<lb/> home and abroad&#44; to the dictates of Holy Writ&#44; is to<lb/> have secured the approval of the just&#44; the association<lb/> of the saints&#44; and the unending blessings of the Eternal<lb/> God&#44; the Protector and Saviour of Israel.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
