<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF11_6</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1897-01" source="" attested="yes">1897</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_6_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_6_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_6_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_6_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_6_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_6_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_6_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_6_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_6_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_6_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_6_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_6_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_6_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_6_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_6_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff11_6_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>14 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADLEPHIA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>111</p>
            
            <p>97<lb/></p>
            <p>On the proposition of<lb/>
                O. J. Simon to gain proselytes<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Our daily prayers contain a benediction pe&#45;<lb/>&#45;culiar in its wording.  I have examined the various<lb/> ancient rituals in my possession&#44; to discover ascertain whe&#45;<lb/>&#45;ther the peculiarity in that benediction agrees<lb/> in each of them.  I found that the Italian&#44;<lb/> which I judge to be the oldest&#44; the Ashkenazic<lb/> and French &#40;Mahzor vitri&#41; the next&#44; and the Sephardic the last&#44; are&#44; with<lb/> scarcely any noticeable difference&#44; identical.<lb/>  The wording to which I allude&#44; is a petition<lb/> to God&#44; that He may bestow His tender mercies<lb/> upon righteous proselytes &#91;Hebrew&#93;.<lb/></p>
            <p>I shall not discuss now the origin and author&#45;<lb/>&#45;ship of that supplication.  While our olden traditions tells<lb/> that on the return of our ancestors from the Ba&#45;<lb/>&#45;bylonian captivity&#44; the great synod &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> presided over by Ezra the priest&#44; formulated a<lb/> Hebrew liturgy for the use of Synagogues&#44; which<lb/> doubtless multiplied fast at that period&#44; modern<lb/> critics hold that our Manual of prayers has<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>undergone alterations at various epochs.<lb/></p>
            <p>What drew my attention just at present to<lb/> the benediction on proselytes&#44; is a question ven&#45;<lb/>&#45;tilated among some of our coreligionists in London.<lb/>  Especially in the &#34;Jewish Quarterly Review&#34; it<lb/> has that question been largely dwelt upon and the editors invited<lb/> a free opinion on its merits&#44; or demerits.<lb/>  A Mr. Oswald John Simon&#44; who writes<lb/> attractively and who appears sincere&#44; has<lb/> proposed a novel plan for winning over to<lb/> Judaism&#44; many of our Christian neighbors.<lb/>  According to it&#44; a place should be chosen and<lb/> there all who have lost faith in the main<lb/> dogmas of the Church&#44; should be convened.<lb/>  On Sunday&#44; the general leisure day&#44; Israelites&#44;<lb/> who firmly believe in the prophecies&#44; as inter&#45;<lb/>&#45;preted by Mr Simon&#39;s followers&#44; ought to deliver<lb/> in English&#44; with uncovered heads&#44; a selection of<lb/> prayers and preach the Unity of god&#44; as pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;claimed by Moses and as emphasized by his<lb/> disciples in subsequent ages.  But not Christ&#45;<lb/>&#45;ians alone must be urged to attend.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Jews also who are weak&#45;kneed and half&#45;hearted<lb/>&#45;&#45;to use Mr Simon&#39;s own phraseology&#45;&#45;must be<lb/> urged to swell the number of the <sic>worshippers</sic>.<lb/>  The good man&#44; is of opinion&#44; that nominal<lb/> Hebrews upon hearing the checkered history of their<lb/> people&#44; the grand effusions of Seers&#44; Psalmists<lb/> and moralists&#44; will have their weak knees strength&#45;<lb/>&#45;ened&#44; and their divided hearts made whole.<lb/></p>
            <p>Worth the while it is to read the clashing views&#44;<lb/> which a literary symposium called forth.<lb/>  I felt interested and pleased&#44; because women&#44;<lb/> like lady Magnus&#44; men like Israel Zangwill&#44; whom<lb/> none would charge with bigotry&#44; set their faces<lb/> against a project very impracticable and pos&#45;<lb/>&#45;sibly mischievous.  I am aware that the<lb/> same idea has often repeatedly struck before persons born<lb/> in our fold.  They declared that unless a vigorous<lb/> effort is made to widen our ranks&#44; we are doomed<lb/> to perish as a distinct people.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>But not only Jews&#44; exhibited anxiety apprehension on<lb/> that score.  Liberal Christians too have pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;nounced the same pessimistic verdict about our future.<lb/>  A professor who deservedly enjoys a high repu&#45;<lb/>&#45;tation by reason of his researches in the science of<lb/> religion&#45;&#45;Max M&#252;ller of Oxford&#45;&#45;in a lecture<lb/> delivered at Westminister Abbey about a quarter<lb/> of a century ago&#44; predicted that the continuance<lb/> of Jews upon earth can remain be but precarious&#44;<lb/> since they do not imitate other denominations.<lb/>  They hsould endeavour&#44; if they wish to live&#44; to<lb/> disseminate the doctrines of the old testament by<lb/> means of devout missionaries.  Well&#44; in our<lb/> own city and elsewhere all over the United States&#44;<lb/> Sunday services have partly for their object an<lb/> accession of number from among Christians&#44; who<lb/> cannot subscribe to the fundamental creeds of their<lb/> parents&#39; religion.  I&#44; without any bias&#59;<lb/> only to subject to a severe scrutiny my best understanding of our<lb/> Scriptures and our Rabbinical teachings&#44; I ask<lb/> myself whether the supplication in the Amidah&#44;<lb/> or Shemon&#233; Esr&#233;&#44; as others call it&#44; can relate<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>to men and women attending a Sunday service&#44;<lb/> as proposed in England and as followed in Ame<lb/>&#45;rica&#59; whether in all reality the epithet of &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;righteous proselytes&#34; applies to them.<lb/></p>
            <p>Mr Simon and others who side with him will<lb/> answer affirmatively.  They quote the prophets&#44;<lb/> principally Isaiah and Malachi to prove them&#45;<lb/>selves correct&#44; insisting that Judaism was meant<lb/> from its very beginning as a missionary&#45;faith.<lb/>  Let us impartially cast a glance on examine a few of<lb/> the sentences triumphantly cited as evidences of the theory advanced.<lb/>  Isaiah is brought out foremost by persons&#44;<lb/> who contend that a bounden duty requires that<lb/> we our going in search of gentiles.  In the 56th chapter<lb/> we read what follows&#58; &#34;Let not the stranger&#44;<lb/> that hath joined himself to the Lord&#44; speak<lb/> saying&#59; &#34;The Lord will surely keep me apart<lb/> from His own people&#63;; neither let the eu&#45;<lb/>nuch say&#58; &#39;Behold I am but a dry tree&#39;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>For&#44; thus saith the Lord of the eunuchs that<lb/> keep Thy Sabbaths&#44; and choose the things<lb/> that I wish&#44; and hold fast upon Thy covenant.<lb/>  Unto them I will give in Thy house and within<lb/> thy walls a memorial and a name better than<lb/> sons and daughters.  I will given them an<lb/> everlasting name&#44; that shall not be cut<lb/> off.  Also the strangers that join them&#45;<lb/>&#45;selves to the Lord&#59; to minister unto Him&#44;<lb/> and to love the name of the Lord&#44; to be His<lb/> servants&#59; every one that keepeth the Sabbath<lb/> not profaning it&#44; and who holdeth fast<lb/> upon Thy covenant&#44; even then will I bring<lb/> to Thy holy mountain&#44; and make them<lb/> joyful in My house of prayer.&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>Clearly&#44; a prediction is here enunciated.  But<lb/> what is it&#44; in all truth&#63;  Does it foretell<lb/> that whosoever chooses voluntarily to alter<lb/> the fourth commandment of the Decalogue&#44;<lb/> and substitutes for it the miscalled &#34;lord&#39;s<lb/> day&#34;&#44; and whosoever chooses to set deliberately aside which<lb/> the ordinances which our forefathers accepted<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>at Sinai&#44; and through whose promised obe&#45;<lb/>&#45;dience thereof&#44; God entered with Israel into<lb/> a covenant&#44; is to be regarded&#44; as one of &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;the righteous proselytes&#34;&#63;  If my mind is<lb/> able to grasp the sense conveyed by the imparting<lb/> of Isaiah&#44; I must answer negatively.<lb/>
                A &#91;Hebrew&#93; whom the compilers of our liturgy had<lb/> in mind&#44; is not he that merely denies the<lb/> unreasonable dogmas of Christianity&#44; but he<lb/> who positively admits the validity of the<lb/> Sinaic statutes.<lb/></p>
            <p>Again&#44; Isaiah is invoked as the authority sanc&#45;<lb/>&#45;ctioning the scheme that Mr Oswald John Simon<lb/> has conceived&#44; namely&#44; the embracing promulgation of a religion<lb/> stripped of every form&#44; every rite&#44; every<lb/> practice&#59; a religion of morality pure and<lb/> simple and naught else.  But if morality be<lb/> is indeed the kernel of Judaism&#44; it is not the<lb/> whole fruit&#44; as entrusted to our guardianship.<lb/>  The inspired son of Amoz did repeatedly call us<lb/> God&#39;s witnesses&#44; but I cannot agree to the notion&#44;<lb/> that he meant our sending missionaries among<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>gentiles&#44; and that unless we Judaize&#44; in a<lb/> fashion&#44; Christendom and heathendom we forfeit<lb/> the title. I believe that our imperishableness<lb/> upon earth&#44; proves us God&#39;s witnesses&#44; attesting<lb/> that there exists a sole creating Lord&#44; who chose Jacob<lb/> for His servant and Israel for His elect&#44; who<lb/> is our Legislator&#44; our King&#44; our Saviour &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;  That is the lesson often impressed issuing<lb/> from the lips purified by the live&#45;coal at the<lb/> hand of an archangel.  Again&#58; to say<lb/> that Malachi hinted at the effect of our<lb/> missionary work among gentiles&#44; is to draw on<lb/> the imagination.  The last of our prophets<lb/> did say that from the spot&#44; where the sun first<lb/> rises unto that in which it sets last&#44; the name<lb/> of God is <sic>worshipped</sic>&#44; but rather than encourage by<lb/> it a hot house proselytism&#44; the last of our prophets&#44; desired to<lb/> reprove born Jews among his contemporaries&#44; who imagined that they<lb/> could propitiate God&#39;s favor by presenting impure oblations.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>He meant to say that God cares not for hypocritical sacrificial rites for even nations mistaken in<lb/> their outward ceremonials&#44; have their thoughts<lb/> directed to the brightest Power&#44; whom they see not.<lb/>  Beautifully has our poet&#44; Solomon Ben Gabriel&#44; ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;pressed nearly the same idea in his Keter Machut<lb/> &#40;the Royal Crown&#41; &#34;Thou art God and all creation<lb/> is Thy servant and adorer&#44; nor is Thy glory<lb/> lessened because others are <sic>worshipped</sic> besides Thee&#44;<lb/> for&#44; all aim to draw night unto Thee.  But they heathens<lb/> act as if blindfolded.  Their faces turn towards<lb/> the King&#39;s high way&#44; yet unknowingly they<lb/> go astray.  One sinks into a pit&#44; another is<lb/> caught in a snare.  They imagine that they<lb/> can attain their goal&#44; but they fatigue themselves<lb/> in vain.  We&#44; thy servants&#44; by walking following at in Thy light&#44; follow pursue<lb/> the straight path&#44; till we arrive at the court<lb/> of the King&#39;s palace.&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>Now I will not contradict the assertion that<lb/> some Talmudical maxims support the suppo&#45;<lb/>&#45;sition that the Rabbis had hoped to gain by our<lb/> dispersion a closer union between gentilism and Judaism&#44;<lb/> but admitting it&#44; I am authorized nevertheless to say<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>that altogether the Sages did not favor prosely&#45;<lb/>&#45;tism&#44; fearing undoubledly interested motives.<lb/>  And I have frequently been surprised at a false<lb/> application of a saying which reads as follows thus.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;A charity showed the<lb/> Almighty to Israel&#44; when He scattered them<lb/> among nations.&#34;  The real meaning of which is<lb/> that had the Lord delivered us into the power<lb/> of a single potentate&#44; or a single people&#44; dire<lb/> persecution&#44; centred in one spot&#44; would soon<lb/> have annihilated us&#44; but exiled through through<lb/> different countries&#44; we discovered outlets to escape<lb/> a total extermination.  Witness the woeful<lb/> episodes in our history through during the middle ages.<lb/></p>  
            <p>I may here be naturally asked&#58; &#34;Do you<lb/> not believe then that mankind will finally<lb/> arrive at the knowledge which we Jews have<lb/> treasured at the price of un<sic>equalled</sic> sufferings&#63;<lb/>  Will the day never dawn&#59; when instead of being<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p>despised we shall be honored&#63; instead of hearing<lb/> the name of Jew accompanied with a curse&#44; blessings<lb/> will be showered down upon the martyred people&#63;<lb/>  I do trustingly look for the <sic>fulfilment</sic> of God&#39;s<lb/> promises &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> I behold that accomplishment in the aspirations<lb/> of souls&#44; whose flight in search of eternal justice&#44;<lb/> reached the heaven of heavens&#44; and heard the oath declaration<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;By My name I swear&#44; saith the Lord&#44; that to<lb/> me shall every knee bow&#44; by Me every tongue<lb/> shall swear.&#34;  But not by offering Christianity<lb/> a diluted Judaism&#44; a phantom&#44; denuded of all flesh&#44;<lb/> will that end be achieved.  Mr Simon may offer tender<lb/> in all sincerity what he imagines an improvement on the<lb/> fallacious doctrine of a trinity and the blasphemies that<lb/> are its inseparable attendants&#44; but weekly gatherings<lb/> interspersed with weak kneed and half hearted Jews&#44; will<lb/> accomplish no permanent good&#44; if they may not&#44; as<lb/> it has been intimated&#44; intensify the antisemitism<lb/> cropping out everywhere.  We will always<lb/> welcome those for whose happiness we pray&#44; even<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="14"/>
            <p>our &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;righteous proselytes&#44;&#34; and<lb/> history has recorded many such of whom<lb/> we may well be proud&#44; but not Sunday<lb/> services proselytes&#44; not mixed marriages converts&#44;<lb/> will strengthen Judaism&#44; and glorify the God<lb/> who selected the seed of His friend Abraham<lb/> the Hebrew&#44; as the undying witness of His<lb/> Oneness and omnipotence.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
