<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF4_7</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1893" source="" attested="yes">1893</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_7_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_7_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_7_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_7_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_7_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_7_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_7_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_7_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_7_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_7_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_7_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_7_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_7_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_7_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_7_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_7_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>A lecture to children<lb/> on Parashat Vayer&#225;.<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  The premises of the argument advanced by<lb/> a clergyman&#44; and reported this week in some of our<lb/> dailies&#44; are entirely false&#44; but its conclusion accords<lb/> precisely with the views I hold.  He stated that when<lb/> the founder of his religion said &#34;Suffer little children to come<lb/> to me&#44;&#34; he the first taught how the future of society de&#45;<lb/>&#45;pends on the judicious training of the young.  Had he<lb/> remembered the oft&#45;repeated command of Moses&#44; to render<lb/> our offspring conversant with the history&#44; the tenets&#44; and<lb/> <sic>cerimonial</sic> ordinances of the revealed Law&#44; he would have<lb/> qualified his assertion.  Had he more especially been acquain&#45;<lb/>&#45;ted with the writings of our Sages&#44; in which the following<lb/> pithy sentence occurs &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;The world at large&#44; subsists only through that which is breathed<lb/> into the minds of school&#45;children&#34;&#44; he would have discovered&#44;<lb/> that in most instances&#44; the parables&#44; maxims and even<lb/> the phraseology of the book of a new dispensation&#44; are<lb/> but a reproduction of the lessons anciently taught by Judaism.<lb/>  Nevertheless&#44; all who think rightly&#44; will assent to his<lb/> reasoning&#44; by which he intended to prove that the pulpit<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>should be&#44; more frequently&#44; than it is&#44; devoted to the<lb/> education of children&#44; forming as they do&#44; an essential part<lb/> of the Congregation.  He argued with some force&#44; that<lb/> unless this be made to feel the importance of their<lb/> presence&#44; they will continue listless&#44; to their detriment&#44;<lb/> and that of the community in which they live.<lb/></p>
            <p>In fact&#44; it has struck me&#44; and it must cannot have<lb/> escaped your observation&#44; that they do not evince sufficient<lb/> attention to interest in ordinary sermons&#44; either because the subject<lb/> treated is above their comprehension&#44; or because the<lb/> language employed is wanting in simplicity.<lb/>  To correct this defect&#44; almost unavoidable in public<lb/> pleading&#44; the addressing of a lad who reached his thirte&#45;<lb/>&#45;enth year&#44; may be considered an appropriate&#44; and<lb/> therefore welcome custom.  The practice&#44; though new<lb/> among us&#44; is by no means&#44; an innovation&#44; and the<lb/> result ought certainly to commend it to general<lb/> favor.  For&#44; it seems that to enlists the attention<lb/> both of the party him immediately concerned&#44; and of his coevals.<lb/>  And this&#44; I would say to all of you&#44; my dear young friends&#44;<lb/> is my principal object.  You should think that<lb/> the words spoken to one separately&#44; are applicable<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>to all indiscriminately&#59; so that through the Bar Mitzva<lb/> you should also learn betimes how to perform religious<lb/> duties.  If I&#44; for instance&#44; in my endeavouring to accomplish<lb/> some good&#44; warn one of your own age against falling into a<lb/> sin now a days prevalent&#59; If I quote the Bible to<lb/> show that disrespect to parents&#44; is a crime that cannot go<lb/> unpunished&#44; you should likewise take the lesson to heart&#44;<lb/> and feel how wicked it is to repay evil for good&#44; to be<lb/> unthankful to those who&#44; under God&#44; gave us life and<lb/> support&#44; watched over the preservation of our health&#44; spent<lb/> anxious days and sleepless nights when we were stretched<lb/> on a bed of sickness&#44; and rejoiced above all temporal gain&#44;<lb/> when the Lord sent healing to our bodies.  If I&#44; to offer a<lb/> bright example of obedience due to parents&#44; relate some<lb/> event recorded in the Scriptures&#44; you should bear in mind<lb/> that the volumes to which I have reference&#44; are not the<lb/> instructors of any one of us especially&#44; but of all&#44;<lb/> without distinction of age&#44; or sex&#44; or condition in life.<lb/>  Now&#44; my dear little friends&#44; while engaged in this topic&#44;<lb/> I would like to point out a narrative which we have<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>read in the section of this Sabbath.  You will see in<lb/> it&#44; how far love for one&#39;s parents&#44; when joint with the<lb/> fear of the Lord&#44; can influence a child&#39;s conduct.<lb/></p>
            <p>You no doubt have heard of the great trial to which the<lb/> fate of Abraham was put.  Never expecting to have<lb/> a child by his beloved Sarah&#44; he experienced the happiness<lb/> of embracing a son&#44; that she bore to him&#44; when he had<lb/> already grown old.  Much care was taken that Isaac<lb/> should from his infancy associate only with the good&#44; for&#44;<lb/> God had declared that through that seed&#44; all the families<lb/> of the earth&#44; would finally be blessed.  So strict were<lb/> his parents father and mother in that respect&#44; that they found it necessary<lb/> to separate him from the company of his step&#45;brother&#44;<lb/> who showed signs of an unruly disposition.  The child<lb/> of promise grew to be had become a lad.  Abraham kept him often<lb/> by his side&#44; that he might learn the adoration of the<lb/> true God.  Sarah watched his every step.  Both bestowed<lb/> on their son the tenderest affection.  But just at that the<lb/> period that the results of a correct education&#44; begin<lb/> to be noticed&#44; and the child is endeared still more to the<lb/> hearts of his parents&#44; just then&#44; a voice&#44; which Abraham<lb/> well understood&#44; was heard to excla cry out.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>&#34;Take now thy son&#44; thine only one&#44; he whom though lovest&#44;<lb/> Isaac&#59; and get thee to the land of Moriah&#44; and offer him<lb/> as a burnt&#45;offering upon one of the mountains&#44; which I will<lb/> tell thee of&#34;  You know&#44; how that father left his joyful<lb/> home.  For three long days he journeyed&#44; in search of the place<lb/> where he would slay his only son&#44; and let his flesh be consumed<lb/> by a devouring fire.  Father and child&#44; <sic>travelled</sic> together through<lb/> uninhabited regions.  Abraham looking intently for the sacred spot&#44;<lb/> in which he should perform his great sacrifice to his God.<lb/>  Isaac imagining he had been summoned to witness some<lb/> extraordinary act of divine worship.  At length&#44; a light<lb/> from above revealed to the patriarch the mountain&#44; whither<lb/> he should direct his steps.  The altar is raised&#44; the word<lb/> is set in order&#44; the human victim is bound&#44; the knife is<lb/> raised.  Faith could not be tried further.  Abraham<lb/> has won the title of &#34;the friend of God&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;; and<lb/> we may well experience a noble pride in claiming such<lb/> an ancestor&#44; but while the merits of that sainted man<lb/> will always stand before the throne of God&#44; and to the end<lb/> of time&#44; benefit us&#44; his lineal descendants&#44; I fain<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>would that you learnt properly to value the virtue<lb/> of his son Isaac.  Holy Writ is silent regarding<lb/> that which transpired during those three days journey.<lb/>  It leaves us to conceive what feelings must have struggled<lb/> within the breast of that dutiful son&#44; when the suspicion<lb/> began to rise that he was the intended offering.<lb/>  &#34;And Isaac spoke to Abraham his father&#44; and said &#34;Father&#44;&#34;<lb/> and he said &#34;How am I my son.&#34;  And he said &#34;Behold the<lb/> fire and the wood&#44; but where is the lamb for the burnt&#45;<lb/>offering&#63;&#34;  And Abraham said &#34;God will provide himself<lb/> a lamb for a burnt&#45;offering&#44; my son&#44; and they both went<lb/> together&#34;.  Not a word of murmur is uttered.  Not a<lb/> motion betraying resistance is shown.  The father wills it&#44;<lb/> God has so ordained.  Let the steel cut the threads of life.<lb/>  Let the father&#44; so pregnant with happiness be renounced.<lb/>  Let one stroke&#44; extinguish the joyous hopes&#44; with the light<lb/> of existence.  Can such filial love be <sic>equalled</sic>&#63;  Can<lb/> such religious sentiments be surpassed&#63;  Surely he who possessed<lb/> them&#44; may be chosen as a study for all who have<lb/> a father and a mother to respect.  None will have their<lb/> fidelity to duty tested so severely as Isaac&#39;s&#44; but many may&#44;<lb/> at times&#44; be called upon to sacrifice their own inclinations<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>to obey their fathers&#44; they may be required to yield some<lb/> anticipated pleasure to gratify their mothers.  At those<lb/> moments&#44; let them look upon the scene presented<lb/> in the twenty second Chapter of Exodus Genesis&#59; and think<lb/> how trifling is the prah self&#45;denial they are demanded<lb/> to practice&#44; when contrasted with that exercised by<lb/> Abraham&#39;s son.  Let them search further in the good<lb/> book&#44; and they will perceive that to respect our parents<lb/> is to obey God.  For&#44; the righteous deed of Isaac has been<lb/> registered in the heavenly pages as a proof of his having<lb/> kept the fear of God the Lord before his eyes.  Therefore it is<lb/> that at the solemn season of our year&#44; when we ask<lb/> forgiveness for our sins&#44; we call upon the Almighty<lb/> as He whom Isaac feared &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  You<lb/> cannot&#44; my dear young friends&#44; you cannot be religious<lb/> and slight your father and mother.  A human<lb/> king will surely be provoked to anger if those he ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;pointed to distribute his favors meet with contempt.<lb/>  In like manner with the Ruler of the Universe be<lb/> wrathful if the representatives of his divine good&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness upon earth&#44; are not duly honored and<lb/> obeyed.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>You&#44; O Bar Mitzvah ought most deeply to be impressed<lb/> with the truth to which I have just given expression.<lb/>  For twice within a short space of time&#44; did your parents<lb/> believe that God sought at their hands a heart&#45;rend&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing sacrifice.  Isaac&#45;&#45;like you&#44; their only son&#44;<lb/> stood on the verge of death.  What anguish they<lb/> experienced&#44; who watched your grappling with a ter&#45;<lb/>&#45;rific disease&#33;  What prayers went up to heaven&#44;<lb/> for your recovery&#33;  What heaving of the breast with<lb/> indescribable emotions&#44; when you gave signs of<lb/> returning consciousness&#33;.... The trial has come to an<lb/> end.  And if the state of your health has not suffered your<lb/> being prepared as customary for the celebration of this<lb/> day&#44; you have been permitted to visit the house of God<lb/> and thank His holy name&#44; &#34;who hath given us His law.&#34;<lb/>  Heed its commands my friend&#33;&#44; none of which is holier<lb/> than the fifth of the Decalogue.  &#34;Honor thy father&#44; and<lb/> thy mother&#44; that thy days may be lengthened&#44; and that<lb/> it may be well with thee.&#34;  It is but little you can<lb/> as yet do to repay their goodness&#44; but obedience and<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>and respect you can and must unwaveringly show.<lb/>  May you lif live long to prove that you were spared<lb/> by Providence for a beneficent purpose.  To cheer the<lb/> declining years and be the support the declining years of your parents&#44; and<lb/> become exemplary in your social and religious conduct.<lb/></p>
            <p>And you all&#44; my beloved hearers&#33; who have been<lb/> pleased to listen to my remarks to the younger branches of<lb/> <sic>of</sic> our Congregation&#44; let me exhort you to say like our father Abraham throughout<lb/> the vicissitude of this terrestrial career.  &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;The Lord<lb/> will provide&#34;.  You may be mentally traversing a<lb/> way&#44; which seems to lead to trouble&#44; say them&#44; like our<lb/> father Abraham &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;the Lord will provide.&#34;<lb/>  You may behold sorrow look looming high at a<lb/> distance.  You may be trembling at the bereaving<lb/> sword lying in wait at your door&#44; say then<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;the Lord will provide&#34;.  Come well weal&#44;<lb/> come woe&#44; le take faith as your staff&#44; you will<lb/> pass unscathed through the devious paths of life&#44; until<lb/> you reach the royal courts&#44; where trust in God&#44;<lb/> will receive a crown of peace and unalloyed<lb/> happiness.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
