<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF7_5</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1886-05" source="" attested="yes">9 May 1886</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_5_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_5_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_5_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_5_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_5_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_5_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_5_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_5_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_5_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_5_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_5_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_5_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>On the strike&#44; on the ministerial conference<lb/>
                of May 3rd&#44; &#38; on the meeting for the seminary May 9th<lb/> 86<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  To let events&#44; that stir up communities&#44;<lb/> go unnoticed by the pulpit&#44; is impossible.  The<lb/> labor question presents difficulties not to be underesti&#45;<lb/>&#45;mated&#44; and it ill becomes inexperienced persons to<lb/> discuss a subject extremely intricate and perplexing.<lb/>  But Religion must necessarily deplore the evils that flow<lb/> from the unsettlement of the vexatious question.<lb/>  While my feelings lean towards the side of the<lb/> working classes&#44; which form the bones and sinews of<lb/> the body politic&#44; my mind tells me that ca&#45;<lb/>&#45;pitalists also have rights which the laborers must are bound<lb/> to respect.  I conceive&#44; however&#44; that if the laws of<lb/> Moses&#44; as beautifully illustrated in the portion section which<lb/> we have just read about the rights duties of the land&#45;<lb/>&#45;owner and the rights privileges of the needy were carried<lb/> out in spirit&#44; if not to the letter&#59; if the rich wealthy em&#45;<lb/>&#45;ployer always evinced a kind and considerate be&#45;<lb/>&#45;haviour&#44; and the employ&#233;e were not prone to<lb/> follow demagogues&#44; matters would might be amicably ad&#45;<lb/>&#45;justed to an incalculable advantage.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>But whatever views persons may<lb/> hold on the causes of the unfortunate strikes<lb/> now still prevailing and on the method of their removal&#44;<lb/> all who possess a sound correct judgment&#44; will look<lb/> with horror upon anarchy.  The heart sick&#45;<lb/>&#45;ens at the report of riotous seditions&#44; of blood&#45;<lb/>&#45;shed and incendiarism&#44; that have no other pur&#45;<lb/>&#45;pose save that of giving vent to a spirit of<lb/> revenge&#44; because the poor are not rich and<lb/> the rich are not poor.  We should blush<lb/> for Europe&#44; whose refuse&#45;gathered in cities of this<lb/> free land&#44; hospitably open to all&#45;&#45;stirs up mu&#45;<lb/>&#45;tiny&#44; and incites the unwary to initiate in America&#44;<lb/> a French reign of terror.</p>  <p>Chicago&#45;&#45;the<lb/> hotbed of fanatical radicalism in politics and<lb/> in religion&#45;&#45;has become the centre of that execrable<lb/> work.  There mad communism is let loose&#44;<lb/> there humanity has been trampled down by a<lb/> hideous monster&#44; miscalled &#34;Socialism&#34;.  But to<lb/> me the confession&#44; which one of the ring leaders of<lb/> mischief made&#44; was a sad revelation.  You may<lb/> have read that when closely questioned&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>the arch <sic>arnachist</sic> said&#58; &#34;I don&#39;t believe in God&#34;.<lb/>  Many centuries ago we were shown the inevi&#45;<lb/>&#45;table issue of Atheism &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;The vile man says in his heart &#39;there is no God&#44;&#39;&#34;<lb/> then the terrible consequences of that avowal are pictured &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;They have become corrupt&#44;<lb/> they act abominably&#44; none does any good&#34;.<lb/>  It was so when the Psalmist penned those<lb/> sentences&#44; and it will manifestly continue so<lb/> on every spot of the earth&#44; while the world<lb/> lasts.<lb/></p>
            <p>But this subject&#44; suggestive of serious thoughts&#44;<lb/> both from a national and a religious stand&#45;point&#44;<lb/> is not that in reference to which I intend<lb/> to detain you briefly.  Two objects more im&#45;<lb/>&#45;mediately connected with us in our character as<lb/> Israelites&#44; have recently engaged my mind.<lb/>  First&#44; a general conference of Hebrew Ministers&#44;<lb/> which I partly attended in New York&#59; secondly&#44;<lb/> a private conference in the same city preliminary<lb/> to a meeting which took place also there last Sunday.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>My action towards the former may<lb/> not unjustly be termed an olive branch&#44; indi&#45;<lb/>&#45;cative of a wish on my part to let a flood<lb/> of theological disputes cease.  Would I could<lb/> honestly say that a like desire pervades the<lb/> hearts of all my colleagues.  But a casual<lb/> visitor at the ministerial conference must have<lb/> perceived from the heat of discussion&#44; that the<lb/> opponents of Mosaics&#45;traditional Judaism try<lb/> with might and main to compel the acceptance<lb/> of their subversive views.  They loudly<lb/> plead for union&#44; but only for such a union<lb/> as they have conceived&#44; as they almost imperative&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly demand.  No concession will they make<lb/> in behalf of a Union which may restore har&#45;<lb/>&#45;mony in the distracted congregations of Israel.<lb/>  All concessions must emanate from those<lb/> who avow their allegiance to ancestral practices&#44;<lb/> who believe that time&#45;honored observances should<lb/> not recklessly be cast aside.<lb/></p>
            <p>When it is asked&#58; &#34;how shall our children be<lb/> trained&#44; that they may remain within the fold&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>&#34;Must they be left in ignorance of laws<lb/> connected with the history of their people&#44; or shall<lb/> they be told that time has rendered such laws null<lb/> and void&#63;&#34;&#44; when that vital query is put&#44; we<lb/> are answered&#58; &#34;Every Rabbi shall follow a plan<lb/> of his own on the tuition of ceremonialism.&#34;  But<lb/> will that course promote Union&#63;  I let those<lb/> who have a mind to think&#44; decide.<lb/></p>
            <p>I admit.  We are all a unit on one point.  There<lb/> can never be a disparity of opinions among Jews<lb/> about the ethics of the Bible.  The most un&#45;<lb/>compromising orthodox dares not have a standard<lb/> of morals differing form that of the most radical<lb/> reformer.  &#34;Righteous balances&#44; righteous measures&#44;&#34;<lb/> righteous judging and righteous speaking&#44; indeed<lb/> all the statutes surpassingly admirable embodied<lb/> in the nineteenth chapter of Leviticus lie at the<lb/> basis of the social edifice.  An Israelite who<lb/> acts in contravention thereof&#44; is guilty of a heinous<lb/> offence.  But are the ordinances in last sabbath&#39;s portion the twenty third chapter<lb/> of Leviticus of so little account&#44; that instruction on them&#44; and the<lb/> enforcing thereof&#44; may be left to every one&#39;s option&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Has the 23rd chapter of Leviticus that great summary of Hebrew ceremonialism&#44; lost its value<lb/> in the eyes of persons born of Hebrew parents&#44; persons<lb/> still claiming the name of Israelites&#63;  Aye&#58;<lb/> here lies the difficulty.  For Chicago&#44; a Sy&#45;<lb/>&#45;nagogue has been definitely closed on the day placed<lb/> foremost in that chapter among the holidays of the<lb/> Lord&#45;&#45;the Sabbath.  From Chicago comes likewise the<lb/> proposition to defer or anticipate festivals&#44; whose<lb/> sanctity is registered in that chapter&#44; in order that<lb/> they may always be celebrated at the most convenient<lb/> time&#45;&#45;Sunday.  They who lightly treat that injunc&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion of fasting on the tenth of the seventh month&#44;<lb/> or sitting in tabernacles on the fifteenth of Tishri&#44;<lb/> would consider the tuition of such behests in our schools&#44;<lb/>as recorded in the 23rd chap. of Levit&#44; a reflection on<lb/> their unjewish conduct.  &#34;We will not staltify ourselves.&#34;<lb/> say they in their hearts.  &#34;We will let each superinten&#45;<lb/>&#45;dent follow the bent of his or her mind&#44; concerning<lb/> those tenets.  The pupils shall not have a text<lb/> book containing rules about the celebration of certain<lb/> of certain days&#44; or the abstaining from certain meats.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>&#34;Enough if they learn and understand ethical<lb/> rules.&#34;  But Yet these genuine disciples of St Paul&#45;&#45;the<lb/> apostatized Saul of Tarsus&#44; who gave precisely nearly the<lb/> same directions about the conversion of the gentiles<lb/> of his time&#44; ask of a ministerial conference&#45;&#45;reckon&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing men of orthodox principles&#44;&#45;&#45;that a delegation be<lb/> sent to the adjourned convention of <sic>Pittsburg</sic> about<lb/> to meet in Cincinnati.  That delegation should act<lb/> in concert with persons pronouncedly heretical&#44; re&#45;<lb/>&#45;garding the adoption of a uniform plan of Sabbath<lb/> School teaching.  The request met with the decided<lb/> antagonism it deserved.  It was not complied with.<lb/>  No&#58; in sorrow I say it&#44; not in anger.  There can never<lb/> be a coalition between individuals who legalize the<lb/> abrogation of statutes binding on Israelites of all<lb/> generations&#44; and the lover of historical Judaism.<lb/>  But there is a means to strengthen the hands of<lb/> the latter&#44; so that the banner unfurled at Sinai belifted<lb/> high&#44; and not suffered to trail the ground.  To<lb/> direct that means judiciously&#44; was the object of a<lb/> private conference held last week in New York.<lb/>  I naturally felt anxious about the result of the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>meeting in the interest of the contemplated seminary in that city.<lb/>  Upon it&#44; I judged&#44; would largely depend the haste&#45;<lb/>&#45;ning or retarding of a scheme&#44; which I have deeply<lb/> at heart.  A holy enthusiasm should be aroused.<lb/>  The choice of wide&#45;hearted trustees&#44; would lead to the<lb/> choice of influential canvassing committees&#44;and these<lb/> would pledge themselves to labor without delay for<lb/> the creation of a fund indispensable to the perpetuity<lb/> of the projected institution.  I confess that the<lb/> mating did not <sic>fulfil</sic> my anticipations.  Too<lb/> much eagerness was displayed by some to gain posts of honor&#44;<lb/> and too little in sacrificing self personal or congregational jealousies for the sake of the<lb/> cause.  Thus time was frittered away&#44; whereas it ought<lb/> to have been seized upon and utilized to a great to a righteous purpose.  But what<lb/> was lost can be recovered.  No more &#91;&#63;&#93;; energy<lb/> and an unselfish determination must urge on the<lb/> work.  Vast means are absolutely necessary.  They must be procured&#44; not by<lb/> promises&#44; which&#44; for a variety reasons of motives&#44; may be broken go unperformed&#44;<lb/> but by tangible&#44; actual gifts of fifties&#44; hundreds and<lb/> thousands.  Then and then only&#44; with God&#39;s blessing&#44;<lb/> will the theological seminary have a permanent realization.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>No gloomy apprehension of failure should<lb/> deter hold back my generous brothers and sisters in faith&#44; who yearn<lb/> for the deliverance of the Torah&#44; now fearfully imperilled.  from<lb/> acting munificently  Without predicting that the<lb/> germs we shall implant will&#44; in every instance&#44; produce<lb/> the fruits looked for&#44; we may reasonably hope that<lb/> precept and example will often strike deep root and yield satisfaction.  It is<lb/> our solemn duty at all events to try to hand down the religion of<lb/> Israel&#44; as our ancestors transmitted it&#44; at greater sacri&#45;<lb/>&#45;fices than we are demanded to make.  With gold at<lb/> our command&#44; we shall through God&#39;s blessing&#44; erect such a monument to Ju&#45;<lb/>&#45;daism in America&#44; as will outlast ages.  &#34;Fealty&#34; shall<lb/> be its name&#59; fealty to Abraham&#45;&#45;the founder of our race&#44;<lb/> the friend of God&#59; fealty to Moses&#44; the deliverer of the<lb/> oppressed slaves&#44; the inspired lawgiver&#44; the benefactor of our<lb/> people&#59; fealty to our prophets&#44; to our sages&#44; to our<lb/> martyrs&#44; to the history past checkered past of forty centuries that has<lb/> made us eternal upon earth.  &#34;Oh&#33; may the gracious<lb/> favor of the Lord our God be with us&#59; the work of<lb/> our hands establish Thou through us&#44; yea&#58; the work<lb/> of our hands establish Thou it.&#34;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
