<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF2_17</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1883" source="" attested="yes">1883</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_17_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_17_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_17_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_17_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_17_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_17_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_17_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_17_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_17_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_17_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_17_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_17_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>On punctual attendance at the Synagogue<lb/>
                for the 23d Anniversary<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  This year has been an exceptional one in<lb/> various ways.  It has been so atmospherically&#44;<lb/> for the weather proved uncommon in this continent&#45;&#45;<lb/>severe storms and snow and frost prevailing in the West<lb/> all spring&#44; while in the East the evidences of an ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;proaching Summer could not be seen till now.  The year<lb/> has been exceptional in the Jewish Calendar&#44; for Pass&#45;<lb/>&#45;over fell nearly at the very end of the period in which<lb/> it can ever happen&#44; according to ancient calculations.<lb/>&#45;&#45;the 24th of April being the full extent<lb/> It has been exceptional in the arrangement of the weekly<lb/> sections of the Pentateuch&#44; for seldom does the portion<lb/> which we have just read precede the feast of<lb/> Pentecost.  Almost always it succeeds our forthcoming holiday.<lb/>  Not less exceptional than was the year was in several<lb/> instances&#44; is the nature of the discourse I am about<lb/> to deliver.  It does not belong to the present season.<lb/>  It may have suited well at the beginning of the term.  It is un&#45;<lb/>&#45;timely at the close of the term.  But if I am un&#45;<lb/>&#45;able to account for the exceptionableness of other<lb/> occurrences&#44; I can give reasons for my delay in saying<lb/> what should have been spoken long before.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>In January the repairing of our sacred edifice<lb/> began&#44; and during the time which it took to complete<lb/> it&#44; scarcely two Sabbaths of sun&#45;shine were ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;perienced.  Still&#44; considering that in addition to that<lb/> fact circumstance&#44; a number of my congregants declined&#44; for mo&#45;<lb/>&#45;tives of their own&#44; to worship in the lower synagogue&#44;<lb/> I had not cause to complain of the attendance.<lb/>  But after we occupied again this beautified <sic>embelished</sic><lb/> building&#44; I had devoutly hoped that a large con&#45;<lb/>&#45;course of my people would be seen therein on each<lb/> returning Sabbath.  In that I was disappointed.<lb/>  Many among my brothers and sisters in faith&#44; who<lb/> formerly came with regularity&#44; have visited this spot<lb/> at intervals or not at all&#59; others were tardy in<lb/> appearing&#44; or they left before the service was concluded.<lb/>  The prayers begin at 9 o&#39;clock&#59; half an hour after that&#44; a few are here.  At 10 the Congregation is yet<lb/> very sparse&#44; and not till much later&#44; many of<lb/> those who mean to attend and remain&#44; are in their<lb/> seats.  Having observed this con&#45;<lb/>&#45;dition of things&#44; I ought to have expressed my<lb/> regret because of it months ago.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>My hearers will deem it entirely out of time to<lb/> refer to it on the Sabbath preceding the season<lb/> in which a number of the <sic>worshippers</sic> leave<lb/> home for places of summer resort&#44; and others who<lb/> remain in town are&#44; curiously strangely enough&#44; in the habit<lb/> of keeping away from Synagogues.  My silence&#44;<lb/> however&#44; was intentional.  I feared to reprice dila&#45;<lb/>toriness&#44; because I discovered that my house is not<lb/> of marble stone proof if that of my neighbor happens to<lb/> be made of glass.  I feared also to allude to<lb/> it&#44; because the fault has been laid at my door.<lb/>  I wished to avoid distasteful discussions and heart&#45;<lb/>burnings.  But now that I shall soon suspend<lb/> lecturing for a while&#44; now that some of my con&#45;<lb/>&#45;gregants will part with me and their sanctuary<lb/> for a time&#44; my words may be felt not as a<lb/> rebuke&#44; but as a reminder and a corrective in<lb/> advance.  It may afford food for thought&#44;<lb/> during an interval of two or three month&#39;s absence.<lb/>  My fellow believers will put their best judgments resolve it in their minds<lb/> to work&#44; and decide whether tardiness in the attendance<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>at the Synagogue is not disrespect to the<lb/> Lord&#44; and a baleful example.  Then they may<lb/> determine to avoid pursuing hereafter the same injurious<lb/> practice.  I shall not cite the<lb/> usage universal among our coreligionists on the eastern side<lb/> of the Atlantic.  Were we to conform with it&#44;<lb/> the principal service we hold would be reduced to a<lb/>....nothingness.  Were we to open the Synagogue<lb/> on the Sabbath morning in winter at 8 o&#39;clock&#44;<lb/> and in summer at 7&#44; scarcely the prescribed quorum<lb/> or Min&#225;n would be present.  We would most<lb/> assuredly be deprived of the main element in public<lb/> worship&#45;&#45;the women of Israel.  I do not Let me imagine that I speak with<lb/> sarcasm&#44; but I am in real earnestness.  No incentive<lb/> whatever in the world have I to play the courtier&#59;<lb/> to fawn and flatter&#58; I do say honestly say that the absence<lb/> of Jewesses from the Sanctuary&#45;&#45;so very general<lb/> in Europe&#45;&#45;would be fatal to the interests of<lb/> Judaism in America.  It is in a vast degree&#44;<lb/> directly or indirectly&#44; through them that public con&#45;<lb/>&#45;vocations are solemnized with somewhat of an attend&#45;<lb/>&#45;ance and with unction and decorum.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>It is in a vast degree through the influence of<lb/> the pulpit on them&#44; that what concerns the welfare<lb/> of our faith congregationally&#44; educationally and bene&#45;<lb/>&#45;ficially is promoted.  No&#58; We cannot dispense<lb/> with that element&#44; and we cannot therefore follow the<lb/> rule which demands the recital of the morning service<lb/> at an early hour.  But 9 or 30 minutes<lb/> after it&#44; or 10 o&#39;clock ought not to be considered too early.<lb/>  For much as I regret that the rehearsal of the portion of the ritual<lb/> preceding the Shemang and Amidah&#45;&#45;and which is<lb/> beautiful&#45;&#45;should be left to a small number&#44; I<lb/> would be glad if when the Sepher Torah is taken<lb/> out of the holy Ark&#44; all were present and joined<lb/> in the hymn which greets its public reading.<lb/>  Let my suggestion be pondered over and acted upon<lb/> at the fall season.  It may perhaps create an<lb/> impression&#44; just because it is made on the Sabbath<lb/> prior to the time in which many temporarily leave<lb/> the Synagogue&#44; and on the twenty third anniversary<lb/> of the erection of our recently embellished beautified structure.<lb/></p> 
            <p>But I cannot pass by as unworthy of my<lb/> attention the complaints of persons who have a right<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>to speak&#44; because they honor themselves by honoring<lb/> the Synagogue.  As I have intimated&#44; it is alleged<lb/> that I ought to shorten the prayers&#44; and begin them<lb/> later&#44; and I ought to modernize the service and<lb/> render it attractive.  Two requests&#44; which&#44; whenever<lb/> made&#44; a deep sense of self reproach lays hold of<lb/> me.  I feel that I have no right to oppose place<lb/> with my settled views&#44; however well founded&#44; to in antagonism to demands of<lb/> many.  I may contend that what is wished of<lb/> me&#44; does not lie in my power singly to do.  I may<lb/> call it presumptuous in men who neither possess<lb/> the authority nor the ability to break down what<lb/> has stood for centuries&#44; to go on indulging in ex&#45;<lb/>perimental &#34;Reform&#44;&#34; in order to draw crowds.  But<lb/> when the popular will is strong in favor of that course&#44;<lb/> there seems to be but one duty for the individual who<lb/> dissents to follow.  You understand me well clearly.  But<lb/> as I cannot quit&#44; and being a new life on the verge of<lb/> old age&#44; I derive some satisfaction from the lessons<lb/> of experience.  I perceive that in spite of changes<lb/> continual and rampant&#44; the desirable goal for the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>attainment of which I am asked to assume<lb/> prerogatives that I do not possess&#44; is just as far as ever.<lb/>  Aye&#58; The impediments are like in a different direction than contended.  They are not<lb/> to be sought and overcome in a shorter or longer liturgy&#44; in<lb/> a more or less harmonious singing.  I have often pointed<lb/> them out those impediments hindrances but I do not purpose discussing the vexatious<lb/> subject this morning.  To all who<lb/> are willing to bear with tread the old beaten path&#44; not&#45;<lb/>&#45;withstanding its drawbacks&#44; rather than venture upon<lb/> ways which have brought us no nearer to a spiri&#45;<lb/>&#45;tualizing Judaism&#44; but have widened divisions&#44; I commend<lb/> the cause I have pleaded&#45;&#45;a punctual attendance in<lb/> this Synagogue.  I hope that when all<lb/> shall revisit our consecrated courts in perfect health&#44;<lb/> they will carry out the suggestions I have made on<lb/> the Sabbath before Pentecost&#44; and the twenty third<lb/> anniversary of our consecrated edifice.<lb/></p>
                <p>I have one request more to make&#44; which may also<lb/> be deemed much out of time.  But to have<lb/> set it forth before&#44; would have been indiscretion&#59; to<lb/> postpone it might be to defeat the object in con&#45;<lb/>&#45;templation.  I am assured that notwith&#45; despite<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>&#45;standing my urgent solicitation last fall&#44; to<lb/> provide for the erection of a new Succah or tabernacle<lb/> at the same time that an amount would be raised for<lb/> the repairing of the Synagogue&#44; we will be com&#45;<lb/>&#45;pelled to ignore altogether the Mosaic ordinance for<lb/> want of means.  I was informed of that deprecatory circumstance shortly<lb/> after our having reentered this hallowed edifice&#44; but<lb/> naturally I dared not then hint at a new collect&#45;<lb/>&#45;ion.  It would have been regarded an imposition.<lb/>  But unless I seize this opportunity&#44; I may become<lb/> myself guilty of a dilatoriness attended with the<lb/> abolition of a Biblical precept.  I must try to keep<lb/> clear of that sin.  If my brothers and sisters in<lb/> faith who may pleasurably meet in their various circles during the summer<lb/> season&#44; will form themselves into a committee of the whole&#44;<lb/> and collect from one another a small contribution&#44; ere<lb/> the solemn festivals of Tishri arrive&#44; a sufficiency will have<lb/> been gathered to meet the necessary expense.  We shall<lb/> then celebrate the feast of Tabernacles&#44; as heretofore&#44; agree&#45;<lb/>ably to the Law and with religious satisfaction to ourselves.<lb/>  &#40;Conclude with a benediction.&#41;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
