<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF6_6</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_6_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_6_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_6_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_6_2v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 1 sheet<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For a funeral<lb/></p>
            
            <p>Brethren&#33;  The occasion which has brought us together is as<lb/> distressing as it is extraordinary.  We&#44; Israelites of America&#44; were never<lb/> made to lament a circumstance casting such gloom upon our<lb/> communities&#44; as that of which the silent coffin we surround<lb/> is the reminder.  But I have not intention to harass your<lb/> feelings with a description of that <sic>woful</sic> night on which many<lb/> of our fellow&#45;believers were hurried into the chamber of death.<lb/>  Enough has each of you been saddened by picturing to himself the<lb/> agony and despair of the hour&#44; when angry waves tore wives from<lb/> their husband&#39;s arms&#44; and lashed tender children into the bottom&#45;<lb/>&#45;less deep.  I have not come to bewail the fate of those<lb/> among my people&#44; who perished in the catastrophe which bereaved<lb/> hundreds in our land.  I have come in obedience to a solemn<lb/> duty&#44; demanding I should give a brother in faith an honored<lb/> burial.  Would that my ardent prayer had been answered&#44;<lb/> and the sea had returned all its victims to mother&#45;earth&#33;<lb/>  Would that she who kept her vow and accompanied this man<lb/> through the journey of life&#44; could also be now interred in the same<lb/> consecrated ground&#33;  Would that the young and innocent she bore<lb/> to him&#44; could lie next to their deceased parents&#33;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>But we must bow to the will of that Being&#44; whose decrees<lb/> are <sic>unsearcheable</sic>&#44; and whom none dare ask &#34;What doest Thou&#63;&#34;.<lb/>  Still trusting in His gracious favor&#44; through which the longing<lb/> of our souls may be fulfilled&#44; let us duly perform the ob&#45;<lb/>&#45;sequies of the brother providentially drawn out of a watery<lb/> grave.  Let us perform them thoughtfully&#44; that the me&#45;<lb/>&#45;lancholy office may profit the survivors.  We all&#44;<lb/> my dear coreligionists&#44; will benefit by the event&#44; if it will<lb/> serve to check our vicious inclinations&#44; teaching us that death<lb/> may be treading upon our heels&#44; while we madly run after<lb/> vanities.  That serious consideration&#44; will cause us&#44; at<lb/> times&#44; to halt and measure the way we follow.  Perhaps<lb/> we have gone beyond the bounds of justice.  Should death<lb/> overtake us&#44; while we are engaged in retracing our steps&#44; and<lb/> removing every vestige of our evil&#45;doings&#44; we may have<lb/> nothing to fear&#59; for&#44; God&#44; speaking through our conscience&#44; will<lb/> give us the comforting assurance of His forgiveness and<lb/> mercy.  but if we are seized upon by the Divine Messen&#45;<lb/>&#45;ger&#44; while in the pursuit of selfish ends&#44; Oh then&#44; we<lb/> may well trouble to be taken before the Judgment&#45;seat<lb/> of Him who hates iniquity&#44; and abhors the impenitent.<lb/>  Now&#44; my hearers&#33;  I did not know our brother in faith&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>so prematurely and without any premonition snatched<lb/> away form the world.  It would therefore ill&#45;become me to<lb/> praise or to censure.  Most likely&#44; he possessed qualities of<lb/> which scarcely a son of Israel is destitute&#44; that is&#44; strong attach&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment to one&#39;s family and people.  And to promote the welfare<lb/> of the former&#44; and to effectually assist the latter&#44; he may have<lb/> given labor and means.  Those traits characteristic of the<lb/> Jew&#44; can&#44; under God&#44; be a spiritual ladder carrying our brother&#39;s<lb/> soul on high.  And I verily believe that if its ascent to heaven&#44;<lb/> was to be hindered by human sin&#44; the unutterable suffering<lb/> which Elias Manheimer endured when the Schiller was<lb/> wrecked on Scylly&#39;s islands&#44; must prove the atoning power&#44;<lb/> clearing away every impediment to the attaining of eternal<lb/> glory.  I shall say nothing more concerning the lamented<lb/> dead.  But it is my duty&#44; as it is my wish to speak<lb/> of the living&#44; of the dear beings&#44; who have been left fatherless<lb/> and motherless&#59; of those two innocent creatures&#44; suddenly bereft<lb/> of their natural guardians&#44; and guides and protectors.  Their sad<lb/> fate appeals to our warmest sympathies&#44; and here over the<lb/> coffin of their loving father&#44; I ask all to look towards them<lb/> with yearning compassion.  But specially you&#44; their maternal<lb/> uncles&#44; I ask&#44; in virtue of my calling&#44; to promise before Israel&#39;s<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>God to direct your efforts in making the orphans happy.<lb/>  Lead them steadily but gently in the path of religion&#59; spare none<lb/> of the means bequeathed to them&#44; in enriching their minds with<lb/> the knowledge of what is useful and profitable.  Have them<lb/> taught in the language and contents of the holy book&#59; let<lb/> them early imbibe in the house of our Lord lessons of humility&#44;<lb/> of piety and beneficence&#59; and you will have been the real<lb/> executors of their parents&#39; will.  Your acting thus will be incom&#45;<lb/>&#45;parably better for your dear charges&#44; than your investing<lb/> their silver and gold in a manner&#44; <sic>yeilding</sic> an interest a hundred<lb/> fold above your anticipations.  Oh may the Almighty stren&#45;<lb/>&#45;gthen your hands&#44; when laboring for the moral advancement<lb/> of your bereaved young relatives.  May He brighten your in&#45;<lb/>&#45;tellects with a light from above&#44; that you may always dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;cover the fittest course to pursue&#44; and never swerve from it<lb/> to the right or to the left.  May your words and your<lb/> example instill into the hearts of your nephew and <sic>neice</sic> sen&#45;<lb/>&#45;timents of reverence for what is sacred&#44; and of detestation for what<lb/> is false and profane.  The sainted father and mother of dear<lb/> little Benjamin and Ida will&#44; from heaven look down approvingly<lb/> upon your conduct&#44; and pray at the throne of God for your length of days &#38; continued prosperity.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
