<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF10_5</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_5_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_5_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_5_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_5_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_5_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_5_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_5_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_5_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_5_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_5_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_5_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_5_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_5_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_5_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_5_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_5_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>An explanatory lecture<lb/>
                on<lb/>
                Parashat Shemot.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  I purpose this Sabbath to take a cursory view<lb/> of the section we have read&#44; explaining as I proceed what<lb/> may need elucidation&#44; and referring to that from which<lb/> we some useful lesson may be drawn.<lb/></p>
            <p>The first book of the Pentateuch closes with a description<lb/> of the happy state enjoyed by Joseph both socially and<lb/> domestically&#44; and of the honors he received at his death&#44;<lb/> as the embalming of his body notably shows.  The<lb/> second book which we have just begun&#44; relates&#44; at<lb/> the outset&#44; that after the brothers of the viceroy of Egypt<lb/> and their contemporaries had passed away from the earth&#44;<lb/> a circumstance arose which wrought much injury against<lb/> the descendants of Jacob.  A new dynasty succeeded<lb/> in establishing itself over the land of Mizraim&#44; and<lb/> whereas the kings of a former race had favored the<lb/> Hebrews because of the advantages which the country<lb/> had derived from one of their ancestors&#44; the rulers now<lb/> in power ignoring past history&#44; followed the opposite<lb/> course.  Seeing a people of foreign origin increase<lb/> amazingly&#44; they harbored suspicions.  They feared that<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>in the event of an invasion&#44; or an insurrection&#44; the same<lb/> people might make common cause with the enemy&#44; and<lb/> even if temporarily subdued&#44; they might leave the country which they<lb/> enriched with their industry.  That apprehension sug&#45;<lb/>&#45;gested a wicked device.  The Israelites must be reduced<lb/> to a degraded condition.  Spurned and contemned because<lb/> of the menial services performed&#44; they would be incapable<lb/> of manly thoughts.  Overburdened with labor&#44; they would<lb/> gradually sink under its weight&#44; and <sic>deminish</sic> in number.<lb/>  Now&#59; when we bear in mind that the sufferings of our<lb/> progenitors were occasioned by their having closely clung toge&#45;<lb/>&#45;ther&#44; and that for upwards of a hundred years&#45;&#45;which<lb/> must necessarily have elapsed since the family of Jacob had<lb/> died off&#45;&#45;a mere tradition sufficed to prevent any amal&#45;<lb/>&#45;gamation with idolaters&#44; we must bestow a meed of praise<lb/> on such religious constancy.  We may admit with the<lb/> Rabbins that a miraculous deliverance was well earned<lb/> by those who long remained distinct in name&#44; in language<lb/> and in character.  Only in one instance does the Pentateuch<lb/> chronicle a deviation from that faithful demeanor&#44; and<lb/> as to demonstrate its ill&#45;effects&#44; it records that how from an<lb/> intermarriage with a heathen&#44; the man was born who became<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>guilty of blasphemy.  The parting words of Joseph<lb/> had been indelibly stamped on the memory of his descend&#61;<lb/>&#45;ants.  From father to son was handed down the promise<lb/> that for the God of the patriarchs would surely visit those that who<lb/> had gone to soju sojurn sojourn in Egypt&#44; and bring them<lb/> form thence to a land of their own possession.  That celestial<lb/> declaration imparted a buoyancy to the mind which kept it<lb/> afloat amid a sl sea of troubles.  For&#44; notwithstanding<lb/> the extreme severity of the work to which they were<lb/> subjected&#44; the Israelites grew numerous and full of<lb/> vigour.  Therefore did the tyrant resort to an expedient<lb/> which he imagined it would accomplish his scheme&#44; without<lb/> being himself <sic>himself</sic> exposed to public odium.  It was after<lb/> he perceived that the secret agents he had employed&#44; refused<lb/> to imbue their hands in innocent blood&#44; that he<lb/> threw off the mask&#44; and commanded that all male&#45;<lb/> infants be cast into the Nile.  How long that inhu&#45;<lb/>&#45;man mandate continued in force we cannot easily ascer&#45;<lb/>&#45;tain&#59; but it seems that it was of short duration.<lb/>  For&#44; it had not evidently been issued at the birth of<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Aaron&#44; which occurred three years prior to that of Moses&#44;<lb/> and after the wondrous rescuing of the latter&#44; it does<lb/> not appear that it was further put into execution.<lb/>  Still its effect on Hebrew families must need shave<lb/> been crushing.  If we credit an ancient legend&#44; Amram<lb/> who had already two children by Jochebed&#44; was terrified by<lb/> that edict into a total separation from his wife&#44; and only<lb/> the reasoning of his daughter Miriam awakened him to<lb/> a sense of the injustice he had committed.  But how<lb/> must the hearts of those parents have sunk within them&#44;<lb/> when their reunion gave existence to a son&#33;  Who<lb/> but the compassionate Lord beheld their watching in the<lb/> dead of night to prevent the infant cry so fatal to their<lb/> happiness&#63;  At every sound they startled.  Every step<lb/> inspired them with dread.  Yet for three months the<lb/> remarkably quiet nature of the child&#44; enabled them to<lb/> evade the vigilance of Pharaoh&#39;s officers.  But at the<lb/> expiration of that period&#44; concealment became impossible.<lb/>  With anguish of spirit but not hopelessly did the mother<lb/> fashion the chest wherein her babe would be shut.<lb/>  She places doubtless had heard from her sires&#44; of the <sic>marvellous</sic><lb/> salvation of Noah&#44; and she also shaped an ark which<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>might&#44; through a heavenly power&#44; defy the surging<lb/> waters.  She placed it on the banks of the river&#44; and<lb/> turned homeward.  Her presence at that spot might<lb/> arouse suspicion.  But strong in faith&#44; she placed<lb/> bid her young daughter watch at a distance.<lb/>  A hand is stretched out.  Her son will not be con&#45;<lb/>&#45;signed to an untimely death grave.  The seed of wicked&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness has singularly <sic>yeilded</sic> a righteous fruit.  From<lb/> the stock of Pharaoh&#44; a branch issued forth&#44; whereon<lb/> Moses held for safety.  Nurtured in a lowly<lb/> dwelling&#44; he was from thence conveyed to a palace.<lb/>  The adopted son of a Princess imbibed rare knowledge.<lb/>  For&#44; the learning of a sacerdotal caste in Egypt&#44; was<lb/> confessedly great.  The favored youth must have been<lb/> initiated in the arts and sciences withheld in the days<lb/> of yore from the multitudes&#44; and imparted solely to the<lb/> privileged few.  But if his mind had been richly<lb/> stored&#44; the education of his heart proved itself most<lb/> complete.  For his nature was open to the tenderest<lb/> emotions&#44; while it revolted against every act of injustice.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>The sentiment which &#91;&#63;&#93; prompted him to fell to the<lb/> ground the dastardly Egyptian who struck the defenseless<lb/> Hebrew&#44; impelled him likewise to rebuke the Israelite<lb/> who wrongfully attacked his fellow&#45;believer.  And the<lb/> same human feeling was a <sic>stimulous</sic> to his manly deed<lb/> at the well in the country of Midian.<lb/></p>
            <p>Not infrequently we meet self&#45;sufficiency as the ac&#45;<lb/>&#45;companiment of a high&#45;spirit.  He who braves dan&#45;<lb/>&#45;ger while engaged in a righteous cause&#44; may be also likely<lb/> to entertain an overweening opinion of his own powers.<lb/>  Moses was daring&#44; but withal meek in the extreme.<lb/>  Reared in the splendour of royalty&#44; he did not disdain<lb/> to take a shepherd&#39;s crook&#44; and go in quest of pasture.<lb/>  The wilderness of Sinai offered some fertile spots&#44; wherein<lb/> his flock might feed and lie down.  Thither he<lb/> wended his steps.  Wrapped in solitude his soul must<lb/> have sorrowed&#44; in contemplating meditating on the oppression<lb/> of his brethren&#59; and &#91;&#63;&#93; forth supplications for their<lb/> speedy deliverance.  But....why does he gaze so<lb/> intently on yonder hill&#63;  The apparition is truly<lb/> un stupendous&#33;  A bush unconsumed amidst a blazing<lb/> fire.  He moves forward.  His eyes must search<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>into a cause so supernatural.  Could the bush<lb/> typify a feeble nation&#44; and the blazing fire its<lb/> fierce enemies&#63;  But how can it remain unscathed&#63;<lb/>  Nay&#44; by a divine influence resting therein.  A voice<lb/> calls.  Moses&#44; Moses thou art the celestially chosen Libera&#45;<lb/>&#45;tor of an oppressed race.  Through thy instrumentality<lb/> will be fulfilled the coe covenant established &#91;&#63;&#93;<lb/> with the righteous patriarchs.  Their progeny will believe<lb/> when thou presentest thyself as the messenger of that<lb/> Being&#44; whose name refer signifies his eternity&#44; and<lb/> whom tradition has taught to recognize as the God of<lb/> Abraham&#44; Isaac and Jacob.  Fear none.  Thy<lb/> staff will become a serpent&#44; with which to scourge the<lb/> &#91;&#63;&#93;&#44; while it will lead the upright to the<lb/> way of freedom.  Thy hand will at times uplift<lb/> the degraded&#44; at others it will strike the d obdurate<lb/> as with leprosy.  And to prove furthermore that the<lb/> elements will be subservient to thy will&#44; in the discharge<lb/> of thy undertaking&#44; thou wilt be enabled to change<lb/> water into blood.  But the meekest of men<lb/> distrust his powers.  He pleads his inab incapacity<lb/> by reason of his present condition in life.  He alleges<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>the difficulty he will encounter in inspiring his brethren<lb/> with confidence.  He dwells on his lack of eloquence&#44;<lb/> and after all arguments advanced are set at rest&#44; he<lb/> betakes himself to prayer.  He entreats the Lord that<lb/> one might be sent whose agency could not possibly<lb/> fail&#59; intimating that as an angel effected the destruction<lb/> of Sodom and the salvation of Lot&#44; so now a celestial<lb/> being might be commissioned to overthrow the king&#45;<lb/>&#45;dom of the Pharaohs&#44; and let the bondmen go free.<lb/>  But more than we ourselves know&#44; Our Maker understands<lb/> the powers of which we are capable.  He who has framed<lb/> our minds sees how <sic>vigourous</sic> or how feeble are the<lb/> faculties we possess.  Moses was beyond question<lb/> the fittest man&#44; by nature and education to be whom<lb/> an authority divine should be delegated.  Who will<lb/> now dispute his preeminence as a leader and a prophet&#63;<lb/>  To quiet his agitated spirits&#44; he was promised a<lb/> coadjutor&#44; but it soon became apparent that he was<lb/> the soul of that mission so marvellous in all its features&#44;<lb/> so momentous in its consequences.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Taking leave of his father&#45;in&#45;law&#44; Moses departed<lb/> for Egypt.  But almost to show human liability to<lb/> error&#44; the Scriptures relate how at the very hour he<lb/> had been selected for a high purpose&#44; the servant of<lb/> the Lord in his anxiety to <sic>fulfil</sic> one duty&#44; became<lb/> oblivious of another.  His negligence might have<lb/> been visited on him with severity&#44; had not his<lb/> sagacious wife made atonement for it&#44; by introducing<lb/> her youngest son into the Abrahamic covenant.<lb/>  Reassured against all dangers&#44; restored to perfect<lb/> health&#44; Moses directed all his thoughts to the deliverance<lb/> of the enthralled.  As he who long <sic>envelopped</sic><lb/> in darkness hails the faint glimmer of the rising<lb/> dawn&#44; so did the afflicted greet the two heralds<lb/> of their forthcoming redemption.  All they had<lb/> learnt from their fathers crowded then their memories.<lb/>  They remembered that what now happened had<lb/> been revealed four hundred years before in a vision<lb/> to the first believer&#44; and they fell prostrate in<lb/> adoration to the great God&#44; whose promises are<lb/> unfailing&#44; and whose attributes are justice<lb/> and goodn mercy.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>Pharaoh denied any knowledge of that eternal<lb/> Being&#44; the avenger of innocent  blood.  He <sic>rivetted</sic><lb/> the chains wound around his slaves.  He commanded<lb/> that their oppression be made more fierce.  The Hebrews<lb/> had heretofore received the straw&#44; which&#44; blended with<lb/> the soft clay of Egypt&#44; imparted to the bricks<lb/> they made more solidity.  But now the supply<lb/> should b withheld.  They should go in search thereof&#44; with&#45;<lb/>&#45;out lessening aught of their customary task.  The<lb/> lash is applied to their weary bodies.  Contumely is<lb/> added to the injury.  But God had said it.<lb/>  &#34;But &#34;The nation whom they shall serve&#44; I will judge&#63;<lb/>  The hour has struck.  Inhabitant of Mizraim<lb/> flee for thy life.  The tempest is raging abroad.<lb/>  It threatens to overwhelm thy life thee.  But.....<lb/> wisdom has departed from Mizraim.  God has poured<lb/> out on her Sages a spirit of stupection stupefaction&#59;<lb/> that they might stumble and fall.  The<lb/> oppressors shall be rooted out from of the earth.<lb/>  The oppressed shall inherit it&#44; and rejoice<lb/> in the salvation of their Lord.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
