<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF27_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff27_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff27_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff27_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff27_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff27_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff27_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff27_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff27_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff27_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff27_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff27_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff27_1_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 3 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  Not until very recently did fully entered fully into the spirit<lb/> of the sentence with which the section of this Sabbath com&#45;<lb/>&#45;mences.  Mark its diction&#44; for&#44; in a few words&#44; it lays<lb/> down two cardinal principles of the Jewish religion.  &#34;Behold<lb/> I set before you this day&#44; a blessing and a curse.&#34;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> It is not written &#91;Hebrew&#93; but &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> as to say&#44; I on penitence for sabbath Elul submit the choice to your free&#45;will.  Your own judgment<lb/> shall determine &#91;Hebrew&#93; or your obedience or disobedience of the ordinances of the<lb/> Pentateuch.  Know&#44; however&#44; that a blessing will flow from<lb/> your adherence to the same behests now commanded&#59; and offered for your acceptance&#44; while a<lb/> curse will attend a disregard of those divine precepts.<lb/>  Thus my dear hearers&#33; we have been pithily taught the permanency<lb/> of the law&#44; and our accountability to the Great Sovereign Judge.<lb/>  Blind belief Upon those two points Judaism mainly rests.  A Blind<lb/> belief does not accord with it.  A wiling and intelligent<lb/> performance of its prescriptions is demanded.  But no<lb/> Israelite can with impunity exonerate himself from discharging<lb/> the ordinances of his religion.  And much less can he allege<lb/> as p a palliation for his neglect&#44; that they <sic>the</sic> Divine<lb/> Legislator intended His behests for other times and places.<lb/>  for We read &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;which a curse...if you lest you turn away aside from the way which I command you<lb/> this day&#34;.  Whosoever teaches otherwise&#44; teaches heresy.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  Were you to ask this day&#44; what is<lb/> that which I desire most in the sacred vocation calling I<lb/> follow&#44; I would answer that I wish my congrega&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion did not need to be preached to lectured.  For&#44; it<lb/> would be an evidence of their piety&#44; and the<lb/> highest testimonial I could produce of my success<lb/> as an servant humble minister of the our Lord.  But neither have<lb/> they reached that degree of righteousness&#44; nor am<lb/> I so enviably situated.  Nay&#44; there are many who<lb/> despite my constant admonitions&#44; will adhere to irreligious<lb/> practices.  So that I&#44; who would rejoice in being<lb/> able to praise&#44; am urged by duty to censure.<lb/>  Yet&#44; knowing that&#44; after all&#44; to sin is human&#44; I could<lb/> find some extenuations to a casual departure from<lb/> the ordinances of God.  I could attribute it to the<lb/> frailty of our nature&#59; to the ceaseless temptations<lb/> laid in our way&#44; and so difficult to overcome&#59; but<lb/> that which I cannot palliate&#44; but which I&#44; on the<lb/> contrary&#44; must strongly condemn&#44; is a growing disbelief<lb/> in the truth enunciated in the section of this Sabbath<lb/> for&#44; that is the source when all impiety arises.<lb/></p>
            <p>I mean a denial of our accountability to a great<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>judge for all our doings on earth&#59; a rejection<lb/> of the doctrine &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;that God will bring every action<lb/> into judgment&#44; and pass sentence on every secret thing&#44;<lb/> whether it be good or evil&#34;.  We are told<lb/> in the book&#44; which should be our only guide and<lb/> standard&#44; that a blessing will flow from our obedience<lb/> of the commandments of the Lord&#44; and a curse from<lb/> our disobedience&#44; but many professing to be Jews&#44; in&#45;<lb/>&#45;credulously say&#44; and they have said it also within my hearing<lb/> &#34;Let the device of the Holy One of Israel&#44; come nigh and<lb/> be effected that we may know it&#44;&#34; then will we believe<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Meanwhile they<lb/> imagine that they can with impunity continue<lb/> to do what is contrary to the expressed will of their<lb/> Maker.  They will eat &#38; drink and think and act in contradiction of the dictates of religion &#38; say in their hearts.  The Lord desires not &#91;Hebrew&#93;  And why&#63;  Because of the long&#45;suffering of<lb/> a beneficent God.  For the reason that He in his mercy<lb/> will not immediately let the rod of his chastisement<lb/> fall upon the back of the sinner.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>  &#34;Because a sentence against an evil action is not<lb/> executed speedily&#44; therefore the sons of man dare to do wrong.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>So wrote the author of Ecclesiastes&#44; and so is<lb/> illustrated by the conduct of men who were born in<lb/> Israel.  But in all this I recognize the result<lb/> of a perverted instruction.  For&#44; In this material our unspiritual material age<lb/> if I may use the expression we are taught to submit every thing to human reason&#44;<lb/> and whatever cannot stand that test must be set<lb/> aside as &#91;&#63;&#93;.  Accordingly we are made to believe that<lb/> God is too exalted to take knowledge of those who<lb/> dwell in tenements of clay.  That He whom the<lb/> whole universe cannot contain&#44; will not condescend<lb/> to note man&#39;s outgoings and coming in.  That all<lb/> causes and their effects in sublunary events&#44; depend<lb/> upon natural laws&#44; and are not to be sought after<lb/> in the actions of individuals.  Oh presumption&#33;  Oh<lb/> fatal incredulity&#33;  Surely&#44; I know&#44; that the th A fallible creature&#44; sets up<lb/> his judgment against the word of the infallible God&#33;<lb/>  Surely&#44; I know&#44; that the Almighty in his dealing with<lb/> the inhabitants of this world&#44; does not work constant miracles.  I am<lb/> fully aware that &#91;Hebrew&#93; Nature follows its fixed<lb/> laws.  But He who is the author of nature has not<lb/> surrendered to it his illimitable powers.  No&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>its workings are but the messengers of His will.<lb/>  They are shaped by the finger of God that they<lb/> may subserve his wise purposes &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Whether to chastise the wicked&#44; or to benefit a people<lb/> or to show mankind his compassion.  Is a country<lb/> prosperous&#63; the Lord&#39;s face of the Lord shines upon it.  Is it<lb/> in a state of internal convuls agitation&#63;  God<lb/> visits upon it the inequity of its inhabitants.<lb/>  And what I have said of a nation&#44; applies with<lb/> equal force to the individuals.  Are we happy<lb/> at home&#44; and successful abroad&#63;  The spirit of God<lb/> hovers around us.  Do we suffer afflictions&#44; or reverses&#63;<lb/>  God admonishes us that we may bethink ourselves<lb/> and return to duty.  Such is my religion&#44;<lb/> such is must should be your religion&#44; my Brethren&#44; in contrast with<lb/> a philosophy that would give unto God only a negative<lb/> existence&#44; while He is the ever&#45;wakeful&#44; the ever<lb/> acting Being&#44; and impartial Judge.  For&#44; this con&#45;<lb/>&#45;solatory doctrine is taught in every page of the<lb/> holy book&#59; it is manifestly sh inculcated by every word maxim of our<lb/> prophets sages&#44; and in the maxims of our Sages every word of our philosophers&#44; but is<lb/> nowhere more explicitly forcibly inculcated than in our the Parasha<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>you are have read this Sabbath.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;A blessing shall attend your obedience of the com&#45;<lb/>&#45;mandments of the Lord your God&#44; but a curse your di&#45;<lb/>&#45;sobedience.&#34;  Yes&#44; the justice of the Lord demands<lb/> that we be responsible for acts&#44; which are the<lb/> issue result of our own volition freedom of will.  His goodness wills that descrys prompts some<lb/> we be to rewarded us for our virtuous deeds.  Disconnect<lb/> these ideas&#44; and where God is enthroned&#44; blind chance<lb/> would be set up.  If the Providence of the Lord<lb/> be not as well as2 general and special1 in its divine character&#44;<lb/> man is then but a sport to uncontrolling events.<lb/>  His individuality is lost&#44; and with it his accountability<lb/> But it is written inspired wisdom can proclaims by the wisest of our &#91;Hebrew&#93; that the eyes<lb/> of God are upon the ways of man&#44; and He observes<lb/> all his steps.  Our impartial judge may not choose<lb/> to requite us <sic>instantenously</sic> according to our deserts&#44;<lb/> but know for certain &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; that all will be<lb/> reckoned up.  Our Rabbins in the Midrash com&#45;<lb/>&#45;menting upon the first sentence of our this week&#39;s lesson<lb/> make use of an allegory illustrative of our subject<lb/> They say&#44; a blessing and a curse have been set before<lb/> us&#44; and it the selection is optional&#58; with no which but it sometime happens<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>that the former blessing bears the semblance of the<lb/> latter cause&#44; and this again is diguised under the barb<lb/> of the other former&#59; which fact can be compared to a high<lb/> way&#44; but branching out into two different roads.<lb/>  One appears the most agreeable and the easiest<lb/> whereby to reach our destination&#44; the other unpleasant and<lb/> difficult to walk upon.  But at the spot where<lb/> those two roads separate&#44; a watchman stands&#44; and<lb/> thus he addresses each passer by.  <sic>Neibour</sic>&#33;  You<lb/> see this road so smooth and so well laid out&#59; if<lb/> you follow it&#44; you will shortly find yourself entangled<lb/> among thorns&#44; which will prick your sides.<lb/>  The other&#44; on the contrary&#44; which has some obstructions<lb/> at the entrance will&#44; no sooner you have overcome<lb/> them&#44; conduct you to the end of your journey through<lb/> a wide and strait path.  My Brethren&#33;  The<lb/> application is obvious.  We often&#44; deceived by ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;pearances often consider that that that to heed our own what our neighbor possesses is<lb/> inclinations is to forward our happiness.  We<lb/> think for instance that riches&#45;&#45;for that seems to be with all<lb/> the great goal to be attained&#45;&#45;we think that riches<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>can but be accumulated by following our a course which<lb/> lies under no restrictions&#44; and we forsake God to we voluntarily<lb/> rush into a way that ends in suffering and truth it&#44; looking not to any farther than only no as far as our own shortsightedness can reach.<lb/>  Another way presents itsf itself before us&#44; but we avoid it.<lb/>  To go through it&#44; we must struggle against our passions&#44;<lb/> and impose on ourselves some restriction a cl check on our cravings&#59; but cannot we do not<lb/> perceive that what we put aside as a temporary evil<lb/> is precisely that which will be the means conducive to our real happiness wellbeing&#44;<lb/> whereas what we perceive prefer&#44; ends in suffering and &#91;&#63;&#93; gnawing remorse.<lb/>  For&#44; if we believe that a just God cannot leave those unpu&#45;<lb/>nished those who rebel against His will to follow their<lb/> own&#44; nor let men go unrewarded&#44; who suppress their wishes<lb/> for the sake of His sacred word&#44; we will not be beguiled by<lb/> the seeming felicity of the wicked.  For For as the preacher<lb/> says &#34;Though a sinner do evil a hundred times&#44; and<lb/> his days chastisement be prolonged deferred put off&#44; yet surely I know that it shall<lb/> be well with them that fear God &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; but it shall not be<lb/> well with the wicked &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Imbued with these comforting ideas we will<lb/> not then call that happiness which is gained by trampling<lb/> upon the ordinances of the Lord&#44; but we will call that<lb/> felicity which proceeds form a conscience of having shaped not deliberately<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>disobeyed our Creator&#44; for this will be a lasting felicity.<lb/>  It will outlive be our sweet spiritual companion &#38; comforter while the body<lb/> exists&#44; and it will follow us beyond the grave when our flesh &#38; bones moulder in the graves.  The<lb/> other b is but transient&#44; and should it even continue<lb/> in this world&#44; it will be converted into a corroding<lb/> warm&#44; where bodily enjoyments can no more be felt.<lb/>  Let us then be aware careful&#44; my friends&#44; of that lest our hearts<lb/> become not tainted with the skeptical notions so pre&#45;<lb/>vailing in this degenerate age&#59; for once that we<lb/> have embraced them&#44; it will be difficult to have cast them<lb/> rooted out away.  When man has early been taught to looks upon this nether<lb/> world&#44; as a ship without a pilot&#44; or on its inha&#45; dwellers<lb/> bitants as mere jugglers striving to supplant<lb/> and overreach one another&#44; when the mind either<lb/> puffed up with worldly knowledge&#44; or void<lb/> of all intelligence&#44; attributes to chance what<lb/> is the emanation of supreme wisdom&#44; then neither<lb/> the gentle admonitions of friends&#44; nor the paternal<lb/> corrections of heaven will effect a change.<lb/></p>
            <p>But we should remember that we have been al forcibly<lb/> cautioned against hearkening to the insinuations of a false prophet<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>to him who seeks to turn us away from the Lord our God&#44;<lb/> we should remember that we are bid close our ears against a teaching<lb/> subversive of what the Almighty Himself has<lb/> vouchsafed to impart to us for our own happiness here<lb/> and hereafter.  We should remember that as a<lb/> preventative against the seductions of the wicked&#44;<lb/> God has given us the following prescription &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;  &#34;Ye shall &#91;&#63;&#93; after the Lord your God&#34; that<lb/> is&#44; you shall endeavour to copy his attributes&#44; and being thus be<lb/> engaged in doing charity and acts of beneficence.  You will &#91;&#63;&#93; evil&#45;doing.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Ye shall fear Him&#34; ye shall entertain a<lb/> continual apprehension of doing aught that may<lb/> displease the Guardian of your existence &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Ye shall keep his command&#34; Ye shall cavil neither<lb/> about the relative importance of his various precepts&#44; nor<lb/> about the object they have in view&#44; but ye shall simply<lb/> obey his voice &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; as that of a father who<lb/> can only wish the welfare of his children.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  Ye shall<lb/> serve him&#34; ye shall worship Him at home in the ideation of your children&#59; &#91;&#63;&#93; in dealing with your fellow&#45;men in his sanctuary&#59;<lb/> Bringing thither an offering of pure lips and of a clean heart.<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;And cleave unto Him.&#34;  Ye shall cling to the<lb/> Dweller of heaven in joy&#44; as the spring of all enjoyments&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>Ye shall cling to Him in sorrow adversity&#44; as to the only anchor<lb/> of salvation.  My Brethren&#33;  This divine prescription<lb/> I now lay before you open for your acceptance.  This day  On this Sabbath&#44; which is the opening of<lb/> a month&#44; which they devoted by those who follow our ritual devote<lb/> to propitiatory prayers&#59; I suggest that you will thus<lb/> early examine your conduct towards God &#38; man.  If you discover<lb/> that your religious habits are not free form reproach&#44; if<lb/> you perceive that you have not always been actuated<lb/> by religious motives&#44; but also by selfishness&#44; and animosity &#38; hatred and avarice&#59;<lb/> of your &#91;&#63;&#93; that you cast the Law of God aside&#44; to follow<lb/> your own propensities&#59; if in searching your inward<lb/> selves you obscure black stains of sin committed against your<lb/> own children&#44; the wife of your bosom&#44; and or your<lb/> confiding friend.  If you&#44; in short detect anything<lb/> antagonistic to the dictates of Holy Writ&#44; speedily amend blot it<lb/> your courses out&#44; that you may on the day of judgment<lb/> uplift your hands hearts on high cleansed from all pollutions<lb/> that you may &#38; say &#34;O Lord&#33;  I have returned unto Thee<lb/> with sincerity&#59; I have mended my ways I will henceforth obey Thy com&#45; precepts<lb/> &#45;mandments&#44; do those from heaven command Thy<lb/> blessing to rest upon me&#59; and be laid upon the<lb/> head of my offspring&#44; and of those I love upon earth.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
