<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF9_19</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1891-06" source="" attested="yes">June 1891</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_19_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_19_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_19_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_19_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_19_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_19_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_19_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_19_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_19_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_19_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_19_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_19_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>15<lb/></p>
            <p>June&#47;91<lb/></p>
            <p>The encyclical letter<lb/>
                &#38; the Decalogue<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>The head of the Catholic Church has issued his encyclical<lb/> letter.  Labor and capital&#44; social duties and family ties&#44;<lb/> the education of the masses&#44; and the authority of religion&#44;<lb/> are subject which&#44; from what we can judge by an<lb/> extract&#44; the Pope discusses in all earnestnessness.  A clear decided im&#45;<lb/>&#45;provement is that encyclical missive upon the public<lb/> addresses of some of the predecessors at occupants of the throne in the Vatican.  I can<lb/> recall the utterances of Gregory XVI.&#44;&#45;&#45;the triple crown sovereign&#45;&#45;who had filled<lb/> to repletion with political prisoners the dungeons of his<lb/> Roman provinces.  He hurled curses at liberty&#44; anathemas<lb/> at the aspirations to liberty&#44; invectives at Protestantism.<lb/>  I remember the words of Pius IX. the last&#44; I hope&#44; of Papal monarchs&#45;&#45;when&#44; after having<lb/> loosened the chains of many who pined away in jail<lb/> for daring to speak or write on freedom&#44; and having<lb/> raised the false expectations of a brighter era for the freedom loving&#44; was seized with a dreading of<lb/> Austria and Catholic potentates&#44; and created a reaction that<lb/> culminated in the abduction of Edgar Mortara.  He<lb/> also cast maledictions upon all who believe that the people<lb/> have rights&#44; and must assert them in spite of the assu&#45;<lb/>&#45;med divine rights of Kings.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Would either of those two Pontiffs have looked across the<lb/> Atlantic&#44; and with so much concern noticed America&#44;<lb/> the country that has cut asunder the bands&#44; which<lb/> fastened the State to the chariot&#45;wheel of the Church&#44; the country that has<lb/> opened an asylum to all who rebel against priest&#45;<lb/>&#45;craft&#63;  It was reserved for Leo XIII&#44; to proclaim&#45;&#45;<lb/>&#45;&#45;wonderful admission for a Pope&#45;&#45;if true&#45;&#45;to proclaim that self&#45;<lb/>&#45;government&#44; as in our the great Republic of the North&#44; is not synonymous with<lb/> anarchy&#59; that the efforts of the working classes to<lb/> become independent do not tend to communism&#59; that<lb/> religion&#44; to perform its mission&#44; must seek the ele&#45;<lb/>&#45;vation of the lowly&#44; and not cringe to the high&#59; that<lb/> it must not teach that the poor shall remain poor&#44;<lb/> to give the rich a chance to mount up to heaven on<lb/> heaps of charity.  At all events&#44; whatever the causes<lb/> may be which brought about a metamorphosis Leo XIII&#44; if report is correct unlike his predecessors&#44; has directed his<lb/> mind to live questions which agitate the masses every&#45;<lb/>where&#44; and he has looked for exponents of his views<lb/> in the United States&#44; in where Catholicism has increased<lb/> amazingly.  He has found Bishops and Arch&#45;<lb/>&#45;bishops and Cardinals&#44; ready and able to represent the highest in<lb/> their hierarchy&#44; as a friend to progress within the line of morality.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>But what is the foundation stone upon which the<lb/> Pope has chosen to build his encyclical letter&#63;  None<lb/> other than that which has been and will ever be the<lb/> basis of human civilization&#44; and without which decep&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion supplants truth&#44; lawlessness runs riot.  The<lb/> Decalogue is the Alpha and the Omega&#45;&#45;the beginning<lb/> and the end&#45;&#45;of the lesson&#45;&#45;as I have read it&#45;&#45;sent forth from the Vatican.<lb/>  Christianity may have arrogated to itself the a<lb/> power&#44; which is not conceded to fallible mortals.  to It has<lb/> tampered with doctrinal points in the heaven revealed ten<lb/> commandments.  To the Omnipotent&#44; Christianity<lb/> has joined a coexisting being&#59; to God who suffers not the<lb/> worship of images as derogatory to His spirituality&#44;<lb/> it has added figures and likenesses.  It has moreover<lb/> authorized the desecration of the day set apart to the<lb/> Lord from the beginning of creation&#44; and has hallowed<lb/> another in its stead&#44; which the policy of Constantine&#44;<lb/> in the fourth century of the vulgar era&#44; originated.<lb/>  But Christianity that has transformed the Unity into a trinity&#44;<lb/> symbolized the latter given bodily forms for adoration&#44; and abrogated the real Sabbath&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>dared not lay its hand on the purely moral tenets<lb/> which the Pope quotes.  It could not construe duty<lb/> to parents otherwise than it is in the imperishable<lb/> documents received by Israel at this never to be for&#45;<lb/>&#45;gotten season.  It could not say that murder is a<lb/> virtue&#44; that adultery is conducive to the health&#45;<lb/>&#45;ful permanence of communities&#44; that to rob and to<lb/> lie&#44; and to covet and to envy are qualities exalting<lb/> nations and individuals.  Wishing to tell how<lb/> society can alone move on progressively and blissfully&#44;<lb/> Leo XIII&#62; must necessarily have pointed to that all&#45;<lb/>irradiating Sun that shone on the summit of Sinai Horeb.<lb/>  It is because men&#39;s visions will turn away from it&#44;<lb/> that so much that which lowers our nature character&#44; so much that<lb/> disgraces mankind&#44; aye&#58; so much that has brought scan&#45;<lb/>&#45;dal and suffering on the city of Philadelphia&#44; is forced<lb/> upon public attention.  Breach of trust&#44; forgery&#44;<lb/> perjury&#44; are crimes&#44; which a disregard of the Magna<lb/> Carta given committed to our safe&#45;keeping&#44; too frequently oc&#45;<lb/>&#45;casions.  We call national laws those which<lb/> our reason accepts&#59; well&#44; be it so&#44; but so strong are our passions for<lb/> riches&#44; for a luxurious living&#44; for indulgence in carnal<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>appetites&#44; that the voice of reason is often hushed&#44;<lb/> or we allow it to speak when too late&#44; when its counsel<lb/> cannot draw us out of the wreck and rain vortex into which<lb/> we have voluntarily glided become got entangled.  I grant<lb/> that the beneficent Being&#44; whom we call Providence&#44;<lb/> has implanted within our f breasts the seeds of<lb/> goodness&#44; I grant that they ought spontaneously to fructify.  The Sages of Israel have acknowledged<lb/> that that had not the Torah been promulgated at<lb/> Horeb Sinai&#44; a close observation of even the habits of some<lb/> of the inferior animals&#44; would have imparted to us<lb/> the rules of life.  But lessons on ethics&#44; though<lb/> agreeing with our nature&#44; if wanting lacking the sanction of<lb/> the Supremest authority&#44; are insufficient to hold us<lb/> in rectitude.  We may assume morality&#44; as an ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;pediency&#44; we may put it on as a mask to hide the<lb/> deformities of a cunning disposition&#44; but sooner or<lb/> later the falsity will stand revealed to our shame.<lb/>  Morality is the central pillar sustaining the social<lb/> fabric&#44; but it must have God as the Architect<lb/> and the regulator watching overlooking that it does not fall<lb/> into fragments.  The very pinnacle of human<lb/> morality is the Jewish idea&#44; the constant thought of a<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>watchful God&#44; who will not allow vice and crime<lb/> to build up a tower defying the arrows of Divine displeasure.<lb/>  Not the fear of the courts&#44; not the horror of the prison&#44;<lb/> but the certainty that we dare not trample on the<lb/> moral tenets of the Decalogue with impunity&#44; is the<lb/> safest guard of society.  I do not means as re&#45;<lb/>&#45;gards the promises of a hereafter&#44; but here&#44; in this<lb/> transitory life&#59; wrongs are avenged by the all&#45;seeing God.<lb/>  A Marsh may pass off a long time for the honest&#45;<lb/>&#45;est man&#44; a Bardsley may enjoy the fairest re&#45;<lb/>&#45;putation&#44; but neither they a Kennedy may dupe<lb/> unsuspecting multitudes&#59; but neither they nor others<lb/> who may make of the Church a wise folding cloak to<lb/> cover their crooked deeds&#44; will have an honored grave.<lb/>  Even royalty is not a screen against turpitudes.<lb/>  Witness the revelations which raise a blush upon<lb/> the cheeks of those who still pay obeisance to<lb/> high titles&#44; and in whose sight positions accident<lb/>&#45;al to birth have a claim to popular reverence.  Wit&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness Do you wonder that conformists and non&#45;conformists<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>among the English feel outraged at the conduct of<lb/> a Prince who carries wherever he goes&#44; not the word of<lb/> God&#44; as a Jewish prince was enjoined&#44; according to the<lb/> sentence in Deuteronomy&#44; but objects encouraging<lb/> among the masses immoral extravagances&#44; subter&#45;<lb/>&#45;fuge and chicanery&#63;  Infinite thanks to the modern<lb/> Herculeses who try to clean the Angean stable&#45;&#45;those<lb/> are the avengers of who lift the moral from the <sic>filfth</sic> into which<lb/> men in with the insignia of office have thrust it.<lb/>  The yare the avengers of the Din Divine commandments<lb/> which teach&#44; &#34;fear not the presence of man&#44; justice is<lb/> the fiat of God.&#34;...&#34;Pervert not justice judgment&#44; respect<lb/> no person&#44; take no bribe.&#34;  Israel can cite as re&#45;<lb/>&#45;presentatives defenders of incorruptibleness&#44; a King Jehoshaphat<lb/> who charged his officers to dread only the Great Master&#44;<lb/> at whose tribunal we must answer for our honest<lb/> administration of justice&#59; a Sage who&#44; before sitting<lb/> at court&#44; felt as if a sword was suspended over<lb/> his head&#44; and prayed that he might return home<lb/> as innocent as when he leftt it.  May such be<lb/> our Judges&#44; our Governors&#44; our Councilmen&#44;<lb/> vindicating the fair name of Philadelphia&#44; and delivering<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>the simple hearted and poor from the fraudulent<lb/> and dishonestly rich.  And now let<lb/> us pray that Popes and Potentates&#44; monarchies<lb/> and republics may raise as a standard of<lb/> their guidance&#44; the banner unfurled at Sinai&#44;<lb/> glorious in its origin&#44; sublime in its teaching&#44;<lb/> full of promises divine for our happiness in<lb/> this life&#44; and our beatitude hereafter.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
