<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF3_4</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_4_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_4_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_4_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_4_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_4_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_4_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_4_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_4_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_4_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_4_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_4_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_4_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>4th Historical lecture.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  History relates that Ecbatana was the<lb/> summer residence of the Kings of Persia&#45;&#45;the winter<lb/> season they spent at Susa.  In the latter city&#44;<lb/> our coreligionists could be found in large numbers&#44; during <lb/>the reign of Artaxerxes Longimanus&#44; but one of them was<lb/> known to enjoy at the court exceeding influence.  Just at this<lb/> time of the year&#44; in the month of Kislev&#44; that per&#45;<lb/>&#45;sonage greeted a brother&#44; who&#44; with several other Judeans&#44;<lb/> had come arrived from the Holy Land.  The anxious ques&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion first asked put was concerning the welfare of the<lb/> Palestinian colony and about Jerusalem.  The<lb/> answer occasioned much pain.  It told that the<lb/> efforts of Zerubabel and Joshua the high priest&#59; the ener&#45;<lb/>&#45;getic endeavours of Ezra the scribe were being defeated<lb/> by hostile neighbors.  The capital had no walls<lb/> of defence&#59; her gates had been razed to the ground&#59; disheartened were the faithful few among the people.  At<lb/> so sad an announcement the man who had put made the<lb/> inquiry wept as he p uttered a prayer.<lb/></p>
            <p>Three months passed by.  Spring had come on.  At the daily hour<lb/> of the repast&#44; on a certain day of Nissan&#44; the royal cup&#45;bearer<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>brought in generous wine.  He presented the goblet<lb/> to his royal sovereign master&#44; but with looks which betrayed<lb/> some internal struggle.  Artaxersces noticed it&#44;<lb/> and asked for the cause of that depression of spirits.  &#34;O King&#44;<lb/> mayest thou live forever&#34; said the cup&#45;bearer&#44; &#34;how can I but<lb/> feel dejected&#44; when the city in which my ancestors<lb/> lie buried is destroyed and at the mercy of heathens inimical tribes&#63;<lb/>  Let me go and build my fathers&#39; home again.&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>Nehemiah&#39;s petition was granted by the king and<lb/> queen&#44; on condition that he would not remain<lb/> away altogether.  By what industry&#44;<lb/> and at what personal sacrifices he overcame the open op&#45;<lb/>&#45;position and the subtle wiles of heathen foes is re&#45;<lb/>&#45;counted in the book which bears his name.  But<lb/> Nehemiah has been taken to task by modern critics.<lb/>  for the He has been accused of egotism&#44; because of in his writings he makes repeated mention he makes in his writings<lb/> of the noble deeds he performed and of his successful exertions.<lb/>  Admit that he was not a Moses in the total<lb/> forgetting of self&#44; while acting righteously&#59; yet&#44; we<lb/> <sic>we</sic> all might wish that men would arise to exercise<lb/> the powers they could beneficially <sic>weild</sic>&#44; in a manner<lb/> similar to that in which Nehemiah exercised his own.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>We might well overlook an occasional expression<lb/> of self&#45;confidence&#59; such as this&#58; They &#34;My God&#33; remember<lb/> me for good&#44; because of all I have done for this people.&#34;<lb/>  And Verily he who so exclaimed&#44; surely deserved that to have his<lb/> name inscribed in the book of eternal life and em&#45;<lb/>&#45;balmed in the memory of posterity.  Threats like<lb/> Jeers&#44; violent attacks like false charges were used in<lb/> vain against a man patriot fully determined to secure by<lb/> his great influence the revival of Judea&#44; and the permanence<lb/> of its Hebrew community.  The walls of the metro&#45;<lb/>&#45;polis must lift up their heads from their ruin and we<lb/> back inimical tribes&#44; even if to do so it cost incessant labour&#44;<lb/> by day and sleepless watching by night.  The humble<lb/> classes must be relieved from the burden exactions of hard&#45;hearted cre&#45;<lb/>&#45;ditors&#44; even if the latter have to give up some of their<lb/> possessions.  The national laws must be respected&#44;<lb/> even if the earnings of one day in the week&#44; and of<lb/> one year in seven have to be lost.  All of this and<lb/> much more was put into execution by the resolute<lb/> cup&#45;bearer of King Artaxerxes.  And when<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>after a wholesome administration of twelve conse&#45;<lb/>&#45;cutive years&#44; the appointed governor resumed his original<lb/> offer&#45;&#45;which in Persia was one of high standing&#45;&#45;he<lb/> immediately unrepiningly quitted it to go to Palestine again&#44; and reform fresh abuses<lb/> which had broken out afresh in Palestine.  The Sabbath<lb/> ceased to be a market&#45;day on which gentile farmers and<lb/> merchants exposed their goods for sale in Jerusalem&#59; the<lb/> Temple had no longer private chambers where gentile<lb/> relatives of unfaithful priests made their rendezvous&#59;<lb/> the support of the sacred service was not neglected&#44;<lb/> when Nehemiah took up th again the staff of command.<lb/>  Aye&#58; admirable he was who so performed his commission&#59; &#34;God&#39;s elect&#44;&#34; as fittingly called by the son of<lb/> Girah.  But in doing justice to a noble patriot&#44; we should<lb/> not pass by a sacerdotal notability and a Sage.  In<lb/> my last lecture Ezra was made considerably to occupy considerably<lb/> your attention&#44; but not proportionately to his deserts.<lb/>  I intimated that in my opinion that great and good<lb/> man was brought back by Nehemiah to play a still<lb/> more important part than before in the work of reform&#45;<lb/>&#45;ation.  And I base my views theory upon the circum&#45;<lb/>&#45;stance that we see Ezra suddenly appear in the<lb/> midst of the busy life of the illustrious governor of<lb/> Judea&#44; as narrated in the eigthth chapter of the book of<lb/> Nehemiah.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Upon our new year&#39;s day&#44; Ezra ascends a pulpit&#59;<lb/> unfolds the scroll of the Law in the presence of a vast<lb/> multitude who rise to their feet&#44; and from early in the morn&#45;<lb/>ing until noon he reads the word of God plainly and under&#45;<lb/>&#45;standingly&#44; while intelligent priests and levites in turn explain<lb/> the text to the uninitiated&#45;&#45;probably in the Aramaic<lb/> language&#44; at that time best understood.  On the<lb/> second day&#44; the heads of families and officials at the Sanc&#45;<lb/>&#45;tuary hold a conference with Ezra.  He shows them the<lb/> obligation of dwelling in tabernacles booths during the ensuing<lb/> festival&#45;&#45;a practice which may have been long neglected&#45;&#45;and its<lb/> performance is assumed with universal acceptance strictness.  Each<lb/> day of the Tabernacle holiday the l Law is read in public&#44;<lb/> and the eighth day of solemn convocation is kept accord&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing to the Mosaic rule.  In view of these facts&#44;<lb/> the traditions which cluster round the name of Ezra&#44; can&#45;<lb/>&#45;not be the offspring of Rabbinical imagination inventions&#44; as hyper&#45;<lb/>critics pretend.  That he was very learned&#44; none<lb/> doubts&#44; that he was popularly sought after in matters<lb/> relating to the Mosaic prescriptions&#44; cannot be denied&#44;<lb/> without blotting out a page of history.  And who will gainsay<lb/> the evidences that he enjoyed the confidence of the Persian<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>monarch and the full trust of his worthy colleague&#44;<lb/> Nehemiah&#63;  Why then&#44; should any sensible person<lb/> refuse to subscribe to what the Talmud sets forth as<lb/> a think which our fathers never disputed&#63;  Ezra<lb/> availing himself of the authority granted by Artaxerxes<lb/> to govern that the Judeans by be governed according to their own laws&#44; became the President<lb/> of chosen men&#44; who jointly made such provisions as<lb/> would guard Judaism everlastingly against the remotest<lb/> possibility of extinction.  That august body is known<lb/> under the name of Keneseth Ha&#45;Gedolah&#44; or &#34;the<lb/> great Synod.&#34;  In do not emphatically stating my<lb/> belief in the existence of that tribunal&#44; I do not mean<lb/> to assert that the one hundred and twenty persons of members individuals to<lb/> which it was composed in whom the Talmudists allude as having been its members&#44;<lb/> lived at one and the same time.  I know that it<lb/> cannot be so&#44; because Simeon the just&#44; considered reckoned the<lb/> last member survivor of that legislative honorable body&#44; is supposed to<lb/> have been a contemporary of Alexander the great&#45;&#45;<lb/>a distance of over one hundred and fifty years&#44; from<lb/> the days of Ezra and Nehemiah.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>What I contend is that&#44; during the whole of the period<lb/> just I have now mentioned&#44; the spirit which had animated the illu&#45;<lb/>&#45;strious scribe still lived with a number of his successor&#44; who met&#44;<lb/> as occasions demanded it&#44; for the welfare of the na&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion.  Ezra had died&#44; but the object of his stre&#45;<lb/>&#45;nuous endeavours remained ever present to those who<lb/> had inherited imbibed his wisdom teaching&#44; or learnt from the fathers elders<lb/> the lessons of his wisdom.  The title which these men<lb/> bore was that of Sopherim&#44; which must not&#44; however&#44;<lb/> be confounded with the sense given at present to that<lb/> word&#44; namely&#58; transcribers of the scrolls of the Law&#44; or<lb/> <sic>philactories</sic>.  Literati we would rather style them<lb/> now&#59; persons of deep learning who understood how<lb/> to restore the Torah its sovereignty&#44; how to broaden and<lb/> heighten and intensify its powers&#59; or to say it with the<lb/> Rabbis&#44; how to make Israelites conquer the Yezer Harang<lb/> or temptation.  To describe what the great Synod<lb/> accomplished for the preservation of our faith&#44; and<lb/> the perpetuity of our people and the sanctification<lb/> of Israel&#39;s God&#44; will form the task I shall<lb/> impose upon myself in my another lecture.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
