<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx2FF1_19b</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Wiley, S. R.</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1874-10" source="" attested="yes">28 October 1874</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx2ff1_19_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx2ff1_19_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx2ff1_19_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx2ff1_19_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx2ff1_19_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx2ff1_19_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx2ff1_19_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx2ff1_19_7v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>6 pages on 3 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. R. Wiley Esqre<lb/></p>
            <p>Philadelphia October 28<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1874<lb/></p>
            <p>Dear Sir<lb/></p>
            <p>First of all&#44; I must apologise for my ap<lb/>parent neglect.  Since receiving your favor dated July 23d&#44;<lb/> I have been unusually busy.  For over six months I had promised<lb/> the editors of the Messenger to prepare some sketches on Hebrew<lb/> literature in Italy&#44; and I had deferred the task from week<lb/> to week&#44; owing to pressing duties in my official capacity.<lb/>  I had just begun&#44; when your letter arrived&#44; and very soon after<lb/> that the fall holidays&#44;&#45;&#45;which last nearly a month&#44; and<lb/> occupy most of my time and thoughts&#44; intervened.  So&#44;<lb/> notwithstanding that your missive lay on my desk&#44; and<lb/> I&#44; occasionally looking at it&#44; was reminded of my obligation&#44;<lb/> I felt unable to perform it.  Having said this much in<lb/> justification of my conduct&#44; and repeating my thanks for<lb/> your attention in forwarding Jewish papers&#44; I shall<lb/> proceed briefly with the subject of your communication.<lb/>  I perfectly agree in the opinion that the derivation of<lb/> names is not a reliable criterion&#44; and that a decision<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>based on it regarding the <hi rend="underline">original language</hi>&#44; might be proved<lb/> hasty and erroneous.  But I am pleased to observe from your<lb/> quotations that Le Clerc shares the views I have advanced.<lb/>  He also thinks that the so called Semitic languages<lb/> sprung form a common source&#44; and gradually separated.<lb/>  You may have misunderstood what I wrote&#44; or possibly<lb/> I was at fault in my expressions&#44; touching Philo.  I revere<lb/> his memory&#44; because I believe him a learned and true Israelite&#59;<lb/> nevertheless&#44; I say what men infinitely my superiors have<lb/> detected&#8212;that he was not a Hebraist in the sense we Jews at&#45;<lb/>tach to that term.  The passage in Genesis 10.20. may<lb/> be considered a general description&#44; prefatory&#44; as it were&#44; to the<lb/> narrative of the confusion of tongues.  Respecting the latter&#44;<lb/> Julius Scaliger and Isaac Abarband have hit upon the<lb/> same idea&#59; though the context does not seem to bear it out.<lb/>  I see no evidence of &#34;the Aramaic being impregnated with<lb/> Hebrew <hi rend="underline">after</hi> the Exodus.  Pardon my saying that the burden<lb/> of proof rests with yourself.  I am open to correction&#44; and<lb/> always glad to learn.  I still claim that during the<lb/> Babylonish captivity the knowledge of the sacred tongue<lb/> was lost&#44; because idolatrous mothers preferred to train<lb/> their children in their respective languages&#44; or dialects&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>which though originally may have been one and the same&#44; at<lb/> the period of history we allude to&#44; they were distinct.<lb/>  Permit me to call your attention to the fact that the staying<lb/> of Jacob&#39;s descendants in Egypt was no more than two centuries&#44;<lb/> and&#44; as acknowledged by our commentators&#44; and by the Septua<lb/>gint&#44; the 4 generations spoken of in the Bible commenced with<lb/> the wanderings of the patriarchs through various lands.  With&#45;<lb/>out assigning the result to a miraculous interposition&#44; we<lb/> may believe that a people&#44; inhabiting a separate locality&#44;<lb/> strongly bound together by ties of blood&#44; of faith&#44; and common<lb/> suffering&#44; retained the ancestral language.  Witness the mere<lb/> effect of locality in the Pennsylvania Dutch&#44; enjoying per&#45;<lb/>fect freedom civilly and religiously.  You are right&#44;<lb/> of course&#44; in stating that &#34;languages are formed from adventitious<lb/> circumstances&#34; and that what is very ancient in history&#44; an<lb/> almost impenetrable darkness hides it from our vision.  Every<lb/> one tries to draw aside the veil&#44; and professes that a greater in&#45;<lb/>sight into matters has been vouchsafed to him than others&#44; but<lb/> all deal in sheer speculations.  Moses&#44; however&#44; wrote<lb/> down his book in Hebrew&#44; and millions of his enfranchised brethren<lb/> heard it&#44; if they all could not read it.  You ask&#44; how<lb/> could he write&#63;  I answer&#58; Some hold that the caste of priests<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>a Mizraim knew the art of representing &#34;the utterance of the<lb/> lips&#34; by characters.  Others again contend that the Deity<lb/> who inspired the archprophet taught it to him&#44; for we<lb/> read after the battle of Amalek &#34;Write this for a memorial<lb/> in a book&#44; and put it <hi rend="underline">in the hearing</hi> &#40;ears&#41; of Joshua&#34;<lb/> &#40;Possibly the latter could not understand writing&#44; which circumstance<lb/> necessitated an oral exposition of the contents&#41;.  Your<lb/> objection derived from the fact that the Decalogue was twice &#34;written<lb/> by the finger of God&#34; does not carry sufficient weight.<lb/>  The summary of all the laws&#44; intended to be shrined in the<lb/> holy ark&#44; was to have inspired all minds with reverential awe.<lb/>  Now fitting then that they should be delineated miraculously<lb/> by the Supreme Intelligence&#33;  The theory that<lb/> Solomon composed the Illead is preposterous.  Equally absurd it<lb/> is to presume that the Greek poet drew his name from<lb/> &#34;Omer&#34; the <hi rend="underline">sayer</hi> or <hi rend="underline">speaker</hi>.  We know that the<lb/> wildest vagaries have met with followers.  Let every one who<lb/> chooses to adopt follies&#44; hug them.  I shall find no fault.<lb/>  But I believe you too sensible to admit freaks of the mind<lb/> as well substantiated facts.  I possess sufficient evidence<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>of your learning&#44; and the very communication I am discuss<lb/>ing attests your discernment as well as your erudition.  Yet&#44;<lb/> excuse my candor&#44; &#34;<hi rend="underline">Your personal views on the subject at issue</hi>&#34;<lb/> are antangonistic to mine.  Were there no other proof than<lb/> the song of Moses&#44; to demonstrate that the leader and his<lb/> flock understood and spoke Hebrew&#44; I would deem that<lb/> quite enough.  No&#58; it is a &#91;&#63;&#93; of our Sages&#44; which I heartily<lb/> endorse&#44; that the Deity does not work miracles&#44; unless natural<lb/> means are inadequate to carry out this wise purpose.  The<lb/> &#34;wonders wrought in the land of Ham&#44;&#34; those upon the sea and<lb/> in Marah&#44; the glorious revelation on the summit of Horeb&#44;<lb/> and prophetic inspiration&#44; were essential&#44; but a miraculous<lb/> imparting of a language&#44; would have been useless&#44; be&#45;<lb/>cause the <hi rend="underline">observance of the laws</hi> and not the speaking of<lb/> this tongue or of another was to distinguish the house of<lb/> Israel from the day of Sinai and thenceforth for ever.  That<lb/> now during a long and far&#45;reaching dispersion the Hebrew<lb/> <hi rend="underline">is</hi> a mighty link I fully grant&#44; but&#44; when a nation in<lb/> Palestine&#44; it did not subserve our present object.  The<lb/> Hebrew became our father&#39;s vernacular tongue&#44; as a natural<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>consequence of its having been inherited from the 70 persons<lb/> who went down to Egypt.  And if Nehemiah deprecated<lb/> its ignorance among the rising generation&#44; the just complaint<lb/> arose from a fear that together with the language of the pagans&#44;<lb/> the worship of paganism would be embraced.<lb/></p>
            <p>I regret that the pen is not always the best exponent of<lb/> our sentiments.  Could we face to face exchange words&#44; we<lb/> might comprehend each other better.  Let me say&#44; how&#45;<lb/>ever&#44; that as far as I can judge&#44; your ideas emanate from<lb/> a pious desire to magnify the dealings of the Lord with<lb/> His chosen witnesses.  As such I appreciate them highly&#44;<lb/> but approving the intention&#44; I disagree with the result of<lb/> your reflections.<lb/></p>
            <p>Respectfully<lb/>
            S. Morais<lb/></p>
            <p>PS. I did not have the pleasure of a personal acquaint&#45;<lb/>ance with Dr Eckman&#44; but from some coreligionists who<lb/> knew him intimately&#44; I <sic><hi rend="underline">learnt</hi></sic> that he was talented and<lb/> conscientious.<lb/></p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
