<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF6_16</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_16_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_16_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_16_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_16_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_16_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_16_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_16_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_16_4v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>6 pages on 2 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For a funeral<lb/></p>
            <p>Israelites&#33;  Persons less closely bound to the bereaved<lb/> family with ties of a long cherished affection&#44; would<lb/> speak&#45;&#45;not more truthfully&#44; but more approvingly<lb/> perhaps of their dear dead than he who now<lb/> addresses this funeral assemblage.  Might<lb/> not my eulogy incur the excusable charge of<lb/> partiality&#45;&#45;be deemed the effect of favors increasingly<lb/> received&#63;  And conversely&#44; might not a single<lb/> utterance of disparagement of the character of a<lb/> friend&#44; be stigmatised as an act of ingratitude&#63;<lb/>  I shall forbear therefore from commending my venerable<lb/> coreligionists for trails not universally known&#44; yet<lb/> existing and deserving of praise in a high degree&#44;<lb/> nor will I even faintly allude to human imperfect&#45;<lb/>&#45;ions which he shared with all of us mortals&#44; so<lb/> liable to err&#44; so fallible in judgment.<lb/></p>
            <p>But to the consolation of the living I love&#44; I will<lb/> tell that the history of the Israelite now enshrouded in this<lb/> coffin&#44; has almost given a denial to a f well Rabbinical<lb/> maxim.  The Sages assure us that &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>no man has ever died having attained<lb/> one half of his heart&#39;s wishes.  This our fellow&#45;<lb/>believer saw many a longing of his soul entirely<lb/> fulfilled.  I may fittingly offer some il&#45;<lb/>&#45;lustrations.  A few years ago&#44; our la&#45;<lb/>&#45;mented coreligionist was lying very ill.  His<lb/> old age&#44; already fully ripe&#44; excited reasonable<lb/> apprehensions touching his recovery.  While<lb/> tossing on the bed of sickness&#44; one thought seem&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed&#44; at that period&#44; supreme in his mind.<lb/>  He had anticipated the spiritual enjoyment<lb/> of attending a forthcoming event.  If he were<lb/> spared to witness its celebration in a state of<lb/> renewed health&#44; he would consider his hap&#45;<lb/>&#45;piness complete.  God&#44; whom the Rabbis<lb/> taught us daily to bless&#44; as &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;the healer of all flesh&#44; wonderful in His doings&#34;<lb/> restored the deceased&#44; that he might behold<lb/> the first born of his oldest son make the<lb/> public declaration of his faith on reaching<lb/> the religious majority&#44; and still grow in years&#44;<lb/> giving promise of a development mental and<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>moral&#44; gratifying to those all who bear<lb/> him love.  Not long after&#44; the<lb/> approaching of an episode in human existence<lb/> as rare solemn as it is solemn rare&#44; kept the Hy......<lb/>family all aglow with joyous expectations.<lb/>  The anniversary of half a century&#39;s wedded life<lb/> would bring together relatives and friends from<lb/> near and from far.  The parents who had<lb/> undergone severe trials to support and liberally<lb/> educate the five surviving children of their numerous<lb/> progeny&#44; would sit patriarchally to receive<lb/> filial homage&#44; and tokens of esteem from in&#45;<lb/>&#45;habitants of Philadelphia and members of the<lb/> Hebrew community.  The incident occasion eagerly<lb/> looked for arrived.  It left an indelible impres&#45;<lb/>&#45;sion upon all who participated therein&#44; by<lb/> reason of the large&#45;hearted hospitality which<lb/> signalized it.  Our deceased fellow religionist<lb/> was then unspeakably happy.  But Yet the<lb/> Almighty in His infinite goodness permitted<lb/> the octogenarian to live two years longer for<lb/> the fruition of late paternal enjoyments still sweeter.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>But such incidents&#45;&#45;forming bright spots<lb/> in a man&#39;s terrestrial journey&#44; are at times<lb/> darkened or erased from f memory&#44; when we<lb/> are compelled to face sad visions arising in<lb/> our domestic horizon.  I mean&#44; when the<lb/> offspring of honored parents&#44; have forfeited<lb/> the respect which their aged father and mother<lb/> commanded.  Then the gladsome past is<lb/> veiled from sight&#59; then&#44; oblivious of that<lb/> delightful past&#44; we dwell with crushing<lb/> sorrow on the melancholy present.<lb/>  Now it is a source of profound satisfaction<lb/> to me&#44; as it doubtless is to the dearly<lb/> beloved widow&#44; and to the venerable departed&#44;<lb/> to know that the five sons of I...and A..<lb/> Hy..... can claim the regard of society&#44;<lb/> and that&#44; not by offensively hiding disowning their<lb/> descent&#44; but for they hold it a privilege to<lb/> be recognized the adherents of Israel&#39;s creed.<lb/>  The contemplation of such antecedents jus&#45; war&#45;<lb/>&#45;tifies &#45;rants my prediction that the successors like will<lb/></p> 
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>follow up in the wake of their predecessors&#44; and never<lb/> become estranged from the ancestral religion&#44;<lb/> to the disquietness of the departed.  For&#44;<lb/> without interpreting to the letter the Talmud&#45;<lb/>&#45;cial allegory that &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> for the sin of the living&#44; the dead are cast out<lb/> of their resting places&#44; we&#44; instructed in the<lb/> doctrine of immortality&#44; may believe that as the<lb/> virtues and righteous deeds of the survivors enhance<lb/> the by bliss of the deceased &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; so<lb/> the vices of impiety of those who outlive us&#44;<lb/> will cause spiritual grief.  But as to this<lb/> Hebrew household&#44; like the second so the third<lb/> generation and the fourth will heighten the<lb/> beatitude of my venerable friend in heaven Eden.<lb/>  Ascend then heavenward with that radiant<lb/> smile which illumined thy countenance&#44; when<lb/> it last met mine intelligently.  Thy thoughts<lb/> still directed to the minor sanctuary whereat<lb/> thou wast wont to make thy devotions&#44; strength<lb/>&#45;ened thy scarcely audible voice to ask of me<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>a favor.  Thou wouldst that I<lb/> offer for thy sake before in aid of the holy shrine&#44;<lb/> a sum which thou didst name.  Now that<lb/> that thou art imparadised&#44; I ask in turn<lb/> a favor of thy undying spirit.  Let it<lb/> offer a prayer above for the welfare God&#39;s<lb/> habitation here below&#44; let it tender supplications that<lb/> its worship may not decay&#44; that religious<lb/> fervor may be enkindled in the heart by the rising generation&#44;<lb/> that thy humble friend may labor successfully<lb/> for the elevation of the Jewish race and for<lb/> the glorification of the Sinaic imparting.<lb/>  We&#44; abiding on this side of the grave&#44; will be&#45;<lb/>&#45;seech the lord that thy benevolent disposition<lb/> evinced by private and public charities&#44; and thy<lb/> attachment to the Law&#44; exhibited by thy attend&#45;<lb/>&#45;ance at the sacred Tabernacle&#44; may atone for thy<lb/> foibles and f backslidings.  We will implore &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; Him the Being whose highest attribute is merely&#44;<lb/> that leaning on the side of compassion&#44; He may bid<lb/> angels greet thy entrance into the ethereal regions&#44; and<lb/> crown thy soul with laurels of unfading glories.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
