<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF12_4</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1888" source="" attested="yes">1888</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_4_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_4_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_4_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_4_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_4_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_4_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_4_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_4_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_4_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_4_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_4_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_4_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>For Beshalach 88<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>
                &#91;Note&#58; The number 47 is written in pencil&#44; circled&#44; in the top right corner.&#93;</p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  The book of Ecclesiastes is&#44; in many<lb/> respects&#44; a source cause of perplexity to students thinkers&#44; for with<lb/> sentiments of deep piety and profound wisdom&#44; we read<lb/> what must sound skeptical and materialistic.  We<lb/> know the obstacles which its admission into the<lb/> sacred canon met.  Whether Solomon wrote that<lb/> scriptural volume towards the close of his career&#44;<lb/> when surfeited with worldly goods&#44; discovered he recognized that all<lb/> striving after temporal gratifications are is vanity of vanities&#44; or whither&#44; as others<lb/> allege&#44; an author of later ages than David&#39;s son&#44; under<lb/> the guise of a luxurious king&#44; raised doubts that we<lb/> might solve&#44; and learn by reflection to avoid excesses of all sorts&#44;<lb/> certain it is that at all events Koheleth is worth studying<lb/> seriously.  One of its sentences gives us this the following instruct&#45;<lb/>ion&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;On the day of prosperity be joyful&#44; but on the day of<lb/> adversity consider.  God has set the one ever against the<lb/> other.&#34;  Now&#58; the our Sabbath section form the Pentateuch&#44; design&#45;<lb/>&#45;ated for this Sabbath&#44; which is&#44; more than ordinarily&#44;<lb/> suggestive&#44; illustrates&#44; I think&#44; in some of the events nar&#45;<lb/>&#45;rated&#44; the saying of the olden preacher&#44; just quoted.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>It presents a graphic picture of a succession of<lb/> changes in human affairs&#44; which as we often witness&#44;<lb/> under different aspects&#44; in our own surroundings.<lb/></p>
            <p>Triumphantly brought out of the sea that <sic>engulphed</sic><lb/> persecuting task masters&#44; and marching on towards the<lb/> Arabian deserts&#44; liberated Israel suffered three days<lb/> for want of water to drink.  The privation was very<lb/> great to over two million creatures and their cattle&#44;<lb/> but journeying further&#44; the precious liquid was at length<lb/> discovered.  Oh&#33; sad disappointment&#33;  Put to the lips&#44; it<lb/> was rejected.  Its acrid taste sorely tried a people&#44; that<lb/> longed to quench their burning thirst.  Providence inter&#45;<lb/>&#45;osed His will and bitterness made room turned to sweetness.  The<lb/> enfranchised slaves proceeded forward.  A delightful oasis with twelve springs and seventy palm trees with their luscious dates appeared was reached&#44; but soon again the<lb/> tongues cleaved to the roof of the mouths&#59; parched<lb/> they were the <sic>travellers</sic> and weary amidst the hot sand of an<lb/> inhospitable wilderness.  Again&#44; God&#39;s intervention<lb/> came to their aid.  Further still they went&#44; to find<lb/> their path intercepted by a wild tribe bent upon slaughter<lb/> and spoil.  The struggle was short.  The God of battles<lb/> fought for with His chosen host&#44; and <sic>tranquillity</sic> was<lb/> restored.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>In these narratives I fancy that I see a favorance&#44; as it were the model a typical representation<lb/> of the contrast which communities everywhere set to view.<lb/>  In one spot a gorgeous mansion.  All is comfort there within&#44; all<lb/> is brilliant with modern inventions.  Not very distant off<lb/> a hovel of misery.  Here the sound shout of noisy <sic>banquetting</sic>&#44;<lb/> there the cry of hunger.  In a chamber of gladness<lb/> over a newly born babe&#59; in another gloom overspread<lb/> by death.  On the streets nuptial music<lb/> and the sound of muffled drams strike the ear of the passerby.<lb/>  Who that has a mind to think&#44; has not noted down<lb/> such contrasts&#63;  But not simply in communities<lb/> at large&#44; is this alternating of pleasure and sorrow per&#45;<lb/>&#45;ceptible.  An hour may suffice to change our state&#59;<lb/> to cast us from the height of prosperity to the depth of<lb/> adversity&#59; while&#44; on the other hand conversely&#44; we may have heard of<lb/> some who lay themselves down in penury&#44; and awoke<lb/> to find a heritage&#44; not dreamt of&#44; within reach.  Again&#58;<lb/> we may have observed how one who yesterday appeared<lb/> so strong as to defy illness&#44; is to day broken down in health.<lb/>  So will the scene of life alter its aspects&#44; as nature does.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Now a storm beclouding the sky&#44; anon calm and<lb/> brightness pervading it.  The Psalmist expresses the<lb/> sentiment thus &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;In the evening<lb/> weeping may be our bed companion&#59; in the morning<lb/> song&#34;.  Realizing then the uncertainty of the<lb/> present&#44; the innumerable occurrences which may alter it&#59; what course ought we mortals to follow&#63;  Ko&#45;<lb/>&#45;helette has showed it &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;  &#34;on the day of prosperity be<lb/> joyful&#44; but on the day of adversity&#44; consider.  God has<lb/> set the one over against the other.&#34;  If we enjoy<lb/> affluence&#44; we should make it conducive it to our hap&#45;<lb/>&#45;piness.  The Almighty wills it.  We should fully avail ourselves of it the Divine boons&#44; but<lb/> not to grow to forget ourselves&#44; not imagining to have gained an immoveable stability&#44; and grow elated&#44; and like a haughty braggart of old&#44;<lb/> say &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;I have gathered wealth<lb/> by the strength of my own hand&#44; and through my own<lb/> wisdom ingenuity&#44; recognizing the instability insecurity of things&#59; hearing in mind possible mutations&#44; for I am intelligent&#34;&#44; but rather we should exclaim&#44; like Jacob&#44;<lb/> exclaim&#44; &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;My father&#39;s God has been<lb/> with me.&#34;  He has prospered my ways.  His sentiment<lb/> will season our pleasures&#59; add zest to human delights&#44; hold us in check &#38; in the path of goodness.<lb/>  If&#44; on the contrary&#44; we are humbly situated&#44; the instabi&#45; insecurity<lb/> &#45;lity of human mutability inconstancy of mundane concerns&#44; will not so depress our spirits<lb/> as to incapacitate us for manly efforts.  We shall will consider.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>At present fortune seems to mock our endeavours&#44;<lb/> our perseverance brings us no reward advantage&#44; but finally<lb/> our a determined resolve to overcome impediments by dint of industry&#44;<lb/> will carry success in its train.  Aye&#58; it is when<lb/> pondering on the changes that individuals&#44; as well as<lb/> communities&#44; undergo&#44; that we will keep our minds<lb/> well balanced.  We shall avoid the madness of those&#44;<lb/> who&#44; whirling round a circle of enjoyments unending schemes for <sic>self&#45;aggrandisement</sic>&#44; never stop<lb/> to heed the demands of humanity&#59; we shall shun<lb/> also the folly of such as sink their manhood into<lb/> a state of depression.  A person ready to accept<lb/> a Divine dispensation&#44; rejoices in humility over wh the<lb/> good&#44; which is at present in his possession&#44; without<lb/> losing sight of the possibility of a different future.<lb/>  His appreciation of that possibility&#44; does not imply<lb/> the necessity of living in dread of reverses&#59; it does not<lb/> counsel the cowardliness of the miser&#44; whom the<lb/> idea of losing his substance robs even of his night&#39;s<lb/> rest.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; but it commends modera&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion&#44; contentment&#44; fellow&#45;feelings with beings who struggle to rise<lb/> honestly&#44; kindliness&#44; thoughtful consideration and&#44;<lb/> above all&#44; implicit reliance in the Supreme Lord Ruler.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>There exists an immeasurable sharp line distinguishing difference distinction between<lb/> a reasonable prudence which is prepared for the un&#45;<lb/>&#45;foreseen and the vulgar fear which constantly<lb/> trembles at imagines descries to be disasters looming up&#59; thus rendering the rich man very poor<lb/> indeed amidst abundant ease&#44; and making his heart&#39;s<lb/> blood so stagnant&#44; so that it cannot be is never quickened<lb/> at the sight of a neighbour&#39;s want.  Why&#44; because<lb/> our condition may change&#44; shall we renounce the<lb/> fruition of blessings granted by a beneficent Lord&#63;<lb/>  Shall we&#44; of our own accord&#44; anticipate evils that<lb/> have not befallen us&#63;  Truly&#44; the improvidence of<lb/> the necessitous&#44; is not so reprehensible as the craven<lb/> apprehensions of the opulent with &#34;seared conscience&#44;<lb/> uninfluenced untouched unmoved by the cry of charity.  But both ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;tremes must be studiously avoided &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;On the day of prosperity<lb/> be joyful&#44; but on the day of adversity&#44; consider.  God has<lb/> set the one over against the other.&#34;  &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Be joyful&#34;<lb/> not narrowly but broadly&#44; seeking pleasure in<lb/> promising pursuits&#44; but also relieving the heavy burdens that many have to bear&#44;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; Consider wiping off tears from the eyes of the distressed&#44; gaining winning a name and<lb/> an eternity by humanity.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Consider&#44;&#34; says Ecclesiastes to the hitherto unfortu&#45;<lb/>&#45;nate&#44; consider not to sink in indolence&#44; but to gird on<lb/> strength to fight obstacles&#44; and conquer &#34;impediments<lb/> to gain a temporal advancement.  In fact&#44; do we<lb/> not occasionally hinder our own forward movements be&#45;<lb/>&#45;cause we choose the pride of sloth as our companion in the journey of life&#63;<lb/>  The decay of families is at times the affect of a stop&#45;<lb/>&#45;page of wholesome exertions to keep up progress.&#44;<lb/> the consequence of extravagance of of lack of system of Judicious government&#44;<lb/> of the a home training of in idleness and recklessness&#44; more<lb/> than the sudden clogging of the wheel of fortune.<lb/>  CContrawise&#44; men&#39;s rising from a lowly state is<lb/> not rarely the as attendant of indefatigable activity and a<lb/> well regulated conduct.  Thus while inertness ac&#45;<lb/>&#45;companied with dejectedness would have plunged the one<lb/> who eng encourages such feelings into the depth of misery&#44;<lb/> his a brave struggle to not to <sic>yeild</sic> to unmanliness&#44; per&#45;<lb/>&#45;formed miracles of success.<lb/></p>
            <p>These considerations will show how wisely vindicate the dealings of God who has<lb/> set the one thing against the other &#91;Hebrew&#93;; prosperity with<lb/> the thought of possible vicissitudes to retain us in virtue&#44; adversity with<lb/> the hope of mounting high on the ladder of material<lb/> and social progress by untiring endeavours.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Ye&#44; brethren&#44; He who governs nations&#44; as well as<lb/> individuals&#44; designed that our enjoyments may grow<lb/> sweeter by contrast with the privations that our fellow&#45; all<lb/> mortals are liable to endure&#44; in the same manner as temporary momentary darkness<lb/> makes light more brilliant in our sight&#44; and as tempo&#45;<lb/>rary sickness makes us value the possession of<lb/> good health more greatly.  The Almighty purposed<lb/> to stir us up to work&#44; to the exercise of our faculties<lb/> bodily and mental&#44; towards our human perfectibility&#44;<lb/> so that meditating on passing events&#44; we might&#44; under all circumstances&#44; recognize<lb/> Him as the Bestower of all the means of our advancement&#44;<lb/> the Arbiter of our destiny&#44; and copying His attributes of mercy and truth&#44; and trusting Him implicitly and entreating<lb/> Him confidently as children an all&#45;loving Father&#44; we<lb/> may become worthy of His unending favors.<lb/></p>
            <p>Oh Ruler of the Universe&#33;  Endow us with the capacity to<lb/> rise higher for our welfare and that of others with whom<lb/> we are associated humanly and religiously.  Cast Thy<lb/> heavenly shield round our lives and our substance&#44; that nei&#45;<lb/>&#45;ther may be exposed to danger&#44; but tech us to ponder on<lb/> the mutations of sublunary affairs&#44; that we may become inspired as with hu&#45;<lb/>&#45;mility&#44; charity and pious serenity now &#38; evermore.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
