<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF10_7</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_7_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_7_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_7_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_7_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_7_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_7_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_7_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_7_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_7_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_7_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_7_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_7_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>G<lb/></p>
            
            <p>Contentment is &#91;&#63;&#93; riches in poverty<lb/>
                For &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>An abundance of food&#44; but no peace&#59; an <sic>overbundance</sic> of luxury&#44;<lb/> but no peace.  Oh&#33; what a blessing is a morsel with <sic>tranquillity</sic>.<lb/>  Words of inspiration&#44; assuming a human voice&#44; speak so in my<lb/> ears.  You cannot have failed&#44; my Brethren&#33; to observe that<lb/> the Arch&#45;prophet promises as a reward to virtue a rich<lb/> crop of whatever man may need or wish for.  The best of<lb/> grain&#44; the most delicious fruits&#44; and all in such profusion<lb/> that what is produced in the spring will engage our full<lb/> time to reap it till the season of vintage arrives&#59; and thus will<lb/> again keep us occupied until late in Autumn&#44; when we plough<lb/> and sow the seed.  But of what advantage will that flowing<lb/> quantity be to us&#44; if the principal ingredient that makes<lb/> it savory is wanting&#63;  Food of prime quality prepared with&#45;<lb/>&#45;out salt will be rejected.  Wine of the choicest grapes&#44; which<lb/> was not given a flavor will be refused.  In the same manner<lb/> affluent means at our disposal will not afford us enjoyment&#44;<lb/> if our home is destitute of the main charm&#45;&#45;<sic>tranquillity</sic>; if<lb/> the country we dwell in is bereft of the chief attraction&#44;&#45;&#45;security.<lb/>  Therefore Moses&#44; after having declared that a large harvest would<lb/> follow our attending to religious duties&#44; says &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>&#34;I will set peace in the land&#44; and you shall lie<lb/> down&#44; with more to be make you afraid&#34;  Rest sweet&#45;<lb/>&#45;ened by a confiding trust in the judicious government of the wife&#44;<lb/> and the contented disposition of the children&#59; sleep refreshing<lb/> the mind by the knowledge of the ability in the rulers to<lb/> protect all&#44; and allow them the undisturbed fruition of<lb/> their earnings&#59; aye&#58; such is the blessing for attaining<lb/> the which we should labor and beseech God.  And we can&#44;<lb/> my Brethren&#33; reach it if we walk in the Statutes of the Lord&#44;<lb/> and not after our own imaginations&#44; leading us far astray.<lb/>  For many neglect to gather what Providence has with un&#45;<lb/>&#45;stinted generosity laid in their path&#44; because they are<lb/> intent upon looking on&#44; what they consider&#44; the endless pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;ductions which others store away.  &#34;What is our scant pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;vision&#44; compared with the overflowing and varied supply set<lb/> before our neighbors&#63;  They enjoy life&#44; they are truly happy.<lb/>  Could we only bid farewell to our drudging we might also<lb/> feel once at rest.&#34;  But is it so as they complain&#63;  Has<lb/> a universal Father denied most of his children the<lb/> means of rendering existence enjoyable&#44; and unfastened<lb/> his treasures exclusively for a privileged few&#63;  Far be<lb/> iniquity from God&#44; and wrong from the Almighty &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>To me it seems that our market&#45;houses had a thousand<lb/> tongues rebuking human ingratitude while rehearsing the<lb/> goodness of God.  When I pas through them at this beauti&#45;<lb/>&#45;ful season&#44; and behold that fulness&#44; that exhaustless wealth<lb/> prepared by an invisible hand and brought within reach of<lb/> the humblest&#44; I feel that to murmur and repine is absolute wickedness.<lb/>  No&#58; our way is not hedged around&#59; we also can move on and<lb/> gather more than we actually need&#44; but we must think<lb/> and thank in order to enjoy what has been generously<lb/> bestowed.  We must carry a high aim before us&#44; when we go<lb/> forth to work.  Then we can enjoy have rest&#44; without considering deprecating<lb/> hard labor as our tyrant.  That aim which smooths the<lb/> rough edge of toil is love and gratitude.  To make the<lb/> beings who depend on our exertions happy&#44; and teach them<lb/> by example to look up to a beneficent Providence should<lb/> be our incentive.  So impelled we will not stop short<lb/> by the way and fold our arms while casting an envious look<lb/> now on that man who rides in a carriage wit ha powered<lb/> footman&#44; and a driver in livery&#59; again upon another bowed<lb/> to by a large number of attendants.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Remembering&#44; that as our Sages asserted&#44; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> He who has too much substance has load of care&#44; or the<lb/> philosopher&#45;king writes &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;the abundance of<lb/> the rich will not suffer him to sleep&#44;&#34; we will proceed<lb/> forward with a steadier step&#59; love for the dear objects<lb/> at home&#44; a desire to promote the temporal and spiritual<lb/> welfare of wife and children will quicken and strengthen<lb/> our faculties.  This I say in a way of<lb/> friendly converse to those of my brethren&#44; who lament that fortune<lb/> has not smiled upon them&#44; as the phrase goes.  The merchant<lb/> can sit quietly behind his desk&#44; give orders&#44; and draw in<lb/> the profits&#59; they on the contrary&#44; have to plod for a pittance.<lb/>  Some rise at late hours&#44; and are driven in coaches to<lb/> their counting&#45;houses&#44; they must walk distances&#44; and stand<lb/> a whole day to complete their task.  Some are dressed in<lb/> broad&#45;cloth&#44; they in coarse apparel.  But you do not know&#44;<lb/> my friends&#33; how under the diamond brilliant studded shirt&#44; the heart may<lb/> palpitate ache&#59; how under the semblance of ease&#44; care may eating<lb/> on the vitals.  You see the magnificence of the palace&#44; but<lb/> not the skeleton within&#59; gay gardens&#44; but not the prickly<lb/> thorns.  The soft bed you envy&#44; may sometime be a rack upon<lb/> which the opulent are tortured by harassing thoughts&#44; while<lb/> you&#45;&#45;humble workmen&#44; lie down with nothing to make you afraid.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>You are rich&#44; my Brethren&#33; in your poverty&#44; if you<lb/> possess the blessing of a virtuous home.  You should<lb/> feel happy in your poverty&#44; if you are supported in<lb/> your hard labor by the affection of those who smile tenderly<lb/> at the arrival in that home of the husband and father.  You should<lb/> be perfectly contented to drudge&#44; if you have every reason to<lb/> hope that your children will rise and reverence the memory of<lb/> their mother&#44; and call their father sainted their saintly benefactor&#59; if you can perceive<lb/> that by your exertions they will gain the knowledge of the useful&#44;<lb/> through the facilities&#44; which this land country of security offers.  For&#44;<lb/> verily you can experience here&#44; if so you will&#44; the <sic>fulfilment</sic> of<lb/> the Divine promise &#34;you shall eat your bread to the full&#44;<lb/> and dwell in your land in safety.&#34;  But if you engraft<lb/> upon the tender hearts of your offspring the rank seeds of<lb/> <sic>of</sic> pithy jealousies&#44; you breed discontent&#44; you give them<lb/> an existence destitute of its most important element&#44; of its<lb/> very salt&#44; of the pleasure flowing from activity of body<lb/> and mind.  Have you&#44; my friends&#33; ever<lb/> read the 128th psalm attentively&#63;  The author describes<lb/> the home of a God&#45;fearing Israelite.  The father of the<lb/> family is engaged in manual work.  He goes to it with<lb/> alacrity&#44; and returns from it with a light heart.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>His wife modestly attends to duty&#44; and craves for nothing<lb/> higher than the welfare of her household.  Like a vine<lb/> planted on a side&#44; scarcely perceptible&#44; but extending its<lb/> ramifications further&#44; so does she make her retiring virtues<lb/> felt beyond her domestic circle.  The children cluster<lb/> around&#44; and cling to their parents.  They are compared<lb/> for the steadfastness of their affection to branches of olive<lb/> trees&#44; retaining fresh fruit through all the changes of the<lb/> seasons.  Then the place in which the God&#45;fearing man<lb/> lives&#44; affords him scope for the pursuit of happiness&#44;<lb/> and&#44; together with a whole grateful people&#44; he enjoys the<lb/> greatest of blessings&#58; peace.  Such is the picture&#44; simple<lb/> but graphic of the dwelling of an Israelite&#44; who understands<lb/> how to distinguish real from imaginary wealth.<lb/></p>
            <p>See&#44; my dear friends in humble circumstances&#33;  See&#33; the Psalm&#45;<lb/>&#45;ist does not portray the happiness of the subject he has deli&#45;<lb/>&#45;neated as derived from the possession of vast estates&#44;<lb/> of summer residences&#44; of fast horses&#44; and of splendid yachts&#44; but from<lb/> the labor of his hand.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>And what he enjoyed all of you can acquire in<lb/> this country of plenty and of freedom.  Let your<lb/> habitation and the inmates thereof be the centre of your<lb/> affection&#59; and raise there a temple of peace&#44; by means<lb/> of your own endeavours&#44; and of by your own trust in a bene&#45;<lb/>ficent Providence&#59; even such a temple let your dear ones <sic>ralley</sic> around it.  Let up then a high &#91;&#63;&#93; as Gideon rais an<lb/> built when reassured and strengthened by heavenly promises.<lb/>  Do you remember the name it he gave it&#63;  He called it<lb/> &#34;Adona&#239; Shalom.&#34;  The Lord is peace.  And He who<lb/> loves peace&#44; and of whom it is written that He reigns<lb/> in heaven the highest with a crown of peace&#59; will abide<lb/> also in your midst.  You will look up unto Him alone&#44;<lb/> and He will refresh your body&#44; redouble your energies&#44;<lb/> so that by industry&#44; by temperance&#44; and by attendance to<lb/> religious duties&#44; you may g gather in abundance provision&#44;<lb/> be down&#44; with nothing to make you afraid.<lb/></p>
            <p>And may He vouchsafe to shower down that invaluable blessing<lb/> upon all of us&#44; rich and poor&#44; the teachers and the thought&#44;<lb/> the afflicted and the consolers&#44; that in us be <sic>fufilled</sic><lb/> the sentence of the good book.  &#34;The Lord g will give<lb/> strength to His people&#44; the Lord will bless His<lb/> people with peace&#34;.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
