<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF2_16</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_16_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_16_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_16_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_16_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_16_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_16_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_16_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_16_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_16_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_16_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_16_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_16_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_16_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_16_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_16_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_16_8v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_16_9r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_16_9v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_16_10r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_16_10v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>17 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>The fear of God<lb/>
                for the<lb/>
                Penitential Sabbath<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Read with your mother&#44; plead&#44; for she is not my wife<lb/> nor am I her husband. &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;And she shall follow her after her lovers&#44; but she shall<lb/> not overtake them&#44; and she shall seek them&#44; but shall<lb/> not find them&#44; then she shall say&#44; I will go up and return<lb/> to my first husband&#44; for then it was better with me<lb/> than now.&#34;  My Brethren&#33;  The prophet Hosea&#44; repre&#45;<lb/>&#45;senting Israel under the figure of a faithless wife&#44; de&#45;<lb/>&#45;serting Israel under the figure of a faithless wife&#44; de&#45;<lb/>scribes in forcible language man&#39;s besetting sin.  It is&#44;<lb/> as you must have already understood from his words&#44;<lb/> a spirit of discontent&#59; a forgetfulness of the blessings we<lb/> enjoy&#44; and a longing after acquisitions&#44; which we magnify<lb/> as being infinitely superior to those we already possess.<lb/>  These feelings which scarcely any of us endeavours to<lb/> conquer&#44; breed the impiety of which we are guilty<lb/> and the heartburnings we frequently suffer.  Imagining<lb/> that man&#39;s joyous state on earth is proportionate to his wealth<lb/> and preferments&#44; we forsake religion to go in quest<lb/> of that which our perverted minds suggest as wanting to<lb/> our happiness.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>We anticipate reaching the end of our desires&#44; by<lb/> disregarding the Divine commands&#44; which act as a<lb/> restraint upon them&#44; but the inspired writer&#44; thus me&#45;<lb/>taphorically addresses each of us.  Man&#33; why wilt<lb/> thou suffer a deceptive light to guide thy steps&#63;<lb/>  See&#33;  Thy way leads to sin and disappointments.<lb/>  Thou wilt exhaust thy strength in the attempt to<lb/> overcome the impediments which surround the path<lb/> thou hast chosen&#44; for none can gain happiness by<lb/> a departure from God.  Return then to Him who alone<lb/> can bestow both the temporal and the spiritual good<lb/>s that gladden human existence.  Acknowledge that a<lb/> lowly condition with His love&#44; is incomparably more<lb/> joyous than a towering station with His displeasure&#44;<lb/> and give thy Creator thanks.<lb/></p>
            <p>Beloved hearers&#33;  On this Sabbath&#44; devoted to penitence&#44; let<lb/> us ponder on and heeds the words which the Lord has<lb/> spoken through his righteous messenger.  Surely<lb/> not one of us will consider them inapplicable to<lb/> his case.  I may venture to assert&#44; without being<lb/> guilty of personal offence&#44; that there will not<lb/> be found in our midst a second Job who can<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>swear &#91;Hebrew&#93; that he has made a covenant<lb/> with his eyes never to be lured away from rectitude&#44; never<lb/> to covet a neighbor&#39;s possessions&#44; nor touch aught with<lb/> his hand that is not legitimately his own.  No&#44;<lb/> we all&#44; in a small or in a high degree&#44; have postponed<lb/> the instincts of the soul to the cravings of the flesh.<lb/>  It may be that sensuality was our instigator.  Per&#45;<lb/>&#45;haps the glittering of gold&#44; inveigled us away&#44; or a<lb/> despicable ambition to shine in fashionable society&#44;<lb/> may have impelled us to abandon religion&#44; and run<lb/> headlong after the vanities of the world.  Many&#44; a<lb/> great many may have been the enticements which<lb/> our eyes and our hearts held forth to make us swerve<lb/> from the rules of probity&#44; for&#44; as our Rabbins declare&#44;<lb/> those two organs of the human frame&#44; are the<lb/> principal instruments of sin &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> But the time is now opportune&#44; when we<lb/> should seek out the root of our backslidings&#44; and<lb/> pluck it off.  Our actions are being tried at<lb/> the bar from whence there is no appeal.  The universal<lb/> Judge seated on a high and exalted throne&#44; holds<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>in his right hand the balance of justice.  Brethren&#33;<lb/>  Let us cast penitence therein&#44; and the weight of our<lb/> sins shall be lightened.  For He who is inexorable<lb/> with the obdurate&#44; yearns with compassion towards those<lb/> who approach him with a contrite and subdued spirit.<lb/>  We need not fear a repulse&#44; if we will only fear Him.<lb/>  We shall be relieved of all uneasiness touching our fate&#44;<lb/> if we will but cleave unto the word of God as to the<lb/> anchor of salvation&#59; for from its observance flows a<lb/> life of contentment here below&#44; and unutterable bliss above.<lb/>  I have said it my beloved hearers&#44; let us only fear the Lord&#44; be&#45;<lb/>&#45;cause if we could penetrate the inmost recesses of the<lb/> human heart&#44; we would discover that a strong incentive<lb/> to irreligion&#44; is the entertaining of some imaginary fear.<lb/>  I will be more explicit.  The miser who is deaf<lb/> to the cry of the needy&#44; while intent upon watching<lb/> over the pelf he has garnered&#59; the avaricious who<lb/> will allow no day of rest to intervene between themselves<lb/> and their grasping disposition&#44; the dissolute who<lb/> cast side every restraint to indulge their appetites&#44;<lb/></p> 
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>the hypocrite and the flatterer&#44; if all of them are<lb/> actuated by the same groundless apprehension.  That<lb/> is the feeling&#44; which&#44; lurking in their breasts&#44; renders<lb/> the one pitiless&#44; lest by acts of generosity he be brought<lb/> to poverty&#59; makes the other trample on religion&#44;<lb/> lest cessation from labor may lessen his wealth.<lb/>  Encourages the third to follow immorality&#44; lest he<lb/> should lose agreeable associates&#59; and the same feeling<lb/> it is&#44; that which caused many to disguise the truth&#44; that<lb/> they may not endanger a lucrative position&#44; or some<lb/> high office.  And yet&#44; oh stupendous contradiction&#33;<lb/> we that are so easily swayed by a fear which is the<lb/> offspring of our vitiated minds&#44; remain undisturbed<lb/> at the thought of an Almighty Being&#44; who can<lb/> suddenly cut off all the means of human enjoyment&#44;<lb/> aye&#44; our own life.  No fear of Him seizes our<lb/> hearts when we violate his law&#44; and deride his or&#45;<lb/>&#45;dinances.  But what renders this inconsistency still more<lb/> glaring is the fact&#44; that the ills we so greatly fear<lb/> and to avoid which&#44; we disregard the dictates of religion&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>are under the absolute control of God &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;Of whom art<lb/> thou in dread&#44; and what dost thou fear&#44; that thou<lb/> liest&#63;  Me&#44; thou hast not remembered&#44; nor placed<lb/> upon they heart&#34;.  so exclaims Isaiah in the name of<lb/> the Most High.  Whereas by bearing in mind that<lb/> whatsoever exists is subject to the will of the Supreme&#44;<lb/> we could calm any apprehension as to the future&#44; and<lb/> exercise righteousness as a sign of gratitude&#44; for bless<lb/>&#45;sings already obtained.  Whereas by having the fear of<lb/> the Lord constantly before our eyes&#44; we would remain<lb/> tranquil even amidst reverses&#44; we create evils and<lb/> intensify them&#44; because we exclude from our bosom<lb/> a sentiment so soothing and so comforting.<lb/></p>
            <p>But mark&#44; my friends&#33;  Mark the difference between<lb/> the man&#44; to whose mind God is ever present&#44; and<lb/> him who is chained to the world and its fleeting<lb/> joys.  Mark it especially in the hour of adversity.<lb/>  Contrast the serenity of one&#44; with the perturbation&#44; with<lb/> the violent agitation of the other.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>A soul that fears the Lord ascribes his injustice<lb/> unto Him&#44; whose attributes are mercy and compassion.<lb/>  Like the righteous Job&#44; a believer in Providence will<lb/> ask himself when afflicted &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Shall we receive good at the<lb/> hand of God&#44; and shall we not receive also evil&#63;&#34;<lb/>  Nay&#44; he will acknowledge no actual evil&#44; save that<lb/> which follows our disobedience of the Law&#44; that is&#44; the<lb/> forfeiting of God&#39;s our Fathers love.  As the rod of Abram&#44; when God&#44; in<lb/> converted into a serpent the hand of Aaron&#44; swelled all the rods of the<lb/> Egyptian soothsayers&#44; so will the fear of the Most<lb/> High erase every human fear from the mind of the<lb/> religious.  Not so with the man of little faith.<lb/>  He chafes and rages under inflictions.  He reproa&#45;<lb/>ches himself&#44; because his foresight on which he<lb/> trusted&#44; did not avert what has befallen him un&#45;<lb/>awares.  He often attributes to &#91;inserted above&#58; charges&#93; the innocent&#44; even to<lb/> those with whom he is bound with most sacred ties&#45;&#45;<lb/>the origin of his suffering&#44; and to use the language<lb/> employed by the son of Amoz &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>&#34;And it shall come to pass that when he shall be<lb/> hungry&#44; he shall fret himself&#44; and curse his King and<lb/> God&#44; looking upward.&#34;  He does not recognize a<lb/> wise Providence&#44; that makes every sublunary event to work<lb/> out his plan in the government of the world.  He<lb/> will not admit that as a tender father studies of the<lb/> welfare of his children&#44; so does the Lord seek the real<lb/> happiness of those who fear him.  He denies that<lb/> though they may be tried as gold is tried&#44; yet those<lb/> who revere his name shall shine as stars in the<lb/> firmament&#59; that the Sun of righteousness with<lb/> healing in its wings will arise and cast a flood of<lb/> light upon them.  Can he be comforted&#63;  Will philosophy impress<lb/> him with those consoling truths&#63;  No&#44; it may tell<lb/> him that to complain of evils which are beyond human<lb/> control is unwise&#44; but it will never impart to his<lb/> soul the contentment which they experience who<lb/> believe in a good and beneficent Creator.<lb/></p>  
            <p>Oh&#33; my beloved hearers&#33; if we could read on man&#39;s<lb/> countenance what passes within his breast&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>many whom we envy&#44; might excite our commiseration&#44;<lb/> while certain occurrences which we deprecated as un&#45;<lb/>&#45;mitigated evils&#44; would appear to us as blessings<lb/> in disguise.  If we could unravel the threads<lb/> of many a circumstances we would stand aghast which we cannot reconcile<lb/> at the with Divine justice&#44; we would stand aghast at the<lb/> wisdom they reveal it displays.  Would that man were<lb/> deeply impressed with the fear of God&#44; for then all<lb/> misgivings&#44; all doubts would dissipate.  We would<lb/> not dismiss religion as our earthly guide and companion&#44;<lb/> because its association curbs our desires.  We would<lb/> not forsake the path of righteousness&#44; which seems<lb/> narrow&#44; to pursue that of impiety&#44; because apparently<lb/> wide.  With God ever present to our minds&#44; we would<lb/> not tremble&#44; though the lowering clouds of misfortune<lb/> encompass us around.  We would&#44; as it were&#44; suck honey<lb/> from even the bitter poison of asps.  Are we<lb/> threatened with the loss of wealth&#63;  There is a greater<lb/> calamity than indigence&#58; the loss of our reputation.<lb/>  Are we stricken down with disease&#63;  There is no sick&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness that can equal in virulence the leprosy of the soul.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>Have we sustained bereavements&#63;  It is better to<lb/> bemoan the dead than grieve over the infamy of<lb/> the living.  Such and similar considerations would<lb/> uphold sustain us under the most trying circumstances.<lb/>  The storms of adversity might rage against us&#44;<lb/> the surging billows of misfortune might upheave<lb/> their heads&#44; but we would be safe on the mountain<lb/> of the Lord&#44; had in the cliff of his impregnable<lb/> rock.  Wou We would then say. &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;We do not fear&#44; though the earth be removed&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;The Lord of hosts is with us&#44; the<lb/> God of Jacob is our refuge.&#34;  My dear<lb/> Brethren&#33;  The history of our predecessors is not desti&#45;<lb/>&#45;tute of examples illustrative of this great truth.  The<lb/> checkered life of David&#44; whose words I have just quoted&#44;<lb/> that of the upright Job&#44; the privations of an Elijah&#44;<lb/> and the suffering of a Jeremiah&#44; confirm it beyond<lb/> contradiction.  But I am now reminded of an<lb/> incident of later date&#44; exhibiting the effects of re&#45;<lb/>ligion in a confiding soul.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>When Rabby Eliezer lay on the bed of sickness&#44; his<lb/> disciples came to visit him.  As he saw them&#44; he<lb/> exclaimed &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;A great wrath has been poured<lb/> on the world through me&#34;.  At this&#44; they burst into tears.<lb/>  Rabbi Akibah alone appeared unmoved.  With surprise&#44; his<lb/> colleagues inquired&#44; how he could remain cheerful&#44; when the<lb/> light of the Law was about to be extinguished.  He replied&#58;<lb/> &#34;Has I seen our teacher enjoying uninterrupted prosperity&#44;<lb/> I might have feared that his merits had already been<lb/> fully remunerated in this life&#44; but now I witness his trials<lb/> and feel that much happiness yet awaits him.  His expla&#45;<lb/>&#45;nation grieved the venerable preceptor&#59; and he asked &#34;<lb/>Dost thou know which command of our holy law I have<lb/> neglected&#34;&#63;  &#34;I cannot tell&#34; rejoined th his scholar&#44; but I have<lb/> been taught to believe that &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> there is not a man&#44; however just&#44; who doeth good&#44;<lb/> and sinneth not.&#34;  Friends&#33;  Let us take this lesson<lb/> to heart.  Have we suffered losses and tribulations during<lb/> the year that has closed upon us&#63;  It was the hand<lb/> of God that chastened us&#44; for our ultimate good.<lb/>  Let us not forget our provocations&#44; and we shall<lb/> feel<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p>that not according to our inequities hath He dealt with<lb/> us&#44; for&#44; we also&#44; moved by groundless fear&#44; have<lb/> often cast aside the fear of the Lord.  If we are<lb/> true to ourselves&#44; we must acknowledge that many<lb/> among has us have set at <sic>nought</sic> his blessed injunctions&#44;<lb/> to grasp shadows&#44; which receded as we in proportion<lb/> as we fancied to have approached them.<lb/>
                He may strive to soothe the pangs of a guilty conscience &#91;inserted above&#58; blast the edge of cutting remorse&#93;<lb/> by specious arguments.  Have we as Israelites&#44; violated the covenant which the Lord made with our fathers in Horeb&#44; not<lb/> to be laughed at by the exposed to the ridicule of scoffers&#63;  Times have changed&#44;<lb/> we will say&#44; the character of our association is such that<lb/> we cannot be tied down to restrictive rules.  Have<lb/> we endeavoured to heighten our position&#44; by spurning &#91;inserted above&#44; in pencil&#58; lowering&#93;<lb/> the word of God&#63;  Have we&#44; with that object in view&#44; &#91;inserted above&#44; in pencil&#58; the standard of our faith in the eyes of the world&#63;&#93;<lb/> profaned the Sabbath&#44; desecrated the festivals&#44;<lb/> fed to satiety on the flesh which the book of books<lb/> declares impure&#63;  We will say&#44; that we must run<lb/> after the current&#44; to use a vulgar phrase&#44; not to<lb/> be left behind unheeded and uncared for.  Have<lb/> we scouted the idea of wearing upon our hand<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="14"/>
            <p>the mark of our redemption from bondage&#44; and<lb/> of bearing it as frontlets between our eyes&#63;  Have we<lb/> left our dwellings void of the most important ornament<lb/> the word of God affixed to our door&#45;posts&#63; we will<lb/> not be at a loss to find a palliation to our irreligious demeanour.  But<lb/> as we are Jews&#44; and wish to remain such and as the<lb/> days of our infancy are brought back to our mind&#44;<lb/> and we remember when our faltering lips learnt to<lb/> declare that the Law of Moses is the perpetual in&#45;<lb/>&#45;heritance of the Congregation of Jacob&#44; we can&#91;n&#93;ot<lb/> but feel that our actions are an insult to God&#44; and a<lb/> lie to our professions.  It would be necessary&#44; in order<lb/> to stifle every sense of remorse&#44; to deny the revelation of Sinai&#44;<lb/> do believe that our prophets and Sages saw false vi&#45;<lb/>&#45;sions&#44; that the teachings of thirty five generations&#44;<lb/> whence upon which the fabric of human society is<lb/> built&#44; are futile inventions and mendacious vanities.<lb/>  But...begone impious thought.  Thou art cast out<lb/> as pollution itself &#44; from this assembly.  No mind<lb/> is so corrupted to harbor thee.  Our hearts have been<lb/> tainted with sin&#44; but we shall wash them it<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="15"/>
            <p>the water fountain of purification&#44; not in the miry pools<lb/> of stagnant water.  Ah&#33; my dear Brethren&#33;  Let<lb/> me hope that beings so wretched who have rejected<lb/> the fear of the Lord&#44; cannot be found among my<lb/> hearers&#44; let me pray that there may never exist<lb/> in Israel one who has defied the command of God.<lb/>  But if you know of any such&#44; Oh implore of them for the<lb/> sake of their future peace&#44; for the sake of their child&#45;<lb/>&#45;ren&#44; on whom their guilt would naturally be entailed&#44;<lb/> and visited&#59; and as they value the blessing of a serene<lb/> death&#44; and of joy beyond the grave beseech them to cast off<lb/> the garments of impunity&#44; and put on a vesture<lb/> of unspotted whiteness.  To let neither the buoyancy<lb/> of youth&#44; nor the vigour of manhood allure them<lb/> for&#44; those days and those years will pass off as a<lb/> shadow&#44; and a night without dawn envelop them.<lb/>  They will then repent&#44; but in vain&#44; of a life <sic>mispent</sic><lb/> in disobeying the kindest parent and Friend.  Confusion<lb/> and horror will seize them&#44; when remembering<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="16"/>
            <p>that they have forsaken a heavenly guide&#44; to<lb/> follow the lead of the worldly and the impious.  Fain<lb/> would they then return to Him they have deserted.  Like<lb/> the faithless wife figuratively spoken of by Hosea&#44;<lb/> each of them may long after a reunion with their first Lord&#44; but they<lb/> will have raised a b abyss to of eternal separation. them from<lb/> their love.  But not alone they who have ar&#45;<lb/>&#45;rogantly raised a standard of rebellion against their<lb/> King&#44; must hasten their return&#44; if they desire a reconciliation&#44;<lb/> but those also that have disobeyed his behests&#44; through<lb/> the promptings of the flesh.  Their crime is not so<lb/> grievous as that of the former&#44; because human frailty<lb/> and not human depravity has occasioned it&#44; yet&#44; who<lb/> stood in secret communion with the Eternal Most High&#44; to<lb/> know how far He will suffer the creatures&#44; whom<lb/> He has endowed with intellect and free will&#44; to be<lb/> governed by the passions&#63;  Let not the mortals temper<lb/> with the salvation of their souls&#44; for in the heavenly<lb/> volumes&#44; it has been written &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;Ye shall<lb/> not tempt the Lord your God.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="17"/>
            <p>Let those therefore who by what cause soever have<lb/> been guilty of dereliction&#44; speedily retrace their steps&#59;<lb/> and come with contrition and sincerity to the footstool<lb/> of the merciful judge.  Let everyone of us&#44; my<lb/> dear Brethren&#33; accurately examine his past career&#44;<lb/> and if he discovers then in its various walks he has<lb/> faltered in the discharge of his duty&#44; if he finds that<lb/> he has opposed the will of God as expressed in the pages<lb/> of truth&#44; let him&#44; the like the righteous Job acknow&#45;<lb/>&#45;ledge that he abhors himself&#44; and repents in dust and<lb/> ashes.  Let him promise with unfeigned lips&#44; that<lb/> during the year we have just entered&#44; he will strive<lb/> to gather a treasure of imperishable value&#44; of piety as<lb/> a Jew&#44; and of charity as a man.  Then He who is<lb/> full of mercy&#44; will afford him the consoling assurance&#44;<lb/> that He &#34;has caused his transgressions to vanish as a<lb/> thick cloud&#44; and his sins as mist.&#34;  That his &#34;He has redeemed<lb/> his soul from perdition&#44; and his life from sorrow.&#34;<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
