<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF1_7</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_7_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_7_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_7_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_7_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_7_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_7_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_7_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_7_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_7_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_7_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_7_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_7_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For Shekalim &#38; 22d of February<lb/>
                together with a Bar Mitzvah<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>It seldom happens that a preacher has three subjects to<lb/> present before to his hearers simultaneously.  That coincidence<lb/> occurs today.  First&#44; the additional lecture form the Penta&#45;<lb/>&#45;teuch reminds us of an event altogether Jewish in its historic&#45;<lb/>&#45;al character.  Secondly&#44; a festive appearance all around&#44; recalls<lb/> a birth&#44; joyful to freedom loving Americans&#44; and thirdly&#44; the<lb/> ascending of upon this desk by a lad&#44; directs our attention to a cere&#45; circum&#45;<lb/>&#45;mony &#45;stance peculiarly congregational.  But Still&#44; the singularity of the<lb/> occasion&#44; will not nevertheless&#44; demand at my hands a lengthy<lb/> discourse.  For&#44; the three topics it suggests&#44; have been enlarged<lb/> upon separately time and again.  I shall not therefore<lb/> explain the ordinances of the half a shekel that has given this Sabbath the name by which it is designated.  There can be none<lb/> within hearing of my voice who have not learnt that before anciently<lb/> the return of the ecclesiastical year at Nissan each Israelite deposited<lb/> into the national treasury before the return of the ecclesiastical year&#44; at Nissan&#44; the coin prescribed in the wilderness<lb/> of Sinai&#59; and that the aggregate amount was devoted to the<lb/> wants of the public worship.  and All are aware likewise that the practice&#44; prevail&#45; of<lb/> &#45;ing in many Hebrew communities&#44; of donating donating a sum equivalent to that at this season&#44; a sum equivalent to the same<lb/> coin at this season coin&#44; for the use of the Synagogue&#45;&#45;as it prevails in many Hebrew communities&#44; is simply<lb/> commemorative of the past.  Nor will I offer to<lb/> view incidents on the life of the father of this country&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>out of deference to his natal day&#44; for&#44; conspiring&#44; indeed&#44; as the theme<lb/> must always be&#44; I could not but repeat myself.  I could not certainly increase in any degree a<lb/> knowledge universally possessed from main to Texas and from the St Lawrence to the Pacific ocean.<lb/>  A tyro will tell why Washington challenges the admira&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion and reverence of all who value sterling virtue&#59; and<lb/> by what means he earned the laurels of immortality.  And as<lb/> to the admission of a youth into our religious fellowship&#44;<lb/> the frequency of the circumstance ceremonies has ceased to elicit<lb/> thoughts strikingly instructive&#44; save&#44; perhaps&#44; to the<lb/> individual immediately concerned.  Yet still&#44; to suffer<lb/> the coincidence to pass by without drawing some moral&#44; would<lb/> ill&#45;become one who must inspire attachment for awaken respect endeavour to vitalize the observances<lb/> of the ancestral faith&#44; and awaken devotion to love for human goodness.<lb/>  Let us then consider.  The equal weight of the coin that<lb/> rich and poor deposited into the Sanctuary&#44; must have<lb/> been intended to impress our people with ideas democratically<lb/> broad.  All should supported in a like manner the house of the<lb/> Lord&#44; and all alike would derived identical advantages from<lb/> the rites performed by the officiating minister.  Thus none<lb/> could boast of personal superiority&#44; alleging that he contributed<lb/> more largely than others to the maintenance of the altar&#44;<lb/> and none could claim a greater favors from a closer proximity to the Deity&#44; urging<lb/></p> 
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>that the piety he evinced assumed a magnificent<lb/> form.  No&#58; a money aristocracy shall not secure a<lb/> seat of honor places of distinction&#44; where the universal Father bids His<lb/> Divinity rest.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Only one half of a com Even the greatest shall come with one half of a coin&#44; for&#44; as expressed by our philosophers&#44; man however exalted<lb/> in the world&#44; is imperfect in the sight of her Maker.  hence the &#91;&#63;&#93; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> sentence which follows &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>  The reputed righteous shall not be given &#91;&#63;&#93; honors&#44;<lb/> that they may look down with holy horror upon miserable<lb/> sinners.  &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#91;Hebrew&#93; The half&#45;shekel was to atone for all souls.<lb/>  A Moses himself&#44; he who had been supernaturally commissioned to communicate<lb/> the ordinance&#44; was included in the number of those for<lb/> whose spiritual welfare the Tabernacle daily resounded with<lb/> invocations and entreaties.  What means then<lb/> the offensive glorification&#44; which the opulent receive in some<lb/> modern Temples&#63;  I call it offensive&#44; because the destitute<lb/> who are scarcely recognized there as fellow&#45;believers&#44; must feel<lb/> deeply wounded by the partiality.  There was a time&#44; when<lb/> the privilege of performing an act&#44; during taking an action part in the worship&#44; deemed was<lb/> meritorious&#44; had to be bought at auction&#59; when the do highest<lb/> bidder performed what he deemed meritorious.  That<lb/> exceedingly objectionable feature in the service of the Al&#45;<lb/>mighty&#44; is&#44; I think&#44; wiped away in every dwelling of<lb/> prayer&#44; claiming respectability.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>But we have not advanced enough.  The democratic<lb/> principles of Mosaism meet with a check whenever the affluent are brought the needy<lb/> are driven into a corner&#44; and left quite unnoticed prominently in the habitation<lb/> of their&#44; as well as the rich man&#39;s&#44; God.  Parti&#45;<lb/>&#45;cularly noticeable is the wrong&#44; when solemn sanctity has<lb/> to makes room for vulgar pomposity&#59; and when noisy piety<lb/> is made to override self&#45;abasing condemned defection.  I forbear citing instances&#44; illustrating my thoughts&#44; but I I rejoice<lb/> that because that notwithstanding radical defects&#44; whose removal&#44;  motives&#44;<lb/> which I do not desire to set forth&#44; prevent&#44; this our minor Sanct&#45;<lb/>&#45;uary approaches&#44; in a measure&#44; my ideal of a Jewish place<lb/> of worship.  With the exception of the reader and lecturer&#44;<lb/> who&#44; to be heard&#44; must unavoidably stand high&#44; a disparity<lb/> of rank or class among the attendants is scarcely perceptible.  And<lb/> all indiscriminately obtain countenance&#44; and the consideration<lb/> due and deeply appointed the humble station to one another&#44; so so highly greatly prized by such as occupy an humble station in the outside<lb/> world.<lb/></p>
                <p>But not always do my brethren prove by their conduct&#44;<lb/> beyond these sacred precincts&#44; that they understand the rules<lb/> of equity.  It was the expressed wish of the greatest American<lb/> as in not less than that of the greatest Hebrew&#44; that we should<lb/> <sic>excell</sic> in righteousness.  To an address of our fathers&#44; Washington<lb/> responded with his usual wisdom and kindliness of sentiments.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Complemented for the valor exhibited on the battle field&#44;<lb/> and for his administrative talents&#44; the recipient of well&#45;deserved<lb/> praises said that he was touched by the words of his fellow&#45;<lb/>citizens of the stock of Abraham&#44; and he prayed that they might<lb/> thenceforth show their title to the liberties immunities guaranteed by the<lb/> constitution and purchased by the life&#45;blood of the brave.  That title is based not on the ability to acquire<lb/> wealth affluence&#44; which the favored land has facilitated&#59; not on the capacity<lb/> to ventilate one&#39;s views at caucus meetings&#44; but on probity&#44;<lb/> and on adherence to truth.  These two traits bright in the<lb/> characters of many among our predecessors&#44; who congregated in<lb/> Newport&#44; New Orleans&#44; New York and Philadelphia&#44; have lately<lb/> grown very pale.  I care nothing for the laudatory articles&#44;<lb/> which the secular press published to our exaltation to our behalf exaltation&#44; be they<lb/> never so dictated by sincerity.  According to the writings going<lb/> the rounds of the secular press&#44; we have attained a meridian<lb/> altitude.  But they men who look with borrowed glasses&#44; not suiting<lb/> exactly their visual organs&#44; cannot see as distinctly as we our&#45;<lb/>&#45;sevles with our natural naked eyes.  Israel of America have not come<lb/> up to the point which the sage of Virginia indicated.<lb/>  The corruption into which agencies which have dragged politics has sank into a slough of corruption&#44; lowered their us down<lb/> also considerably&#59; The demagoguism of sandl&#45;lot orators witness the looseness of morals consequent on the last of &#91;&#63;&#93;.<lb/>  The demagoguism of sand&#45;lot orators has exercised its mischievous<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>influences&#59; witness the figuring of names conspicuously<lb/> Jewish among mountebanks and seditionaries.  They who We might pride ourselves<lb/> possess talents on some fit to shine as stars of the first magnitude&#44; and<lb/> reflect glory shed splendour thereby on the ancestral religion&#44; but they prefer to re&#45;<lb/>&#45;maining satellites.  Very appropriate it is that this day<lb/> on which was born the deliverer of a country to which our the<lb/> race owes descendants of the patriarchs owe infinite thanks&#44; we should scru&#45;<lb/>&#45;tinize our deportment&#44; and recognize the unwelcome fact that<lb/> we have fallen short of the desired expectations.  Had we<lb/> remembered the maxim of the Chiefs of our colleges&#44; we would<lb/> not have neglected that the tacit recommendation of the first President of our republic&#45;&#45;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;Every son of Israel has been proclaimed<lb/> at Sinai a security for the upright demeanour of his fellow<lb/> believer&#34;&#44; teach the Talmudists.  Acting upon that aphorism<lb/> we must have remained faithful to the rules of equity.<lb/>  Nothing is more precious than the good name we must pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;serve as the people of God.  Nothing is more sacred than &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> than to show by practical demonstrations that Judaism gave its votaries is a<lb/> perfect code.  Rich and poor&#44; says Moses&#44; by the ordinance<lb/> of the half a shekel&#44; rich and poor must be impressed with<lb/> the great verity that they have equality of interests to watch over.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>The coheirs of the same laws&#44; and the &#91;&#63;&#93; chosen actors in the<lb/> same mission&#44; ought to feel that to worship at the altar<lb/> of human goodness&#44; is a nobler act no less an evidence of piety than to<lb/> bend at before a consecrated shrine.  Let then the Sabbath<lb/> Shekalim&#44; and the 22d of February rise as monitors.<lb/>  Shaming us because of our shortcomings in years past&#44; let<lb/> them us urge us fast on to a future worthy of our origin<lb/> as Hebrews&#44; and of station given us in civilized society as<lb/> Americans.<lb/></p>
                <p>&#40;Here follows an address to the Bar Mitzvah predicated on<lb/> Sabbath Shekalim and the 22d of February&#41;.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
