<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF5_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_1_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_1_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_1_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_1_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_1_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Post&#45;Biblical<lb/>
                44<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Let us turn away from the present aspect of Synago&#45;<lb/>&#45;gal Judaism.  Ominous is the outlook and to me from my own stand&#45;<lb/>point and sorrowfully disappointing.  Many I have taught&#44;<lb/> many whom I fancied I would now see lead my<lb/> people aright&#44; that it might not become<lb/> entangled in the religious perplexities of this skep&#45;<lb/>&#45;tical age.  But every day brings in its train delusive<lb/> hopes.  Persons less eager than myself about the<lb/> future of the Jewish pulpit in America&#44; remain<lb/> unaffected calmly passive.  Strangely enough&#44; they consider the sight<lb/> of disciples publicly rejecting the instruction of their<lb/> preceptors and going unrebuked&#44; an evidence of broad toleration&#59; of the liberal spirit of the<lb/> time.  I cannot so interpret the rising of the<lb/> young in the ministry against their elders.  I in&#45;<lb/>&#45;cline almost to think that it such occurrences illustrates the sentence<lb/> of Micah &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;the son dishonoreth the father&#34;....<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;A man&#39;s enemies are the men of<lb/> his own house&#34;.  But let us not dwell on the<lb/> grievous events of the present.  This Sabbath I shall<lb/> ask you to lend me your attention&#44; while I call back the<lb/> past&#44; by resuming my series of short lectures on <sic>Palestenian</sic><lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>schools and Hebrew Sages of antiquity.<lb/></p>
            <p>Rabbi Meir of the second century&#44; was the last whose life&#45;work I des&#45;<lb/>&#45;cribed.  That he highly deserved a special mention&#44; al&#45;<lb/>&#45;though he did not fill the chair of President in a<lb/> college&#44; I have endeavoured to prove.  But not less<lb/> interesting than the checkered history of Meir is the character<lb/> of one of his contemporaries and fellow&#45;students.<lb/>  Simeon son of Jocha&#239; was exceedingly learned.  He had<lb/> studied under Rabbi Akiba&#44; the sage so famous in our<lb/> annals.  Even when the hoary headed Master was<lb/> immured in a dungeon by order of the Roman procon&#45;<lb/>&#45;sul to be finally put to a cruel death&#44; Simeon<lb/> craved for Akiba&#39;s teachings.  Probably the anxious pupil<lb/> obtained admittance into the prison through the inter&#45;<lb/>&#45;position of his own father&#44; who seems to have been on<lb/> friendly terms with Roman officials.  Not so his<lb/> son.  Simeon had imbibed form his martyred preceptor&#44;<lb/> sentiments of resentment against the pagan foreigners who ruled<lb/> Judea by force.  On a certain occasion Simeon was in<lb/> company with some of his Rabbinical associates.  The<lb/> conversation turned on Rome&#44; then the mistress of the world.<lb/>  Ita&#239;&#44; who belonged to the party&#44; which we would<lb/> term now a days &#34;the moderates&#34; or the peace&#45;party&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>commended the enterprising spirit of the governing power.<lb/>  He illustrated his point by a reference to stately buildings&#44;<lb/> to public bath&#45;houses&#44; to bridges newly set up.  At that&#44;<lb/> Simeon bluntly remarked&#58; &#34;yes&#44; but we Jews pay dearly for it.<lb/>  Jews We are heavily taxed&#44; while heathens gratify their low<lb/> passions.  We are made to pour out our hard&#45;earned gold for the erection<lb/> of structures&#44; which only serve to pamper the stranger<lb/> and indulge him in extravagance and licentiousness&#59;<lb/> for such is the real purpose of those pretended improve&#45;<lb/>&#45;ments.&#34;  A man within hearing&#44; reported the con&#45;<lb/>&#45;versation.  It  came to the knowledge of the Roman<lb/> authorities&#44; and Simeon would have shared the fate of<lb/> his venerated teacher&#44; had he not fled and hidden<lb/> himself in a cave with his dutiful son Eleazar.  A legend<lb/> tells that he remained in that place of concealment twelve<lb/> years&#44; feeding only on the fruit of a tree that grew near<lb/> by&#44; and drinking water from a spring <sic>providendially</sic><lb/> found in the cavern.  The bodies of both father and<lb/> son were covered with scabs and scars.  After having<lb/> endured borne privations almost beyond human endurance&#44;<lb/> Elijah&#44; who had watched over their preservation&#44; gave them signs<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>of assurance that they might issue forth in safety.<lb/>  But coming again in contact with the outside world&#44; whatever their hands touched was consumed.  A<lb/> voice cried.  &#34;Return to your hiding place and destroy not my<lb/> world creation&#34; and they went back to abide in loneliness twelve<lb/> months longer.  The son in law of Simeon noticing the<lb/> <sic>woful</sic> state to which his revered relative had been reduced through<lb/> physical suffering&#44; exclaimed&#44; &#34;Alas&#33; that I should have<lb/> lived to see thee in so terrible a condition&#33;&#34;  The sage serenely answered&#58;<lb/> &#34;Happy thou that hast seen me thus&#44; for otherwise I<lb/> would not be now what I am&#44;&#34; meaning&#44; I would not<lb/> have gained the vast knowledge which is the result<lb/> of deep meditations in solitude.  This legend<lb/> which none will take to the very letter&#44; has no doubt<lb/> its foundations upon truth.  Simeon&#39;s utterances scattered<lb/> throughout the Talmud&#44; show him a man tenacious in his<lb/> opinions&#44; rigidly austere in his practices.  One who could not<lb/> tamely <sic>yeild</sic> to circumstances and bow to foreign rule&#44; was<lb/> likely to meet with the displeasure of dominant Rome.<lb/>  To avoid the consequence of his independent nature&#44; he must<lb/> have faced severe dangers and troubles.  A less abiding trust<lb/> in Providence than he possessed would have caused the Sage to succumb&#44;<lb/> but Simeon Ben Jocha&#239; believed held that Israel must grap&#45;<lb/>&#45;ple with impediments&#44; to become worthy of the Divine selection<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>and of spiritual gifts.  Such was his maxim&#44;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> we must suffer to triumph blissfully&#59; and that belief&#45;&#45;I judge&#45;&#45;was<lb/> the Elijah that figuratively stood by him and lent him like unto the Tishbite lent his soul zeal<lb/> and courage.  Yet&#44; admirable as the Sage was in his<lb/> personal character&#44; sublime as his teachings were&#44;&#45;&#45;the<lb/> greatest of which I regard that which raises places the crown of a<lb/> good name &#91;Hebrew&#93; name above the crown of learning&#44; of<lb/> priesthood and royalty&#45;&#45;nevertheless notwithstanding all his &#91;&#63;&#93; shining traits Simeon was nevertheless want&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing in impractical&#59; he lacked an insight into the government of the world&#44;<lb/> and that&#44; I imagine&#44; was the thought conveyed by the<lb/> legend which represents him as apt given to burn burning up whatever came<lb/> in contact with his person.  The son of Jocha&#239;<lb/> is the first among the Rabbis to have entertained<lb/> the impossible idea that in order to improve their one&#39;s<lb/> minds&#44; Israelites should not engage in manual labor in trades &#38; professions.<lb/>  He argued so&#58; we are commanded to have the Law al&#45;<lb/>&#45;ways on our lips&#44; but how can we acquire the need&#45;<lb/>&#45;ful erudition if we devote our time to ploughing&#44;<lb/> harvesting&#44; reaping&#44; threshing grain&#44; winnowing<lb/> and similar occupations&#63;  Let Jews obey the precepts<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>of their Lord and their necessities will be divinely supplied.<lb/>  Are not wild animals of the forest and birds the foul of the air supported<lb/> without a trade&#63;  This utopian theory&#44; which<lb/> is in open contradiction with the history and ordinances<lb/> of the Bible&#44; stood also in antagonism against<lb/> the habits of the contemporaries and colleagues of<lb/> him who advanced it.  The Sages busied them&#45;<lb/>&#45;selves in tilling the soil&#44; in raising cotton&#44; in<lb/> cutting stones&#44; in making &#91;&#63;&#93;&#44; in baking bread<lb/> in mending locks&#44; and still they studied and taught<lb/> and disseminated religious lore far and wide.  It might have<lb/> suited one who sustained life for twelve or thirteen a long period<lb/> years with a scanty meal of fruits&#44; and was covered<lb/> with rags worn out garments&#44; to propose what anchorites<lb/> and hermits may follow&#44; and which perhaps the painful condition of the time may have suggested but a more practical view<lb/> was that of the Talmudist who said&#44; that those<lb/> who tried Simeon&#39;s plan did not succeed&#44; while<lb/> others who combined handicraft with study the cultivation of letters pros&#45;<lb/>&#45;pered.  Noteworthy is the coincidence be&#45;<lb/>&#45;tween the impossible idea of the son of Jocha&#239;<lb/> and the teaching attributed to the founder of Christ&#45;<lb/>&#45;ianity.  We read in the New Testament.  &#34;I say<lb/> unto you&#44; be not anxious for your life&#44; what ye shall<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>eat&#44; or what ye shall drink&#44; nor yet for your<lb/> body what ye shall put on...Behold the birds of<lb/> the heaven&#44; that they sow not&#44; neither do they reap&#44;<lb/> nor gather into barns&#44; and your heavenly Father feeds<lb/> them.  Are not ye of much more value than they&#63;....<lb/>  And why are ye anxious concerning raiment&#63;  Con&#45;<lb/>&#45;sider the lilies of the field how they grow&#59; they toil<lb/> not nor do they spin&#44; yet I say unto you that<lb/> even Solomon in all his glory was not arraigned like<lb/> one of these...Seek ye first His kingdom and His<lb/> righteousness and all these things will be added unto<lb/> you....Be not therefore anxious for the morrow....<lb/> Sufficient unto the day is the evil thereof.&#34;  In<lb/> contrast with this teaching is that of our book of Proverbs.  It tells us&#44;<lb/> &#34;the hand of the diligent maketh rich.&#34;  &#34;In all la&#45;<lb/>&#45;bor there is proph profit.&#34;  Seest thou a man diligent<lb/> in his work&#59; he shall stand before kings&#44; he will not<lb/> stand before obscure people.&#34;  And the an eminent Rabbis has said<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;religious learning disjoined from business may prove<lb/> useless&#44; and lead to sin.&#34;  It was by<lb/> reason of his inclination to asceticism&#44; because of his postponing all bodily requirements&#44; all<lb/> life&#45;pleasures in life to a familiarity with the Law<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>and traditions that the name of Simeon Ben<lb/> Jocha&#239; has come down to posterity under a veil<lb/> of mysticism.  He became the hero of many a<lb/> supernatural tale&#44; and to him a book which Kab&#45;<lb/>&#45;balists revere as supremely sacred&#44; is credited.  The<lb/> Zohar&#45;&#45;a comment on the Pentateuch in Aramaic<lb/> language&#44; has been supposed to have issued&#44; in the<lb/> main&#44; from the pen of the son of Jocha&#239;&#44; during the<lb/> long period of his lengthy protracted concealment.  It would carry<lb/> me too far to discuss the pros and cons of that<lb/> supposition&#44; nor would it be consonant with my<lb/> purpose&#44; which is simply to give the young an oppor&#45;<lb/>&#45;tunity to for ma slight acquaintance with our ancient<lb/> schools and their chiefs.  Besides&#44; I candidly confess<lb/> that I do not understand the Zohar.  The little I<lb/> have tried to fathom seemed to me startling and<lb/> perplexing.  To say the least&#44; incompatible with the<lb/> simple yet morally elevating religion of Moses and<lb/> the prophets.  Still&#44; we do meet in the Zohar with<lb/> sublime thoughts&#44; disclosing in the writer profound acumen&#44;<lb/> even anticipating the discoveries of modern science.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>We find the incidents narratives full of pathos and remarkably<lb/> poetical.  I cannot dismiss the subject&#44; with&#45;<lb/>out reproducing&#44; in part&#44; a highly wrought account<lb/> of the death of Simeon Ben Jocha&#239;&#44; the reputed au&#45;<lb/>&#45;thor of the Zohar&#44; an event which Kabbalists claim to<lb/> have been witnessed and handed down was absorbed in<lb/> anticipation contemplating the joys of eternity.  He had quoted<lb/> David&#44; where the Psalmist royal shepherd pictures the blessing of a<lb/> brotherly reunion&#44; gently peaceful like the dew descend&#45;<lb/>ing on Zion&#45;hills.  He had uttered the last words of the psalm&#44; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;life for ever&#34;; and silence followed&#44; I heard no more.  A vivid<lb/> light irradiated the death&#45;chamber.  I dared not<lb/> lift up my eyes from my writing.  A suddenly  we tremor<lb/> trembled seized me on hearing a voice that cried&#58; &#34;Length of days<lb/> and years of life and peace have been added to thee&#34;.<lb/>  Again another voice&#58; He had asked of Thee life&#44; and<lb/> Thou hast given it unto him.&#34;  The light flamed<lb/> upon that whole day. None drew near the master&#44; so bathed<lb/> encircled by in refulgent rays.  I remained prostrate<lb/> in sobs and lamentations.  When the light ceased abated&#44;<lb/> I ventured to look up and saw that the saint had<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>left this world. ceased to breathe.  He lay on his right side&#44;<lb/> with a smiling countenance.  His son Eleazar<lb/> arose&#44; seized grasped his hand&#44; and covered it with kisses.<lb/>  I myself would fain have licked the dust which his feet<lb/> had touched trod upon.  His associates came in and burst into<lb/> tears&#44; but none could not speak&#44; they only wept.  Three<lb/> times Eleazar bent low to the ground&#44; his lips were sealed.<lb/>  Finally he cried&#58; &#39;Father&#44; father&#44; my father&#39;....Only<lb/> Eleazar his son and his favorite pupil Aba prepared<lb/> the holy Sage for burial.  When the bier was raised<lb/> up&#44; the immortal one was seen &#91;&#63;&#93; up ascending the<lb/> heavens&#44; <sic>envelopped</sic> in a blazing fire.  A voice herald<lb/> upon the heights was heard thundered forth &#91;&#63;&#93;&#58; &#34;Come ye saints&#44; assemble<lb/> at for the celestial nuptials of Simeon.  He enters<lb/> the abode of peace&#44; let him rest on the spiritual<lb/> couch of the saints&#39;blessed beatified.&#34;  If The narrative<lb/> is borrowed from the may be the creation of a fervent imagination&#44; but it must be<lb/> conceded that it has deep feelings and genuine<lb/> poetry.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
