<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF5_15</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_15_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_15_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_15_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_15_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_15_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_15_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_15_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_15_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_15_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_15_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_15_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_15_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_15_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_15_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_15_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_15_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET.<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44;  189<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA.<lb/></p>
            
            <p>Post Biblical<lb/>
                58<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>The sketch which I began&#44; in the course of my series&#44;<lb/> relative to Gersonides&#44; the renowned French Jew of<lb/> Bagnoles&#44; who flourished in the fourteenth century&#44;<lb/> would do that author injustice&#44; if&#44; after my having<lb/> alluded to his principal work in disparaging terms&#44;<lb/> I did not show internal evidences supporting my views.<lb/>  Let me then explain what the book Milchamoth<lb/> Ha&#45;Shem really contains.  It is divided into six parts&#44; or treatises.  The first treatise<lb/> devotes its fourteen chapters to the subject of im&#45;<lb/>&#45;mortality.  I will acknowledge at once that I share<lb/> the opinion of orthodox thinkers about the wis&#45;<lb/>&#45;dom of our prophets inspired writers.  They purposely abstained<lb/> from discussing a topic beyond human comprehension.<lb/>  That they believed in a hereafter&#44; their ingenious<lb/> words and their actions prove beyond a shadow of a doubt.<lb/>  For&#44; what means the frequent phrase to be gathered<lb/> to one&#39;s fathers&#44; or to one&#39;s people after death&#59;<lb/> what the expression &#91;Hebrew&#93; met in Holy Writ&#63;&#45;&#45;<lb/> &#34;Thou wilt guide me with Thy counsel&#44; and afterward<lb/> take me on to glory&#44;&#34; what else than an open avowal of a<lb/> reunion with the departed and with the the soul of the Universe&#59; our spiritual Lord&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Again&#58; did Aaron&#44; dreading the extinction of the his<lb/> soul with the dissolution of the body&#44; lament when asked to prepare himself<lb/> to leave this earth&#44; or did Moses complain&#44; when<lb/> the sentence went forth that he would pass away<lb/> from hence&#44; after having surveyed the promised land<lb/> from the top of Pisgah&#63;  No&#58; both believed that &#91;Hebrew&#93; The Lord causeth to die &#38; maketh alive&#44; He bringeth down to the grave &#38; bringeth up again&#34;  I could multiply<lb/> proofs corroborative of the fact&#44; that our Bible<lb/> teaches immortality&#44; yet&#44; it is very true that<lb/> its lessons are mere allusions&#59; not treatises.<lb/>  Quite differently have some of our philosophers<lb/> and Sages acted.  Commencing with the famous<lb/> Saadiah&#44; who presided over the Rabbinical aca&#45;<lb/>&#45;demy at Sura in Persia during the tenth cen&#45;<lb/>&#45;tury&#44; down to the illustrious Mendelssohn of<lb/> last century&#44; Jewish scholars gave us essays and volumes were penned aiming to de&#45;<lb/>&#45;monstrate what is not palpably demonstrable to mor&#45;<lb/>tal vision&#44; but which reasoning enlightened fiath must reasonably accept.<lb/>  Gersonides was no exception to those who chose<lb/> to descant upon that abstruse subject&#44; but in<lb/> the daringness of his investigations the French Jew distanced<lb/> many.  With an astonishing erudition he dwelt<lb/> on ideas advanced by celebrated Greek and Arabian<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>philosophers&#44; whom he partly refutes&#44; setting forth<lb/> at length his own notions&#44; which we must con&#45;<lb/>&#45;sider just as objectionable&#44; as those that he opposes.<lb/>  According to him&#44; the soul is not inherently im&#45;<lb/>&#45;mortal&#44; but it can gain immortality by means<lb/> of &#34;an active intelligence&#34; working with it &#40;&#91;Hebrew&#93;&#41;.  The greater<lb/> the activity of that intelligence&#59; the higher the degree<lb/> of metaphysical knowledge gained through it&#44; the<lb/> greater and higher will be the eternal bliss hereafter.<lb/>  And in order imagining to fortify his notions by quotations&#44; Gersonides gives<lb/> a forced interpretation alike to both Scripture and Talmud.<lb/>  It was perhaps a qualm of conscience that urged the author to say at<lb/> the conclusion of his first treatise&#44; the author said<lb/> what follows&#58; &#34;Should any one hold that human everlasting<lb/> happiness will be attained otherwise than we<lb/> have stated&#44; because he prefers to take to the letter<lb/> what prophetic and legendary books have written&#44;<lb/> concerning reward and punishment after death&#44; we<lb/> are ready to admit our mental shortsightedness&#44;<lb/> although we shaped our views after in a manner which<lb/> we deem in full accord with our religion.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>But in reality those views do not agree with<lb/> Judaism&#44; either Biblical or traditional.  In none<lb/> of our sacred books&#44; we find that the soul is depend&#45;<lb/>&#45;ent on the profound learning which the active intel&#45;<lb/>&#45;lect could grasp&#44; for its existence after it has left<lb/> the body.  The practise of virtue is the pass&#45;<lb/>&#45;port to the regions of immortality.  Righteous&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness&#44; not a mastery of sciences&#44; real or imaginary&#44; positive or speculative<lb/> is insisted upon by the teachers of Israel &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;The memory of the righteous is a blessing&#44;&#34; writes<lb/> the inspired moralist&#44; and the Talmudists in<lb/> their figurative language tell us that in the world<lb/> to come the righteous&#44; crowned in glory&#44; enjoy the<lb/> contemplation of the Divinity &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;  But unjewish it is as it would be unjust&#44; if true&#44; is the theory<lb/> of Gersonides and of the medieval school&#44; because it would cut off the un&#45;<lb/>&#45;instructed young and all among mankind&#44; in&#45;<lb/>capable of deep researches&#44; whereas we read &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;I have made the souls...&#34; says saith the high and lofty<lb/> one that inhabiteth eternity&#44; whose name is Holy&#34;<lb/>  The spirit breathed into us is from God&#44; and<lb/> like Him&#44; it must be deathless&#44; in all human creatures.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>More objectionable Stranger and more startling still&#44; is&#44; in my judgment&#44;<lb/> the second treatise of Milchamoth Ha&#45;shem &#34;the<lb/> battles for the Lord&#34; by Gersonides.  Its eight chapters<lb/> try to explain in what manner the knowledge<lb/> of future events may be disclosed to man.  Our<lb/> philosopher firmly believed in dreams&#44; he even<lb/> credited the magic art&#44; while he claimed to<lb/> put firm have a strong faith in prophecy.  In all earnest&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness he thought that one could dream that a certain person went to<lb/> a certain place&#44; where he found another certain<lb/> person&#44; with whom he had a quarrel and that&#44;<lb/> having exchanged certain words&#44; which brought on<lb/> a fight&#44; both were wounded in a certain part of the<lb/> body.  Gersonides actually held that such a dream<lb/> will be realized in all its details.  And how erratic<lb/> must our philosophizer have been&#44; who fancied that <sic>negros</sic><lb/> are more apt than others to dream what will<lb/> come to pass&#33;  In the course of his second treatise<lb/> the author&#44; who believed that the stars influence<lb/> man&#39;s actions in various ways&#44; assures his readers<lb/> that it is possible for a physician to discover<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>in a dream effective remedies&#44; and even from one<lb/> who never studied medicine&#44; to find out a cure to his<lb/> own ailments.  The most wonderful instance of<lb/> foreknowledge through divination&#44; or the magic<lb/> art&#44; is that told us of a boy six or seven<lb/> years old.  The child could answer all questions<lb/> on subjects of which he was naturally ignorant<lb/> because of his unripe age&#44; and his replies proved<lb/> invariably correct.  Upon that Gerosnides philosophi&#45;<lb/>&#45;zes with his usual acuteness to carry out his<lb/> point&#44; and imagines that his far fetched supports<lb/> from our sacred writings must solve all doubts<lb/> rising in our minds.  Would that he had remem&#45;<lb/>&#45;bered and been instructed by the sentence of Eccle&#45;<lb/>&#45;siastes &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;In many dreams and vanities&#44; there are many<lb/> words&#44; but fear thou God.&#34;  It seems almost<lb/> incredible that a man with a sound understand&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing&#45;&#45;and Gersonides was confessedly a great scholar<lb/> and thinker&#45;&#45;would entertain and defend ideas<lb/> against which common sense rebels&#44; but many<lb/> went astray who in the middle ages and left common sense behind to followed Greek and Arabian preceptors.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>The six chapters of the third treatise<lb/> of Milchamoth Ha shem&#44; discuss a topic&#44;<lb/> which Maimonides with profound wisdom<lb/> avoided by confessing man&#39;s incapacity ever to<lb/> comprehend it&#59; namely&#44; how God knows all<lb/> that happens in its every particular.  The illus&#45;<lb/>&#45;trious Sage of Cordova in his Moreh Nebuchim<lb/> reasoned to show that our endeavouring to discover<lb/> that is tantamount to an attempt arrogant conception on our part&#44; that to<lb/> become ourselves we may ourselves may of our ability to become what God is.  But Gersonides&#44; who<lb/> so admired his great predecessor&#44; did not profit by<lb/> the lesson.  With a skill that reveals the extent<lb/> of his reasoning powers and his vast learning&#44; he<lb/> subjects the question to every possible and impossible<lb/> argument and arrives&#44; after intellectual efforts&#44; at<lb/> a decisive conclusion&#44; which no believing Jew would dare accept.<lb/>  Contrary to Maimonides&#44; who did not consider it<lb/> any detraction of man&#39;s mental faculties to say<lb/> that we are inexpressibly too low to reach up<lb/> to our Maker and discern how the knowledge<lb/> of human affairs comes up to Him in the minutest<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>form&#44; Gersonides lays down as his definite<lb/> decision&#44; that God has a general knowledge<lb/> of what occurs to nations and communities&#44; but<lb/> none of what befalls single individuals.  Thus<lb/> at a single blow stroke the Jewish philosopher would<lb/> cut off asunder the precious golden thread that binds each<lb/> of us to our blessed Creator.  We may suffer&#44; and but<lb/> our suffering remains hidden from Him.  Our<lb/> prayers can be of no avail.  The Lord attends<lb/> to the wants of peoples and nations&#44; not of persons.<lb/>  We&#44; who so daily so address so the Deity &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Thou hearest the prayer of every mouth&#44;&#34; reject<lb/> the soul&#45;withering theory of the French Jewish philosopher.<lb/>  He does try strive hard&#44; as usual to pull the Bible after his<lb/> own manner of thinking with the ropes which his<lb/> fancy manufactured&#44; but in doing so&#44; he twist Holy<lb/> Writ out of all shape.  We on the contrary read it just as it stands<lb/> plainly enough not to be misunderstood. leave room for a misapprehension.  All<lb/> will recall the address of Moses shortly before<lb/> his death.  In it the arch prophet adjured every Israelite to<lb/> remain faithful to the covenant of the Lord&#44; both<lb/> him that was then present and any who did not hearing the admonition and all<lb/></p> 
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>attend that that were not present at the memorable assemblage.<lb/>  But should a man&#44; or woman&#44; a family or<lb/> tribe wickedly say &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;It will be well with me though I should<lb/> walk in the <sic>stubborness</sic> of my heart&#34;&#45;&#45;imagining<lb/> that in the prosperity of the whole nation&#44; the<lb/> prosperity of the individual must necessarily<lb/> follow&#44; the Lord will not forgive such &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> But He will make him&#44; or her&#44; or them feel the<lb/> weight of Divine wrath &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> A still clearer evidence assertion of God&#39;s knowledge of<lb/> every human action is the sentence in Leviticus&#44; where<lb/> the brutal worship of Moloch&#44; to which innocent<lb/> babes were sacrificed is strongly condemned.  We read<lb/> that if the people of the land shall ignore the man&#39;s<lb/> crime of having given some of his offspring to the<lb/> Moloch&#44; God will set His face against that man<lb/> and his accomplices and destroy them.  &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#91;Hebrew&#93;  Too many<lb/> of our thinkers of the middle ages were befogged<lb/> by the lurid lights which Aristotle and his sworn<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>adherents raised high&#44; so that what our<lb/> prophets wrote could no longer be deciphered&#44;<lb/> but we simple&#45;hearted&#44; uninfluenced by a distorted<lb/> philosophy&#44; read our Bible straightly&#44; and do not have<lb/> not the temerity to ask how God knows us<lb/> and our wishes and our wants.  Our hear We feel<lb/> like Elihu of old &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;that His eyes are upon the ways of man and<lb/> <sic>and</sic> He sees all his steps&#44;&#34; and we humbly lo bow to<lb/> <sic>to</sic> the declaration of the son of Amoz in the name<lb/> of his heavenly Master &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;My thoughts are not your thoughts&#44; neither are<lb/> your ways My ways&#44; saith the Lord.  For&#44; as the<lb/> heavens are higher are higher than the earth&#44; so<lb/> are My ways higher than your ways&#44; and My<lb/> thoughts than your thoughts.&#34;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
