<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF1_4</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_4_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_4_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_4_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_4_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_4_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_4_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_4_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_4_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_4_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_4_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_4_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_4_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_4_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_4_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_4_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_4_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>29</p>
            
            <p>For a boy who completed Miny&#225;n<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>For a Bar Mitzvah<lb/></p>
            <p>My Brethren&#33;  In various Congregations a practice has been esta&#45;<lb/>blished that he who attains the age designated by our Sages<lb/> for assuming the performance of Divine precepts&#44; shall publicly<lb/> recite a portion of the book that contains them.  I have no<lb/> doubt that the custom in its original design&#44; has great signi&#45;<lb/>&#45;ficance.  It stands as a tacit avowal from the lad&#44; that the<lb/> Torah will direct his future course through life.  But how pain&#45;<lb/>&#45;ful it must be to perceive that manhood so seldom verifies the<lb/> promise made in the days of youth&#33;  I cast now a searching<lb/> glance around this hallowed structure&#44; and among those whom<lb/> I first called to the law&#44; recognize only a few familiar faces.<lb/>  Have the larger number perjured themselves&#63;  Have they all<lb/> proved false to their people and to their God&#63;  No&#44; they never<lb/> offered a pledge to observe and to obey.  At the very moment<lb/> in which they blessed the volume that reaches Israel his duty&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>their minds remained unimpressed and their hearts unmoved.<lb/>  My friends&#33;  This fact&#44; too palpable to be disguised&#44; must grieve&#44;<lb/> but can scarcely surprise us.  When we <sic>cosider</sic> what system is<lb/> generally followed in the training of your sons&#44; we cannot reasonably<lb/> anticipate a happier result.  I will briefly delineate it.<lb/></p>
            <p>Those scions of the stock of Judah&#44; whose religious culture we should<lb/> specially promote&#44; are suffered to grow wild like thorns and<lb/> briars.  We evince a desire early to initiate our sons in the accom&#45;<lb/>&#45;plishments that grace modern society&#59; but it is only when the<lb/> time draws night that they shall become &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; or religiously<lb/> responsible&#44; that we commit them to the charge of an instructor.<lb/>  For several months they are made assiduously to study.  What&#63;..<lb/> the fundamental principles of Judaism&#63;  Why&#44; parental education<lb/> ought already to have imparted them.  What&#63;...the ceremonial<lb/> observances of Judaism&#63;  Parental example ought much<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>sooner to have rendered these familiar with the same.  What<lb/> then&#63; the national language in which faithful Israelites<lb/> supplicate the throne of mercy&#63;  No&#44; they learan&#45;&#45;too often<lb/> imperfectly&#45;&#45;some words foreign to them&#44; from a volume with<lb/> whose import they have been left unacquainted.  And in<lb/> the accomplishing of that fruitless task&#44; the summary of their<lb/> religious duties and their knowledge of the Hebrew is comprised.<lb/>  Say now&#44; my Brethren.  Ought we to marvel if youths so trained&#44;<lb/> grow indifferent of their ancestral faith&#63;  The Rabbins<lb/> have declared that &#34;the Jewish world is maintained only through<lb/> the words of learning breathed out by the innocent lips of<lb/> youthful scholars&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> but can it continue long to exist&#44; when those lips are sealed to<lb/> the utterance of religious lore&#63;  Aye&#44; it is in the ignorance of our<lb/> sons and the pernicious example set by their parents&#44; that<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>we must seek the origin of the increasing evil we witness.<lb/>  It is to that cause that the estrangement of the new generation<lb/> from the olden path is principally due.<lb/></p>
            <p>I would not&#44; however&#44; my beloved hearers&#33; have detained you this<lb/> Sabbath with the exhibition of so gloomy a picture&#44; but that I<lb/> deemed the foregoing remarks a necessary preface to what I am<lb/> about to say.  The mother of the lad who has just rehearsed<lb/> in your presence a portion of the law&#44; appears solicitous for his<lb/> spiritual wellbeing.  She desires that he may become deeply<lb/> impressed with the object of his declaration&#44; and to effect it&#44;<lb/> she urgently requested that I would address him in public.<lb/>  I could not refuse a maternal wish.<lb/></p>
            <p>My young friend&#33;  If you have read understandingly the<lb/> biblical section&#44; a passage of which has been assigned to you&#44;<lb/> no lecture will be required to point out what your future<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>course through life ought to be.  That you owe your Creator<lb/> unbounded gratitude for having watched over your infancy&#44; and delivered<lb/> you from many of the ills attending it&#44; is a fact so self&#45;evident&#44;<lb/> that I deem it superfluous to advert thereto.  That you are<lb/> indebted to Him for a sound and wel&#45;<sic>developped</sic> body&#44; and for the<lb/> mental faculties wherewith you are gifted&#44; is a truth of which you<lb/> must be equally sensible.  But your obligation to the Almi&#45;<lb/>&#45;ghty is greater than that of many others among your coevals.<lb/>  While they&#44; soon after having reached your age&#44; are compelled to<lb/> ply for a livelihood&#44; you have been blessed with loving parents&#44; whose<lb/> affluence enables you to enjoy a longer ease&#59; the fostering<lb/> cares bestowed on your at home&#44; and a liberal education at the schools.<lb/>  You should therefore ask yourself this day in the language of the Psalmist<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;What shall I render unto the Lord&#44; for all<lb/> His benefits towards me&#63; and you would immediately find the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>suitable reply &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;I will pay my vows unto<lb/> the Lord in the presence of all his people&#34; Yes&#44; you must continue<lb/> to identify yourself with the race to which you belong.  No<lb/> motive should ever estrange you from them nor from the laws that<lb/> govern their communities.  It is not sufficient that you<lb/> say&#58; I revere in my heart the religion of my progenitors.  I am<lb/> My mind is imbued with the grand truths it has enunciated.<lb/>  No&#44; you must openly show it&#44; that your brethren may profit<lb/> by the example.  Judaism is not a negative but a positive religion.<lb/>  It enters in every act&#44; in every moment of our being.  From the<lb/> cradle to the grave it must guide him that is born therein.<lb/>  Your honesty will prove you a worthy member of the social family&#59;<lb/> your charity will testify to your inherent goodness&#59; your vera&#45;<lb/>&#45;city will evince your correct morals&#44; but unless you exercise withal<lb/> the external rites of your religion&#44; you cannot claim affinity with<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>the household of Jacob&#44; for&#44; by those signs are we distinguished as<lb/> the missionaries of the Unity of God.  That verity does the<lb/> section of this Sabbath inculcate&#44; and I have therefore sought to draw<lb/> your attention to it.  But the passage which you have perused&#44;<lb/> especially alludes to a precept&#44; which is&#44; if I may so term it&#44; the<lb/> axle&#45;tree&#45;on which the wheel of ceremonial observances turns.<lb/>  That important behest is evolved from the following sentence.<lb/>  &#34;Then said the Lord unto Moses&#44; behold&#44; I will rain bread from heaven<lb/> for you&#44; and the people shall go out and gather a certain rate<lb/> every day that I may prove them&#44; whether they will walk in<lb/> my law or not.  And it shall come to pass&#44; that on the sixth<lb/> day they shall prepare that which they bring in&#44; and it shall be<lb/> twice as much as they gather daily.&#34;  My dear young friend&#33;  That<lb/> injunction given by God to our ancestors&#44; is a lesson fraught with<lb/> meaning for all of us.  It unfolds the design of the outward<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>practices of Judaism&#44; which is&#44; to curb our appetites and direct<lb/> our minds to the Bestower of all good.  The Supreme<lb/> Being who opened the stores of heaven to nourish our fathers&#44; might<lb/> have as easily provided them daily with a larger portion than<lb/> they really needed.  The men who would fain barter their acquired<lb/> freedom for the surplus until they could exchange it for some<lb/> more delicate viands with the caravans that <sic>travelled</sic> through the<lb/> deserts&#59; but the W wise Donor restrained His hand to teach<lb/> them moderation.  That virtue I most strenuously<lb/> recommend to you.  Let it be the polar star of your future<lb/> career.  Exercise moderation in striving after wealth.  Gather<lb/> every day of the abundance lawfully brought within your<lb/> reach&#59; but let not the thought of the morrow interfere with<lb/> your duty to the beneficent Creator.  Six days are<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Gods gift to man&#59; labor in them&#44; to secure your existence<lb/> against penury and discomfort&#59; but the seventh day appertains<lb/> to the Lord.  The Israelite that gathers thereon&#44; robs his Benefactor<lb/> of that which He has declared His own&#59; denies Providence&#44; and<lb/> becomes recreant to his mission.  My young friend&#33;<lb/>  Through a happy coincidence it has been your prerogative to re&#45;<lb/>&#45;hearse before the Congregation of your brethren&#44; that section of the<lb/> Torah which imparts those sublime truths.  Remember it well.<lb/>  Never permit the hand of time to erase it from your memory.<lb/>  You will shortly enter the busy world.  Tossed about by new<lb/> wishes and new aspirations&#44; it will require all the powers of<lb/> the mind&#44; to preserve your moral equilibrium.  Be master<lb/> of yourself.  Learn betimes to control your tendencies.  Do not<lb/> begrudge your next&#45;door neighbour the coin he may have garnered<lb/> to your disadvantage whilst you were engaged in fulfilling the will of your God&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>whilst you were employed in musing upon his hallowed word&#44;<lb/> verily I tell you&#44; the merits he may possess&#44; have already<lb/> received their reward&#59; but your self&#45;denial for the sake of<lb/> religious principles&#44; will be requested in the book that lies<lb/> open at the foot of the throne of grace.  Your own<lb/> spirituals eyes shall see it there imprinted and sparkle<lb/> with joy.  In fine&#58; be an Israelite both in feelings<lb/> and actions.  Promise to be so in your heart before the<lb/> Lord&#44; whose sacred law you have proclaimed.  Promise it now<lb/> before this assembly of his faithful adorers&#44; and this occa&#45;<lb/>&#45;sion which has been barren of any effect with many<lb/> of your seniors&#44; will form an epoch in your life.  From it<lb/> will date your unflinching devotion to Judaism&#44; your obedience<lb/> to all its dictates&#44; and your reverence for the Sages who unfurled<lb/> its banner and upheld its sanctity.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
