<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF13_8</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_8_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_8_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_8_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_8_2v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 1 sheet<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>a skeleton of a discourse for Parashat Itr&#242;.<lb/></p>
            
            <p>We read in the Medrash.  &#34;The son of a King&#44; after having recovered from<lb/> a serious illness&#44; was requested by his teacher to attend to his schooling.<lb/>  But the royal father objected.  He said My child&#39;s looks betray his<lb/> mobility to submit to a course of study.  Let him&#91;&#63;&#93; his health be recruited&#44;<lb/> during a short period&#44; by healthy &#91;&#63;&#93; means of invigorating sustenance and he will afterward then be better qualified for<lb/> the task.  In like manner did the King of the universe act respecting<lb/> His liberated children.  They might have received the divine imparting teaching<lb/> of Sinai immediately after having been made free&#44; but many among<lb/> them emerging from a state of abject servitude were unprepared for to bend the mind<lb/> to that sublime instruction.  God said.  Let them first be refreshed with<lb/> the gushing waters of a miraculous spring&#44; fed with a heavenly bread&#44;<lb/> afterward &#38; an abundant supply of flesh&#44; then they will be more apt to imbibe and retain the lessons I contem&#45;<lb/>&#45;plate to impart&#34;  Brethren&#33;  This Rabbinical allegory intends<lb/> to signify that truth&#44; which &#91;inserted above&#58; while&#93; a mind entirely uninfluenced by wrong notions&#44;<lb/> will clearly perceive&#44; remains hidden from that mind which is affected with<lb/> perverted baneful thoughts.  From the language of Ezekiel which relates how<lb/> the anger of the Lord was very nigh kindled against Israel&#44; while still<lb/> in the land of Egypt&#44; as we read &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;I had said&#44; that I would pour out my wrath on them&#44;<lb/> exhaust my ire against them&#44; aver in the country of Mizraim&#34;  From that prophetic sentence&#44;<lb/> we obviously infer that pernicious surroundings had<lb/> lowered the standard of morality among our forefathers.  That the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>principles of which the sainted patriarchs had become the exponents&#44;<lb/> were obliterated from the memory of some of their descendants&#44; and<lb/> were supplanted by ideas which the fulsome worship of their masters<lb/> was calculated to instill.  The Almighty deemed it therefore necessary<lb/> to awaken in the breasts of such&#44; feelings of gratitude for benefits<lb/> daily obtained&#59; before he communicated His celestial will.  When de&#45;<lb/>&#45;serving that they were <sic>marvellously</sic> supplied with their wants by<lb/> their Deliverer&#44; they might be willing to listen to His instruction&#44; and<lb/> having listened they might agree to accept it and abide by its consequence.<lb/>  Thus it happened that fifty days were suffered to elapse between<lb/> the time in which the shackles of a physical bondage were broken&#44;<lb/> and that wherein the fetters of a spiritual thraldom were sundered<lb/> apart.  But when that period arrived then &#34;all the people answered together and said<lb/> &#34;all the words which the Lord hath spoken we will do&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  They all bent their heads down to assume<lb/> the yoke of the Law&#44; that yoke so light&#44; so easy to bear unto those<lb/> who receive it in love.  That &#91;Hebrew&#93; which to the pious<lb/> is not a burden&#44; but a healthful restraint.  Our fathers on the day<lb/> of Sinai regarded it as an ornament&#44; &#38; as such they donned it.  We<lb/> their progeny are invested therewith&#44; and will never part with it.<lb/>  But let us reflect a few moments upon the object which the<lb/> imposing of that yoke was designed to effect.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>The inspired son of Amioz speaking in eloquent strains of Israel&#39;s glory&#44;<lb/> gave utterance to the following sentence.  &#34;I have put my word in thy<lb/> mouth&#44; I have th covered thee in the shadow of my hand&#44; to<lb/> plant the heaven&#44; and lay the foundation of the earth&#44; and to<lb/> say unto Zion that thou art my people.&#34;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> The mission of Israel is then to plant the heaven.  To establish the king&#45;<lb/>&#45;dom of heaven amid the denziens of this nether world.  To exhibit<lb/> the close relation existing between the creature and His Creator.  Men incapa&#45;<lb/>ble of comprehending what seemed too ab far above their mental vision&#44;<lb/> towed down to objects within reach of their bemuted view narrow compass.  The lord of<lb/> nature&#44; became the slave of works of nature.  Their altars reeked<lb/> with human blood.  Crimes at which we instinctively shrink with horror<lb/> were perpetuated as an act of divine adoration.  For&#44; dread and not love<lb/> inspired man&#39;s worship.  But Israel was chosen to dethrone false<lb/> deities&#59; and point to that Being who is the sovereign Dweller of heaven.<lb/>  Israel had stood at the foot of mount Horeb&#44; of that memorable spot<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; because from thence would issue forth the instru&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment wherewith to destroy the gods of heathenism&#44; to tear down the shrines<lb/> which priestly craft had dedicated to corruption.  Israel &#34;the holy nation&#34;<lb/> was chosen to plant the heaven.  To cast sow broadest among mortals the seeds of<lb/> happiness.  To offer them the enjoyment of a heaven&#45;like repose<lb/> which is the offspring of obedience to the word of the wise Legislator.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>To show that the Law has eternity in her right hand.  In her<lb/> left contentment and peace.  This teaching was to open before<lb/> our fellow&#45;men a heaven heretofore hidden from his sight.  And the<lb/> more it will be heeded&#44; the brighter and more serene it will grow become.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
