<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF2_14</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1879" source="" attested="yes">1879</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_14_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_14_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_14_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_14_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_14_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_14_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_14_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_14_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_14_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_14_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_14_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_14_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For the 19th anniversary<lb/>
                of<lb/>
                the 7th st Synagogue<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;When God wished to let His Divine presence&#44;<lb/> rest in Israel&#44; He reckoned the people again.&#34;<lb/>  By this sentence the Rabbis meant to tell&#44; that<lb/> since the Tabernacle had been set up raised for public<lb/> worship&#44; and the tribes&#45;&#45;set in array under their<lb/> flags&#45;&#45;would make that holy edifice the central<lb/> point of their direction&#44; the Sovereign Lord counted<lb/> how many were the subjects devoted thenceforth<lb/> for to His service&#44; and deserving of His favor.  But<lb/> noteworthy is the circumstance that the census<lb/> taken in this instance of all persons fully grown<lb/> to manhood tallies exactly with the number of<lb/> those who during the previous year had richly<lb/> contributed to the erection of the Sanctuary. &#40;Exodus Chap 38.26&#41; Time<lb/> in its usual inconstancy had not created a change<lb/> for the worse among the Congregation.  Thus continued<lb/> unimpaired in its condition&#44; because of a Divine spirit<lb/> hovered round about them faithful.  What joy<lb/> must they have experienced&#44; who reported that grati&#45;<lb/>&#45;fying result to the men in power&#33;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Dear brethren.  With the deepest sense of<lb/> gratitude to God&#44; and never&#44; never with a feeling<lb/> of vainglory&#59; with reverential exultation and never<lb/> never with triumph I look back to the past of<lb/> my Congregation our Synagogue&#44; as time marks a new period stage in<lb/> its history.  It was upon this Sabbath nineteen<lb/> years ago that our meeting for devotional exercises<lb/> began in the building now endeared by many and<lb/> sacred associations.  Then&#44; I counted the Hebrews<lb/> who would make this structure their rallying point&#44;<lb/> and my heart was seized with dismay.  For just<lb/> then some had fallen back.  Then anxiously I went<lb/> fo in search of Hebrews of whose gifts might purchase<lb/> for our holy house deliverance&#44; but I returned from<lb/> my mission with a drooping spirit courage and forebodings.<lb/>  Could I dare rely on my own strength and fight diffi&#45;<lb/>&#45;culties&#63;  I knew I did not possess oratical ma&#45;<lb/>&#45;gnetism.  I was made aware of the incapacity to at&#45;<lb/>&#45;tract by the plain chanting of old melodies.  What<lb/> means had I to prevent a threatening decay&#63;  None&#58; But God<lb/> uses other instruments than those which man considers<lb/> all necessary to work salvation.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>&#34;Not by wealth&#44; and not by memorial the strength of public patronage but by<lb/> my spirit saith the Lord of hosts.&#34;  I do see that a<lb/> divine pleasure spirit has rested among us&#59; that the light of<lb/> God&#39;s countenance has dispelled the clouds which had<lb/> gathered over our Synagogue.  After nineteen years<lb/> I reckon my people again&#44; and find that they have not less&#45;<lb/>&#45;ened.  Would that like the chiefs of our fathers in the<lb/> wilderness of Sinai I could relate that I miss none<lb/> who were once numbered among the &#91;Hebrew&#93; the ablest bodies in<lb/> our ranks.  Time has not dealt as gently with us&#44; as<lb/> I would wish&#44; and as agreeably with as our needs call for.  We have<lb/> indeed lost fellow&#45;<sic>worshippers</sic> we could ill&#45;spare&#44; but<lb/> only by natural causes&#59; not one&#44; I believe&#44; by disaffection.<lb/>  The fears of some well intentioned but timid&#44; that our<lb/> disinclination to chime with the notions of the multitude would hasten<lb/> our dissolution are far from being realized.  On the<lb/> contrary&#44; I do not hesitate to state that&#44; under Providence&#44;<lb/> we owe a welcome accession simply to the circumstance<lb/> of having resisted a very severe pressure in order to act as we<lb/> deemed most conducive to the preservation of Judaism.  For&#44; to<lb/> what else should the Synagogue promote&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>I do not speak so in self&#45;lodation&#44; and to<lb/> be regarded by the populace as righteous&#44; on the<lb/> score of adhering to what bears the stamp of antiquity.<lb/>  No&#58; I have never hidden my willingness to harmonize<lb/> in any wise plan for a revision&#44; abridgment and alteration of<lb/> the liturgy and the digest of Rabinnical laws&#44; tending to<lb/> bring about uniformity&#44; and putting an end to arbitrary in&#45;<lb/>&#45;novations&#44; but to nothing will I agree which aims<lb/> at pleasing the worldly&#44; and banishing Jewish character&#45;<lb/>&#45;istics from a Jewish house of prayer.  To that I am<lb/> pledged by conviction of duty&#44; and by the most sacred<lb/> memories of home and of school.  If that is right&#45;<lb/>&#45;eousness in the sight of the thoughtful&#44; may the<lb/> God of Israel inscribe it as such in the book that<lb/> lies open before His judgment&#45;seat.  At all events&#44;<lb/> I am amply rewarded by the palpable evidence that<lb/> without relinquishing settled ideas&#44; the stability of this<lb/> house dwelling devoted to the honor of the One uncreated Lord has been maintained.  At the expiration of<lb/> nineteen years&#44; I reckon my people&#44; and rejoice be&#45;<lb/>&#45;cause greater is the number of the Congregation in the lat&#45;<lb/>&#45;ter house than that of the former.  The sentence of Haggai<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>cannot literally be applied to our case.  And<lb/> I would be destitute of feelings&#44; did I not regret<lb/> that we have not materially temporally improved.  Without<lb/> investigating all the causes producing that effect&#44;<lb/> lest shortcomings and errors be revealed&#44; I shall merely<lb/> allude to and lament the decline of prosperity&#44; which<lb/> has been felt by other institutions&#44; and which could<lb/> not help affecting injuriously the synagogue.<lb/></p>
            <p>My brethren are apt to take a material view of look at the<lb/> question from a material stand&#45;point.  The maintenance of the worship they is con&#45;<lb/>&#45;nected in their mind with the maintenance of<lb/> him that leads it&#44; and as a logical consequence the re&#45;<lb/>&#45;ligious aspect disappears from view.  Urged by their own<lb/> wants to retrenchments&#44; they fail to realize the ne&#45;<lb/>&#45;cessity of holding up the sanctuary in the only man&#45;<lb/>&#45;ner now available&#44; and by every effort on their part.<lb/>  If they do not belong to that class that have turned their backs<lb/> on the Synagogue as a childish object&#44; they will fancy it will<lb/> still continue&#44; though nothing is given by them for its sup&#45;<lb/>&#45;port.  I do not apprehend its fall&#44; but I must reprehend<lb/> the thought which might occasion it.  I feel that the Divinity<lb/> hovers over this edifice&#44; and as it survived the mutations of<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p><sic>of</sic> eighteen years&#44; and the trials of the nineteenth&#44;<lb/> it is&#44; I hope&#44; destined to live prolong life and enjoy peace.<lb/>  But life must be useful to deserve that name&#44; and<lb/> peace must not signify a passive state amidst<lb/> stirring events.  The moment the Synagogue ceases to<lb/> represent a living principle&#44; and an onward move&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment&#44; it&#44; in all reality&#44; degenerates into what<lb/> its enemies style it&#44; into a fat sinecure for sloath&#45;<lb/>&#45;ful pastors.  With us the year just ending has<lb/> been one of activity.  I don&#39;t mean it in the sense<lb/> which the Church Church gives it&#59; reporting the list<lb/> of confirmants&#44; and that of additional pew holders owners&#44; but<lb/> in the sense of having tried to hold fast to practices almost<lb/> universally neglected&#44; inviting all&#44; irrespective of ritual<lb/> differences&#44; to join us in prayer at hours not selected<lb/> by fashion but by a higher rule&#44; the ancient Jewish or&#45;<lb/>&#45;dinance&#44; Evening and morning and noon will I supplicate<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; so as to be in frequent communion<lb/> with the spirit of goodness and purity.  Nor were<lb/> our endeavours on that direction barren of success.<lb/>  I am thankful even for that little which has been partly accomplished.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>But greatly more than for the continuance of<lb/> observances&#44; calculated to keep alive the sentiment<lb/> of solidarity among the scattered members of the house<lb/> of Israel&#44; and of our common dependence of the Almighty<lb/> for breath and food and rest&#44; I rejoice over the fruit<lb/> of pulpit instruction.  I see it in that spark of<lb/> love for Hebrew learning promising to rise into a<lb/> torch which may give us hereafter a clear and<lb/> steady light.  Few&#44; unhappily too few&#44; are kindled<lb/> with it&#44; but I interpret the mere manifestation thereof<lb/> after a long period of darkness as a prognostic of a brighter future.  This year it<lb/> began to show itself visu perceptibly to our mental vision&#44; and<lb/> I am buoyed up with the hope that when the twentieth<lb/> year of our synagogue will be completed&#45;&#45;if permitted to<lb/> live&#44; I will relate that the striving of your minister for a<lb/> loftier standard of Jewish culture has been rewarded&#59;<lb/> that a revival of the days in which the study of the Bible and<lb/> its literature were considered the primary and inviolate<lb/> obligation of every Jew&#44; took place&#59; that they who wor&#45;<lb/>ship in this holy structure base their conservatism not<lb/> exclusively upon hereditary habits&#44; but upon a knowledge<lb/> derived from out history and theology.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>To that end I labor&#59; that goal I am eager to reach&#59;<lb/> that when carried still further&#44; I may hear along<lb/> the satisfaction of having contributed my mite<lb/> towards the perpetuity of an inheritance very nigh<lb/> alienated by my brethren in America&#44; of having<lb/> kept wide awake to the necessity of the hour&#44;<lb/> calling upon my charges early and late to cultivate<lb/> religious knowledge&#44; to heed the precepts&#44; to<lb/> be consistent Israelites in the practical relations of<lb/> life&#44; and to evince attachment to the Synagogue<lb/> by securing for it the presence of the Divinity&#44; which<lb/> dwells among ab hovers above the assembly of the upright in heart.<lb/>  Wealth can relieve this spot of its burden&#44; numerical<lb/> strength can add to this spot impressive dignity&#44; but<lb/> the character of its attendants can alone make spot a blessed<lb/> Temple fit for Cherubim and Seraphim to look upon.<lb/>  &#40;Here followed and appropriate prayer&#41;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
