<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF13_3</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_3_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_3_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_3_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_3_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_3_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_3_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_3_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_3_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_3_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_3_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_3_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_3_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_3_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_3_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_3_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_3_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>A <del>moral lecture</del> Discourse <del>for</del> delivered<lb/>
                on<lb/>
                Sabbath Itr&#243; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>
                by<lb/>
                Revd S. Morais<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>What is a Jew&#63;...A Jew is the noblest of God&#39;s<lb/> creatures.  So I say.  But the world mocks me&#44;<lb/> and sneers at my assertion.  Yet&#44; it is not<lb/> arrogance in me so to speak&#44; for the voice of the<lb/> Universal Creator has prompted the answer.  You<lb/> have all heard it&#44; my dear Brethren &#34;Ye shall be<lb/> unto me a kingdom of priests&#44; and a holy nation.&#34;<lb/>  &#40;Psalms XIX.6.&#41; Is this not a high title&#63;  Or does perchance<lb/> the honor granted by the Omnipotent&#44; need be<lb/> confirmed by human potentates&#63;  No&#44; let those<lb/> who will&#44; decide the thought&#44; but we are the<lb/> nobility of mankind.  We are &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#91;Hebrew&#93; a peculiar treasure<lb/> set apart by the Almighty to enrich the whole<lb/> earth therewith.  But not every one<lb/> of us is entitled to that glorious appellation.<lb/>  They only deserve it&#44; who hearken unto the voice of<lb/> God&#44; and keep his comm covenant &#40;&#91;&#63;&#93; XIX. 5&#41;&#44; for&#44; on the<lb/> <sic>fulfilment</sic> of that condition &#40;Deu XIX. 5&#41; rest the claims we<lb/> may lay to a double portion of Divine grace.<lb/>  The man who in all his daily walks exhibits an<lb/> exemplary demeanour.  The man who&#44; despite allure&#45;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>&#45;rements or difficulties&#44; rigidly adheres to the moral<lb/> and ceremonial precepts&#44; of the Mosaic legislation&#44;<lb/> is a faithful representative of the people whom<lb/> God has called &#34;holy.&#34;  He is a veritable Jew.<lb/>  He&#44; on the contrary&#44; whose moral conduct cannot<lb/> stand the severest scrutiny.  He who rejects as<lb/> valueless the eternal observances enjoined in Holy<lb/> Writ&#44; though born a Jew&#44; has voluntarily sunk<lb/> down from the eminence on which he was stationed.<lb/>  He refused to obey has evinced his determination to disobey God and his<lb/> He has broken the covenant made with God with &#91;&#63;&#93;<lb/> He therefore falsifies the name he bears.  He should not<lb/> be called a Jew.  Yes Aye&#44; my friends&#33; religion<lb/> and morality&#44; piety and social virtues&#58; these are<lb/> the characteristics of the descendants of the favored<lb/> beings&#44; who beheld the Divinity at the summit of Sinai.  And<lb/> those noble traits it behooves us to brightly evince<lb/> in every one of our actions.  For such is our<lb/> the mission imposed on us by our heavenly Father&#44;<lb/> in order that&#45;&#45;as expressed by his ancient Seer&#45;&#45;nations<lb/> may walk in our light&#44; and we bring salvation<lb/> to the uttermost ends of the earth &#40;Isaiah XLIX. 6.&#41; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Let us then clearly and fully comprehend our duty&#44; that<lb/> we may discharge it&#44; in accordance with our high posi&#45;<lb/>tion.  For&#44; if every Hebrew man acknowledges the<lb/> existence of God one Eternal Being&#44; and owns the necessity of obeying his<lb/> revealed word&#59; if every one declares like Joseph &#34;I fear<lb/> God&#34;&#44; all do not seem impressed with the true spirit<lb/> of religion.  All do not realize in what piety does<lb/> consist&#44; and how the worship due to the Deity is<lb/> best tendered.  So likewise&#44; my dear Brethren&#33; though<lb/> the laws of morality are extolled among the Congregations<lb/> of Israel&#44; not all the members thereof act as if<lb/> sensible of their supreme importance.<lb/></p>
            <p>Religion and morality are actual things.  They should<lb/> not be uttered in an equivocal and indefinite sense.<lb/>  We must once for all feel that what raises our<lb/> minds to God is religion&#59; what benefits our fellow<lb/>&#45;beings is morality.  To bear the name of<lb/> our Maker often upon our lips and bless it&#44; is not<lb/> altogether indication of piety.  No&#44; To meditate<lb/> on his attributes&#44; and endeavour to copy them in all our the<lb/> relations of life&#44; is an offering more acceptable unto the<lb/> Lord.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Rather than the chastening of our bodies with frequent<lb/> fasting&#44; He desires the cleansing of our soul.  Rather<lb/> than in ceaseless prayers and thanksgivings&#44; He<lb/> delights in deeds of justice and mercy.  Barren<lb/> is the piety&#44; which is narrowed down within the<lb/> limits of a Synagogue.  Like an arid waste are<lb/> supplications which do not influence our feelings<lb/> with kindness and beneficence.  Nor can that<lb/> Jew be pointed at as an exemplar of morality&#44;<lb/> who quibbles and <sic>wilfully</sic> prevaricates in his customary<lb/> dealings&#59; who will stoop low to gather what would<lb/> have <sic>benefitted</sic> his neighbor&#44; while the acquisition<lb/> thereof can only add to his superfluities&#59; who believes<lb/> that charity begins and ends at home&#59; who lavishes<lb/> treasures on those that look to him for support&#44; but<lb/> is niggardly to the rest of the human family.<lb/></p>
            <p>Let us undeceive ourselves.  The thermometer which<lb/> denotes the degrees of human progress&#59; is not the<lb/> inventions of arts and the discoveries of science&#44; but<lb/> the practice of social virtues.  For the same<lb/> reason&#44; we should judge of the piety of a community&#44;<lb/> not simply by their attendance to outward practices&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>but by their general demeanour.  By the honesty of<lb/> the men&#44; by the chastity of the women&#44; by the strength<lb/> of natural affections&#44; by propriety of speech&#44; by<lb/> deeds of generosity&#44; by evidences of philanthropy.  And this is<lb/> the criterion by which we&#44; O house of Jacob&#33; will be<lb/> judged by God and man.  Woe unto us if we are found<lb/> wanting&#33;.  The world will heap contumely on our<lb/> heads.  The Lord will cast us away as unworthy of his<lb/> celestial trust.  I have said it.  Morality disconnected from<lb/> religious observances is&#44; to the seed of Abraham&#44; the<lb/> forswearing of the covenant made established at Horeb&#44; but<lb/> adherence to ceremonial prescriptions&#44; disjoined from<lb/> social virtues&#44; is the forfeiture of the title with<lb/> which they have been divinely vested&#44; for so has been written<lb/> in the book I have &#91;&#63;&#93; recited this Sabbath in your presence.<lb/>  &#34;And it shall be Now&#44; therefore&#44; if you will diligently hearken unto<lb/> my voice&#44; and keep my covenant&#44; then you shall be<lb/> to me a peculiar treasure above all people&#44; though all<lb/> the &#40;inhabitants creatures of&#41; earth be mine.&#34;  &#40;compare Deut Upon the performance of these conditions&#44;<lb/> depends the countenance or cessation of that noble epithet.<lb/>  In fact if&#44; as we have been taught by the Sages&#44; to walk with<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>God means to imitate his attributes &#40;Lecture B.d. Sotah f. 14&#41; it follows that<lb/> no one can be called pious who does not contribute to<lb/> the welfare of the creatures He has made.  The<lb/> Jew whose life is not a shining pattern of integrity&#44;<lb/> departs from the way of the Lord&#44; for He corrupts his associates&#44; and thereby endangers the public weal.<lb/>  The Jew who does not employ his faculties for the benefit<lb/> of his fellow&#45;mortals&#44; is &#91;&#63;&#93; withered grass in the field<lb/> of human actions labor.  He may perform all the<lb/> ceremonial laws to the letter&#44; but he cannot justly<lb/> be styled religious.  He may flatter himself that<lb/> those practices to which he has long been accustomed&#44;<lb/> are the exclusive means whereby he can gain hap&#45;<lb/>&#45;piness&#44; but his hopes will be blighted.  He will<lb/> not obtain what he seeks for&#44; by reason of the very<lb/> nature of his professed piety.  An egotistical piety&#33; a<lb/> useless devotion&#33; standing on the narrow basis of personal<lb/> advantage.&#43;  He will not obtain what he seeks<lb/> for&#44; because when David asked himself&#44; &#40;Psalms XXIV.3.4.5&#41; &#34;Who shall<lb/> go up to ascend the mountain of the Lord&#44; &#38; who shall stand<lb/> in his holy place&#63;&#34;  The answer given was this.  &#34;He<lb/> who has clean hands and a pure heart&#44; who has<lb/> not lifted up his soul unto vanity&#44; nor sworn<lb/></p>
            
            <p>&#43;The picture character of a pious Israelite has been beautifully delineated by Mr. Judah Hallevi in his philosophical work&#44;<lb/> &#40;See Kuzari. DeMertation&#91;&#63;&#93; III. par 3.&#41;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>deceitfully&#34; He shall receive a blessing from the<lb/> Lord&#44; and righteousness from the God of his salvation.&#34;<lb/>  It is not therefore sufficient that we fulfill<lb/> a portion&#45;&#45;and that undoubtedly the easiest&#45;&#45;of our<lb/> duty.  We must discharge it all&#44; fully and zealously.<lb/>  It is not sufficient that we worship God and bless<lb/> his name outwardly&#44; we must adore him inwardly<lb/> in admiration of his paternal goodness.  The<lb/> service we render to the Creator of all men&#44; must be<lb/> the respect paid to our neighbour&#39;s property&#44; the<lb/> purity of our intentions&#44; our freedom from guile.  It<lb/> must be &#34;our departing from evil and doing good&#34;&#44; exercising our<lb/> cultivating the arts of peace&#44; and promoting them every&#45;<lb/>&#45;where.  &#40;Idem XXXIV. 14. 15.&#41;  This is our duty as social beings&#44; and especially<lb/> as Jews&#44; and the discharge thereof will prove us worthy<lb/> of the high title bestowed upon us by the Almighty.<lb/>  &#34;A Kingdom of priests and a holy nation.&#34;<lb/>
                But with that moral duty is the other&#44; which<lb/> imposes ceremonial observances&#44; inseparably connected.<lb/>  Both emanate from one fountain of celestial wisdom&#59;<lb/> both are with equal authority enjoined.<lb/>  The Jew who continues whatever appertains to the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>latter&#44; is a false representative of God&#39;s chosen<lb/> people.  He may aspire to the name of a champion<lb/> of progress&#44; men may call him enlightened&#44; but he<lb/> is only dazzled by his &#91;&#63;&#93; vain conceptions.  He deems<lb/> himself wiser than his Maker.  That which the<lb/> voice of the Sovereign Legislator&#44; declared a perpetual<lb/> statute&#44; he proclaims obsolete.  What the Father<lb/> of all mankind instituted as an everlasting sign of a<lb/> his covenant between Himself and the witnesses of his<lb/> truth&#44; he dares <sic>stigmatise</sic> as an impediment to human<lb/> advancement&#59; as if he had the happiness of the com&#45;<lb/>&#45;munity at heart&#44; more than the author of us all more than God&#45;&#45;the<lb/> spring of knowledge&#59; the sure guide to moral perfection.<lb/>   Arrogant being&#33;  He casts away breaks down the tables of the law&#44; to<lb/> substitute in their stead his crude inventions.  And can<lb/> such a one be called a Jew&#63;  A missionary of the Lord of<lb/> hosts&#63;....But mark him well&#44; my Brethren.  And you<lb/> will discover this&#58; Personal interest is the impelling<lb/> force that wages his actions.  Progress and civilization<lb/> are only the words he employs to disguise his thoughts.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>He proclaims them but to wage war against those<lb/> practices of religion that curb the desires &#91;&#63;&#93; of the flesh.<lb/>  He does not see that&#44; while fostering preserving our<lb/> body in health&#44; and our mind in vigour&#44; they foster<lb/> moderation and sobriety.  He does not consider<lb/> progress in its true sense&#44; which is a gradual develop&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment of whatsoever is good and useful&#44; but he rushes<lb/> headlong after innovations&#44; mindless of their nature&#44;<lb/> regardless of the time or circumstances&#44; or of the condition<lb/> of the individuals among whom those changes are to<lb/> take place.  Hence his innovations are the<lb/> forerunner of destruction&#59; the lightning which precedes<lb/> the thunder that strikes the tree and tears it by the root.<lb/>  Brethren&#33; Hear this&#44; and ponder thereon&#59; Civilization is not the rejection of all<lb/> ancient usages&#59; nor is every change a progress.<lb/>  I have given you this Sabbath&#44; a summary of your<lb/> duty.  It is drawn from the law which our fathers<lb/> accepted and to which they swore allegiance to at the foot of Sinai.<lb/>  Any innovation clashing with it&#44; is the offspring of<lb/> impurity Cast it away.  Be less concerned<lb/> in the outward form of devotional exercises&#44; and more<lb/> deeply interested in the spirit that calls forth a prayer.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>Watch your steps when going to the house of God&#44; and be more ready<lb/> to hear listen than to give offer a surefire of folly.  &#40;Ecclessiastes IV 17&#41;.<lb/>  Take heed never to neglect not the ordinances that restrain the appetites<lb/> and encourage abstinence moderation&#59; but exercise ever greater care in<lb/> avoiding what might injure your fellow man and<lb/> stain your reputation.  Call sacred the days&#44; which<lb/> you have been instructed to separate to the Lord&#44;<lb/> but strive to improve them by meditating thereon upon<lb/> your obligations as social beings&#44; on your destination<lb/> as mortals&#44; and on your mission as Jews.  Then<lb/> you will go forth on the days destined for labor&#44; girded<lb/> with new strength for to accomplish the task imposed upon you.  Every<lb/> one of you will then bring a stone to rear set up the edifice of<lb/> real progress&#44; which is the <sic>propogation</sic> of the ten com&#45; the knowledge of the glorious<lb/> &#45;mandments imparted to you principles enunciated at Sinai on the glorious day of Sinai for the benefit of all ultimate salvation of<lb/> the whole human race.  The spreading of a that belief that which teaches<lb/> love for God&#44; respect for our neighbour&#39;s possessions&#44; charity<lb/> for all.  When you shall illustrate these sublime principles tenets<lb/> by your daily actions&#44; then will the name of &#34;Jew&#34; be an<lb/> honor among to him that bears it&#59; It will be a glory to God<lb/> who sent us forth as the missionaries apostles of his word.  We<lb/> shall all merit the title of nobility conferred upon us.<lb/>  &#34;A kingdom of priests and a holy nation.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
