<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF31_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet></placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff31_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff31_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff31_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff31_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff31_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff31_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff31_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff31_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff31_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff31_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff31_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff31_1_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>An explanatory lecture on Job<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>In the few remarks made&#44; in the form of a prayer&#44; on<lb/> the eighth day of the last festival&#44; I alluded to Job as &#34;the<lb/> righteous gentile of old&#34;.  Persons whose good opinion I value&#44;<lb/> took exception at the phrase&#44; for the following reasons&#58;<lb/> Firstly&#58; they believed that the whole character of the<lb/> ancient patriarch just mentioned&#44; proves him an Israelite.<lb/>  Secondly&#58; they consider that my expression&#44; if correct&#44; would<lb/> weaken the authority of the Pentateuch&#59; for&#44; if high principles exalted ideas&#44;<lb/> such as those advanced by Job in the book which bears his<lb/> name&#44; can emanate from a mind unenlightened by revelation&#44;<lb/> the Divine teachings of Moses might be deemed almost<lb/> superfluous.  I will endeavour to explain away<lb/> the objections&#44; and while engaged in the task&#44; offer&#44; possibly&#44;<lb/> some of my hearers interesting useful information.  What<lb/> has induced me always to consider regard Job a stranger to our people&#44;<lb/> is the very first words of his history.  For they read thus&#58; &#34;There<lb/> was a man in the land of Uz&#44; whose name was Job&#34;.<lb/>  Now&#44; Uz&#44; was&#44; by the testimony of Holy Writ&#44; a region in the<lb/> territory of Edom.  It derived its appellation&#44; undoubtedly&#44;<lb/> from one of the descendants of Esau&#44; who&#44; as familiarly known&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>had been called Edom&#44; from Adom &#34;red&#44;&#34; the colour of<lb/> the pottage of which he ate&#44; when he parted with his birth<lb/> right in favor of Jacob.  The question then arises&#58; would<lb/> one of the Hebrews&#45;&#45;in Biblical times&#45;&#45;separate himself from his own brethren&#44; and<lb/> take up his residence among men not of his faith&#63;  Without<lb/> arguing at present&#44; as to the time exact period in which Job lived&#45;&#45;though confessedly early&#45;&#45;can it be<lb/> supposed that one who knew Canaan to be the land assigned<lb/> to him by Providence&#44; would prefer to settle in a foreign country&#44;<lb/> and there raise a family&#44; and labor to acquire wealth&#63;  Must<lb/> we not&#44; on learning form the context that Job was not<lb/> simply a sojourner in Uz&#44; butr the head of a numerous house&#45;<lb/>&#45;hold&#44; famous among the Orientals from for riches&#44; conclude<lb/> that he had sprung from a race having no share<lb/> in the inheritance of Jacob&#63;  To me&#44; the inference<lb/> seems very natural.  Again&#58; when we read the<lb/> names of the native places of the three friends who<lb/> came to condole with the patriarch in his misfortune&#44; we<lb/> must be struck by this fact&#58; they are not situated within<lb/> the borders of Israel.  Eliphaz arrived from Teman<lb/> avowedly in Edom.  Bildad from Shuah&#44; a province<lb/> belonging to an Arabian tribe&#44; issued from the offspring<lb/> of Keturah&#44; a concubine of Abraham.  Zophar from Naam&#225;h<lb/></p> 
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>a city of which we possess no definite knowledge.  Had<lb/> Job been an Israelite&#44; his visitors who figure so prominently<lb/> in the book&#44; would&#44; in all likelihood&#44; have hailed from<lb/> places confessedly of appertaining to the Hebrews.  The Talmud<lb/> does not offer any reliable information upon the subject.<lb/>  The views entertained by the Rabbins are very much at vary considerably&#44;<lb/> varisance&#59; but to me that opinion appears the most acceptable&#44;<lb/> which represents Job &#34;as a pious man of the gentiles.&#34;<lb/>  Let us now search whether the character of that patriarch<lb/> of old&#44; shows him a veritable Israelite.  I am bold enough<lb/> to assert that I cannot discover any trait peculiarly<lb/> Jewish.  Admitting that the story as narrated is not<lb/> a fiction&#44; but reality&#44; what does it describe&#63;  An individual<lb/> who stands severe trials with exemplary resignation.  Neither<lb/> the loss of property&#44; nor the sudden death of children shakes<lb/> his belief.  He acknowledges that all emanates proceeds from<lb/> the Lord a higher Power&#44; and as the right owner of our possessions&#44; He the Lord may<lb/> deprive us thereof at His pleasure&#44; &#38; we must unmurmuringly<lb/> submit.  None will deny that the exhibition of such<lb/> sentiments is a virtue&#44; but I think not so inaccessible to the human<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>mind&#44; that it should be unable to attain it without the<lb/> aid of revelation.  We know that philosophy&#44; had taught<lb/> has taught noble lessons&#44; and among the erring multitude&#44;<lb/> we find in the days of antiquity men imbued with principles<lb/> of great excellence.  Job&#39;s reply to his unrighteous wife&#44;<lb/> is indeed a model of endurance&#44; which the compilers of the<lb/> sacred canon did very wisely to placed before our vision.  Rather<lb/> than blaspheme by reason of his misfortune&#44; he exclaimed &#34;The<lb/> Lord gave&#44; and the Lord hath taken away&#58; blessed be the name<lb/> of the Lord&#34;.  Yet&#44; according to my judgment&#44; had Job been<lb/> a disciple of &#34;Abram the Hebrew&#34; he would not&#44; even when under<lb/> bodily suffering&#44; have displayed bef asperity of temper.<lb/>  He asserts his integrity throughout with unyielding persistence&#44;<lb/> and while giving utterance to soul&#45;stirring thoughts tou&#45;<lb/>&#45;ching the Omnipotence of God&#44; and the superiority of divine knowl&#45;<lb/>&#45;ledge over ignorance man&#39;s highest conceptions&#44; he pictures himself as he whom<lb/> Providence the Supreme had wronged.  Only when the Lord is made to ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;pear and reprove his presumption for pleading with His judge&#44; does Job feel humbled.  and When<lb/> owns his incapacity to fathom the dealings of of the Creator the Lord points to the wonders of creation and to His watchful providence&#44; as witnesses<lb/> with His creation of his prescience and might&#44; Job owns that Himself and the virtues he performed<lb/> are nothing&#44; and that silence becomes the best of men.  This consideration circumstance circumstance ought&#44; I conceive&#44;<lb/> to quiet the fear entertained&#44; that by regarding Job as a gentile&#44; the<lb/> imparting of Moses&#44; might be depreciated.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>No&#44; my zealous friends&#33;  What the son of Amram revelation was commissioned<lb/> specially to &#91;&#63;&#93;&#44; the most enlightened of the philosophers sages of yore had not<lb/> learnt.  They studied the handiwork of the Sovereign Maker&#44;<lb/> and perceived therein order and beauty.  They beheld in nature the<lb/> traces of powers illimitable&#44; of wisdom unsearchable&#44; but<lb/> this know not the Lord as the father of believers knew Him&#44;<lb/> and as last more clearly understood by the Chief of all prophets.  &#34;Dominion and dread are with Him.&#34; cried Bildad&#44; while chiding with Job.  The<lb/> Lord of mercy and compassion&#44; How to anger and abundant<lb/> in kindness and truth&#44; was a Being never represented to the<lb/> comprehension of philosophers.  According to the notions they entertained&#44; they<lb/> might have deemed it derogatory of the Deity to invest Him<lb/> with those attributes.  Yet&#44; it is mainly by them that He wishes<lb/> to be recognized&#44; and only by copying the same we are assured<lb/> of His favor.  The selecting of Israel as a peculiar people<lb/> was not solely for the purpose of disseminating the idea<lb/> of one God&#44; who governs the world and its inhabitants&#44; and<lb/> rewards and punishes according to the rules of justice&#44; but<lb/> likewise for the sake of implanting on earth the seeds of<lb/> goodness that they might fructify and afford existence<lb/> veritable delights.  But the sentiments which<lb/> pervades the pages of the Pentateuch are absent in the writings<lb/> of Job.  In these the greatness of God is delineated in language<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>unsurpassed for sublimity and elegance of diction&#44; but the<lb/> goodness of God towards even the sinful is silently passed over.  Whether the book<lb/> under discussion <sic>preceeded</sic> or succeeded the Sinaic volumes&#44; certain<lb/> it is that those two parts of the scriptures bear no analogy<lb/> to each other in design or in importance.  Hence&#44; I am<lb/> confirmed in the opinion that Job was not of the people of Israel.<lb/>  I would not dare to imagine that I can set at rest a question&#44;<lb/> that which all the learned have left undecided.  I will not<lb/> positively state that Job had no knowledge whatever<lb/> of the laws of the Hebrews&#44; but still when I perceive that through&#45;<lb/>&#45;out a work consisting of forty two chapters&#44; we might<lb/> look in vain for the faintest allusion to the tenets of the Torah&#44; or to the<lb/> descendants of Abraham&#44; and their wonderful deliverance from<lb/> bondage.  Even more&#58; when I perceive that the ineffable<lb/> name of the Lord&#44; the quadrilateral&#44; as specially revealed<lb/> to the son of Amram&#44; does not occur once in the long dialogue&#44;<lb/> if I may so call it&#44; between the patriarch and his three visitors&#44;<lb/> and only in the story placed before the poem&#44; is on one<lb/> occasion put in the mouth found on the lips of patient Job&#44; I am led to ascribe<lb/> the authorship of the composition to an enlightened Gentile&#44;<lb/> enlightened&#44; yet unacquainted with the instruction contained in the Pentateuch.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>I am aware that my supposition is open to a weighty objection.<lb/> For it will be reasonably asked&#44; who&#44; among non&#45;Israelites&#44;<lb/> could weild a pen so admirably in the Hebrew language&#63;<lb/> Who&#44; except one perfectly familiar with the sacred tongue&#44;<lb/> could command a style that rivals that of David and Isaiah&#63;<lb/>  Job may be merely a fictitious character.  The writer<lb/> H may have chosen Job him as the hero of his poem&#44; because noted<lb/> in two times the early ages for the virtues he practiced&#44; and possibly for the suf&#45;<lb/>&#45;ferings he endured with pious fortitude.  And the famous synod<lb/> that collected the writings which form our Bible&#44; accepted<lb/> that composition because it breathes a spirit of holiness&#44; and<lb/> at times with lessons healthful and soul&#45;exalting.<lb/>
                I am aware that my supposition is open to a weighty objection.<lb/>  For it will be reasonably asked&#44; who among non&#45;Israelites<lb/> could <sic>weild</sic> a pen so admirably in the Hebrew language&#63;<lb/>  Who&#44; except one perfectly familiar with the sacred tongue&#44;<lb/> could command a style that rivals that of David and<lb/> Isaiah&#63;  To this I reply with the Talmudists&#44;&#45;&#45;though<lb/> likely not according altogether with to their ideas&#45;&#45;&#44; &#34;Moses<lb/> wrote the book of Job&#34;.  I mean that he rendered in<lb/> unexcelled Hebrew&#44; and arranged with a skillful mastery<lb/> what may have been found in a fragmentary form among<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>the people he met&#44; while leading a pastoral life.<lb/>  He of all men could best have reproduced what has enriched<lb/> the pages of the scriptures&#44; and what perhaps became<lb/> the subject of his meditation&#44; while contemplating at a<lb/> distance the suffering of his brethren under the yoke of<lb/> the Pharaohs.  Great as the merits of the book<lb/> of Job are&#44; they rise immeasurably in my estimation at the thought<lb/> that the faithful man of God may have been instrumental<lb/> in exhibiting them to the world.  That charming style&#44; extolled<lb/> by all scholars&#44; grows irresistibly attractive at the men ima&#45;<lb/>&#45;gining that Moses may have moulded it in his heaven&#45;<lb/>inspired mind.  But whether that<lb/> volume of Holy Writ had the origin I have attributed thereto&#44;<lb/> or whether it emanated from another source&#44; we should<lb/> approach it with reverence.  The subject it treats&#44; and<lb/> the moral lessons it conveys&#44; claim our deep attention.<lb/>  In studying them we shall learn that to strive with<lb/> the Supreme is impiety.  That as we cannot fathom<lb/> the dealings of the Creator of with His creatures&#44; we<lb/> should bow down at the strokes of His hand&#44; ever trusting<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>that He who wounds&#44; will also heal up&#59; that<lb/> we ought not to place too great reliance on<lb/> our good deeds&#44; but rather on the powers of the<lb/> Most High&#44; who can convert them into means of<lb/> Salvation.  To conclude a few remarks&#44; on<lb/> a theme requiring a more lengthy discourse&#44; and a<lb/> more worthy expounder&#58; let us&#44; my Brethren&#44; study<lb/> the book which teaches the Eternity of Our Father the Maker<lb/> of heaven and earth&#44; as it is written &#34;I know that<lb/> my Redeemer liveth&#44; and He will remain the last&#44;<lb/> after the creatures of the dust shall have passed away&#34;.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
