<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF3_6</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_6_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_6_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_6_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_6_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_6_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_6_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_6_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_6_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_6_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_6_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_6_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_6_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>For Sabbath Zachor<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>My interest in the organization which has its<lb/> central seat in the French capital and can look for active sympathy branches thereof<lb/> wherever a Jewish community of any size exists&#59; my attachment to it&#45;&#45;I say to the U. S. A. has<lb/> not lessened&#44; because Philadelphia institutions among<lb/> our people principally occupy my thoughts.  I am<lb/> fully alive to the good which the Universal Israelitish<lb/> Alliance has accomplished&#44; during the thirty five years of<lb/> its existence.  Truly incalculable is the benefit<lb/> that Judaism has derived from it&#44; should we view it<lb/> simply as a champion of our rights.  For&#44; frequent have<lb/> been the instances in which its offices were appealed invoked<lb/> to in <sic>defence</sic> of the oppressed of our race.  And if its<lb/> efforts did not always meet with the success<lb/> wished for&#44; it the alliance has always entered a solemn protest against<lb/> persecution.  By its monthly&#44; semiannual and annual<lb/> reports&#44; it has kept the civilized world acquainted<lb/> with the condition of the dispersed of Judah in<lb/> inauspicious regions and created thereby a sentiment of ab&#45;<lb/>&#45;horrence for human injustice.  Its merits&#44; however&#44;<lb/> are manifold&#44; for it has encouraged literature by<lb/> <sic>subsidising</sic> valuable works on Jewish science&#59; it has<lb/> besides fostered love for agricultural and mechanical trades&#59;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>it has converted schools&#44; where our boys lads gained<lb/> only a smattering of Hebrew&#44; into schools where<lb/> the sacred language is taught methodically and<lb/> the vernacular of the various countries in which the<lb/> lot of our fellow believers has been cast&#44; is by no means<lb/> neglected set aside as profane learning.  Girls who in Asiatic<lb/> and African lands&#44; even in some parts of Europe&#44; grew<lb/> in ignorance of secular knowledge and they scarcely could<lb/> ply the needle are trained to become domestically<lb/> and socially useful.  A marked feature in the inter&#45;<lb/>&#45;national exposition at Chicago&#44; was an exhibit<lb/> of numerous specimens of articles manufactured<lb/> in the workshops and schools of the Alliance.  Israel&#45;<lb/>&#45;ites who visited the never to be forgotten cluster of<lb/> wonderful buildings in the white city&#44; must have felt<lb/> gratified in witnessing the beneficent influence which<lb/> the Alliance has exercised over the minds of distant<lb/> sons and daughters of our race.  But the expenditure<lb/> attending a varied and far reaching most comprehensive undertaking is<lb/> continually increasing&#44; and were it not that the<lb/> exhaustless generosity of the prince of philanthropists&#45;&#45;<lb/> Baron Maurice De Hirsch&#45;&#45;and the munificence of S.<lb/> H. Goldschmidt&#44; President of the Alliance yearly come<lb/> to its aid&#44; the organization might run the risk of falling into decline.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Fortunately&#44; the legacy fund to which our venerated sister in<lb/> faith&#45;&#45;the sainted Ellen Phillips&#45;&#45;liberally contributed&#44; is<lb/> not diminishing and that stands as a safeguard against<lb/> future contingencies.  But the vast flow amount flow of subscriptions<lb/> flowing from near and far has considerably ebbed away and the Alliance rightly<lb/> recognizes the cause as regards to ourselves.  It realizes that the unprece&#45;<lb/>&#45;dented influx of a Jewish population in America during the last decade&#44; notably<lb/> from Russia&#44; necessitates a proportionate increase of<lb/> local institutions of different kinds&#44; involving a large<lb/> outlay.  So true it is that by reason of that circum&#45;<lb/>&#45;stance&#44; I have suspended in late years&#44; my usual<lb/> appeal at this pleasurable season of our year in behalf of the com&#45;<lb/>&#45;prehensive organization&#44; whose utility I do deeply ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;preciate.  The demands on our brotherly consideration exertions<lb/> for the sake of men&#44; women and children who belong<lb/> to our religion&#44; exceed now by far beyond comparison the calls formerly<lb/> made upon our personal and financial endeavours.  The<lb/> Hebrew Education Society&#44; whose Jubilee will soon draw nigh&#44;<lb/> has was obliged greatly to widened the sphere of its labors operations.  The various<lb/> institutions emanating from it and connected therewith&#44;<lb/> ought to be strengthened and firmly established against any untoward event.  The Young Women&#39;s Union<lb/> with its shelter&#44; the evening schools&#44; the Hebrew Sunday<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>schools&#44; the maternity association&#44; the <sic>Wafarers</sic><lb/> Lodge&#44; the society which enables young and old infants and sick among<lb/> the needy to enjoy fresh and invigorating air at the<lb/> sea side&#59; indeed all institutions of recent date which<lb/> the kind heartedness of our coreligionists in Phila&#45;<lb/>&#45;delphia has set up multiplied in aid of foreign Israelites&#44; ought<lb/> to command the joint efforts exertions of the benevolent who<lb/> worship the One God.  Now brethren&#44; not with a reprehensibly narrow<lb/> spirit&#44; not with malice aforethought do I deprecate<lb/> a disposition to divert the thoughts minds of Philadelphia<lb/> Jews from from  legitimate channels of charity into others<lb/> which I do not consider so deem legitimate.  My heart does yearn<lb/> with compassion towards all who are poor&#44; towards all<lb/> whose children who require counsel and guidance that they may<lb/> avoid a moral downfall&#44; and&#44; personally I incline to<lb/> contribute to every object lending to ameliorate the<lb/> condition of the lowly of any sect and denomination and improve the physical and moral<lb/> status of all my fellow creatures.  But I feel that<lb/> as a member of the Jewish community and a servant<lb/> thereof&#44; I cannot recommend to extend the sphere<lb/> of our beneficence illimitably.  and I feel that much less ought<lb/> I to urge my congregation to cooperate in projects<lb/> the carrying out of which may conflict with existing<lb/> organizations.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Our public benefactions must necessarily be re&#45;<lb/>stricted&#44; in order to be effectual.  The liberalism which<lb/> tries to lock fasten the whole world in its embrace&#44; will<lb/> meet with a failure.  Rightly have the Rabbis taught<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;  You may keep a little something within<lb/> your grasp&#44; but you will never keep what exceeds<lb/> its holding capacity.  Novel among the designs<lb/> which minds&#44; teeming with schemes&#44; have concocted&#44; is is<lb/> that of supplying for a lif trifle Jews and Christians<lb/> indiscriminately with a dinner. presently I decidedly I objection which to it and<lb/> I am free to submit the reasons to my hearers.  Our gentile<lb/> neighbors&#44; so destitute situated as to require that kind of<lb/> semi&#45;assistance&#44; can obtain it without difficulty in<lb/> many localities.  They may well dispense with ours that which we proffer.<lb/>  Our own people&#44; in Philadelphia at least&#44; whether it<lb/> be from a sense of pride&#44; which I commend&#44; or because<lb/> they doubt the genuineness of the food offered&#44; do not but exceptionally&#45;&#45;I am reliably informed&#45;&#45;<lb/> in general but exceptionally avail themselves of that quasi pseudo charity.<lb/>  And surely if a spark of consistency is still burning within<lb/> their breasts&#44; they will shun a spot&#44; which&#44; on the plan<lb/> of doing good&#44; insults Judaism by the desecration of the<lb/> Sabbath&#44; asking and trafficking in open defiance of Mosaic<lb/> and traditional laws.  Even if actual cooking &#38; trafficking be avoided&#44; as some allege&#44; I brand the undertaking as a profanation and I am&#44; moreover&#44; opposed to add to the <sic>the</sic> &#91;&#63;&#93;&#45;<lb/>&#45;&#91;&#63;&#93; system so greatly in vogue in our midst.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Some irresponsible individual&#44; knowing perhaps my dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;position to help&#59; aware that my brethren who hail<lb/> from Russia trust me&#44; did not scruple to prevaricate<lb/> and state &#38; spread the report in our Jewish Weekly&#44; that I declared it permissible to do whatever<lb/> the trustees of the model soup kitchen consider right<lb/> in response to their surpassing liberalism.  It was a libel.  Not I but others sanctioned gave their approval to the outrage.  And I regret that the Philadelphia Jewish organ&#44; instead of protesting against it&#44; allowed the offense to be per<lb/>&#45;petrated and tacitly&#44; at least&#44; to commend it.  I do not<lb/> set myself up as a mentor&#44; but I cannot help say&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing that men bearing the title of Rabbi&#44; which they<lb/> please to append to their names&#44; have sanctioned sanctioned<lb/> by their conduct many irregularities which formerly<lb/> would have received a universal rebuke.  By way of example&#58; The syna&#45;<lb/>&#45;gogue has made a league with the Church&#44; so that<lb/> trinitarians are asked to address the adorers of the<lb/> Unity&#44; while Hebrew ministers delight in being report&#45; quoted<lb/> &#45;ed as having preached where the man of Nazareth<lb/> is proclaimed god.  Such are the fruits of teaching<lb/> which has planted the seeds of indifference&#44; now<lb/> visibly cropping out&#44; to the sad disappointment<lb/> of those who love the ancestral belief.  It was<lb/> in the evening of Passover&#44; when a the gathering of<lb/> Hebrew&#45;families round the domestic board ought to<lb/> be persuasively urged from the pulpit&#44; that a Rabbi<lb/></p> 
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>in the west&#44; instead of encouraging that time&#45;honored<lb/> practice&#44; invited his Congregation to come and listen<lb/> to the outcry of Christian clergymen&#44; who expa&#45;<lb/>&#45;tiated on the greatness of Jews who gave the world<lb/> statesmen&#44; philosophers&#44; artists and financiers.<lb/>  How delightful our pride&#33;<lb/>  It was more recently that a Hebrew lad&#44; anxious<lb/> to learn the holy tongue&#44; was asked by a Rabbi<lb/> to attend a Baptist Church&#44; where a class would<lb/> be formed to initiate Christians in the language of<lb/> the Bible.  How very consistent&#33;  My voice cannot<lb/> reach far&#44; but to brethren who suffer me still to<lb/> raise it here&#44; I say&#58; Your primary obligation is to<lb/> those who are the coheirs of Abraham&#39;s faith.  Their in&#45;<lb/>&#45;terest&#44; religious&#44; scholastic and social ought to secure<lb/> your active sympathy.  in preference to that of others&#44;  It must have precedence to the sympathies shown others.  Above<lb/> all&#44; you should withhold your cooperation from insti&#45;<lb/>&#45;tutions&#44; which under the guise of liberality&#44; publicly deride<lb/> your belief.  Men whose claim to the appellation of Jews<lb/> has scarcely anything to support it&#44; will call you exclusive&#44;<lb/> narrow minded&#44; proscriptive.  Heed not the charge&#44; knowing<lb/> whence it comes.  Let your demeanour palpably demonstrate them that<lb/> you are not such because you cling to your brethren and prefer<lb/> the ordinances of old to new&#45;fangled doctrines.  At this<lb/> season commemorative of God&#39;s salvation to the faithful&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>come brethren&#44; and<lb/> renew your oath of allegiance to the Torah and Mitzvot.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
