<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF5_17</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_17_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_17_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_17_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_17_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_17_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_17_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_17_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_17_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_17_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_17_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_17_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_17_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Post Biblical<lb/>
                60.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Chasda&#239; Kreskas&#44; whose name I had occasion to men&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion in connection with the principal work of Gersonides&#44;<lb/> which work he severely criticised&#44; sprung from an illustrious noble stock.<lb/>  family Among his ancestors&#44; he reckoned Abraham Hasda&#239;&#44;<lb/> to whose facile pen and poetical vein we owe the book&#44;<lb/> Ben Ha&#45;Melch Ve&#45;hannazir&#44; &#34;the king&#39;s son and his mentor&#44;&#34;<lb/>&#45;&#45;an excellent production&#44; contrasting royalty that weilds<lb/> a sceptre to strike down the powerless with the rule<lb/> of an enlightened and beneficent Prince.  I incline to<lb/> differ with some who deny to Abraham Hasda&#239; the<lb/> authorship of that book and attribute to him simply<lb/> the merit of a translation.  That as a great Arab&#45;<lb/>&#45;ist he rendered into flowing Hebrew a number of valuable<lb/> writings by Jews and by Mohammedans&#44; is true&#44; but<lb/> Ben Ha&#45;Melch Ve&#45;hannazir bears the stamp of original&#45;<lb/>&#45;ity in the holy tongue.  Like that illustrious pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;decessor of his&#44; Hasda&#239; Kreskas was born and lived<lb/> long in Barcelona.  Later in life&#44; towards the close sixth decade<lb/> of the XIVth century&#44; he was chosen Rabbi of the<lb/> Hebrew Congregations at Saragossa&#44; where his re&#45;<lb/>&#45;putation&#45;nown for learning extended far and wide.<lb/>  It is even related that the reigning Monarch advised<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>So very much was he esteemed for his learning&#44; erudition&#44; that<lb/> high officials at the court of John I&#44; asked him<lb/> to write a book on morals and science and morals&#44; which he<lb/> agreed to prepare and which he satisfactorily com&#45;<lb/>&#45;posed in the Spanish language.  It is even related<lb/> that the King himself advised with Kreskas upon<lb/> matters regarding the government&#44; but whether that<lb/> and less probable credible statements be real&#44; or ought to be relegated<lb/> to the domains of the legendary&#44; certain it is that the<lb/> Saragossa Rabbi enjoyed a vast reputation among<lb/> his brethren in faith to whom he ministered.  And here I may<lb/> say&#44; what perhaps has never occurred to me to<lb/> tell before&#59; I mean&#44; that the Rabbinate was not<lb/> then a source of revenue to its professors.  Acting<lb/> on the Talmudical principle&#44; that as we were taught<lb/> Divine laws gratuitously&#44; so must we impart them<lb/> without compensation &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; our religious<lb/> guides served the Jewish community every&#45;<lb/>&#45;where for nothing.  However&#58; In Spain and Portugal&#44;<lb/> during the middle ages&#44; the knowledge of medicine<lb/> procured the Rabbis a livelihood&#44; for&#44; they largely<lb/> exercised the art of physicians and surgeons.  The<lb/> first that history reported to have broken through deviated from a universal<lb/> rule and to have become a salaried officer in the Synagogue&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>was Simon&#44; or Simeon Duran.  He had fled from<lb/> Spain early in the XVth century and had settled in<lb/> Algier&#44; but he arrived there poor&#45;&#45;his property having<lb/> been confiscated&#45;&#45;and his abilities&#44; as a medical doctor&#44; did<lb/> not find the same scope among African Arabs as<lb/> among the Moors in the peninsula&#44; south west of peninsula of<lb/> Europe.  By reason of Upon that scene he justified the ac&#45;<lb/>&#45;ceptance of pay for a position&#44; which his splendid<lb/> attainments&#44; as a scholar&#44; highly dignified.<lb/></p>  
            <p>Kreskas found in Duran a determined antagonist&#44;<lb/> ready to defend his distant relative&#44; Gersonides.<lb/>  For&#44; as I have already stated&#44; Hasda&#239; Kreskas arose<lb/> energetically to combat the views of the author<lb/> of Milchamoth Ha&#45;shem&#44; &#34;the battles of the Lord&#34;.<lb/>  To that end&#44; he projected a colossal work that<lb/> should set aside of supersede all of Maimonides&#39; <sic>gigatic</sic> works productions.<lb/>  That ambitious emanation of his thoughts mind he intend&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed to call Ner Mitzvah  &#34;A lamp to the command&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment&#34;.  It should contain every subject explanatory<lb/> of the ordinances of the Jewish religion and the sys&#45;<lb/>&#45;tem of Jewish philosophy.  Whether his attempt<lb/> was crowned with success&#44; could not be now ascertained.<lb/>  For&#44; only one portion of the vast undertaking reached<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>posterity.  It bears the title of F Or Ha&#45;shem<lb/> &#34;the light of the Lord.&#34;  It is a very comprehensive intro&#45;<lb/>&#45;duction to the main work&#44; Ner Mitzvah.  Judging<lb/> from what Kreskas has left behind&#44; we may not<lb/> hesitate to give him credit for depth of thought&#44;<lb/> originality and a complete familiarity with the<lb/> writings of his predecessors.  But truth compels<lb/> the acknowledgment that he also occasionally<lb/> mistook a will with the wisp for a heavenly light&#44;<lb/> and fell into philosophic errors&#44; not less mislead&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing than those which he detected and censured in others.<lb/></p>
            <p>However&#44; I have made a brief reference to Hasda&#239;<lb/> Kreskas&#44; chiefly for the purpose of introducing<lb/> his famous pupil.  We may thank the teacher&#44;<lb/> who learnedly discussed the foundation and number<lb/> of Jewish dogmas&#44; for the inspiration which brought<lb/> forth such a book as that wherewith Joseph<lb/> Albo enriched Hebrew literature.  Reserving for<lb/> another time to speak of the contents of that production&#44;<lb/> I prefer to allude now to the personal services which<lb/> that son of Israel rendered to Judaism&#44; and show why<lb/> I love him and wish that all may cherish his<lb/> memory.  Persons who are apt to look<lb/> upon Spain of medieval ages as the paradise of Jews&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>ought to pause and notice the not infrequent out&#45;<lb/>&#45;breaks against our people&#44; both in the kingdom of<lb/> Castile Lordoun&#91;&#63;&#93; and that of Leon.  Religious prejudices foment&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed by the Mosque and by the Church&#44; forced some<lb/> of our the worthiest ones among us&#44; to take up the staff of pilgrim&#45;<lb/>&#45;age and wander abroad.  But at times&#45;&#45;I record<lb/> it with unutterable shame&#45;&#45;at times&#44; rebels from<lb/> our midst own fold&#44; exposed us to imminent dan&#45;<lb/>&#45;gers.  It was so in the XV century.  An aposta&#45;<lb/>&#45;te Joshua La Rocca&#44; who at his pubtism baptism assumed<lb/> the name of Jerome de Santa F&#233; gained the favor<lb/> of the rival Pope Benedict XIII residing then living at Avignon&#44; and induced the Roman Pontiff<lb/> to request King Ferdinand of Aragon to issue<lb/> a royal mandate.  Jews who enjoyed the highest<lb/> reputation for their erudition&#44; should be sent for&#44;<lb/> and at Tortosa they should hold a public con&#45;<lb/>&#45;troversy with him&#44; who had given away the Unity<lb/> to embrace the trinity.  Joseph Albo of Monreal<lb/> was known as a ripe scholar&#59; and he was therefore selected among<lb/> the number pointed out by the recreant Joshua La Rocca&#44;<lb/> as those whom he hoped to bring to public shame and<lb/> confusion and disgrace.  The challenge was accepted&#44; but not with<lb/> a light heart.  The controversialists may have remembered the<lb/> sorrows which a similar occasion had heaped upon Nachmanides.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>In the present instance&#44; the Pope presided and opened<lb/> the session nearly in the following language&#58; &#34;Jews&#44; ye that<lb/> in olden times were God&#39;s chosen people&#44; but who are<lb/> now rejected because of your sin&#44; be not backwards<lb/> in this disputation.  No harm shall befall you.  Speak<lb/> out your minds with courage.  Jerome purposes to<lb/> prove form your Talmud that the Messiah did<lb/> come.  You can judge best whether he is wide awake&#44;<lb/> or whether he is dreaming.  Think over the matter<lb/> and return to&#45;morrow.&#34;  So saying&#44; he ordered that<lb/> the messengers be properly housed and provided with<lb/> such food as they could conscientiously partake of.<lb/>  The next day&#44; Joseph Albo and his colleagues were<lb/> taken aback on seeing the hall filled with Cardinals&#44;<lb/> Archbishops and Bishops clothed in their official<lb/> robes&#44; and laymen of high standing among Roman<lb/> Catholics&#44; altogether counting nearly almost a thousand per&#45;<lb/>&#45;sons.  Nevertheless&#44; they to the defenders of our laws and<lb/> traditions braced up&#44; and jointly pronounced the Rab&#45;<lb/>&#45;binical benediction &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Blessed be He who has bestowed some of His glory<lb/> upon mortal beings.&#34;  The Pope began&#58; &#34;Jewish Rab&#45;<lb/>&#45;bins know for sure that I did not send for you<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>to enquire ascertain which of the two religions be true.  I<lb/> am convinced that mine is the correct belief&#44; and that<lb/> yours was so once&#44; but that it is no longer so.  But Now&#44;<lb/> Jerome de Santa F&#233;&#44; wants to quote your superiors&#44;<lb/> the Talmudists&#44; to prove&#44; from their own statement&#44;<lb/> that the Messiah has come.  Confine your remarks<lb/> therefore to that point.  Let Jerome open the con&#45;<lb/>troversy.&#34;  Unique was that polemics&#44; unique<lb/> because of the length of time it lasted&#59; unique by rea&#45;<lb/>&#45;sons of the number of distinguished scholars engaged<lb/> in it&#44; and unique through the artful strokes on one<lb/> side&#44; the clever parrying of the blows on the other.<lb/>  Repeatedly Joseph Albo stood the brunt of the<lb/> battle&#44; resolved to floor and crush the miscreant<lb/> Joshua La Rocca.  Gladly would that champion<lb/> of ours and his faithful eminent associates have with&#45;<lb/>&#45;drawn from a distasteful dispute&#44; but they were<lb/> forcibly dragged into it and continued in it to the<lb/> last very end.  The event has been recorded by Solomon<lb/> Ben Verga in his Shebet Yehudah.  From that<lb/> interesting Hebrew history of our people&#39;s sufferings&#44; we<lb/> learn that sixty eight meetings were held&#44; during<lb/> twenty twenty one months.  The miscreant Jerome de Santa<lb/> F&#233; imagined that he could intimidate our faithful<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>representatives by such sentences as partly quoted<lb/> from our prophets&#58; &#34;Come ye now and let us reason<lb/> together&#34;....but if you refuse and rebel&#44; ye<lb/> shall be devoured by the sword.&#34;  The Pope also&#44;<lb/> notwithstanding his promise of calm impartiality&#44;<lb/> grew angry when baffled in the hope to entrap<lb/> our men in the net spread out to catch their souls.<lb/>  But Joseph Albo&#44; having borne a great mental<lb/> strain in rebutting the subtle arguments of the<lb/> apostate&#44; when home again&#44; feared the consequences<lb/> of the long protracted controversy.  He left Monreal<lb/> and all his its associations and settled in Soria.  There<lb/> he sought rest&#44; and there he produced the work<lb/> which gave him immortality and us valuable instruction.<lb/>  Of that book I shall speak in my next lecture<lb/> of the series.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
