<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF8_7</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1888-01" source="" attested="yes">1888</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_7_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_7_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_7_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_7_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_7_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_7_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_7_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_7_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_7_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_7_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_7_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_7_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>133</p>
            
            <p>About the attempt to make<lb/>
                the government recognize Sunday as Sabbath<lb/>
                88<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  Spasmodic efforts are made&#44; every now and<lb/> then&#44; to chain the State to the clogging wheels of the<lb/> church.  All whom a study of history has taught what<lb/> a drawback will inevitably the success of that perilous untoward scheme must will inevitably be<lb/> be&#44; should try&#44; with might and main&#44; to prevent so<lb/> great a check on human liberty.  But the citizens&#44; whose interests<lb/> would suffer most by the consummation of the attempt&#44; are<lb/> the Jews of America&#44; and they ought&#44; in as quiet and digni&#45;<lb/>&#45;fied manner&#44; as compatible with the object&#44; exercise their influence to defeat it.<lb/>  Fortunately they are not alone in their just antagonism&#59;<lb/> others will determinedly protest.  Now&#44; none<lb/> will deny the wisdom of suspending temporal pursuits<lb/> one day in the week&#44; in order to relieve the tension of<lb/> body and mind.  Least of all&#44; Israelites could oppose<lb/> it on moral ground&#44; for if the Decalogue at Sinai gives<lb/> as a reason for hallowing the Sabbath the necessity<lb/> of commemorating the completion of God&#39;s creation&#44; Moses<lb/> in his repetition of the ten commandments in Deuteronomy&#44;<lb/> clearly alleges the other cogent reason&#44; which was only indirect&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly expressed in Exodus&#44; namely&#44; that laborers as well as their<lb/> employers might enjoy rest. &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>True&#44; to apply to Sunday the name of Sabbath&#44; is<lb/> a to distortion of facts&#44; or to perpetuate a pious fraud&#44; if the phrase<lb/> be less objectionable&#44; and one can scarcely suppress<lb/> a smile on seeing ministers of the gospels floundering<lb/> floundering on from blunder to blunder&#44; finally to<lb/> stand at some huge absurdity.  Specimens of such tactics<lb/> were received this month in the city of Washington at<lb/> reception room of the Senate in the session before &#34;the committee on education and<lb/> labor.&#34;  It was there and then tat a Reverend<lb/> Doctor Byron Sunderland spoke on his pet project<lb/> to christianize the constitution of the United States.<lb/>  Like some a number of his clerical colleagues he had urged the setting<lb/> of the seal of national authority on the observance of the<lb/> first day of the week.  But he capped the climax<lb/> of illogical talk&#44; when undaunted by the testimony of 35 centuries frowning down upon him&#44; he concluded with a mirabile<lb/> dictum.  &#34;On Sunday Nothing&#34;  Our Sunday is the seventh<lb/> day of the Decalogue.&#34;  A new Alexander he cut<lb/> the Gordian Knot.  Till the Reverend Doctor Byron Sunder&#45;<lb/>&#45;land arose&#44; none could master the Hebrew passage<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;But the seventh day is<lb/> the Sabbath of the Lord thy God.&#34;  How grateful pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;phets and Sages must be to the Pastor of the Presbyterian<lb/> Church&#33;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Still&#44; notwithstanding&#44; the persistent inconsistency<lb/> of the Nazarenes&#44; are affor humanitarians must be glad&#44;<lb/> when sentient beings have are afforded a time to think&#44; that&#44; as<lb/> Moses puts it&#44; &#34;Man lives not on bread alone&#44; but<lb/> on whatsoever proceeds from the will of the Lord&#59;&#34; that<lb/> we live by the satisfaction of other and higher needs than<lb/> the mere seeking of material substance.  Would that<lb/> the awakening of such thoughts were in all instances the result of one day&#39;s<lb/> general relaxation&#44; would that while physical strength<lb/> recuperates&#44; spiritual powers widen also.  We should<lb/> not have peremptorily to coerce people into obedience to<lb/> the law of sobriety&#45;&#45;a law broken unfortunately even on<lb/> Sundays by subterfuge&#44; and never perhaps more openly<lb/> and shamelessly than during these church&#45;festivities&#44; when<lb/> intemperance runs riot&#44; and at its heel are heart&#45;stabbing and profanity abroad&#44;<lb/> wife&#45;beating and misery at home.  Who would not<lb/> rejoice&#44; if what our neighbors please to call &#34;the lord&#39;s day&#44;&#34;<lb/> partook everywhere in Christendom of the sanctity of the Eternal Lord&#39;s chosen day&#44;<lb/> glowingly described by Isaiah&#44; as a restorative to the body<lb/> and a delight to the soul&#59; the day which was to be typical<lb/> of a covenant between heaven and earth &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Yet&#44; under the most favorable circumstances&#44; Israelites<lb/> would deplore a compulsory observance of that day by<lb/> the arms of civil authorities.  Encroachments<lb/> upon the right of conscience have already been gradually<lb/> increasing in numerous departments.  Thus&#44; by way of illus&#45;<lb/>&#45;tration&#44; on the plea that the majority rule&#44; our children<lb/> are forced to labor under certain disabilities.  They must keep<lb/> non&#45;biblical holidays&#44; and often sustain losses in their<lb/> standing at schools and colleges&#44; for holding sacred Scriptur&#45;<lb/>&#45;ral festivals.  They must hear readings that do violence<lb/> to their feelings&#44; and prayers to which they cannot con&#45;<lb/>&#45;scientiously respond.  Only a few days ago&#44; I was<lb/> asked by some youths&#44; whether they could&#44; within the<lb/> line of Jewish consistency&#44; sing join in hymns in which the<lb/> birth of the founder of Christianity is declared miraculous divine&#44;<lb/> and his advent&#44; as salvation from perdition.  To do<lb/> so was distasteful to my young fellow&#45;believers&#44; but<lb/> then the idea of being pointed at by teachers and school&#45;<lb/>&#45;mates as separatists&#44; was also disagreeable.  I could but<lb/> advise to bear with the unpleasantness of being considered<lb/> exclusive&#44; rather than prove false contradict&#44; even by a<lb/> word semblance of singing&#44; the teaching of Hosea &#34;&#91;Hebrew&#93;&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>&#34;Thou shalt know no god but Me&#44; for there is<lb/> no Saviour besides Me.&#34;  But the petty<lb/> annoyances to which our children are subjected&#44; and<lb/> others of greater weight ordinarily felt by us&#44; would<lb/> be designedly made thorns to in our eyes&#44; and stings<lb/> in our sides&#44; as soon as the federal government<lb/> should set the signet of approval on the demand<lb/> of the sabbatarians.  Christianity&#44; virtually<lb/> become the dominant religion&#44; would look <sic>askanse</sic><lb/> on all other creeds.  Held at sufferance&#44; they must<lb/> then submit to inquisitorial searchings&#44; and who can<lb/> tell&#44; once that Congress legislates on matters of faith&#44;<lb/> what persecutions may attend disputers&#63;  For&#44; the rules<lb/> contemplated are stringently severe.  Let me quote a few&#58;<lb/> &#34;No person or corporation shall perform any secular labor&#44; nor<lb/> shall any person engage in any play&#44; game&#44; amuse&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment or recreation on that day&#44; in any territory&#44; district&#44;<lb/> vessel or place subject to the executive jurisdiction of<lb/> the United States......and any person who shall break<lb/> the law will be subject to a fine of not less than ten<lb/> dollars&#44; nor more than a thousand...All assemblies&#44; except<lb/> for the due and orderly observance of religious worship are<lb/> forbidden&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>And who shall define the species of &#34;secular labor&#34; in all its branchings<lb/> the character of &#34;a recreation&#44;&#34; the nature of &#34;an assembly&#34;&#63;<lb/>  Why&#44; a theocracy set up where liberty had stood<lb/> watching on the ramparts.  The Palladium of human<lb/> rights converted into a soul&#45;tormentor&#33;  They who<lb/> condemn have a fling at Pharisaism&#44; should ponder on the law of which<lb/> the Reverend Doctor Byron Sunderland is an exponent.<lb/>  Not Pharisaism&#44; but early Caratism itself&#44; so inconsiderately slavish to the<lb/> letter&#44; that would rather let its followers shiver than have a let a fire be kindled<lb/> by some Israelites on the Sabbath&#45;day&#44; might not suffer in comparison<lb/> with this American Christanism which claims &#34;to promote the ob&#45;<lb/>&#45;servance of the first day of the week as a day of religious<lb/> worship.&#34;  But it would not promote it&#44; for religious<lb/> sentiment is the growth of persuasive argument and of a manifestation of disin&#45;<lb/>&#45;terested love for man&#59; never the offspring of coercion.  It<lb/> might breed hypocrisy&#44; which fears the penalty im&#45;<lb/>&#45;osed&#44; but not sterling piety and cease then from importuning at the portals of human legislation&#44; ye unwise leaders.  In the language<lb/> of the son of Amoz&#44; I say to the memorialists &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;Behold&#33; ye are as nothing&#44; and<lb/> your work is naught.&#34;  The Constitution&#44; whose centennial<lb/> celebration&#44; only last year&#44; created three monumental days<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>in Philadelphia&#45;&#45;the birth&#45;place of Freedom&#45;&#45;is<lb/> not to be tampered with by fanaticism&#44; while a<lb/> day of human&#39;s wisdom&#44; illumined by the flambeau of history&#44;<lb/> can peer into the future.  The constitution will<lb/> cover beneath her ample folds all that seek protection<lb/> from the abuse of power&#44; but never will she<lb/> dictate tyrannical terms to those whom she has pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;mised shelter.  Spasmodic efforts will may be made<lb/> every now and then&#44; to chain the state to the<lb/> clogging wheels of the Church&#44; but to no purpose&#44;<lb/> if we the coheirs of glorious invaluable communities keep on the alert&#59; for&#44; eternal vigilance is the price<lb/> of liberty.  To my brethren in faith&#44; I<lb/> say&#58; your dearest interests lie in the continued and<lb/> ever more remoter separation between the civil powers<lb/> and the ecclesiastical.  Too terribly you have suffer&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed by t reason of their illicit alliance.  Fraternize<lb/> therefore with the broad&#45;minded&#44; who will guard against<lb/> a usurpation of any of the franchises guaranteed by<lb/> by the American Magna Charter&#44; but take good<lb/> heed that your liberality does not transcend the limits<lb/> of honor and propriety.  Your religion bids you<lb/> hold the seventh day sacred&#44; but when that God&#45;appointed day<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>and the following also find you defiantly deliberately engaged<lb/> in worldly pursuits&#44; you offend your fellow &#91;&#63;&#93;<lb/> citizens&#44; and compromise the character of all the<lb/> Jewish population.  Beware of scandal<lb/> and of the sin of greed which creates it. is a soul&#45;devouring monster.  Thank&#45;<lb/>ful to Providence&#44; that has cast your lines in hap&#45;<lb/>&#45;py regions&#44; prove your gratitude by a demeanour<lb/> above censure&#44; full of dignity and nobly consistent.<lb/>  You will thus benefit the cause of freedom at large&#44;<lb/> promote the welfare of your fell coreligionists in<lb/> particular&#44; and sanctify Him&#44; who inspired His<lb/> servant to write &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;As the girdle cleaveth to the loins of a man&#44; so have<lb/> I made the of all the the whole house of Israel and the whole house<lb/> of Judah to cleave unto me&#44; saith the Lord&#44; that they<lb/> might be unto me for a people and for a name&#44;<lb/> and for a praise and for a glory.&#34;  And so may<lb/> it be.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
