<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF3_4</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_4_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_4_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_4_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_4_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_4_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_4_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_4_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_4_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_4_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_4_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_4_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_4_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_4_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_4_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_4_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_4_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For the Sabbath before Purim<lb/>
                On the Alliance<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  Were it in my power to perform a<lb/> wonder&#44; you should be carried would this morning from personally contemplate<lb/> hence to stirring scenes in far off lands.  The scenes objects exhibited to<lb/> your vision&#44; would have such touching powerful touching eloquence&#59;<lb/> they would appeal so irresistibly to your feelings&#44; that the spirit stirring within<lb/> you would manifest itself in acts of broad<lb/> generosity.  The sense of speech in man&#44; however<lb/> appropriately exercised&#44; is always at best a very weak as a<lb/> substitute for the sense of sight.  It is the latter which<lb/> influences human nature profoundly deeply intensely.  To see<lb/> misery is to melt with compassion and instinctively<lb/> stretch forth a helping hand.  To have the suffering<lb/> of quivering flesh&#44; before set under directly under our eyes&#44; is to be stirred aroused<lb/> up to the earnest wish of relieving it.  But praise<lb/> be to the Lord of Israel&#33;  This morning I have<lb/> not any immediate cause for asking that you should<lb/> look at on and pity the misfortune of your coreligionists.  Your The<lb/> journey which I fain would desire you directed to take is not to grieve sadden you by a contemplation of the fruits of calamities&#44; but to gladden your hearts by a survey would be to a contemplation of a promising<lb/> harvest of happiness.  And Since it cannot<lb/> be set forth bed out set forth in your presence&#44; let me try to<lb/> describe it sketch it out faintly delineate it.  Imagine you are at<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Smyrna&#44; in Asiatic Turkey.<lb/>  You notice hundreds of your brethren are hurry&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing towards the same spot.  Is it the Synago&#45;<lb/>gue to which they those descendants of Abraham bend their steps&#63;  Why are those men dressed &#38; women attired in a holiday attire dress&#63;  Are Jews<lb/> celebrating one of their solemn festivals&#63;  No&#58;<lb/> it is a working day yet many are hastening to<lb/> a place of meeting.  It is a holy place&#44; their  The place It is not a synagogue yet still it is most holy.<lb/>  Your fellow&#45;believers at Smyrna are going to their children&#39;s school house.  It formerly was<lb/> a Cheder&#44; where a smattering of Hebrew&#44; unsystem&#45;<lb/>&#45;atically taught&#44; constituted the whole sum total of know&#45;<lb/>&#45;ledge acquired by of male pupils.  They spent there<lb/> years under the old discipline of the unspair&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing rod.  Now it has been undergone a total transformation.  into a It has become<lb/> a seminary of religious and secular learning for Jewish girls as well<lb/> as Jewish boys.  The day has arrived in<lb/> which their proficiency must vindicate the<lb/> wisdom of the new method of instruction&#44; and<lb/> commend it to the approval of the right&#45;think&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing in among the people of Israel in every land.  Those children<lb/> of our faith answer the questions which the<lb/> examiners put&#44; not as heretofore in an unintel&#45;<lb/>&#45;ligible mixture of a language that ignorance in&#45;<lb/>vented and clannishness sanctified&#44; but in Turkish<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>or in French with which they have become<lb/> familiar.  Strangers to our creed have been<lb/> invited to see and be convinced that Jews are not exclusive by<lb/> nature or religion&#59; that they eagerly seize the earliest<lb/> opportunities to show their fondness for for gratifying a thirst after a knowledge<lb/> which may enlarge their views and better their<lb/> condition.  The archbishop of the Greek Church<lb/> has attended the public examination of the school<lb/> instituted by the &#34;Universal Israelitish Alliance&#44;&#34;<lb/> and after listening attentively for two hours leaves<lb/> with a favorable impression of touching regarding our people&#39;s intellectuality and<lb/> with expressions of admiration for the society&#44; whose<lb/> beneficent genial influence is almost world&#45;wide.<lb/></p>
            <p>Fancy now that we quit Smyrna and travel to<lb/> Brody&#45;&#45;the Jerusalem of Galicia as it has not been inaptly<lb/> been called.  IT is summer&#44; and the schools have<lb/> just closed for the vacation.  One Hundred and eighty four youths<lb/> born in our believe have undergone stood a searching<lb/> examination in various branches of literature&#44; and&#44;<lb/> as usual everywhere&#44; have acquitted themselves nobly creditably<lb/> and won &#43; high prizes.  They celebrate the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>occasion by what we in America call<lb/> a picnic.  and The excursionists proceed to the spot of their diver&#45;<lb/>&#45;sion in military order under two banners.  One<lb/> bears this inscription&#58; &#34;The Jewish School boys<lb/> and girls of Brody&#34;.  In an Upon the other three mottos<lb/> are impressed.  In the Polish language we read&#58;<lb/> &#34;Thou is born for labor&#44; but a good temper makes<lb/> up for the hardship endured&#34;.  In Hebrew it is we read&#58;<lb/> &#34;There is time for all things&#59; a time for studying&#44;<lb/> and a time for dancing.&#34; &#38; In German we read&#58; &#34;Both study<lb/> and pleasure have excellent merits&#34;.  It is the<lb/> principles of Judaism&#45;&#45;of our religion which is eminently social&#44; and promotive<lb/> of the enjoyment of life&#44; which those young stu&#45;<lb/>&#45;dents who have tasted of the tree of knowledge now carry out.<lb/>  The procession halts in front of a dwelling and<lb/> shouts out words of greetings to the occupant.  It He that lives in is the<lb/> representative of the greatest advocate staunchest and most munificent friend of the &#34;Uni&#45;<lb/>&#45;versal Israelitish Alliance&#34;. which they salute<lb/> Baron Maurice de Hirsch has given it mil&#45;<lb/>&#45;lions to assist congregations in times of famine and pestilence&#44;<lb/> of fires and wars.  He has given them because he <sic>he</sic> has faith in<lb/> its far reaching endeavours workings.  He has given<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>it the Alliance millions principally to aid it in the herculean task<lb/> of exterminating ignorance and its ally superstition<lb/> and setting up aloft learning and its adjunct a liberal<lb/> spirit.  The Baron had commissioned his al&#45;<lb/>&#45;moner Chevalier Veneziani to largely endow in his name<lb/> the school of Brody&#44; where his young coreligionists<lb/> receive obtain the means to so rise socially by mental culture.<lb/>  On that gala day&#44; when the director of the school<lb/> came forward and in a feeling address thanked the<lb/> Alliance and its illustrious champion&#44; Veneziani<lb/> moved to tears at the sight he bel beheld&#44; responded so&#58;<lb/> &#34;May all these youths live to be an honor to the<lb/> olden religion to which whereunto they belong&#34;.  And an out&#45;<lb/>&#45;burst of national feeling repeated&#58; Amen&#44; so may<lb/> it be.<lb/></p>
            <p>If we now could betake ourselves to Palestine&#44; we from the &#91;&#63;&#93; self styled Galilean Jerusalem we should retrace our steps and cross the Mediterranean<lb/> sea to visit the land where the real Jerusalem is found&#44; we<lb/> might tarry a while at the school of Jaffa.  There stands yet the agricultural<lb/> school which was Charles Netter&#39;s dearest thought&#44;<lb/> and which received his body when death suddenly<lb/> forced him away from his labor of love.  Here<lb/> There we might inspire ourselves with the hope<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>of a revival of patriarchal pursuits&#44;<lb/> healthy&#44; profitable&#44; preparatory to the ful&#45;<lb/>filment of the promised blessings when the soil ground<lb/> hallowed by prophets the &#91;&#63;&#93; of labors of the ancient patriarchs fathers of our nation&#44; shall smile again with verdure&#44;<lb/> and the original inhabitants shall find their flock<lb/> in Bashan and Gilead as in the days of yore.<lb/>  From Jaffa on which upon which school the Alliance has bestowed<lb/> vast amounts&#44; we might proceed to Jerusalem the capital of Palestine&#44;<lb/> and examine whether the sanguine expectations<lb/> of new colorists&#44; who formed the plan of tilling<lb/> the ground soil&#44; receive hold out any prospect of realization.<lb/>  or whether the The Alliance has expressed its misgivings of the Alliance upon that score.  It has thought that<lb/> almost insufferable difficulties will blast for the all<lb/> present all endeavours in that direction. are well<lb/> founded We may abstain yet awhile to form an opinion&#44; but we may feel assured that For the organization <sic>centred</sic> at Paris&#44;<lb/> watches with paternal solicitude the incomings<lb/> and outgoings of all who venture to settle in<lb/> the land once our own&#44; but now misruled and<lb/> ruined by impotent and rapacious sheiks&#44; or<lb/> Turks governors.  The Alliance encourages<lb/> industry&#44; notably that aiming to which has for its aim and scope farming and<lb/> husbandry.  Only three weeks ago in its anxiety<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>to foster that art&#44; it submitted a pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;position to all the members of the central committee to sell each pupil of the Jaffa school<lb/> who have completed their apprenticeship some<lb/> acres of land&#44; advancing the money&#44; and receiving<lb/> it back by <sic>instalments</sic> in the course of five<lb/> years.  But The Alliance&#44; however discountenances at&#45;<lb/>tempts which a mistaken piety might turn<lb/> into disasters.  And such may prove the large<lb/> influx of Roumanians peasants in the holy city.<lb/>  No Time will show whose judgment was correct upon this sb subject&#44; but the experience of a quarter of a century during<lb/> which stirring events affecting Israel in the coun&#45;<lb/>&#45;tries of their dispersion have come to pass&#44; vindi<lb/>cated the claims wisdom of an association almost ubiquitous in its<lb/> character&#44; and its claims to universal support.  The names of the men of our faith<lb/> appended to the original call shortly after the<lb/> atrocious stealing of a Jewish boy at Bologna by<lb/> papists&#44; sanctioned by Pius IX&#59; the names of<lb/> Mun Solomon Munk and Adolph Cremieux&#59; the<lb/> names of illustrious dead who welcomed its rising<lb/> and progress as a bulwark of Jewish <sic>defence</sic>;<lb/> the names of S. H. Goldschmidt&#44; its President<lb/> who has bestows on gives it valuable time and abundant<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>gold&#44; of the learned and untiring Isidore<lb/> Loeb&#44; its Secretary&#44; religiously perfectly devoted to its interests&#44; the names of Rabbis&#44;<lb/> Professors&#44; and philanthropists from the<lb/> Alps to the Appenines&#59; from the Danube<lb/> to the Volga&#44; as far as the Caribbean Sea of all who<lb/> labor in unison of sentiments to the same end&#44;<lb/> giving have lent the Alliance a richly deserved prestige which places it<lb/> foremost among institutions of Hebrew beneficence.<lb/>  I have often before pleaded in its behalf&#44; and<lb/> I rejoice that in the absence of some who might<lb/> advocate with happier results a cause I deem<lb/> righteous&#44; I succeeded in gaining a few addi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tional subscribers to the Philadelphia branch<lb/> of the parent association.  But this Sabbath<lb/> preceding the festivity which makes it incumbent<lb/> on us to send gifts to the poor&#44; I ask of<lb/> my congregation that they will offer a notable<lb/> sign of their sympathy with the goodly work<lb/> and the workers.  Let it be known in<lb/> the capital of France and be written recorded in the<lb/> next Bulletin of the Alliance&#44; that my<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>people dwelling in the city of brotherly<lb/> love&#44; fraternally send greetings to the brave<lb/> Jews&#44; even to those whose exertions aim to<lb/> upraise the lowly of their race.  Let it be known<lb/> that wherever that paper circulates&#44; that from a representative community in the new world a generous donation towards educating<lb/> eight thousand boys and girls of the Hebrew race was forwarded was offered forwarded<lb/> anxious that Oh may by our exertion the number of Hebrew youths<lb/> cared whose moral and intellectual progress is cared for by the Alliance may increase hundredfold by our exertions to the glory<lb/> of our Israel&#39;s religion and the sanctification of Israel&#39;s God.<lb/></p>
            
            <p>Donations may be sent to Mr Simon Muhr&#44; 633<lb/> Chestnut St&#44; or&#44; if so preferred&#44; to my house 546 Nth<lb/> 5th st.  The receipt of money will be duly acknow&#45;<lb/>&#45;ledged in the Jewish Record&#44; and sent without much unnecessary<lb/> delay to the Central committee in Paris.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
