<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF16_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1894" source="" attested="yes">1894</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff16_2_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET.<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44;		1894<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>On Elijah for Haftorath &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            <p>61</p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Why has the Jew suffered persecution always&#63;  Because<lb/> he has dared to stand forth as a living protest against<lb/> falsehood.  Demanded to surrender his charter and<lb/> cast it at the feet&#44; now of paganism&#44; anon of Christ&#45;<lb/>&#45;ianity and Islamism that it may might be trampled upon&#44;<lb/> he said&#58; &#34;You Thou cruel gentilism&#44; mayest tread upon my body&#44; but<lb/> I will hold fast even unto death to the instrument<lb/> of my spiritual freedom&#45;&#45;the Torah.&#34;  Our<lb/> philosopher poet Judah Ho&#45;Levy&#44; who called the Jew the heart of the<lb/> world&#44; whose circulating blood prevented mankind<lb/> from stagnating&#44; asked the King of the Rhazars&#44; that<lb/> inclined to undervalue Israel&#44; what he would think thought of<lb/> a nation that could exchange a life of trials for one<lb/> of ease by a simple utterance&#44; and still prefersed afflict&#45;<lb/>ions to falsehood prevarications.  &#34;I bow to Jupiter&#44; I sear by the cross&#44;<lb/> I acknowledge Mohammed God&#39;s prophet.&#34;  Those<lb/> simple few words&#44; would have extinguished for ever the fire<lb/> of persecution.  But the cowardly confession did not<lb/> come.  Of that&#44; the Jew may rightly boast.<lb/>  His sufferings are his glory.  Aye&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> For Thee&#44; O Lord&#33; we have been killed slain every day&#44; we are reckoned<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>like sheep for the slaughter&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> All that has come upon befallen us&#44; yet&#44; we have not<lb/> forgotten Thee&#44; neither have we hid against Thy<lb/> covenant&#34;.  Brethren.  In the Hatorah of<lb/> this Sabbath&#44; loyal Israel is typified.  Elijah<lb/> the avenger of the covenant&#44; wandering in exile<lb/> with a drawn sword hanging over his head&#59; Elijah<lb/> enduring misery&#44; is a fitting symbol of the<lb/> people from where he sprung.  Heathenism<lb/> had triumphed&#44; for a time&#44; over Judaism.  An<lb/> ill&#45;assorted marriage between the son of<lb/> Omri and the daughter of Ethbaal&#44; brought<lb/> in its train the saddest consequences.  Ambition&#44;<lb/> perhaps&#44; led Ahab to wed a princess of Phoe&#45;<lb/>nicia&#44; born and bred in a hotbed of debasing<lb/> idolatry.  The influence of such a woman was<lb/> poisonous.  Her royal husband drank in that<lb/> soul corroding venom&#59; his subjects caught the<lb/> killing infection.  The God of Abraham must<lb/> feel prostrate before the brutal deities of the<lb/> Sidonians.  The altar built at Zion in honor of the Lawgiver<lb/> of Sinai&#44; must make room for those altars reeking with<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>the blood of human sacrifices.  So Jezebel had vowed.  But not all<lb/> in the corrupt kingdom of Israel were corrupt.<lb/>  Jezebel had forced into silence by engines of death&#44;<lb/> every one who moaned and wept over the abroga&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion of the religion of Moses.  Still&#44; in the<lb/> palace of inequity an official lived&#44; who secretly<lb/> labored to mitigate the evil which the impious queen had<lb/> wrought.  But how he God&#45;fearing Obadiah trembled&#44; lest a discovery of<lb/> his fealty to Judaism&#44; might redouble the trials<lb/> of the faithful.  Jezebel was the &#91;&#63;&#93;&#45;eyed monster that never sleeps.  We may consider Jeze&#45;<lb/>&#45;bel&#44; the pagan wife of Ahab the Israelite&#44; the<lb/> initiator of those series of persecution to which<lb/> we are yet exposed.  But whom did our heavenly Deliverer raise then to baffle the scheme<lb/> of the infamous Sidonian&#44; bent upon supplanting<lb/> Monotheism by a compulsory introduction adoration of her<lb/> polytheism&#63;  Like an apparition suddenly<lb/> a the man arose&#44; to who lifted up high the banner of Sinai<lb/> in the face of Jezebel.  Did he issue from<lb/> the school of prophets&#44; which the great Samuel<lb/> had founded and fostered&#63;  We do not know.<lb/>  Equally uncertain we are about his nativity<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>and parentage.  But what of that&#63;  He was<lb/> the child of the hour&#44; born to terrify unright&#45;<lb/>&#45;eousness.  Weird in his appearance&#44; trenchant<lb/> in his language&#44; he brings a hard message from<lb/> the Master whom he served &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;As the Lord God of Israel&#44; before whom<lb/> I stand does him&#44; I swear that in these coming years&#44;<lb/> no dew or rain shall come down&#44; unless I say command it.&#34;<lb/>  Drought&#44; the frequent plaque of the land of<lb/> mountains and valleys&#44; watered by showers from<lb/> the sky &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> The dreaded drought of Palestine comes.  The soil<lb/> is parched.  Man&#39;s tongue cleaves to the roof of<lb/> his mouth.  Sin has shut up the heavens&#44; then precious drops refuse to fall &#91;Hebrew&#93;  &#34;Where is Elijah&#63;  By all the<lb/> goods of Sidon&#44; the herald of a calamity shall<lb/> die.  He must pay with his life for the sorrows he his pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;dicted.  Where does he the hated Tishbite lie hidden&#63;  Let him be<lb/> dragged into the presence of Jezebel.  What prince&#44;<lb/> or what people has dared to give him shelter&#63;  The<lb/> hand of Jezebel will reach all to scourge and<lb/> to tear and devastate&#34;.  &#34;Check thy<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>wrath&#44; thou wicked heathen&#44; who sharest the throne<lb/> of Israel.  The man thou hast compelled to seek<lb/> a scanty meal and a bed among strangers&#44; has<lb/> arrived.  Ahab has met him.&#34;  Ahab and Elijah<lb/> stand face to face.  The crowned head and the stern<lb/> denouncer of wrong.  &#34;Is it thou indeed&#44; thou he who<lb/> hast so troubled Israel&#34;.  &#34;Not I&#44;&#34; answers Elijah.<lb/>  &#34;Not I have troubled Israel&#44; but thou and thy father&#39;s<lb/> house who have have troubled my people.  Thou and thy father&#39;s house&#44; that for led man to cast behind the command of the<lb/> Lord and run after debauching idols.  Let thy false<lb/> prophets&#44; who fatten at the table of Ze Jezebel&#44;<lb/> prove that a spirit from on high rests upon them&#44;<lb/> and I shall kneel before thy heathen queen.&#34;<lb/>  The challenge is accepted.  Our Haftorah<lb/> describes the test thrillingly.  Our mount<lb/> Carmel&#45;&#45;a promontory near the Mediterranean<lb/> sea&#44; Elijah takes his stand.  His gaunt figure&#44;<lb/> his attenuated body&#44; his <sic>dishevelled</sic> hair&#44; his coarse garment tied<lb/> round his the waist with a leather belt&#44; contrasted<lb/> sbv strikingly with the rich b gorgeous robes of the well<lb/> preserved flatterers&#44; who ministered lay increase at the shrine of Jezebel&#39;s idols.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Listen&#44; he is addressing the people multitude who have<lb/> come to see the awful trial.  &#34;How long will ye halt<lb/> between two opinions&#63;  If the Lord that Abraham<lb/> discovered beheld is nature and Moses proclaimed One&#44;<lb/> is the true God&#44; follow Him&#44; and if the idols of Jezebel<lb/> is are gods&#44; follow them.  Here&#44; are those the ministers richly rewarded<lb/> for raising temples to Baal.  Let them sing of his its his praises&#44;<lb/> and ask that he may send a fire to consume<lb/> the offerings made in honor of its his divinity.  If fire<lb/> shall descend from heaven at their bidding&#44; then go<lb/> ye&#44; children of Israel&#44; and deny for ever the rock whence you<lb/> were hewn&#45;&#45;Abraham the Hebrew and Moses who<lb/> led you on guided us with his spirit&#34;.  The altar is set up&#44; the<lb/> sacrifice is laid upon it&#59; the priests pray and cry<lb/> long.  &#34;Oh Baal&#33;  Reveal thy power.&#34;  Elijah mocks<lb/> them.  &#34;Pray louder&#44; cry with a stronger voice&#44; may<lb/> be Baal is not here&#44; he has gone further&#44; or perchance<lb/> other petitioners occupy its his mind.&#34;  Like the wild<lb/> Arabs of the rast desert in their fantastic and fanatical worship&#44; the priests of Baal work them&#45;<lb/>&#45;selves into a state of frenzy.  With swords and lances<lb/> they cut their flesh and slash at one another&#44; until<lb/> they are smeared with streaming blood.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Not fancifully did the Sages of Israel&#44; while<lb/> commenting upon the portion of the Pentateuch which<lb/> we have just read&#44; interpret the action of the<lb/> worshippers adorers of the golden calf&#44; who sang and<lb/> danced&#44; as a worship shockingly revolting &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Now&#44; the sun that had shone with its oriental bright&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness is now on the Eastern summit&#44; commanding a fair view of the Mediterranean sea&#44; was bending towards the West.  Elijah rises<lb/> in the calmness of prophetic majesty.  &#34;Draw nigh<lb/> to me ye progeny of Jacob and see if the living God whom<lb/> you have forsaken liveth&#34; So the austere&#44; but staunch&#45;<lb/>&#45;est believer of in Adona&#239;&#44; speaks.  Israel has gone astray.<lb/>  The nationality which David knit together by military<lb/> genius&#44; his unwise successors have split asunder.<lb/>  Elijah the patriot&#44; Elijah the herald of the One<lb/> God&#44; will not recognize a denationalizing division.<lb/>  Twelve stones he raises to set up his altar&#44; and prays.<lb/>  Not wildly but with intensity of fervor&#44; convinced<lb/> that the Lord who commands lightnings and thunders<lb/> and they go forth&#44; can bid fire to come and con&#45;<lb/>sume the sacrifice offered in honor to His name.<lb/>  &#34;Oh Lord God of Abraham&#44; Isaac and Israel&#59; this day<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>shall it be known&#44; that Thou art God in Israel&#44;<lb/> and that I am Thy servant....Answer me&#44;<lb/> O Lord&#33; Answer me&#44; and let this people know&#44;<lb/> that thou art the only God and that Thou<lb/> hast turned their heart back again.&#34;  You know<lb/> my brethren&#44; the precious confession sevenfold<lb/> repeated by the Jew&#44; everywhere when the sun<lb/> of the holiest day in the year departs.  &#34;The Lord<lb/> He is God.  The Lord He is God.&#34;  That confession&#44;<lb/> from an erring by a penitent people rent the air&#44; as Elijah<lb/> from the top of Carmel saluted the welcomed fire<lb/> that showed proved him God&#39;s ever constant servant.<lb/>  Malachi&#44; the last of our prophets&#44; saw that<lb/> typical avenger of the Unity arrive in advance in spirit before<lb/> of the great and tremendous day&#44; when God will<lb/> redeem His word to faithful Israel.  The Rabbis<lb/> make room for the Tishbite&#44; that he may preside<lb/> in spirit over assemblages initiating those born in Israel<lb/> into Abraham&#39;s covenant&#44; and they greet him it adhere his entrance in spirit to in the honored the evening<lb/> repast of the Passover holiday is held.  They Our Sages look for<lb/> the venerable Seer to hastening to preach union<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; when fathers shall not dispute<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>with their children&#44; nor children with their<lb/> fathers on the religion that has made us one and<lb/> indivisible&#59; all when all with will declare<lb/> that God gave unto Moses in Koreb for all Israel<lb/> statutes and ordinances.  Oh&#33; may Elijah arise&#44;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;to cleanse what is impure&#44; to bring near those<lb/> who have gone far and establish peace in the our<lb/> world&#34;<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
