<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF19_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_2_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>56</p>
            
            <p>On the necessity of a building<lb/>
                down town for school purposes.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Perhaps it might be more agreeable to my hearers&#44;<lb/> and to me certainly more of a mental diversion to myself if I<lb/> were to enter the arena of theology&#44; and rebut false muster up sufficient strength<lb/> teachings stepping forth to defeat falsehood starting out with a glamour of plausibility.<lb/>  To follow such a course I have been urged by clerical<lb/> colleagues.  They see dreadful dangers looming high in the<lb/> large following which a fancys Judaism&#44; a Judaism of<lb/> mere negations&#44; seems to be constantly gaining.  But I<lb/> have grown old in my the ministerial vocation&#44; and time has shown<lb/> me continual changes.  Not infrequently startling re&#45;<lb/>&#45;velations have proved to my mind the unreliableness of popu&#45;<lb/>&#45;larity.  I would deem it culpable in one who believes<lb/> in the final victory of truth&#44; to be wrestling with a<lb/> quixotism that must exhaust itself.  I do deplore<lb/> the fascination which wordy speeches&#44; <sic>tinselled</sic> with<lb/> dazzling rhetoric&#44; casts over men and women of Israel.  I la&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment it principally because of some youths of my<lb/> people&#44; who&#44; unrestrained by home education and example&#44;<lb/> may learn irreverence and arrogance.  But to fear that<lb/> the light which our soul&#45;illumined Moses has given spread through the civilized<lb/> world&#44; will be eclipsed by meteors&#44; by Jaco&#45;lanterns&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>vapory&#44; unsubstantial&#44; would be to sin of incredulity.  The<lb/> Jew is an ever living testimony of a God outside and<lb/> above nature&#44; therefore we do will not discard miracles.<lb/>  The Jew is the clearest <sic>fulfilment</sic> of Scriptural pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;dictions&#44; therefore we do will not discard prophecy.  The<lb/> Jew is the surest evidence of the beneficial influence<lb/> of rites and ceremonies&#44; therefore we do will not discard<lb/> Biblical &#38; Rabbinical institutions.  But of very little<lb/> account it is that we object to discard throw aside the ances&#45;<lb/>&#45;tral belief at the request of declaimers.  Those who<lb/> love the faith in all sincerity must act.  I give my<lb/> hearty assent to this lesson&#45;&#45;which is very old&#44; but which is so self&#45;complacently ad&#45;<lb/>&#45;vanced&#44; as if it were brand new.  We should have a reli&#45;<lb/>&#45;gion more of deeds than of creeds.  So thought our fathers<lb/> who carried out the commandments in every walk<lb/> of life&#44; who postponed their happiness to the glory<lb/> of the Sinaic ordinances&#44; who staked their existence<lb/> that Judaism might not perish from the earth.<lb/>  Now&#44; brethren&#44; why have I recently dwelt on one sub&#45;<lb/>&#45;bject&#44; at the risk of becoming irksome&#44; but<lb/> to raise colaborers that the Law may be held up<lb/> by pure hands&#63;  Each of us is an agent<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>of its preservation&#44; each has been so constituted by the<lb/> immortal legislator who said&#58; &#34;Take heed of thyself<lb/> and open let thy soul be greatly heedful&#44; lest thou forget the things<lb/> that thy eyes have seen&#44; and lest they depart from thy<lb/> heart any days of in thy life&#44; for thou must make them<lb/> known to thy children and to thy children&#39;s children&#34;;<lb/> and later again by the sublimest of orators&#44; who told us<lb/> that the spirit laid upon us and the words put into our<lb/> mouths&#44; must not pass away from out latest progeny<lb/> and for ever.  Each of us is the a custodian of the<lb/> Divine heirloom&#44; but to me&#44; as the one of God&#39;s specially appointed watchman&#44; has the<lb/> golden key of the treasure been entrusted.  I must not<lb/> cowardly surrender it&#44; and let the our first heritage be the<lb/> football of the worldly.  I must hold fast to it and seek our supporters&#44; at all hazards.  Brethren&#44; when&#45;<lb/>&#45;ever I sit among the young of our people&#44; I con&#45; realize<lb/> &#45;sider how very much it behooves me to be watchful and do mission&#45;<lb/>&#45;ary work.  Only last Sunday&#44; answering questions<lb/> put by two intelligent girls&#44; I perceived that Je&#45;<lb/>&#45;remiah&#45;like&#44; I must &#34;root out and pull down....build<lb/> up and replant.&#34;  Speaking of the founder of the<lb/> Christian religion&#44; one said with much feelings&#58; &#34;He<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>was indeed a good man&#44;&#34; and the mother said&#58; &#34;A Reverend<lb/> gentleman alluding to the Messiah&#44; set a whole<lb/> class laughing by telling us in a droll way that he won&#45;<lb/>&#45;dered whether that expected by whom the Jews was expect would be a he or<lb/> a she.&#34;  Yet&#44; there are many who look on Sunday<lb/> Schools as a useless appendage to religious training.<lb/>  Can you not discover the subtle influences brought to bear<lb/> on those of our own flesh and in whose veins runs the blood of the Abraham to alienate them<lb/> from the Synagogue and captivate them to glorify<lb/> the Church&#63;  Now&#44; my protestation of good will<lb/> towards all creatures&#44; independent of their creeds<lb/> or nationality&#44; is not a <sic>pretence</sic>.  No prejudice against<lb/> my fellow beings&#44; as such&#44; is entertained by me&#44; but<lb/> my tolerance is not indifference.  I will not<lb/> allow&#44; where I can prevent it&#44; a stealing of the<lb/> minds which I want to keep firmly attached<lb/> to Israel&#39;s hopes and destiny.  Ought this sentiment of mine<lb/> to be stigmatised as illiberality&#63;  Self&#45;preservation<lb/> is a primary law of nature.  Do not our Nazarene neigh&#45;<lb/>&#45;bors work for the maintenance and dissemination of<lb/> their own doctrines&#63;  Very rare are the instances in which<lb/> strangers to our belief&#44; exercise a liberal spirit <sic>benefitting</sic><lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>us specially in any department of human progress.  The Journ&#45;<lb/>&#45;als of Monday morning last forcibly reminded me of set forth that<lb/> fact.  Their perusal called back vividly to my mind the meeting<lb/> of the memorable jubilee on Saturday night of March 3&#44; 1888 at our Aca&#45;<lb/>&#45;demy of music.  A prominent Christian had been invited<lb/> to speak&#44; and his personal experience lent additional weight to his<lb/> words.  He pointed out the good results of Sunday<lb/> schools&#44; and urged the importance of giving them liberal support.<lb/>  I&#44; among others&#44; notwithstanding my disinclination to<lb/> ask non Israelites to plead for our cause&#44; anticipated that a<lb/> the suitable accompaniment of to the kind utterances would be an I looked for an<lb/> encouraging donation.  I have not heard that this ever<lb/> arrived.  But the same noted gentleman&#44; assisting<lb/> last Sunday at the closing exercises of a church con&#45;<lb/>&#45;vention in Allentown&#44; after having made a powerful<lb/> plea in behalf of a Young Men&#39;s Christian Association<lb/> pledged one thousand dollars as an earnest of his feelings towards the erection of<lb/> a building for its the use of the projected institution.  His contribution drew<lb/> forth others and the scheme will be soon realized.<lb/>  Now&#44; the object in advocacy of which he addressed<lb/> Philadelphia Israelites was also educational&#44; and since<lb/> morally elevating&#44; but then it was Jewish.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Well&#44; let Jews must take care of their own.  If they<lb/> fail to grasp the idea that the children of the lowly<lb/> need mighty levers to be raised from a state of debasement&#44; and<lb/> that schools alone can supply those instruments&#44; they<lb/> must be prepared to suffer the heart burnings and the<lb/> shame of a degeneracy.  A few three columns article<lb/> appeared a few days ago in the New York Herald&#44;<lb/> condemnatory of the thousands of our foreign population<lb/> in that city.  Antisemitism may have dictated<lb/> the writing for to the disgrace of this century it crosses out everywhere&#44; that monster is ubiquitous in its mischief&#45;making &#91;Hebrew&#93; but the cogency of some of the arguments<lb/> advanced was given furnished by the conduct of a large num&#45;<lb/>&#45;ber of our coreligionists hailing from benighted countries.<lb/>  Witness the dragging of congregational and ritual<lb/> disputations before civil courts&#44; bringing our faith<lb/> into public disrepute&#44; and saddening the right&#45;thinking<lb/> in our community.  Here the evil has not taken<lb/> a form so virulent a form as there&#44; still a glance at<lb/> the daily records will show among offenders names<lb/> whose Hebrew origin can easily be traced&#44; even if report&#45;<lb/>&#45;ers do not provokingly point it out&#44; and a casual<lb/> walk in certain localities&#44; will disclose a glaring<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>want of regard for the rules of propriety.  We<lb/> cannot enter the stores of the deceivers&#44; and the<lb/> houses of the which are <sic>squallid</sic> ones within and without and cry out&#58; &#34;Hebrew men &#38; women&#33;  Though you<lb/> pray much and pray long&#44; you will not win public<lb/> approval.  Wash yourselves&#44; make yourselves clean&#44; put<lb/> away your foul actions&#44; cease to do wrong&#34;...None<lb/> of us is an Isaiah that could arrogate to himself that<lb/> authority&#44; but all of us can may gain over to the cause of<lb/> right and social refinement the offspring of such.<lb/>  The facilities to learn morality and manners&#44; which are<lb/> Jewish lessons&#44; must be placed within their easiest reach.<lb/>  Penetrating like the dew of heaven&#44; which gently irrigates<lb/> the soil is the lesson teaching of religion instilled into the young<lb/> hearts.   Civilizers are Hebrew and Sunday Schools and Kindergartens&#59;<lb/> sewing and household schools and manual training.  Handicraft is<lb/> principally the redeemer of Israel from a bondage of degrading pursuits.<lb/>  A building sanctified to the elevation of the progeny of the<lb/> humble stationed among us must rise conspicuously in the<lb/> Southern section of Philadelphia.  Propagandists shall see<lb/> it and ply their trade no more&#59; the generous shall see it and<lb/> bless their inspiration&#44; God will see it and destine for it suc&#45;<lb/>&#45;cess and honor for the rehabilitation of His Law&#44; and hte exalt&#45;<lb/>&#45;ation of His name &#40;Over&#41;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>The questions as to the society under whose aus&#45;<lb/>&#45;pices it shall be reared&#44; who shall take the<lb/> initiative in its erection&#44; what name it shall<lb/> bear&#44; what persons shall pride per preside<lb/> after its establishment&#44; such questions sink<lb/> into insignificance before my mind in compari&#45;<lb/>&#45;son with the whole all&#45;important question object staring us in the face&#44; how to<lb/> the maintain the good name that Philadelphia<lb/> Jews have heretofore enjoyed&#59; how to pave<lb/> the way for the Americanizing of our foreign born<lb/> coreligionists but still within the fold of Judaism.<lb/>  We must possess a building round which to<lb/> centre our forces.  Propagandists &#38;c &#216;<lb/></p>
            
            <p>And now&#44; brethren&#44; let us thank the Keeper of Israel<lb/> who neither slumbers nor sleeps.  The shock which<lb/> this edifice received last Sabbath might have injured<lb/> it and endangered God&#39;s <sic>worshippers</sic>.  But an invi<lb/>&#45;sible shield was cast around us&#44; and it delivered our sacred<lb/> shrine and ourselves from peril.  May our devotion to<lb/> Abraham&#39;s faith render us always deserving of Divine protection&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>our love for our people reward us here with length<lb/> of days&#44; our charity and philanthropy be our<lb/> our guiding angels hereafter.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
