<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF2_11</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_11_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_11_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_11_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_11_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_11_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_11_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_11_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_11_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_11_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_11_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_11_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_11_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_11_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_11_7v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>An explanatory lecture<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;When persons dispute&#44; each aiming at the exaltation of<lb/> God&#44; they will ultimately obtain their laudable design&#44;<lb/> but when&#44; on the contrary&#44; they dispute for the attainment<lb/> of earthly preferments&#44; they will fail in compassing their<lb/> purpose.  As an illustration of the first assertion can be<lb/> instanced the contest that arose between Hillel and<lb/> Shama&#239;&#44; of the second that of Korah and all his<lb/> followers.&#34;  My Brethren&#33;  The thorough definition<lb/> of the meaning implied in the afore cited axiom of our<lb/> Rabbins&#44; would necessarily lead into a theological<lb/> dissertation&#44; foreign to the object of my present address&#44;<lb/> but as the word of our Sages refer also to a biblical<lb/> event that forms the main topic of our weekly section&#44;<lb/> I have deemed it opportune to base thereupon my<lb/> exegetical remarks.  By them shall the maxim<lb/> of our ancient teachers be fully exemplified&#44; and<lb/> we shall also learn to curb an ever&#45;growing desire<lb/> for worldly horrors&#59; for&#44; they will demonstrate<lb/> how ambition impelled Korah to rebellion&#44; and<lb/> hastened him to a fatal end.  And as in his fall<lb/> we shall view those involved&#44; whose hearts he stirred<lb/> to their baneful passion which swayed his actions we shall be admonished<lb/> not to become inveigled by the mellifluous arguings<lb/> of the artful.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Korah was the son of Izhar&#44; a junior brother to<lb/> the father of our national leader.  As such&#44; he grew<lb/> envious of the authority which is two first cousins<lb/> wielded.  He endeavoured to persuade himself that<lb/> as Moses had&#44; at the outset&#44; assumed the highest power&#44;<lb/> the sacerdotal functions should have been committed<lb/> to his charge.  The honorable station to which he had<lb/> been summoned&#44; as a Levite&#44; he considered menial when<lb/> contrasted with the priesthood&#59; and nothing less than to<lb/> supersede Aaron&#44; would satisfy his cravings.<lb/></p>
            <p>But his daring scheme could not be effected without<lb/> the countenance of influential bodies.  He therefore<lb/> abided his time&#44; and watched the opportunity&#44; when<lb/> he might secure adherents.  While the hope. of enjoying the possession of a fertile land&#44; swelled the<lb/> breasts of Israel&#44; it would have been hazardous in the<lb/> extreme to venture on a mutiny&#59; but when after a divine<lb/> sentence had doomed a whole generation to an obscure<lb/> death in the wilderness&#44; a spirit of disaffection might<lb/> find easier access into the hearts of the unwary.<lb/></p>
            <p>Besides he knew&#44; that under circumstances&#44; his subtlety<lb/> could awaken a doubt&#44; in those that had bee n divested<lb/> of authority&#44; as to the <sic>legallity</sic> of the act.  The first<lb/> born&#44; who had been set apart to the Lord on the memo&#45;<lb/>&#45;rable night of the national deliverance&#44; had forfeited<lb/> their rank when they became implicated in the sin<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>of the molten&#45;calf&#44; and they had witnessed&#45;&#45;with wounded<lb/> feelings no doubt&#45;&#45;the ascension of the Levites unto it by<lb/> reason of their fidelity to God.  It required therefore an<lb/> unscrupulous hand to set that smouldering fire into<lb/> a blaze&#44; and Korah applied to it the consuming brand.<lb/>  Two hundred and fifty personages avowedly leagued<lb/> themselves to the conspiracy&#59; others were ready to<lb/> espouse his unrighteous cause&#44; if it betokened success.<lb/>  Goaded on by their ambitious leader&#44; the seditious party<lb/> confronted Moses and boldly charged him with an undue<lb/> arrogation of power for his own and his brother&#39;s benefit<lb/> to the detriment of the whole nation.  To wheedle the<lb/> multitude&#44; they claimed for them an equal degree of<lb/> sanctity as the recipients of the law&#44; and the witnesses<lb/> of the Godhead&#59; thus virtually denying the spiritual<lb/> mission and moral superiority which hitherto the sons<lb/> of Amram had exercised.  The imputation was grievous&#44;<lb/> and the meekest of men bowed momentarily in deep sorrow&#44;<lb/>  but uplifted by the divine afflatus which dwelt in him&#44;<lb/> he felt not dismayed.  At once he dived into the<lb/> principal motive of the rebellion&#44; and addressing Koreh<lb/> together with his accessories&#44; proferred to them a test<lb/> of his truthfulness&#44; and the legitimacy of Aaron&#39;s investi&#45;<lb/>&#45;ture.  They should all on the morrow present the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>customary morning incense&#44; and God would by some<lb/> extraordinary sign&#44; point out to the people&#44; the<lb/> man to whom he had assigned that religious function.<lb/>  And in order to convince them that he had <sic>unravelled</sic><lb/> their plot&#44; he upbraided their ambition&#44; which<lb/> in craving the priesthood&#44; set no proper value on their<lb/> ministerial dignity.  But if the sagacity of Moses<lb/> had enabled him to fathom the guilty scheme of Korah<lb/> and the men of his tribe&#44; the could not readily un&#45;<lb/>fold to him the reason which had prompted those agi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tators&#44; who were not Levites&#44; to join the conspiracy.<lb/>  Wherefore he summoned Dathan and Abaam &#40;On the<lb/> son of Peleth having recanted&#41; unto his presence.<lb/>  With contumely those recreants replied by a message<lb/> which revealed the rank seeds which had taken<lb/> root in them.  &#34;No&#44;&#34; they said &#34;we will not obey<lb/> him who has wantonly led us into uninhabited<lb/> regions&#44; there to perish ingloriously.  To domineer<lb/> over us&#44; he has seduced us away from a fair land&#44;<lb/> with the glowing promise of a happy future&#44; and<lb/> now he thinks to blind us all&#44; touching our sad fate.&#34;<lb/>  Overwhelmed by so atrocious an accusation&#44; the<lb/> man of God betook himself to prayer&#44; and<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>entreated that the Supreme might prove his innocence&#44;<lb/> by refusing to be appeased by the offering of such<lb/> who merited his divine chastisement&#44; for to Him the Omniscient was<lb/> known that he never wronged his neighbour&#44; or<lb/> appropriated aught to himself as a reward for his inces&#45;<lb/>&#45;sant toil.  The petition of his faithful servant<lb/> ascended to the throne of the Lord.  Suddenly the<lb/> mystical cloud stood at the door of the tent&#44; where<lb/> a turbulent multitude had gathered.  General<lb/> would now have been the terrible doom which awaits<lb/> the factious party&#44; if the very men whose humi&#45;<lb/>&#45;liation had been the aim of the sedition&#44; had not<lb/> ardently interceded to avert celestial wrath.  &#34;O God&#34;<lb/> they exclaimed &#34;The God of the spirit of all flesh&#44; shall<lb/> one man sin&#44; and wilt thou be wroth with all the<lb/> congregation&#34;&#63;  But to eschew the impending des&#45;<lb/>&#45;truction&#44; the mere alleging of an enticement practised<lb/> by artful individuals&#44; was insufficient.  They who<lb/> had lent a ready ear to the inveigler&#44; should&#44;<lb/> by a public act retract&#44; hence were the assemblage<lb/> bid to depart from the &#91;&#63;&#93; neighborhood of the refractory<lb/> leaders.  Imperturbably stood the latter with<lb/> their household outside of their tents&#44; and their<lb/> unblushing demeanour seemed to defy the prophet<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>of God.  But.....a crush is heard&#58; the subteren&#45;<lb/>&#45;nean fires no longer compressed by the will of<lb/> the Creator bounced burst with all might&#44; and the earth<lb/> was rent in twain.  But not like the natural<lb/> phenomenon&#44; occasionally experienced in Southern<lb/> climes&#44; was this terrific event&#59; for&#44; while it occurred<lb/> only within a limited space&#59; it varied also in its other<lb/> features.  Justly here therefore our Sages placed<lb/> it in the category of those preternatural creations<lb/> fixed by the hand of the Omnipotent from since the<lb/> primordial days &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44;<lb/> for&#44; what cause can otherwise be assigned to an<lb/> instantaneous irruption which supposes discharges itself at a stated<lb/> moment&#44; in a stated location&#44; that swallows up<lb/> a stated number&#44; that leaves no trace behind&#44; but<lb/> covers its own chasms by the earth it has disrupted&#63;<lb/>  Human ingenuity may have sought to explain<lb/> it&#44; but it has hitherto failed to solve all the queries<lb/> which this <sic>bibblical</sic> incident arouses on a searching mind.<lb/>  And we are forced to acknowledge&#44; that it was the hand<lb/> of the Almighty that worked miraculously.<lb/>  The crime of the rebellious people had been of great<lb/> magnitude&#44; and extraordinary was also their<lb/> condign requital.  Nor was loss severe and portentous the punish<lb/>&#45;ment of their accomplices&#44; who had disputed the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Sacerdotal right of Aaron&#59; for&#44; the fire that should have<lb/> consumed their incense&#44; devoured their lives.  Like<lb/> Korah&#44; they&#44; whom a hankering after worldly honors had<lb/> incited to mutiny&#44; perished ingloriously.  Would&#44; my dear<lb/> Brethren&#33; that we could narrate&#44; what is recorded respect&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing the children of the arch conspirator&#44; namely&#44; that<lb/> the bulk of the nation remained faithful to their God&#59; for&#44;<lb/> Alas&#33; even that catastrophe failed to quell the revolt<lb/> which the ambitious son of Izhar had fostered.  The day<lb/> following two disastrous events&#44; beheld the men of Israel<lb/> with unabated effrontery arraign their leader and their priest<lb/> for the crime of murder.  What they had witnessed&#44; did<lb/> not yet dispell a fatal error engrafted in their minds<lb/> by the subtle and the crafty.  The whole economy<lb/> of the world that should have taught them&#44; how God<lb/> himself established certain gradations among his created<lb/> beings&#44; by endowing some with more and some with<lb/> less intelligence.  Their own selection&#44; as a peculiar<lb/> people&#44; that should have more forcibly convinced<lb/> them of that truth.  All the divine favors the had<lb/> experienced&#44; through the agency of one Superior man&#44;&#45;&#45;so<lb/> powerful an illustration of the same verity remained unheeded by<lb/> them.  Rather than believe in the genuineness of<lb/> Aaron&#39;s exaltation&#44; and that of his progeny and tribe&#44; they<lb/> would attribute his success to sheer <sic>strategems</sic>.<lb/>  Probably on this occasion&#44; the first&#45;born stirred<lb/> the agitation&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>for&#44; we perceive&#44; that not until the rod of Aaron<lb/> had miraculously produced signs which evidenced<lb/> the legitimacy of his authority was <sic>tranquillity</sic><lb/> restored.  When amid the rods representing the<lb/> various tribes&#44; his alone budded and flourished&#44;<lb/> the sacerdotal and levitical rights authority&#44; with which<lb/> his descendants and corelatives had been invested&#44;<lb/> was indisputably acknowledged.  But the<lb/> flagitious conduct of our progenitors&#44; drew upon them<lb/> the indignation of the Lord.  A pestilence raged<lb/> throughout their camps&#44; and wrought a terrible<lb/> havoc.  It was then that they witnessed how<lb/> the censer and the perfume&#44; which in unholy hands<lb/> caused instantaneous death&#44; proved salutary instruments<lb/> in those legally consecrated to the service of the Eternal.<lb/>  They had denied the sanctity of Aaron&#44; and now they<lb/> beheld him walk unscathed among the dead.  They<lb/> had sought his humiliation&#44; and now they saw the<lb/> his eagerness to atone for the sinners&#44; and restore them<lb/> to health.  With his righteous brother&#44; he had be&#45;<lb/>&#45;sought the mercy of God in behalf of his opponents&#44;<lb/> and solicitous for their repentance rather than for<lb/> their perdition&#44; with an anxious face hastened among<lb/> the sufferers&#44; to stay the sword of the Destroyer&#44;<lb/> for &#34;he loved peace&#44; pursued peace&#44; loved his fellow&#45;<lb/>creatures&#44; and desired to reclaim them&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Such is the flattering description which the Sages of the<lb/> Mishna have left of the first Hebrew priest&#59; but<lb/> his ambitious adversaries they held up to ignominy&#44; when&#44;<lb/> in the words of our text&#44; they offend them as an example<lb/> of unrighteous disputants&#44; whose existence was extinguished<lb/> with their wicked hope.  Let us then&#44; my friends&#44;<lb/> learn from the lesson of this Sabbath&#44; to correct a foible<lb/> which greatly prevails among us&#44; and which has<lb/> already proved its banefulness&#44; by cramping reli&#45;<lb/>&#45;gious progress.  Let us accomplish as much good<lb/> as it lies in our power&#44; within our own spheres&#44;<lb/> but let us not be induced to supplant others&#44; or rival<lb/> their positions&#44; by the deceptive thought&#44; that our<lb/> efforts would redound more to public advantage.<lb/>  Let us not over&#45;rate our capacities&#44; or worth&#44; which<lb/> will blend us to those of our neighbour&#44; who perchance<lb/> occupies high authority.  Let us aspire to the honor<lb/> of possessing virtues&#44; for their sake&#44; and not with<lb/> the view that our name may be blazoned before<lb/> an admiring multitude.  Let us&#44; above all&#44; be<lb/> wary of the insidious voice which whispers in our<lb/> ears&#44; pleasing blandishing words&#44; for&#44; adulation begets ambition&#44; and<lb/> the disappointment of the latter engenders a passion&#44;<lb/> will which poisons the channels of life&#44; for&#44; the wisest<lb/> of men has written &#34;that envy is rottenness to the<lb/> bones&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  May it be harbored<lb/> within our breasts&#33;  Amen.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>O God&#33; our hearts are exceedingly deceitful&#44; and<lb/> lead us into temptation.  Guide them Thou<lb/> according to thy fatherly goodness.  Repress<lb/> their vehemence&#44; and subdue their cravings.<lb/>  Oh&#33; suffer not ambition or envy to sunder<lb/> the ties which unite us with our fellow&#45;mor&#45;<lb/>&#45;tals.  Let their virtues excite our emulation&#44;<lb/> their vices our commiseration.  May we never<lb/> conspire to build our fame upon the ruin of<lb/> that which they enjoy&#44; but grant that our<lb/> own righteous efforts and beneficent pursuits&#44;<lb/> may captivate the good&#45;will of men&#44; and thy<lb/> gracious favour.  Grant that the weekly<lb/> recital of thy sacred word may further our<lb/> moral progress&#44; and that by pondering thereon<lb/> we may become purified of the dross of human<lb/> passions&#44; and imbued with a spirit of meekness<lb/> forbearance&#44; and kindliness&#44; for&#44; accompanied<lb/> by those three virtues&#44; our existence shall be<lb/> lengthened in the land of the living&#44; and<lb/> eternized hereafter.  May it ever be so.<lb/>  Amen<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>Rev. S. Morais<lb/> North 5th St<lb/> with A Hart&#39;s thanks<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
