<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF3_16</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1894-01" source="" attested="yes">April 1894</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_17_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_17_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_17_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_17_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_17_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_17_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_17_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_17_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_17_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_17_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_17_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_17_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>94<lb/></p>
            <p>On the Jewish Calendar<lb/>
                for Parashat Ha&#45;Chodesh<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>All must have noticed that Easter Sund happened<lb/> this year four weeks&#44; but one day earlier than the Jewish<lb/> Passover&#44; now approaching.  I do not direct the attention<lb/> of Israelites to that circumstance&#44; with the view of aping<lb/> a practice much in vogue&#44; among the liberals in our<lb/> clergy.  To use the Synagogue for a purpose al&#45;<lb/>&#45;together foreign&#44; I may say hostile&#44; to it&#59; to tell Jews&#44;<lb/> whom I am bound to instruct in the Law and traditions<lb/> of their faith&#44; that the alleged founder of Christianity<lb/> belongs essentially to the best of us highest class type of our Seers and Sages&#44; that he has high every<lb/> claims to our gratitude&#59; that we must acknowledge his<lb/> teaching as most sublime&#44; in a word&#44; that Jesus was as great<lb/> as Moses&#44; such is a system of pulpit preaching which I cannot<lb/> adopt and remain a minister in the service of Israel&#39;s<lb/> God.  The right of the Church to sound the<lb/> praises of the man of Nazareth&#44; is indisputable&#44;<lb/> and the occasions have been frequent on which I publicly<lb/> acknowledged admitted that right.  I have also often expressed<lb/> myself respectfully in regard to towards the followers of the<lb/> Galilean&#44; who is credited to have given origin to a<lb/> new religion.  Only a few weeks ago&#44; declining a<lb/> polite invitation by an enthusiastic conversionist to<lb/> attend a meeting at her house&#44; where I had just reasons<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>to suspect that apostates from our belief would be present&#44;<lb/> I stated that&#44; while I shun the contact of recreants&#44; I<lb/> entertain very kind feelings for born Christians.  I even<lb/> excuse the lady&#39;s <sic>persistance</sic> in flooding me with tracts<lb/> sent to my address in her handwriting.  For&#44; she honestly<lb/> hopes to influence my mind and prevent my dying<lb/> a Jew&#45;&#45;too horrible an end in her imagination.  My<lb/> intention now is not to dwell on the advent which<lb/> Easter commemorates.  I desire neither to honor nor to<lb/> dishonor the author of the creed&#44; the spreading of which<lb/> through the world&#44; brought upon my people sufferings and sorrows unequal<lb/> in extent and depth.  I shall remain silent on that point.<lb/>  As to the dogma connected with Easter&#44; suffice for me to<lb/> say that we reject&#44; without the last reservation&#44; the idea<lb/> connected with attached to that Christian holiday&#44; based as it is on<lb/> the notion that a crucifixion and a bodily resurrection<lb/> were necessary&#44; as an atonement for the transgression of<lb/> the first parents of the human race and for the salvation<lb/> of mankind.  With a trumpet voice tongue&#44; Ezekiel<lb/> warns us against the holding of such a notion&#44; when<lb/> he cried out &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;The soul that sinneth&#44;<lb/> that shall die&#34;  My object this morning&#44;<lb/> however&#44; is simply to offer a measure of information&#44;<lb/> to any of my hearers&#44; who do not possess it.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>During the first centuries of Christianity&#44; what<lb/> now is called Easter&#44; did not exist under that name.<lb/>  Pascha or Pasqua was then the appellation&#44; derived<lb/> from the Hebrew Pesach or Pasach.  In fact&#44; it is so<lb/> called termed yet by the Latin races&#44; Italian&#44; French&#44; Spanish&#44;<lb/> Portuguese&#44; Wallachian&#44; vay varying in the pronuncia&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion&#44; but retaining in the main&#44; the word as in its<lb/> original primitive form.  For&#44; early Christians celebrated<lb/> their festivals simultaneously with the Jews&#44; after according to<lb/> the direction of the Sanhedrin in Judea.  It was in<lb/> the year 325 of our neighbors&#39; reckoning&#44; that<lb/> the emperor Constantin&#44; wishing to put an end to<lb/> disputations which had already arisen in several<lb/> churches&#44; convened a synod or council of very many<lb/> learned priests in the city of Nice in Asia Minor&#44;<lb/> and asked that they should determine how the religion&#44;<lb/> which sprung from Judaism&#44; ought to be governed.<lb/>  Among the decisions arrived at by those prelates&#44; was<lb/> that which demanded a total separation from<lb/> the parent faith in doctrines and practices.  &#34;We will<lb/> not have nothing in common with the hateful Jewish<lb/> people.  We have been shown another way by our Saviour&#44;&#34;<lb/> were the words that opened a chasm between the adherents<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>of the young preacher of Galilee and those whom<lb/> the archprophet of Sinai had instructed.  No more<lb/> would the evening of the fourteenth of Nissan be observed<lb/> to commemorate the circumstance that the man of<lb/> Nazareth had kept the Passover with his disciples&#44;<lb/> but the Sunday after the Spring equinox would always<lb/> be set apart for the festival.  And as heathens<lb/> held then a feast&#44; to greet the season which quickens<lb/> the soil and makes it fruitful&#44; that time was selected<lb/> with the ulterior object of rallying gentiles round<lb/> the banner of the cross&#45;&#45;Easter being in the Asian languages<lb/> Ostara&#44; or &#198;stara&#44; the goddess of spring.  Never&#45;<lb/>&#45;theless&#44; generally Passover and Easter came close to&#45;<lb/>&#45;gether&#44; for&#44; however Christianity may have endeavoured<lb/> to keep aloof from us&#44; as far as possible&#44; it could<lb/> not altar the seasons.  It realized that&#44; according<lb/> to the new testament&#44; the last supper ate at Jerusalem<lb/> by the deified Galilean&#44; was in the month of Abib&#45;&#45;the<lb/> month which we enter this Sabbath and in which Moses<lb/> ordered Israel to sanctify the memorial of their der reden<lb/> redemption from a bodily and spiritual bondage.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Thou shalt perform this service in this month&#44;&#34;<lb/> Are we wrong this year in our computation&#44; or our are<lb/> our neighbors of a later creed at fault&#63;  Neither&#44; as<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>regards the season&#44; for&#44; Abib continues from the fast last<lb/> week of March to the last week in April.  At times&#44; we have<lb/> celebrated Pesach as early as the 26th of March&#44; at<lb/> others&#44; as late as the 24th of April.  It is due to<lb/> the profound knowledge of numerical calculation possessed by the<lb/> ancients in Israel&#44; that we never run counter to the<lb/> Biblical injunction &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Watch for<lb/> the month Abib and do the Passover&#34;.  To equalize<lb/> our lunar years&#44; consisting of 356 days with the solar<lb/> years consisting of 365&#44; an intercalary month is occasion&#45;<lb/>&#45;ally introduced&#59; namely&#44; seven years of thirteen lunar months&#44;<lb/> in a cycle of nineteen years.  The charge that<lb/> Jews learned from Christians to fix their calendar<lb/> with unerring precision&#44; cannot be sustained&#44; for the<lb/> first synod or council held by Christians&#44; where their<lb/> holidays came under discussions&#44; was that of Nice in Asia<lb/> Minor in the year 325 whereas in the Mishnah&#44; compiled<lb/> in the year 135&#44; special mention is made of the inter&#45;<lb/>calary month or second Adar  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  To prove that the<lb/> Almanac by which Jews are guided throughout the<lb/> world&#44; is as correct as a human mind can make it&#44;<lb/> we may point the to the circumstance that there<lb/> is no record of Passover having come earlier than<lb/> when the sun enters the constellation &#198;ries at the spring<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>equinox.  Not so with Christians.  In 1582&#44; it was<lb/> discovered with dismay&#44; that Easter was running back&#45;<lb/>&#45;ward&#44; threatening to gradually to move towards winter&#45;&#45;<lb/> an anomaly that the Church could not tolerate without falsifying its own history.  That<lb/> great irregularity had its origin in the Calendar arranged<lb/> by Julius C Caesar&#44; in the first half century of<lb/> the Christian era.  It That calendar was 11 minutes and 10 seconds<lb/> longer than the solar year really allows.  Those 11<lb/> minutes and 10 seconds gr accumulated into days&#44; so<lb/> that in the year 1582&#44; Easter instead of coming at the<lb/> vernal equinox&#44; or in Abib&#45;&#45;anticipated it considerably.  Bewildered<lb/> and perplexed&#44; Pope Gregory XIII&#44; had recourse to a<lb/> monstrous contrivance.  He ordered that in order to<lb/> shorten the year&#44; and bring Easter to the right time&#44; ten<lb/> days be skipped from October&#44; making it a month<lb/> of 21 days instead of 31.  He furthermore ordered that<lb/> February&#44; which according to Julius C&#230;sar&#39;s calendar&#44; was<lb/> always 29 days&#44; should mostly reckon 28. days<lb/></p> 
            <p>But why have I fatigued my hearers with Arithmetic&#63;<lb/>  Do not all know that we count our months by the<lb/> changes of the moon&#44; and that in order to celebrate<lb/> Passover at spring&#44; which depends upon the revol&#45;<lb/>&#45;ving of the earth round the sun&#44; we occasionally<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>add a month to our year&#63;  Yes&#59; all are fully aware of that&#44; but not all know<lb/> that the Rabbis&#44; now shamelessly derided by the igno&#45;<lb/>&#45;rant and the flippant&#44; had gained familiarity with<lb/> the sciences accessible to them&#44; and had notably acquired a mastery in<lb/> the noblest of sciences&#45;&#45;Astronomy.  Among the achievements<lb/> of the our literary giant&#44;&#45;&#45;the world&#45;famous Maimonides&#45;&#45;his<lb/> treatise on the evolutions of the moon &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; discloses<lb/> the greatness of our olden sages&#44; whom he quotes.  Since the year 358 of<lb/> Christian reckoning&#44; when Hillel the younger&#44; a scion of<lb/> <sic>of</sic> a splendid stock&#44; prepared his calendar to guide<lb/> the outcasts of Judah in every spot of the globe&#44; where<lb/> Providence has placed them&#44; no alteration has been needed&#44;<lb/> to cause us to conform with the Divine commandment<lb/> to celebrate at the proper time &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;the feast of unleavened bread&#44; the feast<lb/> of weeks and the feast of Tabernacles.  All honor<lb/> to the ancestry of which we have a right to boast.<lb/>  Would that we all appreciated the glory which is pe&#45;<lb/>&#45;culiarly ours and valued it as it deserves.  But what<lb/> many of us sinfully despise&#44; or regard with indifference&#44;<lb/> has secured the recognition of non&#45;Jewish authorities of<lb/> high standing.  Joseph Justus Scaliger&#44; who bore the<lb/> title of &#34;father of the science of Chronology&#34; wrote that<lb/> nothing is so accurate and so perfect of its kind&#44; as the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>as the Jewish calculation&#44; and those who have fixed<lb/> the time for the Easter holiday&#44; ought to take lesson<lb/> from it.  Again&#44; an English theologian of renown&#44; mar&#45;<lb/>&#45;vels at the g ingenious and keen intellect evidenced<lb/> by Jews in their calculation of time&#44; and an Italian<lb/> Professor of Astronomy at the Parma university&#44;<lb/> in a pamphlet treating of the celebration of Easter&#44;<lb/> writes&#58; &#34;Jews pride themselves on a greater accuracy<lb/> than the Church respecting the phases of the moon<lb/> etc&#44; and their pride is well rightly founded&#34;.  Well<lb/> then.  This year also although preceded<lb/> by Easter nearly four weeks&#44; it will be observed by<lb/> the house of Israel everywhere as the Almighty<lb/> Legislator ordained &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;The children of Israel shall perform the Passover<lb/> in its due season.&#34;  May it come to us fraught with<lb/> blessings.  May we not hear what grieves us to the core<lb/> almost yearly&#44; even the heartless accusation that works<lb/> desolation.  May it be the harbinger of freedom<lb/> to our brethren in the lands of modern Pharaohs&#44;<lb/> and as the Rabbis prognosticated may redemption follow<lb/> in its train &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
