<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF3_4</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_4_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_4_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_4_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_4_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_4_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_4_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_4_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_4_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_4_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_4_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_4_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_4_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_4_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_4_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_4_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_4_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>13 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>The law of benevolence and justice<lb/>
                &#63;&#40;&#91;Hebrew&#93;&#41;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#34;For I know him&#44; that he will command his children<lb/> and his household after him&#44; and they shall keep<lb/> the way of the Lord&#44; do to do justice and judgment&#34;.<lb/>  Dear Brethren&#33;  This sentence which the writer of the<lb/> Pentateuch was inspired to chronicle&#44; as an honorable me&#45;<lb/>&#45;morial of Abraham&#39;s sterling worth&#44; recalled to my mind&#44;<lb/> when I recently perused it&#44; the expression I once made in<lb/> familiar conversation.  The merits of our the father Abraham<lb/> of our people&#44; and those of the greatest among prophets&#44;<lb/> were discussed&#44; and I was requested to decide&#44; which could<lb/> claim the preeminence.  I briefly answered&#58; The virtues<lb/> of Moses are a reflection of Abraham&#39;s virtues.<lb/></p> 
                <p>And if you will ponder on the subject&#44; you will coincide<lb/> with my opinion.  The son of Amram excelled all<lb/> his contemporaries in humility and religious zeal&#44; because<lb/> he copied the life of one who had been&#44; in his age&#44; the<lb/> prototype of righteousness.  &#34;The meekest of all men&#34;&#44;<lb/> had chosen as his pattern&#44; the patriarch who acknowledged<lb/> himself to be &#34;but dust and ashes.&#34;  He whose love<lb/> of Israel and Israel&#39;s God&#44; rendered him unmindful of his<lb/> own temporal happiness&#44; reproduced the self&#45;denial<lb/> of that parent&#44; who would have yielded his only<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>beloved son&#44; to the worship of his Almighty Protector.<lb/>  But <sic>To</sic> both&#44; my friends&#33; must the whole human race&#44;<lb/> bow with equal reverence&#59; for they alike did&#44; in a<lb/> moral sense&#44; change the face of the world.<lb/></p>
            <p>If the glory of having first unfurled the banner of<lb/> Truth is due to Abraham&#44; that of having widened its<lb/> folds&#44; and spread them far&#44; must be awarded to<lb/> Moses.  Wheresoever brutal force has given<lb/> room to equity&#59; kindliness has superseded selfishness&#44;<lb/> there&#44; have those principles been silently at work&#44; which the founder<lb/> of our nation implanted&#44; and his godly successor caused<lb/> to develop.  There&#44; has mankind learnt to understand the<lb/> pers characters inscribed upon the banner standard we uphold &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;God<lb/> is our father&#44; and we all are the creatures of his love&#34;.<lb/></p>
            <p>Verily I say unto you&#44; that not until every being that draws<lb/> the breath of life&#44; shall have learnt to acknowledge One<lb/> Universal shepherd&#44; with the impartings of those two great<lb/> teachers cease to be proclaimed.<lb/></p>
            <p>But while the <sic>humanising</sic> effects of the Mosaic code are<lb/> admitted by all thinking minds&#44; none adequately show<lb/> the unparalleled worth of that law&#44; which the Apostle of<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>the true God&#44; promulgated in Ur of the Chaldeans&#44;<lb/> and on the plains of Mamri.  The Scriptural<lb/> passage I have quoted above&#44; reveals all its beauty<lb/> in unadorned simplicity.  That tells us&#44; why was Abraham<lb/> so divinely favored&#59; why he was called the &#34;friend of God.&#34;<lb/>  The English rendering of it&#44; however&#44; does not entirely altogether convey<lb/> its meaning.  The verb &#91;Hebrew&#93; occurring in it&#44; is variously<lb/> employed in the Bible&#44; and the word &#91;Hebrew&#93; is too com&#45;<lb/>&#45;prehensive&#44; that we may find in the vernacular an<lb/> equivocal term.  I will endeavour&#44; by a few prefa&#45;<lb/>&#45;tory remarks&#44; to unfold more fully intelligibly lucidly its real signification.<lb/>  When the iniquity of the people of Sodom&#44; exceeded<lb/> the long&#45;suffering of the Deity&#44; He&#44; that chasteneth<lb/> to instruct&#44; made Abraham supernaturally acquainted<lb/> with their impending doom.  The Lord judged it<lb/> necessary that he&#44; through whose virtues all the nations<lb/> of the earth&#44; were ultimately to be blessed&#44; should know<lb/> the fate which awaited those who had contravened the<lb/> law He implanted in every breast.  His righteous<lb/> servant would thus acquire a deeper conviction of its sanctity&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>and strive to imbue therewith the heart of his posterity progeny.<lb/>  Hence does Holy Writ express itself as follows &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;For I have sle selected him&#44; that he may command<lb/> his children and his household after him&#44; to keep<lb/> the way of the Lord&#44; by exercising benevolence and justice.&#34;<lb/>  This&#44; my Brethren&#44; is the law which our father<lb/> Abraham discovered by searching into his noble heart&#59;<lb/> this&#44; is the law which he imparted&#44; when&#44; alone<lb/> among in a heathen world&#44; he practices invoked the name of<lb/> the Eternal God&#44;&#34; and the same law it is&#44; which he<lb/> was commissioned to hand down to unborn generations.<lb/>  Even&#44; Benevolence and justice.  Upon us&#44; as the legitimate<lb/> descendants of the godly patriarch&#44; it is incumbent<lb/> to exemplify those qualities in our daily walks.<lb/>  We are especially to exhibit in our lif lives the virtues<lb/> by which the founder of our nation was distinguished &#38; for which and he was loved by the Almighty<lb/> because&#44; like him&#44; were we set up &#91;Hebrew&#93; as a beacon<lb/> light to the gentiles&#59; because through us will the ce&#45;<lb/>lestial promise made to the first believer be verified.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>The Israelite who exercises benevolence and justice&#44;<lb/> does therefore promote the design of the Most High.<lb/>  He is the messenger of His will&#44; who labors to establish<lb/> the Kingdom of heaven upon earth.  But the practice<lb/> of the n two noble virtues must be inseparably connected.<lb/>  He misapprehends his mission&#44; who upholds obeys the former<lb/> and disregards the latter&#59; or who conceives that an regard unflinching<lb/> adherence to justice&#44; is an exemption from benevolence.<lb/>  What&#44; if a person be kindly disposed&#44; and yet be treated<lb/> with dishonesty&#63;  If Or&#44; if he deals uprightly with the holds in his hands even weights<lb/> world at large&#44; but is stone&#45;hearted towards his fellow&#45;<lb/>mortals&#63;  The faithful child of &#34;Abram the<lb/> Hebrew&#34; my dear Brethren&#33; will neither stoop to<lb/> commit a mean action&#44; nor turn a deaf ear to the cry<lb/> of humanity.  Like an impregnable rack he will<lb/> continue on the stand ing where he was eminently<lb/> raised.  From thence will he teach all the way that leads<lb/> to the Lord.  The exhalations of a corrupt society&#44;<lb/> may gather around him&#44; but he will escape their<lb/> baneful influence.  Cruelty and barbarity may wield The black storms of cruelty may rage<lb/> the sway&#44; but he will not pay obeisance to their rule. abroad&#44; but the gentle breeze of kindliness will not never leave his abode.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>But while I can proudly point to my coreligionists<lb/> as to the exponents of the law of beneficence&#59; as<lb/> the compassionate children of compassionate parents&#44;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; I shall not disguise from you&#44;<lb/> that some of them&#44; give our neighbour of a different<lb/> creed&#44; occasion to charge as with the violation of the<lb/> law of justice&#44; to complain that public wrongs are committed<lb/> or conceived at by us to compass dishonest ends.<lb/></p> 
                <p>Tell me not&#44; that our accusers are perhaps stained<lb/> with a deeper hue of impurity.  I have said it before.<lb/>  Were the whole body politic steeped in vice&#44; we<lb/> must keep free from f the prevailing infection.<lb/>  Abraham was surrounded on all sides by heinous crimes&#44; yet&#44;<lb/> he preserved his innocence.  Nay&#44; he refused what<lb/> he could have legally claimed&#44; lest the world might<lb/> exclaim &#34;Abraham grew rich by spoil and plunder.&#34;<lb/>  But what most grieves my heart is&#44; to hear sundry<lb/> of the Mosaic behests our religious practices continued&#44; by reason of<lb/> our prevarications&#59; and that&#44; not alone by<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="8"/>
                <p>the son of the stranger&#44; but but by by the son of Israelites.<lb/> themselves.  Some among my Brethren&#44; have asserted<lb/> that those who appear most rigid in outward<lb/> observances&#44; are generally less faithful to the law<lb/> of benevolence and justice.  I deny it.  Experience<lb/> has convinced me of the contrary.  He who fears to<lb/> disobey God the ancestral behests&#44; will fear to wrong his neighbour.<lb/></p>
                <p>But conceding the point&#44; for the sake of argument&#44;<lb/> are we to draw thence the inference&#44; that moral<lb/> and ceremonial precepts are antagonistical to each<lb/> other&#63;  Where do we find it written for instance that<lb/> a Hebrew man&#44; by arraying himself with the<lb/> phylacteries &#40;Tephilim&#41; is exonerated from the duty<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; of dealing with rectitude&#63;  That<lb/> by constantly wearing fringes &#40;Zizit&#41; in one of his<lb/> under garments&#44; he is absolved from the obligation<lb/> of assisting his fellow&#45;mortals&#63;  Or&#44; that<lb/> if he daily devotes some of his time to prayers&#44; he<lb/> may engage the rest to the indulgence of a<lb/> wanton disposition&#63;  No&#44; no &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="9"/>
                <p>&#34;The exercise of benevolence and justice is more<lb/> acceptable to the Lord than sacrifices&#34;.<lb/></p>
                <p>The external practices tokens of our religion faith are not the<lb/> key which opens the temple of iniquity&#44; but the<lb/> rivet which fastens its gates and bars.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;The commandments were given for human advantage&#34;.<lb/>  If they strengthen us in the pursuit of integrity&#59; if<lb/> they render us good and kind to all the creatures<lb/> of the earth&#44; and grateful to the Universal Creator&#44;<lb/> they perform&#44; through us&#44; their intended object.<lb/>  If they&#44; on the contrary&#44; are sought after&#44; as a cloak<lb/> to our perversity&#44; then&#44; they lose their efficacy&#44;<lb/> and will not screen their votaries from the fire of<lb/> perdition.  But a son of Israel should<lb/> be the last to attribute to the performance of<lb/> <sic>cerimonial</sic> injunctions a pernicious effect.<lb/>  He should study their sublime purpose&#44; which is&#44;<lb/> to keep us in constant com&#91;m&#93;union with our heavenly<lb/> Maker.  He should not cast false imputations<lb/> at his religion&#44; but rather palliate the short&#45;<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="10"/>
                <p>&#45;comings of his brethren&#44; and pray to God that<lb/> the bright virtues of many&#44; may hide the black<lb/> stains of a few.  The example of our father<lb/> Abraham ought to teach him that course.  He that<lb/> had ever been righteous&#44; did not disdain even to<lb/> intercede for the wicked.  Nay&#44; more&#58; the inhabitants<lb/> of the doomed cities were strangers to him&#44; and they<lb/> had been guilty of most infamous delinquencies crimes.<lb/>  So does Ezekiel describe the iniquity of Sodom.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;And they became haughty Pride&#44; satiety<lb/> abundance of idleness were in hers and in her daughters&#44;<lb/> and the hand of the poor and needy she did not streng<lb/>gthen.&#34;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  &#34;And they grew<lb/> haughty&#44; and committed abominations before me&#34;.<lb/>  Yet for them did Abraham fervently beseech the<lb/> Lord.  The law written upon the tablets of his heart&#44;<lb/> impelled him.  Had he implored that the lives<lb/> of the good might be spared&#44; he would have only<lb/> exhibited a proper sense of justice.  Had he only<lb/> supplicated for the deliverance of his nephew&#44;<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="11"/>
                <p>he would have evinced a natural but not a bene&#45;<lb/>&#45;volent feelings.  No&#44; he committed the salvation<lb/> of Lot to to Divine mercy&#44; but endeavoured to pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;pitiate it also in behalf of those who had forfeited it<lb/> by their flagitious conduct.  His noble<lb/> heart was replete with love for all mankind.<lb/>  Each throbbing of his breast was kindness and com&#45;<lb/>&#45;miseration.  The Rabbins did not exag&#91;g&#93;erate&#44; when<lb/> they wrote that the venerable presence of our patriarch&#44;<lb/> must have been in the mind of Isaiah&#44; as he was<lb/> delineating the qualities of him who shall dwell on<lb/> high&#44; namely&#44; &#34;to walk righteously&#44; and speak up&#45;<lb/>&#45;rightly&#44; to despise the gain of oppression&#44; to shake<lb/> the hand not to hold bribe&#44; to top the ear not to<lb/> hear of blood&#44; and to shut the eyes not to see evil&#34;.<lb/>  For benevolence and justice were the law which our<lb/> godly father professed&#44; and the virtues enumerated<lb/> by the inspired son of Amoz&#44; are its legitimate<lb/> offspring.  Brethren&#33; &#34;look up unto Abraham<lb/> your father&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="12"/>
                <p>He as is one of nature&#39;s noblest creations.  Strive<lb/> to copy that sublime exemplar&#44; and ye also shall also<lb/> abide upon high&#44; your spiritual eyes shall see<lb/> the King of the world in all His glory&#59; they<lb/> shall behold the land that is far off&#44; where joy happiness<lb/> reigns sof supreme &#91;Hebrew&#93;.<lb/>  And as an expression of your fraternal sentiments&#44; let me<lb/> now ask that individuals be appointed from this Congregation&#44; who may<lb/> at a general gathering discuss the merits of a project that<lb/> now occupies at present the mind of many among our fellow&#45;<lb/>believers.  I have&#44; my dear Brethren&#33; been officially<lb/> requested to urge your cooperation in establishing a<lb/> Jewish Hospital in our city.  But the subject commends<lb/> itself to your consideration.  I am not prepared to say<lb/> that the plan is feasible or its adoption expedient&#44; but whether it will<lb/> be shaped effected entirely&#44; or it will be so modified as not to entail the<lb/> large an expenditure which the support of such an institution<lb/> will demand&#44; it must be evident to all that means<lb/> ought to be provided&#44; by which a <sic>consciencious</sic> Israelite<lb/> may not be compelled to feed&#44; in the days of illness&#44;<lb/> on that which he loathed&#44; from religious scruples&#44;<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="13"/>
                <p>while in the enjoyment of health.  Give your<lb/> counsel&#44; and good will arise from the combined efforts<lb/> of the benevolent and just descendants of Abraham<lb/> our father&#44; when imbued with a spirit of benevolence<lb/> and justice.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
