<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF13_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_3_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_3_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_3_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_3_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_3_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_3_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_3_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_3_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_3_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_3_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_3_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_3_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>137</p>
            
            <p>On the death of<lb/>
                Rev Dr Adolph Huebsch<lb/>
                of New York<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>On Simchath Torah&#44; the last of our Fall<lb/> holidays&#44; I alluded in my address to a loss<lb/> which the Jewish pulpit has untimely sustained.<lb/>  The suddenness of the melancholy event had awakened in my heart<lb/> deep emotions&#44; in my heart&#44; and I&#44; following their<lb/> impulse&#44; spoke.  Few&#44; however&#44; were then my words&#44;<lb/> because neither according to the rules of our faith&#44;<lb/> nor according to the dictates of discretion&#44; it is becoming<lb/> to turn a festive day into a day of lamentations.<lb/>  But in Justice to the memory of the man&#44; whose decease<lb/> created a void difficult to fill up&#44; I promised<lb/> that I would refer again to the sorrowful subject.<lb/>  Brethren.  I hold that a congregation in Israel&#44;<lb/> having as a spiritual guide a person who is<lb/> able to draw multitudes to the synagogues&#44;<lb/> and by his oratical magnetism compel at&#45;<lb/>&#45;tention to his teachings&#44; can boast of possessing<lb/> a priceless treasure.  Wisely Rightly has it been written<lb/> that &#34;the tongue of the wise maketh know&#45;<lb/>&#45;ledge acceptable&#34;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>The Reverend Dr. Adolph Huebsch accomplished<lb/> in New York&#44; what others have rarely achieved<lb/> elsewhere.  Upon ordinary Sabbaths the<lb/> number of those who hung on the utterances of his lips&#44;<lb/> was invariably large&#44; never weening through<lb/> fictitious causes.  The secret of this enviable<lb/> popularity lay in a capacity not common<lb/> among preachers.  The Rabbi of the Ahabath<lb/> Chesed congregation reproduced in his character<lb/> what the Talmudists relate of a Rabbi of their<lb/> own times.  Abbahu could command always a throng<lb/> of listeners&#44; because he understood how to enter&#45;<lb/>&#45;tain while offering instruction.  That admirable capacity<lb/> Dr Huebsch held within his sagacious control.<lb/>  Possibly&#44; he acquired the when gift&#44; when sitting<lb/> at the feet of a preceptor&#44; whose familiarity<lb/> with post&#45;biblical learning was simply mar&#45;<lb/>&#45;vellous.  All scholars agree that Solomon Rapo&#45;<lb/>&#45;port of Prague was the prince of Rabbinical<lb/> erudition&#44; not less than a master of criticism<lb/> on Hebrew literature at large.  In him lived again<lb/> Eleazar of Mishnic ages&#44;&#45;&#45;a fountain of knowledge ever copiously flowing.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Leopold Zunz of Berlin&#44; whose ninetieth birth<lb/>day has just evoked a universal ovation in the<lb/> republic of Jewish letters&#44; is unsurpassingly<lb/> great in his researches on the origin of synago&#45;<lb/>&#45;gue rituals.  As the expounder of that branch<lb/> of sacred lore&#45;&#45;inexhuastibly rich and full of pathos&#45;&#45;<lb/> the famous nonogenarian is unrivalled&#44; but the<lb/> late Rapoport stands alone as representative<lb/> of Talmudism&#44; not pilpulism&#44; or hair splitting<lb/> disputations&#44; but as the capment nestor of a broad&#44; sound<lb/> and profound criticism.  From such a<lb/> teacher Dr Huebsch may have learned what en&#45;<lb/>&#45;abled him to diversify the subjects of his discourses<lb/> with narratives and anecdotes abounding in moral<lb/> lessons.  The preacher&#39;s acquaintance with Semitic<lb/> languages&#44; aside from the Hebrew&#44; lent him also<lb/> the facility to utilize ancient sayings and adages<lb/> among Syrians and Arabs&#44; and he did not disdain<lb/> borrowing from Greek and Latin classics to illustrate<lb/> a point &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Accept truth from whatever source it proceeds&#44;<lb/> was his motto.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>His comment on certain parts of the Peshito&#44;<lb/> or the oldest Syriac translation of the Scriptures&#44; and the<lb/> volume which he published seven years ago&#44; under<lb/> the like of &#34;Gems of the Orient&#34; prove his familiarity<lb/> with the writings of the East.  But more than in<lb/> his linguistic acquirements&#44; his congregation prided<lb/> itself in the eloquence of their Rabbi.  For the<lb/> persuasive speech struck a responsive chord&#44; which<lb/> reechoed amidst throngs that crowded the Synagogue.<lb/>  By its force many a youth was impelled vo&#45;<lb/>&#45;luntarily to come forth and aid in improving<lb/> the worship by chanting psalmody and hymns&#59;<lb/> by it many were spurred on to form a literary<lb/> association before which the Rabbi lectured with<lb/> success.  Leading journals in the metropolis<lb/> took pleasure in evinced satisfaction desire often to giveing circulation to the Rabbi&#39;s<lb/> oratical effusions&#44; and religious weeklies vied with<lb/> each other in presenting to the Jewish public<lb/> the salient points or the substance of his addresses.<lb/>  Some of my Philadelphia brethren may have read<lb/> his productions&#44; so deservedly popular&#44; because<lb/> varied in their character and edifying.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>His last sermon descriptive of the feast of<lb/> Tabernacles must notably have attracted attention<lb/> by the sentiments of reverence it breathed for<lb/> Mosaic precepts and the interpretations of Israel&#39;s<lb/> olden Sages.  The favored preacher did not<lb/> imagine that while he spoke of the Succah&#44; typic&#45;<lb/>&#45;al of the frailty and instability of this existence&#44;<lb/> his life was verging on its end&#44; and ere the festi&#45;<lb/>&#45;val had closed&#44; his eyes would be closed in death.<lb/>  The announcement that Dr Adolph Huebsch<lb/> in the meridian of his fame&#44; in the vigour of his<lb/> manhood&#44; in the fulness of his intellect was<lb/> suddenly laid felled to the ground&#44; like a sturdy oak by<lb/> a thunder bolt&#44; shocked the Hebrew community.<lb/>  Israelites of all shades of opinion grieved at<lb/> the event&#44; which created so great a void.<lb/>  They recognized in the departed high qualities.<lb/>  A sympathetic nature which prompted him to<lb/> bestow special care on the religious education of<lb/> children&#44; attending personally to the afternoon Sab&#45;<lb/>&#45;bath services in the interest of children the young&#44; and<lb/> supervising a numerously frequented Sunday school.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Israelites had discovered in the gifted preacher<lb/> a genial temperament which led him to respond to<lb/> the demands made upon his time&#44; lecturing before<lb/> associations promotive of learning&#44; and visiting those<lb/> who stood in need of pastoral advice and and promoting domestic and social harmony.<lb/>  Brethren.  I repeat now in all candor what I assert&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed when I last spoke.  My mind could not ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;prove of the course which the Rev. Dr Huebsch<lb/> followed in his government of the Synagogue&#44; and more<lb/> than once I took exception at the construction he put<lb/> on written and oral laws.  But being obliged&#44;<lb/> in the absence of an intimate intercourse and being necessarily compelled to judge<lb/> from current report&#44; and inferring from the repu&#45;<lb/>&#45;tation enjoyed that the my deceased colleague<lb/> was not disloyal to historical Judaism&#44; but rather<lb/> sought to uphold it&#44; I have deemed it him<lb/> worthy of a eulogy&#44; and I have pronounced it in<lb/> this house of our God.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> The &#34;Praise is becometh the upright.&#34;  Yet&#44; I confess<lb/> again&#44; I might have remained altogether silent&#44; but for recent events.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>I specially particularly consider the departed deserving of com&#45;<lb/>&#45;mendation because of a series of articles which ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;peared last summer&#44; and in which he determinedly<lb/> opposed a destructive theory.  It has been contended<lb/> by some un&#45;Jewish ministers that in the hope&#45;&#45;vain hope&#45;&#45;of<lb/> preserving to our faith the offspring of mixed mar&#45;<lb/>&#45;riages&#44; Rabbis ought to sanctify a matrimonial<lb/> alliance between Hebrews and non&#45;Israelites.  Dr<lb/> Huebsch controverted that suicidal doctrine with a<lb/> cogency of reasoning which made the changelings stagger.<lb/>  I on seeing that&#44; on seeing how young unfledged<lb/> would be masters constantly arise&#45;&#45;young foxes I call them<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#45;&#45;in <sic>Bibblical</sic> language&#45;&#45;young foxes laying waste the<lb/> vineyard of the Lord&#44; I who tremble at the ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;proaching rain of my inherited belief&#44; rejoiced that<lb/> one who commanded wide popularity for his<lb/> eloquence and erudition&#44; exposed the hollowness<lb/> of f arguments as fallacious as they are sub&#45;<lb/>&#45;versive of our dearest interests.  My fervent<lb/> prayer now is for the spiritual future of<lb/> the Congregation bereft of a guide in whom it<lb/> confided.  The honored dead kept it within scriptural bounds.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>During the eighteen years of his pastorship&#44; his<lb/> flock did not break through the ancient fold<lb/> to go astray among fields&#44; which hide virulent poi&#45;<lb/>&#45;son under a smiling surface.  I never heard that<lb/> Dr Huebsch sanctioned a departure from the Sinaic be&#45;<lb/>&#45;hests.  But men who may be <sic>covetting</sic> for a<lb/> vacant position&#44; lucrative and influential&#44; in a body<lb/> that is numerous and wealthy&#59; men of broad ambitions<lb/> but narrow consciences&#44; are impregnated with doctrines<lb/> anti&#45;Judaic&#44; with principles which&#45;&#45;unless the Sa&#45;<lb/>&#45;viour of Israel interposes His help&#45;&#45;will lay Mono&#45;<lb/>&#45;theism prostrate at the feet of Trinitarianism.<lb/>  Witness the pertinacious attempt to transfer the<lb/> holy day of the Decalogue to Sunday&#44; witness the<lb/> audacious endeavour to tear aw out the last object<lb/> of universal veneration in Biblical ceremonialism ritualism<lb/> by declaring the day of atonement abolished.<lb/>  Thus Sabbaths and festivals carried over to the<lb/> Church&#44; dietary laws and marriage laws brought<lb/> down to the level of Christendom&#44; there will be left<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>nought but blatant sermonizers indulging in<lb/> platitudes about the mission of Judaism which<lb/> is no longer Judaism to cater to the depraved taste of Jews<lb/> who are Christianized.  May he whom God has<lb/> early taken hence&#44; avert misfortune by suppli&#45;<lb/>&#45;cations.  May he win the Grace of heaven&#44;<lb/> and become upon earth an invisible angel to those<lb/> over whom he ministered&#44; that they may not<lb/> exchange his teaching for the lessons of perversion.<lb/>  May the servant of our faith now clothed<lb/> in immortality&#44; contemplate from above the regions of bliss the<lb/> real progress of Israel in this country of their dwelling&#44;<lb/> and feel beatifically elevated.  And may<lb/> in all who mourn because of his departure<lb/> from among the living be fulfilled the prophet<lb/>&#45;ic promise given unto Zion.  &#34;Radiant joy<lb/> they shall have instead of sackcloth and ashes&#44;<lb/> sweet aroma instead of grief&#44; a robe of honor<lb/> instead of dejection.  They shall be strong in<lb/> righteousness&#44; they shall be as a plant of<lb/> the Lord&#44; by whose growth He will be Sanct&#45; glorified<lb/> &#45;fied.&#34;  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
