<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF11_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_2_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_2_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_2_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>On Haftorath Bo&#44;<lb/>
                Explanatory<lb/></p>
            
            <p>I introduced some additions&#44; notably about Pharaoh<lb/> Nicho&#39;s attempt to cut a canal across the isthmus<lb/> of Suez &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  The section from the Prophets which<lb/> we have read this morning&#44; bears strong resem&#45;<lb/>&#45;blance to that of last Sabbath.  Both des&#45;<lb/>&#45;cribe the final overthrow of Egypt&#45;&#45;the proud<lb/> kingdom&#44; as it still was towards the close of our<lb/> national existence first commonwealth&#44; when Pharaoh &#91;&#63;&#93; Necho resigned&#44; before the seventy years of<lb/> the Babylonian captivity.  The authors of<lb/> those inspired writings&#44; belonged to the same<lb/> tribe&#44; and spoke at about the same period.<lb/>  Claiming descent from Aaron&#44; they may have worn the ephod &#38;<lb/> ministered at God&#39;s altar in Jerusalem&#44; but<lb/> they lived to lament its destruction by the all conquering armies<lb/> of the Chaldeans.  Jeremiah&#45;&#45;a priest from<lb/> the city of Anathoth&#44; and Ezekiel a priest<lb/> transported by the conqueror of Judea victor to the<lb/> land of the stranger&#44; denounced national wrongs in high places&#44;<lb/> prevalent in their days&#44; and deplored the disastrous<lb/> effects of national sins.  But like a father&#39;s<lb/> chastening of his children&#44; so did those loving tea&#45; mentors<lb/> &#45;chers&#44; while reproving to improve&#44; appealed to the<lb/> heart&#59; they blended admonition with commiseration&#44;<lb/></p> 
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>kindled a hope of Divine mercy&#44; and of a<lb/> brighter future attending a return to freedom and<lb/> independence.  Illumined by a heavenly<lb/> light&#44; they foresaw events yet unfolded&#44; and<lb/> pointed out the rain of peoples that had betrayed<lb/> Israel&#39;s confidence and profited of our downfall to afflicted our race.<lb/>  But the analogy which we discover between Jeremiah and Ezekiel<lb/> in some of their prophecies&#44; is not traceable<lb/> in the history and character of those two prea&#45;<lb/>&#45;chers of old.  Ezekiel wl was born in Pa&#45;<lb/>&#45;lestine&#44; but having been carried away from thence<lb/> early in life&#44; he wrote his impassioned orations in a<lb/> foreign country and in riper years.  From the<lb/> banks of the Cheba in Mesopotamia&#44; he stretched<lb/> his vision to across the plains watered by the Jordan&#44; and<lb/> gave forth utterances of not uncertain sound.  Bold<lb/> and nervous and thrilling was the language of the Seer of<lb/> the exile&#44; but it was like that of one who himself has not<lb/> personally felt the rod of oppression&#59; of one who abides in compa&#45;<lb/>&#45;rative ease&#44; unexposed to daily suffering from<lb/> social or political agitations &#38; from bitter the persecution of bitter foes. foes  For dwelling among the colonists who<lb/> had settled in Babylon&#44; he Ezekiel did not feared not the resent&#45;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>&#45;ment of men from afar&#44; whom he prophetically<lb/> scourged.<lb/></p>
            <p>Jeremiah&#44; was almost a lad&#44; when&#44; walking the<lb/> streets of Jerusalem&#44; was stirred by a heavenly fire<lb/> that let all his whole soul all aglow.  The man of destiny&#44;<lb/> called to <sic>fortell</sic> disasters calamities and bewail national misery<lb/> was he.  In vain he raised his clarion voice&#44; and warned wicked rulers of evils&#44;<lb/> fast coming approaching.  He beheld the waning of Judah&#39;s<lb/> power&#44; the disgrace of his country&#44; and&#44; like fount&#45;<lb/>&#45;ains of tears&#44; his w eyes wept over the sacred<lb/> oracle wrapped in devouring flames.  his plaint&#45;<lb/>&#45;ive strains resounded over echoed forth amidst the ruins desolation of the country land&#44; which<lb/> he loved so well.  And even after Nebuzaradan&#44;<lb/> the Babylonian Chief&#44; allowed the man of sorrow<lb/> to remain in Judea with a small remnant residue<lb/> of his brethren&#44; the zeal which impelled him<lb/> to exhort upbraid and to exhort and urge submission<lb/> to God&#39;s decree&#44; made the prophet a target<lb/> to the barbed arrows of his adversaries.  When<lb/> Gedaliah&#44; chosen by the conqueror to govern a residue small remnant<lb/> of Israelites in Judea Palestine was barbarously murdered&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Johanon son of Kareah and his partisans<lb/> tore the man of God from the spot where<lb/> he had hoped wished to die amidst the relics of a<lb/> grand historic past&#44; and dragged him to Egypt&#44; the<lb/> treacherous land against which he had raised<lb/> a voice of condemnation.  But though Jeremiah<lb/> unlike Ezekiel drank to the dregs the cup of misery&#59; though<lb/> he was struck and wounded for his denunciation<lb/> of sin&#44; though he was imprisoned and fettered&#44;<lb/> cast into a miry pit and publicly reviled&#44;<lb/> he never faltered&#44; never not once did he wavered in his mission.<lb/>  H Undauntedly he proclaimed the will of his<lb/> Master&#44; and&#44; while applying a restorative balm<lb/> to such as believed in the Almighty arbiter of human affairs&#44; he inveighed against trans&#45; the<lb/> &#45;gressors rebellious&#44; regardless of their condition station and state wealth.<lb/>  The Sages of Israel held our sacerdotal Seer<lb/> in so high an estimation regard&#44; that they drew a<lb/> parallel between him and the son of Amram.<lb/>  Commenting on the passage of Deuteronomy&#44;<lb/> in which God&#39;s promise to raise a prophet like<lb/> Moses&#44; is recorded&#44; the Talmudists say that the per&#45;<lb/>&#45;sonage foreshadowed was none other than Jeremiah.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>For the latter like his great predecessor prophesied<lb/> during forty years&#59; both addressed themselves directly<lb/> to the nation at large&#44; both met with violent op&#45;<lb/>&#45;position at the hands of their Own kindred&#45;&#45;Moses<lb/> was charged with an undue arrogation of power<lb/> by his cousin Korah and his adherents who tried to<lb/> stir up a revolt&#59; Jeremiah was hunted down by<lb/> the priests of &#91;&#63;&#93;&#44; who devised to kill him<lb/> by a conspiracy.  And the comparison is continued at<lb/> length by the in Talmudist legendary to show how he who led<lb/> our frathers out of slavery and his successor who<lb/> saw them carried into slavery&#44; preached the sacredness of<lb/> the Sabbath&#44; the evils following its profanation&#44; the<lb/> dispersion of the tribes and their restoration by repent&#45;<lb/>&#45;ance.  Having premised these<lb/> historical remarks&#44; I will offer some explanation of on<lb/> the purport of our Haftorah which suggested them to my mind.  Egypt had<lb/> been struggling hard to retain possession of Car&#45;<lb/>&#45;chemish&#44; a city of geographical importance lying on the Euphrates and<lb/> seized by the Chaldeans&#44; that like a hurricane<lb/> swept every thing before them.  The writer<lb/> carried borne aloft on the wings of inspiration&#44; imagines<lb/></p> 
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>to that he is addressing a congress of nations.  He bids them quietly<lb/> go and tell announce to the haughty land of the Pharaohs<lb/> her impending danger&#59; &#38; invite her to summon up<lb/> courage and try strive to blunt the sword which had<lb/> already made surrounding countries desolate.<lb/>  But knowing the futility of any attempt to<lb/> resistance&#59; certain that victory will perch on<lb/> the standard of the invincible Nebuchadnezzar&#44; he<lb/> taunts Egypt and asks&#58; &#34;Why were the heroes of<lb/> many battles put to a hasty flight&#63;  Why<lb/> did they not bravely face the rude invader&#63;  Oh<lb/> the breath of God scattered them the braggarts like chaff.&#34;<lb/>  For an avenging Lord spread a panic among the<lb/> combatants&#44; so that and they slew one another.  The<lb/> dread occasioned by the Babylonian army was so<lb/> general widespread&#44; that foreigners who swelled the ranks<lb/> of the Egyptians exclaimed&#58; &#34;Let us fall back flee&#44;<lb/> let us return hurry back to our native places&#44; let us<lb/> lest all means of retreat be cut off.  For Pharaoh who<lb/> had raised such a storm by the renown<lb/> of his prowess has cowardly avoided shunned the deadly conflict.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>But as sure as mount Tabor stands immove&#45;<lb/>&#45;ably&#44; and as Carmel is firmly set on the<lb/> Mediterranean sea&#44; so sure it is that the<lb/> Lord of hosts has resolved to stir up incite Chaldea<lb/> against Mizraim.  Then the prophet beholds<lb/> the approaching coming doom of the country once so<lb/> formidable&#59; he sees the chains of captivity forged&#59;<lb/> Noph&#45;&#45;or Memphis&#44; the city of whose beauty<lb/> kings had boasted&#44; is reduced to ashes&#59; an<lb/> aristocracy compared to a pampered heifer&#44;<lb/> ar brought to the shambles together with the<lb/> fattened calves&#44; or the well richly paid adventurers that<lb/> swelled the ranks of the had entered the enlisted in the fighting armies.  The<lb/> steel which has been furbished in the North<lb/> will pitilessly slaughters them all.  He hears the<lb/> shrieks&#44; but the piercing cry will not read the<lb/> veil which iniquities have raised between Egypt<lb/> and the heavens&#44; for God will visits upon it the<lb/> treachery practised against his nation chosen people.  Temples<lb/> dedicated to falsities will lay waste&#44; the worship<lb/> of Jupiter Apen Amon&#44; which&#44; as the supreme deity<lb/> of the Egyptians was placed set up high in No&#44; a famous city<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>called by the Greeks Thebes&#44; is will be is mocked and<lb/> jeered at &#38; abolished.  Like Ezekiel&#44; his contemporary&#44;<lb/> Jeremiah predicts the restorative of Egypt.  He<lb/> does not designate the exact time when the event<lb/> would be consummated&#44; but by the Haftorah of last<lb/> Sabbath&#44; we learn that after the lapse of forty years&#44;<lb/> her exiles would revisit the country of their birth&#44; still<lb/> never again to hold sway under the flag of inde&#45;<lb/>&#45;pendence&#59; for as we read in Ezekiel &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;A prince out of the land of Egypt will<lb/> be no more&#34;.  Study&#44; my brethren the annals<lb/> of that ancient people&#59; consider well her its vicissitudes<lb/> and notice Babylon followed by Persia&#44; and this by<lb/> Macedonia&#44; and the latter by Greece&#44; look at the<lb/> Neo&#45;Persians and the Romans&#44; and the Arabs Saracenes&#44; and<lb/> Mamabukes and Turks mastering in turn the country<lb/> on the Nile&#44; and mark it well down&#59; the vision of our<lb/> prophets remains irrefutably true&#44; &#34;a prince out of the land of Egypt<lb/> will be no more.&#34;  But like the prophet on the<lb/> river Chebar&#44; who closes his predictions with a consolatory<lb/> promise to sorrow&#45;stricken Israel&#44; even so&#44; nay with<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>more pathos&#44; does the plaintive bard of our nation&#44; call upon his<lb/> brethren&#44; who had been forced with him into Egyptian captivity and the whole house of Israel&#44; to stretch<lb/> their looks and let them rest on a happy future reserved by the Supreme<lb/> Ruler of human events.  Though exposed to the consuming fire of an ene&#45; gentile<lb/> &#45;my&#39;s hatred&#44; they were indestructible.  The flames by which Divine Justice<lb/> sought to purify their souls&#44; would devour the existence of nations who realms in which they are mal&#45;<lb/>&#45;treated. them &#91;Hebrew&#93; Neither the Pharaohs&#44; nor the monarchs who sat upon the<lb/> thrones of the East&#44; would be counted among the living&#44; when the seed<lb/> of Jacob became free of inimical yoke.  So concludes&#44; the vision of<lb/> Jeremiah presented by the section of this Sabbath.  Many&#44; very many<lb/> centuries have sunk into eternity since the memorable words we have<lb/> read were uttered&#44; but the countless circumstances which befell man&#45;<lb/>&#45;kind&#44; have not belied the declaration of the priest of Anatholh.  Yes&#44;<lb/> the Eternal has made an end of tyrants who vowed our extermination.  He suffered them to reach<lb/> the apex climax of greatness&#44; but only to crush them by the hig height whence<lb/> they fell.  Fear not&#44; I will exclaim&#44; like Jeremiah&#44; be not dismayed<lb/> because Teutonic or Slavonic despots weigh yet down&#44; my brethren in faith of Roumenia &#38; Russia.  The<lb/> nights without down through which we have passed&#44; have given<lb/> room to a light brightening our horizon.  Observe the unceasing<lb/> changes which the world undergoes&#59; out of them the God of our fathers<lb/> will work out a complete redemption only keep Bo faithful&#44; and be worthy of the salvation&#44; for it is written&#44; Judah shall dwell safely&#44; and<lb/> Israel shall abide in the <sic>tranquillity</sic> by the help of God for evermore.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>Why shall I fatigue my hearers with illustrations from Moses<lb/> whose undimmed vision foresaw the wide&#45;spread dispersion of<lb/> the tribes&#44; to Micah Ben Judah who knew the issue of the battle at Ramoth<lb/> Gilead ere it was fought&#44; and where the iniquitous Ahab would<lb/> surely die&#59; or from Isaiah who reassured the Kingdom of Judah by predict&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing the disruption of the alliance between the kingdom of Israel &#38; Syria&#44; to<lb/> Amos who told the priest Amaziah the royal flatterer&#44; that he would be buried in the<lb/> land of the stranger.<lb/>  Egypt furnishes a bright illustration&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>by recent utterances&#44; aiming to disprove in Jewish prophets the power<lb/> of forthcoming events frequent with mighty consequences in the political<lb/> world.  Let me admit at once that the Hebrew Nabi does not ne&#45;<lb/>&#45;cessarily imply the thought of revealing in advance of time what the<lb/> future hides in its bosom&#44; but to deny that our Nebiim have pictured<lb/> with amazing precision what the human mind&#44; unaided by inspi&#45;<lb/>&#45;ration&#44; could never have imagined possible&#44; would be to set up<lb/> one&#39;s judgment against the infallible testimony of history.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
