<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF2_11</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1876" source="" attested="yes">1876</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_11_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_11_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_11_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_11_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_11_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_11_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_11_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_11_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_11_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_11_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_11_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_11_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_11_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_11_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_11_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_11_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For the 16th anniversary of the<lb/>
                7th st Synagogue<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  In the days of Jeremiah the political condition<lb/> of Israel was deplorable.  Corruption had engendered effeme&#45;<lb/>&#45;nancy&#44; and this invited the stranger to set his iron heel over<lb/> the neck of the powerless.  Yet people fancied themselves in<lb/> a state of perfect security.  The air rung again with the<lb/> clang of advancing armies&#44; but our ancestors saw no thing to<lb/> fear.  The ground they trod sunk almost beneath their steps&#44;<lb/> but to them it felt as firm as the everlasting hills.  Why<lb/> so much hardihood&#63;  Whence the origin of such audaciousness&#63;<lb/>  Listen&#44; my friends&#33;  At that period of our history&#44; men existed<lb/> who styled themselves prophets.  Flattery was the trade they<lb/> plied with marked success.  They earned popularity by<lb/> disposing at a cheap rate of that which all delight to<lb/> procure.  They hoodwinked society into a state of self&#45;com&#45;<lb/>&#45;placence&#44; into the pleasing assurance that they possessed<lb/> a power &#91;&#63;&#93;able.  But those time&#45;serving sycophants<lb/> could not so le lull into security the servant of God.  He<lb/> saw the peril which they would hide&#59; and sounded the<lb/> tocsin.  &#34;Destruction is looming high.  It approaches from<lb/> the North&#44; swiftly as a whirlwind&#44;&#34; he exclaimed.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>But the people from whom he sought to avert a<lb/> mis calamity&#44; branded him as a traitor.  A royal officer<lb/> struck him for his boldness.  He was cast into prison&#44; fo to<lb/> atone for having dared to contradict the prophets in their<lb/> honeyed predictions.  Thus buffetted and contemned&#44; the<lb/> priest of Anatholle would have forcibly held back the<lb/> sentiments&#44; which drew towards him universal ill&#45;will&#59;<lb/> but the heart refused obedience.  It was in an hour of<lb/> deep depression&#44; when after having suffered public indignities<lb/> that he gave utterance to these sentences.  &#34;Thou O Lord&#33; hast<lb/> persuaded me&#44; and I was persuaded&#59; Thou layest strongly a<lb/> hand upon me and didst prevail.  But I am laughed at all<lb/> time&#44; everyone mocketh me.  for&#44; as often as I cry out&#44;<lb/> ruin and wasting I must proclaim&#59; but the word of the<lb/> Lord hath become unto me a disgrace and derision.  Then I<lb/> said&#44; I will not make mention of Him&#59; I will not speak<lb/> any more in His name&#59; but the word of the Lord was<lb/> like a burning fire within my heart&#44; shut up in my bones&#59;<lb/> I was weary with enduring&#44; I could not overcome it.&#34;<lb/>  Dear Brethren&#33;  It is far from my thoughts to institute<lb/> a comparison&#44; which would naturally savor of presumption.<lb/>  I have directed your attention to the circumstance in Holy Writ<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>just narrated&#44; because it bears&#44; in a slight degree&#44; some<lb/> likeness to that in which I have been placed.  Were I to<lb/> study my temporal welfare&#44; that is&#44; the obtaining of<lb/> general favor&#44; which keeps the spirits buoyant&#44; and imparts<lb/> elasticity to the mind&#44; I would&#44; long since&#44; have made com&#45;<lb/>&#45;mon cause with those Israelites who shout &#34;He all hail to<lb/> the religious progress of the time&#34;; and this Sabbath&#44; the<lb/> es sixteenth anniversary of the dedication of our Synagogue&#44;<lb/> I might win golden opinions by a glowing description of the<lb/> rapid strides we had taken in the way of light.  But in<lb/> the same manner as an ancient teacher of our people could<lb/> not <sic>yeild</sic> to a pressure&#44; which very nigh crushed him&#44; be&#45;<lb/>&#45;cause duty asserted its supremacy within his breast&#59; and<lb/> as he arse arose singly against in opposition to a multitude&#44; because<lb/> truth was more precious unto him than even a tranquil<lb/> life&#44; so must I submit to rebuffs&#59; and so must I con&#45;<lb/>&#45;tinue to proclaim what is right&#44; as God has given me to<lb/> understand the right&#44; though distasteful and unpopular.<lb/>  I must proclaim it&#44; not with the view of provoking dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;pleasure&#44; but always with the intention of responding to the<lb/> dictates<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>of conscience.  For&#44; I have not been am able&#44; my friends&#33;<lb/> to perceive what others imagine to have discovered&#44; greatly<lb/> to the gratification of the Jewish community.  In their<lb/> judgment&#44; Judaism is now in America fresher and sounder<lb/> than it has ever been.  They see it grow vigorous&#44; strike<lb/> deep root&#44; and put on a rich vesture of foliage&#44; in<lb/> proportion as it is lopped off.  Unsparingly has indeed<lb/> the pruning&#45;hook been used&#44; but where are the evidences<lb/> of the overshadowing height attained by the Judaic tree&#63;<lb/>  &#34;In the attendance at the divine worship&#34; I am answered.<lb/>  Well&#58; I give my religion a wider scope than that assigned<lb/> to it by a vast number of my fellow&#45;believers.  I do not<lb/> confine its workings  within four walls&#44; however spacious and<lb/> lofty.  I look for its operations in the standard of<lb/> public morality&#44; in the homes of piety&#44; in the schools of<lb/> sacred learning.  But conceding that a throng at the house<lb/> of prayer does prove the vitality of our faith&#59; can you<lb/> point out among the nine synagogues in Philadelphia<lb/> ans to speak of what can be under our immediate ins&#45;<lb/>&#45;pection&#45;&#45;can you point out any&#44; save one&#44; which exhibits<lb/> that gratifying sight&#63;  Yet&#44; few have withheld their<lb/> hands from cutting off and clipping.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Not alone ours is shunned&#44; by reason of appearing in an<lb/> old dress&#44; but some whose service has been arrayed in a<lb/> brand new and quite stylish garb fail to attract.  No&#58;<lb/> Judaism hav does not evince that vigour claimed for it by the<lb/> prophets of the land.  It discloses&#44; on the contrary&#44; symptoms<lb/> of decay&#44; and them I detect in the spot said to be the<lb/> seat of its power.  For in the largest place of worship&#44; a<lb/> boasting of being attached to the este extremist wing of li&#45;<lb/>&#45;berality&#44; the impious design has been concocted to sacrifice<lb/> the Sabbath upon the altar of a modern Molock&#45;reform.<lb/>  Progress&#44; forsooth&#59; when men of our people meet&#44; and a<lb/> father arises and proposes the hallowing of the first day<lb/> of the week&#44; instead of the seventh&#44; lest his children<lb/> learnt at the Synagogue&#44; to call sacred what he profanes.<lb/>  If that is progress&#44; let us step backwards till we reach<lb/> the confines of darkness.  Better to abide in obscurity&#44;<lb/> than to be thought enlightened for parting with a heavenly<lb/> trust.  But are they&#44; who have determined to surrender<lb/> it&#44; certain that they will have thus broken down the<lb/> throng hedge raised between us and gentilism&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Nothing short of a complete abjuration will place<lb/> them socially on a level with the Nazarene citizens of<lb/> the land&#44; even in the minds of individuals supposed to be<lb/> imbued with enlarged ideas.  As Israelites&#44; they will be totally ignored&#44; when questions of great moment arise.<lb/>  Witness it&#44; the language of a Judge&#44; who has repeatedly<lb/> and with all emphasis told us&#44; that this country is supremely<lb/> the property of a Christian people&#59; that the United States govern&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment must be guided by Christian rules&#44; and that to<lb/> protect Christian rights all hands must join together.<lb/>  False teachers may assure those unwary Hebrews that the<lb/> Messianic predictions have all been already fulfilled&#59; that<lb/> their realization is resplendently seen in the cities of America&#44;<lb/> that here the wolf dwells with the lamb&#44; and the leopard<lb/> lies down with the kid.  Would be prophets mayy lull<lb/> such into a state of security&#44; but they who study the interests<lb/> of their brethren will manifest their misgivings at<lb/> the persistent efforts to <sic>ostracise</sic> whosoever does not worship<lb/> within the pale of the church&#59; they will not postpone<lb/> truth to popularity&#44; but at the risk of meeting with<lb/> contumely will they raise the voice of warning&#44; and preach<lb/> that the salvation of Israel proceeds from the Lord&#59; that<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>to abandon Him&#44; and truckle with worldly policy<lb/> is to call down celestial wroth&#44; and put into the hands of<lb/> our religious opponents aggressive arms.  They will denounce<lb/> the son of arrogance&#44; which is the forerunner of a downfall&#44;<lb/> and to ward off the latter&#44; they will urge a return to a f life<lb/> conformable with the tenets of the inspired books.<lb/>  Dear hearers&#33;  I have said that Judaism has gained nothing<lb/> from the system inaugurated by aspirants to the plaudits<lb/> of an unthinking multitude.  Not a grain more of pu&#45;<lb/>&#45;blic esteem&#44; not a little more of spirituality in our<lb/> composition character.  But that Judaism has lost mate&#45;<lb/>&#45;rially by it&#44; the few who have remained staunch can<lb/> with one voice attest.  For whereas formerly the families<lb/> who did not live up to the dietary co laws of Moses could<lb/> be reckoned&#44; now their name is Cegun&#44; and so rife is the<lb/> dereliction&#44; that it has ceased altogether to excite comment.<lb/>  But the Synagogue&#44; the Synagogue&#44; considered the heart&#44;<lb/> whose every throb is to send a flow of invigorating blood<lb/> through our national body&#44; has it kept fresh and spring&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing&#63;  Alas&#33;  <sic>Langor</sic> overspreads it.  Stagnation steals<lb/> over it.  The appliances of modern doctors have mostly<lb/> failed to revive its waning powers.  One remedy alone<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>can stay the hand of death.  Let me tell it plainly.<lb/>  The observance of the Sabbath.  With it permissible changes<lb/> with the view object of to adding solemnity to the service&#44; and increaseing<lb/> the general interest may jointly be effected.  Without it&#44;<lb/> not the fullest consent to the caprices of the changelings&#44;<lb/> will avert the doom which is hanging over many a<lb/> habitation of prayer.  That I lament what on the spec&#45;<lb/>&#45;tacle which ours weekly presents&#44; those who judge<lb/> rightly will believe.  For&#44; aside from the spiritual view<lb/> of the subject&#44; the habitual absence of the largest number<lb/> of my congregation&#44; paralyzes my energy&#44; and breeds<lb/> the harrowing thought that I have been left&#44; after<lb/> all&#44; as a parasitical plant in the field of my religion.<lb/>  Brethren&#33;  When sixteen years ago I stood at this sacred<lb/> desk&#44; and invoked God&#39;s choicest benedictions upon the<lb/> building we raised in honor to His name&#44; a generation was<lb/> then rising that gave promise to have become the sus&#45;<lb/>taining pillars of our sanctuary&#44; the upholders of its<lb/> worship.  Have the children&#44; who inspired me with<lb/> confidence&#44; torn away from their minds the memory<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>of the spot&#44; when grown to manhood&#63;  Have they all<lb/> forgotten the hallowed edifice they were wont to enter with<lb/> light steps and leaping hearts&#59; the oracle before which<lb/> they avowed themselves the adherents of the Sinai covenant&#44;<lb/> the missionaries of the Lord&#63;  Oh&#33; deprive me not of the<lb/> satisfaction to believe that not all have erased from the<lb/> tablets of their hearts the Synagogue&#44; where their parents<lb/> <sic>worshipped</sic>&#44; and they were wont to join in psalmody<lb/> in the days of their innocence.  Let me believe that<lb/> they will not suffer its courts to be deserted&#44; and its treasury<lb/> exhausted&#59; that they will be enkindled anew with the<lb/> fire of zeal&#44; and show it aglow ablaze within these consecrated<lb/> precincts.  And Thou O God of Israel send us<lb/> Thy help from the place of Thy habitation&#44; uplift us from<lb/> lowliness.  Cause us to sing Thy salvation&#44; that we may<lb/> unfold here in the standard of Thy truths.  Let others<lb/> boast of their spires and of their turrets&#44; we shall praise<lb/> ourselves in Thy holy name.  O Lord&#33; deliver thy faithful&#44;<lb/> bless this portion of Thy inheritance&#44; govern guide them and<lb/> exalt then now and evermore.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
