<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF18_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff18_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff18_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff18_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff18_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff18_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff18_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff18_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff18_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff18_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff18_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff18_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff18_1_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff18_1_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff18_1_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff18_1_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff18_1_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>On Parashat Pekud&#233;<lb/>
                descriptive of the beauty of the Book<lb/>
                of Psalms&#44; &#38;<lb/>
                allusive to the character of Zecharias Frankel<lb/></p>
            
            <p>It was altered&#44; lengthened&#44; and corrected<lb/>
                in 1876<lb/></p>
            
            <p>135</p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#34;Moses saw all the work&#44; and behold the children of Israel&#44;<lb/> did it as the Lord had commanded&#44; and Moses blessed them.&#34;<lb/>  The men and women engaged in a holy task&#44; showed rare<lb/> skill and zealousness.  She that woved the finest texture<lb/> and plied the needle to produce rich embroideries&#44; vied with<lb/> him&#44; who set sparkling jewels in gold&#44; and <sic>chilselled</sic> the<lb/> most superb engravings.  They that could compound<lb/> spices to create the sweet perfume of the incense and<lb/> prepare the precious ointment that consecrated priesthood&#44;<lb/> <sic>rivalled</sic> their brethren&#44; from whose hands issued forth<lb/> robes and curtains dyed in bright purple and scarlet.<lb/>  Artists2 and artisans1&#44; both the Hebrew who struck<lb/> the anvil&#44; and his neighbor that drew <sic>marvellous</sic> de&#45;<lb/>signs&#44; had devoted time and the valuable knowledge<lb/> acquired for the completion of the Tabernacle of the Lord.<lb/>  And the munificence of their gifts had <sic>equalled</sic> the generous<lb/> bestowal of their abilities.  The godly shepherd of the tribes<lb/> saw that lavishing of means on a righteous cause.  He<lb/> beheld his sisters in faith&#44; throng the camp to offer<lb/> the plates of polished copper that had served them as mir&#45;<lb/>&#45;rors&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>he beheld the whole congregation exalt that<lb/> by their united efforts a structure would be raised in honor<lb/> of their living Redeemer and he called down on their heads<lb/> a blessing.  He prayed &#40;so teaches tradition&#41; that the<lb/> favor of the Divinity to His chosen people&#44; might become<lb/> visible through the labor accomplished.  And joyful Israel<lb/> repeated after the meek suppliants&#44; &#34;Oh may the grace<lb/> of the Lord our God rest upon us&#59; establish Thou the<lb/> work of our hands&#59; yea&#44; the work of our hands establish<lb/> Thou it&#34;.  A fitting response&#44; my dear hearers&#33; to a<lb/> soul&#45;stirring invocation.  And we&#44; the descendants of<lb/> the men who gave utterance to that response&#44; greet with<lb/> it our working days at the conclusion of the divinely<lb/> instituted Sabbath.  The arch&#45;prophet Thus our ancestors taught us so<lb/> to signify our dependence on the Almighty for the<lb/> success of our weekly undertakings....In the 90th<lb/> Psalm&#44; which concludes with that edifying sentence&#44; Moses<lb/> contrasts the eternity of the Being who ruled supreme<lb/> before the mountains were brought forth&#44; and our fleeting<lb/> existence.  He compares human life to a slumber.<lb/>  We lie down&#59; we sleep&#59; suddenly wake.  Have so<lb/> many hours glided away&#63;  It can scarcely be realized.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>But if we stir ourselves up to duty&#44; If we learn to reckon<lb/> those vanishing hours&#44; so as to control them and direct<lb/> them wisely&#59; then the Author of time will lengthen them<lb/> endlessly by the memorial of goods deeds performed.<lb/>  So does the inspired son of Amram speak admonishingly<lb/> in his psalmodic effusion.  Would&#44; my fellow&#45;be&#45;<lb/>&#45;lievers&#44; that we accustomed ourselves to read intelligently<lb/> the outpourings of our psalmists.  What an inexhaustible<lb/> source of instruction they do open&#33;  What a fountain of<lb/> spiritual delight&#33;  They are truly&#44; as called in the<lb/> sacred tongue&#44; &#34;Tehilim&#34;&#44; devotional hymns to extol<lb/> the Most High&#33;  By them is the human soul represented<lb/> as communing with its Maker.  Nothing is more admi&#45;<lb/>&#45;rably adapted for that intercourse between the creature<lb/> and his Creator.  Have we been prosperous in our<lb/> endeavours&#63;  Let us unfold the pages of that book&#44;<lb/> and words suggestive of a deep&#45;felt thanksgiving&#44;<lb/> which we may rehearse with unction&#44; will be met pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;fusely.  &#91;Hebrew&#93; Are we distressed&#63;  That volumes prof&#91;f&#93;ers<lb/> a soothing balm for our heart&#39;s bleeding wounds.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>It teems with sentiments of confiding trust in God.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> By it are we raised above human fear to the Rock<lb/> of our refuge&#59; the stronghold of Jacob &#91;Hebrew&#93; And<lb/> unto the penitent sinner&#33;  To him that yearns for the<lb/> Lord he has offended&#44; what writing can like that speak<lb/> so encouragingly&#44; inviting him to seek the Parent of<lb/> mercy&#44; the Lord of forgiveness&#63;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  In all the events<lb/> experienced domestically or socially&#44; during this transient<lb/> existence&#44; we will find in that matchless compilation&#44;<lb/> passages or entire psalms suiting the state of our<lb/> feelings&#44; and affording us&#44; by a recital&#44; relief to our pains&#44;<lb/> and additional gladness to our pleasurable emotions.<lb/>  Could we&#44; my dear hearers&#33; summon together the mortals&#44;<lb/> whose sorrows were assuaged&#44; and f whose joys enhanced<lb/> by the praises of our David and his brother psalmists to<lb/> the Dweller of heaven&#44; this would exceed all reckoning.<lb/>  To the ancient tribes in the patriarchal land&#44; that Psalter<lb/> supplied a divine service during the festive gatherings &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> and in the choral songs of every day&#39;s worship by the<lb/> Levites.  In exile&#44; the remnant of Judah carried it<lb/> in their memories&#59; its consolatory words tempered<lb/> the bitterness of the captivity &#91;Hebrew&#93; Nay&#59; the persecutors<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>borrowed form the persecuted&#44; and retained a book from<lb/> which they learned how to pray.  Even now it forms<lb/> the main feature of gentile rituals.  Our neighbours<lb/> who reject the belief we inherited&#44; gladly appropriate<lb/> to themselves what our Asaph and Jeduthim and<lb/> Ethan&#44; and Keman have written.  They agree that to be led rightly in the way of devotion they must be illumined by the bright lights that shout in the Jewish horizon.  Well my Brethren&#33;<lb/>  We can be generous.  We may liberally bestow of<lb/> what is ours&#44; and feel none the less rich.  Only<lb/> let us not slight what we possess plentifully.<lb/>  It is to our discredit that a volume of the scriptures<lb/> thrilling the heart with its genuine poetry&#44; ever fresh<lb/> and lonely&#59; a poetry flowing down like the dew of heaven<lb/> or mount Hermon &#91;Hebrew&#93; it is to our disgrace that a volume<lb/> of the Scriptures so varied in its character&#44; that it re&#45;<lb/>&#45;produces&#44; in a measure&#44; our history&#44; the fears&#44; the<lb/> hopes and wishes of our fathers&#44; the sublime teachings<lb/> of our moralists&#44; a volume I repeat&#44; which has<lb/> been eagerly seized upon by the civilized world&#44; to render<lb/> with it adoration to the universal God&#44; should occupy<lb/> so little of our attention&#33;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>How silly&#33; if not sinful&#44; it is th for Hebrew<lb/> youths to prattle Latin odes and poems&#44; and be<lb/> ignorant of what surpasses them incomparably&#59;<lb/> the book of Tehilim&#33;  Have Horace and Virgil<lb/> greater claims than Moses and David&#63;  Understand&#44;<lb/> I do not advocate the practice followed&#44; with a pious<lb/> motive&#44; but uselessly I think&#44; of reading a number<lb/> of psalms daily&#44; without meditating on their meaning.<lb/>  That system&#44; greatly in vogue among our coreligionists<lb/> abroad&#44; has&#44; I apprehend&#44; lowered in the estimation of<lb/> multitudes&#44; a priceless writing&#44; penned by inspiration.<lb/>  No&#58; I would that we contracted the habit of selecting from<lb/> it such portions as beseeming agree with the state of our feelings.  For<lb/> to derive the comfort and the instruction it imparts&#44; it<lb/> must be perused according to our frame of mind&#44; to the<lb/> longing of our soul.  Eschewing what contains imprecations<lb/> to which the impassioned son of Jesse gave vent&#44; during his<lb/> severe trials&#44; we must choose always what is rich of in praises&#44; thanks&#45;<lb/>&#45;givings and supplications to the Omnipotent Lord.<lb/>  The immortal Mendelssohn&#44; who left a German version<lb/> of the Psalms&#44; which has ever since been regarded a<lb/> standard work&#44; so speaks in his preface&#44; as I<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>gather from a Hebrew comment.<lb/></p>
            <p>&#34;Dear reader&#33;  I offer to your acceptance the fruit of a<lb/> labor of love&#44; to which I devoted the leisure hours of ten<lb/> years&#44; delightful hours which sweetened the cup of my<lb/> afflictions&#33;  As my feelings would dictate&#44; I searched<lb/> among these sacred hymns that which best suited my<lb/> condition of at the time&#44; and I translated it in the verna&#45;<lb/>&#45;cular.  Occasionally the surpassing beauties that one<lb/> exhibited&#44; would draw me to it&#59; again&#44; my determination<lb/> to explain away difficulties which another presented&#44;<lb/> would enchain to it my attention.  I would ponder on it<lb/> for days and months&#44; till it became perfectly clear&#44; and<lb/> I imagined I had dived into the writer&#39;s thoughts.<lb/>  Then I would reproduce in our language his sentiments&#44;<lb/> and aspirations&#44; as well as my capacity allowed.  So&#44;<lb/> dear reader&#33; let me ask that you will follow my plan.<lb/>  Do not recite the volume in the order written&#44; but select<lb/> such portions&#44; that as correspond with the impulses promptings&#44; by which<lb/> you are swayed.  Identify yourself as far as possible<lb/> with the situation described by the authors of these out&#45;<lb/>&#45;pourings&#44; and you will be morally elevated&#44; and un&#45;<lb/>nutterably soothed.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Dear Brethren&#33;  The Sage of Dessau spoke wisely.  Yet&#44;<lb/> in all humility&#44; I venture to ask of my hearers more<lb/> than he requested of his readers.  I advise not alone<lb/> that they will adopt the sensible method suggested&#44; touch&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing the perusal of the book of psalms Tehilim&#44; but that they will<lb/> train themselves and their children to understand it as<lb/> the psalmists penned it&#44;&#45;&#45;in the forcible and com&#45;<lb/>&#45;prehensive Hebrew tongue.  That is the medium through<lb/> which our fathers moaned and rejoiced&#44; made votive of&#45;<lb/>&#45;ferings for their deliverance&#44; were fired unto patriotism&#44;<lb/> in the day of battle&#44; and sung hosannas to the Lord<lb/> of hosts.  That is the stream that swelled high<lb/> in Judah&#44; cleansing and purifying.  Let it not dry<lb/> up&#44; lest our national existence sink with it.<lb/>
                Unhappily&#44; the few who kept it fresh and flowing are<lb/> fast receding from the shore of life.  Another void<lb/> has been created in our literary ranks&#44; a void that cannot<lb/> be filled.  Zecharias Frankel of Bresslau&#44; who&#44;<lb/> since the decease of the illustrious Rapoport&#44; became<lb/> the chief exponent of historical Judaism in Germany&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>has been summoned away from the field of his<lb/> useful labor.  The Seminary&#44; over whose progress<lb/> and permanence he was called upon to watch about a<lb/> quarter of a century ago&#44; and which he directed sagaciously<lb/> by an extensive learning accompanied with unfeigned piety&#44;<lb/> laments the <sic>irreperable</sic> loss sustained.  For&#44; the venerable<lb/> professor&#44; though beyond the allotted three score years and<lb/> ten&#44; retained all his mental vigour&#44; and employed it still<lb/> as heretofore&#44; in disseminating Talmudic lore among the<lb/> many&#44; who came from near and from far to imbibe his<lb/> lessons.  Renowned by reason of his writings&#44; deservedly<lb/> esteemed and loved because of his devotion to his people and<lb/> religion&#44; Zacharias Frankel constituted a cynosure<lb/> to which the eyes of rational orthodoxy were directed.<lb/>  Four Sabbaths have just elapsed from that&#44; in which<lb/> that luminary disappeared from our sky to shine brilliantly<lb/> in the serene realms of bliss.  Our distinguished coreli&#45;<lb/>&#45;gionists who ceaselessly toiled for a righteous cause&#44; had<lb/> been&#44; during one week&#44; forced away by sickness from the lecture room.<lb/>  When the Sabbath arrived&#44; he hoped that the following<lb/> working days would see him again at his post&#59; and<lb/> mistaking the veil&#44; which the angel of death had cast<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>over his eyes&#44; for the shades of night&#44; greeted in the<lb/> words of Moses the approaching week.  He then fell<lb/> into a sleep from which he has surely awakened&#44; where<lb/> a sabbath of sweet rest awaits the good &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>  &#34;The memory of the righteous man is a blessing&#34; For he<lb/> has learnt&#44; to number his days&#44; and so to control them&#44;<lb/> that they may yield durable blessings on earth.  Like<lb/> our ancestors in the wilderness of Sinai&#44; the sainted Israel&#45;<lb/>&#45;ite&#44; whose demise we all must bewail&#44; worked for<lb/> the glory of God.  Nay&#44; his labor surpassed theirs in<lb/> usefulness and in excellence.  For he devoted skill and<lb/> zealousness&#44; the immense wealth of his mind&#44; and<lb/> the kindly feelings of his heart to rear a sanctuary&#44;<lb/> which honors our Lord more than a tabernacle of ordinary<lb/> or even precious stones.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;Dearer is the<lb/> law than riches&#34;&#44; and as the Rabbis rightly comment.<lb/>  &#34;It is dearer in the sight of &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> God&#44; than the worship of the high priest&#44; who<lb/> entered the holy of holies&#34; For the stability of that<lb/> Law&#44; Zecharias Frankel gave his best years and his<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>rare abilities.  &#34;Oh may the grace of the<lb/> Lord our God rest thereupon.  Establish Thou the<lb/> work of his hands&#44; yea&#58; the work of his hands esta&#45;<lb/>&#45;blish Thou it&#34;.  And may the leaders of American<lb/> Judaism&#44; learn from that noble exemplar to understand<lb/> what the present age demands at their hands.  Not to des&#45;<lb/>&#45;cribe in glowing terms the beauties of the scriptures&#44; and the<lb/> wisdom of the sages&#44; but to spread about the knowledge<lb/> thereof&#44; by personal exertions beyond the precincts of<lb/> the synagogue.  To raise a higher monument in this<lb/> land of equality&#44; than cloud&#45;reaching Temples&#44; rival&#45;<lb/>&#45;ling towering churches.   <sic>to</sic> glorify Israel&#39;s God by rend&#45;<lb/>&#45;ering the votaries votaries of His religion conversant with His revealed and tradi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tional statutes so that of them may justly be said &#34;Surely<lb/> this great people&#44; are wise and understanding intelligent.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
