<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF4_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_1_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_1_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_1_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_1_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_1_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>24</p>
            <p>G</p>
            
            <p>a few words about the scheme<lb/>
                of christianizing the State Constitution<lb/>
                For Sabbath Haggadol<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  It neither becomes us to lie supinely&#44; as if<lb/> fearing no molestation&#44; nor is it wise to magnify the<lb/> danger.  Vigilance is the price of liberty.  We should<lb/> therefore watch.  A spirit which the founder of this<lb/> noble state would never have sheltered&#44; is mischievously at<lb/> work.  It conspires to invade our imprescriptable rights.<lb/>  Look to it&#44; Israelites of Pennsylvania&#44; and let the fruit of<lb/> illiberality be nipped in the bud.  Single&#45;handed you<lb/> are not likely to ensure obtain success.  Go then in search of colaborers<lb/> fitted for giving assistance.  Every Hebrew in our midst<lb/> commanding influence in among the Christian community&#44; should<lb/> exercise it in a manner&#44; that the deliberations of that<lb/> body now sitting in convention&#44; be marked by unswerving<lb/> impartiality.  Every Hebrew having at his command<lb/> a running ready pen should use it to stir up the people.  And<lb/> they will parry a blow aimed at religious freedom.  You<lb/> know&#44; my Brethren&#44; the scheme newly concocted.  The zealots<lb/> see rain in the absence of a publicly written confession of<lb/> their belief.  Sodom and Gomorrah fell.  Harrisburg and<lb/> Philadelphia might share the same melancholy fate.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Forgetting that national misfortune is only at the heel<lb/> of national unrighteousness&#59; forgetting that the God of truth<lb/> is honored by the virtues of obedience of His creatures&#44; and not<lb/> by the mere mention of His existence and revealed will in a statute&#45;book&#44; they<lb/> predict unending disasters&#44; unless the dogmas they profess<lb/> are constitutionally legalized as supreme.  The plan<lb/> was originally laid upon a larger scale.  It did not&#44; how&#45;<lb/>&#45;ever&#44; foreshow bright prospects.  Sagaciousness then suggested<lb/> to the propriety of narrowing down its compass.  Perhaps the end goal will be<lb/> reached with more facility.  Once that Pennsylvania<lb/> tamely submits to be tied to the yoke&#44; her sister&#45;states will<lb/> bend to receive it.  The federal government must be<lb/> morally forced to accept the issue.  And a Te Deum will<lb/> resound in the church at the victory of sectarianism over<lb/> religious liberty.  Such is doubtless the hope of the<lb/> few who met a few some evenings ago.  I do not think<lb/> its realization at all probable.  Happily for Israel denomi&#45;<lb/>&#45;national jealousies&#44; and clashing clerical interests may ward<lb/> off the evil contemplated.  But as we would suffer the<lb/> most by the embodying of doctrinal points in the Con&#45;<lb/>&#45;stitution of our commonwealth&#44; we should noiselessly<lb/> but steadily endeavour to put down the first attempt.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>We cannot present an imposing array of strength mino&#45;<lb/>&#45;rically&#44; but we are not destitute of individuals&#44; whose personal<lb/> influence can be felt in high places.  And as we possess men<lb/> who will be listened to deferentially&#44; so we have others&#44; who<lb/> may redress wrongs by means of their pen.<lb/></p>
            <p>But above all we should trust in God&#44; who will not darken<lb/> thus the brightest&#45;spot of His created earth with the shadows<lb/> of our political death.  For&#44; depend upon it&#44; my Brethren&#33;<lb/>  with the admission of a creed into our organic laws the reign<lb/> of proscription will be inaugurated.  The adherents of<lb/> Judaism will be held baref barely at sufferance.  Nothing<lb/> short of <sic>apostacy</sic>will open for them the avenues to pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;ferments.  But the Guardian of Israel &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;disappointeth the devices of the<lb/> cunning&#44; so that their hands cannot perform their en&#45;<lb/>terprise.&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>But pardon the question&#44; American Israelites&#33; have we a<lb/> claim upon God&#39;s interposition in our behalf&#63;  Has not the<lb/> liberty long enjoyed estranged many from His services&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>What is this demand persistently made for changes&#44;<lb/> if not a step towards gentilism&#63;  The Synagogue<lb/> which &#91;&#63;&#93; represented the history&#44; the traditions&#44; the<lb/> hopes of our people&#44; has been so transformed as to baffle<lb/> recognition.  Our modern teachers deb declare that the<lb/> <sic>liberalising</sic> of our antiquated code.  But they who are not<lb/> carried away by the fascination of popular applause&#44; see<lb/> in it a gradual surrendering of principles for which our<lb/> predecessors staked their existence.  Already the effect<lb/> of such imparting can be perceived.  Persons noted for<lb/> their attachment to the observances&#44; have broken loose of<lb/> their pious habits.  Men who would have scrupled on the<lb/> sabbath to unseal a letter&#44; consider it lawful to ride<lb/> and buy and kindle fire.  Women who would have deemed<lb/> the intermixing of certain culinary utensils a pollution&#44; en&#45;<lb/>&#45;tertain their guests with forbidden viands.  And whereas<lb/> formerly Israelites&#44;&#45;&#45;when they sin sinned&#45;&#45;sinned blushingly&#44;<lb/> now they sin arrogantly.  And all this to gain what&#63;<lb/>  Immunities withheld&#63;  Not at all.  A freer community<lb/> than the Hebrews of Pennsylvania could scarcely be conceived.<lb/>  Say changelings&#33;  Did you so act to win the respect of<lb/> our gentile fellow&#45;el citizens&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Our fidelity to the ancestral laws secured it to us&#59; because the<lb/> reflecting will understand that those who are conscientious<lb/> and high&#45;principled in religion&#44; will be so likewise in their<lb/> dealings with mankind at large.  No&#58; you have not only<lb/> gained nothing worth obtaining&#44; but you have gathered<lb/> over all our heads the clouds betokening God&#39;s displeasure.<lb/>  For&#44; as the Rabbis remark &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; When mischief stalks abroad&#44; the good<lb/> and the bad are equally troubled.  Those who kept faith&#45;<lb/>&#45;ful to their mission&#44; and those who deserted it&#44; would be<lb/> involved in the baneful results attending the designs of<lb/> fanaticism.  The threatening storm&#44; will&#44; I believe&#44;<lb/> pass away&#59; for&#44; the Protector of Israel is merciful and long&#45;<lb/>suffering.  He will not put out the light of freedom&#44; and<lb/> force the world back into the dark ages&#44; because of our<lb/> trespasses.  But ought we therefore to tempt the Lord&#63;  Ought we<lb/> to imagine ourselves beyond His controlling power&#44; and act as if<lb/> absolved from His ordinances&#44; because human laws have&#44; so far&#44;<lb/> proved our strong shield&#63;  You have been shown&#44; my Brethren&#33;<lb/> how soon the same laws might be converted &#34;into thorns in our eyes&#44;<lb/> and stings in our sides&#34;.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>A few words added to our statute&#45;book will make<lb/> it the instrument with which our fathers were scourged.<lb/>  To&#45;day the evil counsel will not prevail&#44; but who can<lb/> tell with what evils the morrow may be pregnant&#63;<lb/></p>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Like brooks of water is a King&#39;s heart in the hand of the Lord&#44;<lb/> He turneth it withersoever He pleaseth.&#34;  Here we do not<lb/> depend upon a royal ru will&#44; but the decision of the majo&#45;<lb/>rity&#45;&#45;a sovereign&#45;will&#44; may work to our injury.  Let us<lb/> then bethink ourselves.  While employing all legiti&#45;<lb/>&#45;mate means within our reach to thwart the intention of the<lb/> zealots&#59; let our deliverance from it be followed by a return<lb/> to the principles we have abandoned.  See&#44; my<lb/> friends&#33;  The name of Jews prolific of afflictions&#44; did not<lb/> expose us to danger&#44; nor did it hitherto subject us to dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;abilities in this dear land.  We have bee nthe peers of<lb/> all Americans&#44; notwithstanding that our peculiar usages<lb/> kept us religiously distinct.  Now we betray a mighty wish to<lb/> yield our characteristics and approach gentilism&#44; and<lb/> now we are repelled by the hand we fain would press.<lb/>  Now is prejudice raised in arms against the Hebrews.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Such is the silent admonition of Him &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;who doeth wonders&#44; and we know it not&#34;.  Let us accept<lb/> the wholesome teaching&#44; and behave in a manner becoming<lb/> our dignity and consistent with our duty.  We shall stand<lb/> up before man for our rights&#44; but humble ourselves to the dust before<lb/> God for our backslidings.  We shall bring our influence<lb/> to bear on the f defence of our franchises&#44; but mainly<lb/> commit our cause to our compassionate Lord.<lb/>  It is thus&#44; O Israelites&#33; that the two&#45;edged sword pointed at<lb/> our national breast was blunted even at the memorable<lb/> season we are about to celebrate.  No compromise<lb/> with the enslaving Pharaoh&#59; absolute liberty alone could<lb/> satisfy the bondmen.  Their champion stood imperturbable<lb/> in the presence of the dreaded tyrant&#44; but he looked up to<lb/> the highest Sower for the glorious issue.  &#34;Upon this<lb/> might will the chains drop from your weary feet.&#34;  So<lb/> spoke the messenger of the Most High&#44; and the people<lb/> who did believe&#44; &#34;bent down and prostrated themselves&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Their loins are girded&#44; fastened are their<lb/> sandals&#44; they have laid hold of their staff to set forth on<lb/> the march of freedom&#44; but our father&#39;s obedience betokened<lb/> their depending for salvation upon an all&#45;guiding Providence.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>The door&#45;posts of their houses marked with the blood of the<lb/> lamb&#44; signified their faith.  That animal symbolical<lb/> indeed&#45;&#45;not of a vicarious atonement&#45;&#45;but of the <sic>downfal</sic> of heathen superstitions&#44; that<lb/> animal&#45;&#45;the object of adoration among their Egyptian task&#45;<lb/>masters&#44; was slaughtered as an earnest of our ancestors&#39; alle&#45;<lb/>&#45;giance to the living God.  Let us then upon at this season&#44;<lb/> evince a belief equally firm in our everlasting Redeemer by<lb/> sacrificing the objects that cause us to err&#44; and giving honor<lb/> to truth.  Our paschal oblation should be the yielding of<lb/> modern ideas that clash with the instruction of Sinai.<lb/>  It should be the ye rejection of that love for popularity&#44; which<lb/> leads us blindfolded into the arms of gentilism.  Passover<lb/> will be fittingly observed by removing the leaven which<lb/> makes us swell with vainglory because of the privileges en&#45;<lb/>&#45;joyed.  It will be an acceptable festival to the<lb/> Deliverer of our people&#44; if while performing the rites&#44;<lb/> recalling the past&#44; we shall cast a look towards the<lb/> future&#44; and by our efforts&#44; by our meritorious conduct and<lb/> by our prayers hasten the time&#44; when all the liberated slaves<lb/> of Myraim will share the blessings now peculiarly within our<lb/> reach.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Then will we obtain His celestial boons&#59; and be certain<lb/> that God&#39;s high purposes and not men&#39;s contracted views<lb/> shall prevail.  Then may we laugh to scorn the<lb/> attempt to rob this country of her con crowning beauty&#44;<lb/> so attractive&#44; and so charming&#44; and feel assured that the seed<lb/> of Jacob will&#44; not less than the seed of Esau&#44; will still bask in<lb/> that beauty unsurpassing comeliness.  Each of us seeing our<lb/> hope fulfilled&#44; may have occasion to exclaim&#44; like the<lb/> Psalmist &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;The Lord is my strength and my shield&#44; my heart hath trusted<lb/> in Him&#44; and I was helped&#44; therefore my heart greatly<lb/> rejoiceth&#44; and with my song will I praise him&#34;.<lb/></p>
            
            <p>And you dear Bar Mitzv&#225; &#38;c &#40;concluding with a short address<lb/> to the lad.&#41;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
