<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF10_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1892-06" source="" attested="yes">June 1892</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_1_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>On congregational matters<lb/>
                Jun&#95;92<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Brethren.  Clearly&#44; the scene which this sacred edifice<lb/> presents each returning Sabbath is an open reproach<lb/> How to roll away that shame&#44; has become my an&#45;<lb/>&#45;xious thought&#44; since I heard&#44; while compulsorily<lb/> absent&#44; that the attendance at the worship grew<lb/> perceptibly smaller&#44; to a degree that <sic>forboboded</sic> a<lb/> decline&#59; even a decay which I cannot contemplate<lb/> without a heart&#45;sinking grief.  With a mind<lb/> centred upon the duty that a minister shepherd owes his<lb/> flock&#59; eager to hinder a dissolution&#44; which I hope<lb/> not to see and live&#44; I bethought myself of a plan<lb/> not <sic>unsual</sic> in some foreign countries.  At in&#45;<lb/>&#45;tervals&#44; the local Chief Rabbi issues a pastoral<lb/> letter to the Jewish community.  In it he chides<lb/> his coreligionists&#44; when lukewarmness dampens the<lb/> ardor&#44; which sacred convocations ought to enkindle.<lb/>  The authority wherewith that shepherd minister is clothed and<lb/> which elicits public respect&#44; he exercises to the end<lb/> of stirring up parents into a wiser education of<lb/> their children&#44; depicting in such language as he can<lb/> best command&#44; the sin of neglecting the dearest<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>interests of young sons and daughters&#44; in order<lb/> to go in quest of what will never ensure their<lb/> happiness.  A sensible training in the religion<lb/> which has reason at its basis and the wholesomest<lb/> prescriptions as its leading rules&#44; the Pastor earnestly<lb/> recommends.  Having appealed to those into<lb/> whose safe&#45;keeping nature&#39;s God has entrusted<lb/> the spiritual upbuilding of a rising generation&#44; the<lb/> Rabbi conjures all to stand by the Law of Sinai&#44;<lb/> and show gentilism that consistency is a Jew&#39;s<lb/> badge of honor.  Pastoral letters of that<lb/> description&#44; I have read more than once in<lb/> English&#44; French and Italian.  Would it become<lb/> me to address in like manner Israelites under my<lb/> charge&#44; now that I painfully feel how the means<lb/> of reaching them from this sacred stand are<lb/> being steadily cut off&#63;  Well&#58; if I would belief<lb/> in the efficacy of my official pleading&#44; I would<lb/> commit my words to paper&#44; and bid them god&#45;<lb/>speed with all the fervor of my souls.  But<lb/> neither am I invested with the authority <sic>weilded</sic><lb/> by European Rabbis&#44; nor are American<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>congregations formed upon the same plan as<lb/> those across the ocean.  There&#44; ordinarily&#44; the<lb/> ecclesiastical Chief has a full jurisdiction over all<lb/> the Israelites of his city and not infrequently of<lb/> smaller religious bodies beyond the limits of his<lb/> place of residence.  Among us none is possessed<lb/> of a religious power&#44; to which deference must universally be paid.<lb/>  Each congregation constitutes here a separate sovereignty&#44;<lb/> its Rabbi or minister controlling or being controlled at<lb/> pleasure.  To day the ritual is curtailed at the<lb/> dictum of that a single occupant of the pulpit&#44; or through<lb/> the pressure brought to bear upon him by the Board<lb/> of Managers&#59; to morrow the vernacular supplants<lb/> the Hebrew merely because so wills a single preach&#45;<lb/>&#45;er&#44; or so orders a set of lay directors.  In one instance&#44;<lb/> the attendants at the Synagogue are demanded to keep<lb/> silent&#44; while non&#45;Jewish choristers conduct the service<lb/> and no remonstrance from a superior head is heard&#44;<lb/> because none is recognized as such&#59; in another&#44; persons<lb/> who are perhaps deficient in the very rudiments of<lb/> Jewish lore&#44; decide that the Sabbath may be<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>transferred to Sunday.  This anomaly was<lb/> actually enacted of late in a city of the West&#44;<lb/> where men whose wealth lends them influence<lb/> cast their votes in favor of Christianizing<lb/> Judaism by hallowing the day commemorative<lb/> of the pretended bodily resurrection of a man&#45;god.<lb/></p>
            <p>Indeed&#44; if an acknowledged Chief&#44; or&#44; at least&#44;<lb/> an advisory Rabbinical Board existed&#44; a well<lb/> deserved rebuke would put an end to the outraging<lb/> of many a Synagogue&#44; in whose pulpit not<lb/> alone Jesus of Nazareth is given a place of distinct&#45;<lb/>&#45;ion with our Moses&#44; Isaiah and Hillel&#44; but avowed<lb/> scoffers of all doctrines &#38; creeds&#44; and even pronounced atheists are quoted<lb/> with evident zest&#44; to display a liberality allied to<lb/> profanity.  Now&#44; suppose that&#44; si&#45;<lb/>&#45;tuated as we are in America&#44; I ventured upon<lb/> issuing a written address to my own constituents.<lb/>  In it I would naturally picture the dismal<lb/> scene which meets the vision of a few attendants<lb/> every Sabbath morning&#44; and disclose the fears<lb/> I entertain of a still greater desertion of the Divine<lb/> service on the Divinely appointed day.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>I would not upbraid&#44; not denounce but be&#45;<lb/>seech members and seatholders to prevent the<lb/> threatening result of their absence&#44; by crowding<lb/> these sacred courts with young children&#44; taught<lb/> in the language which is our precious heir&#45;<lb/>&#45;loom.  I would urge the redeeming of the<lb/> name of our venerable congregation&#45;&#45;causing<lb/> the latter to further &#34;the hope of Israel&#34;&#44; by a<lb/> steadfast conservation&#44; and I would promise&#44; on<lb/> my own part to study how best to interest all<lb/> by a preaching drawn from legitimate sources<lb/> the Bible and the traditions.  Imagine that I<lb/> undertook so to do in the capacity of an accept&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed servant of the Lord.  Could I anticipate<lb/> to rejoice over a general abandonment of Sabbath&#45;<lb/>desecration&#44; over a hearty response evinced by<lb/> the inspiring and inspiriting sight of hundreds<lb/> of brethren singing the praises of the Most High<lb/> before the oracle of this house&#63;  My most for&#45;<lb/>&#45;cible utterances would be drowned in the tumult<lb/> which the clashing of opinions raises everywhere through&#45;<lb/>out the Philadelphia community of Jews&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>&#45;&#45;a tumult which no one can silence by dint<lb/> of an authority superlative and revered.<lb/></p>
            <p>But the lack of a general response is not the<lb/> only evil that might attend my appeal.  I<lb/> would expose lay open expose to the derision of many who laugh<lb/> conservation to scorn&#44; the Congregation whose<lb/> creditable standing is dear to me.  I would<lb/> supply our adversaries in and out the camp with<lb/> weapons to deeply wound the hearts of some who<lb/> still cherish the memory of the Communal services<lb/> rendered by the first religious body of Jews in<lb/> Philadelphia&#45;&#45;the Mickve Israel.  No&#58; I must screen my<lb/> congregants from obloquy.  Without falling<lb/> into the sin of prevarication&#44; I must hide from<lb/> the public a bleeding sore.  I will not expose lay it open<lb/> it to view&#44; that free thinkers may point to us<lb/> as a sorry comment on the effect of our barring<lb/> &#34;Radicalism&#34; f out of these consecrated precincts.<lb/>  But here&#44; I dare not keep remain silent.  Reasonably<lb/> hypocritical would be to feign satisfaction&#44;<lb/> when profoundly dissatisfied and grieved.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Here it behooves me to cry aloud&#44; that the <lb/>report of my complaint spreading&#44; through the<lb/> few within reach of my voice&#44; to the many who<lb/> persistently deny me the right to lead them in<lb/> prayer and to instruct&#44; an appreciable number may at all events be won<lb/> back as <sic>worshippers</sic> and listeners&#44; and thus<lb/> consistency may raise its head triumphantly.<lb/>  In the name of all that which eleven decades<lb/> of our communal existence&#44; has endeared to our<lb/> hearts&#44; let me beg of the our temporal officers to<lb/> take up a missionary work&#44; so that the corpo&#45;<lb/>&#45;ration over whose interests they have been chosen<lb/> to watch&#44; may not decay&#59; let me ask of my<lb/> sisters in faith&#44; whose influence is potent to<lb/> exercise it in behalf of this historic religious<lb/> body.  <sic>Counselled</sic> by our women&#44; our men will<lb/> not suffer this dwelling of God to remain stand as a menace by<lb/> reason of its emptiness.  In the well known language<lb/> of David I entreat all &#34;Oh magnify the Lord<lb/> with me&#44; and let us extol His name alto&#45;<lb/>&#45;gether&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> And so may it be.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
