<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF30_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1897" source="" attested="yes">1897</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff30_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff30_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff30_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff30_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff30_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff30_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff30_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff30_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff30_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff30_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff30_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff30_1_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff30_1_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff30_1_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff30_1_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff30_1_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPIHA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>97<lb/>
                On the book of Jonah<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>On Friday of last week&#44; while I was watching the<lb/> ebbing away of a very dear friend&#39;s life&#44; a reporter of one<lb/> of our city journals&#44; called at my house.  In my absence&#44;<lb/> he left a note.  He asked that I would furnish an<lb/> article respecting a question agitating at present some<lb/> of the Churches.  In the evening&#44; the same person<lb/> called again&#44; to inquire whether I had agreed to do<lb/> as he wished.  I answered that I could not attend<lb/> to his request&#44; it being then my Sabbath.  The<lb/> visitor left evidently displeased&#44; because I did not at<lb/> once prepare a writing which might show my<lb/> standing theologically.  His employer would display<lb/> in capital letters how Jewish orthodoxy and Christ&#45;<lb/>&#45;ian orthodoxy share one the same opinion.  But truly&#44; in<lb/> my mind&#44; the very contrary is the fact.  Our neigh&#45;<lb/>&#45;bors&#44; born under what they term a new dispensation&#44;<lb/> are taught to believe that a verbal dictation of all<lb/> of the Scriptures emanated from a heavenly Power.<lb/>  Therefore when a minister of the gospel&#45;&#45;chafing under<lb/> such a restrictive creed&#45;&#45;gives utterance to broader views&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>some of the churches rise up in arms.  Not<lb/> so the Synagogue.  Intelligent Israelites&#44; however<lb/> reverent in their sentiments&#44; will never acknowledge that<lb/> in the lapse of many centuries&#44; during which copyists<lb/> wrote down the different books of our Bible&#44; not<lb/> a single oversight could ever have occurred.  I incline<lb/> to free the Pentateuch from that possibility for two<lb/> reasons&#58; firstly&#44; because it being read seriatim every<lb/> Sabbath&#44; its correct readi wording became fastened upon<lb/> our people&#39;s memory&#59; secondly&#44; because it being<lb/> the very foundation stone of our religion&#44; it command&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed the profoundest attention of our Scribes&#44; so as<lb/> to prevent the last inadvertence.  Not so regarding<lb/> the prophets and Hagiographa.  Notwithstanding the<lb/> care of our copyists to avoid any errors&#44; it may have<lb/> happened that discrepancies about names&#44; dates&#44; locali&#45;<lb/>&#45;ties or even the narrative of some events may have crept<lb/> in.  Now&#44; if Heber Newton&#44; or Professor Briggs&#44;<lb/> or Robertson Smith&#44; or other occupants of Church<lb/> pulpits had confined their criticism to what I have<lb/> just alluded&#44; I certainly would not declare them<lb/> unfit to preach.  Most assuredly I would not<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>raise a hue and cry to have them expelled from their<lb/> office&#44; if they did not subscribe to the absurd notion<lb/>&#45;&#45;held by some Anglican churches&#45;&#45;that the so called authorized version of the English<lb/> Bible&#44; has a Divine sanction.  But those<lb/> learned clergymen have enlisted in the ranks of<lb/> &#34;the higher criticism&#34;&#44; which does not scruple to<lb/> put tear down roots and branches in Holy Writ.<lb/>  The lines of the patriarchs are in their sight sheer<lb/> myths&#59; the stupendous events by which the author<lb/> of all things&#44; made nature transcend its limits to help and to<lb/> instruct some&#59; to punish and confound others&#44; they<lb/> deny and denounce as impossibilities.  Very lately<lb/> Dr Layman Abbath of Brooklyn&#44; scandalized protest&#45;<lb/>&#45;ant churches&#44; by casting ridicule on the story of Jonah.<lb/>  He considered that narrative puerile and incredible&#44; un&#45;<lb/>&#45;worthy of the Bible which Jews have preserved.<lb/>  Archbishop Ryan the head of Catholicism in our city&#44;<lb/> was interviewed&#44; and he spoke.  Rev Dr Henry Clay<lb/> Trumbull&#44; also of Philadelphia&#44; the editor of the Sun&#45;<lb/>day School Times&#44; set forth his opinion.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>The former intimated that he is not disconcert&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed in the least&#44; because his church takes no<lb/> heed of writings opposed to what it has ac&#45;<lb/>&#45;cepted of old&#44; and to which the highest authorities<lb/> at rome&#44; have applied their pontifical seal.  The latter brought<lb/> his erudition to bear on the subject&#44; and discussed<lb/> it in its various features.  I read also on that topic an anony&#45;<lb/>&#45;mous article signed &#34;a Jew&#34; on that f topic&#44; sen&#45;<lb/>&#45;sibly put together from a conservative stand&#45;point.<lb/>  Now&#44; to in my judgment the story of Jonah&#44; has an<lb/> essentially moral value.  Let us first cast a retros&#45;<lb/>&#45;pective glance on the time in which the son of Amit<lb/>&#45;ta&#239; lived.  The ten tribes&#44; who had seceded from<lb/> Judah and Benjamin&#44; after the death of Solomon&#44; &#38; who&#44;<lb/> under Jeroboam the son of Nebat had constituted them&#45;<lb/>&#45;selves into a separate kingdom&#44; were ruled then by<lb/> Jeroboam II.&#44; son of Joash.  That monarch had shown<lb/> himself energetic and valiant.  According to historical<lb/> accounts&#44; he had reconciled by his military prowess&#44; a<lb/> number of cities which Syria had forcibly taken from Israel.<lb/>  But if the political situation of the seceding tribes had<lb/> improved under Jeroboam II.&#44; the religious condition<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>was still fast hurrying on to the a final decline&#91;&#63;&#93;.  Amos&#44; not<lb/> at all misled by the apparent success achieved on the<lb/> battle field&#44; pictured in colours not to be mistaken&#44;<lb/> the moral plagues praying upon the vitals of the<lb/> state&#45;&#45;the oppression of the poor&#59; the luxurious<lb/> extravagance of the rich&#59; the looseness of domestic<lb/> relations&#59; the hypocritical performance of ritual<lb/> ceremonials.  Angered at that&#44; a false preist accused the right&#45;<lb/>&#45;eous prophet of sedition.  He would foretell of coming evils have them ba&#45;<lb/>&#45;nished from the kingdom.  &#34;Go&#34; said he &#34;flee to the land of Judah&#44;<lb/> earn there thy bread&#44; and prophesy there&#34;.  But the<lb/> fearless denouncer of sin answered&#58; &#34;I am not a<lb/> prophet&#44; neither am I a prophet&#39;s son.  I am only<lb/> a herdsman&#44; and a gatherer of wild figs.  But the<lb/> Lord took me from behind the flock and said unto<lb/> me &#39;Go&#44; prophesy against Thy people Israel&#39;&#34;.<lb/></p>
            <p>A contemporary of the undaunted shepherd&#45;seer was Jonah<lb/> son of Amitta&#239;.  Born at Gath Hepher&#45;&#45;a city in the<lb/> tribe of Zebulun&#45;&#45;he could detected the approaching dissolution<lb/> of the kingdom of Israel.  Doubtless&#44; Jonah lamented<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>sincerely the predicted doom of the nation&#44; in whose<lb/> midst he was born and reared.  But he seemed to<lb/> have lacked the courage of his convictions.  A<lb/> firm believer in God&#39;s heavenly attributes&#44; the<lb/> book which bears his name proves him to have<lb/> been.  His own words attests it.  For he says&#58;<lb/> &#34;I know&#44; O Lord&#33; that Thou art a compassionate<lb/> and merciful God&#44; slow to anger&#44; abounding<lb/> in loving&#45;kindness&#44; and recalling an evil sentence.&#34;<lb/>  Yet Jonah could not rise to the height of an<lb/> Amos and hurl the arrows of prophetic rebukes<lb/> at men in power&#44; who dragged a nation to the<lb/> verge of ruin.  Hence&#44; when the celestial vision<lb/> demanded of him a peculiar mission&#44; distasteful to<lb/> his feelings&#44; he demurred.  Jonah&#39;s disobedience was<lb/> not the prompting of wickedness immorality&#44; but rather the ef&#45;<lb/>&#45;fect of a deep&#45;set belief.  How could he go among<lb/> the enemies of his own people&#44; urge repentance&#44; as<lb/> a saving skill against destruction&#59; &#38; witness the<lb/> happy effective immediate results of his exhortations&#63;  Would not Assyria&#44;<lb/> the mighty empire steeped in idolatry&#44; who by hearkening to<lb/> the admonition and repenting&#44; make the obduracy of Israel<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>more shameful&#44; more unpardonable&#44; by contrast&#63;<lb/>  Instead of embarking on a ship going to Nineveh&#44;<lb/> as commanded&#44; Jonah sailed on another bound to Tarshish&#44; or<lb/> Tartisus&#44; a city in Spain&#44; early colonized by<lb/> <sic>Phenicians</sic>.  The story of the storm with its<lb/> consequence is household words.  It needs requires not repe&#45;<lb/>&#45;tition.  The fugitive prophet saw in it the raging tempest the hand of the<lb/> Lord of heaven&#44; who made the sea as well as the dry<lb/> land&#44; &#38; whose universal Power&#44; he&#44; as a Hebrew&#44; feared.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; Such was his confession.  But the moral conveyed by that untoward<lb/> circumstances is deserving of our solemn consideration.<lb/>  The sailors on the vessel were not of the seed of Jacob.<lb/>  They had not received a Law which commands that<lb/> no one should stand idly&#44; when the life of a neigh&#45;<lb/>&#45;bour is threatened &#91;Hebrew&#93;; yet instinct&#45;<lb/>&#45;ively they tried with might and main to save Jonah<lb/> from a watery grave.  For&#44; the Almighty has<lb/> implanted in every human breast feelings of a<lb/> common brotherhood&#44; and men need not be Hebrews&#44;<lb/> in order to obey their dictates&#59; But though those who<lb/> have sprung from Abraham&#44; the Hebrew&#44; must on no<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>occasion&#44; under no provocation turn a deaf ear<lb/> to the humane ordinances of nature&#39;s God.  Now&#44; brethren&#44;<lb/> alluding to mo the tactics of the school of modern skepticism&#44;<lb/> I will remark&#44; that the principal point of attack<lb/> at which &#34;the higher criticism&#34; directs its weapons&#44; is<lb/> the narrative of a sea&#45;monster having swallowed<lb/> Jonah and laid him again unscathed on dry land&#44;<lb/> after three days.  The first mistake lies at the door<lb/> of the new testament&#44; which declares ex cathedra the<lb/> fish to have been a whale.  Hence whales have<lb/> been measured&#44; to show the impossibility of<lb/> the account left in the Jewish scriptures.  But the<lb/> truth is that I find no mention whatever in our<lb/> test of a word justifying the translation inserted in the<lb/> Christian scriptures.  I read thus Jo&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;  &#34;The Lord had prepared a great big fish to swal&#45;<lb/>&#45;low up Jonah&#44;&#34; thus leaving the question of the species of<lb/> that dweller of the sea&#44; undefined.  I shall not<lb/> quote the Rabbis&#44; who say that a special monster<lb/> had been created in the primordial days of the world&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>of such a huge form that might answer a predestined<lb/> Divine purpose.  The Talmudists&#44; may have intended<lb/> in this instance&#44; as usual with them&#44; to allegorize.  Nor<lb/> can I presume to assert&#44; like archbishop Ragan<lb/> that naturalists have discovered how in ancient<lb/> days sea monsters large enough to swallow<lb/> not one persons but a number of persons together did existed&#44; Nei&#45;<lb/>&#45;ther will I theorize like the Reverend Dr Trumbell&#44; on<lb/> the reason for punishing the disobedient messenger by<lb/> means of an acquatic animal&#44; alleging that it was to typify<lb/> Jonah&#39;s mission to Assyria&#44; whose chief deity was Dagon&#44;<lb/> an image partly represented partly in the figure of a man and<lb/> partly in that of a fish.  I simply will say that<lb/> to attempt to explain the inexplicable is folly.<lb/>  The very first chapter of the Pentateuch tells that God<lb/> created &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; that is&#44; marine monsters<lb/> of extraordinary size&#44; the workings of which are absolutely<lb/> unknown to me&#44; but which&#44; no doubt&#44; serve objects designed<lb/> by their Sovereign Maker.  Aside from the great truth great<lb/> who truth&#44; which the Bible means to impart&#44; namely&#44;<lb/> that the Author of nature can mould nature as He<lb/> wishes and that what we call miracles is an amplification<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>of the limits originally assigned to nature by God&#44;<lb/> and not a violence done to it&#44; aside from that verity&#44;<lb/> the story of Jonah teaches that to try to run counter to<lb/> the ordination of our Maker&#44; is to run to self destruction.<lb/>  But a still more important lesson we Jews derive from<lb/> the four chapters of that small book in our Bible.<lb/>  We learn that the prophets of Israel were sent by the<lb/> Universal Father not only for the sake of our people&#44;<lb/> but for the moral improvement of all sentient beings&#44;<lb/> even for the benefit of those who erroneously <sic>worshipped</sic><lb/> imaginary deities&#44; in order to the Almighty would prevent their disastrous end&#44;<lb/> through which national corruption must bring on.  Therefore God commissioned one of<lb/> His servants to warn and to admonish gentiles.  The short&#45;sighted<lb/> messenger did not grasp the sublime object.  He lamented the<lb/> repentance of heathens&#44; lest it reflect on the stubbornness of his<lb/> own people.  Jonah cared more for the &#91;&#63;&#93; which afforded<lb/> him a shelter form the rays of the sun than for myriads of<lb/> the idolatrous Ninevites&#44; and he was rebuked by the Uni&#45;<lb/>&#45;versal Creator.  How fitting it is&#44; that on Yom Kippur&#44;<lb/> the day set aside for our most serious reflection on penitence and<lb/> fraternal reconciliation&#44; how fit it is that the book of Jonah should<lb/> be read in every Synagogue&#44; where believing Congre&#45;<lb/>&#45;gations assemble in prayers and fasting&#33;  I shall<lb/> let the Higher Criticism sharpen the weapons of<lb/> ridicule to strike the little volume in our safe keeping.<lb/>  I will still glory to hold it in our possession and<lb/> point out the broad views and sublime noblest of principles which<lb/> it aims to teach mankind.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
