<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF2_12</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1877" source="" attested="yes">1877</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_12_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_12_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_12_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_12_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_12_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_12_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_12_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_12_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_12_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_12_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_12_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_12_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For the 17th anniversary of<lb/>
                the 7th st Synagogue.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  This year the anniversary sermon has been<lb/> deferred longer than ordinarily.  You may have observed that<lb/> heretofore it was delivered on either of two sacred days.<lb/>  If the New Moon occurred before the Sabbath preceding<lb/> the week in which Pentecost is celebrated&#44; I spoke concern&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing the dedication of our new Synagogue upon that Sabbath.<lb/>  If it happened later&#44; I addressed you on the topic the first<lb/> day of the festival.  I ought&#44; accordingly&#44; to have alluded<lb/> yesterday morning to the occasion&#44; on which we entered<lb/> we this edifice&#44; seventeen years ago.  But a long expe&#45;<lb/>&#45;rience has shown me that of all our holidays&#44; &#34;the feast<lb/> of Weeks&#34; attracts the smallest number of my American<lb/> coreligionists to the house of God.  Why it should be<lb/> so&#44; I am at a loss to divine.  For&#44; were I asked&#44; which<lb/> of our solemn seasons might claim priority&#44; I would<lb/> unhesitatingly answer&#58; that wherein we learnt our duties&#44;<lb/> is entitled to the highest distinction.  Admitting<lb/> that Judaism&#44; and the religions derived form it&#44; hinge<lb/> on the event of the Passover&#59; for&#44; unless we had be&#45;<lb/>&#45;come a separate and free nation&#44; the knowledge of<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Holy Writ could neither have been acquired&#44; nor<lb/> disseminated&#44;&#45;&#45;a fact of which we are reminded<lb/> by the compilers of our ritual&#44; who to the performance<lb/> of almost every practice they attach the sentence &#34;a memorial<lb/> of the coming out of Egypt&#34;&#45;&#45;; Admitting that Ju&#45; also that<lb/> &#45;daism the institution of the Sabbath had precedence to the<lb/> delivery of the Decalogue&#44; and that the latter meant only<lb/> to give it the strongest confirmation&#59; still&#44; the day<lb/> of Sinai may be rightly regarded as a central light&#44;<lb/> from which&#44; like so many luminous rays&#44; the tenets and<lb/> ordinances of our faith emanate.  Why it should<lb/> not exhibit the largest multitude of <sic>worshippers</sic> in the<lb/> sanctuary&#44; I cannot imagine.  To raise the ob&#45;<lb/>&#45;jection&#44;&#45;&#45;captiously made by some&#44; that the Scriptures<lb/> are silent about the real season&#44; which we now cele&#45;<lb/>&#45;brate&#44; would be a denial of both the written and the<lb/> oral law.  To say that the fiftieth day form the<lb/> presentation of the first sheaf of the barley&#45;produce to the<lb/> Temple has lost its significance since our dispersion&#44;<lb/> and to solemnize on it the promulgation of the ten<lb/> commandments is to do what history does not warrant&#44;<lb/> would show a want of reflection inexcusable in any Israelite.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>We cannot prove to the world mathematically<lb/> that the sixth of Sivan is the day on which the<lb/> Duty revealed His will to a priestly assemblage&#44;<lb/> but we can approximately demonstrate it&#44; even with&#45;<lb/>&#45;out taking into consideration the oral teachings of the<lb/> fathers.  That this is the third month of the ec&#45;<lb/>&#45;clesiastical year&#44;&#45;&#45;which&#44; in deference to the great event<lb/> of the deliverance from bondage begins in Nissan&#45;&#45;&#44;<lb/> none can doubt&#59; that the word Chodesh&#44; as in &#34;Ba&#45;<lb/>&#45;Chodesh Hashelishi&#34; often stands by itself in Biblical<lb/> style to signify the New Moon&#44; none acquainted<lb/> with the Hebrew language will gainsay.  Consequently&#44;<lb/> we may believe what is accepted by our comment&#45;<lb/>&#45;ators&#44; that the day of our fathers&#39; arrival at Sinai<lb/> was the first of Sivan.  And as we are told that<lb/> the people&#44; upon reaching that desert in Arabia&#44;<lb/> encamped opposite the mountain&#44; namely&#44; the mount&#45;<lb/>&#45;ain of which Moses must have spoken&#44; as having been<lb/> hallowed by the vision of the burning&#45;bush&#44; and by the<lb/> expressed pre&#45;ordination of God&#44; it follows clearly&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>that soon after that&#44; the three days preparatory<lb/> to the promulgation of the Decalogue commenced.<lb/>  Hence&#44; the greatest of all events in history&#44; must&#44; of neces&#45;<lb/>&#45;sity&#44; have taken place early in Sivan.  But we<lb/> believe also what men who obtained instruction from<lb/> prophets&#44; have handed down.  They have assured poster&#45;<lb/>&#45;rity that the festival which Israel solemnize at this<lb/> period of our year is doubly sacred&#59; that it recalls<lb/> the sense of gratitude evinced by their ancestors at<lb/> God&#39;s blessing&#44; when the fields smiled with the a pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;mised abundance&#44; and its recipients conveyed to<lb/> the habitation of the Lord two loaves made of the first<lb/> wheat the soil had yielded&#44; and that it is&#44; more&#45;<lb/>&#45;over&#44; the anniversary of the birth&#45;day of that<lb/> matchless declaration&#44; which underlies the constitu&#45;<lb/>&#45;tions of civilized mankind.  And this double feature&#44;<lb/> they set before us&#44; when they wrote in our liturgy&#44;<lb/> &#34;Thou &#40;O Lord&#41; hast given us this feast of Weeks&#44; the<lb/> season of the delivery of our Law&#34;&#44; an utterance&#44; my<lb/> brethren&#44; universally repeated in Israel&#44; and sanctioned&#44;<lb/> likewise&#44; by authors&#44; who&#44; cannot be said&#44; to have been<lb/> influenced by Rabbinical imparting.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Why&#44; then&#44; the disciples of the Sages should esteem lightly<lb/> what is of primary importance&#44; I am unable to explain&#44;<lb/> but&#44; as they do not as a role prove they adequately value it&#44; by<lb/> a thronged gathering in throngs at the Tabernacle of prayer&#44; I have<lb/> postponed that which I wished ot say to my congrega&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion&#44; to the Sabbath&#45;day&#59; when I hoped that a larger<lb/> number than usual would of assemble in our consecrated<lb/> edifice.  Well&#58; dear hearers&#33;  We have some cause<lb/> this year&#44; for self&#45;gratulation.  This religious body of ours&#44;<lb/> having attained the venerable age of nearly a hund&#45;<lb/>&#45;red years&#44; was considered decrepit&#44; and verging on the<lb/> grave of dissolution.  Thanks to a watchful Providence&#44;<lb/> not alone it has kept alive&#44; but it has given signs<lb/> of renewed vigor.  Our Synagogue has had the power<lb/> to draw persons&#44; who derive pleasure from carrying<lb/> out ancestral usages.  For&#44; scarcely once in all the<lb/> services here performed&#44;&#45;&#45;independent of the ordinary<lb/> Friday evenings and Sabbath morning&#45;worship&#45;&#45;&#44; scarce&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly once has the requisite number been found wanting.<lb/>  The minor sanctuary of the Mikv&#233; Israel Congregation&#44;<lb/> is now the cynosure of all eyes&#44; that are not closed to the ne&#45;<lb/>&#45;cessity of supporting Judaism by outward as well as by inward<lb/> agencies.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Coreligionists&#44; connected with other congregations&#44; attend it<lb/> with great frequency&#44; certain to meet&#44; what is at<lb/> present&#44; rarely met observed elsewhere&#44; I mean&#44; the per&#45;<lb/>&#45;formance of the worship with undeviating regularity&#44;<lb/> and an indiscriminate bestowal of religious honors<lb/> on all attendants.  But another cause for rejoi&#45;<lb/>&#45;cing&#44; is the faint but still perceptible wish in parents&#44;<lb/>&#45;&#45;who contribute to the stability of our Synagogue&#45;&#45;&#44;<lb/> to supply their sons with instruction in Hebrew.  A<lb/> wish which I interpret as a happy prognostic&#59; for<lb/> it may beget a revival&#44; the good effects of which can<lb/> never be overestimated.  The distinguishing character&#45;<lb/>&#45;istic of the dwelling where the God of Sinai receives<lb/> the homage of His adorers&#44; must indispensably be<lb/> the use of the language in which He delivered His<lb/> will to the priestly nation.  None born of our race&#44;<lb/> should remain entirely ignorant thereof&#44; but our<lb/> sons ought early to acquire a taste for the culti&#45;<lb/>&#45;vation of a learning which alone can save the bond<lb/> of our unity from disruption&#44; and Jewish communities<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>from extinction.  Grateful to all fathers and mothers<lb/> who&#44; impressed with a their solemn obligation&#44; do not<lb/> begrudge the remuneration given to the private teachers&#44;<lb/> striding to enable their offspring to sing understanding&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly the sacred hymns and psalms of the Synagogue.  I<lb/> must also express my satisfaction that some of my young brethren have<lb/> availed themselves of my gratuitous efforts&#44; in larger<lb/> numbers and with more constancy than formerly.<lb/></p>
            <p>If our new structure&#44; has not perceived in its 16th year&#44;<lb/> the realization of that for which every stone thereof must<lb/> long&#45;&#45;its deliverance from any entanglement with an<lb/> association which may partly claim it as its possess&#45;<lb/>&#45;ion&#44; it has nevertheless not suffered temporarily&#44; while<lb/> it has&#44; in a small degree&#44; prospered spiritually.<lb/></p>
            <p>Its temporal directors still evince great interest&#44; and have<lb/> not slackened their exertions in promoting its welfare.<lb/>  Under their administration&#44; broad but judicious&#44; liberal<lb/> but economical&#44; firm but mild&#44; the permanence of the<lb/> Mickv&#233; Israel Congregation&#44; whose 17th anniversary&#44; we celebrate<lb/> will be secured.  &#34;The glory of this latter house&#44; shall<lb/> be greater than the former&#45;&#45;and in this place will I give<lb/> give peace saith the Lord of hosts.&#34;  So may it be.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
