<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF3_8</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_8_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_8_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_8_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_8_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_8_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_8_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_8_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_8_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_8_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_8_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_8_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_8_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>8th lecture on Post&#45;Biblical<lb/>
                History.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  It was comparatively easy to acquaint you with<lb/> the origin of the sect of the Sadducees&#44; for I drew my in&#45;<lb/>&#45;formation from Jewish sources&#44; as and which are mostly agreed upon to by<lb/> Jewish scholars.  But It is far from however&#44; anything but easy to tell&#44; with<lb/> anything approaching historical exactness&#44; what gave<lb/> rise to the sect of the Essenes&#44; and whence the name<lb/> it took was has been derived.  The Talmudists are silent on<lb/> the subject.  Frequently as they mention allude in their writings to the Sadducees&#44;<lb/> it did not occur to them once to mention the existence<lb/> of a separate religious body&#44; called &#34;Essenes&#34;.  This peculiar<lb/> circumstance&#44; leads me to believe that the Rabbis did<lb/> not look upon the Essenes as seceders or schismatics&#44;<lb/> but considered them as belonging to the general mass bulk an integral part of the general masses of<lb/> our the Hebrew people.<lb/></p>
            <p>Josephus&#44; their contemporary of that sect&#44; and who in his autobiography makes<lb/> the questionable statement that of having at one time he lived become af&#45;<lb/>&#45;filiated to their sect it&#44; describes then its votaries as enthusiasts&#59; as<lb/> men totally indifferent to worldly honors or mundane pleasures&#45;&#45;living<lb/> upon little&#44; which they shared in common&#44; unswervedly as men tenaciously strict<lb/> in the observance of precepts and ceremonies&#44; and men who were willing<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>to submit to any bear suffering rather than swerve from<lb/> duty or prevaricate.  Nor is Josephus the only authority&#44;<lb/> who gives the Essenes a high character for religion and pure religiousness and pure<lb/> morality.  Another person&#44; whom I respect more still more trustworthy&#44; I thinks than<lb/> our historian&#44; represents them described pictures their lens of conduct demeanour in<lb/> glowing terms.  Philo Judea Judaeus of Alexandria&#45;&#45;illustrious<lb/> for his varied learning and for the services he once ren&#45;<lb/>&#45;dered his nation&#45;&#45;&#44; has recorded this his splendid testimony in<lb/> behalf of the Essenes.  He gives them preeminence<lb/> for honesty of dealings&#44; devotion to pious exercises habits&#44; for<lb/> self&#45;denial and humility&#44; and for mutual kindness and<lb/> ready assistance.  Another again&#44; who was not of<lb/> our own faith&#44; has added chronicled his favorable opinion.<lb/>  Pliny&#44; the elder a celebrated Roman who <sic>travelled</sic> much<lb/> and wrote extensively knowingly intelligently&#44; admired a sect he had seen<lb/> in Palestine.  For&#44; its members enjoyed a long existence<lb/> through a conduct of perfect self&#45;restraint and<lb/> integrity.  The Roman writer must doubtless alluded have had reference to the Essenes.<lb/>  Now&#44; on hearing a body of Jews praised so greatly praised<lb/> by three far&#45;famed contemporaries who could not have copied from each other&#44; one may feel sur&#45;<lb/> curious to learn why it did not call forth also the<lb/> encomium of the Sages of Israel.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Without citing it as a distinct sect the Mishna and<lb/> Talmud might have pointed to some of the most noted among its followers as excep&#45;<lb/>&#45;tional votaries representatives of the Hebrew written and oral Law.<lb/>  I hold it as my opinion that the Essenes did not com&#45;<lb/>&#45;mand the special attention of the ancient our Rabbis&#44; be&#45;<lb/>&#45;cause their leading rules could not never command an our Rabbis unqualified<lb/> approval.  Most of the Essenes lived unmarried&#44; whereas<lb/> Judaism encourages man to secure the domestic ties of<lb/> wife and children&#59; most of the Essenes devoted an undue<lb/> portion of their time to ritual exercises and metaphysical<lb/> speculations&#44; whereas Judaism wishes man to be practical&#44;<lb/> laboring to earn a competence&#59; most of the Essenes<lb/> preferred seclusion seclusion to social intercourse&#44; whereas Ju&#45;<lb/>&#45;daism teaches man that he was created to associate<lb/> with his neighbors.  We may esteem the Essenes<lb/> for their probity&#59; we may respect them for their fidelity to<lb/> one another&#44; but the sages could not consistently<lb/> have presented offered them to their own disciples as models worthy of imitation.<lb/>  I agree with the critics who argue that a sect so<lb/> anti&#45;Judaic in part&#44; and so pre&#45;Judaic on the whole&#44; must<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>have sprung up during the period in which<lb/> the land of our fathers was unhappily the foot ball<lb/> of contending parties.  Seeing To avoid a seething corruption&#44;<lb/> a few selected spirits may have sought to breathe in isolation a<lb/> pure atmosphere in isolation  And then the bloody strug&#45;<lb/>&#45;gle against Rome&#59; and the unscrupulousness of the<lb/> fiery zealots may have kept the terror of the moderate in politics&#44; all of that may have contributed in still keeping those few still away within<lb/> from the outside world a narrow sphere&#44; to enjoy a degree of <sic>tranquillity</sic><lb/> which they could not obtain in the outward world.<lb/></p>
            <p>The appellation &#34;Essenes&#34; may have been applied to them<lb/> by the people&#44; from the Syrian word Hassia &#91;Hebrew&#93; meaning<lb/> &#34;pious&#34; in Syriac&#44; the generally spoken language then generally spoken&#45;&#45;&#34;pious.&#34;  Many&#44; however&#44; contend that we ought<lb/> to read it Assiac &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#91;Hebrew&#93; which&#44; in the Syriac&#44; thn gener&#45;<lb/> &#45;ally spoken signified phy &#34;medical doctor&#44;&#34; implying<lb/> that the system of governing the Essenes was a cure to diseased<lb/> souls.  I am strongly inclined to adopt the former<lb/> interpretation&#44; for the epithet of pietists&#44; or ascetics<lb/> fits well in its liber literal sense to the sect I have<lb/> described&#44; while that of physicians&#44; even in its<lb/> figurative sense rendering&#44; seems to me strained and far&#45;<lb/>fetched.  I acknowledge&#44; however&#44; that to attempt to<lb/> decide would be an impossible undertaking.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Besides&#58; I dare not dwell on a on any single subject of any of my post&#45;biblical<lb/> sketches short lectures series sketches.  The sect of the Essenes presents many point several features<lb/> deserving of our consideration&#44; but there is another&#44; if it may<lb/> be proper to call it a sect&#45;&#45;which has a primary title to<lb/> our reflection and study&#44; and reflection  For I must pay it some attention&#44; for I have recognize its value&#44; since it has preserved Judaism<lb/> to this very day.  You have heard it often mentioned&#44;<lb/> but only as a term of reproach.  The books which our neighbors&#44;<lb/> the Nazarenes&#44; hold sacred&#44; paint set it forth in the<lb/> uggliest aspect.  Its adherents are made synony&#45;<lb/>&#45;mous of with fraud and hypocrisy. and cheating with evil doing  But you will be<lb/> surprised to learn that the Talmud itself draws a<lb/> picture in as black colours and repulsive colours of men<lb/> of that sect in colours as black and repulsive as painted in the new Testament used.  Look at it.<lb/>  Here passes before us a Schershecker Schechemite Shechemite Pharisee.  The<lb/> man returns from performing some ritual ceremony.  He<lb/> wanted by it aimed solely to reach some a selfish end.  A self&#45;drag&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing Pharisee follows He who walks close to the walls&#44; and<lb/> so slow &#91;&#63;&#93; softly&#44; that none may notice how humble&#44; forsooth&#44; he is&#33;<lb/>  see that Pharisee with the head bowed like a bulrush.  The He<lb/> corners of his eyes though spy who admire his meekness. elbows no body&#45;&#45;why should he&#44; when a touch from a stranger might be &#91;&#63;&#93; contamination&#63;  Now<lb/> we got hold of a Pharisee who that cries&#58; &#34;People&#44; let me know<lb/> my duty&#44; what duty I have left undone&#44; and I shall do it.&#34;  Then the calculating Pharisee<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>arrives.  He has reckoned well how much profit the<lb/> discharge of that observance will <sic>yeild</sic>&#44; or of how much<lb/> inconvenience he will avoid by pretending to be wrapped in<lb/> prayer devotions....But are the denominations of attributed to the founder<lb/> of Christianity&#44; and the withering rebukes met registered administered<lb/> by the authors writers of the volumes of which contain Jewish traditions universal are they meant as a standard Jewish traditions of universal application&#63;<lb/>  Are they meant as a standard to guide us in our judgment of Pharisaism&#63;  I un&#45;<lb/>&#45;hesitatingly give an emphatic negative.  No&#58; Pharisaism<lb/> is sublime in its principles conceptions&#44; grand in its doctrines&#44; but many<lb/> who are reckoned among its disciples are hollow and in their professions&#44; false<lb/> and wicked in their professions conduct.  Is Republicanism synonymous<lb/> with anarchy&#44; because a numbers of men those who claim<lb/> to be under its government are lawless and ruffianly would prefer bench law to judicial procedure&#63;<lb/>  Hear it.  In Pharisaism were cradled our authors&#44; who created<lb/> a rich and soul&#45;elevating literature&#59; from at the breast of Pharisaism<lb/> drew their blood nurture our martyrs who left us a legacy of<lb/> resistance to Wrong&#44; and firmness in right.  Love<lb/> of country&#44; reverence for its rulers&#44; obedience to law&#44; and<lb/> social rectitude&#44; charity and mercy are sentiments flowing from out of Pharisaism<lb/> and nourishing permeating those who draw come nigh unto it.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Who will deny that Pharisees of broad phylacteries&#44; and<lb/> a broad cloak to hide their imposture deformities have always existed&#63;<lb/>  We all may have met those whitened sepulchres&#44; within<lb/> which are rotten bones.  We all may know of men<lb/> who pray much but ignore much&#44; aye&#58; they inquire wife&#44; children&#44; their<lb/> surroundings and the community in which they live.  verily<lb/> I tell say unto you&#44; they are pestilential vapors in the nostrils of<lb/> Pharisaism.  This honorable name Parushim which possibly may have<lb/> originally conveyed the idea of avoidance of remaining free from bodily<lb/> uncleanness pollution&#44; according to the Mishnic sentence&#58; &#34;cleanliness leads to holiness&#44;&#34; this honorable name has come down to later ages as significant<lb/> of spiritual impurity&#44; only through the <sic>pretentions</sic> of its<lb/> supposed adherents.  But let this an incontestable fact be borne<lb/> in mind.  The Pharisees have always constituted the<lb/> bulk of of our people&#44; whereas other sects never counted<lb/> vast multitudes.  Among millions&#44; there may be<lb/> hundreds who prove themselves unrighteous and worthless&#44; still one score<lb/> among thousands&#44; will more than counterbalance those<lb/> hundreds.  If the testimony of Josephus who asserts that<lb/> the controlling leading principles of the Pharisees were to live sparingly moderately&#44;<lb/> to shun wantonness&#44; to exercise self&#45;control and forbearance&#44;<lb/> be discredited as one&#45;sided and biased&#59; if the evidence of<lb/> historical fact which shows that John Hyracam Alexander Jo&#39;nneus&#44; repented on his<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>death&#45;bed of having joined&#44; in a fit of anger&#44; favored the sect<lb/> of Sadducees who rejected the doctrines of Gods providence Divine prescience&#44;<lb/> personal accountability and a hereafter&#44; and that he begged<lb/> of his wife&#44; queen Alexandria&#44; to conciliate again the God&#45;trusting pharisees&#44;<lb/> be interpreted as a stroke of policy&#44; then I shall call<lb/> in the evidence of the most pronounced opponent of the<lb/> Pharisees&#45;&#45;even the man of Nazareth.  Addressing He shall give<lb/> a sermon his evidence against his will.  Addressing<lb/> his disciples&#44; he the founder of Christianity said&#58; &#34;The scribes and Pharisees sit in<lb/> Moses&#39; seat.  All therefore that they bid you observe&#44;<lb/> that observed an do.&#34;  And what is in very deed<lb/> that which a veritable genuine representative of Pharisaism<lb/> bids us all to do&#63;  The Nazarene quoted it&#44; without<lb/> crediting it to the right source.  &#34;All things what&#45;<lb/>&#45;soever ye would that men should do to you&#44; do ye<lb/> even so to them&#58; for this is the law of and the prophets.&#34;<lb/>  Have you not recognized the origin of that maxim&#63;  It is the<lb/> creation of a Pharisee&#44; aye&#58; of a Pharisee of Pharisees&#44; the immortal chief of<lb/> the schools of Pharisees Judea&#45;&#45;our Hillel&#44; the<lb/> lover of his kind&#44; the lowly good and the true Pharisee.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
