<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF6_30</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_30_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_30_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_30_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_30_2v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 1 sheet<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For a funeral<lb/></p>
            <p>My heart&#33;  stir me not.  I must suppress thy failings.<lb/>  Shall I add grief when consolation is sought&#63;  Shall I lead<lb/> to despair when solemn duty demands that I point the way to<lb/> resignation&#63;  My heart&#33; be still urge me not to wail.....  Yes&#58; Comely was my<lb/> friend and gentle.  A joyful mother the dear one might<lb/> have become&#44; and how sincerely I would have congratulated<lb/> husband and father and sisters&#44; all entwined in the silvery<lb/> chord chain of affection&#33;  But....Oh&#33; Lord&#44; &#34;Thy judgments are an<lb/> impenetrable deep&#44;&#34; who shall fathom them&#63;  &#34;I am igno&#45;<lb/>&#45;rant and know not&#59;&#34; but Thou canst dictate words that may<lb/> allay distress.  Lox A sudden blight has fallen over the hopes<lb/> of entertained by the dweller of this house&#44; yet&#44; I look and ponder search and<lb/> discover a living spring of comfort.  Sorrow Bereavement A visitation but not a deso&#45;<lb/>&#45;lation abides here.  The wife turn from your bosom.<lb/>  O my brother has bequeathed to you a sweet pledge of<lb/> conjugal affection tenderness.  Cherish it as such&#59; it is meant<lb/> for your solace and for the bliss of the creature sphered<lb/> in immortality.  Let your a watchful care of the<lb/> son&#44; for whom his mother <sic>yeilded</sic> a precious life existence in her<lb/> blooming years&#44; be your watchful sensible study&#44;<lb/> bestow upon his training constant solicitude<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Teach his innocent lips to utter in sweet reverential accents the name<lb/> of her that gave him birth&#59; fitly honor your own self her memory&#44; that<lb/> he may learn to place it as a signet ring upon<lb/> his hand finger&#44; and a beacon light before his eyes.  A con&#45;<lb/>&#45;fiding friend&#44; not less than a revered venerated parent you will<lb/> become to that son&#59; each pulsation of his young heart<lb/> responding to yours&#44; will be celestially grateful to his<lb/> sainted mother&#59; to her who lavished upon you the<lb/> tenderest devotion.  Your life joined in harmony accord<lb/> of sentiments with that of your child will glide away by<lb/> contentedly&#44; recalling the associations of a short but<lb/> delight some past&#44; and forming noble aspirations for<lb/> a long future.  So do my instincts&#44; which<lb/> I interpret as the voice of God&#44; speak at this most<lb/> solemn hour of a terrestrial separation.  Oh&#33;  May my<lb/> words be productive of abundant comfort.<lb/></p>
            <p>Towards you&#44; O father of my young deceased friend&#44; my yearning<lb/> soul now turns yearns.  Afflictions have often ex compressed you<lb/> around&#44; and I have stood prayfully over the remains of many who<lb/> bore your family name&#44; but this loss is attended with sur&#45;<lb/>&#45;roundings breathing the keenest grief.  Verily&#44; your faith has<lb/> been indeed severely sorely tried.  Pained and perplexed I<lb/> remain in contemplation&#44; but I shall not waver<lb/> always will I believe<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>that our Creator is a merciful Lord&#44; taking pleasure in our<lb/> happiness&#44; not in our anguish.  Who am I fallible short sighted mortal&#44; that shall dare<lb/> say&#44; &#34;no wise purpose was to be accomplished by the present<lb/> bereavement&#34;&#63;  May it not be God&#39;s will to purify your<lb/> existence thus sevenfold&#44; as silver is purified in fire&#63;  To uplift<lb/> your mind heavenward&#44; while yet treading the earth&#63;...<lb/> Oh&#33; my sorrow&#45;stricken friend&#33;  Rise even above this piercing stroke.<lb/>  Joys are in store for your advancing years age.  The child of<lb/> your imparadised Esther may become an exhaustless source<lb/> of pleasure&#44; a crown to his sire&#44; a glory to his people.  To<lb/> behold him&#44; as he shall step forward under the guidance<lb/> of wisdom to the conquest of ennobling qualities&#44; will procure<lb/> you ineffable consolation.  Nay more&#58; your<lb/> surviving daughters&#44; dutiful and reverential and loving<lb/> will divert your thoughts from gloom&#44; and so illumine your<lb/> mental horizon that only what is cheering and eleva&#45;<lb/>&#45;ting and superlative good is offered to your views.<lb/>  Come brother&#44; like a chief who brings those under his<lb/> command closer together&#44; in proportion as others have drop&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed by the way&#44;k so do you draw all you hold dear<lb/> nearer to themselves and to your heart.  The wish to<lb/> seek their welfare and domestic home <sic>tranquillity</sic>&#44; will lend you<lb/> new strength&#44; fresher energy&#44; till you experience&#44; as told in Holy Writ&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>you feel &#34;that former troubles have been forgotten.&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>And you L. C. &#38; E.&#44; be a threefold chord that will never be<lb/> severed&#44; firm in the determination to cling to your father&#44; in<lb/> indissoluble love&#44; and in aiding to raise the motherless child&#44;<lb/> in watching over his bodily growth&#44; but also over his moral and religious<lb/> progress.  The undying spirit of your gentle sister&#44; will<lb/> joy in your efforts and bless them and pray to the Supreme<lb/> Lord that felicity endurable be your lot.<lb/></p>
            <p>And you relatives of the bereft&#44; let your sympathy be practically<lb/> evinced&#44; and steadily continued.  It will lel lighten a burden<lb/> of affliction and increase contentment.  I beseech<lb/> Him from whom godly inspirations flow&#44; to infuse in<lb/> all of you Divine tender compassion&#44; and that to may let His Divine<lb/> grace may abide rest with you&#44; as you will contribute to the<lb/> solace and consolation of the afflicted sorrowful distressed.  Grant it<lb/> O Father&#33;  Thou who employest human agencies to effect<lb/> blissful ends.  Make us all instrumental in chasing<lb/> away sorrow&#44; in leading on gladness into the habitation<lb/> of mourning.  May we all be thus beneficently engaged<lb/> here below&#44; and receive Thy approving smile when we shall<lb/> be summoned to contemplate Thy showing shining trult truths above.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
