<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF2_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_1_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_1_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_1_7v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>An exegetical lecture<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Beloved hearers&#33;  It has been my aim &#40;though probably with&#45;<lb/>&#45;out success through my deficiencies&#41; to unfold before your<lb/> eyes the beauties and truths treasured up in Holy Writ.<lb/>  Accordingly I have seized every opportunity to draw your<lb/> attention to certain passages in the respective lesson of<lb/> the Sabbath&#44; which might furnish your minds with new and<lb/> useful ideas.  But I confess that had I made the exegesis<lb/> of the Bible the exclusive subject of my discourses&#44; I should<lb/> not have imparted one a thousandth part of the profitable<lb/> knowledge to be derived from that heavenly book.<lb/>  A long experience has convinced me that only an incessant<lb/> study of the original&#44; can exhibit in its true light the<lb/> matchless worth of the code which is Jacob&#39;s inheritance.<lb/>  No exposition however accurate can reproduce the weighty<lb/> sense of the sacred text.  We may by its means sip<lb/> some refreshing water from the spring of wisdom&#44; but<lb/> it will never enable us to quaff thereat.  It may<lb/> be argued&#44; that such result is the common lot of any<lb/> translated work&#44; for&#44; each language possesses peculiarities&#44;<lb/> which are totally lost when couched in a foreign diction.<lb/>  But while I admit the correctness of such reasoning&#44; I<lb/> contend that neither in extent nor in importance is the<lb/> difference&#44; in other cases&#44; so great as with regard to the Hebrew.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>The Rabbis have said&#44; that when the Greek translation of<lb/> the Pentateuch was executed by order of Ptolomey Philadelphus&#44;<lb/> darkness envelopped the earth&#59; which hyperbole undoubtedly<lb/> signifies how&#44; through that human production&#44; erroneous<lb/> conceptions would be formed touching the word of the inspired<lb/> legislator.  No&#44; my friends&#33; a thorough acquaintance with<lb/> the language&#44; which is the bounden duty of Israelites to learn&#44;<lb/> is solely capable to open our understanding to the compre&#45;<lb/>&#45;hensive meaning and spirit of the volumes we revere.<lb/>  The section of this morning offers many striking instances&#44;<lb/> in support of my opinion&#44; but for the sake of brevity&#44;<lb/> I will cite only two.  And in commencing with the very<lb/> first verse of the Parasha we have recited&#44; I need but repeat<lb/> the general interpretation to demonstrate its inadequacy to<lb/> express its import &#34;and God spoke unto Moses&#44; and said<lb/> unto him&#44; I am the Lord&#34; I may have formed a wrong<lb/> judgment&#44; but I consider that the proper definition of<lb/> that sentence&#44; will ever remain concealed to him who is<lb/> not versed in the sacred tongue.  Moses had assumed<lb/> with extreme hesitation the task imposed by the Deity.<lb/>  The know consciousness of his want of eloquence&#44; and his exceeding<lb/> meekness combined to deter him from confronting a mighty<lb/> king&#44; and demanding the freedom of his bondmen.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Yet&#44; inspired with commiseration for the oppressed and assured<lb/> of his brothers&#39; cooperation&#44; he had at length undertaken the<lb/> momentous charge.  But when the deeper anguish of his fellow&#45;<lb/>believers&#44; evinced that his zealous endeavours had been abortive&#59;<lb/> that instead of loosening the fetters that chained his victims&#44; the<lb/> tyrant had rivetted them&#44; the heart of the son of Amram grieved<lb/> to its core&#44; and he laid his complaint before the Lord.  To comfort<lb/> his servant&#44; and reanimate his gloomy spirits&#44; God appeared<lb/> to him and said &#91;Hebrew&#93; I am &#34;Adonai&#34; But what<lb/> does that single word contain&#44; must the untutored in Hebrew<lb/> ask&#44; that it could suffice to arouse the prophet form his<lb/> despondency&#44; and breathe into him an unflinching faith&#63;...<lb/> In answer to that query&#44; the learned will show the lack of<lb/> a corresponding term in any language to express a word&#44; each<lb/> letter of which bears a distinct meaning.  For&#44; Yod&#44; Ha Vav&#44;<lb/> Ha&#44;&#45;&#45;that ineffable name uttered only by the high priests<lb/> in the sanctuary&#45;&#45;denotes not alone the self&#45;sustaining<lb/> existence of the Eternal&#44; but also his attributes of mercy.  All<lb/> the nations of antiquity recognized some superior being&#44; pos&#45;<lb/>&#45;sessed of unlimited powers&#44; whom in their respective language tongues&#44;<lb/> they styled a God&#59; but Israel alone has a word in his<lb/> language&#44; which comprises the Omniscience&#44; the Omnipre&#45;<lb/>&#45;sence&#44; the Omnipotence&#44; and boundless goodness of Him&#44; who<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>never had a beginning.  It is well known by every<lb/> scholar&#44; that though the punctuations of that adorable name&#44;<lb/> direct us to pronounce it &#34;Adonai&#44;&#34; or&#44; the Lord we worship&#44;<lb/> still its literal formation&#44; impresses on the mind the grand<lb/> truth&#44; that the future&#45;&#45;&#40;indicated by the Yod&#45;&#45;&#41; is&#44; like the<lb/> present &#40;pointed out by the Ha &#38; Vav&#45;&#41; revealed before the<lb/> supreme&#44; and that the present past &#40;signified by the last Ha&#45;&#41;<lb/> is made to accord with his wise and beneficent govern&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment of the universe and its inhabitants.  So that if<lb/> we desired to convey a faint idea of the knowledge com&#45;<lb/>&#45;municated to Moses by the term under discussion&#44; we would<lb/> be obliged thus to paraphrase it.  &#34;I am He that liveth<lb/> eternally&#44; that guideth current events&#44; and remembereth all<lb/> that has past since the creation&#44; rewording the righteous<lb/> according to his piety&#44; and meteing out to the wicked his deserts.&#34;<lb/>  For&#44; it was by so sublime an imparting that the Almighty sought<lb/> to <sic>dispell</sic> the sorrow occasioned at the sight of unrelenting per&#45;<lb/>&#45;secution&#44; and to strengthen the hand of his missionary of<lb/> liberty.  Weherefore he continued&#58; The fathers of the nation&#44;<lb/> whose enfranchisement thou must accomplish&#44; acknowledged<lb/> me as the Dispenser of all good &#34;El Shaddai&#34; The God&#44; who<lb/> supplies the maintenance of his creatures&#44; with the solicitude<lb/> which the loving mother exhibits when nurturing her infant at<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>the breast&#59; but thou whom I have more brightly illumined by the<lb/> revelation of my higher attributes&#44; wilt understand that it is<lb/> my well as it is in my power&#44; to <sic>fulfil</sic> the promise I made to<lb/> the patriarchs.  And notwithstanding that the actual position<lb/> of their descendants seems to human eye to preclude all hope&#44;<lb/> yet they shall march to freedom&#44; and become my to me a people<lb/> of treasure.  Such is&#44; my dear Brethren&#33; the pith of the<lb/> sentence wherewith the lesson of this Sabbath opens&#44; and of the<lb/> five that immediately succeed it&#59; all of which depending<lb/> in a great measure upon the correct definition of the unutter&#45;<lb/>&#45;able name of the Supreme&#44; prove the necessity of our drawing<lb/> instruction from the original source&#44; instead of gathering it<lb/> from small small streams.<lb/></p>
            <p>The second passage to by which I propose to substantiate my<lb/> argument&#44; and for the comprehension of which&#44; I am indebted<lb/> to the writing of the renowned Naftali Hetz Wessel&#44; occurs<lb/> towards the end of our Parasha.  Among the punishments<lb/> which the obduracy of Pharaoh brought upon Egypt&#44; there<lb/> came a terrible storm accompanied with hail&#44; which de&#45;<lb/>&#45;vastated the land.  Subdued by bodily suffering&#44; but not<lb/> by sincere contrition&#44; the refractory king&#44; besought Moses&#44;<lb/> as he was wont&#44; to pray for the removal of that infliction.<lb/>  The servant of God&#44; raised his voice to heaven&#44; &#38; calm ensued.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>But in recording that fact&#44; the Hebrew uses an expression<lb/> which is imperfectly rendered in the accepted version &#34;And<lb/> the rain was not poured out &#40;any more&#41; upon the earth&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> But the verb &#91;Hebrew&#93; is not equivalent to&#44; &#34;pouring out&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> or &#91;Hebrew&#93; would correspond to that English phrase.  Yet the<lb/> sacred text must no doubt appear strangely worded&#44; to him<lb/> who will not ponder thereon&#44; for&#44; it would read &#34;The rain was not<lb/> melted down upon the earth&#34;  But&#44; mark well&#44; my friend&#44;<lb/> for&#44; that which at the first sight is deemed inapplicable&#44; will<lb/> be adjudged scientifically precise&#44; when scanned with serious<lb/> reflection.  The language in which the Pentateuch was transmitted<lb/> to us&#44; is that which the Eternal spoke&#44; when He communicated<lb/> his will to man&#44; consequently it partakes of the perfection of<lb/> the celestial speaker.  So that in this instance&#44; what excites<lb/> our surprise&#44; because singular&#44; has treasured up a knowledge<lb/> at which the world has arrived only after thousands of years&#44;<lb/> and most profound researches&#59; namely&#44; the causes which producing rain.<lb/>  That the exhalations from the earth&#44; and watery evaporations are<lb/> converted into clouds&#44; when at a certain height in the atmosphere&#44;<lb/> is a theory universally accepted.  But how those condensed<lb/> bodies are again dissolved into a fluid&#44; and made to drop<lb/> down&#44; is a question that has engaged the attention of the learned<lb/> from the remotest ages.  It has been said&#44; that as they come<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>in close contact&#44; they strike against each other and occasion their<lb/> decomposition.  But that that action would be insufficient by<lb/> itself to effect the breaking and precipitating of a compactness<lb/> of vapours&#44; becomes obvious&#44; when we bear in mind that in<lb/> Egypt&#44; for example&#44; the falling of rain is an exceptional occur&#45;<lb/>&#45;rence.  Yet it is surrounded by seas&#44; and its celebrated Nile<lb/> irrigates the entire land.  Can it be supposed that throughout<lb/> the year&#44; and under a skry of intense heat&#44; the Sun has no<lb/> power to absorb the moisture emanating from those great<lb/> sources &#38; form clouds therewith&#63;  Reason and the senses<lb/> answer negatively.  If then it is so&#44; beyond contradiction&#44; we<lb/> must necessarily conclude that together with the mutual<lb/> pressure of the clouds&#44; to which I have alluded above&#44; a<lb/> stronger force must combine in opening them&#44; and causing<lb/> their contents to be discharged.  And that likewise to the<lb/> absence of that force&#44; is the want of rain to be ascribed.<lb/>  Now&#44; my Brethren&#33; what that force is&#44; which remained unknown<lb/> to the scientific world until within a comparatively modern age&#44;<lb/> Holy Writ teaches in one simple phrase &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;And the rain was not melted down upon the earth&#34;  The<lb/> subtle substance which produces liquefaction&#44; departed from<lb/> the Egyptian atmosphere.  In short&#44; it is electric<lb/> fire that actually dissolves the accumulated exhalations&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>when they distill water upon the ground.  And that self&#45;same<lb/> powerful agent which at the bidding of its Creator had brought<lb/> on proud Myriam as fearful a visitation as it was uncommon&#44;<lb/> ceased to act at the petition of the faithful messenger of the Lord.<lb/>  The country which by an ordinance of Providence is fertilized<lb/> through the overflowing of its rivers&#44; witnessed no more what<lb/> it experienced&#44; through its inequity&#44; in the days of Moses.  For&#44;<lb/> the vapors it raises are not forced downward by electrical<lb/> impulse.  And the interesting knowledge derived from<lb/> the passage at issue&#44; is graphically revealed&#44; if I may say so&#44;<lb/> in the philological composition of a sentence in the book of<lb/> Psalms &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;He causeth exhalations&#44;&#34; or&#44; literally&#44; what<lb/> can be uplifted&#44;&#34; to ascend from the bottom of the earth&#44;&#34; but as<lb/> they by themselves are unable to drop down again&#44; it continues<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;He made lightnings for the rain&#34; the fire they<lb/> contain separate the watery mass and it returns whence it came.<lb/>  And it beautifully concludes &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;He bringeth forth<lb/> wind out of his treasures&#59; the air put in motion&#44; drifts the rain<lb/> wheresoever God has designed.  Beloved hearers&#33;  The two<lb/> instances which I have adduced to prove the comprehensiveness<lb/> and vigour of the language which bears the impress of the<lb/> Almighty&#44; form but an insignificant minority to the evidences<lb/> that the student can discover while pondering on the original<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>text of the Scriptures.  Not without cause have our Rabbins called<lb/> it &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;the holy tongue&#34;&#44; for independently of the halo cast around<lb/> it at on the memorable day that Israel heard the Decalogue&#44; it<lb/> possesses an inherent sanctity.  Its very expressions are a health&#45;<lb/>&#45;ful knowledge to those who seek it its phrases are a fountain of wisdom.  Shall we then&#44;<lb/> my friends&#33; cast it away from our midst as unworthy of utterance&#63;<lb/>  Shall we follow the impure current of innovations&#44; and address<lb/> our God in languages comparably inferior to that of our prophets<lb/> and Sages&#63;  Shall we cease to acknowledge our faith in those<lb/> blessed words&#44; which have ever thrilled the hearts of Israel&#44; and which<lb/> sound lifeless in the tongues of the gentiles&#63;  Oh never&#33;  Let every<lb/> one of us who has been reared in ignorance of his national language&#44;<lb/> privately commune with his Maker in that which he best com&#45;<lb/>&#45;prehends&#44; but let him not attempt deliberately or by indirect means<lb/> to remodel therewith our public worship.  Let him rather atone<lb/> for his neglect&#44; and betake himself to a study&#44; which will open<lb/> to him treasures&#44; not of material&#44; but of spiritual gain&#59; that<lb/> is&#44; the truths and beauties of the heavenly volumes.  And if<lb/> age or circumstances withhold from him that important acquisition&#44;<lb/> let him procure it for his children.  In lieu of cramming their young<lb/> minds with learning&#44; which&#44; in all likelihood&#44; will prove superfluous in<lb/> their future walks of life&#44; let him employ their faculties in mastering<lb/> a language&#44; which awakens invigorating thoughts&#44; noble aspirations&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>universal love.  Accept&#44; my friends&#33; my humble advice&#44; as My friends&#33;  Prompted by a sincere desire to render my scanty knowledge<lb/> you may dispose of my feeble strenuous efforts in disseminating the conducive to the dissemination of our holy language.  Deeply imbued with a sense of the duties<lb/> knowledge of our holy language. which my position demands of me&#44; I have&#44; at various times offered gratuitous instruction.  A few availed themselves thereof&#44; but the majority &#43;  And may the Almighty<lb/> grant every one of us acumen of intellect to learn with ease&#44;<lb/> a strong memory to retain our knowledge&#44; facility to impart<lb/> it to our fellow&#45;beings&#44; and an unflinching will to observe<lb/> and execute the spiritual teaching of his inspired servants<lb/> and Israel&#39;s sages.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            
            <p>&#43; disregarded the call.  This day&#44; on which I have endeavoured to<lb/> impress on your mind the necessity of cultivating the field of Hebrew<lb/> literature&#44; let my exhortation be accompanied with the frequently<lb/> repeated assurance&#44; that my strenuous efforts are at the disposal<lb/> of the Congregation&#44; whose spiritual improvement I have at heart&#44;<lb/> whether it be by public or private tuition.  And may the<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
