<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF18_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff18_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff18_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff18_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff18_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff18_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff18_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff18_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff18_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff18_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff18_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff18_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff18_2_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff18_2_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff18_2_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff18_2_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff18_2_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>On the occasion of dedicating<lb/>
                2 Sepharim at the Netherland<lb/>
                Synagogue.<lb/></p>
            
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>A prayer for the dedication of a new Sepher<lb/></p>
            <p>Holy Law&#44; the unerring manifestation of the will of the Most High&#33;<lb/>  Let our greetings betoken ardency of zeal&#59; the unceasing devotion<lb/> of our lives to the cause of truth&#44; thou wast commissioned to<lb/> advance.  Holy Law that speakest in accents divine.  May<lb/> thy coming in our midst&#44; thrill the faithful with spiritual delight.<lb/>  And in like manner as their hearts should ever beat high with love<lb/> for Thy celestial Author&#44; so let their understanding be ever illumined<lb/> by thy teachings.  For&#44; verily when our reason shall have fathomed<lb/> the depth of wisdom wherewith thou teemest&#44; our eagerness to be<lb/> guided by they word will increase&#59; and unwavering will become our<lb/> resolves to abide solely by thy directions.  Holy Law&#33;  This season<lb/> around which gladsome memories cluster&#44; this season in which thou<lb/> hast bid us rejoice&#44; has been chosen by thy votaries to show<lb/> the honor&#44; and I an humble adherent of thy dictates&#44; am sought<lb/> for that I may petition for the reward that their action may have<lb/> won.  Oh breathe thou unto me the word I may utter&#44; for thus<lb/> will the prayer I offer be acceptable to the Lord&#44; and it will also<lb/> propitiate His grace.<lb/></p>
            <p>Almighty Creator&#33;  Universal Father&#33; but the special Guardian<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>and Protector of the adorers of Thy Unity&#33;  Grant that the deed now performed<lb/> by the Congregation&#44; may yield an abundance of blessings.<lb/>  May the effect of Thy heavenly boons be discernible in all their<lb/> walks of life.  May they may be proven by their me virtuous demeanour<lb/> towards as members of the social family&#44; by their piety as descendents<lb/> of the righteous patriarchs&#44; by their fidelity to the divine trust as<lb/> missionaries of Thy eternal verities.  Grant that the imparting<lb/> of Thy servants who will this day address Thy suppliants in<lb/> language drawn from the source of purity may incite them<lb/> further to the pursuit of integrity&#44; of sincerity and goodness&#59;<lb/> for when they shall have woven that threefold chord their existence will<lb/> be indissolubly bound with Thee&#44; who art the absolute Essence of<lb/> perfection.  May the heads of this organization follow<lb/> the tenets enunciated at Sinai&#44; and let their commanding influence<lb/> be reflected in the doings of the whole religious body.<lb/></p>
            <p>Let harmony signalize the dealings of this portion of thy chosen<lb/> race&#59; and may they fully realize that the inheriting of spiritual<lb/> privileges entails therewith upon the recipients of the discharge<lb/> of momentous duties towards the community of their brethren&#44;<lb/> and towards mankind at large.  May this Synagogue<lb/> be the exponent of Thy the principles of the Torah&#44; and secure<lb/> its general recognition as a dwelling whereon Thou mayest<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>vouchsafe to rest to let Thy Divinity rest.  Grant that<lb/> the respective home of this assemblage may&#44; like their Sanctuary&#44;<lb/> reveal constant obedience to Thy behests&#44; and even as their habitations so<lb/> may also their vocations obviously evince that rectitude is their<lb/> standard&#44; and that he is can be called a veritable Israelite&#44; whose conduct<lb/> represents all that is good&#44; holy and true<sic>&#44;</sic>.  May vainglory<lb/> never be harbored within in this sacred spot&#44; but humility distinguish<lb/> the service tendered unto Thee within these hallowed courts.<lb/>  Grant that as upon this day&#44; on which the ceremonies performed<lb/> tacitly signify our attachment to the olden law faith&#44; so may<lb/> they all who worship here&#44; ever exclaim and believe that<lb/> the instruction Law Thou hast commanded for us unto Moses&#44; will ever<lb/> remain the heritage of the Congregation of Jacob.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>What means the festive appearance which this edifice<lb/> present&#63;  Why the choral songs that have resounded<lb/> through its isles&#63;  A solemn assembly is held<lb/> by Hebrews upon a day of no peculiar sacredness to<lb/> Israel.  Whom do you&#44; dear Brethren&#33; thus delight to honor&#63;<lb/>  Ah&#33;  I recognize thee&#44; the just cause of this celebration&#33;<lb/>  Word of the Lord&#33;  May thy chosen custodians ever<lb/> greet thy entrance into their holy shrines.  May<lb/> they to the end of time&#44; assign to thee a place most<lb/> conspicuous in their dwellings of prayer.  Rest as<lb/> It behooves them to evince reverential awe for the<lb/> messenger of the Most High.  Rest then amidst<lb/>  the faithful&#44; thou bearer of happy tidings.  They<lb/> who chose emphatically to be called &#34;B&#233;ne Israel&#34;&#44;<lb/> will watch for thy preservation.  They will keep<lb/> thee unscathed.  Am I&#44; then&#44;  my<lb/> fellow&#45;believers&#44; so to interpret the ceremony just<lb/> performed&#63;  Does it in very deed stand as the<lb/> exponent of your religious principles&#63;  I dare not<lb/> impugn your motives.  I trust that you are actuated<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>by pure intentions.  But I have been asked<lb/> briefly to speak on the occasion that has brought<lb/> us together&#44; and I must seek to improve it to my<lb/> own advantage.  I cannot permit an opportunity to<lb/> escape&#44; by which I may obtain some compensation fo to<lb/> my exertions.  Learn the price.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;He that admonisheth a man&#44; will after&#45;<lb/>&#45;wards find more favor than he who flattereth with<lb/> the tongue.&#34;  Your good opinion&#44; my dear Brethren&#44;<lb/> is the goal which I am striving to reach.  And I will<lb/> pave my way thereto by holding to a divine instrument&#59;<lb/> even to Truth &#91;Hebrew&#93;.<lb/></p>
            <p>Well then&#44; my beloved hearers&#33;  Willing to judge you<lb/> all most favorably&#44; I&#44; still&#44; am not so certain that every one within reach of my voice views the present<lb/> celebration in the light which alone can lend to it<lb/> importance.  I will be explicit.  Two copies<lb/> of a manuscript have been deposited in this holy ark.<lb/>  The antiquary will regard it with special interest&#44; as<lb/> a monument of the remotest time.  The wise cannot<lb/> fail to have discovered therein the parent of human<lb/> cv civilization.  But for you&#44; &#34;O children of Israel&#44;&#34; that<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>scroll has a much deeper significance.  It represents<lb/> the mandate of our Sovereign Legislator.  It is the un&#45;<lb/>&#45;changeable will of the God of Sinai&#44; and which<lb/> you cannot a set aside&#44; without proving recreant to a<lb/> heavenly trust.  For alike to the highest and to the<lb/> humblest among us&#44; is that heavenly imparting an<lb/> inalienable heirloom &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;The law which Moses commanded us&#44; is the inheritance of<lb/> the Congregation of Jacob&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;  Must<lb/> I interpret it to be simply the possession of the poste&#45;<lb/>&#45;rity of kings&#63; remarks our Rabbins.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Or&#44; must I understand it as being an object which only<lb/> the descendants of people of lower ranks should treasure<lb/> up&#63;  No&#44; it is written&#44; &#34;Ye are standing this day all of<lb/> you&#44; before the Lord your God&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> None is excluded.  The opulence of the most successful<lb/> Hebrew man&#44; cannot exonerate him from any of the<lb/> duties which God has imposed&#59; nor can the pressing wants<lb/> of the indigent&#44; be an exemption therefrom.<lb/></p>
            <p>Dear Brethren&#33;  If the outward tokens of respect&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>which attended the admission of those volumes in<lb/> your sanctuary are an expression of your acceptance of<lb/> that truth.  If you feel devotionally glad that your<lb/> synagogue has been the recipient of that gift&#44; because<lb/> you cherish the ancestral bequest&#59; because you take<lb/> pleasure in reading from a book&#44; which forms the<lb/> standard of your actions&#59; then the festival now held&#44;<lb/> assumes a grand&#44; a sublime aspect.  But if you consi&#45;<lb/>&#45;der that you have graced the oracle of the Lord&#39;s house&#44;<lb/> by placing therein the law of Horeb&#44; though its summons<lb/> have ceased to awaken responsive feelings in your breasts&#44;<lb/> then the ceremonies through which you have gone&#44; are futile.<lb/>  For&#44; what honor can He receive whose teachings are pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;served in vellum&#44; and encased in ornaments&#44; but they<lb/> are neither heeded nor pondered upon&#63;<lb/></p>
            <p>I do not undervalue the merit of furnishing the dwelling<lb/> of prayer with written copies of the Mosaic code.  On the<lb/> contrary&#58; I commend you&#44; O congregation Ben&#233; Israel&#44; for<lb/> having sought to add to their number.  For they are<lb/> greatly to be prized more than the architectural beauties&#44;<lb/> and sumptuous structures.  And I think&#44; my two generous<lb/> Brethren&#33; whose presents have given occasion to our religious<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>gathering.  But knowing how liable we all<lb/> are to self&#45;delusions&#44; I have come before you with<lb/> a word of friendly caution.  For&#44; &#34;the commandment is<lb/> a lamp&#44; but the Law is the Light&#44; and the admonitions<lb/> of instruction are the way of life&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Observe&#44; my dear hearers&#33;  The adhering<lb/> to some precept of the heavenly Legislation&#44; has been com&#45;<lb/>&#45;pared to an object which can illumine our steps only for<lb/> a time&#59; while the exemplifying of all the celestial behests&#44;<lb/> has been likened to the radiance of the Sun&#44; which shines<lb/> perpetually&#59; purposing to signify that an Israelite can&#45;<lb/>&#45;not hope to be encircled by the arm of the Lord&#44; and screened<lb/> from perils&#44; unless the services he renders to the Great<lb/> Master&#44; are continuous and thorough.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> To illustrate that sentence of King Solomon&#44; our Sages<lb/> in the Medrash&#44; have imagined the case of an individual<lb/> starting on a journey at night.  His path lies among<lb/> steeps and precipices.  But while <sic>envelopped</sic> in dark&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness&#44; he finds a taper.  By its means some of the<lb/> obstacles which impede his course are overcome.  Yet&#44; he<lb/> is in constant danger&#59; and only when the bright luminary<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>of the day breaks forth&#44; he can walk perfectly<lb/> at large.  In like manner&#44; my dear Brethren&#44; will<lb/> it happen with us.  A partial obedience to the<lb/> will of God&#44; may relieve us from some of the ills which<lb/> encompass our existence here below&#44; but if we cling un&#45;<lb/>&#45;waveringly to the whole Law&#44; then evil will become<lb/> pointless against us.  We shall be safe&#44; though<lb/> the grave be yawning beneath our steps &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> The truth of the Lord shall be our shield and buckler.<lb/>  Now&#44; it is because I earnestly wish that you may<lb/> be so happily circumstanced&#44; that I have spoken in<lb/> this strain.  And of all times and seasons the present<lb/> is certainly the fittest for offering admonitions of instruction&#44;<lb/> leading to the way of life.  One week hence our<lb/> deeds will pass in review before the tribunal of the<lb/> Omniscient Judge.  The trespasses hidden from human<lb/> eyes&#44; and those which brought scandal to Israel&#44; will<lb/> be equally stamped upon with a mark of god&#39;s displeasure<lb/> yet&#44; if we can set against them an array of virtue&#44; or&#44;<lb/> if at least&#44; signs of contrition and repentance can be<lb/> produced&#44; the unbounded mercy of the Lord may<lb/> lengthen our days&#44; and award unto us health and continued<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>prosperity.  Oh&#33; let our assembling on this<lb/> occasion be effect a glorious end.  My voice<lb/> may have failed to impress&#44;  Our Torah&#44; which is the<lb/> personified wisdom of the book of Proverbs&#44; calls upon us.<lb/>  With pe From the height of her standing&#44; she addresses<lb/> all with persuasive eloquence&#44; and counsels a return to<lb/> God&#44; by a demeanour consistent with the rules of<lb/> morality&#44; not of with the dica dictates of charity and piety.<lb/>  My voice may have failed to impress&#59; but you will lend<lb/> an attentive ear to the voice of that heavenly monitor&#44; and<lb/> with one sweet accord of feelings&#44; answer &#34;Yes&#44;&#34; the law<lb/> which Moses commanded us&#44; is &#38; will ever be the valued inheritance of the<lb/> congregation of Jacob.&#34;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
