<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF13_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_1_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>139</p>
            <p>An address at the funeral of Dr A. De Sola<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>An address at the funeral of Dr Ab De Sola.<lb/></p>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> This Rabbinical sentence&#44; which savors of Orientalism&#44;<lb/> is&#44; in the present melancholy instance&#44; applicable<lb/> to its very letter.  &#34;When a wise man dies&#44; he leaves<lb/> a void which cannot be filled&#59; when a king dies another<lb/> will be found to supply his place.&#34;<lb/></p>
                <p>Not with flattery which a public approves of&#59; not<lb/> with exaggerations which an audience applauds do I<lb/> come to perform funeral obsequies&#44; but with a profound<lb/> belief that the loss sustained is in all truth irreparable.<lb/>  Judaism in which I recognize a God&#45;given trust never<lb/> to be bartered away nor surrendered at any price&#44; found<lb/> in Abraham De Sola an un<sic>yeilding</sic> defender.  In his early<lb/> days he put on the armor with the ardency of youth&#44;<lb/> and not once did he desert his post&#59; not once did he suffer<lb/> the Siren that has allured many&#44; to sing him into<lb/> self&#45;forgetfulness.  That is glory to man&#58; to have<lb/> arrived at the gates which lead to eternity&#44; and looking<lb/> back on the path trodden&#44; perceive that the steps taken<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>unswervedly followed a line of rectitude.  But<lb/> we&#44; who still remain on the side where mortality<lb/> abides&#44; look aghast at the closing of those gates&#44; which<lb/> had flung open to admit the righteous.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;When a wise man dies&#44; he leaves behind<lb/> a void which cannot be filled.&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>I do not wish to wrong the living&#44; while doing<lb/> justice to the dead&#44; but as I survey the field in<lb/> which the departed long labored&#44; I fail to discover&#44;<lb/> among my acquaintances&#44; a man that can bring to<lb/> the work the mental acumen&#44; unflinching principles<lb/> and ripe experience of the deceased&#44; and thus reconcile<lb/> intellectual Orthodoxy to the loss it must now bear.<lb/>  For know ye all that the conservation of Abraham<lb/> De Sola was not simply a natural sequence of the<lb/> law of heredity&#59; it was not obedience to instincts.  It<lb/> proceeded from searchings&#44; deep and conscientious&#59; search&#45;<lb/>&#45;ings which began in the age of boyhood and never<lb/> ceased until the heart ceased to throb.<lb/></p>
            <p>I shall not deny the effects of home training and<lb/> general surrounding.  The tuition of a very scholarly<lb/> father&#44; ministering in a Sanctuary&#44; which recalls<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>the efforts of a Menasseh Ben Israel&#59; the<lb/> impartings of divines renowned for their piety<lb/> nor less than their lore&#44; must have needs largely<lb/> contributed to the moulding of my friend&#39;s thoughts.<lb/>  Yet&#44; paying due homage to David Aaron De Sola and<lb/> the Portuguese Synagogue of London&#59; to Dr Loe Loewe<lb/> and Dr Raphall&#44; I still hold that the merit of having<lb/> kept fast by the old flag and lifted it high&#44; chal&#45;<lb/>&#45;lenging for it universal respect&#44; is mainly atrribu&#45;<lb/>&#45;table to the reflectingly hard student himself.<lb/>  He did not feel satisfied to lie supinely&#44; resting<lb/> on the results of other minds.  As he saw many&#44;<lb/> whose early education may not have widely differed from<lb/> his own fall back from the beaten road&#44; and plan out<lb/> a new course of action for the preservation of a Mon&#45;<lb/>theistic people and the Sinaic covenant&#44; he pondered<lb/> well on the novel means conducive to that end.<lb/>  He found them woefully wanting&#44; and with that<lb/> courage&#44; that daringness which deep&#45;set convictions<lb/> alone can inspire&#44; he proclaimed conservatism&#44; as<lb/></p> 
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Israel&#39;s saving principles&#59; preached it on the<lb/> pulpit&#44; expounded it in the press&#44; and illustrated<lb/> in a life which shed lasting credit upon the ancient<lb/> faith.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;When For a wise<lb/> man dies&#44; he leaves a void&#44; which cannot be filled.&#34;<lb/>  For Abraham De Sola bore a title conferred by an in&#45;<lb/>&#45;stitution in which his learning set for him a<lb/> professor&#39;s chair.  He appended to his name the<lb/> epithet of &#34;Doctor of Law&#34;&#44; as an evidence of the<lb/> appreciation of non&#45;Israelites&#44; for a consistent Jew&#44;<lb/> whose varied knowledge <sic>benefitted</sic> the community at<lb/> large.<lb/></p>
                <p>Montreal in Canada will becomingly rehears the praises<lb/> of one of her inhabitants&#44; who during thirty five years<lb/> directed his teaching and his counsel to the forma&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion of a well&#45;bred and usefully instructed generation.<lb/>  M&#39;Gill college will make public acknowledgment of<lb/> the services rendered by a member of its Faculty&#44;<lb/> whose ripe judgment and dignified demeanour ra en&#45;<lb/>&#45;hanced its prestige.  The Congregation&#44; to whose<lb/> ministry my lamented brother was called in the<lb/> spring of his manhood&#44;&#45;&#45;bereft of so noble a Guide&#45;&#45;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>will give expression to its sorrow&#44; and the city<lb/> of London&#44; the place of his birth and of his love&#44; and<lb/> the people who still assemble at Bevis Marks&#44; within<lb/> these venerated halls&#44; where the boy was wont to make<lb/> his devotions&#44; and those also who worship in Dukes<lb/> Place and other spots of the great metropolis will<lb/> mention with reverence and pride the distinguished scholar<lb/> and professor&#44; the divine and author&#44; unhappily called<lb/> hence ere he had gathered all the honors in store<lb/> to cheer his advancing age.<lb/></p>
            <p>But I who&#44; as a youth&#44; knew him as a youth in<lb/> England.  I who met him a few years later in<lb/> this new Continent&#44; where Providence had cast our lots&#44;<lb/> must nor at this solemn hour&#44; speak a word&#44; which<lb/> may attest the noble worth of my departed coreligionist<lb/> and colleague.  Thirty seven years ago we<lb/> were competitors for a position&#44; which neither of us obtained&#44;<lb/> but that rivalry did not create resentment rankling<lb/> in our breasts.  My opponent welcomed my arrival<lb/> in this country in a letter breathing friendship&#59;<lb/> his hand grasped mine fraternally when he visited<lb/> Philadelphia&#44; and seldom did he pass through it&#44; without<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>visiting his former competitor.  Our correspondence<lb/> continuing uninterruptedly over three decades has<lb/> been imm gratifying&#44; and if I introduced him to<lb/> some Italian scholars&#44; he reciprocated the favor with<lb/> deeds of thoughtful consideration.  Alas&#63; that the<lb/> hand which but a few weeks ago penned for me<lb/> words of kindliness&#44; is palsied in death.  Alas&#33; that<lb/> a wife whom he respected above himself &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> has lost the object of her tenderest affection&#59; a family<lb/> reared to virtue by his example and precept&#44; bemoan<lb/> the departure of him who was their shining crown.<lb/>  But that diadem is sparkling yet.  Never will<lb/> it be tarnished&#44; while the children still cling to<lb/> the principles which formed the standard and<lb/> guide of their father.  Should they forget their<lb/> descent from the Meldolas and the DeSolas&#44; and<lb/> part with those principles to win a deceptive popu&#45;<lb/>&#45;larity&#44; then...Oh no&#33;  Mount up to bliss&#44; spirit<lb/> of Abraham the faithful.  No fear of defection<lb/> in those thou still lovest&#44; shall obscure thy glory.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>They will honor thee by honoring the doctrines<lb/> thou didst bravely defend.  May so the house<lb/> of Israel cleave to to thy belief.  May it see that thou<lb/> hast not labored fruitlessly&#59; for though the sentence<lb/> of the Sages be in thy present instance case literally true&#44; yet<lb/> by the will and interposition of the ever&#45;living God&#44;<lb/> men may arise to proclaim like thyself historical<lb/> Judaism indestructible&#44; eternal.  And now<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
