<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF3_3</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1888-03" source="" attested="yes">16 March 1888</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_3_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_3_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_3_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_3_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_3_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_3_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_3_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_3_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_3_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_3_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_3_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_3_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>On my 37th anniversary<lb/>
                of the ministry.</p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  A practice quite prevalent among<lb/> clergymen&#44; is that of stating reporting periodically the<lb/> temporal condition of their respective churches.<lb/>  You have doubtless noticed it almost weekly<lb/> in our city papers.  I have read also of Jewish<lb/> Ministers also who&#44; at stated intervals&#44; will detain<lb/> their congregations with a detailed account of the<lb/> number of children they have named&#59; of marriages weddings and fu&#45;<lb/>&#45;nerals at which they have officiated.  To me<lb/> a presentation of such statistics appears value&#45;<lb/>&#45;less&#44; from a religious standpoint.  A natural<lb/> process it is to be born&#44; to become wedded get married and to<lb/> die.  When those events occur&#44; Church or Syna&#45;<lb/>&#45;gogal rites are generally called into requisition.<lb/>  Very few persons will then dispense with pastoral<lb/> services.  Surely&#44; that is no cause for special<lb/> gratulations.  Real advancement will not<lb/> be gauged by a measure of that character&#44; nor<lb/> even by the evidences of a swelling list of<lb/> pew&#45;holders&#44; but by the conversions made among<lb/> all classes&#44; and in all directions.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>The changing of vicious habits into the practice<lb/> actual exercise of virtues&#44; of sinful propensities into right&#45;<lb/>&#45;eous aspirations&#44; of inertness inactivity in the field of edu&#45;<lb/>&#45;cation into energetic active energetic cooperation&#44; of lukewarmness<lb/> into enthusiasm for what is useful and beneficial<lb/> to the human race.  That should be the proof test<lb/> of a shepherd&#39;s influence among his flock.  Jere&#45;<lb/>&#45;miah of old was assured by the Divine Word&#44; that he<lb/> would stand next to God who sent him forth to<lb/> chide and exhort&#44; if he could draw but one sunk<lb/> in shame out of his lowness and raise him<lb/> to a high plane &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Now&#58; it has been my greatest ambition&#44; during<lb/> the thirty seven years which I have just com&#45;<lb/>&#45;pleted in the service of this Congregation&#44; to<lb/> win the heavenly grace of my Master&#44; as promised<lb/> to the ancient prophet.  I craved for the a self<lb/> gratulation proceeding by the from my knowledge of men and<lb/> women of my the chosen race&#44; whom my endeavours brought<lb/> nearer to the God of Israel in humility and closer<lb/> to their fellow mortals in sentiments of charity<lb/> and of love and charity.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>I did not&#44; of course&#44; lightly esteem numeric&#45;<lb/>&#45;al strength&#44; for by its means alone I could work.<lb/>  With none to listen to my utterances&#44; or to my<lb/> delivering performance of our public worship&#44; I could accomplish<lb/> nothing.  Therefore in the same degree that a lessen&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing of our members by from various causes&#44; at different<lb/> periods of my ministration&#44; grieved me to the core&#44; so<lb/> did our occasional increase fill my heart with<lb/> profound satisfaction.  The Sages&#44; applying<lb/> figuratively a sentence from Proverbs&#44; tell us that<lb/> the King of the world is extolled when many crowds assem&#45;<lb/>&#45;ble to do Him homage at consecrated spots &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  I have tried my best utmost by the force of example to<lb/> make bring many to this minor sanctuary and let the latter resound with the voices<lb/> of Hebrews&#44; coming to glorifying our Sovereign Lord&#59;<lb/> and here I sought also opportunities to gain for Him loyal<lb/> adherents.<lb/></p>
            <p>But if I have ever distrusted my capacity to reach<lb/> the goal I strove for&#44; current events developments have discouraged<lb/> me completely.  I have discovered that the pabulum spiritual nutriment<lb/> in which the present generation feeds is not in my possession.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Formerly scriptural lessons applied<lb/> to our condition&#44; commanded attention&#59; admonishing<lb/> counsels&#44; respecting the preservation of our Jewish<lb/> distinctiveness&#44; would be considered in keeping with<lb/> the principles governing the Synagogue&#59; a mere spontaneous<lb/> popular chanting of time&#45;honored hymns and pray<lb/>&#45;ers would create an impression.  Not so at present.<lb/>  The books holding our prophetic teachings have<lb/> been made to given room to modern philosophies.  Hebrew<lb/> characteristics are preached against as stumbling<lb/> blocks in the way of progress.  Individuals must not<lb/> dare to disturb the harmony of non&#45;Israelitish<lb/> hired choristers.  Week after week pamphlets<lb/> embodying thoughts&#44; the current of which I often find<lb/> it too difficult to follow&#44; are sent to my address.  They<lb/> come form more than one city of the Union&#44;<lb/> as the utterances of ordained Rabbis&#44; whose po&#45;<lb/>&#45;pularity is growing immensely.  Farming a<lb/> criterion from what is submitted to my perusal&#44;<lb/> I must conclude that a radical change has taken<lb/> place&#59; and that what I might have hoped remotely to ac&#45;<lb/>&#45;complish heretofore&#44; is now a days altogether beyond my reach.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>To secure a hearing from the rising generation&#44;<lb/> a person must be abreast with the whole evolu&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion of science.  He must&#44; moreover&#44; cite German<lb/> and English authors with the same ease as I might<lb/> quote passages in Hebrew from in Holy Writ.  Unless a Minister<lb/> can display that rich equipment of learning&#44; he<lb/> may as well beg to be superannuated.  But<lb/> notwithstanding my unusually long continuance<lb/> in office&#44; I am not prepared&#44; and I hope trust<lb/> never to be compelled&#44; to make that request.<lb/>  There are&#44; my brethren&#44; various natures&#44; each having<lb/> its own pride.  Some are proud of their looks&#44; which<lb/> they take great pains to preserve to an advanced age&#59; others are<lb/> proud of their wealth&#44; which they deem the supremest<lb/> good and with which they will not part&#59;<lb/> some are proud of their learning&#44; which they will<lb/> seeking the every opportunity to pompously set it off.<lb/>  My pride&#45;&#45;pardon the freedom&#45;&#45;is my independ&#45;<lb/>&#45;ence.  Deeply touched&#44; as I am indeed deeply by the<lb/> slightest token of affection or regard from any of my<lb/> fellow&#45;creatures&#44; and more especially of my congregants&#44;<lb/> I would nevertheless consider a pension&#44; degradation.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>So long as my the heavenly Guide authors of my existence permits me<lb/> to retain my physical and mental powers&#44; they<lb/> shall be devoted to the task which I assumed<lb/> at this season thirty seven years ago.  My con&#45;<lb/>&#45;stant supplication to God&#44; is not to survive my useful&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness.  But will this be felt have wide scope any appreciable scope&#44; under such altered<lb/> circumstances&#63;  That is the question&#44; burning within<lb/> me like fire.  There stands facing me vexa&#45;<lb/>&#45;tiously&#44; the fact that my contemporaries reject<lb/> that which satisfied their fathers.  They must<lb/> be entertained at &#34;the Temple&#44;&#34; both vocally and<lb/> instrumentally.  They demand a ritual&#44; brief&#44; yet<lb/> so broad as to be no longer distinguished by its He&#45;<lb/>&#45;brew characteristics&#59; it must be clear ofrom demina&#45;<lb/>&#45;tionalism&#44; perfectly cosmopolitan.  Fiery<lb/> eloquence in the sermon is looked for&#44; positive<lb/> Judaism shall be eliminated&#44; to allow a place<lb/> for the admixture of poetical effusions out of<lb/> Greek&#44; Latin and Teutonic classics.  I need not<lb/> confess my inability to rise equal to that degree standard or so alter to shape my<lb/> course as to agree with the spirit of the time.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>But were I in possession of the varied ca&#45;<lb/>&#45;pacities now required exacted&#44; or could I do violence to<lb/> my convictions and yield in some matters&#44; in<lb/> order to please modern taste&#44; why might i not be asked to please<lb/> also about the in transferring of the Sabbath&#63;  Rabbis<lb/> who are earning the plaudits of vast multitudes for<lb/> having introduced Sunday services&#44; ostensibly as sup&#45;<lb/>&#45;plements to the worship or the holy convocation commanded enjoined upon the day of the Decalogue&#44; unmista&#45;<lb/>&#45;kingly advocate the total abolition of the latter.<lb/>  It has been recently contended that &#34;Reform&#44;&#34; to claim<lb/> that title&#44; must not &#34;tolerate the continuance of<lb/> an exclusive Saturday service&#44; in which God is<lb/> thanked for the Sabbath rest which the members<lb/> are not enjoying&#44; and which estranges thousands<lb/> from our faith.&#34;  You have heard it then&#59; because<lb/> many refuse obedience to the Law&#44; the Law must<lb/> be put down to <sic>accomodate</sic> the disobedient.  Thus&#44; in<lb/> a number of wealthy and large congregations East and<lb/> West&#44; Sunday the Church edict of the early church is stealing a march on the fourth<lb/> commandment of Sinai.  Woe for the hour that<lb/> the work of Moses shall be supplanted by what is falsely called stolidly termed &#34;American<lb/> Judaism.&#34;  Christianity shall have won the victory.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Brethren.  At the completion of thirty seven years<lb/> in the Jewish Ministry&#44; I take my stand<lb/> where my congregation first placed me.  I<lb/> shall not swerve.  Contumely I am prepared<lb/> to bear.  The jeers of such as call me &#34;the un&#45;<lb/>&#45;progressive one&#44;&#34; will not scare me into an ac&#45; a com&#45;<lb/>&#45;quiescence in pliance with that which I consider destructive a gradual surrendering of<lb/> my father&#39;s belief.  At this period of my<lb/> life I cannot promise a fresh supply of know&#45;<lb/>&#45;ledge in the discharge of duty&#59; too late would<lb/> it be for me to qualify myself and bring to bear upon it a familiar<lb/> acquaintance with philosophy and science&#44; or undergo a series of musical teachings training&#59; but a<lb/> determination not to shrink from labor within the range of my faculties&#44; to apply<lb/> myself to it earnestly and faithfully&#44; I can pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;mise.  Those who ask for no more&#44; and are will&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing to remain under my unpretending pastorship&#44; will not&#44; I<lb/> trust&#44; be put to shame &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;And may these words<lb/> wherewith I make supplication before the Lord&#44; be nigh<lb/> unto the Lord our God day and night&#44; that He may maint&#45;<lb/>&#45;ain the cause of His servant&#44; which is the cause<lb/> of His people Israel continually.&#34;  Amen.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>I am happy to relieve my <sic>Jeremiade</sic> on<lb/> this&#44; to me commemorative&#44; Sabbath by congratu&#45;<lb/>&#45;lating the Congregation &#34;Mickv&#232; Israel&#34; on the<lb/> receipt of a legacy&#45;&#45;the highest in material value<lb/> ever deposited into its treasury.  May the generous<lb/> gift prove an incentive to disburden this Sanctuary<lb/> from the weight which a combination of untoward<lb/> circumstances laid upon it&#59; so that it may be<lb/> truthfully called &#34;the house of God.&#34;  And may<lb/> she be ever blessed&#44; who righteously provided for<lb/> a hereafter by deeds&#44; securing the further worship<lb/> of her living Redeemer&#44; <sic>benefitting</sic> the orphans<lb/> and the sick of his people&#44; her sisters in faith<lb/> in the hour of distress trial and her brethren in poverty&#44;<lb/> promoting religious education at home and industry<lb/> abroad.  May the memory of Katharine Kaas<lb/> be praised on earth&#44; and angels in heaven inef&#45;<lb/>&#45;faceably record her charities in the book of a<lb/> life blissful and everlastingly blissful.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
