<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF2_4</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_4_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_4_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_4_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_4_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_4_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_4_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_4_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_4_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_4_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_4_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_4_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_4_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_4_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_4_7v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>On Noah<lb/>
                This lecture was improved upon<lb/> in the course of delivery<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;  &#34;Noah walked with God&#34;; so<lb/> reads the opening sentence of to day&#39;s section of<lb/> the Pentateuch.  Brethren.  There are gradations<lb/> in virtues&#44; as there are gradations in vice.  Few<lb/> have ever attained a state of perfection&#44; but rare&#44;<lb/> exceedingly rare&#44; thank God&#44; are the instances of a<lb/> universal&#44; irremediable depravity.  We may<lb/> meet persons whose uncontrollable temper is a<lb/> bone that turns into gall the sweetest of human<lb/> associations&#44; but who nevertheless possess genero&#45;<lb/>&#45;sity as a redeeming quality.  Others may be<lb/> niggardly&#44; yet of a gentle disposition.  Some&#44;<lb/> again&#44; show rudeness in their behavior and greed<lb/> in their dealings with the world&#44; but are not<lb/> inaccessible to the appeals of humanity.  Exception&#45;<lb/>&#45;ally vile are they who evince haughtiness&#44; avarice<lb/> and cruelty withal.  Now conversely&#58; we<lb/> may find man anxious to be governed by the rules<lb/> of morality&#44; but who need constant watching<lb/> so as to be held within the lines of probity&#59; others<lb/> have set up a lofty standard of integrity&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>which they keep always in sight&#44; as a<lb/> beacon light&#44; and there are a few who have drawn<lb/> so near to perfection&#44; that their lives may serve<lb/> as models and examples.<lb/></p>
            <p>The Rabbis illustrate this variety of characters<lb/> in one of their legends&#44; by picturing a father who<lb/> has three sons of different ages.  He trusts the<lb/> oldest implicitly&#44; for he knows the high minded&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness of his first born&#44; the noble manliness he gained<lb/> by long and deep reflections.  &#34;Go forth&#34; he tells the<lb/> child in whose integrity he confides&#58; &#34;Go forth and<lb/> herald the principles of uprightness which thou<lb/> hast learned well&#34;.  The younger son&#44; who<lb/> has not been sufficiently schooled in experience&#44;<lb/> the father admonishes.  He bids the youth to observe<lb/> the parent as he moved on and follow his footsteps<lb/>. unswervedly.  But the youngest and least ac&#45;<lb/>&#45;customed to overcome the difficulties which evil<lb/> surroundings present&#44; the parent keeps close by him&#44;<lb/> and does not allow to proceed alone &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Noah walked with God.&#34;  Noah is in the<lb/> opinion of some of the Sages comparable to the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>last named child.  He lived at an exceptionally<lb/> corrupt time.  Society was thoroughly disorganized<lb/> and the lowest passions run riot.  Already one<lb/> of his ancestors&#44; bearing the same name as Noah&#39;s<lb/> own parent&#45;&#45;Lemech&#45;&#45;had opened the way to that<lb/> disorganization by abandoning the natural law&#44;<lb/> sanctioned in the very first pages of the Bible&#45;&#45;<lb/> Monogamy&#45;&#45;&#44; as it is written &#34;Man will leave<lb/> his father and his mother and cleave to his wife&#34;<lb/>  By becoming a polygamist&#44; Lemech forged the<lb/> engines to undermine the foundations of domestic<lb/> harmony&#44; which is the main factor of social<lb/> union.  His address to Adah and Zillah&#44; his<lb/> two wives&#44; though not clear in its sense&#44; discloses<lb/> at all events&#44; a roughness of character&#44; ill fitted<lb/> to promote home happiness and the interests<lb/> of the community at large.  As we seek fur&#45;<lb/>&#45;ther&#44; we learn from tradition how in the days of<lb/> Enoch&#44; idolatry had grown so rampant&#44; that some<lb/> who had remained faithful&#44; proclaimed the name<lb/> of the Lord&#44; at public assemblies&#44; in the vain effort<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>to reclaim sinners&#44; and counteract a soul<lb/> withering evil.  We perceive likewise that Enoch&#44;<lb/> being righteous&#44; was Providentially taken up to God&#44;<lb/> earlier than the usual term of life was in the pri&#45;<lb/>&#45;mitive ages&#44; lest he be tainted with the almost<lb/> universal depravity.  I shall not venture<lb/> an opinion on the passage&#44; which tells us that<lb/> Ben&#233; Hahdohim&#45;&#45;translated &#34;the sons of God&#34;&#45;&#45;<lb/> became guilty of wantonness with Benoth Haadam<lb/> &#45;&#45;translated &#34;the daughters of man&#34;.  That sentence<lb/> has given rise to so many clashing views&#44; that<lb/> I will not add to the number.  I limit my&#45;<lb/>&#45;self to uttering my dissent from the mythologi&#45;<lb/>&#45;cal theory of fallen angels committing crimi&#45;<lb/>nal acts&#44; even though the idea is approved<lb/> by a late critic of great renown&#45;&#45;Francois Lever&#45;<lb/>mant&#45;&#45;who considers the story a floating<lb/> oriental legend&#44; which Holy Writ saw fit to<lb/> perpetuate&#44; to show that the Creator alone<lb/> is free from carnal passions.  Were I guided<lb/> solely by my understanding of scriptural lan&#45;<lb/>&#45;guage&#44; I would prefer to <sic>blieve</sic> that Bene Haelohim<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>were a caste of men higher than the corrupt<lb/> majority&#44; but who finally sunk low&#44; by suffering<lb/> animal propensities to overpower their purer<lb/> nature.  But let the real meaning of that<lb/> obscure passage be what it may&#44; the context<lb/> proves that a state of defiant revolt existed<lb/> against the laws by which the Supreme Lord<lb/> originally intended mankind to be guided.<lb/>  &#34;The whole earth was filled with violence &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44;<lb/> writes the inspired historian&#44; and the word Chamas<lb/> conveys a sense so broad that the English term<lb/> &#34;violence&#34; represents it but faintly&#44; Chamas&#44; says<lb/> a Talmudist supporting his assertion on Biblical<lb/> authority&#44; Chamas means idolatry&#44; incest&#44; murder&#44;<lb/> robbery &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Could Noah move in that sink of vice and re&#45;<lb/>main unpolluted&#63;  A disposition to righteous&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness was perhaps inherited&#44; and I am far from<lb/> undervaluing inborn qualities&#44; though alas&#33; so fre&#45;<lb/>&#45;quently neutralized by vicious associates.  He<lb/> had been given moreover&#44; an a name which<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>was to be a reminder of his filial duty&#44;<lb/> to comfort and assist his hard driven parents&#44; who<lb/> tilled an ungracious soil &#91;Hebrew&#93; should afford &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> rest&#44; &#91;Hebrew&#93; consolation.  Still an outward pres&#45;<lb/>&#45;sure was forcing every one down into a moral preci&#45;<lb/>&#45;pice.  Could he grapple with such influences&#44;<lb/> and hold himself aloft&#63;  God beheld the im&#45;<lb/>&#45;pending danger&#44; the extreme difficulty to overcome<lb/> it simply by an inherent force of character and<lb/> He providentially came to the rescue.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Noah walked with God.&#34;  In the<lb/> Rabbinical legend&#44; Noah represents the young&#45;<lb/>&#45;est child&#44; keeping close by the side of his father<lb/> for fear of being led away.  The Dweller in heaven<lb/> beckoned him near&#44; as it were&#44; to deliver a righteously<lb/> inclined man from a fearful peril &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> He who seeks his own purification&#44; obtains a celestial<lb/> assistance&#44; write the Talmudists.  Noah did not<lb/> rise spontaneously to that towering height which<lb/> makes one a crowned chief&#44; yet placed on a level<lb/> with with his contemporaries&#44; he stood head and<lb/> shoulders above all.  He was in reality<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>what some of the Talmudists liken him<lb/> to.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> a chest of perfume&#44; which emits a grateful<lb/> odor&#44; even among decaying matter.  Hence<lb/> the merit of having experienced an <sic>unequalled</sic> sal&#45;<lb/>&#45;vation.  &#34;The Lord said to Noah&#44; enter thou and<lb/> all thy household into the ark&#44; for thee have<lb/> I seen righteous in my presence in this ge&#45;<lb/>&#45;neration.&#34;  Hence likewise the merit of having<lb/> become in the hands of Providence the means<lb/> of reconstructing humanity on a firmer basis&#45;&#45;<lb/> with a less hardy body&#44; but stronger spirit&#44; with<lb/> a shorter existence but a broader intelligence.<lb/>  Still an agency more sublime than that of Noah<lb/> was employed by the Eternal to urge mankind<lb/> onward and upward in the march of spirituality.<lb/>  In the Rabbinical legend&#44; which I quoted&#44;<lb/> the oldest son on whom his parent implicitly<lb/> relied and whom he put forth on a mission&#44;<lb/> typifies the illustrious exile of Ur Chasdim<lb/> Abraham was greater than his great predecessor.<lb/>  The One God he discovered by a profound searching<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>into nature proclaimed it to the world&#44; when<lb/> He said &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Walk before me and<lb/> be perfect&#34;; or to put it in the language of the<lb/> sages &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44;<lb/> instead of displaying the divine light thou possess&#45;<lb/>est simply in a narrow spot&#44; go and let it shine<lb/> further and wider.<lb/></p>
            <p>None who have studied the history of civilization<lb/> with an unbiased mind&#44; can fail to admit<lb/> that to the founder of the Hebrew race belongs<lb/> the glory of having known and promulgated the<lb/> truth&#44; on which are being remitted now the mental looks<lb/> of the intelligent of all races&#44; still the love<lb/> of novelty has raised bold deniers.  It is pain&#45;<lb/>&#45;ful to those who will not swear by a modern<lb/> school&#44; to hear critics and their credulous disci&#45;<lb/>&#45;ples contend that the belief in One Universal<lb/> God is the product of an evolutionary unfolding<lb/> of the intellect at a much later age than that<lb/> of our patriarch.  And this is confidently de&#45;<lb/>clared&#44; in the face of such expressions as<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>ingeniously fell from the lips of Abraham.<lb/>  &#34;Adonai El Ehim&#44; the owner of heaven and earth&#44;&#34; and<lb/> again&#58; &#34;Adona&#239; the God of the heavens and of the<lb/> earth&#34;.  But what more convincing proof of the<lb/> universality of the God to whom Abraham erected<lb/> altars in the sight of gentilism can be adduced&#44;<lb/> than the patriarch&#39;s intercession in behalf of<lb/> the people of Sodom&#44; who were we strangers to him&#44;<lb/> in these terms &#34;shall the Judge of all the earth not<lb/> do justice&#33;&#34;  However&#44; I must not<lb/> wander from the main subject&#44; even in defense of<lb/> a principle night to my heart.  Brethren.  To carry<lb/> out the Talmudical legend&#44; I have tried to show the<lb/> comparative estimate made of the man signally<lb/> saved by the Lord&#44; and the man chosen for the apo&#45;<lb/>&#45;stleship of the all saving Lord.  The former mo&#45;<lb/>&#45;ving in a sphere of moral darkness&#44; stood&#45;&#45;child like&#44;<lb/> in need of the interposition of a higher power to hold<lb/> him up&#59; the latter illumined by the verities he<lb/> had discovered&#44; proceeded steadfastly as the forerunner<lb/> of celestial promises.  &#34;In thee all the families of<lb/> the earth shall be blessed&#34;.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>But the legend speaks also of a son whom<lb/> his father bid follow believed&#44; watch the parental<lb/> footprints and take similar steps.  And since<lb/> I must address this morning a lad whom I wish to<lb/> hail hereafter as an adherent of the teachings<lb/> of Judaism&#44; I will say&#58; My young brother&#44; the<lb/> parent whose ways a Jewish child must copy<lb/> is the Supreme Being whom we daily acknowledge<lb/> as the only God&#44; and or whose Law you have just<lb/> pronounced a confessional benediction.  Moses so<lb/> commanded our ancestors when he wrote &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Ye shall walk after the Lord your God&#34;&#44;<lb/> which the Rabbis interpret thus &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  You must imitate the<lb/> forbearance&#44; the forgiveness&#44; the loving kindness of<lb/> the Almighty.  Can I add aught to that instruct&#45;<lb/>&#45;ion given you by the archprophet and the sages of<lb/> your people&#63;  On this sabbath you enter a new<lb/> stage of religious existence.  Determine in your<lb/> mind to pursue a course that will distinguish<lb/> you as a Jew without guile&#59; and as a man<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>adorned with the admirable virtues I have<lb/> named.  The heavenly Father you shall have<lb/> followed&#44; will turn towards you with radiant<lb/> smiles&#44; and His approval will bring joys lasting<lb/> and ever sweeter.<lb/></p>
            <p>The address to the Bar Mitzvah was continued at length.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
