<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF32_2a</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_2_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>On the character of Aaron<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Many characters that figure prominently<lb/> in the Bible&#44; have been chosen as subjects<lb/> of reflection&#44; upon which able writers found<lb/> pleasure to dwell.  Miss O&#39;Keefe&#39;s &#34;pa&#45;<lb/>&#45;triarchal times&#34;&#45;&#45;a work which I was wont<lb/> to read as an exercise&#44; while studying to learn<lb/> idiomatic English&#45;&#45;&#44; is&#44; for instance&#44; a production<lb/> teeming with literary merits.  The sketches are<lb/> attractive in their delineation&#44; and instructive<lb/> by reason of the moral lessons which they<lb/> strive always to convey.  It is not to our<lb/> credit&#44; that non&#45;Israelites have notably ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;celled in the art of blending truth with some<lb/> permissible fiction&#44; in order to fasten the<lb/> reader&#39;s thoughts pleasantly on the sacred pages&#59;<lb/> nevertheless&#44; that fact must be acknowledged.<lb/></p>
            <p>B However&#44; in the course of my studies I do<lb/> not remember to have ever seen&#44; in modern<lb/> languages&#44; a delineation of the character of the<lb/> first priest who ministered in the tabernacle<lb/> of the Eternal&#59; I mean such as pro portrait<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>as becoming a personage on whose brows the<lb/> golden mitre shone with &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Holiness to the<lb/> Lord&#34;&#45;&#45;the luminous token of a Divine selection.<lb/>  The Sages of our people alone seem to have duly<lb/> appreciated the virtues which adorned Aaron.<lb/>  They have called him &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;the peace<lb/> lover&#44; and peace maker&#34;&#44; and they claim to have<lb/> discovered in Malachi&#39;s sublime picture of a<lb/> servant of God&#44; a faithful representation of the<lb/> sacerdotal son of Amram.  What the Talmudists<lb/> dilate upon with delight&#44; touching his loveable<lb/> disposition&#44; may have its foundation largely<lb/> upon traditional legendary&#44; but as I was reading<lb/> today&#39;s initial portion in the book of Exodus&#44;<lb/> an expression <sic>occuring</sic> therein&#44; enchained my<lb/> attention&#44; as ingenuously revealing the sentiments<lb/> nurtured in the breast of the godly Aaron.<lb/>  Moses&#44; with that extreme humility which has<lb/> won for him the title for &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;the meekest<lb/> of all men&#44;&#34; had been unable to overcome his<lb/> self&#45;distrust.  He had petitioned the Lord to<lb/> send another to face Pharaoh with the fearful<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>mission imposed.  The vision of the burning<lb/> bush closes with this announcement&#58; &#34;Behold<lb/> Aaron thy brother&#44; the Levite&#44; will speak&#44; I<lb/> surely know&#59; he is even coming forth to meet<lb/> thee&#44; and&#44; seeing thee&#44; he will be glad in his heart.&#34;<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Upon which the Midrash<lb/> remarks.  Great was the joy which the older<lb/> brother felt in clasping to his breast the younger<lb/> &#40;so long absent in enforced exile&#41;&#44; but his delight<lb/> would have increased tenfold&#44; had be heard the All<lb/> seeing God who searches our inmost parts&#44; declare<lb/> him an affectionate brother.  He might then have<lb/> made soul reviving music precede his steps<lb/> towards the mountain of the Lord&#44; where the<lb/> two fondly embraced.  From that hour<lb/> they became inseparable companions in a task<lb/> of the greatest magnitude.  Closely associated<lb/> in the momentous enterprise of working redemp&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion&#44; the older unobtrusively held a subordinate<lb/> position.  Envious feelings did not mar fraternal<lb/> harmony.  He who had daily grieved at the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>sigh of oppression&#44; at the fierceness of task<lb/> masters&#44; and he who with anguish of mind had<lb/> contemplated from afar in the country of the stran&#45;<lb/>&#45;ger&#44; the abject misery of his people&#44; had<lb/> alike learned from the same parental precept to<lb/> devote their lives to the cause of national liberty<lb/> and enlightenment.  What matter if the last<lb/> born weilded a superior power&#44; when the labor<lb/> of both tended to create a nation free and Divinely<lb/> taught&#63;  Such were the sentiments which knit<lb/> two beings in one&#59; so noble an example Aaron&#39;s<lb/> conduct illustrated.  His majestic figure<lb/> disappears almost completely behind that &#91;&#63;&#93;&#44;<lb/> yet&#44; it was he who spoke and acted in the land of<lb/> Mizraim&#59; it was he who warned and chastised<lb/> the tyrants&#59; he who <sic>counselled</sic> and comforted the<lb/> afflicted&#59; he for so it is explicitly stated &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;He shall be thy mouth piece&#44;<lb/> and thou shalt be to him as a divinity&#34;.  The trusty<lb/> interpreter of his brother&#39;s inspired command pos&#45;<lb/>&#45;sessed that nobility of spirit&#44; which recognizes<lb/> in another a larger share of intellect&#59; a deeper<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>insight in the knowledge of God&#39;s will and<lb/> the government of men.  Mark Aaron<lb/> at the battle of Rephidim.  A youth&#45;&#45;a<lb/> hitherto comparative stranger&#44; had been honored<lb/> with the generalship of the combatants that<lb/> were to repel the attack of brutal Amalek.<lb/>  Not to cover himself with military glory did<lb/> the older brother crave of Moses crave&#44; not to enter<lb/> the lists and carry off trophies.  Upon the<lb/> top of the hill where the archprophet raised<lb/> his hands heavenward&#44; that Israel might vanquish<lb/> a deadly foe&#44; Aaron stood with Hur and looked<lb/> and upheld his hands heavenward&#44; that the arms which should not drop down<lb/> wearily until the sound of victory echoed forth<lb/> among myriads of Israel.  Observe Aaron&#44;<lb/> again&#44; when the jealously of a relative&#44; stirred up<lb/> a conspiracy that aimed to divest him of his sa&#45;<lb/>&#45;cerdotal authority.  Unscrupulous Korah incited<lb/> a sedition&#44; pointing to Aaron as the usurper of<lb/> of an office given him by partiality.  But the<lb/> object of ill will did not exhibit resentment&#59;<lb/> no remonstrance issued from the lips of the unambitious<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>priest.  Moses in his own defence; in vindication of<lb/> the Divine mandate received&#44; arose majestically<lb/> upon the occasion&#44; when the his legation would undergo<lb/> a crucial test&#59; Moses asked the rebellious &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Aaron what is &#40;guilty of&#41; that ye<lb/> murmur against him&#63;&#34;  Confessedly&#44;<lb/> the older son of Amram fell far behind the younger<lb/> in the possession of such qualities as make a<lb/> leader of communities.  He loved peace dearly&#44; but he<lb/> lacked the energy that can rise equal to an emer&#45;<lb/>&#45;gency&#44; quick in appliances to meet it successfully.<lb/>  The weakness displayed at the humiliating circum&#45;<lb/>&#45;stance of the mother calf&#44; whether through a<lb/> wish to temporize in the hope of preventing the<lb/> sin by the return of Moses&#44; as some of our expositors<lb/> allege&#44; or whether under threat&#44; as others have<lb/> surmised&#44; shows&#44; at all events&#44; an incapacity to<lb/> cope with extreme difficulties.  But if Aaron&#39;s<lb/> intellectual strength&#44; was not on a par with that<lb/> by which the character of our archprophet was<lb/> signalized&#44; his spiritual strength would not<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>suffer by comparison.  It is in the hour of the severest<lb/> trials that our virtues are best put to the test.  Then<lb/> can the beholder discover men&#39;s brave mettle.<lb/></p>
            <p>Joy was universal upon the day that the first<lb/> priest was installed into his office.  The hands<lb/> consecrated to bless God&#39;s people had been uplifted in<lb/> prayerful attitude.  The threefold benediction had been<lb/> pronounced.  Suddenly a shriek of horror strikes thralls<lb/> all hearts.  Two sons of the Pontiff have met with<lb/> an instantaneous death.  Their presumption to<lb/> enter the holy of holies without summons&#44; had digged<lb/> their graves.  Plunged in sorrow is the unhappy<lb/> father.  Fain would he retire to bemoan his sad<lb/> loss.  But he is the minister of religion&#59; he shall<lb/> refrain from wailings and lamentations.  Said<lb/> it &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;by those who come nigh unto me I<lb/> must be hallowed&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;  My decree must<lb/> be honored in the sight of all the people.  Tears are<lb/> forced back&#59; a silence follows&#44; the silence of pious<lb/> resignation &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Now&#59; reared as<lb/> I have been in the lap of Rabbinism&#44; which is<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>full of praise for Aaron&#44; as the modest exemplar<lb/> of peace&#44; admiring many of the traits in Aaron&#39;s<lb/> character&#44; as clearly evinced in the Scripture&#44; I<lb/> wish that I could explain in his defence an event<lb/> of his life which seems to contradict what I have en&#45;<lb/>&#45;deavoured to prove.  Still&#44; I may justly remark<lb/> that the incident which misled him once into an<lb/> act of unbrotherly conduct&#44; is so obscurely set forth<lb/> in Holy Writ&#44; that it is almost impossible to<lb/> Judge of the cause which incited the fault.<lb/>  Miriam&#44; who certainly had loved Moses and gloried in<lb/> the deliverance he had divinely wrought&#44; could not have<lb/> wished to deny his greatness&#44; but she is mentioned first<lb/> as culpable of rash words&#44; and she must have been the<lb/> principal offender&#44; as she bore the penalty.  Who the Ethio&#45;<lb/>&#45;pian woman was&#44; who indirectly provoked the offense&#44;<lb/> we do not learn form the Scriptural text.  Ancient<lb/> chronicles&#44; differently presented by Hebrew writers&#44; and<lb/> by the historian Josephus&#44; would lead us to believe that<lb/> Moses&#44; after having fled from Egypt&#44; had emigrated to<lb/> Ethiopia&#44; and that the King&#39;s daughter enamoured with<lb/> his manly beauty and his valor in battle had pledged<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>herself to him in marriage&#44; and finally had joined the camp<lb/> of Israel in the wilderness.  To pronounce a judgment upon the<lb/> merits of a case&#44; which it is impossible obviously to define&#44;<lb/> would be rash&#44; and though I might quote opinions among<lb/> ancient and modern authors&#44; I prefer to leave the question open.<lb/>  But if the instance just cited&#44; Aaron became involved in the sin<lb/> of uncharitable speaking against Moses&#44; how worthy of imita&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion was his ready confession&#44; that both he and Miriam had<lb/> done great wrongs &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  How humble his apology<lb/> and his entreaty that his sister chastened with a loathsome ill&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness by the rod of justice&#44; might soon be restored to perfect<lb/> health&#33;  In the language of a Hebrew writer we may well say<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;happy is he whose faults can be<lb/> numbered&#34;.  Barring the wickedness inherent in too yielding a<lb/> temperament&#44; Aaron may still serve as a model of righteousness&#44;<lb/> as a servant of God &#34;who walked in peace and integrity&#44; and brought<lb/> many back from iniquity&#44;&#34; as Malachi expresses it.  And so did<lb/> the greatest of men consider him&#44; as memorably enunciated in<lb/> his parting blessing to the tribes&#58; &#34;Thy thummim and Thy Urim<lb/> &#40;O God&#41; were given to Thy pious one&#34;....&#40;whose progeny&#41; shall<lb/> teach Thy ordinances to Jacob and Thy Law unto Israel&#34;<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
