<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF10_5</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_5_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_5_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_5_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_5_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_5_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_5_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_5_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_5_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_5_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_5_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_5_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_5_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. Fifth St.<lb/>
                Philadelphia&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>On the blessing of Peace<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Whoever examines the Jewish liturgy thoughtfully&#44; cannot<lb/> fail to notice the emphasis which it lays on the value of<lb/> God&#39;s greatest blessing to mortals&#45;&#45;the blessing enjoyment of peace.  The Kaddish&#44; or<lb/> sanctification of the name of the Lord&#44; with which the ritual<lb/> proper&#44; begins and ends&#44; has a an earnest petition for peace &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>  &#34;May abundant peace from heaven be given showered upon us.&#34;  So also the<lb/> principal prayer of each service&#44; which the Sephardim call<lb/> Amidah or standing up devotionally and the Ashkenazim Shemon&#232; Esri or 18 benedictions&#44; concludes with<lb/> an entreaty for peace &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;May He who establishes<lb/> peace in His high heaven&#44; grant us peace&#44; according to His mercies.&#34;<lb/>  Even in the our ordinary intercourse&#44; the mutual greeting in Hebrew among of Hebrews is &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Peace be with you.&#34;  It might be therefore rea&#45;<lb/>&#45;sonable to suppose that every Jew thoroughly appreciates<lb/> the celestial gift of peace and knows how to secure that precious boon.<lb/>  And if in all reality it were so&#44; in reality&#44; a Jew would represent a being<lb/> typically virtuous&#44; for&#44; to express it in the language of<lb/> Isaiah&#44; peace follows uprightness very closely &#91;Hebrew&#93; is the intimate associate of uprightness.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  The working of charity accompaniment of righteousness is peace&#44; and the labor endeavour<lb/> of charity righteousness&#44; <sic>tranquillity</sic> and sincerity for evermore.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>But how open liable to misapprehensions the causes of peace<lb/> and its their effects are.  Few understand for peace to be the offspring of one&#39;s efforts to in over coming difficulties faults.  Little he understands does he realize the nature<lb/> of that Divine blessing&#44; who imagines peace to be mistakes it for  masterly inactivity.<lb/>  repore&#44; il doke far minte&#44; &#34;the sweet doing nothing&#34; of<lb/> the idlers.  As well might he believe that the lack<lb/> of sound constitutes harmony&#44; as to think that the absence<lb/> of live actions is synonymous with peace.  The energy Not sleepiness<lb/> exercised but the keeping of the mind wide awake&#44; ready to<lb/> respond to the call of duty will brings peace.  The energy exer&#45;<lb/>&#45;cised in rising above ourselves to conquer low propensities&#44;<lb/> forces open the sky that showsg us the rainbow of promise&#45;&#45;peace.<lb/>  Not he who lies supinely when his obligations urge<lb/> him on to exertions enjoys repose the rest predicted by the prophet I quoted&#44; but he who stirs up<lb/> his soul to noble sublime elevating purposes.  Isaac The patriarch&#44; whom<lb/> the section of this sabbath&#44; places prominently&#44;<lb/> supplies an a fair illustration of the prophetic Isaiah&#39;s teaching that the<lb/> work&#44; accompaniment of righteousness is peace.  Diligently had Isaac<lb/> labored and had his to coin success.  In the field he had<lb/> made his sinewy arms had <sic>yeilded</sic> abundance&#44; in the<lb/> plain his industry had enriched arid spots with<lb/> wells gushing forth refreshing water.  A well noble<lb/> spirit manhood had the son of Abraham exhibited among strangers.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>But his prosperity so rightly earned&#44; aroused rankling<lb/> jealousy.  It hurled Envy sharpened its arrows at him and he became their victim.<lb/>  The gain he had anticipated and deserved was denied<lb/> him by the ill will of men to whom his father had shown<lb/> kindness.  Did he then seek peace by a vile agency&#63;  Did he then consider peace the wages<lb/> of revenge&#63;  Did he seek peace  by their vile agency&#63; No&#58; the price of peace repose rest is g righteousness<lb/> not vengeance&#44; grudge or spite&#44; we are assured by inspiration.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  By subduing his offended feelings the<lb/> patriarch&#44; wrongly dealt with&#44; disarmed opposition&#44; conciliated his foes and conquered<lb/> peace.  Most wisely was Solomon&#39;s wrote maxim &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;he who rules over his spirit is greater than he<lb/> who captures a cl city.&#34;  Unhappy King Saul.  He strikingly il&#45;<lb/>&#45;lustrates the literally the opposite character.  He could not rule his spirit.  Fortune had<lb/> smiled on him&#59; being a member of a the smallest<lb/> tribe in Israel&#44; and himself of humble descent&#44; he was<lb/> nevertheless unexpectedly raised to the throne.  A<lb/> victory obtained in the dawn of his reign&#44; ensured<lb/> for him fame and conciliated the disaffected against royalty.  But<lb/> in governing his own life&#44; Saul lost the compass that<lb/> regulates our actions existence&#44; and he was tossed on a surging sea of<lb/> troubles&#44; he found no peace.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>At one time the melodious strains of a harp in the hand a masterly skillful<lb/> of a youthful shepherd hand cheered him&#59; at another they exiled kindled<lb/> his anger.  He feared David detested the minstrel shepherd when near&#44; and when David was<lb/> far&#44; he dreaded the brave youth&#39;s influence.  Now touched<lb/> by tokens of loyalty&#44; he praised the warrior&#44; anon he laid a<lb/> snare at his feet.  Dark suspicions estranged the monarch<lb/> from his own household&#44; suspicions stained him with the<lb/> blood of eighty five innocent beings.  He risked Samuel&#39;s<lb/> displeasure while the prophet lived&#44; and in a fit of su&#45;<lb/>&#45;perstition he sought to consult him dead.  Truly&#44; peace<lb/> refuses to abide with him who has left behind whole&#45;<lb/>&#45;some restraints&#44; and lets his passion go unbridled.<lb/></p>
            <p>Witness it in the insatiably ambitious&#59; to day b buoyed<lb/> up with hopes which depressing fears drown on the morrow&#59; at<lb/> this hour excited to the highest pitch of expectations&#44; at<lb/> another the next weary with disappointments.  And<lb/> the intemperate&#59; they &#34;who rise up early to imbibe strong<lb/> drink&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; who set up late at<lb/> night&#44; till wines denaturalize them.  The wretched one who says<lb/> of his wife &#34;I know her not&#44;&#34; and of his children &#34;I have<lb/> not begotten them.&#34;  He who consumes their substance<lb/> in vice&#44; can he enjoy God&#39;s greatest blessing&#45;&#45;peace&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>What agitation like his&#44; if he can at sober intervals notice face the<lb/> the progress of his work of destruction&#33; wreck he had wrought which labor insobriety wrought&#33;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;The work associate of righteousness is peace&#44;&#34; but all passions<lb/> rob us of that celestial boon&#44; because the sure one identic&#45;<lb/>&#45;al law&#44; rules governs individuals and societies&#44; and in the same<lb/> manner that in order to preserve peace between ourselves and<lb/> our fellow creatures mortals&#44; we must incessantly control lay our<lb/> passions under control&#44; so must we check them to<lb/> keep our body and soul at rest.  But more a sense<lb/> even higher a higher motive than self&#45;preservation must  be at work should stimulate us in our endea&#45;<lb/>&#45;vours to gain peace&#45;&#45;a sense of beneficence&#44; of justice&#44;<lb/> of mercy should impel us &#91;&#63;&#93; onward.  That a union<lb/> of love among creatures endowed by the Creator with<lb/> intelligence was the original intention of the universal<lb/> Parent&#44; is evident from his having formed one only<lb/> being as the root of the human family.  And our Sages<lb/> have undoubtedly so intended to express it&#44; when they figu&#45;<lb/>&#45;ratively wrote that God gathered portions of the dust from<lb/> the whole earth&#44; and of out of them He made Adam&#44; so<lb/> that in future generations none should boast of a<lb/> higher extraction than his neighbor&#44; and but deeming them&#45;<lb/>&#45;selves equal&#44; should help one another here below to make life pleasurable.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Alas&#33; that an evil spirit has often broken torn asunder those sacred ties&#44;<lb/> and man brutally inhumanly rose against man and by brutal<lb/> force&#44; by rapine fierceness and ferocity has overpowered<lb/> her weaker brother.  Shame upon us that such deeds have<lb/> f been pointed at with self&#45;glorification.  Everlasting<lb/> shame disgrace upon us of this boastful age&#44; in which humanity is horrified<lb/> by the narrative of barbarities perpetrated by whites<lb/> against powerless defenceless blacks&#44; on the plea of of furthering<lb/> civilization.  Such are the trophies of a heartless<lb/> progress science &#44;and the men who carry them aloft receive the plaudits<lb/> of the world not unlike They are In reading of refined cruelties in the dark continent I am reminded of the Greek artist&#44; who to graphically paint<lb/> the suffering of Prometheus and graphically and win<lb/> fame&#44; tortured a slave to death.  &#34;Avoid them&#44; cries<lb/> the Hebrew moralist &#34;who eat the bread of wickedness&#44; and<lb/> drink the wine of violence&#44;&#34; who silence rebel against nature&#39;s instincts<lb/> and crown selfishness popularity as their queen Sovereign lord.<lb/>  But not alone they destroy the social harmony&#44; who<lb/> overstep the bounds set by Divine and human laws.<lb/>  Peace is also warred against by them who in the garb<lb/> of religion&#44; set themselves up as mentors and magnify<lb/> evils to make a show of zeal to champion claim the championship of religious progress.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>A mischievous zeal&#44; which drives away peace from<lb/> the congregations of the Lord.  True zeal aiming at<lb/> the betterment of man and the glorification of God is<lb/> modest&#44; the faults it detects&#44; it tries to remove by<lb/> gentle persuasion&#44; it does not tear the brier&#44; lest the<lb/> rose also be destroyed&#44; but it preserves the latter by<lb/> cautiously lopping off the former.  True zeal is that<lb/> which even at a sacrifice&#44; promotes union among brethren&#44;<lb/> hides differences&#44; does not divulge them &#91;&#63;&#93; display them from the house top at the sound of<lb/> trumpets.  True zeal is a light which dissipates but errors does not<lb/> seek&#44; errors expose to view them to view.  It is strength employed to overcome obstacles&#44;<lb/> not to raise them up &#91;Hebrew&#93;  The work associate of<lb/> righteousness is peace.  That peace is greatly disturbed<lb/> now adays&#44; through the unhappy contest between the<lb/> &#91;&#63;&#93; of innovations senseless adorers of superstitions&#44; and those who mistake improvement infidelity<lb/> for improvement&#44; between those who lay an impious<lb/> hand on the ark of the Lord&#44; and those who would not<lb/> forego even a superstition a local custom&#59; between those who would<lb/> model our worship after a gentile pattern&#44; and those<lb/> who refuse to conduct it with becoming order and<lb/> decorum.  Oh&#33; when shall we joyfully sing with the Psalmist&#58;<lb/> &#34;How good and sweet it is for brethren to dwell together in unity&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>But to be at peace with one another&#44; we must be at peace<lb/> with God &#34;Much Abundant Plenteous peace they have who love Thy law&#44;&#34;<lb/> exclaims the psalmist.  There can be no peace accord harmony of feelings between<lb/> such as with studied effrontery deny decry His command&#45;<lb/>&#45;ments&#44; and expose laugh His behests to derision scorn&#44; and Israelites<lb/> who bow reverently to the revealed Word.  Let us<lb/> then brethren and fellow&#45;<sic>worshippers</sic> band together&#44; we&#44; who in our liturgy still pray<lb/> for peace&#44; and having learnting to value that Divine blessing&#44;<lb/> as the highest boon&#59; let us &#91;Hebrew&#93; invite it that boon to our homes by a<lb/> conduct unexceptionally in agreeble to tallying with the dictates<lb/> of our faith&#44; by suppressing our inclinations&#44; when<lb/> clashing with rectitude&#44; by <sic>practising</sic> ourselves<lb/> what we would enforce on our children.  Let us even obtain<lb/> abundant peace for this religious body&#44; so that let whatever<lb/> be discordant may harmonize through kindness<lb/> and gentle consideration&#44; and in us will be verified the<lb/> sentence of the ancient seer &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Peace peace&#44; to those him who<lb/> are is far&#44; and to those who are him that is near&#44; says the<lb/> Lord&#44;&#34; and I He will heal all divisions.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
