<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF3_4</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1889" source="" attested="yes">1889</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_4_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_4_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_4_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_4_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_4_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_4_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_4_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_4_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_4_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_4_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_4_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_4_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>On the 38th anniversary<lb/>
                of my ministration&#47;89<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  Ought I to rejoice&#44; or to lament upon<lb/> this Sabbath&#44; commemorative of a leading event<lb/> in my life&#63;  Thirty eight years ago I ascended took my<lb/> stand for the first time at this same Tebah&#44; which<lb/> has served as a prayer&#45;reading desk and a pul&#45;<lb/>&#45;pit to several of my clerical predecessors&#44; as<lb/> well as to myself.  But none since the esta&#45;<lb/>&#45;blishment of the pioneer Hebrew congregation<lb/> of Philadelphia&#44; that reckons almost a decade<lb/> over a century&#44; ministered during so long a term<lb/> uninterruptedly&#44; as he who now addresses you.  That<lb/> is a privilege which I acknowledge at the hand<lb/> of the Supreme Ruler of human affairs&#44; hence I might<lb/> be glad that I was permitted to remain thus steadily at<lb/> my post.  But as I search for what I would delight<lb/> to find&#44; I miss it.  With a few exceptions&#45;&#45;and<lb/> may they who are such continue with us as such in the fruition<lb/> of health and strength&#45;&#45;those who listened to my im&#45;<lb/>&#45;perfect delivery on the Sabbath succeeding the Purim<lb/> of 1851&#44; have gone from hence for ever.  It was na&#45;<lb/>&#45;tural and beyond my control&#44; therefore it should not<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>be a cause of complaint&#44; but the offspring&#44;<lb/> the sons and daughters of the departed do not&#44; to any<lb/> appreciable extent&#44; fill up the places left vacant<lb/> by the decease of their parents&#44; consequently I have reasons to grieve.  Were it not<lb/> that brothers and sisters in faith from abroad&#44; or<lb/> from religious bodies that deemed it necessary to<lb/> dissolve&#44; had closed up the gap&#44; our Mickv&#233;<lb/> Isra&#232;l&#44; &#34;the hope of Israel&#34; would have altogether<lb/> ceased to exist.  Upon that I ponder with<lb/> self&#45;reflection.  I observe that all regular congre&#45;<lb/>&#45;gations in this city&#45;&#45;leaving aside those of a very<lb/> recent date in a Southern direction&#45;have gradually lapsed<lb/> into the so&#45;called &#34;Reform&#34;&#44; as means to increase<lb/> the attendance at their respective Synagogues.<lb/>  It does not lie in my power to personally ascertain<lb/> whether the end has been invariably reached&#44; but<lb/> communing with my own self I often ask&#44; whe&#45;<lb/>&#45;ther my declination to let ours follow a similar<lb/> plan is not obstinacy rather than consistency&#44;<lb/> whether it has or it has not some of the leaven of human pride that loves exclusiveness.<lb/> Many have so condemned it&#44; loudly enough to let make<lb/> me hear that at my door lies the fault of having<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>driven the rising generation to other shrines.<lb/>  It is contended that if  I had abridged the ritual formulary of prayers&#59;<lb/> changed it into a spoken language  the vernacular&#44; recognized the ef&#45;<lb/>&#45;fectiveness of choral music&#44; and introduced the seating<lb/> arrangement&#44; as generally adopted&#44; I would not have<lb/> lost what was ours by inheritance.  Heavy is<lb/> the charge&#44; and heavily it lays on my heart&#44; but on<lb/> the day which that recalls my undertaking of a mission&#44;<lb/> which impressed me so profoundly with its responsi&#45;<lb/>&#45;bilities that  twice&#44; in former years&#44; I had resolved to aban&#45;<lb/>&#45;don it&#44; and I only retained it in deference to the earnest<lb/> request solicitations of friends&#59; on this Sabbath I may confess why<lb/> I preferred to bearing the reproach of some many to altering the<lb/> course of my ministration.  Little as I am given<lb/> to self&#45;appreciation&#44; when I think calmly and dispassionate&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly&#44; think&#44; I cannot consider adherence to a solemn promise&#44;<lb/> sheer obstinacy.  At the period that I entered upon<lb/> my official duties&#44; Reform was unknown in Philadelphia.<lb/>  It had scarcely any foothold in the United States<lb/> anywhere.  I then affixed my signature to a<lb/> paper which bound me to the performance of certain<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>functions conformably to the regulations&#44; which<lb/> had governed this Congregation from its origin.  I<lb/> might not have approved of the document in all its<lb/> particulars&#44; but so long as my name remained attached<lb/> to it&#44; I dared not allow my conduct to oppose its<lb/> enactments.  Yet&#44; what I felt unauthorized to do<lb/> singly&#44; I tried to accomplish by a congregational<lb/> Union.  Noticing the dangerous strides taken by<lb/> a Reform which was bent on casting down every land&#45;<lb/>mark set up by the ancients&#44; I began some twenty<lb/> five years ago to agitate the question of a revision<lb/> to the Jewish liturgy and ritual laws&#44; under an<lb/> advisory council&#44; with the view of uniting American<lb/> Israelites in worship&#44; in school training&#44; and in out&#45;<lb/>&#45;ward practices.  Finally in 1875&#44; the late Reverend<lb/> Samuel Myer Isaacs of New York&#44; then editor of the<lb/> Jewish Messenger&#44; issued a call for a meeting of<lb/> those among the ministers who shared my views sentiments&#44; as ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;pressed in a series of articles.  The attempt proved<lb/> abortive.  No alternative was left to me but<lb/> either to add to the existing evil by presuming to do<lb/> alone what would have been a breach of promise&#44; and<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>would have surely caused created a division in fatal to this religious<lb/> body&#59; or to proceed as heretofore suitably to the<lb/> accepted Sephardic customs&#44; in which I myself was have<lb/> been raised.  I chose the latter course&#44; admitting<lb/> unreservedly its being open to improvements.  Had<lb/> I yielded to the pressure&#44; sometime brought upon<lb/> me imperiously overbearingly&#44; I might perhaps have gained<lb/> back&#44; for a short time season a few of those who had become<lb/> estranged from this Syangogue&#44; but only at the risk<lb/> of alienating from it altogether the largest number who would<lb/> not have submitted to arbitrary innovations.<lb/></p>
            <p>But is it so&#44; in all truth&#44; that the children progeny of our<lb/> old members have left us to become affiliated to<lb/> congregations more congenial with their mode of<lb/> thinking&#63;  Sorrowfully I acknowledge that<lb/> not even such a non&#45;descript as that body&#44; which<lb/> boasts of brays flauntingly proclaims its radical Reform&#44; holding Sunday services&#44;<lb/> making light of the Passover&#44; declaring its indif&#45;<lb/>&#45;ference to the atonement fast&#44; quoting the man<lb/> of Nazareth&#44; and placing him in juxtaposition<lb/> with Israel&#39;s prophets&#59; no&#44; not even the building<lb/> of such in which Hebrew is cried down&#44; and Christian<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>singing echoes forth&#44; can boast of having drawn<lb/> the men and women whom we have lost.  Inex&#45;<lb/>&#45;pressibley satisfaction would have been my satisfaction to have kept them loyally<lb/> within the fold of Judaism&#44; but by no fault of mine<lb/> own has agnotsticism seized upon them&#44; and mate&#45;<lb/>&#45;rialism made them its votaries.  They are found<lb/> nowhere among Jews&#44; nor could they be converted to<lb/> the ancestral faith by the preaching of pulpits&#44; which<lb/> are but dynamites to undermine and blow shutter into atoms<lb/> the fabric of Israel&#39;s religion.  The West has<lb/> largely helped insidiously to sap its foundation&#44; and in my I spurred on<lb/> wrath at the to the defence by the &#91;&#63;&#93; vacillating conduct of the man I had once<lb/> weakly trusted&#44; notwithstanding its reprehensible<lb/> antecedents&#44;&#45;&#45;the man who presides over the destiny<lb/> of the Cincinnati College&#44; and who presided in<lb/> Pittsburg at a conference that framed an anti&#45;<lb/>Jew&#45;<lb/>&#45;ish platform&#44;&#45;&#45;I&#44; looked cast about for a counteracting force&#44;<lb/> and designed planned the Jewish Theological Seminary<lb/> which I set planted the Jewish Theological Seminary<lb/> which I set planted in New York.  What fruits this will<lb/> bring forth&#44; it is too premature to say divine.  My<lb/> hopes and my prayers are for its success.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Much will depend on the support the insti&#45;<lb/>&#45;tution receives&#44; whether the ideas which gave it<lb/> origin&#44; will result blissfully.  Meanwhile<lb/> the weeds at home grow daily more pressing&#44; and<lb/> my age and my labors ought to command suffi&#45;<lb/>&#45;cient influence to supply those wants.  But the six or seven<lb/> hundred children whom I met last Sunday at<lb/> Kelly&#39;s hall&#44; proved my insufficiency.  If the<lb/> words I speak&#44; carried any weight&#44; the building which<lb/> I have long pleaded for would have arisen&#44; though its cost<lb/> be large.  Mission schools would not allege as a<lb/> reason for sheltering Hebrew infants&#44; the absence of<lb/> such conveniences as they offer to the squalid&#44; the un&#45;<lb/>&#45;tutored and the destitute.  But <sic>wherefor</sic> shall I com&#45;<lb/>&#45;plain of my powerlessness outside of the Synagogue&#44;<lb/> when the Synagogue itself&#44; where I ought to wield<lb/> some influence shows that thirty eight years have failed<lb/> to endow clothe me with it&#63;  The demeanour of those<lb/> who habitually leave it that they may not listen&#44;<lb/> and of others who deliberately remain listless&#44; clearly<lb/> manifests the feeble hold I have on the minds of<lb/> my constituents.  I shall not add another word&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>lest I be suspected of craving for the approval&#44;<lb/> or the plaudits of the world&#44; rather than the inward<lb/> satisfaction of discharging a duty.  But I have<lb/> said it lately&#59; prayers without instruction may de&#45;<lb/>&#45;generate into habits <sic>profitly</sic> to individuals or to society.<lb/>  If better teaching&#44; a more attractive diction&#44; greater<lb/> force in expressing enunciating truths are demanded&#44; why&#44; I shall<lb/> not stand in the way of procuring the desired object.<lb/>  I also would rejoice over a crowded assemblage&#44; while whereas<lb/> I now lament a decrease of number&#59; I also would rejoice<lb/> that from this pulpit the fire of inspiration issues forth<lb/> to melt the hardness of hearts harboring sin&#44; while whereas<lb/> I now lament the desecration of Sabbath and festivals&#44;<lb/> the disregard of dietary laws by men and women who con&#45;<lb/>&#45;tribute to the maintenance of a conservative Synagogue<lb/> and its minister.  I also would rejoice over a revival<lb/> of the Hebrew language brought about by this body of<lb/> Jews&#44; while whereas I now lament its decay&#45;&#45;&#45;the forerun&#45;<lb/>&#45;er of dangers to Israel&#39;s unity.  Brethren.  As I have<lb/> freely disclosed to day my sentiments&#44; so do you consider<lb/> what may best fe benefit our common belief&#44; the status<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>of our own population in Philadelphia and the character<lb/> of the venerable congregation&#44; that I have tried faithfully<lb/> to serve thirty eight years.<lb/></p>
            <p>&#40;Here follows an address to two Bar Mitzvah.&#41;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
