<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF6_42</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1879-06" source="" attested="yes">June 1879</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_42_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_42_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_42_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_42_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_42_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_42_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_42_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_42_4v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>6 pages on 2 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For a funeral<lb/></p>
            <p>The pillars in the palace of a Roman Emperor at<lb/> Cesarea&#44; which had often seen Rabbi Abbahu enter&#44;<lb/> shed tears when the Sage expired.  So does the Talmud&#44;<lb/> in its eastern phraseology&#44; describe the loss which the<lb/> community sustained by the decease of a man deserving<lb/> well of his coreligionists.  The older representative of<lb/> his brethren had <sic>weilded</sic> the influence he could command&#44;<lb/> most righteously&#59; while his stately form and the characters<lb/> of the five heirs of his learning and virtue&#44; added dignity<lb/> to the position held.<lb/></p>
            <p>Israelites&#33;  On Friday last when the sun verging to its<lb/> decline was about to usher in the holy Sabbath&#44; the<lb/> pillars in the palace mansion of our living King wept<lb/> for grief.  He&#44; whom they had seen come and stand<lb/> eminently&#44; would be no more visit the consecrated courts.<lb/>  Henry Cohen had died was dead.  The powers he exercised for good<lb/> had sunk with the body heretofore restlessly active to give<lb/> the habitation of our Sovereign Lord glorious permanence.<lb/>  That portly figure which that which imparted &#40;imposingness&#41; to<lb/> the station occupied&#44; had changed into a motionless corpse.<lb/>  And I who grasped the hand extended&#44; as if in the act<lb/> of craving imploring the last office which a believing Jew wishes craves<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>from one of god&#39;s servants&#44; felt&#44; when that hand was<lb/> seized by death&#44; the whole weight of the calamity&#44; which disaster I felt that a deep great calamity<lb/> had befallen the weeping Synagogue.  At that fear&#45;<lb/>&#45;ful moment&#44; the past flashed before my mind and con&#45;<lb/>&#45;jured up visions sad to contemplate.  I beheld a host of well&#45;<lb/>trained defenders of our hoary&#45;headed Mother&#45;&#45;the Jewish<lb/> Church&#45;&#45;summoned away&#44; leaving their posts often to the<lb/> onset of unnatural children.  I remembered also how<lb/> the msiles of inconstant fortune had turned into angry<lb/> looks.  I bethought myself of the struggle between<lb/> bodily infirmities and unabated zeal&#44; and of the cruel<lb/> victory which the former won.  Most severe was indeed<lb/> deemed then the last blow&#44; for few had had remained to<lb/> assuage the pain it had it inflicted.<lb/></p>
            <p>Three years ago we chose as our temporal leader this<lb/> Hebrew man.  What suggested his name spontaneously<lb/> to every reflecting member of the congregation&#63;  His<lb/> social standing&#44; and a general knowledge of the views<lb/> he entertained.  For&#44; Henry Cohen did not hide his<lb/> attachment to the ancestral observances because he<lb/> enjoyed the familiar intercourse of the cultured and<lb/> respected among the professors of another creed.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>He reverenced his religion&#44; and held tenaciously thereto thereunto&#44;<lb/>&#45;&#45;as an inalienable birth&#45;&#45;right&#44; in the presence of the<lb/> world.  Without seeking a controversy&#44; the intelligent Hebrew<lb/> keenly relished the opportunity which enabled him to<lb/> explain the reason for continuing loyal to the Law and the<lb/> Prophets.  Nor was had our Chief&#44; whose demise I deplore<lb/> been merely an occasional visitor in the minor sanctuary.  All saw<lb/> him&#44; undeterred by distance&#44; a in his usual seat&#44; a<lb/> love worship <sic>worshipper</sic>&#44; ready to signify his appreciation<lb/> of the honors belonging to his tribe as scions of the<lb/> stock of Aaron&#44; by generous donations.  The selection<lb/> had been therefore wisely designed and merited.  Did it<lb/> prove so&#63;....Who puts that question&#63;  Would<lb/> I utter a strained lament before the dead&#59; lie to the<lb/> living&#44; if the late President of my congregation had<lb/> as such&#44; intentionally fallen short of his duties&#63;  If<lb/> he had been untrue to his trust&#63;  If he had deceived the confidence<lb/> founded on a widely established reputation&#63;  Never.<lb/>  Eagerness to promote the welfare of the synagogue<lb/> he unequivocally showed on solemn days by deeds of<lb/> liberality.  An ardent desire to enhance the impressioness<lb/> of our ancient service&#44; he so obviously evinced on winter<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>nights&#44; when despite a fatal malady stealing<lb/> upon his body&#44; the President <sic>travelled</sic> from afar to<lb/> meet the Minister and aid help in the efforts of training<lb/> the votaries that offered their voices to sing to God har&#45;<lb/>&#45;moniously.  These traits in the official deportment<lb/> of our temporal Director assumed a bright vivid form&#44; when<lb/> declarations of our faith &#34;Adona&#239;&#44; He is God&#34;.  &#34;The<lb/> Eternal Lord is One&#44;&#34; and I wept.  Not for the dear<lb/> object lost&#44; because that had already found its destined<lb/> place.  It was deposited in the treasury of the Omnipotent<lb/> King.  I wept for us the losers&#44; for us who must<lb/> needs go in search of what&#44; alas&#33; is growing daily more<lb/> rare.<lb/></p>
            <p>In a narrow limit the departed compared with the<lb/> Talmudical Sage of Cesarea.  He possessed distinction in<lb/> the sphere wherein he had long moved&#44; and commanded besides<lb/> disposable means.  Appearance and influence&#44; he<lb/> could also bring to bear usefully in the discharge of his va&#45;<lb/>&#45;rious duties.  And I pondered on that as I closed his<lb/> eyes.  But I cast a look around and recognized then<lb/> another point of resemblance.  It inspired a comforting<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>thought.  Like the Rabbi at whose demise&#45;&#45;according to the Talmudic hyperbole&#45;&#45;the pillars<lb/> in the palace of the Roman Emperor shed tears. according to<lb/> the Talmudic hyperbole.  Henry Cohen had fine descendants<lb/> whom neither their country nor their people will have<lb/> cause to disclaim.  There they stood in anguish&#44; but<lb/> with the fortitude which a pious training had breathed.<lb/>  Bent in agony to hear the last breathing of their<lb/> father&#44; but uplifted in spirit to Him whose goodness<lb/> they have been were early taught to adore.  Sublime spectacle<lb/> in its sorrowfulness&#33;  Grand scene spite of its distressing features&#33;...<lb/> Heirs of my friend&#33;  Your present and prospective de&#45;<lb/>&#45;meanour socially and religiously was the pride of your<lb/> parent&#44; while he lavished on you the abundance of his<lb/> affection.  And you will&#44; I am certain&#44; add honor to his<lb/> memory by exceeding the expectations he had sanguinely<lb/> formed.  More it does not become me to say.<lb/></p>
            <p>But the throbbings of my heart speak with a flowing<lb/> eloquence&#44; which my lips refuse to shape into words&#44; when<lb/> I recall the self&#45;denial of your mother&#44; her vigils and<lb/> breathless watching&#44; the suppressing of every emotion which<lb/> might betray the startling fear of the approaching a lasting separation<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>on earth from the husband&#59; aye&#58; the confiding lover&#44; as<lb/> in early days.  The silvery chord is broken sundered apart.  She<lb/> feels as if rent in her very vitals.  Be you her<lb/> soothing restorative&#44; her stay&#44; her abiding consolation.<lb/>  Be a unit in acts and sentiments to cheer the wrath<lb/> of her existence&#44; that she may not long experience<lb/> the piercing chill of this <sic>woful</sic> pass.<lb/></p>
            <p>And Thou Sovereign Lord&#33;  Bid angels of peace hover<lb/> over this dwelling of bereavement&#44; and but Oh&#33; vouchsafe<lb/> likewise to raise deliverers for Thy holy habitation.  Hebrews<lb/> fresh with f vigour&#44; glowing with zeal&#44; employing<lb/> alacrity quickly to fill up a gap&#44; sagacity readily<lb/> to remedy defects.  Hebrews like of old&#44; rising gigant&#45;<lb/>&#45;ically as a bulwark to traditional Judaism defending it at great that it<lb/> may receive protection and an eternity of name. a name and a place sacrifices&#44; to all eternity.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
