<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF14_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_2_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>2d lecture on Revelation<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  In asserting In my last lecture of the series&#44;<lb/> I asserted the necessity for of a more direct manifestation of the will of<lb/> the Lord unto man than originally provided for. by I explained that our inborn sentiments&#44;<lb/> and the and the knowledge divined from a contemplation of nature&#39;s work I did not yet set became insufficient by reason of the rising of passions&#44; which are also inhering in human flesh.<lb/>  forth clearly enough the object of Revelation But while setting forth the necessity of Revelation&#44; I did not clearly enough point out its object.  The idea mostly<lb/> held by believers&#44; is&#44; that the Deity communed supernaturally<lb/> with some chosen ones in order for this exclusive purpose.  He wished that by their teachings and example<lb/> of the inspired few the world might be brought to acknowledge confess One God&#44; and offer<lb/> Him an acceptable worship.  If my I understand my<lb/> religion correctly&#45;&#45;and may the Source of Light illumine my mind<lb/> if I am at fault&#45;&#45;I may dare pronounce that prevailing idea imperfect.<lb/>  Let us consider the question with all the requisite seriousness which its<lb/> importance demands.  We have agreed&#44; I think&#44; that creation the universe was<lb/> the result of design&#44; and of not of chance&#59; and as creation is not only amazingly<lb/> grand&#44; but supremely useful&#44; we have a right to argue that<lb/> it must have been the effect of Divine love.  Again&#58;<lb/> man placed in that creation&#44; or at all events&#44; in a magnificent<lb/> part of it&#44; which we call earth&#44; is not only <sic>marvellous</sic> in form body<lb/> and intellect&#44; but eminently fitted for the enjoyment of his which life<lb/> surroundings procures.  His must formation also must have been the effect of<lb/> Divine love.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Well then&#58; the end which the Omnipotent wished to<lb/> attain by His hands work was not personal&#44; so to say&#44; but beneficial.<lb/>  The Creator sought there by it the happiness of His creatures.<lb/>  Precisely the same&#44; I conceive&#44; was the object of Revelation.<lb/>  Not the merely the securing of a recognition of His existence and Power&#44; nor the reception<lb/> of homage and reverence&#44; but principally and primarily the promotion of the world&#39;s hap&#45;<lb/>&#45;piness was the primary motive of God&#39;s communion with<lb/> man.  The Spirit that fills all space is beatified in<lb/> Himself. and Nothing that we may do or think devise can affect<lb/> His essence&#59; but the Almighty is concerned in the felicity<lb/> of the beings He has endowed with feelings and reason.<lb/></p>
            <p>Now&#58; the admission of a plurality of gods is destructive having its<lb/> origin in a mental aberration perversion&#44; and in the excitement of passions perversion a misdirection of low our instincts<lb/> is destruction of human happiness&#44; because it engenders and fosters ill&#45;<lb/>will between people and people&#44; city and city&#44; family<lb/> and family.  It is fatal to human happiness because it<lb/> demoralizes the individual&#44; inasmuch as the different gods are represented<lb/> under different aspects&#44; none being perfect&#45;&#45;else one would<lb/> suffice&#45;&#45;&#44; but all displaying defects which their <sic>worshippers</sic><lb/> try to copy.  Hence immorality and cruelty often supplant chas&#45;<lb/>&#45;tity and compassion.  And thus is the felicity&#45;&#45;designed by the beneficent Providence&#45;&#45;sacrificed.<lb/>  I do not need illustrate my assertion.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Those who have not made themselves acquainted with the history<lb/> of pagan nations&#44; as told in hundreds of volumes&#44; will find<lb/> in the Bible enough sufficient matter to judge of the<lb/> wantonness and ferocity sanctioned by heathenism.<lb/>  Abraham&#44; the first of the One God&#39;s missionaries&#44; was to carry<lb/> out the intentions of the Creator whom he discovered on nature&#44;<lb/> and whose will had been supernaturally manifested to his spirit soul.<lb/>  He was to commence the work&#44; which his posterity would<lb/> continue&#44; so as finally to bring again the state which<lb/> the intelligent dwellers of the earth ought always to have<lb/> enjoyed.  In a word&#59; he was to show that only by Zedakah &#38; Mishpat &#34;right&#45;<lb/>&#45;eousness and justice&#34; alone &#45;&#45;which he was bid to disseminate&#45;&#45;&#40;Gen XVIII.19&#41; can terrestrial happiness be esta&#45;<lb/>&#45;blished.  Observe this point&#44; my brethren&#44; which<lb/> I consider deem all&#45;important.  The actions of our patriarch in<lb/> which his character shines most brightly brilliantly are those that exhibit his<lb/> pure conception of the Lord&#44; whose attributes he strove to imi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tate.  A desire to promote peace&#44; to be long&#45;suffering and to<lb/> abundantly help.  His conduct towards his nephew&#44; discloses<lb/> those sentiments.  Generosity to strangers&#44; pity for the fallen&#44;<lb/> integrity with even men who had dealt dishonestly with him&#44;<lb/> are traits which stand forth preeminently in Abraham&#39;s demeanour<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>An exquisite sense of veneration and affection for<lb/> the departed&#44; and a disinterested and self&#45;denying disposition<lb/> crown the character of him&#44; concerning whom we read&#45;&#45;even before the Decalogue had been delivered&#45;&#45;&#44; that<lb/> he kept the charge of the Lord&#44; His commandments&#44; His sta&#45;<lb/>&#45;tutes and His laws.  The founder of our people was a mor&#45;<lb/>&#45;tal&#44; hence therefore fallible&#44; and He shared in a slight no doubt&#44; i a degree&#44; the<lb/> weaknesses of his the age he lived in&#44; but he exceeded all his<lb/> contemporaries in the qualities of the heart&#44; as much greatly as he must<lb/> have towered above them them all in a clear massive&#44; solid intellect understanding.<lb/>  By In the exercise of those practical virtues which were formed his bright adorn&#45;<lb/>&#45;ments&#44; he Abraham reflected the will of the universal Father.<lb/>  And when the patriarch man of Ur Chasdim&#44; who loved the Archetype of goodness which<lb/> his own deeds mirrored forth&#44; showed polytheists that his Faith was not simply negative&#45;&#45;as they erroneously may have styled&#45;&#45;&#44; when he signified his readiness<lb/> to part with the dearest of objects for the sake of his God&#59;<lb/> and when he drew back from making his hands from a human sacrifice&#44; an not forced by parental emotions&#44; but by the will of<lb/> an act not desired by the Lord of who delights in mercy&#44; he incontestably<lb/> proved himself worthy of a world&#45;redeeming mission.<lb/>  Moses was the next selected to take up the work&#44; which<lb/> Abraham began and give it a more durable f enduring shape.  The time was ripe&#44; and the man<lb/> was the fittest.  It is foreign to my purpose to relate<lb/> the history of the inspired lawgiver&#44; but I must recall<lb/> a fact&#44; bearing upon the point I intend to illustrate elucidate.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Before the leader of the priestly people had heard a super&#45;<lb/>&#45;natural voice communing with his spirit&#44; he had displayed<lb/> the qualities needed of an messenger of the One God exponent of Revelation.  Righteousness<lb/> and Justice&#44;&#45;&#45;the traits which had won for the patriarch a<lb/> Divine trust&#45;&#45;&#44; were early <sic>developped</sic> in the character of the<lb/> arch&#45;prophet.  He evinced those principles in the land of his<lb/> birth&#44; when an an inmate of a royal palace&#59; he illustrated<lb/> them in a strange land towards strangers.  And who can<lb/> tell how frequently the sentiments which had impelled him&#44; in<lb/> the days of youth&#44; to strike down the dastardly ruthless Egyptian who was<lb/> lashing tearing the flesh of a defenseless Hebrew&#59; the sentiments which urged him<lb/> in his manhood to hasten rise to the rescue of Jethro&#39;s daughters&#44;<lb/> stirred in in his breast&#44; when age crept on and found him<lb/> still an exile&#63;  In the solitary wilderness&#44; where his<lb/> flock pastured&#44; while the pensive shepherd may have<lb/> contemplated afar off from afar the condition of the enslaved<lb/> Israel&#44; his tender nature may have revolted at the objection<lb/> of a race issuing from the noble Abraham.  A longing<lb/> for their liberation may have being agitating his heart&#44; when<lb/> the vision of the burning bush broke upon him.<lb/></p>
            <p>Mark well the words first uttered in that vision.  The<lb/> God whom Moses had heard his brethren invoke in amidst their sufferings&#44;<lb/> speaks.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Perhaps&#44; the mother of the y royally trained babe taught had whispered<lb/> him in his ears the name of the great Creator and the national expectations&#44; in her visits to the king&#39;s<lb/> courts&#44; as a nurse to the princess&#39; adopted child.  Moses<lb/> recognizes the Lord of patriarchal tradition&#44; and he is seized<lb/> with awe at the apparition.  Yet How consonant are the<lb/> heavenly accents with the feelings of him who yearned with<lb/> pity&#59; how thrilling to the soul of the listener who hoped<lb/> for a salvation liberation.  Aye&#58; No A deed of righteousness was the end<lb/> of that revelation&#59; the vindication of justice the aim of<lb/> that celestial manifestation.  Hark&#58; &#34;I have seen the affliction<lb/> of my people...I know his pains...I have come to deliver<lb/> him...The cry of the children of Israel has come unto<lb/> me.  I have seen the oppression with which the Egyptians<lb/> distress them.&#34;˄  The deepest of a responsive chord was touched.<lb/>  And Yet Moses stood motionless.  He did not leap with<lb/> joy at the announcement&#44; and exclaim &#34;behold&#44; here am I&#44; send<lb/> me.&#34;  Has it never happened to you&#44; my<lb/> brethren&#44; that&#44; looking forward to some event&#44; which was<lb/> to decide the fate of a man&#44; or of a body of men&#44; when realizing<lb/> that you were to play in it the most import part&#44; in it&#44; you shrunk<lb/> back in dismay&#44; you completely mistrusted your powers&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Draw then your inference.  Moses must have often<lb/> pondered on the declarations of God to the fathers.  In his<lb/> ardent devotion to the cause of truth&#44; he may have even<lb/> warmed himself up in the belief that&#44; if called to the<lb/> work of redemption&#44; he could have been equal to it.<lb/>  Still&#44; when brought face to face with the stern fact that<lb/> the fiat of the Most High had destined him&#44; as the arm<lb/> of salvation&#44; he trembled at the bare thought of the assuming<lb/> the mighty undertaking.  Of course&#44; to institute a com&#45;<lb/>&#45;parison between ourselves and him who knew the Arbiter<lb/> of human affairs better than any living being that has ever<lb/> trod the earth&#44; would be the height of presumption&#44; but taking<lb/> as a criterion our own feelings&#44;&#45;&#45;when placed in a situation slightly si&#45;<lb/>&#45;milar&#45;&#45;&#44; we may form an idea of those which pervaded<lb/> the heart of Moses&#44; when demanded to assume a task&#44; of a<lb/> magnitude unsurpassed in the annals of the world.<lb/>  The evidences of a divine selection could not overcome the<lb/> dread of being inadequate to the requirements.  Why then<lb/> then the pressure brought by the Great &#34;I am&#34; upon the<lb/> soul of the shepherd&#44; in the awful vision of the burn&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing&#45;bush&#63;  Why was not the burden laid upon another&#44;<lb/> bolder and more eager of winning lasting him glory&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>I answer those questions by setting forth again my own<lb/> conviction.  The deepest sense of Righteousness and Justice&#44;<lb/> are the pre&#45;requisites of a messenger of the One God.<lb/></p>
            <p>Revelation which&#44; as I understand it&#44; was not intended to<lb/> compel the acceptance of dogmas nor essentially to teach a mode of worship&#44; but to impart the rules<lb/> of goodness and equity&#59; revelation which was a voluntary<lb/> detraction of the honor of the Creator&#44; who&#44; by means of a few&#44;<lb/> would humanize the world and thus make it happy&#59; reve&#45;<lb/>&#45;lation claimed Moses as its noblest exponent.  The<lb/> a twofold share of the spirit of Abraham had rested on him.  A total abne&#45;<lb/>&#45;gation for the sake of the principle&#45;&#45;not the enthusiasm of<lb/> the hour&#44; which vanishes with time and the passing circumstances&#45;&#45;&#44; but<lb/> a patient endurance&#44; a determined resolve to forget self in the<lb/> welfare of a nation&#44; an un<sic>yeilding</sic> faith in the final triumph<lb/> of Truth&#44; which resists menacing impediments.  And withal a<lb/> penetrating wisdom and a sagacious judgment capable suggesting<lb/> means adapted to the end&#44; and capable of carrying out the will<lb/> of the Omnipotent Master.<lb/></p>
            <p>Such was were the traits of the man through whose miraculous<lb/> agency Israel was drawn from the brick&#45;kiln to the foot of Sinai&#44;<lb/> there to become the people of Revelation to be robed with the sacred raiment that was ever to distinguish him as the people of Revelation.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
