<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF13_7</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_7_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_7_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_7_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_7_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_7_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_7_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_7_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_7_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_7_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_7_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_7_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_7_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>For Sabbath Itr&#243;<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>A woman in Egypt became once the mother of six hundred thou&#45;<lb/>&#45;sand children.  This announcement made in a college&#44; existing<lb/> during the days long gone by&#44; startled all the students.  But they<lb/> soon learnt that it was a moral under cover of a fable.<lb/>  That being through whom we derive a higher knowledge of the aim<lb/> of life&#44; than of what we share in common with lower animals&#44;<lb/> may rightly claim the title of our parent.  The wife of<lb/> Jo Amram&#44; in giving the world her second son&#44; supplied the<lb/> means&#44; wherewith to create a nation.  The number of male<lb/> adults issued from brutalizing slavery&#44; received a new birth<lb/> from the vitalizing influence of that child of Jochebed.  How<lb/> he exercised his superior faculties for good&#44; we have just read.<lb/>  From morning till evening Moses sat to adjust men&#39;s difficulties&#44;<lb/> to teach men the duties of life.  Long he bore the fatigue&#44;<lb/> unweariedly he endured it&#44; upheld by the thought which<lb/> will always prove the strongest incentive&#59; the mightiest support in<lb/> a righteous undertaking&#58; the belief that he worked for and<lb/> with Almighty God&#59; that in striving to improve indivi&#45;<lb/>duals&#44; he led the van of social advancement.<lb/>  With justice it has therefore been written&#44; that of the merits<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>of the ancient champion of Israel&#44; could have been placed on<lb/> a scale&#44; they would have outweighed all those acquired by the<lb/> six hundred thousand men he delivered from degrading bondage &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> For&#44; every action ennobling human nature&#44; every deed of<lb/> goodness and charity thus performed&#44; redounded again to<lb/> the honor of the zealous instructor.  You remember&#44; my<lb/> Brethren&#33; his answer to Jethro.  The latter astonished<lb/> at a self&#45;imposed task&#44; most onerous and responsible&#44;<lb/> undertaken without help&#44; inquired into its object.  Moses<lb/> said&#58; &#34;When the people have any matter of dispute&#44; it<lb/> is brought to me&#44; and I judge between man and his neigh&#45;<lb/>&#45;bor&#44; and impart the statutes of God&#44; and His laws.&#34;  From<lb/> his own lips he would that all&#44; without wondrous distinction of grade<lb/> or standing&#44; might hear what it is means to conform to the will<lb/> of the universal Father.  To spare himself by drawing<lb/> a dividing line between one Hebrew and another&#59; To attend<lb/> personally to affairs deemed of high importance&#44; and leave<lb/> to subordinates the decision of cases considered of less moment&#44;<lb/> did not agree with his keen sense of pastoral duties.  And<lb/> though he Moses deferentially listened to the advice of his father&#45;in<lb/>law&#44; who suggested that plan&#44; you will observe that we have<lb/> no proof of his having practically followed it till long after.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>During his absence of forty days on the mountain&#44; he ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;pointed Aaron and his nephew Hur as his substitutes&#44; and<lb/> only in the second year of his administration&#44; when our an&#45;<lb/>&#45;cestors&#44; stirred up by the mixed multitude of unbelieving Egyp&#45;<lb/>&#45;ptians&#44; became too unruly and too importunate in their demands&#44;<lb/> did their indefatigable leader allow myhimself some respite<lb/> by the choice&#44; Divinely made&#44; of seventy coadjutors.<lb/>  Now&#44; I cannot say what others who have assumed the<lb/> spiritual guide of a Congregation think&#44; but to me the<lb/> model conduct of the greatest shepherd in Israel stands as both<lb/> as a lesson and a rebuke.  Slight&#44; insignificant&#44; indeed&#44; as<lb/> the work I am bound to perform is&#44; in comparison with<lb/> that which he accomplished single&#45;handed&#44; yet&#44; weariness<lb/> will at times creep all over my being.  Fain would I then<lb/> slip lapse into a state of inertness.  Is it ambition ungratified<lb/> which as takes that form shape&#63;  Perhaps so.  My aspirations to are too lofty.<lb/>  I am eager to acquire the merit of creating a generation of high&#45;toned Israelites&#44;<lb/> all noblemen in society&#44; every one a shining star in our<lb/> religious horizon&#44; a band of brethren clustering together to ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;raise the standard of Sinai&#44; and glorify the living God.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>And feeling how much faster the wish can travel than<lb/> the reality&#44; I let fatigue steal away my energies.<lb/>  Shame upon any&#44; who having voluntarily taken the<lb/> lead&#44; grows faint by the way.  From morning till<lb/> evening the righteous son of Jochebed bent his powers<lb/> to the grand object in view.  From morning till evening&#44;<lb/> he served the cause he had been called upon to promote.<lb/>  Did success always come forward to meet him with radiant<lb/> smiles&#63;  Did it never turn its back on his <sic>unremmitting</sic><lb/> efforts&#63;  Among the six hundred thousand male adults&#44;<lb/> whose wrongs he righted&#44; and whose mistaken notions of<lb/> the aim of life he corrected&#44; did none give him occasion<lb/> to grieve over said disappointments&#63;  Listen&#44; my Brethren&#33;<lb/> When Moses was about to quit for ever his work labors and the<lb/> people he had loved so well the pen forced to write what inspiration dictated&#44;<lb/> traced this words sentence&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>  &#34;He executed the justice of the Lord and His judgments with<lb/> Israel&#34; That is the highest testimony of unswerving fidelity.<lb/>  The tried servant did not falter in sight of obstacles&#44; he<lb/> did not flinch despite the impediments with which a desire to<lb/> discharge his full duty must have presented.  A lesson is that<lb/> and a rebuke to all&#44; who in the ministration of religions<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>suffer hindrances to awe them back into a state of inac&#45;<lb/>tivity.<lb/></p>
            <p>But do you imagine&#44; my Brethren&#33; that I address you this<lb/> Sabbath&#44; simply to make a clean breast of my own<lb/> shortcomings&#63;  No&#58; the drift of my speech is to let you<lb/> feel that if I am not up to the mark&#44; many of you fall<lb/> very short of the point.  All of us have been furnished with<lb/> the instruments to work salvation.  You have&#44; in common<lb/> with me&#44; a high mission.  I may be bound to show the way<lb/> to the altar&#44; but there you are all each of you is an officiating priests.<lb/>  To fancy contend that I must actively serve&#44; and you may passively<lb/> look on&#44; would be to falsify the message which the son<lb/> of Amram brought us from above.  He was directed to &#34;say<lb/> to the house of Jacob&#44;&#34; and not to a few&#44; to &#34;tell the<lb/> children of Israel&#34; and not to some privileged individuals&#44; that<lb/> the observance of the Sinaic covenant is the badge of<lb/> honor by which the descendants of the people set apart for as the patriarchs must be distinguished the as ministers of truth.  But does<lb/> the congregation of the Lord wear that token of a divine<lb/> selection&#63;  I cannot deny that quite a number<lb/> of my brethren&#44; consider the Dene Decalogue a fitting<lb/> ornament.  Their very chambers seems to illustrate<lb/> that thought.  But&#44; Alas&#33;  What decorates the walls&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>fails to adorn the heart&#44; and beautify the mind.  The<lb/> fine print engraving of the ten commandments&#44; and the elegant frame are not substitutes for<lb/> the <sic>obedyence</sic> due to the law.  Tear down&#44; I would<lb/> cry to such tear down the picture and palpably show love<lb/> for the object it represents.  Bend before God and not<lb/> to idols of gold&#59; be never guilty of profanity&#59; give<lb/> the seventh day to whom it rightly belongs&#59; Treat your<lb/> parents as your superiors.  Do not destroy your neigh&#45;<lb/>&#45;bor&#39;s character&#44; or domestic happiness&#59; deal honestly&#59;<lb/> Let not greed close your ears to the demands of justice.<lb/>  Let all see To Your relations of life you must prove yourselves descent and your labor as that you&#44; the priests<lb/> of the Almighty.  Care nothing about being recognized<lb/> as Jews from certain Hebrew characters bedecking the walls of<lb/> your dwellings&#44; if they stand there as dead letters.<lb/>  Chase away the prevailing idea&#44; that a strict conformity<lb/> to the precepts is the business of one clothed in a the<lb/> robe of a religious office.  Whence the all subverting<lb/> notion emanated&#44; I know not&#44; but it is utterly false&#44;<lb/> and subversive of the cardinal tenets of our faith.  You<lb/> all&#44; like myself&#44; form an integral part of that body<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>styled by God &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; meaning&#44; a nation devoted to<lb/> a grand purpose.  And this is surely to be carried out by<lb/> personal endeavours&#44; and not by proxy.  Were I a<lb/> Moses&#44; and had I seven hundred&#44; instead of seventy elders<lb/> to teach with the me&#44; sacred obligations&#44; I would accomplish<lb/> nothing&#44; if you believed it is my concern and not none of yours<lb/> to hold fast to the Constitution written with the finger of<lb/> God.  You need&#44; of course&#44; expect that the appointed<lb/> watchman will always be seen uplifting that stand&#45;<lb/>&#45;ard with unsullied hands&#44; and if he aims at being &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; the promoter of righteousness&#44; he will make his<lb/> deeds exemplify his words&#44; but verily I tell you the humblest<lb/> among my coreligionists&#44; is like the highest an ordained<lb/> minister&#59; and as such he dares not as such refuse his cooperation<lb/> in rendering the Torah honorable&#44; and the name of the<lb/> Giver glorious.  All stood at the foot of Sinai&#44;<lb/> and declared that they would do hearken and obey.  Who among<lb/> us will perjure himself&#44; who among us&#44; being a<lb/> professing Jew&#44; will let the barrier of heavenly truths<lb/> trail the earth&#44; because he does not wish to rather than put forth<lb/> his hand and upraise it&#63;  To you my Brethren<lb/> who abide in lowliness&#44; I direct my word&#44; and in the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>language of paternal affection say&#44; that you can<lb/> extol your religion and gain the lasting merit of<lb/> serving your Father Israel&#39;s Legislator.  You can verify the prophecy<lb/> of Isaiah &#34;Their seed shall be known among gentiles&#44; and<lb/> their offspring amidst peoples&#34;  Cling tenaciously to the<lb/> ten berities you have heard this day&#59; be not lured away<lb/> by false appearances&#44; by the tinsel of riches&#44; value the<lb/> title bestowed upon you by the Almighty&#44; more than the asso&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciation of the worldly&#44; and through you will be fulfilled<lb/> the promise &#34;Ye shall be called priests of the Lord&#59; the<lb/> ministers of our God shall be the appellation name applied to you&#34;<lb/>  Oh&#33; my hearers&#33; since we are the chosen of our Parent as missionaries of the Most High&#44; since<lb/> we have a common parentage&#44; and we are the coheirs of the<lb/> same truths&#44; the possessors of the same traditions&#44; and of the<lb/> same indestructible hopes&#44; let us band together without<lb/> distinction of grade or station&#44; and work for the elevation<lb/> of our faith.  And may let us pray that when the Supreme Lord grant that<lb/> which He visits His flock he may still find&#44; a remnant among<lb/> us a remnant of the Judaic tree whose stem is rooted in the ground&#44; and will <sic>yeild</sic> a holy<lb/> seed &#91;Hebrew&#93; for ever.  Amen<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
