<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF3_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1897" source="" attested="yes">1897</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_1_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>S. MORAIS.<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET.<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>97<lb/>
                For &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>If I were asked in what the highest honor of our<lb/> father Abraham consisted&#44; I would unhesitatingly answer&#44; that it consist&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed in his having taken intellectually an eagle like flight to<lb/> rise immesearably superior beyond measure to all his surroundings.  Neat<lb/> unique mental effort&#44; earned for the founder of the He&#45;<lb/>&#45;brew people the title appellation by which Isaiah bringing a message from above in to day&#39;s Hap&#45;<lb/>&#45;torah designated him in the name of Y &#91;&#63;&#93; inspiration &#34;the friend of God.&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93; When all the world all<lb/> paid homage bent the knee before to the servants of the Omnipotent mas&#45;<lb/>&#45;ter&#44; our patriarch beheld recognized in the servants only a re&#45;<lb/>&#45;flection of the Master&#39;s Almightiness.  Sabeans&#44; or<lb/> Sabians were his contemporaries.  They believed in<lb/> Astrology&#44; or in the influence exercised over our fate by of the host of heaven&#44; which<lb/> a Supreme Power created for the service of the world&#44; in<lb/> which we move&#44; and perhaps of countless unknown worlds.<lb/>  To the sun and moon and planets they bowed&#44; and the image<lb/> of objects&#44; that whirl round the illimitable space<lb/> above us&#44; they fashioned for their senseless worship.  Super&#45;<lb/>&#45;stition was the creed by which those ancient heathens swore&#44;<lb/> and in that falsity Abraham was reared.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>But the voice that which spoke within the mind of<lb/> that searcher of after truth&#44; exorcised&#44; as it were&#44; the<lb/> false belief&#44; when it did bid Abraham go forth and<lb/> <sic>and</sic> look heavenward upward.  So has the Midrash partly<lb/> taught in its comment on a sentence in our Parashah<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;He brought him forth abroad &#39;viz;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Lave behind thy astrological notions&#34; the voice said<lb/> A Credibility in the influence of objects that people<lb/> the firmament&#44; has been always condemned by the<lb/> prophets&#44; and by none more forcibly than by Jeremiah&#44; who<lb/> thus cautioned admonished Israel of yore his country&#58; &#34;Learn not the way of<lb/> gentiles&#44; and yea&#59; be not dismayed at the signs of the<lb/> heavens&#44; though nations may be afraid of them.  For the<lb/> rules customs practices of those peoples are vanity....Be stand not in dread<lb/> of them&#44; for they can do no harm&#44; nor is there any power in<lb/> them to do good.&#34;  But say brethren&#44; are all Jews in this supposed enlightened age above the<lb/> absurdities of false beliefs&#63;  It must I will not be denyd<lb/> that many are free from superstitions&#59; but how<lb/> large the number of those&#44; whose mind&#44; like a ship<lb/> in a stormy sea&#44; is tossed continually upon the waves<lb/> of idle fancies&#33;  It might excite laughter&#44; if the subject<lb/> were not serious&#44; to hear one relate that he could have foretold<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>disasters&#44; for from his having seen shooting stars in the sky&#33;  More sur&#45;<lb/>&#45;passingly ridiculous than that is the a prevalent notion&#44; that the<lb/> casual circumstance of thirteen persons sitting together&#44;<lb/> predicts portends some evil misfortune.  If Why&#44; if brother Israelites were I inclined to put forth in prognostics&#44; I would<lb/> on the contrary call that circumstance a good omen&#44; inasmuch as at 13th<lb/> a Hebrew lad is initiated in the performance of the com&#45;<lb/>&#45;mandments&#44; and 13 are the Divine attributes taught imported to<lb/> Moses in the cleft of the rock at Sinai&#44; and 13 are<lb/> the Jewish creeds as formulated by Maimonides&#44; and in<lb/> Rabbinical literature 13 are the rules for interpreting<lb/> the Law. &#91;Hebrew&#93; But even more humiliating to the human<lb/> understanding are some of the still existing the superstitions surely are still in vogue.<lb/>  Not long ago a family&#44; sadly bereaved&#44; said to me that<lb/> the loss sustained&#44; had been foreshadowed by the un&#45;<lb/>&#45;accountable falling of a looking glass&#44; reduced to frag&#45;<lb/>&#45;ments. without any human agency. And I remember<lb/> how the pranks of a mischievous servant girl&#44; occa&#45;<lb/>&#45;sioned in Philadelphia the belief that a certain house<lb/> was haunted by ghosts&#45;&#45;if such have ever appeared.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Now&#44; if those only who have cast aside the be&#45;<lb/>&#45;lief in an ever&#45;present and all sustaining protecting God&#44; were affected by follies<lb/> of that nature&#44; I might venture to assign a reason for<lb/> it.  I would argue&#44; that the absence of a reverential<lb/> awe for a Supreme Being&#44; has made room for a dread<lb/> of imaginary things&#44; which a heated fancy created begot.  For begun For<lb/> I hold that he who scoffs at religion&#44; is apt to substitute for it conjure up in its stead<lb/> errors of his own invention.  But it happens that the<lb/> false ideas&#44; which I deprecate&#44; are entertained also by men&#44;<lb/> who&#44; seemingly at least&#44; honor the Lord God.  I cannot<lb/>  conceive how an Israelite&#44; who has read his Bible<lb/> intelligently can reconcile with it a belief in omens and<lb/> prognostics.  Where is the absolutely unapproachable foreknowledge of the<lb/> Eternal&#44; in the destiny of nations and individuals&#44; if perish&#45;<lb/>&#45;able beings can read their fate in fortuitous events&#63;<lb/>  Where is the mercy of the Eternal&#44; if His creatures are to<lb/> be harrowed by a foreknowledge of approaching evils&#63;<lb/>  That it is folly&#44; nay&#44; wickedness in mortals to pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;tend that they can unfold what is concealed in the bosom benat beneath the impenetrable<lb/> veil of the future&#59; and that the Lord has given us a stand&#45;<lb/>&#45;ard by which to regulate our actions and had and avow not heeding superstition&#59; that our individual conduct<lb/> and not chance calls down upon us a blessing&#44; or a curse&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>all that&#44; I might prove by <sic>exhaustless</sic> quotations.  For&#44; the<lb/> books of br Moses&#44; the writings of the prophets&#44; the<lb/> inspired effusions of our psalmists&#44; moralists and poets&#44;<lb/> abound teem with them &#91;&#63;&#93; rules and maxims to that effect&#44; but this morning&#44; I prefer to<lb/> let an inimitable orator speak that truth rehearse teach us a lesson.<lb/>  You have heard Isaiah son of Amoz preach&#58; speak&#58; &#34;Why wilt thou<lb/> so say so O Jacob&#44; and thus speak thus O Israel&#33;  My way<lb/> is hidden from the Lord&#44; and my cause is passed over from<lb/> by the cognizance of my God&#34;.  A long association with Sabeans&#44;<lb/> or <sic>worshippers</sic> of heavenly bodies&#44; had given rise to a bane&#45;<lb/>&#45;ful thought.  Our ancestors were led to believe that God had<lb/> peopled the sky with spirits under in the semblance of stars to into whose power He had<lb/> consigned the creatures of the earth.  If the star&#44; under<lb/> which a man person was born was proved happened to be an auspicious one his live would&#45;&#45;<lb/>independently of his own exertions&#45;&#45;be prove happy.  If&#44; on the con&#45;<lb/>&#45;trary&#44; an unpropitious star ruled at the hour of his birth&#44;<lb/> he was doomed to suffer.  God would not deign to direct<lb/> human concerns.  Glad at having completed His handiwork&#44; He rest&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed on His throne&#44; surrounded by angels and archangels&#44; who paid<lb/> Him homage.  This false doctrine&#44; which obtained too many<lb/> followers&#44; even among some of the brightest intellects&#44; is fought<lb/> against in the Haptorah of this sabbath.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>He Isaiah tells that the Creator of the universe is not a<lb/> human sovereign&#44; entrusting to subordinate officers the<lb/> government of his Kingdom.  Hast thou not heard&#44;<lb/> the prophet asks&#44; that the everlasting God&#44; the Lord&#44; who created the ends<lb/> of the earth&#44; fainteth not&#44; neither is He ever weary&#59; that<lb/> those only who trust only in Him will reach a tower&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing height as an eagle in its upward flight&#44; but those<lb/> who rely on vanity shall stumble and fall&#63;  Then&#44;<lb/> directing the his inspired word to nations that stood in<lb/> fear of imaginary gods&#44; he the great Seer sets before their vision<lb/> a pattern worthy of imitation&#45;&#45;our father Abraham.<lb/>  Who hath raised up one from the East&#44; whom right&#45;<lb/>eousness met at his every steps&#63;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  For&#44; he our patriarch also had been trained to<lb/> believe that the fate of man is unalterably ordained by<lb/> the planets.  But with the strength force of his intellect he<lb/> repelled that baneful doctrine&#44; and laid hold of the<lb/> soul elevating belief in One God&#44; whose providence extends<lb/> to the whole human race.  Such is the purport of Isaiah&#39;s<lb/> sermon&#44; when he calls upon distant isles to listen to him in silence<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93; But to the seed of Abraham&#45;&#45;the witnesses<lb/> of the truth&#44; which their immortal father discovered&#45;&#45;Isaiah<lb/> appeals in persuasive language&#44; to remain the chosen<lb/> servants of a <sic>humanising</sic> cause &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            <p>Comforting&#44; as and courage inspiring<lb/> are the closing sentences of the section set apart for<lb/> the Haptorah of this sabbath.  &#34;Fear not O Israel&#44; for<lb/> I am with thee&#44; be not dismayed&#44; for&#44; I am thy<lb/> God&#44; I will strengthen thee&#59; yea&#44; I will help thee&#59;<lb/> I will uphold thee with the right hand of my righteousness.&#34;<lb/>  How consoling to a people that has woefully suffered<lb/> and does yet suffers still not to betray a Divine trust&#59; how consoling&#44; to<lb/> be prophetically assured that it will come forth un&#45;<lb/>&#45;scathed from the flames which a prejudiced world has kindled all<lb/> around it to consume it.  A Happy the Yes&#44; most noble if &#91;Hebrew&#93; people&#44; the people of the God of Abraham&#44; that<lb/> immoveable in its adherence to the idea given by Abraham left received as<lb/> an eternal inheritance&#44; defies prejudice and persecution.<lb/>  Have you noticed&#44; my Brethren&#44; a quaint expression&#44; near<lb/> the end of our Haftorah&#63;  It reads thus&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Fear not&#44; thou<lb/> worm Jacob.&#34;  Wherefore did the Seer chose a word in his<lb/> metaphorical language&#44; a word <sic>significative</sic> of abjection&#44;<lb/> while he surely knew how to find select one of exaltation&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>The Midrash answers replies so to that question &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  In the same manner<lb/> as the worm&#44; though&#44; among the very lowest among of creatures&#44; can<lb/> pierce with its gnawing teeth the lofty cedars of<lb/> Lebanon&#44; so can Israel&#44; when <sic>levelled</sic> with the ground&#44;<lb/> pierce the vaults of heavens with the utterance of their lips&#44;<lb/> Let us then open our lips in prayer<lb/> and draw down strength and salvation continuous vigor resisting power.  Let us then<lb/> yet be firm&#44; while praying that the trials&#44; to which the progeny of the<lb/> friend of God are exposed everywhere through inveterate<lb/> ill&#45;will&#44; may soon cease.  Let us pray for the dawning<lb/> of that glorious era when one Shepherd and one Lord shall<lb/> be universally recognized acknowledged.  Let us pray that the prediction<lb/> twice foretold with firm conviction&#44; be speedily realized&#59; when<lb/> many peoples shall come and say&#58; &#34;Let us go up to the<lb/> mountain of the Lord&#44; to the house of the God of Jacob&#44;<lb/> and He will teach us some of His ways&#44; and we will<lb/> walk in His paths.  Then the promise&#44; as in the ceasing &#91;&#63;&#93; of our Haftorah&#44;<lb/> will be fulfilled&#58; We shall rejoice in the &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Lord&#44; and glory in the Holy One of Israel.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
