<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF11_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_2_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>The laws of clean food and clean body<lb/>
                predicated on remarks made at the conference<lb/>
                for organizing societies of charitable Relef Relief<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.<lb/></p>
            <p>I owe the Congregation an apology.  I should have an&#45;<lb/>&#45;nounced last Sabbath that my hading received during the week a communication<lb/> from the society&#44; which aims to suppress mendicancy for organizing charitable relief.<lb/>  In that letter paper I was urged to speak on the workings of that<lb/> organization&#44; show that they commend themselves to univer&#45;<lb/>&#45;sal approval and invite all my hearers to attend some<lb/> of the different sessions held on Tuesday in various localities.<lb/>  I regret my forgetfulness&#44; the more so because I have<lb/> been informed that my colleagues being in receipt of the<lb/> same paper document&#44; introduced the subject to which it referred<lb/> in their lectures.  My compunction for the uninten&#45;<lb/>&#45;tional negligence&#44; is&#44; however&#44; lessened by the thought<lb/> that I am avowedly in sympathy with the aforenamed<lb/> association&#44; and that more than once I have of late allu&#45;<lb/>&#45;ded to its excellencies.  Specially have I presented one a<lb/> of the features in it which I deem extremely becoming&#44; and<lb/> which cannot too often enough be brought out exhibited forward for the<lb/> serious consideration of the wise and the good.<lb/>  It is that which looks to spies out forthcoming evils&#44; and<lb/> endeavours to avert them by sagacious measures.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>It is I mean the suppression of mendicancy by education<lb/> which elevates nature and refines manners&#44; be it<lb/> even compulsory education.  For the plan of coercion has had its strenuous advocates&#44; and it was discussed with warmth at a recent conference.  But I hear people com&#45;<lb/>plain &#34;It is very hard&#45;&#45;they say&#45;&#45;that parents should not be al&#45;<lb/>&#45;lowed full control over their offspring.  What sort<lb/> of a free country is that in which the government<lb/> forces a father to send his sons and daughters to pu&#45;<lb/>&#45;blic schools&#44; when they are needed at home to do<lb/> the drudgery&#63;&#34;  But I ask in my turn&#58; &#34;What kind<lb/> of citizens are they who expect the government to<lb/> guard their property from the prowling thief&#44; to protect<lb/> their lives from the dagger of the highwayman&#44; to<lb/> defend the honor of their females from the ref ruffianly<lb/> drunkard&#44; and yet will raise in their premises the off&#45;<lb/>&#45;scouring of society&#44; for whom prisons and houses of<lb/> correction must be built and supported&#63;&#34;  &#34;It is<lb/> a bad rule which does not work both ways&#34; says I believe to be<lb/> the a common but correct adage.  Byt a tact agreement&#44; the<lb/> inhabitants of a civilized country&#44; can demand that<lb/> a shield be thrown round their persons&#44; their dwellings places<lb/> and substance&#44; but by reason of the same compact<lb/> each of one is bound to contribute to the welfare of<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>the commonwealth or to try at least to try that his residence<lb/> be not an injury to it thereto.  And no greater harm can<lb/> be inflicted upon a state than to populate people it<lb/> with youths plying naught but beggary&#44; because they have as the only resort for having been<lb/> culpably left untaught to in of the art of handling the pen or the tool.<lb/>  Compulsion may sound harsh in republican ears&#44; but<lb/> better to wound our susceptibilities than fill the land with reeking pollution defilement.<lb/>  I was prevented from attending the public meetings<lb/> held on Tuesday last&#44; but interested in the proceedings&#44;<lb/> I read them carefully&#44; and noticed that we Israelites re&#45;<lb/>&#45;ceived a meed of praise.  It is gratifying to be well&#45;<lb/>thought of&#44; still when we are all alone by ourselves&#44;<lb/> we may consult one another&#44; and examine whether<lb/> the virtues with which we have been credited have a<lb/> reality.  It was reported at some of the sessions<lb/> that we have taken initiatory steps to train our poor<lb/> to agricultural pursuits&#44; and that earnest experiments<lb/> had are being made to that effect test the practicability of the scheme.  Would it were<lb/> a fact would I could tell that the bundle and the little shop will be exchanged for the spade and the ploughshare.  Would I could now relate that the healthy wholesome&#44;<lb/> profitable and peaceful promoting vocation of our patriarchs&#44; has<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>found in those vast regions followers among<lb/> the needy of our communities.  What a blessing to over<lb/> crowded cities&#33;  What saving of means now wasted to feed paupers&#63;<lb/>  What an air of comfort would surround hundreds of families<lb/> now in a state of squalidity and destitution&#63;  But though three months have passed<lb/> since loud peals form standard Hall in New York<lb/> proclaimed that schools for farming would be opened<lb/> in the far west&#44; that acres of land by2 by the score had1<lb/> been donated&#44; that arrangements were pending in preparation progressing and would soon<lb/> would be completed&#44; nothing leading to the consummation<lb/> of that project has yet transpired.  The only school in which<lb/> Hebrews learn the ancient Jewish art of tilling the ground<lb/> is at Jaffa in Palestine&#44; and that to a limited extent<lb/> under the vigilance of that lynx eyed or rather argus&#45;eyed association&#44; the<lb/> Israelitish Universal Alliance.  The al eulogy bestowed<lb/> was not therefore deserved&#44; however I should might Delight to boast<lb/> it were that it was merited&#44; not for its the sake of vainglory&#44; but for<lb/> the il elevation of myriads of our coreligionists&#44; who con&#45;<lb/>&#45;gregate &#38; regulate in certain localities&#44; here and elsewhere particularly in a neighboring city&#44; and who<lb/> do require the influences of country life and its the simplicity<lb/> of habits it engenders&#44; to be redeemed from a a very<lb/> lowly condition.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>But another share of praise was given us last Tuesday<lb/> at one of its the sessions for organizing charitable relief.  Dr. Benjamin Lee of whose sa&#45;<lb/>&#45;gacious views on the sanitary laws of the Pentateuch I have<lb/> had occasion to speak on a former occasion before&#44; stated that<lb/> among us that the rules of health hygiene and the rules of morals<lb/> are intermingled.  He meant to say that convey this idea.  The manner<lb/> in which we prepare our food in accordance with olden<lb/> prescriptions&#44; that the frequent washing of our hands and of<lb/> our bodies&#44; that the avoidance of diverse pollutions described minutely in the books which we hold sacred&#44; all of that has kept us stri&#45;<lb/>&#45;kingly free from diseases to which other nations are liable&#44;<lb/> and he further argues that the enjoyment of physical strength hereditary health among us&#44; has affected<lb/> beneficially our whole character.  Well&#44; my brethren&#44;<lb/> what the Dr wisely asserted is true&#44; but it does not scarcely<lb/> applies to this age&#44; not certainly to this country.<lb/>  Neither as hygienic medical nor as religious commandments measures do<lb/> modern Israelites heed the Mosaic regulations directions.  Abstaining<lb/> from blood and from the flesh of unruminating specified ani&#45;<lb/>&#45;mals and of fishes devoid of fins and scales is a practice<lb/> which has ceased to be regarded declared unnecessary and<lb/> irksome restrictions.  Dr Lee and Dr Houghs and Dr Packard and other notedle phy&#45;<lb/>&#45;sicians may give us the result of the scientific researches&#44;<lb/> but our Solons&#44; the new generation knows better.  It is all bosh &#40;excuse<lb/> the vulgar term&#41;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Now with regard to the ablutions and the abundant<lb/> use of fresh water and soap by Israelites&#44; I say with sor&#45;<lb/>&#45;row and shame that many hundreds who are the most preten&#45; clamo<lb/>&#45;tious in claiming piety &#45;rous for the retention of all minutia detailed in the Shulchan Aruch&#44; are the least heedful of the re&#45;<lb/>&#45;gulations pertaining to cleanliness.  Aye&#58; they may wash in some fashion<lb/> let some water drop over their hands before eating a meal or even before pronouncing<lb/> a benediction&#44; they may be excessively scrupulous about<lb/> the substance with which to raise their children wash cleanse kitchen utensils&#44;<lb/> but they allow nevertheless the accumulation of filth<lb/> in their houses&#44; if not in their persons.  Those men are<lb/> not unsuitably described depicted in the books of our religious op&#45;<lb/>&#45;ponents&#44; as people &#34;who strain at a gnat and swallow<lb/> a camel.&#34;  For they forget They should remember the maxim of our Sages in<lb/> the Mishna &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Purity of thoughts&#44; &#38; purity<lb/> of actions are associated with the purity of the body.  Why&#44;<lb/> my brethren&#44; one and the same is the word which si&#45;<lb/>&#45;gnifies in Hebrew&#44; cleanness and innocence &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Learning is honorable&#44; but when associated with foul&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness is repulsive.  I say this advisedly&#44; because I wish it<lb/> to be clearly understood&#44; that by the laws of the Talmud<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>not less than by the ordinances of Moses he is<lb/> unfit for social intercourse&#44; however erudite&#44; who<lb/> neglects his outward appearance.  So expresses himself does the<lb/> great Maimonides express himself upon this subject.  &#34;Let him that<lb/> is called a scholar wear a neat and clean garments.<lb/>  Let him be careful that not even a stain is seen on his<lb/> raiment.&#34;  And as the eminent practitioner he that Rabbi was&#44;<lb/> he recommends the plunging of the whole body in pure<lb/> water at no longer intervals than a week.<lb/></p>
            <p>I would that they who claim orthodoxy as their standard&#44;<lb/> abided by all its rules&#44; and not merely by such as give them<lb/> the semblance of piety&#44; and I would that those who deride<lb/> orthodoxy knew more of the spirit pervading it&#44; and chose<lb/> it as a guide.  We would individually would be the gainers<lb/> in physical and moral health&#59; congregations would benefit through<lb/> a revival of worship now decaying because its ws sworn<lb/> votaries are busy in undermining their constitutions and their<lb/> minds by ceaseless unceasing work.  Society would profit<lb/> by the example of men and women remarkable in all<lb/> the relations of life&#44; and the literal carrying out of<lb/> the regulations which Dr Lee declares admirable&#44; would<lb/> glorify the God of Israel&#44; our Deliverer and Legislator.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
