<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF9_9</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1890-12" source="" attested="yes">December 1890</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_9_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_9_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_9_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_9_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_9_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_9_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_9_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_9_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_9_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_9_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_9_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_9_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. Fifth St.<lb/></p>
            <p>Philadelphia&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Dec&#47;90<lb/>
                On the Kaddish<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Brethren&#44;<lb/></p>
            <p>A paper war is being waged by three parties&#44; orthodox<lb/> reformed and radicals.  The cause of the contest is such<lb/> as to excite curiosity.  A western institution which has<lb/> assumed the title of &#34;Union College&#34;&#44; wishing to increase<lb/> its revenue&#44; or any large gift by members of a bereaved<lb/> Jewish family&#44; will ensure the dead a Kaddish at each<lb/> anniversary of their departure from earth.  A Hebrew<lb/> weekly at in New York&#44; hostile to the president of that<lb/> college&#44; condemns the plan as hypocritical&#44; as encou&#45;<lb/>&#45;raging the false belief that the Kaddish possesses the<lb/> power to blot out sin and compel the allotment of a<lb/> position in the world to come.  That N. Y. periodical<lb/> attacks severely&#44; but not unjustly&#44; a leader who has taught<lb/> by precept and example the abandonment of many a<lb/> Jewish law&#44; but who&#44; for interested motives&#44; ascribes the<lb/> highest importance to a matter of small light significance&#44;<lb/> when compared with Mosaic commandments and oral<lb/> precepts most venerable with age and holy.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>That paper calls upon the head of the Western in&#45;<lb/>&#45;stitution to raise Rabbis who will revere the Sabbath<lb/> and Festivals as prescribed by prophets and sages&#44; to respect the dietary laws&#44; propagate<lb/> the knowledge of the language of the Bible and of<lb/> our literature&#44; and keep the synagogue unadulterated&#44; and not lay so much stress on that which is evidently<lb/> a means to selfish ends.  This reasoning appeal&#44; which<lb/>I consider sound well founded&#44; and which I would decidedly ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;prove of were it free from caustic remarks&#44; is<lb/> opposed by Reform&#44; mainly represented by the disciples<lb/> of the Chief of the Union College.  Men who<lb/> have not scrupled to alter and to curtail and to totally<lb/> to abolish prayers that date as far back as the days<lb/> of Ezra and his illustrious synod&#44; are tenacious about<lb/> about the retention of the Kaddish&#44; not that which<lb/> the minister reads and which precedes or follows cer&#45;<lb/>&#45;tain parts of the ritual&#44; but that which cus&#45;<lb/>&#45;tom has assigned to mourners.  Preachers of<lb/> the new school&#45;&#45;and I will not deny then the virtue of sincerity&#45;&#45;&#44; argue in its favor&#44; on the ground of<lb/> filial dutifulness.  In their minds the child who<lb/> praises God at a Sanctuary in honor of his deceased parents&#44;<lb/> has a claim to the name of good Israelite.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>He may break many of the Sinaic precepts ordinances&#59; still<lb/> his keeping intact the fifth injunction of the Decalogue&#44; is<lb/> a soul redeeming quality.  I myself might concede<lb/> a vast deal on that score&#44; if the rehearsal of the<lb/> Kaddish were in all reality indicative of a filial love and<lb/> veneration&#44; which the grave has not buried away&#44; but which<lb/> survives the dear objects entombed.  For the associate<lb/> the memory of those who gave us existence on earth&#44;<lb/> with the Dweller in heaven&#44; from whom whatever<lb/> ennobles our nature emanates&#44; is a glorious thought&#44;<lb/> but I am not prepared to so interpret the reciting of the Kaddish by reformers otherwise non confor<lb/>mists.<lb/></p>
            <p>Radicalism&#44; widely at variance with Orthodoxy<lb/> and Reform&#44; is uncompromising.  It frowns upon a<lb/> usage which it declares anti&#45;Judaic&#44; asserting that<lb/> it was borrowed from Spanish Catholicism&#59; that it sa&#45;<lb/>&#45;vors therefore of the mass which pretends to deliver<lb/> transgressors from purgatory&#59; that it is a rank<lb/> superstition&#44; calculated to deform the worship.  Radic&#45;<lb/>&#45;als insist upon the performance of good works&#44; as<lb/> tokens of imperishable affection to the dead.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Thus&#44; the endowing of free beds at hospitals&#59; for sick in reduced circumstances&#44; of<lb/> scholarships at universities for orphans&#44; the liberal con&#45;<lb/>&#45;tributing to widows homes&#44; is deemed the only sole efficacious method<lb/> to prove one&#39;s lovely deep rooted lovely remembrance of those who<lb/> were called hence to the world of spirits.  The<lb/> Kaddish&#44; say our Radicals&#44; is a cheap payment<lb/> for the pains and cares and deep concerns of a fa&#45;<lb/>&#45;ther or mother.  The will have none of it.  The<lb/> Divine service which they offered in their temples&#44; must<lb/> not be shamed by such a travesty of religion.  I dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;agree with the ideas held by the adherents of a school<lb/> iconoclastic&#59; a school matchlessly successful in<lb/> tearing down&#44; but leaving the open spots bare&#44; with&#45;<lb/>&#45;out supplying a finer or more solid stone to replace<lb/> what was wantonly pulled down.<lb/></p>
            <p>But since we are engaged on the subject&#44; let us un&#45;<lb/>derstand it clearly.  All are perfectly aware of the<lb/> fact taht the Kaddish has not a Biblical origin&#44;<lb/> nor a Talmudical either&#44; in connection with as far as it concerns regards the mourn&#45;<lb/>&#45;ers.  The Sages of our people in their figurative lan&#45;<lb/>&#45;guage write that when Israelites enter Synagogues and<lb/> colleges&#44; and cry out &#34;May the great name of God be blessed&#44;&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>the Almighty approvingly responds &#34;Happy the<lb/> King who is so extolled in His own house&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;  No special reference<lb/> is here made to the bereaved&#44; but Israelites in gene&#45;<lb/>&#45;ral are mentioned.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Again&#58; From some Talmudical passages&#44; we might be justi&#45;<lb/>&#45;fied in inferring that the Kaddish was first composed<lb/> in Hebrew&#44; and that it was translated into Aramaic&#44;<lb/> to enable persons who came to listen to attended the lecture&#45;&#45;<lb/>which invariably concluded with the Kaddish&#45;&#45;to join<lb/> in it in their own vernacular.  Whether it is so&#44; or<lb/> not&#44; the formula handed down is chiefly Aramaic&#44;<lb/> to which in later ages&#44; the Sephardim made arbitrary<lb/> additions towards the end&#44; in Hebrew.  The attempt<lb/> to reproduce it altogether in Hebrew&#44; was incorrectly made<lb/>&#45;&#45;but not correctly&#45;&#45;fity fifty years ago in London by the compiler of the<lb/> liturgy&#44; used in the Synagogue of self&#45;styled &#34;British<lb/> Jews&#34;.  America&#44; which is the land of surprises&#44;<lb/> has found some who proposed to have a version<lb/> in English.  In point of fact&#44; since the abolition of<lb/> the ritual in the language transmitted by the fathers<lb/> is strongly urgently advocated&#44; and each Minister&#44; or Rabbi&#44; assumes<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>the authority to exchange Davidic hymns odes psalms for church<lb/> hymns or doggerel songs&#45;&#45;foreign altogether to the synagogue<lb/> the Kaddish&#44; if retained&#44; might as well be read rendered in<lb/> the tongue best understood.  It is scarcely<lb/> needful that I should express my own views.  By<lb/> nature and education I am conservative.  I hold the<lb/> our history enshrined on my heart of hearts.  What<lb/> gave our ancestors comfort&#44; I strongly incline to preserve intact<lb/> as a bridge connecting the eventful past with the<lb/> present.  But I object to a perfunctory dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;charge of sacred duties&#44; just as I shrink from the<lb/> thought of making a religious practice the me&#45;<lb/>&#45;dium for disingenuously improving the finances of<lb/> congregations&#44; or schools.  The Kaddish&#44;<lb/> which&#44; till the present century&#44; when a change was<lb/> largely adopted in Germany and America&#44; had not<lb/> the least reference whatever to the dead&#44; is a sublime confes&#45;<lb/>&#45;sion of our recognition of God&#39;s creative powers and<lb/> sovereignty.  As an invocation to the Deity&#44;<lb/> and a petition for the blessing of peace&#44; it is very<lb/> comprehensive.  Appropriately therefore do Israelites&#44;<lb/> who have been deprived of loved objects&#44; recite it.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Let the origin of that usage be Rabbinical&#44; or Kab&#45;<lb/>&#45;balistical as some contend&#44; it becomes behooves the sorrow strick&#45;<lb/>&#45;en to publicly tacitly to acknowledge that a celestial Parent<lb/> who brought all into existence and preserves all&#44;<lb/> can give them afflicted solace and consolation.  No<lb/> Catholic mass indeed for the spiritual relief of the<lb/> departed is the Kaddish.  Nay&#44; even the Kashcabah<lb/> or Mazkin Hazkareth Neshamoth&#44; is simply a prayer to the<lb/> Almighty for the happiness of our dear ones&#44; in an ethe&#45;<lb/>&#45;real association of companionship with the pure and pious.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  Still&#44; how<lb/> often have I not been grieved to the core by the<lb/> irreverence of the living&#44; who fancied to do the dead<lb/> reverence.  What a sad spectacle&#33;&#44; That of men re&#45;<lb/>&#45;hearsing hurriedly&#44; unintelligently and unintelligible&#44;<lb/> the Kaddish&#44; and then rush immediately off to the desecration of<lb/> the Sabbath&#45;day.  What an egregious error&#33;&#44; That of<lb/> children who imagine they can afford their deceased<lb/> parents pleasure by a repetition of certain words&#44; and but<lb/> who dishonor their memory by a conduct unbecoming the<lb/> spot&#44; where the Shekinah dwells.  In truth&#44; were<lb/> it not that my complaints might sound like egotism<lb/> or undue self&#45;appreciation&#44; I would speak at length<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>of the lateness of comers&#44; of their unnecessary converse&#44;<lb/> of their undisguised eagerness to leave the Synagogue&#44;<lb/> of their evident restlessness at being momentarily de&#45;<lb/>&#45;tained by the lecturer&#44; and principally would I point<lb/> out the inconsistency of Israelites&#44; who attend worship<lb/> during eleven months after having met with an irre&#45;<lb/>&#45;parable loss&#44; but who at the expiration of that period<lb/> keep entirely determinedly aloof&#44; save perhaps at very distant intervals.<lb/>  But I forbear&#44; because it is as distasteful to me<lb/> to upbraid&#44; as it must be disagreeable to my<lb/> hearers to listen to reproaches.  Instead of remonstran&#45;<lb/>&#45;ces&#44; let friendly entreaties&#44; induce a demeanour more<lb/> in accord with our obligations as conservative Jews&#44; more<lb/> in consonance with the sanctity of this oracle of our<lb/> Lord&#44; visiting it early&#44; and remaining therein therein devotion&#45;<lb/>&#45;ally.  And to my brethren who observe the year<lb/> of mourning&#44; I am enjoined to say&#44; in the name of<lb/> our ancient teachers &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; a child can enhance<lb/> his parents&#39; joys above.  Together with invocations and praises<lb/> to God&#44; actions must prove that the memorial of the de&#45;<lb/>partes &#45;ceased lives in our hearts.  Charity to the needy&#44; sympathy<lb/> with the sufferers&#44; and forgiveness towards offenders&#44; while<lb/> ennobling our lives&#44; are a sweet savor to the soul of the departed.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
