<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF3_5</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1889-03" source="" attested="yes">March 1890</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_5_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_5_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_5_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_5_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_5_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_5_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_5_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_5_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_5_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_5_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_5_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_5_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. Fifth St.<lb/></p>
            <p>Philadelphia&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>On the 39th anniversary<lb/>
                of my ministry<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>March 1890<lb/></p>
            <p>Brethren.  I have been a member of the Young Men&#39;s He&#45;<lb/>&#45;brew Association from its very beginning.  I might even<lb/> claim the title of pioneer of that organization.  Long<lb/> before a spacious building with reading&#44; lecturing and<lb/> meeting rooms had been hired for the <sic>accomodation</sic> of<lb/> its five or six hundred contributors&#44; a few Philadelphia<lb/> young men of our persuasion&#44; anxious to learn their people&#39;s<lb/> history and practice debating&#44; came together every Sunday<lb/> evening&#44; in a small room of a Jewish Boarding House<lb/> at 5th &#38; Race sts&#44; and subsequently in other humble<lb/> localities in the upper part of our city.  I led them.<lb/>  Nathan Wisenstein&#44; who died early in life&#44; twelve<lb/> years ago&#44; might awarded the merit due to his memory.<lb/>  He tried hard to keep up the interest of his coevals<lb/> in literary exercises&#44; but it gradually waned away<lb/> despite his strenuous efforts&#44; and his failure in that<lb/> direction was the rising of the same organization&#44; under<lb/> different auspices&#44; and on a much wider plan.<lb/></p>
            <p>When that took place&#44; I still continued to lend my material<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>and moral cooperation.  I paid the annual subscript&#45;<lb/>&#45;ion&#44; and lectured with frequency&#44; till warm<lb/> enthusiasm cooled off into chilling apathy&#44; and<lb/> neither myself nor others who assumed to instruct&#44;<lb/> could secure an audience&#44; any longer.  At the<lb/> monthly entertainment of the Y M. H A&#44;<lb/> I addressed the vast assemblage only once&#44;<lb/> when they were held at Concordia Hall on Callow&#45;<lb/>&#45;hill st near 4th&#44; as I have always prefer&#45;<lb/>&#45;red by disposition&#44; to teach at the desk rather<lb/> than deliver orations at the rostrum.  Besides&#44;<lb/> those entertainments at which melodious mu&#45;<lb/>&#45;sic is often discoursed&#44; are interspersed with<lb/> amusements&#44; which do not&#44; as a rule&#44; accord with<lb/> my taste&#44; so that I very seldom attend them.<lb/>  But on one occasion&#44; I listened to the President<lb/> of the organization at the opening of the season<lb/> in the Mercantile Hall.  He spoke with his<lb/> acknowledged ability of education&#44; and dwelt on the<lb/> advantages which our young men&#39;s Hebrew<lb/> association offers.  He explained that&#44; without<lb/> pretending to make its members adept in<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p><sic>in</sic> Jewish learning&#44; or to qualify them to discuss<lb/> the merits of each phase which Judaism nowadays<lb/> presents&#44; it has brought the rising generation of our<lb/> people closer together in cultured intercourse&#44; and<lb/> mutual toleration.  To support his assertion&#44; touch&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing the popularity of the institution&#44; the President<lb/> pointed to the throng that faced him&#44; and contrasted<lb/> it with the sight which Philadelphia Synagogues<lb/> present&#44; even on the highest scriptural holidays.<lb/>  He said&#58; This crowded audience is the strongest proof<lb/> of the usefulness of our organization.  But had<lb/> I been allowed to interpose a remark&#44; I would&#44;<lb/> after begging the speaker&#39;s pardon&#44; have given him<lb/> an honest assurance that not even the rhetoric of<lb/> the most finished orator could repeatedly draw<lb/> the immense concourse of Israelites who had come<lb/> to hear him.  I would have demonstrated that the<lb/> monthly entertainments bring our young men and<lb/> women largely together&#44; principally because attractions<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>of a varied character&#45;&#45;disconnected with the literary&#45;&#45;<lb/>are offered to them.  In fact&#44; the listless&#44; sometime<lb/> noisy&#44; reception which the lecture meets with at<lb/> the hands of many&#44; shows the unripeness of the<lb/> generality of our youths for thoughtful diversions.<lb/>  If the synagogue could hold out the same<lb/> inducements as the Y. M. H. A.&#44; or&#44; at least&#44;<lb/> if it could consistently invite Jews upon a<lb/> leisure day to hear the songstress trill her lay&#44;<lb/> the preacher might hope for the satisfaction<lb/> of seeing the place in which he ministers<lb/> full every returning week.  That satisfact&#45;<lb/>&#45;ion has been withheld from me&#44; perhaps through<lb/> the absence of attractions&#44; perhaps for other causes&#44;<lb/> for which I am responsible&#44; but it has been denied<lb/> to me always during my long incumbency&#44; and never<lb/> more strikingly than of late.  I have deplored<lb/> the fast diminishing of my fellow&#45;worshippers&#59; first&#44;<lb/> because it manifests an open contempt for the<lb/> holy convocations which the inspired lawgiver<lb/> ordered&#44; as reminders of our dependence on the<lb/> Creator&#44; and of the bond of Union in Israel&#59;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>secondly&#44; because&#44; inadequate as my teaching<lb/> may be&#44; it is here that it can influence for<lb/> good some of my brothers and sisters in faith.<lb/>  The sacredness of the surroundings&#44; urging me to<lb/> lend emphasis and force to my words&#44; affects blissfully<lb/> also those within hearing of my voice.  But<lb/> how very few are now the latter&#33;  To me the<lb/> vacant seats bear a look of reproach.  They<lb/> stare at me angrily.  This Sabbath more<lb/> irefully than usual&#44; for on it thirty nine years ago with<lb/> trepidation but with confiding trust in the Lord&#44; while<lb/> as ascending this same Tebah&#44; I looked prayfully<lb/> forward to a successful ministration.  I could<lb/> not anticipate to rival my predecessor&#44; whose<lb/> restless activity in the field of Judaism and Jewish<lb/> letters forms at present the theme of post humous<lb/> laudations&#44; even from such as&#44; during his life<lb/> time held him in light estimation.  He possessed<lb/> versatility of mind&#44; I brought to the task barely<lb/> medicority.  He exercised the invaluable quality of<lb/> self&#45;reliance&#44; I constantly feared to fall short of<lb/> my charges.  Yet&#44; I imagined that a mighty<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>wish to serve the cause I had taken up&#44; des&#45;<lb/>&#45;pite the impediments lying in the way&#44; would<lb/> make me of use to my coreligionists.  If I<lb/> did not lay the press heavily under tribute&#44; I<lb/> could command&#44; under all circumstances&#44; a<lb/> heart overflowing with sympathy.  If I did not<lb/> enchain attention by conversional powers&#44; I tried<lb/> to bind to me the affection of young children.<lb/>  To have that&#44; is veritable joy to me&#44; but that<lb/> does it mellow down into kindly consideration&#44;<lb/> when manhood and womanhood are attained&#63;<lb/>  The increasing desertion of the Synagogue returns a<lb/> painful answer.  Sunday services are<lb/> the direct outgrowth of the evil which I lament.<lb/>  I hear persons who contribute to the maintenance<lb/> of this Synagogue&#44; denounce in unmeasured turns the<lb/> Christianizing of the Sabbath&#44; nevertheless they are<lb/> those who unthinkingly encourage it&#44; and leave<lb/> me to grieve at the inconsistency of persons<lb/> whom I cannot improve.  Why&#44; the<lb/> appellation of &#34;Orthodox&#34; applied to thus &#91;&#63;&#93;<lb/> &#91;&#63;&#93; &#34;Hope of Israel&#34;&#44; sounds like a satire&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>in view of the incontrovertible fact that people<lb/> might reckon with their fingers my congregants&#44;<lb/> who adhere even to clearly defined Mosaic precepts.<lb/>  But wide&#45;spread as negligence on that score may<lb/> have been for many years&#44; still my memory&#44; going<lb/> back to a period of residence in Philadelphia ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;proaching that during which the son of Amram<lb/> governed the tribes&#44; cannot recalls so flagrant&#44;<lb/> so general a disregard of the Sabbath&#44; as witnessed<lb/> by the slenderest attendance&#45;&#45;comparatively<lb/> speaking&#45;&#45;at the services in our Synagogue.<lb/>  Formerly&#44; spring&#44; winter and autumn saw here<lb/> a goodly gathering&#45;&#45;in the galleries most<lb/> especially&#45;&#45;now&#44; even the day of atonement fails<lb/> to present a crowded assemblage.  Rosh Hashanah is<lb/> the sole occasion on which every seat in this sanctuary<lb/> is occupied.  That one conventional day in the year suf&#45;<lb/>&#45;fices my conservative constituents for a communion<lb/> with their Lord.  And then the prevalent contempt<lb/> for the Hebrew language relegated to oblivion&#45;&#45;<lb/>a contempt which is the sure prelude of a tragedy&#45;<lb/>the death of the Jewish worship.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Brethren.  I know that in ordinary cases&#44; the<lb/> anniversary of one&#39;s induction into the ministry&#44;<lb/> affords occasion for self&#45;gratulation.  At all<lb/> events&#44; on the part of the celebrant&#44; who tells of<lb/> the large accession of number to his flock&#59; of the progress<lb/> of his hearers in the observances of the faith in which<lb/> they were born.  But it would be unmitigated hy&#45;<lb/>&#45;pocrisy in me to boast of my achievements.  My<lb/> thanks are due to God&#44; because He has vouchsafed<lb/> to spare some who still love this sanctuary&#44; and<lb/> by their presence&#44; by their means&#44; by their in&#45;<lb/>&#45;fluence promote its perpetuity&#44; and direct from<lb/> hence a kindly thought to Israelites in need of<lb/> active consideration&#44; fraternal benefaction and<lb/> far reaching philanthropy.  May their example<lb/>&#45;&#45;long exhibited upon earth&#45;&#45;become a ministration<lb/> of goodness&#44; and through it&#44; may this venerable<lb/> religious body grow in spiritual strength&#44; and<lb/> deserve&#44; in all truth&#44; the name it was originally<lb/> given&#45;&#45;Mickv&#232; Israel &#34;the hope of Israel&#44;&#34; now<lb/> and always.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            <p>&#40;Here follows an address to a Bar Mitzvah&#41;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
