<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF13_4</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_4_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_4_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_4_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_4_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_4_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_4_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_4_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_4_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_4_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_4_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_4_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_4_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>4th lecture on immortality<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  One evening during last winter&#44; a clergyman of the<lb/> Christian church called upon me and propounded put some<lb/> questions&#44; to which I could not give any definite answer.<lb/>  HE wished to know what is the accepted doctrine among<lb/> Jews respecting the immortality state of the soul in the world to come.  I said<lb/> that the belief in a world to come immortality is universal with<lb/> us&#59; that to me the very word &#34;Hayim&#34; used to express<lb/> life&#44; being always in the plural&#44; is an indication&#44; if<lb/> not a proof&#44; of the prevailing idea among Hebrews<lb/> of another existence besides the bodily one&#44; but that<lb/> with regard to the nature of that existence we have no<lb/> ruling dogma.  I showed that Moses has kept si&#45;<lb/>&#45;lent on it&#44; that the language of the prophets speaking of reward and when<lb/> punishment evidently allusive to a hereafter&#44; but in lan&#45;<lb/>&#45;guage which cannot be taken to the letter&#44; so figurative<lb/> it undisputably manifestly is&#44; and that the Biblical &#34;Sheol&#34; tran&#45;<lb/>slated nether world&#44; or hell is may be made synonymous with grave<lb/> or as any place where decay and dissolution gradually<lb/> befall our flesh and bones undergo dissolution.  My visitor who adhered<lb/> to the catechism of his denomination about eternal everlasting suf&#45;<lb/>&#45;fering and irremediable utter perdition attending the commission<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>of sin&#44; urged me to tell what the Talmud teaches contains<lb/> respecting in reference to a future state.  I acknowledged that the<lb/> books of our traditions abound with particulars in<lb/> relation to pleasures and pains experienced by the<lb/> departed&#44; but&#44; I added&#44; that Jewish thinkers and phi&#45;<lb/>&#45;losophers have tried to reconcile with reason what much<lb/> &#45;ever that sounds extravagant and incongruous inconsistent in the<lb/> sayings of the Rabbis.  In fact&#44; Gan Eden<lb/> and Gehinnam which figure so conspicuously<lb/> in the writings of our Sages&#44; bear no analogy to the<lb/> &#34;heaven&#34; and &#34;hell&#34; of the Christian church.  As I<lb/> explained many years ago in one of my lectures&#44; those<lb/> scriptural words are obviously a substitute which<lb/> human ignorance of a spiritual state had to invent.<lb/>  In order to offer an very faint idea however faint of the joys of im&#45;<lb/>&#45;mortality&#44; Talmudists chose for a type thereof a dwelling in the spot<lb/> described in Genesis&#44;&#45;&#45;a garden planted by God with<lb/> delicious fruits as the abode of the first pair<lb/> whom His hand had made.  Again&#58; To signify<lb/> the suffering of being denied association with<lb/> the righteous in the land of spirits imagination lighted upon the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>the comparison of being cast in the valley of Hinnom&#44; where children were burnt alive<lb/> to the hideous Molock.  But no rational mind<lb/> can ever harbor the thought that&#44; according to our<lb/> preceptors&#44; the spirit soul will be agreeably affected by the<lb/> smell or taste of earthly productions&#44; or consumed by<lb/> a <sic>subterrenean</sic> fire.  I would in any event&#44; reject<lb/> that thought as antagonistic to clashing with my understanding on<lb/> one side&#44; and as revolting to my feelings on the other.<lb/>  For I am comforted by the belief in the ethereal na&#45;<lb/>&#45;nture of my soul&#44; and in the loving kindness of God<lb/> Almighty&#44; who will not divest it thereof and con&#45;<lb/>sign it to torments or extinction.  Respectful<lb/> as I am and will always remain to the opinion of the<lb/> ancient teachers of my people&#44; I could not get per&#45;<lb/>&#45;suaded by their combined wisdom to accept notions&#44;<lb/> if such were their real import&#44; notions which represent<lb/> to my intellect a Creator&#44; a Father&#44; delivering His<lb/> to my intellect a children to endless anguish or annihilation.  I Let<lb/> other religious systems frighten if they deem it best frighten their followers into<lb/> doing good by the picture of a lake of fire&#44; or be retained<lb/> in probity by the promise of a seat next to at the right hand of the Great Master&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>I as a Hebrew minister prefer inculcating the principle of that Antigonus<lb/> of Soco who taught his scholars to serve our Lord<lb/> disinterestedly for the sake of virtue&#44; which is sure to<lb/> bring along its own reward&#44; and leave all the rest in to<lb/> that celestial hand ruler that dispensesg even justice.<lb/></p>
            <p>This&#44; my brethren&#44; was the gist of my conversation reply to<lb/> with the anxious enquirer.  But the clergyman still<lb/> pressed me with questions about the fate of the wicked&#44;<lb/> according to Jewish authorities&#44; about that of sinless<lb/> infants&#44; about the destination of the semi righteous<lb/> and of the perfect righteous.  I kept answering&#58;<lb/> I don&#39;t know&#44; for opinions naturally vary where<lb/> the object of our researches lies far beyond our mental<lb/> reach.  But as the God I worship has given me<lb/> a soul full of love and compassion for all beings I find within my&#45;<lb/>&#45;self a reflection&#44; dim indeed though it be&#44; comparable<lb/> to a small taper before a refulgent sun&#44; or to basin rather to a pin drop<lb/> of water before an ocean&#44; a reflection&#44; I say&#44; of those<lb/> attributes which will not suffer a single being creature to be<lb/> lost.<lb/></p>
            <p>Sometime after that winter evening interview conversation&#44; I remembered<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>that the Churches had been greatly agitated because of<lb/> clashing ideas conflicting pulpit teaching instruction among leaders concerning the character of<lb/> reward and punishment in a life to come.  A few<lb/> of the most prominent preachers in England and Ame&#45;<lb/>&#45;rica repudiated passages in the new Testament con&#45; interpreted heretofore<lb/> &#45;signing to as a the doom of damnation against men of little faith&#44; doubters of<lb/> dogmas or or to make them those sentences agree with Divine Mercy they put upon those sentences them a more<lb/> liberal construction than the literal. to make them<lb/> agree with Divine mercy.  Those Christian clergymen advanced<lb/> then an idea which may have sounded startling to the Christ&#45; startled some of their denominations be reason<lb/> &#45;ian world&#44; of its novelty&#44; but which is as old as Moses to the Jew<lb/> who has read his scriptures.  The idea is this.  The<lb/> teachings of inspiration are perfectly clear and com&#45;<lb/>&#45;prehensible on moral duties.  No allegory covers up<lb/> their meaning as with a veil.  Naked truths they are<lb/> which the mind needs not fatigue itself to unfold.<lb/>  A simple look suffices to show whether stealing<lb/> offends God&#44; lying is an abomination in His sight&#44;<lb/> cruelty licentiousness&#44; drunkenness and profanity stand in op&#45;<lb/>&#45;position to the Divine will.  He that runs may read<lb/> the lessons of honest&#44; of truthfulness&#44; of moderation<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>in our desires&#44; the exhortations to watch over and restrain<lb/> our mouths and lips&#44; to wash our hands in innocence&#44;<lb/> to pity and ot help and to forgive and to side with<lb/> the oppressed and never with the oppressors.  A per&#45;<lb/>&#45;son may deliberately break all the laws&#44; but not<lb/> on the plea that he misunderstood the lesson.<lb/>  It is when referring to things invisible and unfathom&#45;<lb/>&#45;able that the volumes of revelation mostly team with<lb/> similes and metaphors.  The God&#39;s displeasure of God is the<lb/> rushing tearing of as whirlwind&#59; His pleasures a refreshing breeze.<lb/>  The unhappiness of the wicked is being struck dumb a&#45;<lb/>&#45;midst enshrouding darkness&#59; the happiness of the right&#45;<lb/>&#45;eous walking at large with morning star shining over head<lb/> breaking forth into a perfect day light.  Let literalists<lb/> construe it allegories as they will.  I consider him very audacious<lb/> who dares set up upon figures of speech a dogma about<lb/> engines of torture for sinners&#44; and high thrones for the<lb/> spotless.<lb/></p>
            <p>Do I mean to deny the creed of a condign Divine celestial retribution&#63;<lb/>  Far be it from me.  I subscribe fully &#38; &#91;&#63;&#93; unreservedly to it.  Surely&#44;<lb/> the Lord gives the upright the fruits of their actions sowing&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>and makes wrong doers reap the thorns they have<lb/> sowed planted.  And that in this life not less than<lb/> in that thy life to come.  For my conception of God&#39;s justice<lb/> is broader than that of the generality of men.  I reject<lb/> the theory that watchful Providence allows us to go un&#45;<lb/>&#45;requited here&#44; and reserves altogether for a future state<lb/> pleasures and pains.  It is inconsistent with His attri&#45;<lb/>&#45;butes&#44; repugnant to reason.  We short&#45;sighted creatures are seldom able to dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;cover how He does commensurately pay&#44; because our judg&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment is exceedingly fallible&#59; because we are apt erro&#45;<lb/>&#45;neously to call evil what is good&#44; and good what is evil&#44;<lb/> and because we make our own standard&#44; we have our own<lb/> measures and weights&#44; but God employs different balances<lb/> and meteyards from ours.  This is not&#44; however&#44; the pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;sent subject of my reflections.  Not to justify my<lb/> Maker have I spoken thus far&#44; but to tell what my meditations ponderings<lb/> have suggested about immortality.<lb/></p>
            <p>That there must be a spirit life I have endeavoured<lb/> to prove&#44; that the notion of everlasting vengeance<lb/> or a complete extinction awaiting the unfortunate<lb/> sinner is incompatible with the quality of mercy&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>I have essayed to show&#59; that we have nothing<lb/> to fear from our living Father I have sought to<lb/> instill into the hearts of my fellow mortals.  I might<lb/> now close my the series&#44; confessing my inability to<lb/> throw any brighter clearer light than what that which I my ponderings<lb/> have gathered in the course of my meditations.  But I have named our Rabbis and<lb/> philosophers in connection with this serious topic.  It<lb/> is due to them&#44; and it may be satisfactory for you&#44;<lb/> that I shall present some of their views which the house of Israelites<lb/> have everywhere adopted&#44; and others to which my mind has<lb/> satisfactorily assented.  I shall make that the theme of my next dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;course.  Meanwhile I commend to your study a Psalm&#44;<lb/> whose every sentence breathes hope in the tender mercies<lb/> of God&#44; trust in the power of virtue&#44;&#45;&#45;the richest inherit&#45;<lb/>&#45;ance we may leave our children&#45;&#45;; a psalm that<lb/> relieves the soul from the nightmare of terrors to come&#44;<lb/> and opens the vista of to view a joy&#45;inspiring revelation vision point&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing to a yearning Goodness that hovers above us here&#44; and<lb/> will encircle us everywhere beyond the tomb&#44; inviting us to be saved through<lb/> obedience to the Law&#44; and submissively to accept the<lb/> penalty of a desertion from the Law as at the hands<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>of a kind Parent&#44; to turn again and again to that<lb/> Law&#44; to face its radiance splendour&#44; leaving behind the long<lb/> shadow of doubts&#44; misgivings&#44; or spiritual anguish.  Brethren.  Study<lb/> the 103d psalm 103.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
