<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF7_7</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1887" source="" attested="yes">1887</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff7_7_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff7_7_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff7_7_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff7_7_2v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 1 sheet<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For a funeral<lb/></p>
            <p>Brethren.  As I watched the life&#45;ebbing of the Jewess&#44; now enshrouded<lb/> in this casket&#44; I imagined that a superhuman voice addressed<lb/> me&#44; and asked that I should ponder on the contents of one of David&#39;s<lb/> sublime psalms&#44; and observe for I would discover partly discover in what lay before me&#44; a reflection of the poets inspired<lb/> outpourings.  The author of that splendid composition in sentiments of the deepest devotion&#44; ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;horts his undying to tell spirit to recount the benefactions of the Creator &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;O my soul&#44; bless the Lord&#44; and forget not<lb/> all His mercies.&#34;  He urges his whole being to acknowledge that at the<lb/> hands of the Most High it received temporal healing support in the hour days<lb/> of trails&#44; unending favors outliving the perishable body.<lb/>  God&#39;s loving kindness which never fails&#44; but which is daily<lb/> hourly manifested to those who have a mind to think and a<lb/> heart to feel&#44; the great bare of old compares to a diadem encircling<lb/> his brow&#44; and beautifying all his person &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Seek&#44; my brother&#45;Israelites for that elevating lesson you will find it in psalm<lb/> 103&#44; which I call a prelude to the song of nature as sung in<lb/> the following psalm ode never surpassed in grandeur and truthful&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness&#44; inviting all to witness the glory of the Lord which that en&#45;<lb/>dureth everlastingly&#44; and see saying telling how the lord rejoiceth in his handi&#45;<lb/>work &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  It was in the effusions<lb/> of the Shepherd&#45;King&#44; that I measurably beheld a representation of the history<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>of Mrs Betti Gans&#44; as if reflected in a mirror.<lb/></p>
            <p>Mounting up gradually and always progressively from<lb/> humbleness to affluence&#59; occasionally diseased&#44; but as frequent&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly raised by Providence from the couch of sickness&#44; sur&#45;<lb/>&#45;rounded with home comforts as with a crown this Jewess she led domes&#45;<lb/>&#45;tically half a century&#39;s of connubial life in the companionship<lb/> of the Israelite&#44; who had wedded her in the early days of his<lb/> lowliness.  Can fancy rehearse the pleasures enjoyed during<lb/> a period so unusually divisively lengthened&#63;  That it was not free<lb/> from disappointments and pains&#44; all will readily conceive&#44; but<lb/> our occasional sufferings are also the issue of Divine celestial wis&#45;<lb/>&#45;dom&#44; to chasten our minds and thoughts and heighten the delights derived from value of innumerable<lb/> blessings experienced.  But to Mrs Betty Gans was<lb/> granted moreover what many have been denied.  She was never<lb/> bereaved of those creatures to whom she had given birth.  They grew<lb/> under her immediate vision and care&#44; and they temporally pros&#45;<lb/>&#45;pered.  The are here to honor the memory of their aged<lb/> mother&#44; and with her own sons and daughters are we see their off&#45;<lb/>&#45;spring paying homage to her spirit and clustering round<lb/> their venerable sire&#44; full of years and of God&#39;s mani&#45;<lb/>&#45;fold blessings benefactions.  For those are obviously demonstrated in his<lb/> retention of all faculties and the full capacity of fruition.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>The departure of that mother from earth is now lamented&#44;<lb/> and it were unnatural that it should not call forth sobs and<lb/> sighs.  It were an offence to morality and an insult to God&#44;<lb/> the Sinaic proclaimer of the Decalogue&#44; not3 to grieve over<lb/> this terrestrial separation.  Verily&#44; I can judge how keenly<lb/> is the demise of our sister in faith felt by her hoary headed<lb/> copartner of fifty years1 conjugal relations.  He notably com&#45;<lb/>&#45;mands our profound sympathies and our respectful com&#45;<lb/>&#45;miseration.  But commending the tokens of marital<lb/> and filial sadness as a tribute to nature and domestic tenderness devotion&#44; I would deem it unreasonable to<lb/> indulge in loud lamentations wailings and murmurings&#44; or even in silent re&#45;<lb/>&#45;grets.  Time&#44; which allays afflictions&#44; reflection that by which we over&#45;<lb/>&#45;comes the effects of losses sustained&#44; and religion whose un&#45;<lb/>&#45;failing promises act as a balm&#44; will unitedly&#44; and speedily<lb/> I trust&#44; restore calm and serenity.  A tear will occasionally drop<lb/> over the grave of Betti Gans&#44; flowing springing from the eyes that were wont to sparkle<lb/> with pleasure at meeting hers&#59; but the tears which I long<lb/> to see copiously flow are those of pure joy at the restor&#45;<lb/>&#45;ation of a perfect and joyous unutterable health of some who the diseased enthroned<lb/> in the sweetest affections of these present dear mourners&#59; delightsome<lb/> tears&#44; at which angels rejoice&#44; for they daily respond to the peti&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion which the faithful offer in their morning and evening prayers.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>May He who bids Peace rule in the highest<lb/> heavens&#44; allow that queen of joys to abide with us<lb/> and the whole household of Israel.  That is my<lb/> heartfelt petition ardent supplication.  And now let us pray offer make petition entreaties for the sake<lb/> of our deceased sister in faith.  At this hour in which<lb/> she stands before the august presence of her maker&#44; may<lb/> her shortcomings&#44; while walking this nether path&#45;&#45;for&#44;<lb/> indeed to sin is human&#45;&#45;&#44; be forgiven because of her merits<lb/> in the relations of wife&#44; mother and a coheiress of the Law<lb/> of God we have inherited.  May her spirit be assigned a lofty seat in<lb/> the realms of <sic>tranquillity</sic>&#44; escorted thither by her<lb/> virtues&#44; assuming the form of Celestial Supernal Intelligences.<lb/>  Eternal Sovereign Lord&#33;  Vouchsafe to Thy handmaid&#44; the fulfilment<lb/> of the declaration made by David in the psalm which I mentally re&#45;<lb/>&#45;hearsed when she had very nigh reached the borders of eternity.<lb/>  &#34;The Lord is merciful and compassionate&#44; slow to anger and plen&#45;<lb/>&#45;teous in loving&#45;kindness.&#34;  Grant that from the lofty glorious habitation in<lb/> which her soul is sphered&#44; she may behold here gladness&#44;<lb/> success&#44; harmony and the tenderest love&#44; and feel that her<lb/> bliss is heightened enhanced by that sublime vision.  So may<lb/> it be.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
