<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF2_5</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1864" source="" attested="yes">1864</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_5_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_5_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_5_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_5_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_5_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_5_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_5_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_5_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_5_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_5_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_5_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_5_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_5_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_5_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_5_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_5_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>14 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>On Shabungot for<lb/>
                The 4th anniversary of the Synagogue<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;This is the day appointed by the Lord&#44; let<lb/> us rejoice and be glad thereon&#34;<lb/>  Brethren&#33;  The devotional joy&#44; wherewith the dawning of<lb/> this auspicious day&#44; ought to fill the heart of every son<lb/> of Israel&#44; must be experienced with still more intensity by us&#44;<lb/> the members&#44; constituting the Congregation &#34;Mikv&#233; Israel.&#34;<lb/>  This comely dwelling wherein we have convened to cele&#45;<lb/>&#45;brate the birth&#45;day of a heavenly religion&#44; has just completed<lb/> the fourth year of its existence.  And as we ponder on its short<lb/> but checkered history&#44; we must needs discover motives for<lb/> self&#45;gratulation.  You all remember well&#44; when&#44;<lb/> despite our apparently lowly station&#44; we ranked foremost<lb/> among Hebrew religious associations.  The tide of our<lb/> prosperity had gently but uniformly flowed.  Four score<lb/> of years had passed over this Congregation&#44; and it never<lb/> saw the happy stream recede&#44; until the swelling of<lb/> human vanity&#44; raised the unpropitious wind&#44; that seemed<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>to have at once dried up its source.  Many then&#44; like<lb/> myself&#44; were seized with dismay at the impending<lb/> dissolution of our religious existence.  Many despondingly asked<lb/> one another&#44; shall we survive our fall&#63;  Will we<lb/> ever retrieve the loss of our character and standing&#63;......<lb/> But the rod that chastened us&#44; designed our correction.<lb/>  We were brought low&#44; only that we might learn from the<lb/> trials of the past&#44; to exercise moderation and thrift in<lb/> the future.  I now cast a searching glance at our<lb/> temporal condition&#59; and lo&#33; the clouds that hovered<lb/> around this edifice&#44; are scattering apace.  I know&#44; we<lb/> are still far from recovering the lofty position whence<lb/> we have descended&#44; but God has averted from us an<lb/> imminent danger.  He has spared us the burning shame<lb/> that would have attended the dismemberment of our<lb/> venerable institution.  I fully concur in the<lb/> idea that as long as any individual or corporation holds<lb/> in any degree&#44; virtual possession of a house professedly<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>dedicated to God&#44; gratulations are ill&#45;timed<lb/> and premature.  But the progress recently<lb/> made&#44; is to me a presage of a still greater<lb/> advancement.  Besides&#44; I have not relinquished the sanguine<lb/> expectation that cheered me in gloomier hours.  Nay&#44; when<lb/> I learn of the unprecedented success&#44; which sundry of my<lb/> fellow&#45;believers have attained in commercial pursuits&#44; the<lb/> prospect of its realization grows brighter before my vision.<lb/>  Brothers and sisters&#33;  Ye on whom Providence has showered<lb/> down exuberant wealth&#44; give honor to the God of Israel&#44;<lb/> and eternize your memory.  Let your righteous deeds<lb/> precede you to the everlasting abode&#44; and the glory of the<lb/> Lord will gather your immortal souls.  A young scion<lb/> of the stock of Levy&#44; has already set forth the example&#44;<lb/> you should strive to copy.  With a liberal spirit worthy<lb/> of the days of Moses and David&#44; he has tendered to the<lb/> Administrators of a Congregation in a neighbouring city&#44;<lb/> a sum that will efficaciously contribute towards<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>the rearing of a contemplated new stricture.  Your muni&#45;<lb/>&#45;ficent gifts&#44; my beloved friends&#33; will secure&#44; beyond any<lb/> contingencies&#44; the existence and dignity of this mansion&#44;<lb/> which you devoted&#44; four years ago&#44; to the worship of the<lb/> Most High.  Then on this day which the Lord has ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;pointed&#44; we will ever rejoice and be exceedingly glad.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            <p>But if the object toward which I have sought to<lb/> draw your hearts is of vital importance to us and I delight<lb/> to dwell on the events that foretoken its consummation&#44;<lb/> it should not nevertheless form the main topic of discussion<lb/> upon this heaven&#45;inspiring day.  Our minds must take<lb/> a higher flight.  Not the material but the spiritual<lb/> progress of our Community ought chiefly to arrest our<lb/> consideration.  A sense of self&#45;respect&#44; or the desire<lb/> to transmit unimpaired the fair fame bequeathed to<lb/> us by our predecessors&#44; may stir up some generous<lb/> spirits to replenish the treasury of the Lord&#44; but<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>what&#44; if the walls of his holy dwelling remain<lb/> deserted&#63;  If but a few enter these gates with<lb/> song&#44; these courts with thanksgivings&#63;<lb/>  Let us therefore rejoice this day&#44; because with the improve&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment of our finances&#44; the attendance at the public service<lb/> of our Lord&#44; has also kept pace.  Both have indeed been<lb/> very limited&#44; yet they are sufficiently perceptible&#44; to excite<lb/> pleasurable feelings in the observer.  And as I am frequent&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly impelled by duty to exhibit to view the effects of un&#45;<lb/>&#45;checkered sin&#44; so must I likewise openly declare the<lb/> praises due to the reclaimed sinner.  Yes&#44; my dear<lb/> hearers&#33;  The constant presence in this sacred habitation&#44; of<lb/> those who but rarely visited it&#44; is a progress that cannot<lb/> be overestimated.  For it denotes a change in the heart<lb/> and mind conducive to the most salutary results.  It<lb/> proves that man has at length learnt to set a higher<lb/> value on the will of his Maker&#44; than on the fleeting<lb/> goods of the earth.  That he is true to his professions&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>and he will not falsify them for the love of lucre.<lb/>  Understand me well&#44; it is not the mere participating of<lb/> this divine communion that elicits my congratulations&#44;<lb/> but the reverence for the Sabbath&#45;day&#44; which it implies.<lb/>  I rejoice thereat because it evidences moreover a desire<lb/> to identify <sic>onself</sic> with the time&#45;honored practices of<lb/> our people&#59; because it indirectly promotes the cultivation<lb/> of the national language&#44; in which the name of the Most<lb/> High is here extolled by his adorers in unison of voices.<lb/>  I highly commend it because when I behold parents conduct<lb/> their offspring to the dwelling of prayer&#44; I foresee the<lb/> rising of a new generation better tutored in their religion&#44;<lb/> better imbued with the eternal principles it has enunciated&#44;<lb/> more exalted enlightened in their views of life and its obligations&#44; less<lb/> worldly and more spiritual.  Like dew upon tender<lb/> grass will the precepts read and expounded from the<lb/> pulpit&#44; drop into the heart of the child.  Fostered<lb/> by parental example&#44; it will in dire season yield<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>an exuberance of moral good.  Let us then<lb/> upon this day which the Lord has appointed&#44; rejoice<lb/> and be glad&#44; by reason of our material and spiritual<lb/> progress &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            <p>But while I acknowledge with feelings of gratitude to<lb/> God even a slight advancement in the right direction&#44;<lb/> it behooves me to point out the obstructions to the<lb/> attaining of our final goal.  The absence of devotion<lb/> among some of our youths&#44; is an impediment that<lb/> strongly militates against our success.  I was<lb/> pained at my very heart&#44; to discover their listlessness<lb/> during the recital of the prayers.  To detect an indisposition<lb/> on their part to lend their aid in executing the ceremonies<lb/> connected with the divine service.  While any one born<lb/> in Israel ought to consider it an honor to have been<lb/> assigned the office of presenting to the reader the hea&#45;<lb/>&#45;venly volume&#44; from which he is to rehearse a portion&#44;<lb/> and to deposit it again into the ark&#44; I have marked<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>the uneasiness with which some of my young hearers<lb/> are seized when so selected.  Furthermore&#44; to judge<lb/> from the appearance&#44; it might be imagined that the<lb/> four fringed garment they wear&#44; is a leaden weight<lb/> of which they long to disburthen themselves&#44; so loosely<lb/> they cast it around their persons.  When called to the law&#44; their action might be construed as the a fear of too close<lb/> a contact with the sacred scroll&#44; for they will not remove<lb/> the gloves that cover their hands&#59; and both their<lb/> posture and deportment betray a reprehensible indifference<lb/> for the sanctuary of the Lord and his worship.<lb/></p>
            <p>But the irreverence exhibited by some among the ju&#45;<lb/>&#45;nior portion of our Congregation&#44; is a in a measure&#44;<lb/> attributable to the defective example set by their<lb/> senior.  The Sages of our people have been<lb/> so eager to preserve the sanctity of a house dedi&#45;<lb/>&#45;cated to God&#44; that they condemned as a detraction<lb/> thereof&#44; even a passing remark on a subject<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>foreign to the religious exercises.  Is it not then<lb/> incomprehensible how individuals who avow their ad&#45;<lb/>&#45;herence to Rabbinical injunctions&#44; will permit them&#45;<lb/>&#45;selves light converse&#44; needless walking&#44; and acts of<lb/> levity on the spot&#44; where we address the Creator&#63;<lb/>  Does not such a demeanour encourage the young and the untutored in<lb/> the belief that the simple act of repairing hither&#44; and<lb/> reciting an established ritual&#44; though in a devoutless<lb/> manner and with absence of thought&#44; is the worship<lb/> required by a son of Israel&#63;  But will you&#44; my<lb/> friends&#33; be the means of converting the spiritual out&#45;<lb/>&#45;pourings offered at the Altar of the Omnipotent&#44; into a<lb/> vapid and unmeaning form&#63;  No&#44; let the fear of the<lb/> Majestic Being to whom this house appertains&#44; deter<lb/> every one from disregarding its sanctity.  Thus&#44; like<lb/> the one aforenamed&#44; is an impediment which we must<lb/> sedulously endeavour to remove&#44; in order to gain for our Con&#45;<lb/>&#45;gregation a name and glory among our people.<lb/></p> 
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>But another cause has newly arisen which<lb/> greatly detracts of the dignity and decorum&#44; to<lb/> be maintained at the Synagogue.  It existed before&#44;<lb/>&#45;&#45;and I have at times animadverted thereon&#44;&#45;&#45;but<lb/> never&#44; I judge&#44; to the extent exhibited of late.<lb/>  I refer to our tardy attendance.  At a season<lb/> which might warrant our holding the morning<lb/> service at a much earlier hour than we are wont&#44;<lb/> a very sparse assembly gathers at its commence&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment&#44; and only when far advanced in it&#44; others join<lb/> it at intervals.  To correct this impropriety by<lb/> the system adopted by various modern Congregations&#44; is not that of which I altogether approve.<lb/>  I would consent at no time to deny my brother or<lb/> sister in faith admission to our holy communion&#44; for&#44;<lb/> circumstances beyond control may have occasioned a<lb/> delay&#59; but the evil has become so rife&#44; so general&#44;<lb/> that it must be reformed.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>I will then appeal to the understanding of my<lb/> intelligent hearers&#44; and as they must admit the just&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness of my complaints&#44; I will exhort them to follow<lb/> the dictates of reason and piety.  Both will urge<lb/> then the necessity of a different course form that hitherto almost<lb/> universally pursued.  The appearance of a vast<lb/> assemblage gathering at one time and with one<lb/> consent to adore the Monarch of the world&#44; must<lb/> impress the mind with devotional awe&#44; it must<lb/> enhance the dignity of the service&#44; it must lend<lb/> our external ceremonies a more imposing and<lb/> attractive character&#59; whereas our tardiness is indi&#45;<lb/>&#45;cative of want of earnestness in serving the Lord<lb/> and of respect for the constant punctual attendants at His worshippers.<lb/></p>
            <p>My beloved friends&#33;  Supremely among my thought<lb/>s reigns that of rendering our religious body and this<lb/> minor Sanctuary the prototype of a Jewish commu&#45;<lb/>&#45;nity.  Will you aid me in my efforts&#63;  Shall<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p>it our concerted labor&#44; during another year&#44; bring<lb/> us to the happy goal&#63;  See&#33; the way distance<lb/> is yet great.  It cannot be reached without the<lb/> disposition of means and sacrifice of time.  Will<lb/> you offer them to your people national honor and faith&#63;...<lb/> Oh&#33; may they be blessed of the Lord&#44; who so will.<lb/>  May they thrice be blessed who will pour forth<lb/> gold to immoveably set up the pillars of this<lb/> holy house.  May they be blessed who will<lb/> watch at its portals&#44; and gather into this sacred<lb/> fold&#44; the wandering among the flock and the mis&#45;<lb/>&#45;guided.  May they be blessed&#44; who will promise<lb/> in their hearts to hail the coming of the Sabbath&#44; to<lb/> seek thereupon the face of the Lord with sedulousness<lb/> and devotion&#44; to cast away as a polluting object<lb/> the gain obtained by the profanation of the se&#45;<lb/>&#45;venth day&#59; they who promise to become exem&#45;<lb/>&#45;plary for their reverence and humility&#44; they who<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="14"/>
            <p>will lay hold on the standard unfurled this<lb/> glorious morning &#40;thirty five centuries ago&#41; at the<lb/> summit of Horeb&#44; as on the sheet&#45;anchor of salvation&#44;<lb/> they who will live in it&#44; and proclaim its verities with<lb/> their last breath.  And may the exercise of these<lb/> virtues&#44; draw upon the head of all this assemblage<lb/> the heavenly blessing I have invoked.  Then will this<lb/> day which the Lord has appointed&#44; be ever to us one<lb/> of rejoicing and exceeding gladness.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
