<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF8_15</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1889-01" source="" attested="yes">1889</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_15_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_15_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_15_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_15_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_15_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_15_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_15_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_15_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_15_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_15_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_15_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_15_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>On Intoxication<lb/>
                predicated on the intended Abolition of<lb/>
                the sale of liquors in Penna. &#47;89<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  I might fill columns of newspapers<lb/> with the correspondence that I have had regarding<lb/> the wine of which Jews have ordinarily made use.<lb/>  Notably one person in our city&#44; has submitted to<lb/> my consideration his writings and those of his anta&#45;<lb/>&#45;gonists&#44; and asked that I would decide who is right&#44;<lb/> according to my knowledge of our laws and customs.<lb/>  The whole controversy&#44; among Christian ministers&#44;<lb/> hinges largely upon an incident told in the new testament.<lb/>  The wish to draw the man who figures in it most<lb/> conspicuously on one side or the other of the burning<lb/> question which has taken nowadays a political<lb/> shape&#44; is the cause of the great dispute.  To be<lb/> clearly understood&#44; I must necessarily refer to the<lb/> events&#44; as recorded in the books which our neighbors&#44;<lb/> who differ from our monotheistic creed&#44; hold sacred.  When<lb/> Passover was close at hand&#44; the disciples of the<lb/> man of Nazareth inquired where he purposed per&#45;<lb/>&#45;forming the home service of the first evening.  The<lb/> place was pointed out&#44; and as all sat at table&#44; the<lb/> master raised to his lips the cup&#44; over which he<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>had pronounced a benediction&#44; and passing it around&#44;<lb/> said&#58; &#34;drink&#34;...&#34;This is my blood of the new testament covenant&#44; which is<lb/> shed for many for the remission of sins.&#34;  Now the<lb/> zealots among &#34;Prohibitionists&#34; contend&#44; that he whom<lb/> millions worship&#44; as a redeeming god&#44; could not<lb/> have encouraged the sin of intemperance&#44; while making<lb/> a vicarious atonemnet for other sins&#44; consequently what he par&#45;<lb/>took of must have been a non&#45;intoxicating beverage.<lb/>  The fanatics of the opposite party&#44; claim that every<lb/> act of a being&#44; deemed to have been clothed with received a<lb/> divine nature&#44; must stand as a lesson to all gene&#45;<lb/>&#45;rations&#44; consequently there can be no harm in drink&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing liquor common among Jews and of which he<lb/> drank.  It will be seen that with faithful Christ&#45;<lb/>&#45;ians&#44; the question is mainly based on theological ground applicable<lb/> to the sacrament&#44; or the so termed&#44; &#34;lord&#39;s supper&#34;&#44;<lb/> in which wine is called into requisition.  Accordingly&#44;<lb/> meetings of various denominational bodies are con&#45;<lb/>&#45;tinually taking place on that score.  A week ago&#44;<lb/> at a conference of Presbyterian ministers in<lb/> Philadelphia the subject was warmly discus&#45;<lb/>&#45;sed.  Dr Howard Crosby&#44; known for<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>his conservative views&#44; took strong grounds against<lb/> the theory that there are two sorts of wine&#44; one which<lb/> intoxicates and is Biblically forbidden&#44; and another<lb/> which is unfermented and allowed.  He did not<lb/> go the whole length of a certain clergyman&#44; who<lb/> declared Prohibitionists offenders against the Scriptures&#44;<lb/> and defamers of the founder of Christianity.  He<lb/> admitted that drunkenness is an unmitigated evil&#44; which<lb/> the pulpit must try to check&#44; but he forcibly denied<lb/> that the use of liquor is a sin&#44; which the church ought<lb/> unqualifiedly to condemn.  In his opinion&#44; the latter commits<lb/> itself wrongfully when it approves of any scheme&#44;<lb/> which reflects upon the doings of the one in whose<lb/> vicarious expiatory mediation he puts implicit faith.<lb/>  To Dr. Crosby&#39;s mind&#44; the gospel is the sole guide<lb/> to mortals&#44; and because no denunciation of spirituous<lb/> liquors is met in it&#44; therefore these should not be<lb/> denounced.  Against his views&#44; a Reverend<lb/> Dr Patterson rushed entered a solemn protest.  He assumed<lb/> to have studied the topic thoroughly&#44; and to have ar&#45;<lb/>&#45;rived at the conclusion&#44; that there actually are<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>two kinds of wine&#44; and that the man of Naza&#45;<lb/>&#45;reth&#44; on the night of the Passover&#44; must have drank<lb/> such only as was unfermented.  To think<lb/> otherwise would be in his conception to level lower the character of<lb/> an incarnate deity to the level of worthless inc&#45;<lb/>&#45;loriates.  Truly&#44; my Brethren&#44; the Rabbinical maxim<lb/> fits well even in this instance also &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;  Both love and hatred<lb/> are apt to overstep the bounds of discretion.<lb/>  Conceding that what the new testament chroni&#45;<lb/>&#45;cles possesses historical value&#44; it is preposterous<lb/> to deny that the wine drunk by the master<lb/> and his disciples was fermented&#44; and equally absurd<lb/> to cast reflections&#44; because it was so.  When<lb/>&#45;ever I was requested to act as an umpire&#44; I<lb/> unequivocally stated that Jews have at all<lb/> times partaken of fermented&#44; or regular wines&#44;<lb/> prepared by their own people&#44; on Passover as<lb/> always.  For the law of leaven in connection with<lb/> the festival that recalls our freedom from Egyptian<lb/> bondage&#44; does not extend further than to grain<lb/> fermentation&#44; in commemoration of the bread eaten<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>by our ancestors when they marched on to liberty.<lb/>  It was a surprise to me to have heard that some<lb/> of my colleagues held forth opposite views&#44; having<lb/> asserted that during the coming holiday particularly&#44;<lb/> but generally when we offer prayers on wine&#44; we<lb/> are allowed only the juice of boiled raisins.  A<lb/> mere exception in countries where regular spirituous<lb/> wines are comparatively dear&#44; has been unac&#45;<lb/>&#45;countably mistaken for a rule.  In Palestine<lb/> the luscious grapes of which a specimen was brought<lb/> in the days of Moses&#44; by the explorers of Canaan to the wilderness of<lb/> Paran&#44; festooned&#44; as it were&#44; the whole land&#44;<lb/> and those persons must have read the old testament to<lb/> no purpose who failed to discover that many of<lb/> the similes employed by the prophets were taken<lb/> from the luxuriant bowers&#44; beneath whose shades<lb/> our forefathers sat at one period of their history<lb/> tranquilly in their ancient homes.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> We are made by our poetical seers almost to<lb/> hear the cheerful melodies of young men and<lb/> damsels&#44; at vintage time&#44; when wine flowed<lb/> from the press.  Indeed&#44; the passage in Isaiah&#58;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Ye shall have a song like in the night of ce&#45;<lb/>&#45;lebrating the festival&#34; has been understood by some<lb/> of our expositors as allusive to the night of Pass&#45;<lb/>&#45;over&#44; when amid holy devotional chanting we empty out four glasses&#44; typical<lb/> of the four expressions of liberty in the second<lb/> book of Moses the Pentateuch&#44; promising our ancestors&#39; redemption<lb/> from thraldom.  TO remember all that<lb/> and say that the man of Nazareth&#44; born in Judea&#44;<lb/> reared after its laws&#44; and following its customs&#44;<lb/> drank at his last supper simply the decoction<lb/> of dry raisins&#44; sounds ludicrous.  Yet&#44; such<lb/> is the folly&#44; which some churchmen in their just<lb/> hatred of intoxication&#44; reason themselves into.<lb/>  The Hebrew Bible does brand intoxication intemperance with an<lb/> indelible mark of disgrace&#44; and nowhere more<lb/> deeply than when it declares that &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; like lewdness&#44; so wine old or new robs man of his mind&#44;<lb/> but no where&#44; in the other hand&#44; it prohibits<lb/> a moderate use.  The Nazarite who of<lb/> his own accord took a pledge to abstain for<lb/> a time&#44; was obliged at its expiration to bring<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>a trespass offering&#44; because&#44; as some Talmudists<lb/> explain&#44; he unnecessarily subjected himself to a<lb/> privation.  In fact&#44; Israelites whe&#45;<lb/>&#45;ther in their patriarchal land&#44; or in the countries of<lb/> their adoption&#44; have remained faithful to the Rab&#45;<lb/>&#45;binical principle that teaches &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; the<lb/> middle course is the correct.  To be sure&#44; Jewish<lb/> men&#45;&#45;I never met Jewish women drunk&#45;&#45;Jewish men become occasion&#45;<lb/>&#45;ally addicted to the accursed vice which desolates<lb/> homes and fills prisons&#44; but thanks to the domes&#45;<lb/>&#45;tic habits hereditary among the disciples of<lb/> Moses&#44; the instances in which a father&#44; or<lb/> a son wastes his week&#39;s wages in sinks of cor&#45;<lb/>&#45;ruption&#44; and leaves his family in destitution&#44; are<lb/> very rare.  Therefore I have not acceded to<lb/> urgent requests made of late&#44; that I would either<lb/> raise my voice in favor of the prohibitory law<lb/> soon to be tested by popular vote&#44; or show<lb/> my advocacy of it by attending a crowded meetings resoun&#45; demand<lb/> &#45;mand ing its passage.  I hold drunkenness<lb/> in utter abhorrence&#44; and hail any regulation with&#45;<lb/> &#45;in constitutionally powers enacted tending to curb its sinful<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>indulgence&#44; but I believe that the legitimate pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;vince of pastors lies in the moral suasion which<lb/> they are able to employ&#44; to keep their flock in within the<lb/> bounds of morality moderation.  They must summon to their<lb/> aid the holy books&#44; history and the personal expe&#45;<lb/>rience which their vocation offers&#44; so as obviously<lb/> to prove that insobriety is a crime&#44; nay&#44; it is a two double edged sword&#44; cutting<lb/> him asunder who holds ho on to it&#44; and severing the<lb/> sweetest ties&#59; to ministers must demonstrate that the effect of habi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tual inebriety is the loss of manhood&#44; and the loss of<lb/> home affections&#44; it is harm and misery.  Fortunately&#44; the prerogative<lb/> of the Jewish pulpit is to show that a true Israel&#45;<lb/>&#45;ite can greet the Sabbath and festivals on the brim&#45;<lb/>&#45;ful cup of wine&#44; quaff the prescribed measure on<lb/> the memorable night of Passover&#44; and never sink<lb/> his dignity&#44; but remain socially virtuous and domestic&#45;<lb/>&#45;ally pure.  May such be our prerogative<lb/> always.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
