<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF9_14</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1891-05" source="" attested="yes">May 1891</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_14_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_14_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_14_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_14_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_14_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_14_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_14_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_14_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_14_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_14_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_14_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_14_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/></p>
            <p>PHILADELPHIA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>112<lb/></p>
            <p><del>Nissan</del> Iyar May 91<lb/></p>
            <p>On ministerial defections<lb/>
                based on Dr Briggs&#39; controversy<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Brethren.  From the time that Bishop Colenso&#45;&#45;sent<lb/> by England to convert heathens to Christianity&#45;&#45;turned<lb/> against Christian dogmas&#44; there has not been a any lack<lb/> of churchmen&#44; who took up arms against the church.<lb/>  In our own days&#44; Germany has an deserves the unenviable credit honor of<lb/> having lifted up high the which she boasts to have she has lifted up a standard of rebellion altho&#39; against the criticism sable<lb/> whereon she emblazoned the deceptive words&#58; A &#34;higher criticism&#34;<lb/> Great Britain less bold could reckon also more than one who in former<lb/> years&#44; who relished the bread and fishes of the ministerial office&#44; but cared not<lb/> to earn them legitimately&#59; by fidelity to their trust.<lb/></p> 
            <p>As to her John William Colenso&#44; who was commissioned<lb/> to teach the Bible and the divinity of the founder<lb/> of the Nazarene religion&#44; but who cast doubts upon<lb/> the authenticity of the former&#44; and the claims of the<lb/> latter&#44; the curious anomaly was that all endeavours<lb/> to depose the man&#44; to stop his salary&#44; or disgrace him<lb/> were in vain to no purpose.  He continued to use his pen with impu&#45;<lb/>&#45;nity to the injury of Christian orthodoxy&#44; still en&#45;<lb/>&#45;joying a stipulated income&#44; as a prelate of the An&#45;<lb/>&#45;glican Church.  A case not unlike that of<lb/> the Bishop of Natal in South Africa&#59; a cus which created<lb/> a great stir over thirty years ago&#59; happened lately<lb/> in America.  The Rev Dr Heber Newton&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>fired at the Bible&#44; attacking it once both or what he considered vulnerable points historically and<lb/> doctrinally points.  Quite a tempest was raised&#44; when&#44;<lb/> following in the wake of the Scottman Robertson<lb/> Smith&#44; the New York minister published his ra&#45;<lb/>&#45;dical views in book form&#44; placing them within reach<lb/> of the whole reading public.  &#34;Surely&#34; people said&#58;<lb/> &#34;Surely his superiors in the Episcopal council will<lb/> demand a recantation&#44; or command that the skeptic<lb/> preacher shall step down and out of his subversive pulpit.&#34;  The storm however blew<lb/> over and the passionate outbursts of Father Ignatius<lb/> will avail nothing to bring about the excommunication&#44;<lb/> which that English Jesuit so vehemently insists upon by that English Jesuit.  The most<lb/> famous instance of modern defections in the ministry&#44;<lb/> is perhaps that which the Presbytery in America is now<lb/> engaged to sift out.  The Rev Dr Charles A. Briggs<lb/> gained a large following among students of Hebrew<lb/> in the Union Theological Seminary of New York.<lb/>  He taught that branch of learning successfully&#44;<lb/> and obtained therefore won promotion.  Last January in his<lb/> inaugural address&#44; as Professor of Biblical theology<lb/> in the same institution&#44; the speaker made assertions that<lb/> startled very many&#44; and at which some of his colleagues<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>declared themselves scandalized.  Since then the name of<lb/> that professor of theology has become a household word&#44;<lb/> for scarcely a day passes&#44; but without reports are being made<lb/> of investigations&#44; or of sermons&#44; connected with his object&#45;<lb/>&#45;ionable utterances.  He that runs can read them in<lb/> any journals printed in the English language.<lb/></p>  
            <p>I notice that Rabbis also have entered the lists&#44; and<lb/> taken different sides.  According to those who allow<lb/> ministers of any every creed &#38; denomination whatever&#44; the<lb/> widest latitude to ventilate their notions however clashing with their charge&#44; Dr Briggs<lb/> ought not to be questioned about his denial of or<lb/> opposition to accepted tenets.  Such Rabbis argue so&#58;<lb/> The professor&#39;s conscientious studies meditations have led him to<lb/> certain conclusions and he is and the ideas he firmly holds&#44; he should be at liberty to proclaim<lb/> them to the world at large.  Persons who call him to account<lb/> are persecutors&#44; heresy&#45;hunters&#44; tyrants&#44; inquisitors&#44; ana&#45;<lb/>&#45;thematizing bigots.  Their conduct can only excite the<lb/> contempt of the right thinking.  I need not tell<lb/> how I differ disagree with this pseudo liberalism&#59; how I hold cherish it as a maxim of pure<lb/> ethics&#44; that as soon as an official in any public<lb/> position capacity&#44; has ceased to be in harmony with the principles<lb/> guiding his trust&#44; he ought to be put off the insignia of his office.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Other Rabbis&#44; stretching their looks forward&#44; believe fancy<lb/> that they can see&#44; through the disputations carried<lb/> on&#44; the triumph of Judaism at no distant future.<lb/>  The religion to which we adhere to is not sworn to the<lb/> iron bound rules that govern the Church in each of its nu&#45;<lb/>&#45;merous divisions.  No Westminster articles of faith&#59;<lb/> no blood atonement&#44; no papal infallibility&#44; no imma&#45;<lb/>&#45;culate conception&#44; no confessional&#44; no eucharist&#44; none<lb/> of that intermingles with our intrudes upon the government of the Sy&#45;<lb/>&#45;nagogue&#44; therefore the final settlement of those points<lb/> of dispute&#44; which have too often raised the hand of<lb/> brother against brother&#44; will be the acceptance of the<lb/> simple&#44; reasonable&#44; and merciful belief which Jews<lb/> cling to.  I am sorry that my sight is not so<lb/> far&#45;reaching&#44; as to perceive the forthcoming glories that some of my<lb/> colleagues predict anticipate for our creed religion&#44; because of the doubts<lb/> which are cast upon Christianity.  I admit that<lb/> a vast deal which elicits the healed polemics on ac&#45; controversies polemics due<lb/> &#45;count of to Dr Briggs&#39; &#34;heresy&#44;&#34; as some call it&#44; has<lb/> no meaning with us.  Nowhere have we been enjoined<lb/> to subscribe to the creed that Holy Writ throughout is a verbal dicta&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion from on high&#59; that every word in it emanates<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>from God&#59; No&#58; the thoughts are divine&#44; but the lan&#45;<lb/>&#45;gauge is human.  In order not to be misunderstood&#44;<lb/> I will say&#44; that the Pentateuch&#44; which embodies our<lb/> leading rules of conduct life&#44; is&#44; in part&#44; an exception to my<lb/> statement.  But as regards the rest of the Scriptures&#44;<lb/> the Talmudists themselves agree that &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;not two prophets use the same vocabulary&#59; the same<lb/> style&#34;.  Thus&#44; to offer a slight illustration.  Can<lb/> any person suppose that Isaiah who foretold the fall<lb/> of Babylon in his immutable majestic diction&#44; and Jeremiah who<lb/> predicted it also&#44; but not with the marked original&#45;<lb/>&#45;ity and grandeur of his predecessor.  Now&#44; can any one suppose that both wrote upon the identical subject<lb/> in differently&#44; words so but word for word as dictated verbatim by a heavenly inspiration&#63;<lb/>  Reason will not allow that supposition&#44; and reason<lb/> is with us Jews a powerful factor in the acceptance of<lb/> belief.  Not in the sense which Dr Briggs is charged<lb/> of having said intimated in his inaugural address&#44; namely&#44; that<lb/> the reason and the Bible stand on a level&#44; for the wisest<lb/> among us is fallible&#59; but when an idea is so clearly<lb/> inadmissible&#44; that our unbiased mind rejects it&#44; to<lb/> advance it as entitled to our credence&#44; must seem<lb/> complete blindness.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Now would any Jew be brought to trial&#44; for believing that mistake&#44; have crept in&#44;<lb/> which either the ignorance or inadvertence of copyists occasioned to the very scholars<lb/> and obscuring the text.  The <sic>inornancy</sic> of the scriptures&#44; is a delusive creed&#44; which none of<lb/> us entertains&#44; notwithstanding the very laborious endeavours of the Masso&#45;<lb/>&#45;rites.<lb/></p>
            <p>Still&#44; some of the questions which agitate the Church Just at present&#44;<lb/> do concern us also&#44; and deeply so.  They have a greater<lb/> significance than a this wrangling about a verbal or spiri&#45;<lb/>&#45;tual emanation of prophetic writings and their preservation from errors textual errors.  They concern the<lb/> authenticity of the Mosaic records&#44; the dependence we<lb/> may place upon the authorship of any of the books&#44;<lb/> which constitute our Bible&#59; nay&#44; the very existence of<lb/> our ancient Seers.  If Moses wrote nothing&#44; or<lb/> next to nothing&#44; as Dr Briggs positively asserts&#59; if<lb/> the history of our patriarchs is a sheer myth as some contend&#59; if those whose<lb/> memory we have always looked upon with as our godly held in veneration&#44; are not our genuine instructors&#44;<lb/> but others have assumed their names in late ages and palmed off as divinely inspired their own inventions&#44; as divinely inspired&#44; if Daniel<lb/> is a fiction&#44; and his dreams visions were invented concocted centuries after<lb/> to covertly represent current events&#59; in short&#44; if<lb/> the Bible possesses no higher value than according to what is now dignified by the term of &#34;higher criticism&#44;&#34; the value<lb/> of the Bible consists only in its moral maxims&#44; just<lb/> as Epictetus among the Greeks&#44; and Cicero among<lb/> the Romans will inspire are deserving of respect by reason of their<lb/> ethical teachings then to claim a belief in inspi&#45; then the foundations of Judaism are uprooted&#44; and neither Christianity nor Mohammedanism can<lb/> stand.  They must tumble down&#59; and for a churchman to claim saturated with<lb/> lation and in the infallibility of the scriptures ideas flowing from the swelling current of German incredulity&#44; to claim loyalty<lb/> regarding saving truths&#44; is to the Scriptures&#44; as the infallible receptacle of Divine truths&#44; appears to me a deception&#44; a sub<lb/> subterfuge to avoid a deposition the humiliation of a dismissal.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>But why do I refer at all to a controversy distur&#45;<lb/>&#45;bing the quiet of the Presbyterian Church&#63;  That<lb/> denomination has can point at least&#44; to some acknowledged au&#45;<lb/>&#45;thority&#44; at whose tribunal persons in office&#44; suspected<lb/> of defection a deviation from its rules&#44; can be questioned and<lb/> catechized.  Among us Jews&#44; an inextricable con&#45;<lb/>&#45;fusion exists&#44; through which a man&#44; however fla&#45;<lb/>&#45;grantly offensive&#44; can escape all punishment.  A<lb/> Rabbi may preach the most subversive theories&#44; em&#45;<lb/>&#45;body them in writings spread broadcast&#44; and enjoy<lb/> more than the bread and fishes&#59; aye&#58; receive plaudits for<lb/> his independence&#40;&#63;&#41; A Recenlty we were regaled with a series of articles appeared<lb/> very recently over the signature of one who ministers<lb/> in New York to a congregation&#44; that would resent<lb/> as an offence affront its being called &#34;Radical.&#34;  Yet&#44; I<lb/> am not dealing in exaggerations&#44; when I state that nei&#45;<lb/>&#45;ther Benedict Spinoza in his &#34;Fructatus Politicus&#34;&#44; nor<lb/> Thomas Paine in his &#34;Age of reason&#34; used our Scriptures<lb/> more irreverently&#44; nor lowered more the character of our prophets&#44;<lb/> than that Rabbi.  According to him Joshua was a re&#45; forced back<lb/> &#45;trogressist for having the wheel of progress by having allowed the Abrahamic<lb/> covenant to be performed&#44; at Gilgal.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Elijah was a disturber of the public peace&#59; Elisha<lb/> an unscrupulous agitator&#44; and much which we now<lb/> have always considered sacred history is simply a ro&#45;<lb/>&#45;mance.  Where is the synod&#59; where the council&#44; or<lb/> the ecclesiastical advisory Board of revision that might summon<lb/> the heretical minister&#44; and bring him to grief&#63;  None<lb/> exists to vindicate right&#44; and show how morally wrong<lb/> it is in a man to receive from Hebrews a generous emolument&#44;<lb/> with the object of for teaching the Hebrew faith&#44; but who and<lb/> &#91;&#63;&#93; in spite of it set all at defiance&#44; as an instigator of infidelity<lb/> and profanity.  Do I recommend proscription&#63;<lb/>  Not at all.  I insist upon honesty&#44; and I would<lb/> hail the appointing of a some accepted body of man having a jurisdiction&#44; that might&#44; by<lb/> general consent&#44; decide what is expected of a Rabbi in<lb/> his capacity as the exponent of Biblical virtues and<lb/> the traditions.  The &#34;Radicals&#34; in our camp we cannot<lb/> reach&#44; but religious bodies corporations that still profess alle&#45;<lb/>&#45;giance to the ancestral faith&#44; ought to be rid of<lb/> false teachers.  Let them not be suffered to<lb/> tear the Torah into shreds&#44; to make a foot stool to<lb/> trample on.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
