<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF14_5</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_5_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_5_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_5_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_5_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_5_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_5_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_5_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_5_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_5_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_5_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_5_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff14_5_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>5th lecture of Revelation<lb/></p>
            
            <p>The sixth lecture on Revelation was afterwards<lb/>
                lengthened and altered&#44; and it formed a series<lb/> of 4 articles to combat Dr Kohlers ideas<lb/>
                in his article &#34;Old &#38; modern Judaism&#34;<lb/>
                as published in the 25 No of The Hebrew Review<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>The last paragraph in the section of the Pentateuch&#44;<lb/> designated for this Sabbath&#44; supplies me with the<lb/> cue for catering into the subject which&#44; in the pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;secution of my l series&#44; I wish now to discuss.<lb/>  The battle against a savage assailant is fought and<lb/> won.  Moses stirred by inspiration consigns to eter&#45;<lb/>&#45;nal ignominy the name of pitiless Amalek.  He<lb/> will record the doom of extinction divinely decreed against<lb/> that ungodly people&#44; and rehearse the narrative within the<lb/> hearing of his faithful attendant.  At the re&#45;<lb/>&#45;counting of this incident&#44; a swarm of infidels rises up.<lb/>  Titters&#44; grimaces&#44; and derisive looks meet us around&#44;<lb/> &#34;Preposterous&#34; mutters Dr Wette&#44; &#34;impossible&#34; cries Vol&#45;<lb/>&#45;taire&#44; &#34;incredible&#34; says Colleus&#44; and Colenso &#44; and<lb/> Kuenen and Bernstein and other Eichhorn&#44; radicals of the same stripe school respond<lb/> <sic>consentingly</sic> to the harsh utterances.<lb/></p>
            <p>Brethren.  It cannot be a secret to intelligent Israelites&#44;<lb/> and it should not remain concealed from our youths&#44;<lb/> that the ability of the arch&#45;prophet to use the Alphabet<lb/> in the composition of the holy books&#44; has been disputed<lb/> by some critics with determined <sic>persistance</sic>.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>That question they made one of the main points of<lb/> attack.  Against it they directed the battering&#45;rams<lb/> of their untied sharp acute reasonings.  For they felt that if the pre&#45;<lb/>vailing idea that the Pentateuch is the written monu&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment of God&#39;s revelation to the son of Amram be once demo&#45;<lb/>&#45;lished&#44; all the whole fabric must fall with it.  With a ferocity Not<lb/> unlike that the ferocity of Amalek against the enfranchised slaves&#44;<lb/> was that wherewith critics have rushed upon the life&#45;guiding standard of<lb/> the liberated tribes.  &#34;The art of conveying ideas by<lb/> letters was unborn three thousand years ago.  How futile&#44;<lb/> how absurd then the belief that a man committed to writing<lb/> a complex legislation&#33;&#34;  And the emphatical denial seeks<lb/> support in history.  The hieroglyphics&#44; or picture<lb/> writings of ancient Egypt become the bulwark of un&#45;<lb/>believers.<lb/></p>
            <p>The argument is logical.  Such a process&#44; as then <sic>practised</sic><lb/> would seem&#44; at the first blush&#44; to indicate the absence<lb/> of an easier method for representing thoughts.  For no one will resort to a difficult plan&#44; when another offers every facility.  Indeed&#44;<lb/> were it irrefutably so&#59; had history left no trace of<lb/> human capacity&#44; so far back&#44; to hand down events&#44;<lb/> save by means of figures upon stones or metals&#44; our belief<lb/> in the authority authenticity of the five books must be shaken from its foundation&#44; it must be surrendered as sheer<lb/> credulity.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>The incidents narratives and the ordinances recorded in volumes<lb/> extensively set out&#44; before a people&#44; could not&#44; in any<lb/> p feasible probability journeys&#44; and preserved till the time arrived<lb/> when they should be entrusted to writing.  But ano&#45;<lb/>&#45;ther weighty consideration opposes the notion of such an unlike improbable pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;cedure.  The Pentateuch contains allusions to the tracing<lb/> of plain characters&#44; intelligible to all&#44; and upon ma&#45;<lb/>&#45;terials reasonably less <sic>unweildy</sic> than stones or metals.<lb/>  I have no particular reference to the paragraph at the<lb/> end of this day&#39;s portion.  Numerous are the instances<lb/> implying the necessity of writing after a system si&#45;<lb/>milar to the present.  Let me cite one&#44; by way of<lb/> illustration.  According to the Mosaic code of matri&#45;<lb/>&#45;monial separation was to be effected in the following<lb/> manner.  The husband would write a bill of divorce&#45;&#45;<lb/>in the literal Hebrew &#34;a book&#44; or scroll of cutting off&#34; connection&#45;&#45;<lb/>and deliver it into the hand of his wife.  Here we<lb/> must pause and think dispassionately.  Either the art of writing was<lb/> known&#44; or Moses did not lay down that regulation&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>nor any other of that book which the Jewish<lb/> world recognizes as authoritative.  For it was that&#44;<lb/> we are told&#44; which the prophet ordered in his last days<lb/> to have placed at the side of the ark of the covenant&#44;<lb/> holding the two tables of the Decalogue.  The dilemma<lb/> is very serious&#59; but fortunately we are not left long<lb/> in suspense.  Profane history teaches us how to<lb/> choose.  Profane history assists men who credit<lb/> the truths of the most sacred of histories&#44; better than<lb/> hieroglyphics aid its opponents.<lb/></p>
            <p>Herodotus&#44; who flourished during some decades shortly after the period in which<lb/> the Hebrews were still captives of Babylon succeeded in returned to in reestablishing the solemn the worship in the patriarchal land&#44; Babylonina captives&#44; that is&#44;<lb/> upward of twenty two centuries ago&#44; attests that<lb/> in the course of his travels through the East&#44; he had<lb/> seen inscriptions made by Sedostris.  In them the Egypt&#45;<lb/>&#45;ian king related the many victories achieved.  Mark&#44;<lb/> my young friends.  The ruler of whom the Greek historian<lb/> speaks was not his contemporary&#44; but a monarch of<lb/> high antiquity&#44; perchance anterior to the time a coeval the Pharaoh of Moses.<lb/>  What say to that the unbelievers at that&#63;  Three thousand years<lb/> ago the art of writing was surely known and <sic>practised</sic>.<lb/>  I am asked&#58; will you not tell us then who wears the laurels won<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>by that grand invention&#44; for the man or people&#44; who<lb/> deserves so well of mankind&#44; ought to be extolled in all<lb/> generation&#63;..  None has ever been so clever as to solve<lb/> that query.  The ocean of time has swept away&#44; the<lb/> together with countless memorials&#44; that of the author<lb/> of a most important and beneficial discovery.  In my<lb/> younger days&#44; influenced by a saying of the Rabbis in<lb/> the Mishnah of Aboth&#44; and by the perusal of a Hebrew<lb/> work&#44; whose style pleased me much&#44; I inclined to attri&#45;<lb/>&#45;bute the wonderful art to a direct revelation from<lb/> the Deity.  Since then my ideas have undergone a<lb/> considerable change.  Now I am of opinion that the<lb/> letters were the effect of human ingenuity&#44; or rather a<lb/> gradual development of and improvement on picture&#45;writing.<lb/></p>
            <p><sic>Heroduts</sic> tells his readers that the Greeks owed the<lb/> introduction of the invaluable art in the midst&#44; to the<lb/> Phoenicians&#44; and I venture to add that those Hametes&#44;<lb/> whose spirit of enterprise grew afterward to be illimitable&#44;<lb/> may have early pushed their incursions as far as the Nile<lb/> and spread abroad the knowledge they possessed.<lb/></p>
            <p>Recent researches point to the Euphrates&#44; as the cradle&#45;birth<lb/> of the Alphabet.  In the ruins of Assyria&#44; written tablets<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>have been unearthed&#44; of an antiquity exceedingly remote.<lb/>  It is said to have preceded the time when the Hebrews<lb/> were bondmen in the country of Mizraim.  I am incompetent<lb/> to decide whether the assertion is entitled to implicit<lb/> credence.  Nor is it needful for the object which<lb/> I have at heart&#44; that I resolve upon accepting or reject&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing what the lamented George Smith has disclosed to the<lb/> learned world.  My vindication of the authenticity of<lb/> the Pentateuch does not depend on the evidences drawn<lb/> from monumental remains in Nineveh or Persepolis.<lb/>  When Herodotus&#44; who could have no interest in falsifying<lb/> history&#44; touching this point&#44; relates to me that the Ionians&#44;<lb/> one of the oldest Grecian tribes&#44; wrote already in ancient<lb/> days upon scrolls made of parchment&#59; when I further<lb/> learn that papyrus abounded in Egypt&#44; and in other<lb/> hot climates&#44; and it was so prepared as to be employed<lb/> by the understanding to record events&#44; while hieroglyphics&#44; or<lb/> picture&#45;writing served as a popular means of instruction&#59;<lb/> when&#44; I say&#44; the ingenious attestation of history declares to me<lb/> that I have not been hugging a delusion&#44; I feel my faith<lb/> upheld and strengthened immeasurably.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>I set myself then on high ground and with an air<lb/> of defiance return the critics&#39; derisive looks.  For<lb/> I know that Moses did have the characters to write with<lb/> and the materials to write upon the five volumes&#44;<lb/> which are the inestimable heritage of the congregation<lb/> of Jacob.  Some among modern cavilers&#44; pressed<lb/> against the wall by the concurrent testimony joint force of history and<lb/> recent discoveries&#44; have <sic>yeilded</sic> that point.  Still&#44; entrenched<lb/> behind the rampart of their incredulity&#44; they throw new<lb/> missiles of war.  I have not engaged in a literary strife.<lb/>  My mission is not to measure arms with infidels&#44; but to<lb/> keep watch and guard my young brethren from the dangers perils<lb/> of skepticism.  Nevertheless I must stop and combat another<lb/> dangerous idea connected with the topic.  It is con&#45;<lb/>&#45;tended that the arch&#45;prophet could not&#44; in any event&#44; have<lb/> written the Pentateuch&#44; because the Coptic or Egyptian<lb/> characters with which he may have known been familiar&#44; differ widely in shape and<lb/> sound from the Hebrew.  Again Herodotus hastened to<lb/> my help.  He&#45;&#45;a native of Greece&#45;&#45;narrates that his na&#45;<lb/>tion originally accepted from the Phoenicians the form and<lb/> name of the letters&#44; and gradually altered them both.<lb/>  Why might not the Egyptians have followed the same<lb/> course&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Is the inference too irrational in the minds of the critics&#44;<lb/> who can give upon this subject absolutely nothing&#44; ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;cept denials or contradictions&#63;  I will not pass off<lb/> my supposition surmise as a fact&#44; incapable of refutation&#44; yet<lb/> it deserves support from an general admission wi extensively admitted theory that the<lb/> Hebrew characters used by Moses and his successors till<lb/> later centuries&#44; bore the closest resemblance to the Phoenician.<lb/>  The Samaritans&#44; who still retain the Pentateuch in those<lb/> characters&#44; claim to be in possession of the primitive writing<lb/> and truly when a comparison is made between it and the<lb/> letters impressed on the shekles <sic>Sheckels</sic> struck by the Maccabees&#44;<lb/> the acknowledgment forces itself out&#44; that the boast of<lb/> these schismatics has strong foundations.  It is not at<lb/> all improbable that the men of the Great Synod&#44; to raise<lb/> a wall of partition between the faithful and the faithless&#44;<lb/> who became an eyes sore to Israel&#44; advisedly adopted another a new<lb/> alphabet in the transcribing of the holy books.  They may<lb/> have kept the original one on their coins&#44; to facilitate com&#45;<lb/>&#45;merce with the Phoenicians and neighboring peoples&#44; but<lb/> the square letters&#44; or Chaldaic which we are now in use&#44; superseded the f others&#44;<lb/> in the hands of Sages and Scribes.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>I am aware that opinions are not in perfect<lb/> harmony concerning this interesting subject.  And I<lb/> have but lightly touched upon that which deserves demands<lb/> profound researches and a lengthy and thorough dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;sertation.  Imperfectly as the task has been<lb/> accomplished it will not have proved useless&#44; if I<lb/> have succeeded in the object which suggested my<lb/> thoughts&#59; if I have demonstrated not alone the<lb/> possibility&#44; but the certainty of our prophet&#39;s ca&#45;<lb/>&#45;pacity to prepare for all generations the grand<lb/> code which has civilized mankind&#44; and which we<lb/> treasure up as the most precious inheritance.<lb/></p>
            <p>My young brothers and sisters in faith must be<lb/> edified and I trust that they have derived some instruction&#44;<lb/> they must convinced&#44; and I hope that they are con&#45;<lb/>&#45;firmed in their belief.  May they&#44; when yonder scroll<lb/> is elevated in the sight of a <sic>prayful</sic> multitude&#44;<lb/> exclaim in all sincerity and heartiness &#34;This is the<lb/> law which Moses has set before the children of Israel&#34;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
