<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF3_7</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_7_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_7_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_7_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_7_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_7_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_7_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_7_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_7_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_7_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_7_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_7_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_7_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_7_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_7_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_7_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_7_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For the Sabbath<lb/>
                before Purim<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#34;The Jews had light and gladness&#44; joy and honor.&#34;<lb/>  Avaunt then ye gloomy thoughts&#33;  Joy shall brighten<lb/> our souls.  The wonders of the living God&#44; must occupy<lb/> this day&#44; the minds too often suddenly the memory of the dead.<lb/>  Members of that race&#44; of which we&#44; my hearers&#44; from an<lb/> integral part&#44; now avert their eyes from the dreary present&#44;<lb/> to cast a look on the glorious past.  The rod of oppression affliction&#44;<lb/> the oppressor&#39;s wrongs&#44; cease to be felt&#44; at a season that<lb/> Israel sing the deliverance wrought by their almighty God.<lb/>  Shall private sorrows withhold us from joining in the<lb/> national anthem&#63;  Never&#58; Our voices&#44; O American<lb/> Israelites&#44; should be preeminently heard.  For the Hamans<lb/> of this age&#44; cannot devise our destruction.  We share with<lb/> all mortals the ills incident to human nature&#44; but we<lb/> are free from the sufferings laid upon our brethren by the<lb/> hand of despotism.  He is neither strong in judgment&#44;<lb/> nor strong in power&#44; whose project would rej reduce the<lb/> adorers of the One God in this land&#44; to the condition of the<lb/> Sudras and the Pariahs.  He may&#44; like our ancient<lb/> adversary in Persia&#44; cast lots to discover by false divinations&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>the time most propitious for the consummation of his<lb/> scheme.  But in vain.  It will be frustrated.  Be<lb/> confident&#44; my fellow&#45;believers&#33;  The guardians of our rights&#44;<lb/> seated in the hall of legislation&#44; will not permit a tampering&#44;<lb/> which would deface the noblest of documents&#44; and destroy<lb/> its avowed object.  At each return of our Purim&#44; the<lb/> same occasion will be afforded us to thank our everlasting<lb/> Saviour.  As in the days of Mordecai and Esther we<lb/> shall enjoy in our borders the exhilarating air of liberty&#44;<lb/> &#34;light and gladness&#44; joy and honor.&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>Would it were so with our brethren throughout their habitations&#33;<lb/>  But.....what have I said&#63;  Many of our brethren&#44;<lb/> Alas&#33; th are denied a habitation.  In Russia&#44; a cruel<lb/> ukase drives them from the coasts to the interior&#44; from<lb/> cities to villages.  The front of the army is the dwelling<lb/> place of their youths.  The aged and the women are cast<lb/> out of their dismal hands.  The knout is applied<lb/> to their bleeding flesh&#59; but who pities a stiff&#45;necked<lb/> people&#44; who will persistently refuse to better their condition&#44;<lb/> by parting with their olden religion&#63;  Even the<lb/> representative of the most liberal of governments&#44; could<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>not find a word of reprobation for an autocracy under<lb/> which&#44; human beings&#45;&#45;though they be Jews&#45;&#45;are systemati&#45;<lb/>&#45;cally crushed&#63;  Their short&#45;comings were heralded abroad<lb/> to justify a barbarous treatment&#44; forgetting that those faults<lb/> are the legitimate results of a state of degradation&#59; of an<lb/> inhuman policy which of binds man in fetters&#44; and then<lb/> strikes him because he can will not&#44; forsooth&#44; employ his hands<lb/> in lofty occupations&#33;  And in Roumania&#44;<lb/> where can they who belong to our race&#44; find a home of security&#63;<lb/>  The remonstrances of a mighty Power in Europe did not alter<lb/> a little the restrictive laws&#44; over the maintenance of which<lb/> the jaundiced eye of prejudice constantly watches.  To let<lb/> their creed merge in that of the majority&#44; or submit<lb/> to proscription&#44; is the alternative offered to our brethren<lb/> in the dominions of Charles of Hohenzollern.  Yet&#44;<lb/> an advocate of&#45;&#45;so called&#45;&#45;reform in Judaism&#44; became<lb/> so enamoured with his own conceptions&#44; that he saw in<lb/> a flight of the imagination&#44; Israel seated everywhere under<lb/> their vines and fig&#45;trees&#44; with none to make them afraid.<lb/>  Absorbed in that vision&#44; he grew oblivious of melancholy<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>but real fast&#44; and with much emphasis declared that<lb/> our redemption from exile is to be prayed for nevermore&#44; for<lb/> it is not needed&#44; since &#34;religious persecution rests in<lb/> the tomb of the past.&#34;  Perhaps he drew his<lb/> inspiration from the glowing description of the state of<lb/> the Hebrews in Rome&#44; with which the correspondent of a<lb/> New York Journal&#44; recently regaled its readers.  For&#44; according<lb/> to it five thousand of our people&#44; owe the mitred King<lb/> a debt of infinite gratitude.  He who is infallible<lb/> and knows the inherent depravity of Jewish hearts&#44; has<lb/> vouchsafed to break down the gates bars that caged within<lb/> a narrow pale those guilty of deicide.  He even granted<lb/> to them the inestimable privilege of hawking their wares<lb/> outside of those contracted limits.  He likewise exempted<lb/> them from the duty of kneeling before images in the<lb/> shrine devoted to the man&#45;god&#44; and receiving a curse from<lb/> the mouth of a father.  And only at the time of the<lb/> coronation&#44; he requires their principal Rabbis to bear<lb/> silently a rebuke for their incredulity.  But that<lb/> veracious apologist of papal misrule&#44; who informs<lb/> the world that notwithstanding those invaluable boons&#44;<lb/> &#34;Israelites prefer to grow fat and rich in the ghetto&#44;&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>because they can there best &#40;he says&#41; perform the precepts of their<lb/> ancient religion&#44; that upholder of the holy See&#44; does<lb/> not assign the right cause for such a predilection.<lb/>
                He fails to acquaint t civilized mankind with this<lb/> fact&#44; but raging humanity&#59; beyond the filthy enclosure<lb/> by the side of the Tiber&#44; our brethren could not obtain<lb/> in the eternal city a dwelling wherein to live in safety.<lb/>  But why strive to prove the folly of defending priestly<lb/> tyranny&#44; when every stone in the desolates homes of<lb/> the Mortaras and the Coens&#44; cries vengeance <sic>againt</sic> that<lb/> Pontiff&#44; who now imperiously demands a universal assent<lb/> to his blasphemous <sic>pretentions</sic>&#63;  No&#44; my Brethren&#44;<lb/> persecution against our race is not dead&#44; not even in<lb/> that continent&#44; which justly claims a high degree of<lb/> enlightenment.  We are still a mark to contumely<lb/> and oppression.  Nevertheless&#44; the humblest abode<lb/> of the men of Israel&#44; will give evidence&#44; at this period&#44;<lb/> of the hilarity which Purim occasions.  They wh upon<lb/> whose heads lowering clouds continually descend&#44; rehearse<lb/> with pleasurable emotions the words with which their<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>sacred historian pictures the victory of righteousness<lb/> over wickedness.  &#34;The Jews had light and gladness&#44; joy<lb/> and honor&#34;.  For&#44; Our afflicted coreligionists believe<lb/> in the final triumph of truth.  They believe that those<lb/> who have borne the contempt of ages for the love of<lb/> God&#44; will be adjudged worthy of a miraculous deliverance.<lb/>  They believe in the divine promise that &#34;He who hath<lb/> scattered Israel&#44; will gather him again&#44; and keep him<lb/> as a shepherd doth his flock.&#34;  &#34;Noble beings&#63;<lb/>  &#34;We declare you this day&#44; our teachers&#44; our superiors.<lb/>  &#34;For&#44; by what actions did do we prove our indissoluble at&#45;<lb/>&#34;&#45;tachment to the faith of Abraham&#63;  We stand side<lb/> &#34;by side with the votaries of other confessions&#44; and dare<lb/> &#34;any one assail our persons by reason of our creed.  But<lb/> &#34;upon you a vial of vituperation is constantly poured<lb/> &#34;down.  The fanatics call you accursed.  The spoilers<lb/> &#34;seize upon your earnings.  A demoralized public<lb/> &#34;brands you as outlaws.  All this you have endured&#44;<lb/> &#34;not to forswear your allegiance to the One Eternal<lb/> &#34;Lord.&#34;  Israelites&#33;  Are you ashamed to<lb/> own national affinity with the martyrs of a sublime<lb/> cause&#63;............<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>You especially will I address O Bar Mitzv&#225;&#33;<lb/>  Do you imagine yourself higher before our Maker&#44;<lb/> because you saw first the light of day in free America&#63;<lb/>  For the sake of truth&#44; I trust you do not.  Dear brother&#33;<lb/>  That thought is the parent of apostacy.  Some who<lb/> have altogether abandoned our fold&#44; and others whose minds<lb/> are estranged from Judaism&#44; were led on at the outset&#44;<lb/> by an overweening opinion of their superiority over above<lb/> a despised race.  By a transition easily accounted for&#44;<lb/> their antipathy against their people&#44; was transferred<lb/> to the religion the latter profess.  And now they stand<lb/> perjured of the avowal which&#44; like yourself&#44; they<lb/> once made&#44; and open for the retribution of an<lb/> offended God.  I pray that their lot may not<lb/> be yours.  The example of parents&#44; whom material<lb/> for temporal prosperity never elated&#59; who have remained<lb/> attached to the path of their ancestors&#44; and who acknow&#45;<lb/>&#45;ledge&#44; by tokens of fraternal kindness&#44; their identity with<lb/> all the members of the Jewish family&#44; augurs well<lb/> for the future conduct of their son.  You will<lb/> not degenerate.  But since I am now<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>speaking mainly for your benefit&#44; I will draw your<lb/> attention to a somewhat singular ordinance recorded in the<lb/> portion&#44; which you have read before this congregation.<lb/>  It is the following.  &#34;Ye shall burn neither leaven<lb/> nor honey in any of the offerings of the Lord made by<lb/> fire&#34;.  Do you wish to learn thereason&#63;  Hear it.<lb/>  A proud heart is an abomination to the Lord.<lb/>  The two aforenamed substances blended with a farmacious<lb/> offering&#44; would have caused it quickly to raise and bubble&#44;<lb/> just as the idea of one&#39;s self&#45;importance when admitted<lb/> into the heart&#45;&#45;which was solely to be devoted to the service<lb/> of the Creator&#45;&#45;will make it swell and turn against<lb/> human creatures.  That command teaches you and us<lb/> a lesson of humility.  Let humility then distinguish<lb/> you from many whose riches render them insufferably<lb/> proud.  Enjoy parental wealth with gratitude<lb/> to its great Bestower.  Let your honest exertions<lb/> augment it.  Acquire learning&#44; that you may<lb/> comprehend the wonders of God in nature and in history.<lb/>  But should you even become most opulent and wise&#44;<lb/> remember your extraction&#44; and the duties attending it.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Be never too proud to confess that the least among your<lb/> brethren who suffers for conscience&#45;sake&#44; is a nobler being<lb/> than yourself surrounded by comforts and at your<lb/> ease.  Be ever ready to identify yourself with the<lb/> despised and oppressed of our race.  Have a tear for<lb/> their afflictions.  Rejoice at their release from trials.<lb/>  And when the propitious auspicious season of Purim<lb/> returns&#44; entreat the Almighty&#44; that&#44; like in the days<lb/> of Mordecai and Esther&#44; Israel may enjoy everywhere<lb/> &#34;light and gladness&#44; joy and honor.&#34;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
