<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF17_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1886-04" source="" attested="yes">April 1886</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff17_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff17_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff17_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff17_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff17_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff17_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff17_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff17_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff17_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff17_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff17_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff17_1_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>143</p>
            
            <p>On the death of Leopold Zunz<lb/>
                April 1886<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  Two Sabbaths ago&#44; the submarine<lb/> cable conveyed a news which was not startling<lb/> to the commercial or political world&#44; but which<lb/> must have occasioned a stir in the world of<lb/> letters.  For it announced the death of Leopold<lb/> Zunz&#45;&#45;the nonagenarian Jew to whom the creation<lb/> of a unique literature is confessedly due.  Had<lb/> I heard of the demise of that famous coreligionist<lb/> of ours&#44; early in the same morning&#44; before the service<lb/> at the synagogue began&#44; I might have ventured<lb/> some pertinent remarks&#44; necessarily brief&#44; but of<lb/> a eulogistic character&#44; such as the subject called<lb/> for&#44; although my annual pleading in behalf of<lb/> the Alliance was expected upon that day preceding Purim.<lb/>  Last sabbath I would not fittingly introduce that<lb/> topic.  I naturally felt prompted to confine<lb/> my address to the thirty fifth anniversary of<lb/> my having stood at this sacred desk.  But<lb/> I must not defer any longer a religious duty&#45;&#45;the duty<lb/> incumbent on the old in Israel to show the young<lb/> that we have a history to which we may point with<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>pride&#44; and that one of our brethren has<lb/> splendidly illustrated it&#59; that Zunz devoted his except&#45;<lb/>&#45;ional talents to the task of searching out and set&#45;<lb/>&#45;ting to view what sheds glory upon our people.<lb/>  The celebrated author who died recently in Berlin&#44;<lb/> wrote principally in German&#44; but parts of his<lb/> productions which have been rendered in other lan&#45;<lb/>&#45;guages&#44; and several articles issued from his prolific<lb/> pen in Hebrew&#44; have enabled me to form the<lb/> literary acquaintance of the venerable sage.  I<lb/> admire his marvellous industry&#44; which yielded<lb/> a masterly delineation of a literature vast and su&#45;<lb/>&#45;blime&#44; but which the prejudiced ignore&#44; and ignorance<lb/> despises.  For ages has the syna&#45;<lb/>&#45;gogue liturgy been recited&#44; devotionally by some&#44; me&#45;<lb/>&#45;chanically by others&#44; but neither the lip <sic>worshippers</sic><lb/> nor the pious understood the origin of many prayers<lb/> intended to lift up the soul to its Maker&#44; nor<lb/> the causes that elicited national elegies breathing<lb/> forth hatred against oppression.  Zunz revealed<lb/> what had been hidden&#59; his <sic>unrivalled</sic> powers imparted<lb/> to it life and beauty.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>So likewise&#44; all knew that immense volumes of<lb/> a legendary character exist&#44; besides instructive parables and<lb/> stories abounding in interspersed through the Talmud&#44; but no scholar<lb/> at the commencement of this century&#44; had attempt&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed the herculean almost superhuman task to make those writings tell disclose<lb/> the places of their nativity&#44; their ages and their<lb/> authorship.  Zunz&#44; the giant of intellect assumed<lb/> that undertaking soon crowned with marvellous success.  Again&#58;<lb/> of all medieval Rabbis&#44; Rashi is perhaps the<lb/> most familiar name to Israelites&#44; even they<lb/> never he read a line of his extension comments&#44; but<lb/> who could tell with accuracy what the disciples<lb/> of that Prince of the Judaic French school brought<lb/> forth&#63;  Zunz summoned to his aid untiring ener&#45;<lb/>&#45;gy and a deep mighty love for our ancient lore literature&#44; and<lb/> dived into depths that none had sounded before.<lb/>  His luminous mind saw precious gems where benighted<lb/> arrogance supposed there would be naught but<lb/> worthless pebbles.  When the man of Berlin gave <lb/>us his &#34;something about Rabbinical literature lore&#34; he laid<lb/> out a treasure of learning at which his contemporaries<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>looked in wonderment.  But when the<lb/> history of the Synagogue&#44; the liturgy of the Syna&#45;<lb/>&#45;gogue&#44; and the poetry of the Synagogue were<lb/> unfolded with a wealth of erudition simply ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;haustless&#44; professors in high seats of European<lb/> universities&#44; arose to hail the creator of a new liter&#45;<lb/>&#45;ature.  Men who speak the language that the<lb/> famous nonagenarian enriched&#44; pay homage to that<lb/> creative genius.  They invoke it in their dedicatory<lb/> addresses&#44; in books&#44; in pamphlets&#44; in essays in&#45;<lb/>&#45;scribed to the name of Zunz.  But it is no<lb/> light honor to the German&#44; that the world&#45;renowned<lb/> Italian Hebraist&#45;&#45;Samuel David Luzzatto&#45;&#45;sang<lb/> in verses the glories of his senior contemporary&#44; of one<lb/> he gracefully called&#44; a <sic>jewelled</sic> diadem that adorns<lb/> the chosen race.  Sterling merits mirrored<lb/> in one another&#44; and recognizing each other&#39;s greatness&#33;<lb/></p>  
            <p>But has any among my audience perused por&#45;<lb/>tions of Zunz&#39;s &#34;Hebrew characteristics&#34; in English&#44; defective as the translation obviously is&#63;  The mo&#45;<lb/>&#45;rality of Rabbis who lived in the middle ages is<lb/> made to shine more resplendently by a contrast<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>with the brutality&#44; debauchery&#44; bigotry and<lb/> dishonesty of the would be champions of Christianity&#45;&#45;<lb/> with reprobate crusaders who turned Europe and<lb/> Western Asia into a charnel house&#44; where innocent<lb/> Jews lay murdered&#59; with depraved knight&#45;templars&#44;<lb/> whose villainy makes chastity veil her face.<lb/>  I feel always sad when I hear my people speak<lb/> contemptuously of the Rabbis&#44; as if our olden teachers<lb/> were the impersonation of superstition and narrow<lb/> prejudice.  I am pained because I detect Hebrew<lb/> illiteracy.  I read of a man like Asher Ben Je&#45;<lb/>&#45;chiel&#44; who in the fourteenth century fled from<lb/> Germany to Spain by reason of insufferable perse&#45;<lb/>&#45;cution&#44; still bidding his children in his last will<lb/> and testament never to speak ill blacken the characters of their neighbors&#44;<lb/> never to mock or revile a human being&#44; nor raise<lb/> the hand to strike even an offender&#44; and before<lb/> the meek German Rabbi had so enjoined upon<lb/> his offspring&#44; the French Moses of Concy had<lb/> told his brethren&#44;&#45;&#45;while Christians repudiated their<lb/> debts to the Jews&#45;&#45;never to dare deceive any persons<lb/> be they of whatever religion and race&#59; and earlier<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>still Judah Ben Samuel&#44; styled Chasid&#45;&#45;the<lb/> pious&#45;&#45;ordered that if a contract be entered into<lb/> between a Jew and a non&#45;Israelite&#44; though the latter<lb/> fail to perform his part&#44; the former must carry<lb/> out that about which he has pledged his sacred honor.<lb/>  Leopold Zunz with that keen satire which he could<lb/> use most effectively says&#58; that the Jews of the<lb/> middle ages &#34;children of the devil&#44;&#34; as they were called&#44;<lb/> stood immeasurably higher than their fill persecutors and<lb/> of leaders in the Church&#44; noted only for their idleness<lb/> and gluttony&#44; for the stupidity into which they were<lb/> stuped.  Competent judges have credited<lb/> Zunz into with a force of diction unsurpassed.  But the<lb/> sage of Berlin whose object was the vindication<lb/> of Israel&#44; did not rest on the laurels he had even<lb/> by his productions in a classical German style.<lb/>  He studied foreign languages in the pursuit of his<lb/> noble scheme.  Knowing that the archives of<lb/> Hebrew congregations in the peninsula between the<lb/> Alps and the Appenines&#44; contained documents that<lb/> cast a flood of light on the life of our people&#44; he<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>studied Italian and searched out Italian<lb/> libraries&#44; and Italian chronicles.  Thus was<lb/> he enabled to produce his &#34;history of the Jews<lb/> in Sicily&#44;&#34; a volume penned with that thorough&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness which signalize mark out all the works of Zunz.<lb/>  Its contents are&#44; as might be anticipated&#44; a nar&#45;<lb/>&#45;rative of spoliation&#44; suffering and banishment.<lb/>  Zunz wrote it in German&#44; but his admirer&#44; Peter<lb/> Perreau&#44;&#45;&#45;a catholic prelate&#44; royal librarian at Parma&#44;<lb/> whose exertions in our behalf of our literature are a<lb/> reproach to Jews&#45;&#45;has rendered made a version of the<lb/> book into faultless Italian&#44; enriching it with a number<lb/> of annotations.  But long before the product&#45;<lb/>&#45;ion of the illustrious Jew of Berlin attracted my notice<lb/> by translations in part or in their <sic>entirity</sic>&#44; I had<lb/> opportunities to form some conceptions of his almost<lb/> illimitable erudition.  His contributions to an<lb/> invaluable periodical&#44; published years ago in Hebrew<lb/> in the interest of the sacred language and of Jewish science&#44;<lb/> afforded me those means.  One article on Rabbi<lb/> Azariah De Rossi of the sixteenth century&#45;&#45;the father<lb/> of modern Talmudical criticism&#45;&#45;would have sufficed<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>to give the writer fame&#44; but Zunz brought the vast<lb/> range of his scholarship to bear also on a discussion carried<lb/> on in the Hebrew language about the birth place of<lb/> Kalir&#45;&#45;a prolific author of poems writer synagogoical poet&#44; whose effusions forming no insi&#45;<lb/>&#45;gnificant part of the Ashkenazic ritual.<lb/></p>
            <p>To me individually&#44; a most acceptable feature in the<lb/> character of Leopold Zunz is the stand he took regarding<lb/> the nascent &#34;Reform&#34; of Judaic Germany.  He had<lb/> favored the novel idea&#44; and&#44; I regret to add&#44; had en&#45;<lb/>&#45;couraged it by writings damaging to our national<lb/> traditions&#44; but his far&#45;sighted sagacity was not<lb/> long to discover that German Reform led to meant unbelief<lb/> and led to apostacy.  The soul of the immortal Zunz<lb/> shrunk back in horror.  Mosaism was to<lb/> have been converted into nihilism&#44; or&#44; at best&#44; into<lb/> a hypocritical compromise with the popular creed<lb/> for temporal gains.  Zunz cut loose of the association<lb/> of the worldly&#44; and returned to the path of enlightened<lb/> conservatism.  There posterity will search for the great<lb/> nonagenarian.  In the pantheon of celebrities&#44; raised to<lb/> the memory of distinguished Jewish authors of the nineteenth<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>century&#44; future generations will see foremost<lb/> and admire the hoary headed Leopold Zunz.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
