<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF1_18</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1893-01" source="" attested="yes">1893</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_17_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_17_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_17_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_17_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_17_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_17_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_17_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_17_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_17_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_17_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_17_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_17_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>For Ki Tav&#243;t<lb/>
                About Bikkurim &#38; a<lb/>
                Bar Mitzvah<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Last winter a year&#44; in the course of a series of talks given upon<lb/> the Hebrew ritual&#44; which I gave before the Mickv&#232; Israel<lb/> literary association&#44; I incidentally referred to the section<lb/> of the Law that was read this morning.  I said&#44; that&#44;<lb/> according to tradition&#44; there were certain instances in<lb/> which in which benedictions&#44; confessions and prayers must<lb/> have been read only in the sacred language&#44; just as<lb/> recorded in the five books of Moses.  One of those instances is<lb/> chronicled in our Parasha.  The Oral code&#44; or Mishnah&#44;<lb/> has left an interesting account of the occasion on which&#44;<lb/> our forefathers&#45;&#45;the happy owners of the a soil made fruit&#45;<lb/>&#45;ful by an industrious cultivation&#45;&#45;publicly acknowledged<lb/> God&#39;s benefactions&#44; by offering the first ripe fruits of<lb/> their ground.  Let me relate the narrative.<lb/></p>
            <p>A number of representatives of different various cli cities&#44; met<lb/> at a place previously agreed upon&#44; near Jerusalem.  In the morn&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing&#44; when about to they started for the capital of Judea&#44; the ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;pointed chief&#44; who acted as a guide&#44; cried aloud&#58; &#34;Rise<lb/> and let us go up to Zion&#44; to the house of the Lord<lb/> our God.&#34;  At that call&#44; the company moved slowly<lb/> on&#44; rehearsing in concert David&#39;s psalmody.  Entering<lb/> the metropolis&#44; they glowingly sung out&#58; &#34;Our feet are standing<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>within thy gates&#44; O Jerusalem&#33;  Jerusalem compactly built&#44;<lb/> as if another city had been joined to it.  For&#44; there tribes go up&#44;<lb/> even the tribes of God&#44; as a statute for Israel&#44; that they<lb/> may thank the name of the Lord.&#34;  Men of wealth<lb/> would present lay their fruits in baskets of golden or silver&#59; baskets&#44; others<lb/> in baskets artistically made of willow.  The horns of<lb/> the animals carrying on their backs the votive offerings<lb/> were guilded.  Round their head wreaths of olive branches<lb/> were entwined.  At the sound of drums the multitude<lb/> proceeded went forth&#44; greeted everywhere by peasants and journey&#45;<lb/>&#45;men&#44; and by mechanics that abounded in Jerusalem.<lb/>  Now&#44; mount Moriah&#44; on whose summit the Temple raised<lb/> its spires turrets&#44; is reached.  There At that sight even of a King resides would lift up his bas&#45;<lb/>&#45;ket on his shoulder and says with fervor chant&#58; &#34;Hallelujah&#44; O praise ye<lb/> God in His sanctuary&#59; let every living being praise God&#34;<lb/> Having entered the porch of the Temple&#44; the Levites&#45;&#45;<lb/> the choristers charged by the Divine Legislator to attune<lb/> their voices to sacred hymns as chosen the appointed choristers and players struck the harp and the<lb/> cymbal and in behalf of the nation sung&#58; &#34;I will<lb/> extol Thee&#44; O Lord&#33; for Thou hast raised me up&#44; and<lb/> rost payt hast not suffered my enemies to rejoice over me.&#34;<lb/>  Soon That completed the officiating priests placed their hands under<lb/> the hands of the Israelites&#44; who offered the product<lb/> of their soil&#44; waving the basket to and fro&#44; while<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>the person who had brought presented the votive choice fruits&#44; read in<lb/> Hebrew what our Bar Mitzvah was privileged to repeat.<lb/>  You must have noticed&#44; my brethren&#44; that the confession&#44;<lb/> which&#44; according to traditions must have been said in Hebrew&#44; the holy language<lb/> is not such as national or&#44; racial pride&#45;&#45;as now a days called&#45;&#45;<lb/> would elicit.  How different with peoples of antiquity&#33;  They boasted of the very highest<lb/> origin imaginable&#44; or unimaginable.  Many pointed to an extraction supernatural to a<lb/> descant from the very deities but they adored.  A weakness which has extended much further for not only nations and tribes indulged<lb/> in that vanity&#44; individuals also would wish to make us believe<lb/> that they have issued from a stock signally excelling in nobility&#44; as if that by itself should insure universal respect.  I know<lb/> of some who resented as an unpardonable offence the mere<lb/> intimation that they had sprung from a humble parentage.<lb/>  Mark then well what the rich professor of fields and<lb/> vineyards&#59; the opulent farmer&#44; confessed before God.  &#34;My father was a Syrian ready<lb/> to perish&#59;&#34; that is&#44; Jacob from whom the twelve tribes proceeded<lb/> left his parental house to roam abroad and earn in Aram a livelihood by the<lb/> work of his hands.  He grew slowly at first in number and riches wealth<lb/> and when he became larger his progeny grew more affluently and stronger&#44; he was enslaved&#44; reviled<lb/> and scourged.  He might have been altogether lost by rea&#45;<lb/>&#45;son of a crushing oppression&#44; had not a compassionate Lord<lb/> torn off the yoke and brought the seed of Jacob Israel to safety.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Say&#44; my Brethren&#44; was there any disgrace in that admis&#45;<lb/>&#45;sion of a lowly beginning&#63;  None&#44; in the least your thinking minds will immediately answer.  Nay&#44; it was you will recognize it as most honorable&#44; because<lb/> it called forth expressions of gratitude to the Most High&#44;<lb/> who uplifts the lowly that they may acquire nobility&#44;<lb/> worthy of a on which righteousness prides itself&#45;&#45;the nobility of character.<lb/>  Mark again&#44; how sublime in its closing sentence the portion perused by our young<lb/> brother. in its closing sentence  The religion of Moses&#44;<lb/> which is the religion of reason and the religion of human<lb/> kindness&#44; invites the wealthy owner of oxen and sheep<lb/> and gardens and orchards&#44; to rejoice because of all the<lb/> good which the Lord has vouchsafed to bestow.  But<lb/> how was he to rejoice&#63;  By storing every thing away that<lb/> he had gathered&#63;  By looking for the opportunity when<lb/> he may might sell to the greatest advantage&#44; even if he fattened<lb/> on the flesh of creatures who have been reduced to penury&#63;<lb/>  You have heard the sentence from the lips of the lad whom we welcome<lb/> as a fellow congregant.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Thou shalt rejoice in all the good that the<lb/> Lord thy God has given unto thee and to thy household&#44; thou and<lb/> the Levite and the stranger that is in the midst of<lb/> thee.&#34;  To enjoy wealth then means&#44; in the language<lb/> of the Hebrew scriptures&#44; to share it the Lord&#39;s benefactions with those<lb/> who do not possess it the organs to gain riches&#59; such as the Levites of old&#44; who<lb/> had no portion in the land&#44; depending on the votive offerings of the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>faithful&#44; in compensation of for their officiating at the Temple&#44;<lb/> and teaching the Law of God to multitudes&#59; such were<lb/> also the strangers&#44; who did not own a land&#44; but for whom<lb/> the Pentateuch demanded that they be treated with the greatest<lb/> consideration as it often repeats&#58; &#34;Ye shall love the stranger for strangers ye were in the land of Egypt.&#34;  My Dear Bar Mitzvah.  What you have<lb/> read for our edification&#44; is the teaching of the religion&#44; which<lb/> will acknowledge you form this day a member qualified<lb/> to form a quorum for the services&#44; publicly rendered in the house<lb/> of God.  Here your own father stood to make pronounce declare his<lb/> allegiance to the Torah&#44; when at the age which you have<lb/> just attained.  Here your father&#39;s father stood&#44; repre&#45;<lb/>&#45;senting at a stage of this congregation&#39;s in history its temporal government interests&#44; and<lb/> here&#44; I hope&#44; you will continue to worship the One Eter&#45;<lb/>&#45;nal God.  for that I make supplication.  I eagerly<lb/> wish desire that you may remain attached to the venerable<lb/> Mickv&#233; Israel in spirit&#44; as well as personally.  Ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;preciate your descent from the tribe to which you belong.<lb/>  It is honorable&#44; because tradition relates that Aaron gloried<lb/> in serving God by serving His creatures.  The books of our<lb/> post Biblical literature state that the first High Priest<lb/> consecrated to the service of the Lord&#44; found delight in promoting peace.  He would call to his<lb/> aid for that blissful purpose&#44; exhortations&#44; gentle coun&#45;<lb/>&#45;sel&#44; entreaties&#44; all means arts of fine persuasion in order to restore <sic>tranquillity</sic> among families&#44; to bring the<lb/> hearts of children closer to the hearts of their parents&#44; to<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>endear ever to one another those who were fed at<lb/> the same parental table&#44; cared and cared for and provided for for by<lb/> the same father and mother earthly guardians of our childhood and youth.  May you follow<lb/> in that respect the footsteps of the first Cohen.<lb/>  Both the Scriptures and the Talmud regard you the Cohen with<lb/> special value&#44; as the conservators of the Torah in various<lb/> stages periods of our history.  Therefore certain prerogatives have<lb/> been granted to the Cohen&#44; one of which you exercised<lb/> this morning&#44; when you ascended this sacred desk and perused for us a portion most fittingly applyc applicable.<lb/>  Let this day be then a mile stone in your life&#44; at which<lb/> you will retrospectively look&#44; and keep in the path<lb/> of traditional Judaism.  This day&#44; on which your<lb/> best of friends&#44; your father and mother are doubtless glad&#45;<lb/>&#45;dened because you have been spared to them&#44; endeavour try to heighten<lb/> their joyfulness by the assurance that you will grow<lb/> from a manly boy to a man irreproachably good&#44; un&#45;<lb/>&#45;swervedly true.  May the knowledge which you will<lb/> acquire hereafter widen your intellect&#44; but also soften your<lb/> feelings&#44; and let me give offer you the assurance of my<lb/> sincere wishes for your happiness here until a very<lb/> old age shall have justified the anticipations the<lb/> formed by your relations and friends on the Sabbath Ki Tabot of<lb/> of the year 5654 of the world&#39;s creation.  creation 5654 of the<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
