<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF2_16</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1881" source="" attested="yes">1881</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_16_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_16_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_16_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_16_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_16_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_16_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_16_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_16_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_16_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_16_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_16_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_16_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>On the 21st anniversary<lb/>
                of<lb/>
                The Seventh St Synagogue.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  Twenty one years are said to be the<lb/> legal time&#44; when a youth may carry one a business&#44;<lb/> and receive the recognition of the courts to his transactions.<lb/>  Why only just then&#44; I am unable to tell&#44; for<lb/> there are&#44; undoubtedly&#44; young men under that age<lb/> reliable for the possession of clear judgment and foresight&#44; while a<lb/> great number who have gone far beyond those years that period those years<lb/> are unfit to be trusted&#44; for the lack of discretion and<lb/> steadiness.  Among the ancient Hebrews&#44; the period<lb/> of manhood was reached earlier.  Possibly&#44; because in the<lb/> country inhabited by our ancestors&#44; body and mind develop&#45;<lb/>&#45;ped faster.  At all events&#44; its clear evident that an American youth<lb/> on attaining his twenty first year&#44; must try to gain<lb/> the confidence of society by showing himself in the<lb/> light which he is looked upon by the laws of his coun&#45;<lb/>&#45;try.  He must leave behind what is of uncertain<lb/> benefit&#44; and determine on a course of life useful and honor&#45;<lb/>&#45;able.  The days of wavering must come to an end.  A<lb/> resolution to definitely choose a way and pursue it undeter&#45;<lb/>&#45;red by obstacles ought to be taken.  &#34;<sic>Proscratination</sic> is the<lb/> thief of time&#34; says a proverb&#44; but procrastination may prove worse<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>It may become a destroyer&#44; steal the spirit life giving spirit&#44; bringing shame with<lb/> losses.  The want of provisions for a long future leads&#44;<lb/> not infrequently&#44; to crooked and ruinous paths.<lb/>  Now&#44; my brethren&#44; what a sense of right dictates res&#45;<lb/>&#45;pecting single individuals&#44; honesty demands also<lb/> of corporate bodies.  These must always stand on<lb/> a solid basis.  Infancy and adolescence are unmeaning<lb/> words with regard to them.  But Still when twenty one<lb/> years have passed over their heads&#44; they must surely<lb/> be set on broad foundations&#44; so as never to risk meeting<lb/> with a downfall.  My hearers can easily ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;ply the lesson.  I have announced this Sabbath<lb/> the month from which we may date the attain&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing of our Synagogue&#39;s &#34;majority.&#34;  A Understand<lb/> well.  Bricks and mortar have no life.  Even the<lb/> ark and the deposited scrolls laid therein&#44; and to which we bow&#44; are<lb/> inanimate objects with no inherent spirit&#59; mere wood and parchment of<lb/> little value.  But the idea <sic>inseperable</sic> from them<lb/> makes renders them most holy.  The very walls and windows<lb/> and benches acquire a high degree of sanctity by<lb/> the association of that idea.  I enter&#44; and remember that this is a place&#44; where<lb/> a number of persons&#44; believing that Judaism is worth<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>preserving&#44; assemble to express their convictions in<lb/> ancient prayers and psalmody&#59; where they listen<lb/> to teachings which aim to confirm the truths given<lb/> to Israel&#39;s safe&#45;keeping.  Only a meeting room<lb/> it is&#59; yet the a beseeming palace for the King of the<lb/> universe&#59; a meeting room&#44; still encircled surrounded with a halo&#44; because there allegiance<lb/> to Monotheism&#44; to the revealed Law and its verities is<lb/> constantly renewed&#59; because there&#44; are the traditions of<lb/> the fathers jealously guarded against obliteration.<lb/>  You men women and children of my people form the<lb/> Synagogue&#59; or rather the sentiments which I must<lb/> suppose&#44;&#45;&#45;unless you deceive me&#44; yourselves and your God&#45;&#45;<lb/> to pervade your hearts&#44; constitute you a corporation uni&#45;<lb/>&#45;ted for a specific purpose.  Call this &#34;orthodoxy&#44;&#34;<lb/> &#34;conservatism&#44;&#34; &#34;historical Judaism&#44;&#34; I care little for<lb/> names&#44; provided that the sentiments do exist.  I mean<lb/> the aspiration to remain&#44; if needful&#44; the only defying prot pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;test against a novel system&#44; pretentious in its ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;pellation&#44; but destructive in its results&#59; a system<lb/> which has created divisions among the coheirs of the same<lb/> heritage&#44; after its having given the lie to Moses &#38; the prophets<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Well&#58; you have seen the twenty first anniversary of<lb/> your first entrance here&#44; on &#34;the majority&#34; of this Syna custodian<lb/> &#45;gogue of the Torah as interpreted handed down by the Ages.  How do you design providing for the future&#44;<lb/> to prevent destitution and disgrace&#63;  I have a telling<lb/> register book in my possession.  Its stories are of a sombre<lb/> character&#59; but they mark out facts with lines which can&#45;<lb/>&#45;not be mistaken misapprehended.  I have consulted it that register book very lately&#44; and<lb/> found that this account chronicled therein.  During the period now closing I have accom&#45;<lb/>&#45;panied to their graves more than one hundred contributors to our corpo&#45;<lb/>&#45;rate preservation&#44; irrespectively of members of their families<lb/> and of a quantity of strangers.  Admit&#58; we have gained meanwhile<lb/> many whose coming in our midst has benefitted our cause&#44;<lb/> but the accession has in no degree counterbalanced the<lb/> loss.  I let you infer what the issue must<lb/> naturally be when another score of years shall have<lb/> rolled away&#44; unless you begin now at once to devise means<lb/> which will rear again this religious body in strength and<lb/> energetic activity.  The time for putting off and wa&#45;<lb/>&#45;vering must cease.  When you perceive that the children<lb/> of those men who are prided themselves on belonging to this congregation<lb/> keep insultingly aloof&#44; you must supply the places left vacant&#44; with<lb/> Israelites who have not learnt yet to despise what<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>their parents considered an honor privilege.<lb/>  I disclaim the knowledge of administration managing public affairs.  I have no<lb/> abilities talents whatever in that line&#44; and hence I have in&#45;<lb/>&#45;variably declined an office in any association requiring<lb/> administrative abilities&#44; but it strikes me that every one<lb/> having a p share in the government of a corporation&#44; ought<lb/> to devote hours of thoughts to a study of its improvement.<lb/>  He ought to take up the apostleship&#44; as it were&#44; of<lb/> the cause&#44; and plead it before his friends and acquaint&#45;<lb/>&#45;ances.  And every Jew who sincerely loves his religion one elector who deems it an honor to be an elector because<lb/> and he acknowledges this Synagogue as its the best interpreter of his religion&#44;<lb/> ought to speak abroad in its behalf abroad and procure for it<lb/> new seat&#45;holders and members&#44; even if it involved a necessity<lb/> of furnishing the new comers with the ritual books&#44; specially<lb/> for the Fall holidays.  All who hold occupy a position war&#45;<lb/>&#45;ranting the suppo belief surmise that they are interested in the<lb/> principle carried out here&#44; ought to see that none of its followers desert it&#44; that without a shadow of exaction&#44; the humblest<lb/> among the attendants is encouraged to give his or her<lb/> mite&#59; that the smallest coin is thankfully received and thankfully ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;propriated to the support of that principle.  I mighty say<lb/> much more and pertinently but it is a point so open to misconstructions&#44; that<lb/> I am forcibly compelled to refrain from speaking with the boldness<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>which the urgent importance of the subject case demands.<lb/></p>  
            <p>One thought&#44; however&#44; I cannot withhold.  The standing<lb/> of this Congregation shall not be lowered with my expressed<lb/> or tacit consent.  It has pleased journalists this to call our religious<lb/> body &#34;stupid&#59;&#34; to describe it as waning in influence&#44; and<lb/> decaying in power&#44; but if it has allowed inertness to injure unhappily allowed its interests to be insured no paper shall record its undignified humiliation<lb/> demeanour by its inertness no American Hebrew shall relate that it has<lb/> gone begging from hucksters and fruiterers to save itself from<lb/> bankruptcy.  No g disguised gambling and no open flirting<lb/> shall be charged entrusted with the liquidation of its debts.  If those<lb/> whom God has endowed with the means to come to the rescue&#44;<lb/> cannot be stirred up to action by the example of the self<lb/> denial exercised by such as have willingly made sacri&#45;<lb/>fices to raise high the standard of conservatism&#44; if pe&#45;<lb/>&#45;nurisousness and indifference have determined upon the<lb/> dissolution of this corporation&#44; let us we shall fall with the proud<lb/> thought that the Mikv&#233; Israel Congregation has not<lb/> falsified its past history&#44; nor compromised its dignity and shamed the memory<lb/> of its founders.  This building will be surrendered to whom<lb/> it virtually now belongs&#44; and a room where ten shall gather<lb/> in the name of the Lord will be have equally sanctity sanctity.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>I certainly do not contemplate that issue with satis&#45;<lb/>&#45;faction.  I would most deeply lament it&#44; because I feel<lb/> that our sinking into a state of obscurity may lend ad&#45;<lb/>&#45;ditional light glitter to Reform.  When a congregation respected<lb/> for its age&#44; the talents and social position of its mem&#45;<lb/>&#45;bers shall dwindle down into a knot of <sic>worshippers</sic> at in some by&#45;<lb/>&#45;way&#44; Orthodoxy conservatism will become very nigh extinguished in Ame&#45;<lb/>&#45;rica.  German or English will supplant everywhere<lb/> supplant the Hebrew&#59; gentile singing will silence a prayful<lb/> multitude&#44; the advocacy of a rejection of Mosaic<lb/> institutions will be strenuous and pertinacious to an ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;tent as to expose to public scorn whosoever prays in the<lb/> language of the Scriptures&#44; or follows the prescriptions tenets ordinances of the<lb/> Levitical ceremonial code.  Already the impossibility of reconci&#45;<lb/>&#45;ling pure orthodoxy with &#34;the spirit of the time&#34; is predi&#45;<lb/>&#45;cated on events drawn on the imagination.  They the coming of an event anticipated by fancy.  That event will not<lb/> come to pass&#44; but the decay dismemberment of this religious body may hap&#45;<lb/>&#45;pen.  And it depends upon each of us to aver the sad fate.<lb/>  It largely depends on the abnegation of which every one of<lb/> us is capable&#44; not for the sake of a man or of an edifice&#44; but<lb/> for that of a lofty idea&#44; whether our posterity shall see the vigorous<lb/> and prosperous growth of this synagogue&#44; or its extinction.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Deliver it O Lord from a threatening danger.  Incline<lb/> towards it the hearts of Philadelphia Israelites.<lb/>  Many are they who have been hitherto been derelict in<lb/> their duty&#59; many who have failed to make a slight<lb/> return unto Thee for the bounties by the support of the worship of Thy Unity.<lb/>  May they be sought after&#44; and enlisted among the<lb/> defenders of the truths which Thou hast committed to<lb/> Israel&#39;s guardianship.  Cause also a spirit of<lb/> generosity to stir among those our congregants who enjoy the fruits of<lb/> Thy blessings in the store and in the field&#44; and their acts of<lb/> piety will honor Thee&#44; and eternize their names.  May<lb/> they remember&#44; before the hour of their departure&#44; the needs<lb/> of the house dedicated to Thy service on earth&#44; and Thou&#44;<lb/> in Thy abundant mercy&#44; wilt prepare for them as shelter<lb/> in Thy dwelling&#45;place in the heaven of heavens.  Oh<lb/> may righteousness flourish in our days&#44; and its attendants<lb/> be as foretold by Thy prophet&#44; peace&#44; security and<lb/> ease.  So that Then this Synagogue&#44; now completing its<lb/> twenty first birth day may will live in the fruition of a con&#45; purely<lb/> servative traditional Judaism unto the end of time.  Amen. as taught by thy chosen servants&#44; until the messenger&#44; announcing<lb/> the salvation of the dispersed of Judah shall be heard in on mount Zion.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
