<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF9_6</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1890-11" source="" attested="yes">November 1890</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_6_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_6_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_6_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_6_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_6_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_6_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_6_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_6_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_6_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_6_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_6_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_6_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>7 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. Fifth St.<lb/></p>
            <p>Philadelphia&#44; Nov&#47;90<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>USC<lb/></p>
            
            <p>A few words<lb/>
                For thanksgiving day<lb/>
                at the Adath Jeshurun Syn.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Brethren.<lb/></p>
            <p>The announcement in a Jewish and a secular<lb/> paper was faulty&#59; but if it has misled any&#44; I am guiltless.<lb/>  I do chant all Hebrew prayers in the Synagogue&#44; where<lb/> I officiate as Hazan&#44; or Cantor&#44; but my proposition in the<lb/> present occasion to your minister was&#44; that I should address a few words<lb/> in the vernacular to the audience of in this synagogue&#44; and<lb/> close with an invocation in the same language.  Let me<lb/> hope that this explanation will set me right before<lb/> my hearers.<lb/></p>
            <p>Friends.  There has been a time&#44; in which a sacred convocation<lb/> nationally held&#44; disconnected with denominationalism&#44;<lb/> awakened in my heart glowing enthusiasm.  I would then<lb/> call to my aid the best words at my I could command to stir up in others<lb/> the love I cherish for the Union created by the victorious<lb/> arms of Washington and given permanence by the far&#45;<lb/>sighted wisdom of Jefferson.  Years have&#44; how&#45;<lb/>&#45;ever&#44; wrought a change&#44; not in my sentiments of<lb/> grateful admiration for the asylum of the oppressed&#44;<lb/> but in the ideas I have formed touching the advisability<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>of withdrawing a large vast population from its usual<lb/> pursuits on a day which religion has not hallowed.<lb/>  A stroll round our thoroughfares will obviously show<lb/> the reason for my having become less eager in the<lb/> observance of the annual occasion that has brought<lb/> us together.  Aside from the disputed right of the<lb/> state to step in where the Church alone should tread&#44;<lb/> I fear that the working man&#39;s wages be consumed<lb/> by hours of enforced idleness.  I do not malign<lb/> Americans by asserting that the number of those laborers<lb/> who are lured to seats the seductive halls of insobriety&#44; exceeds&#44; in com&#45;<lb/>&#45;parison&#44; that which is drawn just now to the shrines<lb/> of devotion.  Nevertheless&#44; since my personal<lb/> views will not carry any weight either towards abo&#45;<lb/>&#45;lishing the day&#44; or preventing multitudes from<lb/> using it injuriously&#44; I consider deem it appropriate to<lb/> heed the counsel of the President of our Republic.<lb/>  It is contained in the closing sentence of his concisely<lb/> written proclamation.  It reads so&#58; &#34;Let us en&#45;<lb/>&#45;deavour to merit the promised recompense of<lb/> charity and the gracious acceptance of our praises.&#34;<lb/>  I agree that we may render the occasion blissful<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>to ourselves and pleasing in the sight of our Maker.<lb/>  Privileged Allowed thus publicly to speak to brethren<lb/> not immediately under my stewardship&#44; I seize<lb/> the opportunity to commend to their kind consideration a work attended with<lb/> Divine reward.  It is charity&#59; but not simply the feeding<lb/> of the hungry&#44; the clothing of the naked&#44; and the shelt&#45;<lb/>&#45;ering of the homeless&#45;&#45;highly meritorious acts&#44; still<lb/> wrongfully interpreted as the limits bounds set to human<lb/> benefaction.  A noble spirited Israelite&#44; whose<lb/> startling death recently thrilled a whole community&#44;<lb/> taught you more effectively than my exhortations any utterance of mine could<lb/> tell teach&#44; that the quality of mercy is not narrow but<lb/> illimitably wide.  I am assured by the reflected<lb/> occupant of this pulpit&#44; that not content with<lb/> having placed a deserving institution on a firmer<lb/> basis by his own tireless exertions&#44; he your lamented fellow&#45;congregant felt disposed<lb/> to generously encourage the promotion of another<lb/> charity&#44; most sublime.  It is not to challenge<lb/> invidious comparisons that I call a school of industry<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>&#34;a charity most sublime.&#34;  Heartily interested as I have<lb/> been form their very incipiency in our city organizations tend&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing to the welfare of my Hebrew brethren&#44; I give ne&#45;<lb/>&#45;vertheless the palm to such as inspire self&#45;dependence&#44;<lb/> innoble handicraft&#44; and raise our social standing<lb/> to a higher plane.  I plead in your presence&#44; my friends&#44; for the building<lb/> which ought long ago to have arisen aloft where our<lb/> young of foreign birth essentially need it.  From thence they may learn<lb/> the language&#44; the manners&#44; the history of this country<lb/> of their deliverance&#44; to learn the controlling princi&#45;<lb/>&#45;ples which have made it strong and prosperous.<lb/>  The comprehensive building&#44; where the skilled artisan with hammer and<lb/> chisel will shame into extinction&#44; the peddler&#39;s<lb/> bundle and his basket&#59; the building where practical<lb/> tuition will keep pace with a sensibly imparted<lb/> knowledge of the spirit of our faith&#44; is that which the de&#45;<lb/>&#45;ceased whose memory you wish to honor had resolved to<lb/> a benefit.  Let the wealthy in your midst&#44; supply<lb/> the vacancy which a universally bewailed departure has<lb/> made created in your religious body.  Let a well combined support speed the erect&#45;<lb/>&#45;ion of the Temple consecrated to industry&#44; liberal do&#45;<lb/>&#45;nations give it stability.  The privilege you<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>have granted that I should address you from<lb/> this pulpit will have been then to a splendid purpose&#59; and I shall<lb/> rejoice and our thanksgiving day will have become the herald<lb/> of progress&#44; the harbinger of a moral exaltation.<lb/></p>
            
            <p>Universal Father&#33;  Thou openest Thy hand&#44; and<lb/> all living gather the abundance of Thy goodness.<lb/>  But unto us&#44; the dwellers of a land of freedom&#44; Thou<lb/> hast shown this year Thy benign Residence by signal favors.  Thou has brought<lb/> us out unhurt from a crucial trial.  Thou didst<lb/> not suffer party passions to kindle strife.  Law&#45;abiding<lb/> millions accepted the issue of the contest&#44; because Thou<lb/> madest didst command Peace to guard our walls&#44; <sic>tranquillity</sic> our homes.<lb/>  May those sweet messengers of Thy will never depart<lb/> from America&#59; that she may will continue then to offer<lb/> the oppressed rest&#44; the diligent success&#44; the ho&#45;<lb/>&#45;nest honors and preferments.  And vouchsafe&#44;<lb/> O Lord&#33; to hasten the time when the rule of wick&#45;<lb/>&#45;edness shall be broken&#44; and the reign of human&#45;<lb/>&#45;ity shall have spread from one end of Thy created<lb/> world to its uttermost end&#44; and every soul shall will<lb/> acknowledge Thee&#44; the merciful Parents of all that has<lb/> existence.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
