<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF5_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1876-07" source="" attested="yes">July 1896</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_1_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_1_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_1_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_1_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_1_8v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_1_9r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_1_9v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_1_10r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_1_10v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_1_11r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_1_11v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_1_12r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_1_12v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 7 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>49</p>
            
            <p>For the 4 of July 1876<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;<lb/></p>
            <p>The newly elected President of the Board of Hebrew<lb/> Delegates&#44;&#45;&#45;in which body this Congregation is repre&#45;<lb/>&#45;sented&#45;&#45;&#44; has <sic>signalised</sic> his induction into office&#44; by<lb/> an evidence of patriotism.  In a sensibly written<lb/> paper&#44; circulated through the Jewish press&#44; he recom&#45;<lb/>&#45;mended that the hundredth birth day of American Inde&#45;<lb/>&#45;pendence&#44; should elicit a joint recognition of the blessings<lb/> which Israel has enjoyed&#44; under the government of the<lb/> Republic.  His call struck a chord which vibrated<lb/> in the breasts of some&#44; who deem it a glorious privilege&#44;<lb/> not less than a duty&#44; to keep alive the ennobling senti&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment of the love of country by words which religion dic&#45;<lb/>&#45;tates&#44; even&#44; the religion derived from the book that breathes<lb/> so tender an affection for one&#39;s native soil&#44; as to find ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;pressions of endearment for the stones thereof and for its<lb/> dust.<lb/></p>
            <p>Yet&#44; the Hebrew Ministers of this city&#44; have judged that<lb/> the very exceptional occasion&#44; which suggested the recom&#45;<lb/>&#45;mendation&#44; would prevent its being fulfilled in the<lb/> exact manner designated.  They could foresee that<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>the minds of their coreligionists in Philadelphia&#44;<lb/> would instinctively be drawn towards the spot&#44; which<lb/> the grandest of all incidents in modern history has<lb/> hallowed&#59; that to witness the commemorative ceremonies<lb/> there performed&#44; to listen&#44; with due reverence&#44; to a rehearsal<lb/> of the immortal document&#44; which made the colonists<lb/> free&#44; and participate afterwards in the national festi&#45;<lb/>&#45;vities&#44; enlivening the myriads that have gathered to<lb/> admire the creations of genius&#44; and the product of skill&#44;<lb/> would be the occupation of Israelites in our midst&#44; on the<lb/> fourth of July of this never to be forgotten year.  Act&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing under that impression&#44; the Rabbis and Preachers agreed<lb/> to address their respective congregations on the subject<lb/> of the Centennial anniversary&#44; the Sabbath preceding<lb/> the celebration.  But since they so determined&#44; a<lb/> proclamation has been issued by the Chief Executive.<lb/>  It invites all to assemble at a time and at places<lb/> most convenient&#44; and greet the forthcoming event with<lb/> public thanksgivings.  How that call&#44; emanating from<lb/> so high an authority&#44; has afflicted a resolve previously<lb/> taken&#44; I can answer only as far as it concerns my indi&#45;<lb/>&#45;vidual self&#59; for I have not been asked&#44; by the chairman<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>of the Board of Hebrew Ministers to meet my colleagues<lb/> and discuss the point.  I believe who that when<lb/> I urge my Brethren to follow the bent of their minds&#44;<lb/> leading their steps before the hall&#44; where a Divine superior wisdom<lb/> spoke once through the lips of purity&#44; and look from thence<lb/> heavenward with grateful emotions&#59; that when I counsel<lb/> them to feast their eyes with on the original writing from<lb/> whose declaration much happiness has&#44; under Providence&#44;<lb/> flowed down to posterity&#44; I act in the spirit of the<lb/> President&#39;s proclamation.  He wishes that the occasion<lb/> may set a proper value in our estimation on the<lb/> favors of showered down bestowed by the Almighty upon the land<lb/> consecrated one hundred years ago to human liberty&#44; and<lb/> verily the scene presented in Independence Square is<lb/> meant to effect that pious object.<lb/></p>
            <p>But this morning that we have assembled convened together denomina&#45;<lb/>&#45;tionally&#44; as members of the house of Israel&#44; loving<lb/> America fondly as our mother country&#44; or as the home<lb/> of our choice&#59; this morning that we are at the entrance <sic>threshhold</sic><lb/> of another era in her annals&#44; we may cast a retrospective<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>look glance upon the ground&#44; which our people have trod<lb/>&#45;den since the Sages of 1776 deliberated on the destinies<lb/> of a newly&#45;born nation&#44; whose sponsors they stood in the presence of<lb/> a whole world.<lb/></p>
            <p>France&#44; that to cripple the power of her rival across the<lb/> channel&#44; sent to Rhode Island her well&#61;manned ships<lb/> and her cannons&#44; did not fight then injustice at home.<lb/>  France&#44; that to wage retrieve the past glories of which she<lb/> had been shorn by Great Britain&#44; girded the loins of her<lb/> brave soldiers and made them co&#45;workers in a righteous<lb/> cause&#44; dishonored her name character still by the treatment of the<lb/> Jew upon her soil.  When Lafayette bled in <sic>defence</sic><lb/> of human rights&#44; his country&#44; did would not admit that the<lb/> son of Israel had any title even to human sympathy.<lb/>  But America&#44; the revolutionist&#44; that thundered forth<lb/> a new political revelation&#44; shamed her ally into the<lb/> adoption of a liberal generous code.  Who should now brand with<lb/> opprobrious names a Cremieux a Simon&#44; a Periere&#63;<lb/>  And England&#44; has she not benefitted been liberalized by the example<lb/> of her emancipated colonists&#63;  Slow she is to<lb/> learn&#44; but once that she has imbibed the lesson she<lb/> holds to it with abiding steadfastness.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>It took her long to wipe off the stains made on her<lb/> legislation in the dark ages.  All will remember her persistent un&#45;<lb/>&#45;willingness t ocancel rules anciently imprinted on her<lb/> statute&#45;book&#44; but she did finally overcome a leaning<lb/> to oppressive conservatism&#44; and her broad policy has<lb/> given her a Moses Montefiore&#44; a David Salomon&#44; a George<lb/> Jessel&#44; an Arthur Cohen&#44; Israelites at whose mention she<lb/> needs not stand abashed.  But nowhere&#44; throughout<lb/> civilized Europe&#44; has the sublime teaching of the Republic<lb/> of the North received a more striking illustration than in<lb/> Italy.  With a steady gaze upon the standard unfurled ensign set up<lb/> by Washington&#44; Italy struggled mightily to set upon plant in her<lb/> soil a standard of equality.  Appalling were the dif&#45;<lb/>ficulties to be surmounted.  Bleeding at every pore&#44; she<lb/> still grappled with obstacles&#44;and hers is the glory of<lb/> a victory unsurpassed.  Aye&#58; in the country that forged<lb/> the prisoners&#39; chains&#44; to shackle the Hebrews&#44; the be&#45;<lb/>&#45;lievers in the Unity gather&#44; more extensively than in any other<lb/> region&#44; civic and national honors.  Germany has a<lb/> right proudly to point to her Lasker&#44; her Jacoby<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>and Lazarus&#44; as a proof of rapid advancement in the<lb/> way opened by America&#44; but Italy&#44; reckoning Jewish<lb/> dignitaries notabilities by the score&#44; shows moreover a Samuel Alatri&#44;<lb/> chosen by the voice of his Christian fellow citizens as the first chief<lb/> Magistrate of the metropolis&#44; even of Rome&#44; by yesterday<lb/> the fiery furnace wherein the life of the Jew was consuming.<lb/>  That The modesty of that popular sin of our race which led<lb/> him to decline the distinction&#44; does not affect the principle<lb/> which its bestowal denotes.  The spirit of liberality per&#45;<lb/>&#45;meating society in the peninsula is still revealed thereby and<lb/> its existence may be traced to the working of that instrument<lb/> which broke down fictitious barriers&#44; redeemed shielded the powerless<lb/> from oppression&#44; uplifted the masses&#44; recognized impressed more vividly on<lb/> every man the dignity stamped upon him by nature&#59; that is&#44;<lb/> the matchless declaration of American Independence&#44; which<lb/> discards any religious test&#44; and favors no dogma.<lb/></p>
            <p>From beyond the shattered gates of the horrid ghetto&#44; as spring<lb/> of human gratitude wells up.  It runs deeper It flows<lb/> more copiously more copiously this year towards the land<lb/> which celebrates her Jubilee&#58; For&#44; the descendants of the<lb/> captives of Judea&#44; forcibly dragged beneath the triumphal<lb/> arch to the seven&#45;hilled city&#44; have met face to face<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>rising and falling empires&#59; republics did also did<lb/> contend in turn for the mastery of a the soil wherein those Judeans they still<lb/> dwell in&#59; but they have never beheld&#44; what they now<lb/> see reflected as in a mirror&#58; The glorious humane song results of<lb/> the existence of a model nation.  The One hundred years<lb/> passed over her head have made her famous&#44; not for her because of<lb/> bloody victories&#44; but for the conquest of peace.  Her<lb/> trophies are the discoveries of science&#44; the inventions of<lb/> mechanical industry&#44; and a freedom enjoyed by forty<lb/> millions&#44; seeking happiness marching on to progress on the exercise of their <sic>inaliable</sic> rights.<lb/>  Therefore is her name a blessing&#44; and people beyond her<lb/> sea&#44; rise and call her happy.<lb/></p>
            <p>But we&#44; my hearers&#33; that are the immediate participants<lb/> of the glories which America has achieved in whatever is<lb/> useful and true&#44; must bend before Almighty God<lb/> her Leader and Protector.  At her birth&#44; he stationed around beside<lb/> her a guardian angel&#44; that no harm might befall<lb/> her&#44; and as she grew&#44; He gave her a strength that<lb/> proved invincible&#44; a mind that towered aloft&#44;<lb/> till greetings meet her on all sides&#44; and she is recognized as<lb/> a Divine&#45;appointed mistress of a new world&#44; and the tutoress of the old.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Thanks and praises unto Thee O Lord of all flesh&#44;<lb/> whose hands holdest the balance of justice in Thy hand.  Because the me&#45;<lb/>&#45;rits of America outweigh her failings&#44; Thou hast opened<lb/> Thy treasures and satisfied her with good.  We do recognize acknoweldg <sic>recognise</sic><lb/> Thy mercy in overlooking faults of private and nation&#45;<lb/>&#45;al character&#59; but we acknowledge that Thy blessings<lb/> are a reward Thou has assigned to virtue.  We do not<lb/> hypocritically stand before Thee&#44; all&#45;seeing God&#33; and<lb/> cry.  &#34;The people of the land are steeped in sin&#59; they<lb/> are unworthy of Thy bounties.&#34;  Verily&#58; we believe<lb/> that Thou&#44; who art the Father of all creatures&#44;<lb/> hast taken delight in the Republic which elevates<lb/> man&#44; dignifies labor&#44; and grants her moral sup&#45;<lb/>&#45;port to the down&#45;trodden.  May the tokens of<lb/> Thy acceptance of such deeds&#44; O Most High&#33; be<lb/> shown in the future like in the past.<lb/></p>
            <p>A hundred years in the life of a people&#44; are like yester&#45;<lb/>&#45;day that when it is past&#44; but how numerous and how<lb/> signal have been Thy of celestial favors during that period of<lb/> this nation&#39;s existence.  Many a Often times America<lb/> might have been brought hurled down into a precipice&#44; had<lb/> not Thy might arm been stretched forth&#44; encircled her around and brought her<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>to safety.  When the lovers of freedom stood in<lb/> dread by reason of the danger to which she was exposed&#44;<lb/> and despotism felt inspired with hope&#44; Thou gavest the<lb/> first former the sign of Thy watchfulness&#44; and shamedst the<lb/> latter even to confusion.  Purified by a stream of<lb/> passing trials&#44; made brighter by the strokes of temporary<lb/> adversity&#44; the Republic stands now forth in all her<lb/> natural comeliness.  Princes2 and Emperors hasten to<lb/> her presence.  At1 the tidings of her excellencies&#44; They<lb/> look and admire&#58; again they gaze and marvel.  The<lb/> features she exhibits intensify their pleasure&#59; enraptures<lb/> their feelings.  Grant O God&#33; that what constitutes the<lb/> sterling beauty of this land may never fade away.<lb/>  May Civil and religious liberty be the badge boon of every inhabitant.<lb/>  May free schools and colleges&#44; become the laboratory pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;paring an enlarged and liberal knowledge.  May the work&#45;<lb/>shops still produce what contributes to domestic comfort&#44;<lb/> facilitates social intercourse&#44; and brings mankind more<lb/> closely together.<lb/></p>
            <p>Grant O Lord&#44; that these United States&#44; which Thou hast<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>set up high as a beacon light to distant peoples&#44;<lb/> may vie with each other in reforming abuses&#44; in up&#45;<lb/>&#45;rooting wrongs&#44; in effacing any rule which may bear<lb/> heavily upon the humblest or the smallest portion of the<lb/> Community.  And let Thy gracious will be that these present<lb/> centennial festivities&#44; may be prove the dawning of a glorious<lb/> age&#44; in which all will recognize that Thou art the only<lb/> Father and shepherd&#44; and to Thee belongs the kingdom<lb/> over the creatures of the earth from everlasting to ever<lb/>&#45;lasting.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
