<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF2_11</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_11_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_11_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_11_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_11_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_11_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_11_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_11_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_11_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_11_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_11_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_11_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_11_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_11_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_11_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_11_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_11_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>On Penitence<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>An invisible hand laid hold of the Seer prophet who pro&#45;<lb/> &#45;phesied lived in the country of the Chaldeans&#44; and carried him<lb/> by a lock of his hair to the holy city of Jerusalem.  When<lb/> there&#44; a voice whispered.  &#34;Son of man&#44; come and bear<lb/> witness to the abominations&#44; which the house of Israel<lb/> commit in concealment secret.&#34;  At that command&#44; Ezekiel<lb/> opened himself a way through a crevice in the wall&#44;<lb/> and looked in.  Shameful sight&#33;  Debasing scene&#33;<lb/>  Altars were burning with incense perfume in honor to reptiles<lb/> and loathsome creatures painted whose image stood engraved all around.  &#34;Such<lb/> is the doing of the elders of thy people&#44;&#34; continued the<lb/> same voice &#34;for&#44; they say &#39;the Lord sees us not<lb/>&#39;&#34; He has<lb/> forsaken the land&#39;&#34;.<lb/></p>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  In reading the history of the ancients I have<lb/> often wondered at the homage that stupidity of men who would pay homage<lb/> to the lowest of objects in creation.  I could easily<lb/> understand&#44; how awe struck with awe at the majesty of the lu&#45;<lb/>&#45;minary which rides through the measureless space&#44;<lb/> they heathens would bend down in adoration.  Or&#44; how in the clap<lb/> of thunder they fancied they could hear the rebuke<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>of some angry god&#59; for because&#44; untaught by revelation<lb/> they hazans mistook the workings of nature for its all&#45;<lb/>moving Cause the Omnipotent.  But that they should should<lb/> do reverence to beasts&#44; that they should deify creeping<lb/> insects&#44; seemed to me inexplicable.  &#34;Has man&#44;&#34;<lb/> I would ask myself&#44; &#34;has man voluntarily parted<lb/> with the noblest of his possessions&#45;&#45;Intellect&#63;&#34;<lb/>  But that which at one time excited my asto&#45;<lb/>&#45;nishment has ceased to surprise me.  The vision of<lb/> Ezekiel affords instruction information.  Thus&#44; prompted<lb/> by instinct to worship some object&#44; gave pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;ference to those creatures which might not check by<lb/> their dreaded power&#44; an indulgence in low appetites.<lb/>  An imperfect indistinct notion of a Supreme Lord may have been entertained by the masses&#44; but<lb/> then said &#34;the Lord sees us not&#44;&#34; and they had and that hence Reason<lb/> was used crookedly.  They People tried to be convinced that worldly<lb/> affairs cannot fall under the direction of a King<lb/> enthroned in the highest.  That attending to such concerns would<lb/> be incompatible with His the state of one so glorious&#44; stale&#59; therefore and as they felt at liberty to select their own gods they<lb/> chose as &#91;&#63;&#93; earthly things representing brutal fostering a prurient wish for animal<lb/> passions&#59; things which inspired no terror of future punish&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment.<lb/>
                But that baneful error common among pagans&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>ought never to have been entertained harbored by the disciples<lb/> of Moses.  The checkered history of the father of their<lb/> nation&#44; and their miraculous deliverance of the tribes from a galling bond&#45;<lb/>&#45;age should have sufficed to ineffaceably imprint on<lb/> the tablets of their hearts the belief that &#34;the Lord is high&#44; but still<lb/> looks below.&#34;  That alone should have prevented the hallucina&#45;<lb/>&#45;tions of idolatry.  But I imagine I hear you<lb/> now say&#58; what is all that narrative to prove&#63;  What<lb/> is it to us if our fathers stultified themselves&#63;  We have<lb/> learnt better than to bow to perishable objects below our stand&#45; below our standards<lb/> &#45;ards.  Well&#58; if it were really so if we tendered adoration only to the Sovereign Creator&#44; and to none of His creatures the recalling<lb/> of our ancestors&#39; fatal errors might answer serve no<lb/> purpose&#59; it might be altogether useless&#44; but when we see<lb/> the same wrongs reproduced in other shapes and<lb/> forms&#44; it is fitting that our the minds should be<lb/> directed to the past and we be made to feel as to an historical warning and the lips be made to confess<lb/> that in the prophetic confession ought to issue from language<lb/> our lips &#34;we know O Lord our wickedness&#44; and the<lb/> iniquity of our fathers&#34;.  We consider ourselves<lb/> more enlightened than our predecessors&#44; and in some instances we may claim superiority&#44; but were our hearts to be probed&#44;<lb/> but with regard to sterling&#44; not feigned&#44; religion&#44; if our hearts were probed<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>it might be discovered that like in theirs false notions<lb/> have supplanted the veneration we owe the only<lb/> adorable God&#59; that we don&#39;t worship not irrational beings in the world but we worship the world itself full of irrationality&#44; the world&#44; or rather the world itself&#44; the world the<lb/> opinion we wish it to holds about our standing in commercial<lb/> or social circles&#59; that we sacrifice our highest to secure to that opinion&#44; often irrational&#44; always unstable&#44; we devote<lb/> our faculties&#44; our noblest instincts to a popularity built best energies<lb/> on the ruin of not infrequently we sacrifice to it virtue&#44; which is practical religion.<lb/>  And they who have apparently succeeded best in<lb/> gaining their point&#44; lead the van of sin.  They<lb/> are the elders whom Ezekiel described as burning<lb/> incense to imaginary deities.  But verily more sense&#45;<lb/>&#45;less are they than those ancient chiefs of our people&#59;<lb/> for&#44; to worship popularity is to set oneself on the<lb/> mouth of a volcano.  Suddenly you may be shattered<lb/> into atoms.  &#34;The Lord sees us not&#34; &#34;The Lord can do us no harm&#44;&#34; say think<lb/> they who walk among the great move in high circles.  &#34;The world is a<lb/> tower of strength&#44; a wall of defence.&#34;  Yes&#58; so long as<lb/> layers of gold lie at the foundations&#44; yes&#44; bold men&#44;<lb/> may take shelter therein&#44; but bela beware of trusting<lb/> yourselves thereat in such strongholds when the deposit of the precious<lb/> metal begins to thin off.  You may seek in vain<lb/> for the means of deliverance.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>&#34;Thus far I have nothing to fear.  My possessions property is<lb/> are perfectly secure.  I own rich lands.&#34;  But not<lb/> richer nor larger as vast than those of Ahab the Ruler of Israel.&#34;<lb/>  Yet&#44; the absence of rain had made almost an end<lb/> of his dominions.  &#34;My ships cross the sea freighted<lb/> with goods&#44;&#34; Jeoshaphat King of Judah had also had famous<lb/> vessels which were to make a far extended voyage&#44;<lb/> but a <sic>trecherous</sic> wind wrecked them into a shapeless form to pieces.  &#34;The<lb/> many houses I own call mine&#44; cannot be stolen from me&#34; No&#58; but they a pestilential air<lb/> may become render them valueless.  &#34;The stock I have got&#44; yields<lb/> largely&#34;&#44; but it may grow in size to be ultimately like the apple of<lb/> the dead sea.  You think you have seized a fine fruit&#44; but<lb/> it is ashes.  Insecure are all human possessions&#44; and as they leave<lb/> us&#44; so does the object we preferred to the adorable if Lord<lb/> the Almighty&#59; whose blessing alone can make rich the object we thought a rock of<lb/> defense shake under our feet slip from under us&#44; and lets us fall.  Alas&#33; How many<lb/> who conceived they were held up high in the arms<lb/> of the world&#44; felt the effects of its fickle nature.<lb/>  They experienced then that a false idol had deceived beguiled<lb/> and veiled their understanding.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>But supposing that we are not doomed to<lb/> suffer such results&#44; that despite our backslidings<lb/> our affluence will remains unimpaired&#44; and hence our po&#45;<lb/>&#45;pularity intact&#59; ought we therefore to be hardened follow<lb/> in sin&#44; to provoke God by disobeying His commands&#63; set aside the law of God&#63;<lb/>  What if our defiance calls down a punishment severer<lb/> than the loss of wealth&#63;  Say my Brethren.  Is not<lb/> a man on very humble circumstances&#44; but with a<lb/> sound body richer than the diseased opulent&#63;  King<lb/> Asa could baost of magnificent mansions&#44; but<lb/> when his audacious culpable conduct towards the admonishing<lb/> prophet deprived him of the power of locomotion&#44; he<lb/> must have deemed himself poor indeed.  And what Useless<lb/> is a table laden with luxuries&#44; if we dare not&#44; save<lb/> at the risk of our health&#44; lay our hands thereon&#63;.  It<lb/> would be then of no avail that our store&#45;rooms are<lb/> overflowing with delicacies&#44; our cellars with delicious wines.<lb/>  A very plain meal&#44; seasoned with the capacity for<lb/> enjoyment after a day&#39;s labor&#44; or an appetizing<lb/> walk&#44; is infinitely sweeter than are covetted a repast greatly to be craved for.<lb/>  A gift it is&#44; writes the moralist of old&#44; that God in<lb/> His mercy grants.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>But why harbor any apprehension&#44; cry my youthful<lb/> hearers.  We are in the spring of life&#44; we are<lb/> vigorous&#44; illness is a stranger to us.  The world smiling<lb/> upon us&#44; and invites us to pleasure radiant with smiles&#44; promises interminable pleasures&#44; if we will only<lb/> pay homage to it.  Ah&#44; my friends.  Could you examine<lb/> every fibre with which your body is interwoven&#44; you<lb/> would cease boasting.  Could you see reflected as in<lb/> a mirror the interlacing of arteries and veins&#44; which throb in run through your<lb/> frame you would be struck dumb&#44; and never again<lb/> pride yourselves on your strength.  You would wonder<lb/> how so complex a texture can remain any time with&#45;<lb/>&#45;out some disarrangements.  &#34;I will praise thee&#44;&#34; prayfully<lb/> exclaimed David in a prayful outburst of feelings &#34;for I was fearfully and wonderfully<lb/> made.  Marvellous are Thy works&#44; and my soul knows it<lb/> well.&#34;  Is it not the height of temerity in him&#44; whose<lb/> construction physical corporeal structure may in an instant be shattered&#44; to harden<lb/> his heart in sin&#44; by reason of his physical powers&#63;<lb/>  Man&#33; will I say in the language of Job&#58; why does thy<lb/> mind carry thee away&#44; and what do thine eyes wink at&#44;<lb/> that then turnest thy spirit against God&#63;  &#34;Art thou<lb/> not a worm in comparison with Him&#44; at whose word<lb/> space was filled studded with lights&#44; and the earth was peopled with<lb/> beings&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Thou mayest have escaped hitherto His consu&#45;<lb/>&#45;ming wrath&#44; when running counter to His will&#44; for mercy tempers rigor&#44; but it may<lb/> overtake thee while thou art bent mounting up<lb/> the ladder of prosperity.  The wicked son of<lb/> Omri had engaged&#44; despite the warning of the<lb/> prophet&#44; in a war against the Syrians.  To avoid<lb/> recognition&#44; he disguised himself in the garments<lb/> generally worn by his royal ally of the house of Judah.<lb/>  The victory was nearly won&#44; when&#44; a bow drawn<lb/> at venture&#44; discharged the arrow that pierced<lb/> the heart of the impious King of Israel.  Nor is<lb/> it solely with the spear and the lance&#44; amidst the<lb/> battle&#39;s din of war the battle&#44; that Divine justice exacts its due&#59; light&#45;<lb/>&#45;er weapons&#44; agencies very subtle can break up snap off asunder this<lb/> intricately made body of ours.  For many and various are the messengers<lb/> that the Lord employs.  But He has held them<lb/> back&#44; that they may not visit us&#44; because of His<lb/> infinite goodness&#44; not by reason of our merits.<lb/>  He has borne with derelictions from duty&#44; that<lb/> we might live to discover and reform our wrong doings.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Let us not mistake a fatherly tenderness for<lb/> want of power&#59; let us not attribute construe a love for pardoning into indifference a disregard<lb/> for our conduct.  To the contemporaries of Ezekiel<lb/> who said &#34;the Lord sees us not&#44;&#34; and secretly sold them&#45;<lb/>&#45;selves to a false worship was announced evils a future too<lb/> literally fulfilled realized.  Be admonished and instructed&#44;<lb/> brother sinners.  Cast off the idols of your imagi&#45;<lb/>&#45;nation and adore the Only God&#44; who opens for us denies not<lb/> a refuge when the world has turned its back upon with indif<lb/> the unfortunate &#45;ference to our fate.  Cease to bow to a receding shadow&#44;<lb/> the world&#39;s opinion&#44; and bend before the Son of truth<lb/> who that will never withhold beneficent rays to warm and to<lb/> quicken our existence&#44; when it seemed all but extinguished.<lb/>  Trust not in wealth&#44; lest you find too when late&#44; that<lb/> you have leaned upon a broken reed.  Trust not in<lb/> health&#44; which a puff of wind may blight.  But<lb/> confide in the Omnipotent&#44; upon whose arm all creation<lb/> hangs for support.  Calling on Him in the hour of<lb/> need&#44; and receive thankfully the blessings He bestows&#59;<lb/> not with a rebellious look because it does not equal<lb/> your ambition&#44; not with a murmur because it<lb/> will not gratify all your anticipators.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>Learn to believe this most essential truth&#59; that hap&#45;<lb/>&#45;piness is a sentiment&#44; kept a fresh by a current run&#45;<lb/>&#45;ning inwardly not outwardly&#44; that the consciousness of<lb/> having worthily employed nature&#39;s faculties of having cherished ennobling aspirations intensifies<lb/> that sentiment&#44; by &#91;&#63;&#93; and giving the sweetest turn to the bread shared with<lb/> loved beings.  In short&#44; dear Israelites&#44; seek felicity.<lb/>  He will command&#59; and they will compass our city<lb/> and our homes&#44; avert misfortune&#44; speed on<lb/> healing&#44; and draw every day of the year&#44;<lb/> whose entrance we have greeted with psalmody&#44;<lb/> from the choicest treasures prosperity and uninter&#45;<lb/>&#45;rupted peace.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
