<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF9_8</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1890-12" source="" attested="yes">December 1890</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_8_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_8_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_8_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_8_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_8_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_8_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_8_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_8_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_8_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_8_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_8_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_8_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. Fifth St.<lb/></p>
            <p>Philadelphia&#44; Dec&#47;90<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>On burials<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Brethren.<lb/></p>
            <p>The closing chapters of the book of Genesis&#44; set a<lb/> never tarnishing diadem on filial devotion.  What is<lb/> the vaunted iron crown of the ancient Longobardian dynasty&#44; compared with the<lb/> <sic>jewelled</sic> one which Joseph the Hebrew wore&#63;  The<lb/> cathedral of Mourza retained long as a relic that which<lb/> was the pride of extinctguished monarchies.  The first vo&#45;<lb/>&#45;lume of our Scriptures&#44; preserves imperishably that which<lb/> is a glory to immortal Israel in all ages.  The<lb/> affection which Joseph paid to his evinced toward his venerated father&#44; after having<lb/> at length joyfully met again&#44; was surpassingly ten&#45;<lb/>&#45;der.  Who will not admire the anxious consi&#45;<lb/>&#45;deration of the exemplary son&#44; which made the seven&#45;<lb/>&#45;teen years of the patriarch&#39;s residence in a foreign<lb/> land&#44; flow gently&#59; that profound sublime self&#45;denial which<lb/> suppressed the knowledge of past events that might<lb/> have marred the <sic>tranquillity</sic> needed at senility&#63;<lb/>  But as I read the directions of the dutiful child&#44;<lb/> by which he sought to offer his fond parent the<lb/> last tribute of respect&#44; I discover a peculiarity<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>conflicting with ancestral usages&#44; certainly new to<lb/> that parent&#44; and confessedly belonging to the heathen<lb/> stranger.  The singularity I notice is the order that<lb/> the body of the venerable sire be embalmed&#44; to preserve guard<lb/> it from decay.  Not so had Abraham com&#45;<lb/>&#45;manded&#44; when the wife for whom he yearned&#44; and whose<lb/> demise he lamented and wept for&#44; was to be laid<lb/> into the cave of Machelah&#59; nor did Esau and Jacob<lb/> ask that the mortal remains of Isaac should under&#45;<lb/>&#45;go that complicated process&#59; while Rachel was<lb/> given a grave on the way to Ephrath near Bethlehem&#44;<lb/> that she might not long be kept unburied.<lb/></p>
            <p>The whole range of Jewish history does not present<lb/> a single instance in which our dead were subjected<lb/> to the elaborate operation of embalming&#45;&#45;as minutely<lb/> described by Herodotus&#45;&#45;save in that related in the<lb/> last portion of Genesis&#59; namely&#44; in the case of Jacob<lb/> and Joseph.  Admitting that the distance through<lb/> which the body of the former was to be conveyed&#44;<lb/> necessitated extraordinary care to prevent decomposi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion and its deleterious consequences&#44; still other<lb/> contrivances might have been resorted to not to<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>allow forty days to elapse&#45;&#45;independent of the thirty<lb/> observed by the Egyptians as a period of mourning&#45;&#45;before<lb/> starting for the place of interment.  But Joseph&#44;<lb/> though an exceptional Hebrew&#44; was human and therefore<lb/> affected by his surroundings&#44; just as we all gradually<lb/>&#45;&#45;imperceptibly perhaps&#45;&#45;adopt customs prevalent among<lb/> our immediate neighbors.  To rise above one&#39;s environ&#45;<lb/>ment is hardly given to any man.  Joseph may have<lb/> involuntarily become identified with habits universal in<lb/> Egypt&#44; or he may have found himself incapable of<lb/> setting aside in his own behalf a rule which all followed<lb/> in the land where he was called to govern.  To have acted<lb/> antagonistically to it&#44; might have seemed odd&#44; possibly<lb/> offensive.  For the embalming of the deceased was<lb/> a deep rooted institution in the country of the Pharaohs&#44;<lb/> connected with the popular belief that a bodily resurrect&#45;<lb/>&#45;ion depended absolutely upon it&#44; and from Herodotus<lb/> we learn that the higher had the dead ranked in society&#44;<lb/> the more costly and painstaking were the arrangements<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>which preceded their consignment to the sepulchre.<lb/>  Now fellow Israelites.  The simplifying of many<lb/> customs of doubtful sanctity&#44; specially respecting fu&#45;<lb/>&#45;nerals and burials&#44; we owe to the Rabbis.  They who<lb/> wisely regarded the welfare of the living as of pri&#45;<lb/>&#45;mary importance&#45;&#45;superior to all other considerations&#45;&#45;; who understood well that the<lb/> departed cannot be spiritually <sic>benefitted</sic> by our large<lb/> outlays&#44; and that the great <sic>leveller</sic>&#45;&#45;death&#45;&#45;equalizes<lb/> us all under the ground &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> the Rabbis&#44; I say&#44; sensibly made rules which sagacity<lb/> dictates.  Would that we conformed therewith&#63;  But<lb/> so strong is our weakness on the point of disposing of<lb/> our dead&#44; that in every age exuberant means and<lb/> excessive care have been bestowed on those who left us<lb/> for another world.  Unfortunately&#44; such morbid feel&#45;<lb/>&#45;ings proved&#44; not infrequently&#44; very hurtful to the<lb/> <sic>wel&#45;being</sic> of the survivors.  The extravagance had reached<lb/> so unlimited a degree&#44; that in order to check it&#44; a<lb/> prohibition was enacted against preparing the dead<lb/> in any other manner than the plainest.  All<lb/> know that Rabbi Gamliel who stood preeminently a Chief of the Sanhedrin&#44; and who descended from<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>the illustrious house of Hillel&#44; at the initia&#45;<lb/>&#45;tory example&#44; by requesting that a single simple white<lb/> robe should enshroud his body and that his inhuma&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion be unostentatious.  The Sages of later ages<lb/> centuries added force to that rule&#44; and condemned as<lb/> culpably wasteful the rich garments and all the<lb/> expensive concomitants of funerals.  But we<lb/> Israelites do not heed the wholesome advice.  We<lb/> prefer copying practices attended with serious evils&#44;<lb/> because the fear of being looked upon as wanting in<lb/> affection to the dear ones&#44; who have been summoned<lb/> from earth&#44; has a mighty hold on our minds&#44; and<lb/> incites some to make sacrifices entailing sufferings<lb/> to those who are left behind.  Rather contract<lb/> obligations very difficult to meet&#44; than let the deceased<lb/> go to their resting place without a train of carriages&#44;<lb/> floral ornamentations&#44; silver plates&#44; silver mountings&#44;<lb/> and an the anticipation of a marble monument.<lb/>  In my love for humanity&#44; I was pleased on various<lb/> occasions to notice the absence of useless trappings&#44;<lb/> particularly so when the Jewish families I was called<lb/> upon to console&#44; required all they saved thereby&#44; and<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>more too for their comfort.  At the con&#45;<lb/>&#45;ference of Jewish ministers held at this season in<lb/> Philadelphia two years ago&#44; it was proposed that<lb/> the Rabbis should recommend from their pulpits&#44; and<lb/> whenever the opportunity offered&#44; the introduction of<lb/> funeral services at Synagogues.  The aim was twofold&#44;<lb/> to create a deeper impression touching our common mor&#45;<lb/>&#45;tality by the imposingness of the sacred plan&#44; and&#44;<lb/> again&#44; to put an end to the cort&#233;ge&#44; consisting of many<lb/> carriages&#59; for at the conclusion of the solemn ceremonies&#44;<lb/> the hearse and the accompanying officiating minister<lb/> would proceed to the cemetery with only the immediate mourners&#44; and&#44;<lb/> if needed&#44; with the required quorum or Min&#225;n.  The<lb/> motion was not acted upon&#44; and really circumstanced as<lb/> we are&#45;&#45;some intentionally withholding any connection<lb/> with a congregation&#44; others preferring spots which have<lb/> lost every claim to the title of houses of Jewish prayers&#44;<lb/> the idea advanced&#44; however good in theory&#44; is scarcely<lb/> feasible in practice.  But the Board of healths of<lb/> Pennsylvania has just issued a circular bearing&#44; in<lb/> a measure&#44; upon the subject&#44; and that document is<lb/> entitled to careful attention.  It is directed<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>to the clergy of all creeds and denominations urging<lb/> them to exert their influence healthfully with families&#59;<lb/> reflecting on the wrong done to the living by exposing<lb/> the dead to public gaze&#44; and allowing throngs to<lb/> fill beyond its capacity a hall or a parlor&#44; inhaling<lb/> an air tainted perhaps with disease breeding poison.<lb/>  That circular is supported by the testimony of noted<lb/> physicians who declare that the gathering of many<lb/> persons&#44; where a sickness of a contagious or semi conta&#45;<lb/>&#45;gious nature had caused death&#44; proved fatal to friends<lb/> who sought to do the departed honor by their presence.<lb/></p>
            <p>I may perchance be reminded of a Talmudical in&#45;<lb/>&#45;junction&#44; according to which it would seem imperative<lb/> on us&#44; at all hazards&#44; to be found where the deceased are<lb/> about to be carried to their final home&#44; and where<lb/> mourners sit&#44; but&#44; if I understand the drift of Rab&#45;<lb/>&#45;binical teaching correctly&#44; I see no necessity for<lb/> overcrowding a funeral house&#44; with the view of<lb/> fulfilling that pious ordinance.  By &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> was meant what our predecessors were wont to do&#44; namely&#44;<lb/> suspend usual pursuits when a funeral passed by&#59; walk<lb/> a certain distance&#44; as a token of reverence to the disembodied<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>spirit&#44; and&#44; where a the practice prevailed of saluting<lb/> the bereaved with the word &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;May the Almighty<lb/> comfort you&#34; act accordingly in all sincerity.  At all<lb/> wants&#44; the law of self&#45;preservation has always been dwelt<lb/> upon with the greatest emphasis by our ancient teachers&#44;<lb/> so much so that they have laid out this maxim &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; signifying that when faced by dangers&#44; we should<lb/> not hesitate to leave aside&#45;&#45;for the time being&#45;&#45;the performance<lb/> of religious rules.  Hence throughout the Talmud are inter&#45;<lb/>&#45;spersed regulations to shield us from perils which the<lb/> food we eat&#44; the water we drink&#44; the air we breathe&#44;<lb/> the clothes we put on&#44; may expose us to.  Maimo&#45;<lb/>&#45;nides&#44; who combined with a far&#45;reaching knowledge<lb/> of Jewish Theology&#44; a thorough acquaintance with me&#45;<lb/>&#45;dical science&#44; has devoted a chapter of his ritual work&#45;&#45;<lb/> Mishn&#233; Torah&#44; a Yad Ha&#45;Chazakah&#44; to the system we<lb/> should follow&#44; in order to keep a sound mind in a sound<lb/> body to the utmost length of time allotted to us upon<lb/> earth.  Let us study to attain that end.<lb/>  Better than swelling the number of visitors&#44; where the<lb/> deceased are unwisely laid out to cater to a depraved<lb/> taste&#44; or demurely making circuits all around<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>after the conventionalities of secret orders&#59; better it is<lb/> to live and let live&#44; to bring healing to the sick&#44; and<lb/> help to the hale to keep healthy by dint of timely<lb/> relief.  Best of all it is for those whom the<lb/> Almighty has favored with riches to U bestow thereof<lb/> on whatever tends to prolong existence and make<lb/> it pleasurable&#44; aiding institution which encourage<lb/> sobriety&#44; foster virtue&#44; inspire love for manual<lb/> exercises&#44; educate the mind&#44; soften the feelings&#44;<lb/> refine and elevate the mortals.  Oh&#33; blessed<lb/> they who thus sanctify the wealth they possess&#59;<lb/> thrice blessed they who&#44; while enjoying abundance&#44; make<lb/> many partakers of human delights.  No silver&#45;<lb/>handle casket&#44; no st satin lining&#44; no flowery arches<lb/> or columns or pillars&#44; nor even the eloquently pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;nounced oration will gladden their spirits&#44; but the<lb/> undying memory of their deeds of mercy will beatify<lb/> their souls in the contemplation of the Lord&#44; the<lb/> Parent of mercy.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
