<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF9_17</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1891-05" source="" attested="yes">May 1891</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_17_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_17_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_17_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_17_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_17_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_17_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_17_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_17_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_17_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_17_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_17_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_17_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/></p>
            <p>PHILADELPHIA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>73<lb/></p>
            <p>May&#47;91<lb/></p>
            <p>On Philo Judea<lb/>
                in connection with the fast on the day of atonement<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>In a series of lectures which I delivered before this<lb/> congregation in years times past&#44; I had occasion to mention<lb/> a Jew who lived over eighteen hundred years ago.  Admirable<lb/> he was in his personal character&#44; great he was he in his<lb/> learning.  yet&#44; deserving as the man would have been of a<lb/> world&#45;wide reputation&#44; he does not enjoy the universally<lb/> popular fame which others&#44; perhaps not quite so meritorious&#44;<lb/> have acquired.  Searching for the motives&#44; we may dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;cover them in two connecting circumstances.  First&#58;<lb/> the noble&#45;minded Jew who did with singleness of pur&#45;<lb/>&#45;pose labor for the honor of his people and religion&#44; had<lb/> his home far away from a centre of Judaism&#59; secondly&#44;<lb/> his pen&#44; which <sic>yeilded</sic> plentifully was necessarily unavoidably<lb/> guided by a non&#45;Jewish philosophy influences.  Philo&#44; or&#44;<lb/> as Hebrew authors authors call him Yedidjah Ha Lech&#45;<lb/> sandri&#45;&#44; might have attained the same degree of ce&#45;<lb/>&#45;lebrity among all classes of his coreligionists&#44; as his<lb/> Palestinian contemporary&#44; Josephus&#44; had not his<lb/> birth&#45;place been in Egypt.  He flourished in Alex&#45;<lb/>&#45;andria and his thoughts were shaped after the philosophic sys&#45;<lb/>&#45;tem prevailing in his time and then in his native land.<lb/>  The vast erudition which he possessed&#44; and which<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>he made subservient to a sublime ends was not<lb/> drawn from Hebrew sources.  It has been even ques&#45;<lb/>&#45;tioned whether he could read the Bible understandingly<lb/> in the original text.  An Italian Rabbi of the<lb/> XVIth century of the common era&#44; a Rabbi who may be termed<lb/> the father of modern Jewish cities&#44; acknow&#45;<lb/>&#45;ledging the excellencies of the Alexandrian<lb/> Jew in his individuality and in his literary productions&#44;<lb/> concludes nevertheless that neither Hebrew&#44; nor<lb/> Aramaic&#44; its kindred language&#44; was known to him<lb/> who enriched literature with scores of treatises in<lb/> classical Greek.  All things considered&#44; Philo<lb/> can lay claim to our reverence for his steadfast en&#45;<lb/>&#45;deavour to shame the Jews of his days into the belief<lb/> and the observance of the laws of Moses.  With<lb/> a masterly ability&#44; he showed that Plato and<lb/> Aristotle&#44; whom many of his coreligionists in Egypt<lb/> preferred to the prophet of Sinai&#44; ranked below<lb/> the man who created a people nation hallowed to virtue.<lb/>  But more than veneration by reason of his splendid<lb/> capacities so righteously directed&#44; we owe him gra&#45;<lb/>&#45;titude for his personal services.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>When the mad Caligula&#44; to gratify an insatiable<lb/> ambition&#44; demanded that the Jews of Alexandria&#44;<lb/> worship his image in their Synagogue&#44; as that of a god&#44; Philo&#44; though<lb/> advanced in life&#44; headed a deputation to Rome&#44; seeking sent<lb/> to divert the mind of the wretched emperor from its<lb/> wicked impious design.  But the high esteem in which<lb/> I hold the brilliant writer and pious Israelite&#44; can&#45;<lb/>&#45;not induce me to follow his lead in his interpre&#45;<lb/>&#45;tation of the Scriptures.  Philo&#39;s unacquaint&#45;<lb/>&#45;ance with Hebrew&#44; and his strong leaning to Greek<lb/> metaphysics&#44; caused him often to apply to Holy Writ<lb/> a sense altogether foreign to it.  In his anxiety<lb/> to find a perfect identity between the tenets of the<lb/> sacred code and the sciences of his age&#44; he fell into<lb/> frequent errors.  Specially at fault is he&#44; when<lb/> allegorizing on that which is plain history&#44; and<lb/> calling symbols what are simply divine commands.<lb/>  He meant it well&#44; I am certain.  He wished to<lb/> silence many of those born in our faith&#44; who cavilled<lb/> at the narratives&#44; or at the precepts of the five books&#44;<lb/> but it did not occur to the good man that by a me&#45;<lb/>&#45;taphysical process all the ordinances of the Law&#44; might<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>be explained away.  If&#44; for instance&#44; the<lb/> sanctity of the Sabbath is based on a Pythagorean<lb/> notion regarding the properties of the number seven&#44;<lb/> or if the unleavened bread of Passover signifies the<lb/> importance of bringing under control passions that swell<lb/> in our breast.  Why shall think I&#44; who care nothing for Pythagoras&#39; speculations&#44; or you who may conceive to be able to check your propensities&#44; pay regard to the rules of the seventh day and the unfermented cakes&#33;  Thou know what a strong handle would be thus given to who to Jews who are ill at ease under all religious re&#45;<lb/>&#45;straints&#44; to strike off ritual Judaism&#33;  I do not<lb/> insinuate that Philo&#44; in his reasonings&#44; aimed at such<lb/> an issue&#59; for there is every cause to believe that he<lb/> was <sic>stanch</sic> in his observances&#44; but that which he would<lb/> have been loth to part with&#44; was cast aside by many<lb/> others.  In fact&#44; Alexandrian Jews&#44; bore the un&#45;<lb/>&#45;enviable reputation of being audaciously self sufficient&#44;<lb/> disinclined to submit to rules that curb our ani&#45;<lb/>&#45;mal appetites.  The very best among them&#44; Philo&#44;<lb/> may slightly&#44; though innocently&#44; have contributed<lb/> to that result.  But in reading his<lb/> treatise on &#34;the festivals&#34; of the Lord&#44; I was gratified<lb/> to finding that a Jew of upwards of eighteen hundred<lb/> years ago&#44; a Jew not open to the charge of being biased by<lb/> Rabbinical subletics&#44; as some will call ancestral<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>traditions&#59; a Jew&#44; possibly ignorant of the exact<lb/> words and by Moses in his inspired volumes&#44; when<lb/> referring to the day of atonement&#44; mentions it as<lb/> &#34;the greatest of the festivals&#44;&#34; alleging three reasons for it.<lb/>  First&#44; because to be indifferent to meat and drink&#44; evin&#45;<lb/>&#45;ces a capacity to rise above our national nature&#59;<lb/> secondly&#44; because to devote a day from morning till<lb/> evening to prayer&#44; imploring pardon and hoping for mercy&#44;<lb/> illustrates the sentiment of our dependence upon the a<lb/> Lord higher Power than our own&#59; thirdly&#44; because a universal fast held at a<lb/> season in which the fruits of the earth are gathered in&#44;<lb/> indicates that more than worldly goods&#44; Israelites value<lb/> the approval of a close communion with the Almighty.  I do not say that<lb/> every expression of Philo respecting Yom Kippur accords<lb/> with my views&#44; but this I do assert&#44; that the Alexandrian<lb/> Jew rebukes the unrighteous attempt made in our<lb/> days by the School of Reform to virtually abolish a<lb/> national institution most holy&#44; and which perhaps has<lb/> contributed more than any other in preventing our people<lb/> from breaking loose of from all rules the dictates of morality&#44; tacitly saying&#58; Re&#45; To<lb/> &#45;member that there is an eye that see&#44; an ear that ears&#44; and thy actions are registered in a book &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> To this unbeliever who pretends that the words of Moses<lb/> do not convey the idea of abstaining from food&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>but only of humbling oneself completely mentally&#44; Philo<lb/> speaks in unequivocal terms&#44; and tells that &#34;to afflict<lb/> one&#39;s soul&#34; has never received among us Jews any<lb/> other meaning than that of fasting.  To that caviller<lb/> who teaches the impropriety of asking forgiveness&#44;<lb/> on the plea that God is not <sic>revengful</sic>&#44; Philo<lb/> administers a reprimand and calls it an impardon&#45;<lb/>&#45;able arrogance in a child who has disobeyed his Father&#44;<lb/> to refuse acknowledging himself at fault.  To the<lb/> skeptical critic who argues in favor of the abrogation of the fast&#44; from the absence of<lb/> any record of its injunction outside of the book of Leviticus&#44; of the or&#45;<lb/>&#45;dinance of abstaining from eating on the tenth of<lb/> Tishri Philo brings an uninterrupted chain of oral<lb/> teachings imparting&#44; to testify to the truth that what is chro&#45;<lb/>&#45;nicled in the third book of the Torah&#44; sufficed<lb/> as an everlasting guide to Israel in every country<lb/> and in every age.  In fact&#44; Josephus&#44; whom<lb/> none dares would venture to accuse of ignorance of the Hebrew language&#44;<lb/> and who lived in the capital of Judea during the existence<lb/> of the second Temple&#44; relates that Herod&#44; the usurper<lb/> and murderer of the Asmonean dynasty&#44; captured Je&#45;<lb/>&#45;rusalem on &#34;the solemn day of the fast&#34;&#44; as Pompey<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>had seized it some twenty five or thirty years before.  I do<lb/> not quote the Talmud&#44; which alludes to a super&#45;<lb/>&#45;human voice heard by John Hyreams&#91;&#63;&#93; in the<lb/> Holy of Holies on the day of atonement&#44; telling him<lb/> that his sons had vanquished Antiochus&#44; nor do I<lb/> cite the Talmud in reference to Simeon the Just&#44; who<lb/> supernaturally heard in the Holy of Holies&#44; on the day<lb/> of atonement&#44; the announcement that an impending<lb/> evil had been providentially averted.  I do not do so&#44;k to prove our continuous adherence to the fast on the tenth of Tishri.  I refrain&#44; for<lb/> Jews who deny the continuous constant keeping of that awe&#45;<lb/>inspiring day everywhere at all times&#44; might reject<lb/> the evidence as that of an interested party.  But<lb/> I have often reflected on the matchless sermon of<lb/> Isaiah&#44; which we fittingly rehearse in the morning ser&#45;<lb/>&#45;vice of Kippur&#44; and have my mind has read in it a public ga&#45;<lb/>&#45;thering of much lighter weight than the inspired son of<lb/> Amoz.  There stands the prophet in the midst<lb/> of an assembled throng.  Like a clarion his voice<lb/> thrillingly reproaches sin.  Hypocrisy has entered<lb/> the Temple&#44; and men dare beseech for mercy.  Slaves<lb/> are made to dragging the chains&#44; and their masters ask for grace.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>No&#44; not such is the afflicting of the soul which<lb/> the God of Israel has commanded.  Lift up your heads<lb/> bent like bulrushes and look where inequity abides&#59; root<lb/> it out.  See where misery lies down with despair&#59;<lb/> relieve them.  Sanctify the Sabbath&#44; which the Lord<lb/> Himself has called holy&#44; then will the Parent of Justice<lb/> raise you up to Him&#44; spiritually and call you His heritage.<lb/>  Israelites.  Is th not that a pen picture a faithful reflection of the<lb/> fast day kept by our fathers long after Moses had ordered<lb/> its observance&#63;  Purify it&#44; I say&#44; of all dross&#44; proclaiming with<lb/> the Rabbis&#44; that our wrongs to man will not be forgiven<lb/> unless redressed&#44; &#91;Hebrew&#93; preach&#44; like the Rabbis&#44; that whosoever ima&#45;<lb/>&#45;gines that he can repeat his former backslidings&#44; because<lb/> the day of atonement will cleanse them out&#44; cuts himself<lb/> from salvation &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Cast a halo round the blissful<lb/> day&#44; but do not lay upon it impious hands.  Do not<lb/> destroy what God&#39;s wisdom designed for Israelites the general<lb/> permanence of His priestly nation&#44; uphold it that<lb/> it may not be kept in the increasing darkness overcast beneath forgotten and lost in the lowering clouds of incre&#45;<lb/>&#45;dulity&#44; then shall your light rise in obscurity&#44; and your<lb/> darkness be as the noon day&#44; and the Lord shall guide<lb/> you continually&#59; yea&#44; the mouth of the Lord hath spoken it.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
