<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF7_3</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1885-01" source="" attested="yes">January 1885</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_3_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_3_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_3_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_3_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_3_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_3_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_3_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_3_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_3_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_3_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_3_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_3_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>115</p>
            
            <p>On the first Ministerial<lb/>
                Conference in N. Y. Jan. 1885.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  A brief account of a recent event incident in Judaism of America&#44; may<lb/> not be inappropriate&#44; nor distasteful to my hearers.<lb/>  What was the object of has the Conference of Jewish reverend Mi&#45;<lb/>&#45;nisters just held in the city of New York had in view&#44; and what results<lb/> it produced&#44; are questions that I have been asked<lb/> by many.  It was reasonably thought that the<lb/> meeting of a considerable number of persons holding occupying<lb/> religious offices&#44; but differing widely in their views ideas&#44;<lb/> had for its principal aim a conciliative reconciling of opposite<lb/> ideas opinions to the welfare of Judaism at large.  At the<lb/> outset&#44; I had myself entertained that belief&#44; and had wel&#45;<lb/>&#45;comed in my mind the contemplated conference&#44; as<lb/> means to a blissful end.  I had entertained had no doubt&#44; but<lb/> that a dispassionate discussion of the logical sub&#45;<lb/>&#45;jects would have shown the necessity of checking<lb/> the irregular proceedings of &#34;Reform&#44;&#34;&#45;&#45;as it is called&#45;&#45;&#44;<lb/> and have thus vindicated the course followed by<lb/> cultured conservatives not to venture upon institu changes without Synodic authority.  But the anticipations&#44; which<lb/> others&#44; like myself&#44; had originally formed&#44; were<lb/> frustrated.  The wording of the circular of invitation&#44;<lb/> debarred the possibility of debating theological points.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Hence&#44; nothing properly belonging to the doctrines<lb/> and precepts observances of Judaism was brought forth at<lb/> the conference.  On the contrary&#44; it became clearly mani&#45;<lb/>&#45;fest&#44; on all sides&#44; that the endeavours of the speakers&#39;<lb/> endeavour was to studiously to avoid whatever might savor<lb/> of ritualism and or touch upon Synagogue government.<lb/>  I regretted that circumstance&#44; because some<lb/> enthusiastic friends had urged my attendance&#44;<lb/> fearing that my absence from the ministerial<lb/> meeting might give room to a misconstruction.<lb/>  It might be interpreted as an unyielding deter&#45;<lb/>&#45;mination&#44; on the part of Orthodoxy&#44; to deny every<lb/> concession even when an through by so doing its obstinacy a golden opportunity to effect a re&#45;<lb/>&#45;ligious unification is presented lost.  Well&#58; the<lb/> Conference was amicable&#44; agreeable&#44; very social&#44; and to<lb/> myself personally&#44; beyond expectation&#44; satisfactory.<lb/>  Still&#44; it was not at all calculated to bring or&#45;<lb/>&#45;der out of the chaotic state into which the<lb/> ancestral faith has been involved.  An almost<lb/> fastidious care was prescribed exercised&#44; not to give open congregational <sic>offence</sic>&#44;<lb/> nor wound in the least each other&#39;s suscep&#45;<lb/>&#45;tibilities.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>I do not underrate the advantage of seeing face<lb/> to face men whom&#44; we from principle we may have unsparingly strenuously opposed<lb/> in writing for conscience sake&#44; and hearing from their own lips assurances<lb/> of good will and regard.  It is pleasant&#44; and pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;motive of brotherly feelings.  It is also negatively<lb/> useful&#44; inasmuch as it inspires respect for religion&#44;<lb/> disproving the charge that those who represent it&#44;<lb/> are always at variance.  But Israel of<lb/> America needs a great deal more than that in order to<lb/> be drawn obediently to the Divine Law.  It must<lb/> receive positive signs of a unanimity of sentiments<lb/> among our the Hebrew clergy&#44; touching Mosaic tenets and<lb/> the traditions of the fathers.  His all&#45;import&#45;<lb/>&#45;ant desideratum was not gratified accomplished by the meeting<lb/> which took place&#44; this week lately in New York.<lb/>  Nevertheless Papers were read and approved&#44; and complimentary resolutions were passed&#44; and all parties satisfied&#44; doctrinally nothing was gained.  Nevertheless I do not regret my partial attend&#45;<lb/>&#45;ance&#44; for upon the second of the two days du&#45;<lb/>&#45;ring which it lasted&#44; I read perused myself and listened to <sic>writ&#45;<lb/>&#45;tings</sic> papers&#44; whose contents bid fair to be product&#45;<lb/>&#45;ive of permanent good.  Not to ourselves us immediately&#44; thank fortune&#44; for we do not stand in need of help&#44;<lb/> but to hapless creatures to whom we are bound with sacred ties.<lb/></p>  
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Those writings aimed at pressing forward<lb/> the work of the Universal Israelitish Alliance&#44;<lb/> extending its operations in America&#44; where&#44; outside<lb/> of Pennsylvania&#44; and a few cities beyond it in other in neighboring states&#44; it has<lb/> no foothold.  As I judge that the ministers<lb/> who agreed to exercise their influence in behalf<lb/> of that all&#45;embracing organization are men of<lb/> their word&#44; I look forward anticipate with unfeigned sa&#45;<lb/>&#45;tisfaction to a happy result.  The favored He&#45;<lb/>&#45;brews who dwell in the United States&#44; will prac&#45;<lb/>&#45;tically sympathise with their suffering coreligionists<lb/> in oppressive lands&#44; by aiding in its labors an<lb/> association ever alive to the wants of the perse&#45;<lb/>&#45;cuted.  If such&#44; as I hope&#44; is the issue of<lb/> the first Ministerial Conference&#44; none will sure&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly accuse it of its having been held in vain.<lb/></p>
            <p>But a printed paper which was handed to<lb/> me by its author&#44; just as the Tuesday <sic>the</sic> second day&#39;s morning<lb/> session opened&#44; deserves our consideration&#44; and I<lb/> will deem it advisable to refer to its object.  It advocates conferences<lb/> among teachers&#44; as well as Rabbis&#44; to discuss all<lb/> pending essential questions&#44; and pave the way to harmonious action.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Sensibly&#44; that paper gives precedence to Sab&#45;<lb/>&#45;bath or Sunday Schools reform to all other genuine<lb/> reforms&#59; for&#44; situated as we are in our country&#44;<lb/> those institutions are may be regarded as the germs of a religious life. and<lb/> Upon their the growth the future of Judaism vastly depends.<lb/>  The writer argues with much force the need of an<lb/> exinterchange of thoughts with a view to unify&#44; simplify&#44;<lb/> improve and widen the range of studies pursued<lb/> in our schools.  None will deny that the obj idea is excellent.  All will admit likewise admit that the adoption<lb/> of the same text books&#44; imparting the knowledge<lb/> of Jewish morals and the history of our people<lb/> would be might prove of incalculable advantage.  Our child&#45;<lb/>&#45;ren would early learn to understand&#44; and to<lb/> practise alike their duties&#59; no clashing instruction would<lb/> set them at variance&#44; and peace and kind feelings<lb/> would increase.  At present&#44; the same evil<lb/> existing about prayer books&#44; prevails about school<lb/> books.  Each writer pleads for his own creation&#59;<lb/> he holds that what has proceeded from his pen<lb/> cannot be surpassed.  A pardonable self&#45;esteem<lb/> makes him urge the acceptance of his production.  Possi&#45;<lb/>&#45;bly self&#45;interest may be the leaven mixed up in that desire blending with that solicitation.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>It follows At all events&#44; through that scarcely two schools will be are found<lb/> and scarcely two superintendents who guided by the same standard of tuition regulations&#44;<lb/> in which an identical system prevails is followed.  A year<lb/> ago I opposed on this pulpit and in the Jewish<lb/> press&#44; the proposition emanating from the West that<lb/> catechisms and historical volumes of one character and<lb/> Diction should be introduced in all schools.  I op&#45;<lb/>&#45;posed it notwithstanding my advocacy of uniformity of method in training our youths&#59; because the person who headed the scheme<lb/> had acknowledged&#44; with otherwise laudable candor&#44; that he<lb/> meant it in the interest of &#34;Reform&#34;&#45;&#45;so called.  Now&#44;<lb/> he who proposes the plan of harmonising our children&#39;s<lb/> system of tuition mode manner of instruction&#44; belongs to the same party&#45;&#45;if the<lb/> term may be allowed&#44; yet he displays a liberal conciliatory spirit&#44;<lb/> commending itself to all parties&#44; and offers suggest&#45;<lb/>&#45;ions deserving of our approval.  The writer of the<lb/> paper to which I have reference sees the injudi&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciousness of formulating our teaching after that<lb/> of gentilism&#59; he complains that we accept volumes<lb/> on Biblical or post&#45;Biblical history at the hands of<lb/> the Church&#44; instead of composing some ourselves&#44; based<lb/> upon our Rabbinical and post&#45;Rabbinical literature&#44;<lb/> so inexhaustively rich&#44; and so adapted to our purposes.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>He approves of illustrating subjects in scriptures<lb/> and in later writings by pictures&#44; as means to reach let<lb/> the attention of young pupils be <sic>rivetted</sic> thereon&#44; but he is<lb/> strongly against such engravings such as those with which<lb/> Sunday school books abound&#44; and which are mostly<lb/> borrowed from non&#45;Israelites to benefit a religion that<lb/> we repudiate.  A feature which I like<lb/> best much in that paper&#44; is a recommendation to make<lb/> the study of the Hebrew language obligatory upon<lb/> our young sons&#44; and not optional&#44; as customary now<lb/> a days.  I also fully coincide with the writer<lb/> that to interest the young in the sacred language&#44;<lb/> the teaching must be less mechanical&#59; that more<lb/> life must be breathed into it&#44; that the imparting<lb/> of elementary rules&#44; always dry and wearisome&#44; must<lb/> be varied with a simultaneous gradual training at the same time<lb/> into the translation of words &#38; of and phrases.  Many are<lb/> the points on which the writer and myself would<lb/> act in perfect accord of sentiments&#44; yet I never<lb/> could recommend his plan.  My objection to it<lb/> rises principally from the <sic>irronconcilable</sic> divergence of<lb/> opinion between believers in revelation and unbelievers.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Could I advocate the adoption of a catechisms&#44; or<lb/> of historical books which ignore altogether the cere&#45;<lb/>&#45;monial code of the Pentateuch&#44; and are perfectly keep are entirely<lb/> silent about the oral laws&#63;  Walking in the light<lb/> I have received&#44; I do not see the possibility<lb/> of a Judaism&#44; without Jewish laws ceremonialism&#59; of a history<lb/> of our people&#44; without the explaining and enforcing of fasts and festivals. and<lb/> fasts.  It is all well to make the ethical<lb/> portion of our faith its ground work&#44; and convince explain to point out to<lb/> our offspring that nothing which is humanising<lb/> and refining needs be borrowed from our neighbors<lb/> of another creed.  Unless our progeny are told shown in<lb/> all earnestness and very early in life&#44; when impres&#45;<lb/>&#45;sions are lasting the necessity of outward forms&#59; unless they are convincingly told the ceremonial practices of<lb/> Mosaism and traditionalism are essential to our<lb/> national existence&#44; our sons and daughters will<lb/> be apt to exchange the unpopular Synagogue for<lb/> the popular Church.  No&#58; so long as Reform<lb/> arrogates to itself the right to draw a dividing<lb/> line between what suits its ever changing reason&#44;<lb/> and that which the prophets and the sages have<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>ordained&#44; so long we will be compelled to discard their its<lb/> books&#44; and reject its plans.<lb/></p>
            <p>But just because we prefer to remaining alone<lb/> to dealing falsely with the Torah&#44; therefore<lb/> ought we to keep close to each other&#44; to join<lb/> hands in whatever will give permanence to<lb/> our institutions.  We ought to improve them better their condition to support<lb/> them amply&#44; to increase their number and popularity.  In a word&#59; we<lb/> must prove that our conservativism is not iron&#45;bound&#44; but enlightened<lb/> and progressive visibly&#44; incontestably progressive.<lb/></p>
            <p>&#40;Here followed an address to a Bar Mitzvah&#41;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
