<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF7_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_1_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>158</p>
            
            <p>About Sabbath&#45;breaking<lb/>
                &#38; the Convention of B B in 1879<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  A school which commends itself<lb/> to the sympathy of all the right&#45;minded&#44; exists in the<lb/> state of Virginia.  Its foundation is due to a senti&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment&#44; that recognizes in every being gifted with the<lb/> power of uttering words intelligently&#44; a capacity for self&#45;<lb/>improvement.  If that institution succeeds&#44; as I trust&#44;<lb/> in the beneficent ends it purposes to attain&#44; it will<lb/> make the theories&#44; which man&#39;s narrow wisdom has built&#44;<lb/> dissolve into air.  It will show that divisions of races&#44;<lb/> like divisions of languages&#44; are not the effect of a dif&#45;<lb/>&#45;ference of descent in the origin work of creation&#59; that<lb/> not because a portion of the human family&#44; styled<lb/> Caucasians&#44; is through a freak of nature&#44; of a superior<lb/> breed&#44; has knowledge spread far and wide in its midst.<lb/>  It will demonstrably show prove&#44; that others&#44; fancifully<lb/> classified as Indians or Ethiopians&#44; if equally favored<lb/> by circumstances would have risen as high in the scale<lb/> of civilization.  The Virginia school will afford the<lb/> clearest evidence&#44; that to say&#44; this caste was by physi&#45;<lb/>&#45;cal confirmation intended to serve&#44; and that to rule&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>this was placed beyond the reach of progress&#44; and<lb/> that possesses an exclusive right to monopolize learn&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing&#44; as unscientific as well as unrighteous.  I have<lb/> always considered it wrong in any&#44; but specially<lb/> in an Israelite&#44; to draw dividing lines among<lb/> God&#39;s sentient creatures.  Believing in the Hebrew<lb/> Bible&#44; and unequivocally admitting a common ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;traction to mankind&#44; I held fast to the doctrine<lb/> of human perfectibility&#44; and rejoiced at every effort<lb/> to bring it about.  I do not scruple<lb/> to acknowledge&#44; that&#44; while glorying in being a<lb/> Jew&#44;&#45;&#45;divinely chosen&#44; not as an object of predilection&#44;<lb/> but as a receptacle of precious truths&#45;&#45;&#44; I have admired &#34;the<lb/> Society of Friends&#34; for its abiding confidence in the<lb/> crowning work of God&#44; and for its unwearied endeavours<lb/> to draw out by gentleness and kindly consideration&#44;<lb/> whatever is inherently good in the nature of man.<lb/>  I am not certain that the Hampton Institute&#44;<lb/> in which the lean&#45;savage red&#45;skin&#91;n&#93;ed&#44; and the illiterate<lb/> black learn to copy the whites&#44; in what is worth emu&#45;<lb/>&#45;lating&#44; receives support from that liberal denomi&#45;<lb/>&#45;nation.  I incline to think that the Quaker<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>element is felt there&#44; as are many a philanthro&#45;<lb/>&#45;pic undertaking&#44; but my reference to it and to<lb/> the school patronized by the progressive&#44; was meant<lb/> this day&#44; as a lesson to our own selves&#44; the disciples<lb/> of Moses.<lb/></p>
            <p>Among the agencies put forth to improve the in&#45;<lb/>&#45;mates of the Virginia institution is the publication<lb/> of pamphlets&#44; written in easy style.  The topics<lb/> discussed are moral and historical.  They broaden the<lb/> mind&#44; without fatiguing it.  They appeal to the<lb/> heart&#44; softening the roughness of character&#44; and refusing<lb/> manners.  I was lent one of these tracts.  I read<lb/> it and my gratification increased as I proceeded.  In it<lb/> a Christian woman related to heathens and Christians&#44;<lb/> what the greatest prophet among Jews had recommended&#44;<lb/> in order to keep health and strength&#44; the chief instruments<lb/> to work out human happiness.  She assured her<lb/> pupils that by attending to the rules&#44; Moses laid<lb/> down for cleanliness&#44;&#45;&#45;purity in the flesh&#44; in thought<lb/> and words&#45;&#45;&#44; practical righteousness is observed&#44; and we<lb/> do what is just to ourselves&#44; and to one another.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Mark&#33;  Not a minister still clinging to &#34;old<lb/> Judaism&#34; spoke in a strain&#44; laudatory of our law&#45;<lb/>giver&#59; but a person born outside of the ancient faith.<lb/>  She explained the wor depth of wisdom discovered in command&#45;<lb/>&#45;ments&#44; which concern our eating and drinking&#44; the<lb/> internal arrangement of our households&#44; the treatment<lb/> of bodily ailments&#44; the performance of all physical<lb/> functions.  The teacher did not paint that por&#45;<lb/>&#45;trait in black colours and call it&#44; as some Doctors<lb/> of Divinity in Israel term levitical and ceremonial<lb/> precepts&#44; &#34;the kitchen&#91;&#63;&#93; of religion&#44;&#34; &#34;the Ghetto&#39;s regime&#34;.<lb/>  Oh no&#33; she pictured it in brightly&#44; and pointed out<lb/> one by one the beauties and merits her delineation possesses.<lb/>  As natural&#44; the authoress of the pamphlet&#44;<lb/> looked upon the laws of the Pentateuch from a different<lb/> stand&#45;point than we Israelites ought to regard them.  For<lb/> that we must make every allowance should be made.  Referring<lb/> to the ordinance of resting one day in seven&#44; she<lb/> remarked that a change in that regulation&#44; would must<lb/> be inevitably injurious to our constitution.  The<lb/> attempt to alter it was once made tried by the French<lb/> revolutionists&#44; who&#44; running to excesses&#44; would fain<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>dethrone the Supreme&#44; and set up fallible reason<lb/> as an all sufficient guide&#44; but the undertaking<lb/> proved a dead failure.  The twelfth days Sabbath&#44;<lb/> or rather revelry&#44; to spite religion&#44; did not agree<lb/> with man&#39;s muscles&#44; and the wisdom of Moses<lb/> was vindicated.  But that which Miss<lb/> Helen W. Ludlow declares a measure preservative<lb/> of health and strength&#44; the sacred pages we have<lb/> recited this morning&#44; represent besides&#44; as our<lb/> people&#39;s first entrance into the temple of spirituality.<lb/>  The Sabbath was the first statute whose keeping<lb/> would grace our persons with the badge of a celestial<lb/> order.  It is the most honorable of all badges&#44; because<lb/> it comes from the highest.  The gift of the Sabbath<lb/> &#40;&#91;Hebrew&#93;&#41; had precedence to the glory of Sinai.<lb/>  The evidence of its divine origin was renewed fifty two<lb/> times in a year&#44; during forty years.  A whole popu&#45;<lb/>&#45;lation visibly saw it and transmitted it to posterity&#44;<lb/> that it might be never forgotten.  The master of<lb/> eloquence expressed it well&#44; when he said &#34;If thou<lb/> refrainest thy foot for the sake of the Sabbath.....<lb/> &#40;then wilt thou be seem&#44; even as if&#41; riding on the altitudes of the earth&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Is it not then a sign of our decline&#44; that a body of<lb/> men trying to prove the genuineness of its mission by<lb/> displaying before the world a badge&#44; on which is embla&#45;<lb/>&#45;zoned in golden letters &#34;sons of the covenant&#34; did not<lb/> restrain the foot on the Sabbath day&#63;  Is it not astound&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing&#44; that a rare occasion should be marked by the dese&#45;<lb/>&#45;cration of the all&#45;important statute of God&#63;<lb/>
                I shall pass no strictures on the selection of the place when<lb/> hospitably to entertain Hebrew delegates&#44; during their<lb/> five day&#39;s sojourn in our midst.  When I recall<lb/> the incident which occurred last summer in Milwaukee&#44;<lb/> I congratulate myself&#44; at all events&#44; on its not having<lb/> been reenacted in Philadelphia.  For there&#44; to welcome<lb/> a convention represented by a number of our ministers&#44;<lb/> food which the letter of the Law forbid&#44; was served at<lb/> a sumptuous banquet.  The inconsistent madness<lb/> was not perpetrated at the repast given last week<lb/> in our city.  But I cannot forbear lamenting the<lb/> fact that with a few exceptions&#44; the two hundred and fifty<lb/> men who wl met at St George&#39;s hall&#44; in the capacity of<lb/> exponents of Jewish principles&#44; <sic>travelled</sic> on the Sabbath to arrive<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>here the following Sunday.  What avail rhetorical<lb/> polish and oratorical eloquence to extol Mosaic verities&#44;<lb/> of that which underlies Mosaism is uprooted&#63;  Oh&#33;<lb/> give me the bil blunt honesty of our fathers&#44; their rough<lb/> sincerity&#33;  Admit&#44; that asylums and hospi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tals&#44; public libraries and Hebrew consulates are aided<lb/> or maintained by the order of Beni Berith&#44; what<lb/>of the fosterer of those organizations&#44; is conspicuous<lb/> for the rejection of the Sabbath&#63;  Can it lay claim<lb/> to having fulfilled the mission which the title it bears<lb/> implies&#63;  Most assuredly not.  Beneficent it may<lb/> be called&#59; humanitarian may confessedly be a fitting<lb/> name&#44; but &#34;custodian and propagator of the covenant&#44;&#34;<lb/> would sound like a satire when applied to a corporation&#44;<lb/> heedless of the sanctity of the Sabbath.  For&#44; I find written<lb/> in our Parasha &#34;See&#44; that the Lord hath given you the Sabbath&#34;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#39;See&#44; the gem given to your safe&#45;<lb/>&#45;keeping&#34;  Grace had her olympiads&#44; Rome her ides&#44; Israel<lb/> alone had the Sabbath&#44; the spiritual day&#44; typical of that<lb/> in which the righteous sit enthroned in glorious repose.<lb/>  The recognition of revelation is interwoven with that precept.<lb/>  Trample upon it&#44; and the very heart of Judaism ceases to throb.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Hence upon it more than upon any other ceremonial tenets&#44; have<lb/> prophets of early and later ages dwelt with frequency and<lb/> emphasis.  I find no fault with the noble&#45;minded<lb/> Christian&#44; who instructs her charges to rest one day out of<lb/> seven&#44; in obedience to the laws of nature&#44; which are also<lb/> the laws of God.  I lodge no complaint whatever against<lb/> Quakers&#44; who recognize only the p ministry of morality.<lb/>  My reproof is directed against individuals&#44; who ought<lb/> to see in the seventh day a seal to their credentials<lb/> as priests of a grand idea&#44; and notwithstanding many<lb/> public professions&#44; defile it in an open manner.<lb/>  Surely&#58; they might have so disposed apportioned their time&#44; that the<lb/> revision of the Bene Berith ritual&#44; should not occasion<lb/> the violation the violation of the ancestral code&#44; even if<lb/> compelled thereby to forego diversions&#44; and a convivial gathering.<lb/>  What a glory it would have shed on the order&#44; if its general<lb/> assembly&#44; mindful of a religious duty&#44; had not contemplated<lb/> the consuming devoting of nearly a whole day to purposes foreign to<lb/> the object&#59; if it had begun its setting a day later&#44; to restrain<lb/> the foot on the sabbath&#33;  We would now point to it&#44; with pride&#44;<lb/> in the face of a gentile world&#44; for honesty of professions and unswerving consistency.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>But the censure I felt prompted to express is not unqua&#45;<lb/>&#45;lified.  I rejoice that to approve has fallen likewise to<lb/> my lot.  The last convention of at Philadelphia rose to its<lb/> height&#44; when it acknowledged the services which the &#34;Alliance<lb/> Israelite Universelle&#34; has rendered to Judaism.  Becoming<lb/> was the request that a supporting arm be extended to an<lb/> organization which had drawn our brethren in the East<lb/> out of the hiding place wherein they had sunk for centuries&#59;<lb/> which has forced them to walk erect&#44; which is laboring<lb/> hard to remove the crust of ignorance and superstition whi that<lb/> ages of oppression have formed.  Yes&#58; under the direction<lb/> of that wide&#45;spread corporation a systematic scheme for cultivating the<lb/> soul&#44; and the mind is chasing way sloth and clannishness.<lb/>  Money is freely expended to elevate a portions of our brethren<lb/> hitherto cut off from the refining influences of civilized society.<lb/>  A general atmosphere is being created&#44; in which&#44; under through God&#39;s<lb/> blessing&#44; freedom will blossom&#44; and pure Judaism bud and<lb/> yield flowers.  The American order of B. B. has urged that the<lb/> festivity of Purim be enhanced by sending the European<lb/> association greetings and tangible signs of approval.  That<lb/> &#91;&#63;&#93; I heartily endorse.  Joyful&#44; doubly joyful will be<lb/> the memory of our deliverance through such evidence of our brotherhood<lb/> &#40;Here follows an exhortation to members of the BBO.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
