<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF7_8</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1887-12" source="" attested="yes">December 1887</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_8_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_8_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_8_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_8_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_8_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_8_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_8_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_8_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_8_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_8_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_8_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_8_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>74</p>
            <p>A defense of the Pharisees<lb/>
                Dec. 87<lb/>
                It was lengthened &#38; improved in delivering it<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  The Synagogue is not the arena<lb/> of polemics and and during my long ministration I have endeavoured to render it a vehicle of instruction&#44; as God has given me to understand duty.  I solemnly declare&#44; once for all&#44;<lb/> that denunciations from here hurled from hence at the recreancy<lb/> of Jews&#44; are not the gratification of vulgar spite personalities.<lb/>  They are not in the least another&#44; the indulgence of a rankling ill&#45;will<lb/> against any whom I consider deem inimical to the principles<lb/> by which I live.  I condemn desertions from the faith what I consider such&#44;&#44; but personal<lb/> hatred does not harbor in in my breast.  It is foreign to my nature.  Besides&#59; my<lb/> course is nearly run&#59; I have nothing to gain by trying<lb/> to win a victory over religious antagonists&#44; and secure<lb/> by my public utterances&#44; the plaudits of the very few who share my sentiments&#59;<lb/> by my public utterances&#44; nor do I&#44; at my age and<lb/> after so many ineffectual trials to raise the stand&#45;<lb/>&#45;ard of traditional Judaism aloft&#44; have a wish to engage<lb/> in exciting controversies.  I know but too well&#44;<lb/> that&#44; as it was thrown in my teeth last Monday&#44; and as told for to my vexation by Eastern correspondents of a Western Weeklies&#44;<lb/> I represent a cause which&#44; to all appearances&#44; has<lb/> no longer a hold on the American born&#59; that&#44; barring<lb/> some rare exceptions&#44; I can boast of no following<lb/> even among those&#44; who see fit still to retain my<lb/> ministerial services.  Too It is sadly humiliatingly but true.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>If I refer this day to another man&#39;s pulpit<lb/> speaking&#44; it is I do so to place myself aright before my<lb/> congregants and vindicate no offended history.  Indeed&#44;<lb/> this duty also I would also refrain from performing&#44;<lb/> lest I give room to apprehensions&#44; to the idea lest I arouse the thoughts that<lb/> petty jealousy dictates my words&#44; were it not<lb/> that some who attend the Synagogue in which I<lb/> chant prayers and deliver talk lectures&#44; frequent &#34;temples&#34;<lb/> while I am misrepresented and where facts are inexcu&#45;<lb/>&#45;sably distorted.  We may lament that the secular<lb/> press should be made the vehicle for conveying im&#45;<lb/>&#45;ressions derogatory to the character of the custodians<lb/> of our belief&#44; but I shall not retaliate.  I would not&#44;<lb/> at any pride&#44; let the Christian world construe re&#45;<lb/>futations and rejoinders into clerical quarrels.  Enough that we are aware of the sore plague of ritual Jewish divisions.  But<lb/> those who habitually listen to me from this desk&#44;<lb/> must do me justice.  They will have observed<lb/> how destitute of truth was the assertion that I &#34;com&#45;<lb/>pared to Antiochus Epiphanes&#34;&#45;&#45;the arch fiend who<lb/> vowed to exterminate Judaism&#45;&#45;my brethren &#34;who do<lb/> not keep three separate sets of dishes&#44; one for<lb/> milk diets&#44; one for meat diets and one for the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Passover Feast&#44;&#34; and likewise &#34;because commer&#45;<lb/>&#45;cial <sic>travellers</sic>&#34; among my coreligionists &#34;do not<lb/> carry&#44; in addition to their three or four trunks&#44; one<lb/> more yet&#44; that shall contain a little miniature<lb/> kitchen with Kosher supplies for a three months&#39;<lb/> trip.&#34;  Refresh your memories&#44; brethren&#59; you will<lb/> recall this fact.  On the Sabbath commemorative of<lb/> the deeds of the heroic Maccabees&#44; I implored Israelites<lb/> to honor the unselfishness of their old defenders&#44; by<lb/> the rehabilitation of Mosaic ordinances for the perpe&#45;<lb/>&#45;tuation of which Mattathias and his gallant sons<lb/> staked their lives.  I called friends of the Asmoneans those who strive to eternize the Torah&#44; and enemies of the Asmoneans those who deliberately repudiate it.  I was asked for but declined the<lb/> full publication of my discourse&#44; for my ambition never<lb/> ran high&#44; still from synopses inserted in various<lb/> papers&#44; Philadelphians may judge how well follow&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed was the subject brought forward last Sunday the first day of this week with a view<lb/> to expose me to disgrace as an unmitigated bigot&#44;<lb/> and to ridicule me&#44; as incapable of distinguishing between<lb/> essentials in our religion&#44; and matters of secondary<lb/> importance&#59; to make me a laughing stock in the presence of a thronged attend&#45;<lb/>&#45;ance at Sunday&#45;services in our city&#44; an assemblage who doubt&#45;<lb/>less will have learnt to consider me a dullard far behind the age.  Enough But&#44; no more of this.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Pained as I naturally felt at reading myself<lb/> in the Ledger the butt of contempt&#44; I was most deep&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly chagrined to see Israel&#39;s my people&#39;s history maligned beyond<lb/> measure&#44; as means a medium to extol the founder of Christianity<lb/> and applauding his alleged mission.  What the<lb/> man of Nazareth really was&#59; what he attempted to do&#44; and<lb/> the consequences of his endeavours&#44; are points that<lb/> I deem it inappropriate to discuss in a house devoted<lb/> to the service worship of Israel&#39;s God.  I contend that<lb/> to tell Jews their duties&#44; even at the risk of be&#45;<lb/>&#45;coming unpopular&#59; to furnish the young with<lb/> instruction in their past&#44; and fit them as sincere<lb/> upholders of their belief in the future&#44; should con&#45;<lb/>&#45;stitute the purport of pulpit teachings in Syna&#45;<lb/>&#45;gogues.  Our neighbors of another creed&#44; have men<lb/> who expound the origin and doctrine and the origin of the Church.<lb/>  But when a Hebrew preacher&#44; A catching the spirit<lb/> of the New Testament which calls the Pharisees &#34;serpents and vipers&#44;&#34;<lb/> gives his sanction to those offensive ignominious appellations&#44; and<lb/> when he moreover pictures the materialistic Saddu&#45;<lb/>&#45;cees&#44; as the exponents of the culture of the time&#44;<lb/> I must caution my Congregants against views that are<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>unjewish&#44; untrue&#44; and heretical.<lb/></p>
            <p>I should would repeat myself&#44; if I undertook to explain<lb/> in details the nature of the three sects existing<lb/> in Judea&#44; during the latter part of the second com&#45;<lb/>&#45;monwealth&#44; for it may be remembered that in<lb/> the course of my post&#45;biblical series&#44; which I hope<lb/> to resume&#44; I offered all the information that I could<lb/> reliably draw about the Essenes&#44; the Sadduccees and<lb/> Pharisees.  Those who heard me then know that<lb/> the first named were never numerous&#44; and their asce&#45;<lb/>&#45;tisism&#44; ill according with the religion of Moses which<lb/> is eminently practical&#44; must have sprung from<lb/> the mistaken idea that to shun the corruption fos&#45;<lb/>&#45;tered by Roman domination&#44; a life of retirement<lb/> and voluntary privations was virtue.  The very<lb/> opposite of the Essenes were the Sadducees.  They re&#45;<lb/>&#45;presented&#44; not the culture&#45;&#45;as asserted&#45;&#45;but the depraved notions of the time.<lb/>  They did not leave testimonies of their intellectual powers&#59; we only meet with their disputations regarding traditions not spiritual advancement predicated on the belief in an all&#45;seeing and perfect Judge.<lb/>  Pleasure seeking was to them the aim of existence&#44; for<lb/> for they held that God is too exalted to take cognizance of human affairs&#44; and that beyond the grave eternal silence alone has dominion.<lb/>  No reckoning of our deeds&#44; no remorse for a <sic>mispent</sic><lb/> life&#44; no joys for virtues practised.  <sic>Punctilius</sic> were<lb/> they the Sadducees about the letter of the Law in support of their skepticism&#44; but they cared they cared not for its spirit. nothing for the inner sense of Holy Writ.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Those epicureans&#59; deniers of a hereafter&#44;<lb/> could not entertain fellow&#45;feelings for the poor<lb/> and the lowly stationed&#44; and they were deservedly dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;liked by the multitudes.  The Pharisee&#44; on the con&#45;<lb/>&#45;trary&#44; exercised great influence over the masses&#44; be&#45;<lb/>&#45;cause they were the friends of the of their fellow&#45;beings humbly situated&#44;<lb/> &#38; sought their elevation&#44; &#38; infused into their souls fortitude<lb/> in sorrow&#59; gratitude for Providential favors.<lb/>  The Pharisees taught that there is an eye which is<lb/> never closed over our actions&#44; an ears ever opened<lb/> to the cry of oppression&#44; a book in which all<lb/> we do is registered&#44; and that a strict account will<lb/> be asked&#44; verily&#58; None have ever been more maligned calumniated<lb/> than the conservators of the oral interpretations<lb/> of the Scriptures&#44; yet to them we owe all which<lb/> is of valueable after the closing of the sacred canon&#59;<lb/> such sublime maxims as embodied in Aboth&#44; or<lb/> the Ethics of the fathers&#44; such a civil and criminal legislation as<lb/> incorporated in the Talmud&#44; and before which the<lb/> twelve tables and the &#91;&#63;&#93; of the Romans<lb/> lose their prestige&#59; such astronomical calculations as<lb/> reflected in a calendar <sic>marvellous</sic> in its construction and utility.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>A person must deliberately wipe out from<lb/> our annals&#44; the names of a Simeon the Just&#44;<lb/> of a Hillel the meek teacher of a Johanna ben<lb/> Zaccha&#239;&#44; the restorer guardian angel of our sacred lore nationality academical lore&#44; the names of<lb/> hosts of Sages&#44; and moralists&#44; and historians and chiefs<lb/> of Academies&#59; he must ignore centuries of mental<lb/> activity who decries the Pharisees as foes to progress&#44;<lb/> making life &#34;one constant burden&#44;&#34; denying it all joys.<lb/>  While the Grecian &#91;&#63;&#93; for philosophy with which the<lb/> Sadducees were permeated produced no good&#44; and the ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;travagant pietism of the Essenes&#44; yielded no advantage&#44;<lb/> the learning and sagacity of the Pharisees have given<lb/> us a literature which forms even now the study<lb/> of archaeologists&#44; philologists lexicographers and scientists.  But<lb/> more than that we do owe the Pharisees.  We are in&#45;<lb/>&#45;debted to them for the Synagogue&#44; which has maintained<lb/> us alive through an unparalleled dispersion&#44; for<lb/> the correct understanding of the unpunctuated Torah&#44;<lb/> for national prayers&#44; for home worship&#44; fastening<lb/> the family ties&#44; and promoting those domestic vir&#45;<lb/>&#45;tues&#44; which were wont to form our well founded<lb/> boast&#44; but which&#44; alas&#33; are being cast away.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>There were hypocrites among the Pharisees&#44;&#45;&#45;and<lb/> I wonder if modern our liberal &#34;Reformers&#34; claim exemption from<lb/> that sin&#45;&#45;but the Talmud which is essentially the<lb/> work of Phariseism&#44; points to such with a finger of<lb/> scorn.  It enumerates several kinds of imposters in<lb/> their ranks&#44; and does not spare them&#44; but exposes<lb/> their falsity as found unequivocally as the man of Naza&#45;<lb/>&#45;reth when he reproached his contemporaries for making<lb/> their phylacteries broad&#44; and enlarging the board<lb/> of their garments&#44; in order to gain the uppermost rooms at<lb/> feasts&#44; and the Chief seats in the Synagogues&#44; and<lb/> receive greetings in the markets&#44; and be called &#34;Rabbis<lb/> Rabbi&#34;.  It is the Talmudists who declare&#44; that<lb/> among those whom against whom the portals of heaven will be found shut&#44; are<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; the sect of hypocrites.<lb/></p>
            <p>In sorrow&#44; not in anger&#44; I say it.  The fruits of Western<lb/> planting has been now engrafted also on our tree.  I<lb/> am made to swallow their taste its bitterness taste&#44; and the field<lb/> which Israel&#39;s sages have cultivated would become<lb/> poisoned therewith&#44; were it not that history and<lb/> truth are the Cherubim keeping it&#44; and thrusting<lb/> back intruders.  And so may it always be.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
