<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF8_4</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1888-01" source="" attested="yes">1888</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_4_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_4_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_4_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_4_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_4_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_4_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_4_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_4_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_4_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_4_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_4_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_4_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>114</p>
            
            <p>On the Jewish Minister&#39;s conference<lb/>
                88<lb/>
                I<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  It may not be inopportune briefly to relate<lb/> what the conference of Hebrew Ministers&#44; held in our<lb/> city this week&#44; the did&#44; or tried well usefully to accomplish usefully  That<lb/> Jewish preachers who&#44; anomalously enough&#44; are not of<lb/> one the same mind on scriptural and traditional doctrines&#44; should<lb/> meet in a friendly spirit and dispassionately discuss<lb/> important questions&#44; I consider of some advantage.<lb/>  If the Talmudical maxim that scholars coming toge&#45;<lb/>&#45;ther will improve each other in the knowledge of ri&#45;<lb/>&#45;tual decisions &#91;Hebrew&#93; may not be ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;plicable in the present instance&#44; the sentence of So&#45;<lb/>&#45;lomon may imperceptibly yet effectually be applyable fit.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;As iron sharpens iron&#44;<lb/> so does one man sharpen himself on his neighbor&#39;s coun&#45;<lb/>&#45;tenance&#44;&#34; meaning that by contact&#44; some of the rough<lb/> edges of certain individualities&#44; will be smoothed down &#38; wear away.  Thus by way of illustration&#44; it<lb/> may happen that a pleasing intercourse with temperate<lb/> conservatives&#44; will finally influence for good intemperate<lb/> radicals.  So may it be.  I was glad&#44; at all events&#44; for the honor of our<lb/> city to have heard the President of the Convention openly<lb/> acknowledge declare at the concluding session&#44; that the meetings<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>in our midst proved the most satisfactory&#44; because<lb/> it was they were characterized by a calm treatment of the sub&#45;<lb/>&#45;jects brought forth&#44; and by an obvious wish to act harmo&#45;<lb/>&#45;niously&#44; to a purpose.  However&#44; without not to fatigue my hearers&#44; I will say that the two propositions<lb/> offered at the conference&#44; and which I consider deem worthy of<lb/> your special attention are the following&#58; First&#59; to draw<lb/> the working classes to the public worship and bring<lb/> them under religious influences.  Secondly&#59; to simplify<lb/> the funeral and subsequent mourning services&#44; and make them<lb/> consolatorily edifying.  Having been appointed a chairman of<lb/> the committee to which the first proposition was refer&#45;<lb/>&#45;red&#44; I bestowed on it serious reflection.  It was<lb/> contended by  Its author contended&#44; that laborers and employees<lb/> of any description&#44; cannot spare the time to attend<lb/> Synagogue services&#44; and that therefore one evening<lb/> at some stated intervals&#44; ought&#44; at least&#44; to be set apart<lb/> for their spiritual and moral tuition.  He argued furthermore that even when<lb/> those journeymen have time at their disposal&#44; they do<lb/> not choose to enter Synagogues&#44; where they would be<lb/> regarded as intruders or unwelcome paupers&#44; and that<lb/> therefore a semi&#45;congregational union ought to be<lb/> separately formed among such&#44; and be encouraged by their employers<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>and fostered and preserved by the local Jewish Minis&#45;<lb/>&#45;ters.  These were the main points strongly<lb/> presented&#44; others were connected therewith as corollary.<lb/>  Now&#44; Brethren&#44; that the Israelites in the humblest<lb/> walks of life should find every facility to unite in<lb/> holy conventions with men and women of their faith&#44;<lb/> none will deny who is imbued with the spirit under&#45;<lb/>&#45;lying the Mosaic legislation.  Our inspired lawgiver<lb/> would that&#44; without the slightest distinction&#44; all might<lb/> become the recipients of an essential instruction and the be<lb/> recognized as integral parts of communal gatherings assemblages.  For&#44;<lb/> thank God&#44; no division of castes has ever existed in<lb/> Israel.  But I hold that a working classes semi&#45;Congregation&#44; would<lb/> destroy the unity&#44; designed by the greatest of teachers.<lb/>  It would create a division&#44; insidious and self&#45;humiliating.<lb/>  In my report I did not favor a proposition which&#44; appeared to my judgment&#44; anti&#45;de&#45;<lb/>mocratic&#44; but I do will not disguise the fact that another<lb/> powerful motive influenced prompted my action.  I saw that<lb/> the acceptance of the plan would inevitably result in<lb/> a Sunday evening service&#44; just as the plea of incapacity<lb/> to observe the Sabbath of the Decalogue by wealthy<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>employers led to their tacit consecration of the morn&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing of the day hallowed as a compromise in the 4th century of the vulgar era&#44; to a sun&#45;god or to a god&#39;s<lb/> son coexisting with the father&#44; after agreeably to the mind&#45;bewildering<lb/> dogma of the Nazarenes Church.  I could not be party to<lb/> such a proposition.  After a long debate&#44; action on<lb/> the resolution was postponed to the next conference in<lb/> the spring.  Meanwhile the scheme may have been<lb/> more maturely considered in all its hearings at by local meetings and personal interviews&#44; and possibly<lb/> be adopted in a shape acceptable from a Jewish<lb/> stand&#45;point.  But I ask&#44; my brethren&#59; is it not deplorably<lb/> true that employe&#233;s and laborers&#45;&#45;to speak par&#45;<lb/>&#45;ticularly of them such&#45;&#45;seldom&#44; save perhaps twice a<lb/> year conventionally meet for worship&#63;  Is it not deplorably<lb/> true that lessons on the laws tenets and practices and<lb/> history and literature of their own people are withheld<lb/> from most the vast majority of them&#44; because the opportunities to acquire<lb/> that learning lie beyond their reach&#63;  We may grieve<lb/> over the desecration of the Sabbath&#45;&#45;and happy would<lb/> I indeed feel&#44; if it were in my power to rehabilitate<lb/> the day of Sinai&#45;&#45;&#44; but ought we not to ponder f<lb/> deeply and prayfully that we may discover devise some means<lb/> by which to hold our own within our fold&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Note the efforts of Christians to proselytize&#59; mark their<lb/> planting&#44; in the very neighborhood of our thickets<lb/> population&#44; institutions of propaganda.  Must we<lb/> fold our arms&#44; and&#44; seeing wolves ready to tear our<lb/> flesh from off our bodies and folding our arms instinctively cry &#34;We can&#39;t help it&#63;&#34;<lb/>  In my report to the convention&#44; I counselled mere liberality<lb/> on the part of congregations&#59; their offering of their Sy&#45;<lb/>&#45;nagogues&#44; or vestry rooms at any time&#45;&#45;except when<lb/> it might lead the mind astray&#45;&#45;to all classes for wor&#45;<lb/>&#45;ship and instruction.  For&#44; as a rule&#44; our Synagouges<lb/> in America are exclusive sovereignties&#44; respectively swayed by a few moneyed<lb/> men&#44; who generally hold their ministers tight to<lb/> their purse&#45;strings.  No wonder that the indepen&#45;<lb/>&#45;dent poor keep aloof.  Notably so in our luxurious<lb/> age and in this country&#44; which when simplicity is discarded&#44; and luxury usurps its place&#44; when Synagogues are com&#45;<lb/>&#45;plex bodies&#44; containing various parts&#44; each of which<lb/> entails an expenditure&#44; swelling up extravagantly in the aggregate.<lb/>  They Temples are inaccessible to our high&#45;spirited middle<lb/> classes&#44; or shunned by them as aristocratic concerns.<lb/>  Thus&#44; in a manner&#44; we encourage the objectionable<lb/> Hebroth system&#44; which extending far and wide&#44; to the discredit<lb/> of God&#39;s service&#44; and to the alienation of the rising generation&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>who&#44; unimpressed and untaught&#44; will leave us<lb/> to become wedded to indifferentism&#44; or to make com&#45;<lb/>&#45;mon cause with the adherents of the popular belief.<lb/>  In my report&#44; I urged that the Synagogue should<lb/> stimulate a noble rivalry among all associations<lb/> tending to our people&#39;s progress&#44; alike religious<lb/> and mental.  I indirectly arraigned our congregations<lb/> for a lack of that spirit of solidarity that recog&#45;<lb/>&#45;nizes our intercommunal interests.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;  &#34;All Israelites are a guarantee for<lb/> each other&#39;s social standing.&#34;  But as it is<lb/> always easy to find fault and theorize&#44; and very extremely<lb/> difficult to remedy existing evils&#44; I ask crave your counsel<lb/> in a thought that struck me of late&#44; and your concur&#45;<lb/>&#45;rence in carrying it out&#44; if it be at all practicable.<lb/>  I am assured that in Paris&#44; whose Jewish population<lb/> may compare with ours&#44; regarding a prevalent neglect<lb/> of the Sabbath&#44; Zadoc Kahn&#45;&#45;Grand Rabbi at<lb/> the Metropolis and deservedly esteemed for his inde&#45;<lb/>&#45;fatigable zeal&#45;&#44;found his sabbath afternoon ser&#45;<lb/>&#45;vices with chanting and popular sermons&#44; very efficacious.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>So successful has that eminent divine been<lb/> in his pastoral endeavours&#44; that although his mitre<lb/> assent to a universal wish&#44; would ensure secure for him the<lb/> highly honorable and lucrative position of Grand Rabbi<lb/> of all France and her <sic>dependecies</sic>&#44; to replace the late<lb/> Lazare Isidor&#44; his anxiety to be constantly useful more than &#91;&#63;&#93;&#45;<lb/> &#91;&#63;&#93; by moving among all classes&#44; holds him<lb/> to his toilsome post.  Might we not copy to<lb/> advantage&#63;  I mean as far as it relates to the promo&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion of Sabbath afternoon services&#63;  Might we not<lb/> establish in a central location an absolutely free Sy&#45;<lb/>&#45;nagogue&#44; to which our young and old of both sexes&#44;&#45;&#45;un&#45;<lb/>&#45;happily cut off by circumstances from a Sabbath morning<lb/> convocation&#44; could go on Saturday before the sacred day is has<lb/> set&#44; and unite in a short but edifying service in He&#45;<lb/>&#45;brew&#44; with an easy address and English hymns that<lb/> should be formulated for them by some competent Rabbi&#63;<lb/>  I simply throw a hint&#44; but you can render it a<lb/> blissful reality&#44; if the urgent need of our community<lb/> for which I have so frequently pleaded is met.  A<lb/> spacious building ought confessedly to rise in the sou&#45;<lb/>&#45;thern neighborhood of Philadelphia.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>With a large basement for industrial training&#44;<lb/> an upper floor for Sunday School purposes&#44;<lb/> a second floor for a synagogue&#44; and side rooms<lb/> for a Kindergarten&#44; for Hebrew and household and<lb/> sewing and evening schools&#44; we may practically<lb/> further the cause of Judaism&#44; serving Israel&#39;s God&#44;<lb/> by redeeming our fellow&#45;believers humbly situated&#44;<lb/> from the sin of irreligion and from ignorance.<lb/></p>
            <p>Brethren.  I command my thought to your consider&#45;<lb/>&#45;ation and generosity.  Models on which you may measure your beneficence&#44; are every day set by our christian neighbors.  <sic>seek</sic> to imitate.  As I have reached the limit<lb/> which I generally assign to my weekly lectures&#44; I<lb/> will reserve to next week my remarks on the se&#45;<lb/>&#45;cond proposition of importance advanced at the last<lb/> Jewish Minister&#39;s conference of Jewish Ministers held in our city.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
