<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF3_7</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_7_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_7_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_7_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_7_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_7_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_7_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_7_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_7_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_7_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_7_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_7_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_7_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>7th lecture on post Biblical History.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  I have spoken of the providential inter&#45;<lb/>&#45;position through which the land of our fathers&#44; threatened<lb/> by the army of the young King of Macedea&#44; escaped a<lb/> very serious and imminent danger.  In the same lecture&#44; which I<lb/> partly devoted to the a description of the meeting be&#45;<lb/>&#45;tween the Jewish high&#45;priest and the conqueror of Western Asia&#44;<lb/> I alluded to the material advantages that our nation derived from the<lb/> goodwill which Alexander had shown.  But in<lb/> my closing remarks I deprecated the moral consequences brought on by that<lb/> the change of sovereignty by through which Judea became tributary<lb/> to Greece instead of Persia.  finally brought on  To day<lb/> I shall illustrate my point by directing your atten&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion to the rising a new sect in our religion in Judaism.<lb/>  Simeon the just the last survivor of the Great Synod had died&#44; and in his death much<lb/> of the primitive lustre surrounding the Great Synod<lb/> or the Keneseth Ha&#45;gedolah&#44; faded away.  It would<lb/> seem that the venerated body of prophets and sages&#44;<lb/> once presided over by the immortal Ezra&#44; received<lb/> its autonomy from Alexander&#44; or from some of his im&#45;<lb/>&#45;mediate successors.  For it took the name of &#34;Sanhedrin&#44;&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>meaning in Greek&#44; an assembly.  Whether<lb/> this appellation was voluntary&#44; or forced by<lb/> circumstances&#44; is still an open question.  Its dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;cussion&#44; however&#44; would profit little.  I will shall there&#45;<lb/>&#45;fore avoid it&#44; and proceed to explain how the teaching of a chief<lb/> of that Sanhedrin was wickedly distorted into the crea&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion of a schism in Judaism our religion.<lb/></p>
            <p>Antigonus&#44; an inhabitant of the city of Socho&#44; was<lb/> recognized&#44; after the decease of Simeon&#44; as the highest<lb/> authority in traditional lore.  Many sought his<lb/> instruction and he imparted it to men of all classes grades<lb/> of society.  But the times demanded a peculiar system of tuition&#59; a defensive<lb/> tuition&#44; so to say.  That wise preceptor could not<lb/> be ignorant of the inroad which Grecian ideas<lb/> were making into the faith of Israel.  For&#44; as in<lb/> the middle ages&#44; the Arabs affected the general<lb/> mode of thinking&#44; and as in our century the Ger&#45;<lb/>&#45;mans mould European ideas thoughts&#44; so in those days<lb/> the academies of Plato and the Stoas of <sic>Zeuss</sic> influenced our ancestors considerably.<lb/>  Anitgonus realized the necessity of opposing subversive<lb/> notions in the course of his lessons.  Accordingly&#44; he<lb/> formulated a maxim on which he used to dwell.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>He said to his scholars&#58; &#34;Be not like servants who wait<lb/> on their master&#44; on condition of gaining earning gaining a restoration&#44;<lb/> but be like servants who wait on their masters with&#45;<lb/>&#45;out such a condition.  And let the fear of God rest be present<lb/> upon before you.&#34;  Now&#58; to enter into the spirit of that<lb/> aphorism&#44; we must consider bestow our thoughts reflect on another&#44; then very<lb/> current&#44; and attributed to the famous or infamous Epicurus.<lb/>  This Greek philosopher is credited with having taught<lb/> that &#34;pleasure is the chief good.&#34;  I admit it.  Epicurus<lb/> qualified his materialistic maxim by adding that virtue affords<lb/> the greatest pleasure.  But clearly the limitation thus<lb/> intended to be set to the passions was meaningless useless.  For&#44; what<lb/> is virtue without the recognition of a sovereign Law&#59; what is virtue&#44; with&#45;<lb/>&#45;out a divinely perfect model&#63;  As Epicurus denied that the existence of any<lb/> Supreme Being exists who will take knowledge of our<lb/> actions&#59; as he rejected a belief in our accountability&#44;<lb/> he left it with every one to decide for himself what<lb/> is virtue&#44; or the greatest pleasure.  Egotism is must be the na&#45; inevitable<lb/> &#45;tural outcrop of that philosophy&#44; and therefore has the name of its<lb/> teacher has originator come down to posterity branded with an ineffaceable<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>stigma.  Antigonus would designed to draw a contrast<lb/> between the loose and calculating morality of the Greeks&#44; and<lb/> the pure chaste and unselfish ethics of the Rabbis.  The Sages of<lb/> Israel also had told that virtue is its own reward&#44;<lb/> but they did not speak evasively nor equivocally&#59; they plainly pointed<lb/> to the highest loftiest standard which man should look up<lb/> to.  The heavenly Master is the archetype of<lb/> righteousness.  To serve Him disinterestedly that is&#44; namely&#58; to<lb/> do right for Right&#39;s sake&#44; is man&#39;s sublimest noblest ideal.<lb/>  Antigonus did not mean by that to contradict the Mosaic<lb/> volumes&#44; which teem with temporal promises of temporal pleasures to the<lb/> adherents of the Law.  He simply wished to raise<lb/> his disciples to a lofty higher plane.  To follow rectitude only<lb/> with a view to reap certain advantages&#44; may lead to a<lb/> prudential course&#59; to a sagacious course&#44; which strains to that may hide from that is<lb/> society our ulterior motives&#44; but not sterling purity virtue&#44; that is not a line<lb/> of conduct worthy of the people who have been given which will exalt the intellectual ones who recognize can contem<lb/>&#45;plate a pattern of perfection moral sublimity.<lb/></p>
            <p>Now&#58; Among the attendants at the college in which<lb/> the chief of the Sanhedrin imparted a sound knowledge&#44;<lb/> there were two who belonged to what we would term the<lb/> upper classes.  They were rich&#44; hence fond of luxuries and worldly honors.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>On hearing their preceptor harp upon his maxim&#59; again and again praise a<lb/> life of goodness which does not want for strive after any recompense&#44;<lb/> they drew a harmful conclusion.  They argued so&#58; Ju&#45;<lb/>&#45;daism is a religion which <sic>yeilds</sic> its adherents no professes no adherents no appreciable benefit.<lb/>  In this world we fail to see that success always invariably at&#45;<lb/>&#45;tends persons who obey the precepts.  Of the other world&#44;<lb/> we know nothing.  Our teacher recommends us not to<lb/> set our hearts on the enjoyment of any pleasure there.<lb/>  The philosophy of Epicurus is then preferable&#44; it accords<lb/> better with our natural cravings.  We shall follow it.<lb/>  But as to cast off Mosaism entirely&#44; would have been<lb/> to expose oneself to popular indignation and defeat one&#39;s ambitious ends&#44; those men<lb/> professed to comply with the letter of the Pentateuch&#44;<lb/> abjuring however ancestral traditions and the doctrine of a future<lb/> life upon both of and resurrection upon all of which the Rabbis insisted. upon.  The disaffected<lb/> pupils of Antigonus did not find it difficult to gather a number<lb/> of young rich wealthy Jews tinctured with Grecianism&#44; and to form a sect.<lb/>  Its partisans assumed the name of Saducees from<lb/> Sadoc&#44; one of its founders&#44; who very likely&#44; exercised most the widest<lb/> influence.<lb/></p>
            <p>I scarcely think I will be condemned charged with prejudice for asserting that<lb/> a <sic>wilful</sic> perversion withdrew those schismatics from the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>majority of their brethren.  For&#44; even If even the maxim<lb/> of Antigonus the chief of the Sanhedrin could have given room to doubts concern&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing divine reward and punishment&#44; the words of Moses<lb/> For the son of Amram&#44; illumined by inspiration&#44; understood well that community cannot be<lb/> guided by abstractions.  Individuals may rise up to ideals&#44; and cling to virtue for its own sake&#44; but multi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tudes must be made certain of a compensation to duty.  Therefore the Pentateuch&#45;&#45;<lb/> should have dispelled misapprehensions&#44;  The Pen&#45;<lb/> &#45;tateuch itself without mentioning post&#45;Mosaic writings&#45;&#45;<lb/> holds out promises of a recompense to virtue of veritable pleasures here and<lb/> hereafter.  Thus&#44; for instance&#44; when&#44; before his death&#44; the<lb/> arch&#45;prophet admonished our people&#44; he told them&#45;&#45;and<lb/> the sentences form the closing part of the 6th chapter<lb/> of Deuteronomy&#45;&#45;that God enjoined upon us statutes<lb/> and rules for our good welfare always&#44; ending concluding his exhortation by<lb/> saying&#58; &#34;And it will be accounted righteousness unto us<lb/> in the presence of the Lord our God when we observe to<lb/> do all this commandment as He ordered us.&#34;  The inspired saintly<lb/> speaker purposed to signify that by a correct conduct&#44;<lb/> agreeable to the will of the celestial Legislator&#44; we shall<lb/> be not only be the gainers physically&#44; mentally and<lb/> socially&#44; but we shall have a claim to a merit in the<lb/> sight of the Almighty.  And what can that claim<lb/> be after we have derived all the advantages of a righteous<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>demeanour here below&#59; what&#44; but a durable blessing<lb/> above&#63;  With profound wisdom&#44; Moses explained nothing<lb/> further about immortality.  His references to immortality it are various but<lb/> veiled&#44; as immortality will ever be&#44; while we walk in<lb/> flesh.  To bear the image of God&#44; to be taken up by God&#44;<lb/> to be as holy as God&#44; to be gathered to one&#39;s fathers&#44; or to one&#39;s people after our demise and similar phases are interspersed through the<lb/> five sacred books.  If language has any significance&#44; those<lb/> phrases expressions evidence the universal acceptance of the dogma<lb/> of man&#39;s spirituality which is imperishable.  It was incorruptible &#38; inextinguishable. and.<lb/> not The doctrine of an existence beyond the grave&#44; that Mo&#45;<lb/> &#45;saism needed to no inculcation from our seer&#44; but rather the duty of avoid&#45; the importance of guarding<lb/> &#45;ing against the aberrations of mind&#44; to which that doctrine occasioned&#44;<lb/> among surrounding heathens became very requisite.  Hence&#44; the prohibition of<lb/> seeking the dead&#44; of exercising the spirits&#44; evoking the shades of the departed<lb/> and numerous other practices rife among ancient heathens&#44; and con&#45;<lb/>&#45;trary to the religion that wants for the discharge of its<lb/> obligations a sane mind in a sound body.<lb/></p>
            <p>All of this must have been familiar to men who<lb/> stat at the feet of the Chief of the Sanhedrin.  I<lb/> contend&#44; therefore&#44; that not a misapprehension caused a seces&#45; the secession was not the offspring of a<lb/> &#45;sion misapprehension&#44; but that sensualism bred gave birth to Sadducism.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Josephus&#44; who in early life joined this sect purposely<lb/> to test its controlling principles&#44; testifies from personal ex&#45;<lb/>perience that its votaries formed a pretentious aristo&#45;<lb/>&#45;cracy&#44; unrestrained in their habits by any fear of punish&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment&#44; and rude in their manners towards all peoples and classes.<lb/>  Maimonides&#44; however&#44; falls into the common error<lb/> of blending two distinct bodies into one&#59; of confounding the Sadducees of olden times with the Caraites of his own &#91;&#63;&#93; own days.  I hold<lb/> it as that they are altogether entirely different&#44; and it is my private opinion&#44; that those schismatics atoned&#44;<lb/> during the last years of the our national wars existence&#44; for their ill&#45;deeds in former<lb/> ages.  They never were numerous nor popular.<lb/>  Wealth and self&#45;assertion procured for them social power.  Es&#45;<lb/>&#45;pecially after the estrangement of John Hyrcamus<lb/> of the Asmonean dynasty from the Pharisees&#44; the<lb/> Sadducees occupied prominent positions in the courts<lb/> of the Temple and in the halls of legislation&#44; but still when<lb/> Judea groaned in the throes of despair&#44; doctrinal bias<lb/> was must have been cast aside&#44; and the secessionists fought like the<lb/> loyalists of tradition rest of their brethren for country and home.  Alas&#33;<lb/>  that all of them together were doomed to be both were torn by the talons of the cruel<lb/> Roman eagle&#33;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
