<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF9_13</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1891-04" source="" attested="yes">April 1891</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_13_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_13_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_13_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_13_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_13_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_13_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_13_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_13_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_13_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_13_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_13_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_13_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/></p>
            <p>PHILADELPHIA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>26<lb/></p>
            <p>April&#47;91<lb/></p>
            <p>On Egyptian discoveries<lb/>
                predicated on an article in the Ledger<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Brethren.  An article which appeared in last Thursday&#39;s<lb/> issue of the Philadelphia Public Ledger&#44; might have seemed&#44; as<lb/> if purposely prepared to recall the festival&#44; that Isra&#45;<lb/>&#45;elites throughout the world&#44; had just began just then to celebrate.<lb/>  It suited the historic occasion well&#44; for it dwelt descanted truth discussed at<lb/> some length&#44; on discoveries of recent date in Egypt&#45;&#45;a<lb/> country the memory of whose horay antiquity is pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;served in our Bible&#59; even most frequently alluded to in our liturgy&#44;<lb/> but a country it is which has a living record of its exceeding old age annals&#44; in the bread that feeds believ&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing Jews&#44; during a week of this memorable season.<lb/>  The author of the writing to which I have reference is a woman&#44; glowingly en&#45;<lb/>&#45;thusiastic over the achievements of explorers who have widened<lb/> &#45;ing the departments of a science&#44; in which she herself is an<lb/> adept.  I would judge the writer fair authoress to be an Ame&#45;<lb/>&#45;rican&#44; but in deference to truth all who are at all whoever possesses the least<lb/> acquaintance with the subject&#44; will confess that the<lb/> success of later discoveries excavations&#44; at which people marvel&#44;<lb/> is vastly due to a nation that pioneered a patient and<lb/> courageous work.  That nation It dared unearth what<lb/> lay buried had lain already deep beyond human vision&#44; ere Moses<lb/> had arisen to lead the van of human freedom&#45;&#45;a<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>necropolis of illustrious dead.  From the mo&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment that Boussard discovered discovered the Raschid<lb/> or tribunal Rosetta stone&#44; which gave handed the key to the deci&#45;<lb/>&#45;pherment of the hieroglyphics&#44; or pictoral writings<lb/> on the pyramids&#44; and the great Champolnin<lb/> followed up Boussard with his own unwearied efforts&#44; to French&#45;<lb/>&#45;men have offered given the results of invaluable re&#45;<lb/>searches in the field of Egyptology.  Their fruits of<lb/> their labors&#44; enrich now famous galleries&#44; and the Bri&#45;<lb/>&#45;tish museum especially offers the lovers of archeo&#45;<lb/>&#45;logy a harvest of rare and far reaching instruction.<lb/>  However&#44; France has not been alone&#44; in the<lb/> presentation diffusion of a knowledge of that which ages kept what for ages<lb/> had kept jealously hidden for ages.  Italy by her<lb/> Rosellini&#44; Germany by her Brugsch Bey and<lb/> celebrities from other nationalities have contributed<lb/> largely to a learning&#44; at present accessible in our days time about<lb/> the living and the dead the stupendous past of the land of the Pharaohs.<lb/>  None should feel drawn to a study of that<lb/> nature more than we&#44; the disciples of the pro&#45;<lb/>phet who first saw the light of day where the<lb/> Nile still flows&#44; and the descendants of his the tribes he redeemed.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>tribes.  We must welcome all information and<lb/> all informants on that topic.  But as it<lb/> often happens among the with cultivators of a certain<lb/> branch of learning&#44; that they become so enamored<lb/> with their subject&#44; as to be able to view it only<lb/> through magnifying glasses&#44; so it has likewise<lb/> occurred respecting Egyptology.  During last<lb/> winter&#44; intelligent audiences in Philadelphia listened<lb/> to an English lady&#44; notably qualified to enchain<lb/> public attention to Egyptian literature.  Miss<lb/> Amelia B. Edwards delivered a series of lectures&#44;<lb/> deservedly praised for very favorably spoken of because of commented on by the press because of the interest which her fami&#45;<lb/>&#45;liar style and easy manners awakened towards a<lb/> knowledge&#44; otherwise abstruse and obscure. dry and intricate.  But<lb/> in one of her discourses addresses&#44; she referred to dwelt on the beauty of two victo&#45;<lb/>&#45;rious songs&#59; the second of which&#44; recording enumerating the conquests<lb/> of Rameses II.&#44; she designated described as &#34;the most celebrated<lb/> masterpiece of Egyptian poetry.&#34;  That poetry&#44;<lb/> Miss Edwards considered ranked among the best as being&#44; dignifying it with the title &#34;poetry of a high order&#34;.  And&#44; car&#45;<lb/>&#45;ried away by her enthusiasm the lady speaker added&#44; that<lb/> Rameses&#44; who is the hero of the poem epic song&#44; had it<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>perpetuated in a manner so costly splendid&#44; that it<lb/> would put modern publishers to the blush.  An<lb/> edition was sculptured in stone and copies were<lb/> written on papyrus by professional scribes.<lb/>  Let us read that effusion traced out at an enor&#45;<lb/>mous expenditure&#44; and now disinterred after thirty five<lb/> centuries.  Let us learn how Where are the soul&#45;elevating are<lb/> its thoughts how which constitute real poetry&#44; where the inspiring its diction&#63;  A tyran&#45;<lb/>&#45;nically vain mortal extolled into deification&#59;<lb/> false and debauching deities forming the refrain<lb/> of an effusion a composition dictated by fulsome adulation.  Compare that poem<lb/> with the spontaneous outburst of national grati&#45; thanksgivings<lb/>&#45;tude that from shore to shore reverberated when<lb/> the bondmen of Rameses II shook off the dust<lb/> of the his enslaving land.  &#34;God is my strength and<lb/> the burden of my psalmody.  He was my salvation&#59;<lb/> He is my God&#44; and I well must rehearse His praises&#44;<lb/> my father&#39;s God&#59; and I will exalt Him.&#34;<lb/>  &#34;Who is like unto Thee among the mighty <sic>heros</sic> O Lord&#33; who<lb/> is like unto Thee girded with in holiness&#44; worthy of mar&#45; infinite<lb/> &#45;vellous praises doing wonders.&#34;  And then ponder<lb/> on the idea set forth sublime idea intimated in the perforation of that out&#45;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>&#45;pouring of the free grateful&#58; &#34;The Lord shall reign for ever<lb/> and ever.&#34;  The time will arrive when through redeem&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed Israel&#44; the kingdom of the uncreated and Eternal<lb/> God will be spread all over mankind.  The<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;song of the sea&#34;&#44; is not encased in the<lb/> Louvre&#44; nor in the British Museum does not hold it as a stupendous curiosity&#59; Hear It is shrined<lb/> it this day in the sanctuaries congreagtions of the myriads of Israel&#44; for it is enshrined<lb/> in the heart of a deathless people&#44; who has witnessed<lb/> the overthrow of many Pharaohs and of their boast&#45;<lb/>&#45;ful &#45;ed power glory prowess.  &#34;Fear not&#44; Thy servant Jacob&#44; says<lb/> the Lord&#44; for I am with thee&#44; yea&#58; I may make an<lb/> end of all nations among whom I have driven thee&#44;<lb/> but of thee I will not make an end.&#34;  Now&#44;<lb/> Brethren&#44; my ass allusion to the Ledger article of last Thurs&#45;<lb/>&#45;day had particularly for its aim an the illustration of<lb/> a prophecy&#44; occurring in the same chapter&#44; where<lb/> the passage fro sentence which I have just cited&#44; is met.<lb/>  Monsieur Grebant had descended down into almost into the<lb/> bowels of the earth.  It was at Thebes that he<lb/> explored among the mummified dead departed.  Lo&#33; he<lb/> has found what filled him his whole being with expectant delight.<lb/>  Coffins sumptuously decorated&#59; elaborately gilded.<lb/>  Who were the illustrious renowned ones&#44; so honored after<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>they had quitted the sphere of their terrestrial<lb/> endeavours&#63;  Priests and priestesses of<lb/> the supreme deity of Mizraim&#45;&#45;Amon.  There<lb/> had they lain&#44; forgotten by posterity for upwards<lb/> of three thousand years forgotten by posterity&#44; yet&#44; how mighty when<lb/> <sic>the</sic> wore the vestments of their sacerdotal caste&#33;<lb/>  Let me quote in part the Ledger article.  &#34;The priesthood of Thebes had.....<lb/> gradually acquired great wealth and power.  Not<lb/> only did it exercise an immense influence over<lb/> the mass of the people&#44; upon whose superstitious<lb/> feelings it played&#44; but having the monopoly<lb/> of the education of the great in the land&#44; its sacred<lb/> colleges controlled public opinion.  Moreover&#44; as the<lb/> higher priesthood often held important offices of<lb/> State&#44; the power it <sic>weilded</sic> was direct and real.<lb/>  The large share made over to the temples&#44; of the<lb/> booty brought home by the great conquerors of the<lb/> eighteenth and nineteenth dynasties&#44; as well as<lb/> the enormous gifts made to them by short sighted<lb/> monarchs&#44; anxious to secure the good will of the priests&#44;<lb/> culminated into one of that caste&#44; sitting himself<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>upon the throne of the Pharaohs&#34;.  Jeremiah<lb/> forced away&#44; by an ill advised unwise political party away from<lb/> the soul&#44; in which he fain would have preferred to<lb/> let his weary bones lie&#44; may have seen in men heard seen in<lb/> Thebes the worship of Amon&#44; in all its deceptive<lb/> splendour grandeur.  Stretching his looks&#44; he saw prophetic looks&#44; he<lb/> was made to behold a formidable host&#44; led on by a giant<lb/> from Western Asia&#44; armed with axes to tear down<lb/> the temples of the false lying false god ministered them by lying priests and priestesses.  &#34;I will send visit&#45;<lb/>&#45;ation on Amon of No&#34;&#45;&#45;for so was called the false fabulous<lb/> deity in the capital of upper Egypt in the shape of a youth with the head of a partly man &#38; partly ram&#44; when<lb/> conquered shattered by that thunderbolt of war Nebuchad&#45;<lb/>nezzar.  But Ezekiel&#44; mounting still higher<lb/> on the wings of inspiration&#44; he saw the total<lb/> overthrow of the false gods of Memphis and Tanis&#44;<lb/> of Dafne and Pelusium and of Thebes.  He saw<lb/> more.  Egypt is covered as with an impenetrable<lb/> cloud.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  Shorn of its former glory&#44; she is govern&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed f by foreigners&#59; never more does one of the seed<lb/> of her famous Rameseses wears the crown.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>  &#34;Among the kingdoms she shall be low&#44; neither shall it she raise<lb/> herself any more above the nations.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Consult history&#44; O Israelites&#44; and the truths<lb/> revealed to the far&#45;reaching minds of your guides&#44;<lb/> will stand luminously forth&#59; unchallenged.  God<lb/> who has given us eternity upon earth&#44; God&#44; the<lb/> agents of whose will all intelligent beings are&#44; uses<lb/> now man&#39;s enlightened patience&#44; and widened talents<lb/> to verify what the pens of His servants have traced dipped in inspiration have anticipated<lb/> truly traced out.  Is the account of our fathers&#39; stay in Egypt denied&#63;<lb/>  Men with armed with pickaxes and spades dig out&#44;<lb/> to disclose facts the genuineness of narratives in the five books.  Today is Pithom&#44; the city for of granaries built<lb/> by the sweat of the Hebrews&#44; whom taskmasters<lb/> lashed&#44; is brought again to view&#59; the next day a<lb/> painting is in a neglected spot&#44; shows men and wo&#45;<lb/>&#45;men whose looks and raiment betray a foreign descent among the natives.<lb/>  Science&#44; the handmaid of religion&#44; is at work for to the<lb/> vindication of Moses and the prophets.  May<lb/> it ever continue so always so labor&#44; avenging scriptural verities&#44; while we&#44; following the counsel of<lb/> the olden shepherd given upon this day never to be forgotten glorious morning&#44; shall stand<lb/> keeping silent&#44; witnessing the deliverance wrought<lb/> by the Lord&#44; who was&#44; who is&#44; and will always ever be.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
