<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF2_6</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1893" source="" attested="yes">1893</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_6_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_6_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_6_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_6_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_6_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_6_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_6_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_6_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_6_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_6_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_6_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_6_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>5 pages on 2 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET.<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;1893<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>On the Shechitah question<lb/> 
                For Parashat Noah<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>The Shechitah question&#44; or the principle<lb/> involving either humanity or&#45;&#45;according to some&#45;&#45;inhumanity in the me&#45;<lb/>&#45;thod of slaughtering animals&#44; whose flesh is per&#45;<lb/>&#45;missible to Jews&#44; has exercised the minds of our<lb/> neighbors of the Christian creed&#44; quite often.<lb/></p>
            <p>Perhaps&#44; Switzerland can claim the unenviable<lb/> credit of having led the van of the opposition.<lb/>  More than once she determinedly set her face<lb/> against our traditional system.  Years ago some<lb/> of the cantons forbade it altogether&#44; thus placing<lb/> our brethren of the Helvetic Confederacy&#44; who are<lb/> observant of the Law&#44; in a great predicament.<lb/>  I remember that when that happened&#44; the Rev.<lb/> Isaac Leeser wrote forcibly to disprove the<lb/> charges of cruelty touching our regulations&#44; while<lb/> myself and others united to the same purpose&#44;<lb/> in more recent years times.<lb/></p>
            <p>Now&#44; it is very ungracious in any one to ac&#45;<lb/>&#45;cuse individuals or nations of nurturing inveterate<lb/> prejudice&#44; but I do not think believe that I wrong&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>out of malice aforethought&#44; the country of<lb/> William Tell&#44; when I accuse her of cherishing<lb/> a deep rooted ill will.  She has repeatedly and<lb/> persistently hampered Israelites by her anticipations&#44;<lb/> and the feelings which she undisguisedly mani&#45;<lb/>&#45;fested would have influenced other lands&#44; if the<lb/> authority of a &#91;&#63;&#93; and scientists of a like<lb/> standing in France&#44; Italy and England had<lb/> not disarmed opposition.  Shame upon some<lb/> pseudo rabbis who&#44; to play the liberal&#44; advanced<lb/> flimsy and untenable arguments&#44; to sanction encourage wink at<lb/> religious persecution&#33;  Persecution I<lb/> call it and a fitting appellation it is&#44; when<lb/> applied to the conduct of Switzerland towards<lb/> her Hebrew citizens.  For&#44; she may cure<lb/> nothing for Judaism&#44; but she must know<lb/> that there are Jews&#45;&#45;and not a few&#45;&#45;within her<lb/> borders&#44; who would rather suffer hunger than<lb/> feed upon that which their conscience rejects.<lb/>  Ought a well regulated government to coerce<lb/> a portion of the population into the accept&#45;<lb/>&#45;ance of measures that imperil their existence&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>while <sic>benefitting</sic> in no shape or form other por&#45;<lb/>&#45;tions of the same population&#63;  Even on the<lb/> score of kindness to the brute creation&#44; such pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;ceedings would be unwarranted.  For&#44; surely the<lb/> preservation of men&#39;s lives is a matter of higher<lb/> consideration&#44; than that of sparing animals<lb/> acute pains.  But the majority of<lb/> voters who&#44; at the Referendum decided to prevent<lb/> our Shechitah process&#44; cannot justify their action<lb/> on the ground of humanity&#44; because it has<lb/> been authoritatively shown that the Jewish me&#45;<lb/>&#45;thod is the best for a number of reasons.  By<lb/> it the loss of all sensation in the animal is<lb/> instantaneous&#59; the flesh will keep softer<lb/> and healthier because of the flow of the blood&#44;<lb/> which is the mainspring of corruption&#44; while the<lb/> examination of the lungs&#44; must act as a safe&#45;<lb/>&#45;guard against the communication of diseases&#44;<lb/> apt to become engrafted upon our own lungs.<lb/>  Did I not fear to repeat myself&#44; I would<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>set forth the results of my personal researches<lb/> into that subject&#44; and mention also my experience<lb/> in connection with the Philadelphia society of<lb/> prevention of cruelty to animals.  Suffice to say&#44;<lb/> that by the ingenious confession of men&#44; whose interest<lb/> it is to encourage the prevailing system among gentiles&#44;<lb/> our is declared preferable from a humane and a wholesome<lb/> point of view and by reason of wholesomeness.  I do honor men and women&#44;<lb/> who vigilantly watch that no unnecessary suf&#45;<lb/>&#45;fering be inflicted upon dumb creatures&#44; although&#44;<lb/> at times&#44; the over zeal has done us injustice.<lb/>  To us&#44; whom Moses commanded to relieve a beast<lb/> crouching under a heavy burden&#44; if it even belongs<lb/> to a person who openly hates us&#59; to bring back<lb/> to our enemy his ox or his ass when straying<lb/> away from the customary shelter&#59; to us&#44; Israel&#45;<lb/>&#45;ites&#44; I say&#44; the sight of a horse or of a mule<lb/> beaten by a brutal driver&#44; must be revolting.<lb/>  No one who has profitably read the Bible&#44;<lb/> or has caught the spirit of numerous maxims<lb/> and legends of the Rabbis&#44; regarding the humane kindly<lb/> feelings which we should exhibit towards<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>domestic animals&#44; can help exercising tender con&#45;<lb/>sideration in the use of beings of the lower creation&#44;<lb/> that do us service.  Mark what we<lb/> have perused in to day&#39;s Pentateuch portion and<lb/> let it serv be our guide.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;But flesh with the life thereof&#44; which is the blood<lb/> thereof&#44; ye shall not eat&#34; signifying that while<lb/> the animal is alive&#44; we shall not dare to<lb/> feed upon it&#44; by cutting off any part of its<lb/> body to satisfy our greed or our hunger&#45;&#45;a practice<lb/> not rare among savage some barbarous tribes.  That prohibit&#45;<lb/>&#45;ion gave origin to the <sic>instilation</sic> of the Shechitah&#44;<lb/> essentially the operation imparted by tradition&#44;<lb/> as the safest to man in his nutriment&#44; and the least painful<lb/> to irrational beings.  Indeed&#44; had not Holy<lb/> Writ and the Talmud left as rules and apho&#45;<lb/>&#45;risms&#44; showing that the Almight cares for<lb/> the defenceless creatures&#44; which He placed under<lb/> our dominion&#44; a sentence in the same Parashah<lb/> would go far to prove that all are in His<lb/> compassionate thought.  The promise<lb/> given to Noah that the earth would never<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>undergo such a catastrophe as it had suffered<lb/> by the deluge&#44; included every thing that has exist&#45;<lb/>ance &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;And I&#44; behold I establish My covenant with you<lb/> and with your seed after you and with every<lb/> living creature that is with you&#44; the fowl&#44; the<lb/> cattle and every beast of the earth with you&#34;.<lb/>  Would that mankind did not need to subject ani&#45;<lb/>mals to the loss of life&#44; but the permission to<lb/> deprive beasts of their existence&#44; in order to sustain<lb/> ours&#44; does not imply a license to cruelly torture<lb/> them&#44; as they surely do those who indulge in<lb/> the wanton sport of the chase&#44; or who degrade<lb/> to their manhood by inciting beasts to the fight.<lb/>  Very contrary to that&#44; a legend which illustrates<lb/> the regret felt by the sages of Israel at the<lb/> necessity of shedding the blood of animals even<lb/> for our own subsistence&#44; is most touching.  Let<lb/> me relate it.  The famous Judah the Prince<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; who formulated the text of<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>of the Mishnah was on a certain day while walking abroad was<lb/> followed by a young calf that made a noise as<lb/> if crying imploring to be hidden under the folds of the<lb/> Rabbi&#39;s garment&#44; and not to be driven into<lb/> the slaughter&#45;house.  Judah the Prince&#44; turned<lb/> around and chasing the animal away said &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Go to thy destiny&#44; for thy lot is to be<lb/> killed&#34;  Harsh words were they which cost the<lb/> sage bodily infirmities.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; So wrote the misjudged and abused Tal&#45;<lb/>&#45;mudists.  Oh&#33; that gentilism would learn to<lb/> appreciate the principles of tender humanity&#44; which<lb/> underlie the Jewish religion&#33;  We would not see&#44;<lb/></p> <p>ignorance&#44; allied to malevolence&#44; vex and hamper<lb/> the children of Abraham.  We would not hear of the<lb/> unrighteous decisions of Cantons in self&#45;styled free<lb/> Switzerland.  The peace and good&#45;will preached in<lb/> churches would become a reality and not an empty<lb/> invocation.  The law Bible and the traditions would stand vind&#45;<lb/>icated&#44; for the former teaches that &#34;the Lord is good to<lb/> all and His tender mercies are towards all His work&#34;&#44;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> while the latter tells us that &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>to spare the brute creation by not subjecting it to un&#45;<lb/>&#45;necessary pain and burden&#44; is a controlling rule in<lb/> the Jewish religion.  May we ever conform with it.<lb/></p>
            
            <p>This lecture was lengthened by quoting Rabbinical sayings &#38; legends.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
