<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF5_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_2_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_2_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_2_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_2_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff5_2_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>13 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>108</p>
            
            <p>A lecture On the<lb/>
                Observance of the Sabbath.<lb/>
                <del>by</del><lb/>
                <del>a Jewish clergyman</del><lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Dear hearers&#33;  It is remarkably singular&#44; that in<lb/> the warmth of the contest now carried on&#44; to establish<lb/> or reject the sanctity of the first day of the week&#44; the advocates<lb/> of either system&#44; will misapprehend facts.  If the error&#44; how&#45;<lb/>&#45;ever&#44; emanated from persons of no literary pretensions&#44; a notice<lb/> of it might be superfluous&#44; but when it receives support from<lb/> the position&#44; real or fictitious&#44; of the individuals who have<lb/> advanced brought advanced it forward then&#44; I am of opinion&#44; that it ought not to go<lb/> unrefuted.  I cannot presume that my voice will reach<lb/> multitudes&#44; and bring home conviction to every mind&#44; but as<lb/> my main duty2 and object1 are to prevent your imbibing<lb/> false ideas&#44; I will examine what strength have some of<lb/> the arguments you must have read in favor and against<lb/> the question agitated of late through the weekly press.<lb/>  This day whereupon the Decalogue has been rehearsed&#44; may<lb/> fittingly be devoted to discuss a point relating to one of<lb/> its commands precepts.  My friends&#33; I have no doubt that<lb/> even those among our brethren&#44; who are unmindful of<lb/> their religious duties&#44; will admit that the Scriptures<lb/> recognizes but the seventh day as the Sabbath of the<lb/> Lord.  They may palliate their disregard for it&#44; but<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>they will scarcely attempt to defend it by means of quibbles and<lb/> evasions.  Yet&#44; who would believe it&#63;  Such are<lb/> the means to which instruments they resort <sic>weild</sic>&#44; &#34;whose lips should keep<lb/> knowledge&#44; and from at whose mouths instruction should be<lb/> sought&#34;&#33;  One of our city divines&#44; in his eagerness to oppose<lb/> a movement which he deems hurtful to the tenets of his<lb/> religion&#44; uttered this sentence.  &#34;Hear it&#58; The Lord in the thunders<lb/> of mount Sinai&#44; has given the fourth commandment&#44;<lb/> not to keep holy the seventh day&#44; but to keep holy the<lb/> Sabbath&#45;day.&#34;  What a glaring misrepresentation&#33; what<lb/> a stupendous abuse of human credulity&#33;  Were I&#44; to make<lb/> such a declaration in your presence&#44; my intelligent hearers&#44;<lb/> you2 would1 forthwith not put2 me1 forthwith to confusion shame&#63;  You Would<lb/> you not repeat with one loud voice the words of our unchangeable<lb/> Legislator&#44; &#34;but the seventh day is a Sabbath to the Lord<lb/> thy God&#34;&#63; &#40;Exodus XX.10&#41;  Would you not force me to confront a witness<lb/> that establishes <sic>immoveably</sic> in the mind of all believers&#44;<lb/> the sacredness of the seventh day&#63;  Even&#44; the recorded fact<lb/> that during forty years the manna did not once fall upon<lb/> that day in the camp of Israel&#63; &#40;Exodus XVI. 27&#41;.<lb/></p>
            <p>To assert that the Almighty is equally honored&#44; if<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>we set apart to His service any other period of time&#44;<lb/> is an equivocation incompatible with the character of those<lb/> who should be the exponents of truth.  Certainly&#58; we believe<lb/> that the beneficent Creator accepts always with favor on the tokens of<lb/> our filial reverence.  We further believe&#44; that each moment we<lb/> employ in doing a good action&#44; in speaking a righteous<lb/> word&#44; is most holy in His eyes&#44; but th does that empower us to<lb/> alter what He has established ordained by revelation&#63;....For not<lb/> alone in the two passages to which I have just referred&#44;<lb/> is the ordinance of the Sabbath jointly named with the<lb/> seventh day&#44; but in almost every other instance&#44; wherein<lb/> its observance is recommended&#44; the Divine Law defines in<lb/> the clearest terms&#44; the time we should weekly devote to God.<lb/>  Whether the obligation is binding on the gentile world&#59;<lb/> or whether with the rejection of all ceremonial statutes&#44;<lb/> another day of rest upon different principles&#44; can must not consistently<lb/> be established&#44; are questions in which we&#44; as Israelites<lb/> can have not direct concern.  Our immediate interest<lb/> lies in guarding against being swayed from our allegiance<lb/> to the Code of Sinai.  Wherefore have I spoken.  Brethren&#33;<lb/>  The least concession made to opinions&#44; which would fain<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>argue away the sanctity of the seventh day&#44; while main&#45;<lb/>&#45;taining the necessity of a Sabbath&#44; will place us beyond the<lb/> pale of Judaism.  For&#44; like the circumcision&#44; the Sabbath<lb/> of the Decalogue stands as a token of everlasting covenant<lb/> only between God and his chosen people &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Only Surely my Sabbaths ye shall keep&#44; for it is a sign<lb/> between me and you throughout your generations&#44; that ye may<lb/> know that I am the Lord who doth sanctify you&#34;.  Exodus XXXI. 13.&#41;<lb/> Whatever advantage we&#44; as a constituted nation of the earth&#44;<lb/> may have temporally derived from a un general obedience<lb/> to the fourth commandment&#45;&#45;when forming a separate nation on the earth&#44; it cannot have outweighed<lb/> the spiritual object yet and for evermore connected with<lb/> its observance.  The Hebrew who hallows the seventh day&#44;<lb/> bears testimony to all the truths of revelation taught by enunciated in the &#91;&#63;&#93; inspired volumes.  To the<lb/> existential power of God&#44; as displayed in the shown by the work of creation&#44; to the unity<lb/> of the human race&#44; to the selection of one family of<lb/> men&#44; as the harbingers of salvation&#44; and to the promise<lb/> of a heavenly kingdom reward.  Therefore have the sages written<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; that &#34;the keeping of<lb/> the Sabbath&#44; is equivalent to that of the entire Law.&#34;<lb/>  &#40;See Maimonides at the end of twelve Sabbats Shabbat&#44; after the Talmud&#41;<lb/> But in order to celebrate the seventh day in accordance<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>with its right spirit&#44; we should not remain satisfied<lb/> with the mere cessation from labor.  The hallowing of<lb/> the Sabbath&#44; so often and so emphatically recommended&#44;<lb/> implies more than a negative observance&#44; it means a positive<lb/> performance of arc actions&#44; calculated to edify the mind&#44; &#38;<lb/> exalt the characters of its votaries.  For &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Kaddesh&#34; which is the<lb/> term used in Hebrew&#44; applies to the devoting of any<lb/> object to certain direct purposes&#59; hence is the Sanctuary<lb/> called &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Mikdash Mi&#45;kdash&#44;&#34; from its being wholly dedicated to the service<lb/> of God&#44; hence did the words &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Kodesh ladonai&#34; shine upon the<lb/> forehead of the high priest who ministered at the altar.<lb/>  The Divine author of the Pentateuch did not impose a set<lb/> of rules regarding the manner in which the day of the Lord<lb/> should be employed.  He preferred leaving to the leaders<lb/> of Israel&#44; to suit to time and circumstances the system to<lb/> be adopted&#59; but that it should be chosen with a view<lb/> to lead to promote righteousness&#44; they were made plainly to<lb/> understand by the declaration that the seventh day<lb/> is to be &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;A solemn great period of rest&#44; for a<lb/> holy convocation&#34; &#40;Leviticus XXIII. 3&#41; see Nachmanides in loco&#41;  In fact&#44; if we search through<lb/> the various stages of epochs in our history annals&#44; we shall learn<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>that the practice of assembling thereon for instruc&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion and prayer was general among our ancestors.  That&#44;<lb/> by way of illustration&#44; when the Shunammite<lb/> expressed a wish to visit Elisha&#44; her husband&#44; who was<lb/> ignorant of the true motive&#44; asked &#34;Why wilt thou go<lb/> to him this day&#63;  It is neither a new moon nor a<lb/> Sabbath &#40;Kings IV. 23.&#41;&#34;; implying from which its implied obviously inferred that what was unusual on the<lb/> working days&#44; was customary had become a settled custom on sacred occasions&#44;<lb/> namely&#59; to seek the servants of God&#44; that we might<lb/> imbibe wholesome knowledge from their lips.  So<lb/> likewise&#44; the prophet Isaiah&#44; while inveighing against<lb/> the hypocrisy of his contemporaries&#44; who attended only<lb/> to outward ceremonies&#44; speaks as follows.  &#34;Continue not<lb/> to bring a false useless oblation.....upon the new moon<lb/> and the Sabbath to call an assembly together&#44; I cannot<lb/> bear iniquity with a solemn gathering.&#34; &#40;Is. I. 13&#41;.  And Josephus<lb/> in his antiquities of the Jews&#44; quoting from an appeal<lb/> made to the Greeks&#44; by Nicolaus to Marais Agrippa that we the Jews dwelling in Jewish inhabitants of Greece might be privileged<lb/> to exercise our their laws without restraint or detriment&#44;&#45;&#45;says writes &#34;.<lb/> &#34;The seventh day we set apart from labor&#58; it is<lb/> dedicated to the learning of our usages customs and laws.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>We think it proper to reflect on them&#44; as well<lb/> as on any other good subject&#44; in order that we may to our<lb/> avoiding of sinning &#40;Antiquities b XVI. p 3.&#41;  And if we consult the Rabbis&#44;<lb/> we shall be told that &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Sabbaths and festivals were given to Israel&#44; only<lb/> that they might be enabled to ponder on the Law&#34;. &#40;Treatise Pessachin &#38; elsewhere&#41;<lb/> Now&#44; my Brethren&#33;  What I have hitherto said explained&#44; will enable<lb/> you to repel the arguments of those who misapply<lb/> their zeal by through a misapprehension of our practices.<lb/>  When you hear individuals&#44; assuming the title of &#34;Bible<lb/> Students&#34; in their endeavours to combat the equally fallacious reasoning of clergymen&#44; make these assertions &#34;From Moses down<lb/> to Malachi&#44; a period of a thousand years&#44; there<lb/> was no special religious meeting on the Sabbath.&#34;<lb/>  And &#34;as we contemplate the Jewish nation on that<lb/> day&#44; we must think of a people in complete<lb/> idleness&#34;; when you hear&#44; I say&#44; such ones declare&#44; that<lb/> &#34;the Jews kept their Sabbath&#34; simply by leaving off work&#34;<lb/> you will measure their Scriptural knowledge with<lb/> the mete&#45;yard of facts&#44; and you will find it woefully<lb/> wanting.  In addition to the references already made<lb/> to from Holy Writ&#44; you will further prove by the same<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>authority the falsity of their position.  For&#44; the striking<lb/> circumstance that our the prophets&#44; who specially preached<lb/> moral duties&#44; have laid great stress on the importance<lb/> of hallowing the Sabbath&#44; shows beyond doubt its intimate<lb/> <sic>connexion</sic> with whatsoever is conducive to righteousness.<lb/>  Aye&#44; you will evoke the spirit of our Seers&#44; to deny that<lb/> our Sabbath was &#34;a wide spread leisure&#44;&#34; from &#34;Dan to<lb/> Beersheba&#34;; because&#44; unless we did habitually congregate<lb/> in large numbers to offer our devotions on that day&#44; Ezekiel<lb/> would not have so ordained prescribed&#44; respecting the reconstruction<lb/> of the temple &#34;The gate of the inner court that looketh<lb/> toward the East shall be shut the six working days&#44;<lb/> but on the Sabbath it shall be opened&#44; and on the day<lb/> of the new moon it shall be opened&#44;...And the people<lb/> of the land shall bow themselves down at the entrance of<lb/> this gate before the Lord&#44; on the Sabbaths&#44; and in the new&#45;<lb/>moons.&#34; &#40;Ezek XLVI. 1. 3.&#41; For What other meaning can be attached to these<lb/> sentences&#59; but that a wider space should be allowed<lb/> for a vast concourse of people coming on those occasions<lb/> to worship towards the place&#44; where the Divinity<lb/> dwelt amidst the Cherubim&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Were it not even precisely so&#44; the son of Amoz would<lb/> not have concluded the book of his sublime visions<lb/> in the following significant language &#34;And it<lb/> shall be that on every revolving Sabbath new moon&#44;<lb/> and on every revolving Sabbath&#44; all creatures shall<lb/> come to prostrate themselves before th me&#44; sayeth<lb/> the Lord.&#34; &#40;Is. LXVI. 23.&#41; His inspired mind saw all mankind&#44; enlightened<lb/> in the knowledge of One true God&#44; and he pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;dicted that every human being would finally join Israel in the<lb/> homage they were wont to pay&#44; on such days&#44; to their<lb/> Saviour and Protector.<lb/></p>
            <p>But now that I have presented a correct view of the<lb/> Sabbath&#44; as proclaimed on Sinai&#44; as interpreted by<lb/> our prophets and Sages&#44; and as handed down to<lb/> us by our predecessors&#44; I may pertinently ask&#59; whe&#45;<lb/>&#45;ther our observance of it accords exactly with its sanctity.<lb/>  Friends Brethren&#33;  Admit that we do no servile work there&#45;<lb/>&#45;on&#59; admit that we then repair to the house of prayer&#44;<lb/> &#40;would it were so&#33;&#41; have we then solemnized the<lb/> day in the spirit of the Bible&#63;  Have we then<lb/> so honored it&#44; that we may claim the reward<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>accompanying its faithful keeping&#63;  Understand<lb/> me well&#58; I am not of those who would surround<lb/> the Sabbath with a gloom&#59; I assert&#44; on the contrary&#44;<lb/> that to promote kind feelings by friendly visits&#44; or<lb/> that even to enjoy a goodly &#91;inserted above&#58; convivial&#93; repast with thanks to the<lb/> beneficent Providence&#44; are actions not at all detracting<lb/> from the holiness sacredness of the fourth commandment&#44; but are<lb/> frivolous entertainments consistent with it&#63;  Is Would&#44; for example&#44; the<lb/> spending of a whole Sabbath&#45;eve in the temple of<lb/> fashion and song&#44; &#40;the witnessing of theatrical represen&#45;<lb/>&#45;tations&#41;&#44; or the yielding of sacred devoted hours to the dance and<lb/> to the song game&#44; compatible with a period of time&#44;<lb/> in which Isaiah recommends&#44; that &#34;we seek not our own<lb/> pleasure&#44; nor speak of a word&#34; that might pollute it. &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#40;Is. XVIII. 13.&#41;&#63;  Friends&#33;  It is but recently that I pain&#45;<lb/>&#45;fully learnt with pain how some Hebrew mothers among us choose the seventh<lb/> day&#44; as the most opportune time&#44; for having their<lb/> young sons and daughters taught to perform on<lb/> instruments&#44; and to shine at balls.  It is but<lb/> recently that I was informed how Jewish some of our youths<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>lost so far their self&#45;respect&#44; as to engage<lb/> a public hall&#44; wherein the Sabbath might be greeted<lb/> by them with sports &#38; revelry and mirth.  True&#44; our re&#45;<lb/>&#45;ligion does not condemn hilarity and diversions&#44; but it<lb/> preaches to reserve every thing for its proper season&#44;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#40;Ecclesiastes III.&#41;  To indulge unduly in undue merriment and<lb/> gaiety on the seventh day&#44; is an act of irreverence<lb/> towards the Lord&#44; a pernicious example to<lb/> our household&#44; and a cause of merited reproach before<lb/> the gentile world.  I trust that I have<lb/> said sufficiently.  Dear Brethren Hearers&#33;  Should<lb/> any of you have so trespassed&#44; let him bethink<lb/> himself of his fault and desist&#59; should any son of Israelite within<lb/> whose hearing your voice can reach&#44; have permitted<lb/> to himself that reprehensibly acts conduct practice impropriety reason with<lb/> him that he may retract&#44; and keep henceforth<lb/> &#38; evermore the Sabbath henceforth &#38; evermore&#44; in spirit and practice&#44; as it behooves<lb/> the people of God&#44; and the witnesses of his revealed<lb/> truths.&#34;  Oh  Blessed is be the man that doeth this&#44; &#38; the son<lb/> of man that layeth hold on it&#44; that keepeth the<lb/> Sabbath from polluting it&#44; &#38; keepeth his hand from<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p>doi doing any evil&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; May that blessing be our the portion<lb/> lot allotted to each of us&#59; and say ye&#58; with me Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
