<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF13_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_2_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>For Sabbath Ytr&#242;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  The battle most gloriously fought&#44; is<lb/> that in which a man&#39;s principles conquered a man&#39;s<lb/> desires.  For&#44; He is truly valiant&#44; who&#44; beset by pressing<lb/> wants&#44; holds fast then keeps steadfast into the way of righteousness.<lb/>  Yet&#44; such <sic>heros</sic>&#44; who ought to command universal respect&#44;<lb/> are regarded as individuals weak&#45;minded and over scru&#45;<lb/>&#45;pulous.  So accustomed we are to see justice<lb/> make room for expediency&#44; and vital questions to be<lb/> settled by a compromise&#44; that we cannot duly<lb/> appreciate a mind that which knows not a middle course<lb/> between right and wrong.  Hence it is that the<lb/> <sic>concientious</sic> and the pious suffer.  The section I will briefly<lb/> of this Sabbath suggests an illustration to my illustrate my assertion.<lb/> assertion.  Imagine one of our brothers in faith<lb/> seeking a situation in life.  He possesses all the<lb/> requisites to fill it creditably.  But in order to<lb/> reach the object in view&#44; he must overstep the<lb/> bounds set by God by his heavenly legislator.  He pauses to reflect.<lb/>  Shall I trespass&#63;  Or&#44; shall I destroy my future<lb/> prospects&#63;  I also long to rise by my own exer&#45;<lb/>&#45;tions.  Why&#44; shall I not&#44; like others&#44; acquire a<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>competency and a name&#63;  But a voice resounds<lb/> in his ears &#91;Hebrew&#93;. it cries&#58; &#34;Remember the Sabbath&#45;day to keep it<lb/> holy&#59;&#34; it cries.  He cannot&#44; he dares not disobey.<lb/>  His Sovereign Creator has spoken.  His final<lb/> judge has pronounced the sentence &#34;Whosoever doeth<lb/> work on that seventh day of Sabbath&#44; that soul shall be<lb/> cut off from among its people terrifies him God&#39;s eternal displeasure&#34;  Between the<lb/> sin of rebellion&#44; and constant privations&#44; he chooses the<lb/> latter.  We then&#45;&#45;the witnesses of a self&#45;denial<lb/> so great and noble noble to human nature&#45;&#45;should practically evince the respect<lb/> it inspires.  We should stretch forth our hand and say&#58;<lb/> Brother&#33;  Your high principles must not stand as a<lb/> barrier against your temporal advancement.  Success<lb/> shall attend your endeavours&#44; even through my own<lb/> agency.  But we&#44; on the contrary&#44; can only find<lb/> simply a word of pity for him whose sense of his obli&#45;<lb/>&#45;gations&#44; is so very keen.  We deem it rather un&#45;<lb/>&#45;fortunate that while possessing the qualifications ena&#45;<lb/>&#45;bling him to obtain preferments&#44; he should be ham&#45;<lb/>&#45;pered by religious scruples.<lb/></p>
            <p>So general is the desecration of the fourth command&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment of the Decalogue&#44; that to learn that any one Hebrews<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>would is be ready to sacrifice to its observance a lucrative position&#44;<lb/> creates astonishment.  &#34;Necessity knows no law&#44;&#34;<lb/> one will say.  &#34;Times have changed very materially&#44;&#34;<lb/> another will exclaim&#44; &#34;we can no more adhere to<lb/> practices conflicting with the present state of society.<lb/>  Our forefathers did not follow so extensively engage in commercial<lb/> pursuits&#44; and could therefore devote the seventh day to<lb/> religious purposes&#44; but we would be exceedingly incon&#45;<lb/>&#45;venienced by imitating their example.&#34;  Thus it<lb/> happens that the men who profess to believe in the<lb/> book that teaches &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;It is Sabbath for you to the Lord in all<lb/> your habitations&#44;&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; in the holy land &#38; in foreign&#45;<lb/>climes&#59; thus it happens that those men very men place this land beyond the limits of<lb/> that divine ordinance.  Now&#44; my friends&#33;<lb/> that any man one in Israel should so think&#44; and so act<lb/> is really lamentable&#45;&#45;for the violation of the Sabbath&#45;&#45;<lb/> is the sure forerunner of other grievous transgressions&#44; but that by<lb/> reason of that laxity of principles&#44; the high&#45;minded should<lb/> be exposed to severe trials&#44; is deplorable in the extreme.<lb/>  Often have my feelings been harrowed when told that<lb/> the condition by which an Israelite was offered employ&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment by his coreligionist&#44; was that the seventh day should<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>be desecrated.  Alas&#33; I know of incidents&#44; in which<lb/> a stranger to our faith granted what the Hebrew man<lb/> had peremptorily refused.  Say ye&#44; o parents<lb/> that fear the Lord&#33; is this not a thought that weighs<lb/> heavily upon your minds&#63;  How will our sons<lb/> secure a position in society&#44; and cling to the ances&#45;<lb/>&#45;tral religion&#63;  Will we be forced to wince at&#45;&#45;if not<lb/> to sanction&#44; their backslidings open derelictions&#63;  For&#44; many have I<lb/> beheld that struggled mightily&#44; but could not stand<lb/> proof against all temptations.  Impelled by nature<lb/> to activity&#44; and restrained by religious motives&#44; they<lb/> finally succumbed.  The act did violence to<lb/> their feelings&#58; it grieved the hearts of the parents&#59;<lb/> but few my friends&#33; are the <sic>heros</sic> that can&#44; under urgent nece&#45;<lb/>ssities&#44; cling unflinchingly to principles.<lb/></p>
            <p>This day a lad has assumed in your presence the per&#45;<lb/>&#45;formance of sacred duties.  I am fully convinced<lb/> that at this moment he shrinks from the idea of<lb/> making his future conduct belie his present professions.  He<lb/> doubtless believes that in order to keep fast to one&#39;s<lb/> pledge&#44; the observance sanctity of the sabbath cannot under<lb/> any circumstance be tampered with.  But what difficulties<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>will he not have to encounter&#63;  How forcefully strong<lb/> will be the seductions inciting him to sin&#33;  He will<lb/> see his coevals enjoy lucrative situations&#44; while he<lb/> may perhaps barely earn a subsistence.  He will see<lb/> others brought to preeminence&#44; while he may be compel&#45;<lb/>&#45;led to continue remain in a state of dependence.  Among his<lb/> associates&#44; one will advise that he shall set aside all<lb/> religious restraints&#59; another will pronounce it unwise to<lb/> check his aspirations for the sake of an ancient law prescriptions.  Were<lb/> he even my own son&#44; I could not vouch for his ability to<lb/> withstand those seductions allurements.  Precept has a decided<lb/> influence&#44; example is very efficacious&#44; but a ceaseless<lb/> contrast between ourselves&#45;&#45;the victims of abstract high principles&#44;<lb/> and our neighbors&#44; in the fruition of wealth and honors&#44; through<lb/> their disregard of the law&#44; will work with fatal results<lb/> upon the susceptible minds of susceptible youths.<lb/>
                Is there then no remedy to this growing evil&#63;  Shall<lb/> we continue to offer our children an alternative so painful<lb/> as that I have just described&#63;...Dear Brethren&#33;  You possess<lb/> the means&#44; whereby to relieve the mind of God&#45;fearing<lb/> parents&#44; and benefitting your souls&#44; while <sic>benefitting</sic> your fellow&#45;believers.  Resolve<lb/> that henceforth your storehouses shall all be closed in the Sabbath&#45;day.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>I have been informed that in other cities&#44; the object<lb/> has been was attained by a general agreement all Israelites consented to abstain from servile labor on the seventh day.  The<lb/> plan commends itself also to ourselves our consideration&#44; but not it should not be followed in the<lb/> its exact form.  I do wish that we establish a covenant&#44; but<lb/> not with men&#44; but with God&#59; not a covenant founded upon selfishness.<lb/>  Not a covenant&#44; that has for its basis a mutual un&#45;<lb/>&#45;derstanding that no one shall suffer pecuniarily&#44; through<lb/> business transacted by a Jewish neighbor on the Sabbath<lb/> day&#44; but such a covenant as that made at Horeb &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Ye<lb/> shall be my people&#44; and I will be your God&#34; a covenant<lb/> of righteousness&#44; a renewal of the promise that we would<lb/> sanctify the name of the Lord among the nations of the<lb/> earth&#44; and He would signally protect our race.  In<lb/> other words&#58; I most eagerly desire that you be impressed<lb/> with the necessity of proving yourselves consistent<lb/> before men&#44; and faithful to your God.  That you feel it your<lb/> bounden duty to adhere to the fourth as to the rest of<lb/> the tenets promulgated at Sinai for no line of demarcation separates them.  I desire that you<lb/> feel how wrong&#44; how false it is to stand before the<lb/> book of the law&#44; blessing the Lord for having<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>vouchsafed it unto Israel&#44; and immediately violate<lb/> it by repairing on this day to your habitual vocations&#44; on this day&#59; by intentionally and<lb/> publicly desecrating the Sabbath.  And when deeply<lb/> imbued with the idea that the institution of the Sabbath is<lb/> essential to the preservation of our distinct nationality&#44;<lb/> that to enforce its observance upon your offspring sons&#44; is<lb/> equally important as to admit them into the covenant of<lb/> Abraham&#44; I would thus address you.  Brethren&#33;  Reward<lb/> those of youth your faith&#44; who cling to its holy ordinances.<lb/>  Let them find in your employ&#44; the facility to pursue<lb/> righteousness.  Yonder youth might have fre&#45;<lb/>&#45;quently obtained an honorable position&#44; but he<lb/> refused it not to dishonor God.  You may trust<lb/> him&#44; for&#44; he is honest.  The man who wavers in<lb/> opinion about religious obligations may deceive and<lb/> defraud&#59; but he who is firm with God&#44; he who has constantly that has the fear of the Lord Almighty before<lb/> his eyes&#44; will serve you with fidelity&#44; and promote<lb/> your interests.  But more than your material<lb/> welfare&#44; your spiritual happiness will increase through<lb/> that means.  You will have David a fellow&#45;believer from<lb/> the power of temptation&#44; and God will save you in the day<lb/> of judgment&#44; when summoned ot give an account of your deeds on earth you will have given your brother&#45;Israelite his Sabbath<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>and God will receive for you a Sabbath of<lb/> everlasting rest&#44; &#38; peace unalleged.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
