<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF13_5</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_5_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_5_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_5_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_5_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_5_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_5_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_5_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_5_4v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>5 pages on 2 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>16</p>
            <p>A few words delivered on &#91;Hebrew&#93; Subse&#45;<lb/>
                &#45;quent to the burial of the Revd. J. J. Lyons of N. Y.<lb/></p>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  It is due to departed worth that a meed of<lb/> praise be bestowed therefrom.  I will be brief and truthful<lb/> Jaques J. Lyons has just been summoned before that bar<lb/> of justice&#44; where the verdict is pronounced not according<lb/> to circumstantial evidence&#44; but according to an <sic>inffallible</sic><lb/> record made of man&#39;s honest intentions.  Believing so&#44;<lb/> I bear the joyful conviction that the servant of Israel&#39;s<lb/> God will be awarded a high seat &#34;in the sphere of the<lb/> holy and pure&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Called&#44; while<lb/> still a youth&#44; to fill the position of Reader in a very influen&#45;<lb/>&#45;tial Sephardic congregation&#44; he discharge the various<lb/> duties attending his calling most acceptably and conscien&#45;<lb/>&#45;tiously.  During a series of years&#44; the manner in which<lb/> my former colleague chanted the Hebrew melodies&#44; and his<lb/> demeanour at the sacred desk&#44; formed the topic of<lb/> familiar conversation among the numerous attendants at<lb/> the synagogue in the principal city of this land&#44; and gave<lb/> the young minister an enviable reputation.<lb/>  But &#34;temporu mutantur&#34; is the Latin saying&#58;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>And he is wise&#44; who alive to that fact&#44; endeavours<lb/> to make newly&#45;arisen circumstances harmonize as closely<lb/> as it is possible with the cherished ideas of the past.<lb/>  In the possession of that wisdom&#44; my revered colleague<lb/> was wanting.  He failed to perceive that what was<lb/> wont to create ecstatic pleasure in the fathers&#44; had<lb/> become vapid to the children&#39;s taste.  He might&#44; if<lb/> had early so determined&#44; have effected the reconciliation<lb/> of two opposites&#44; greatly to his own credit&#44; and to the<lb/> lasting benefit of Judaism.  But&#44; constitutionally&#44; he<lb/> could view matters only from his own stand&#45;point&#44; con&#45;<lb/>&#45;sequently his good working was shorn of much that might<lb/> have increased its utility.  He did not realize that<lb/> to prevent the breakers ahead carrying everything before<lb/> them&#44; the lashing of the sea with a shepherd&#39;s crook<lb/> would be profitless&#44; that a well&#45;grounded and high<lb/> bank must be set up for that purpose&#44; but he con&#45;<lb/>&#45;sidered such an undertaking of little or no advantage.<lb/>  He trusted in Providence&#44; and in his own personal character<lb/> for the continuance of historical Judaism&#44; and made not<lb/> the strenuous effort demanded for its permanent pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;servation.  In other words&#58; Thy deceased colaborer<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>never realized the full importance of pulpit and college<lb/> to stem the torrent of skepticism&#44; and redeem from destruction<lb/> Law and traditions.<lb/></p>
            <p>Having said this simply in deference to Truth&#44; I will now<lb/> repeat that the Hazan of the Sheareth Israel Congre&#45;<lb/>&#45;gation of New York challenges universal regard for<lb/> the religious consistency of his conduct&#44; during a ministerial<lb/> career lasting over 40 years.  &#43;.  While defection surrounded<lb/> him on all sides&#44; he remained constant alike to the prin&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciples of the faith&#44; and to the time&#45;honored customs of<lb/> the fathers.  He peculiarly delighted in the service<lb/> tendered to God at the synagogue&#44; and notwithstanding<lb/> failing health&#44; he would be always found in the holy<lb/> shrines glowing with ardor&#44; while singing the ancient<lb/> hymns of the Spanish and Portuguese liturgy.  Those<lb/> under his immediate ministration&#44; are of one mind re&#45;<lb/>&#45;garding the pathos he imparted to funeral rites&#44; and<lb/> the solemnity which his voice and words added to the<lb/> marriage ceremony.  Slight as my acquaintance<lb/> with the reverend gentleman was&#44; I can nevertheless testify<lb/></p>
            
            <p>&#43; Two years he officiated in Richmond Va&#44; and<lb/> thirty eight in New York.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>to a trait in his character always deserving com&#45;<lb/>&#45;mendation.  He would hospitably entertain the stranger&#59;<lb/> and the few times which I&#44; on some extraordinary occasion&#44;<lb/> happened to be absent from my home and congregation&#44;<lb/> and I visited either his place of worship or his residence&#44;<lb/> he would not suffer me to leave&#44; without my having<lb/> first sat at his generous board.<lb/></p>
            <p>But a monument to his memory on which all who<lb/> love our belief must look with veneration is pastoral<lb/> dignity&#44; which he so becomingly upheld.  He felt<lb/> that to swerve even once from the path of moral<lb/> rectitude&#44; would have been to lower the standard of<lb/> those whose good shepherd he had vowed to become&#44;<lb/> and cast therewithal shame upon the Hebrew race.<lb/>  Led by that wholesome thought&#44; he kept uncorrupt<lb/> amidst seething corruption.  Not even a shadow of<lb/> suspicion rested on his reputation&#44; while the shifting<lb/> and shuffling and capering of newly ordained ministers&#59;<lb/> aye&#58; of time serving&#44; money loving cormorants disgraced<lb/> the name they bore&#44; and &#91;&#63;&#93; the age with religion<lb/> and its representatives.  J. J. Lyons may not<lb/> have been endowed with mental capacities to shine<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>in oratory or to make his mark as a college&#45;<lb/>professor&#44; but if he preached little and taught only<lb/> rudiments&#44; his every day&#39;s life instructed young and old&#59;<lb/> it practically showed the way of a Jew must pursue&#44;<lb/> if he wishes to honor his people and sanctify his God.<lb/>  Purity my co&#45;worker wore as his habitual gar&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment&#44; honesty became the girdle wherewith he<lb/> fastened his loins.  May He who abides in<lb/> purity&#44; and bids honesty weave crown for His glo&#45;<lb/>&#45;rious Divinity&#44; call to happiness his servant&#44; the<lb/> son of This handmaid.  May the minister of &#34;the<lb/> remnant of Israel&#34; hear angels attune their voices<lb/> to rehearse his social and domestic virtues&#44; as he in<lb/> the ardency of religiousness made the Synagogue resound<lb/> with the praises of the Most High.  And may the con&#45;<lb/>&#45;solation which he afforded the bereaved and afflicted&#44;<lb/> while in the discharge of his duties&#44; gain lasting<lb/> comfort to his distressed widow&#44; to his sons and<lb/> daughter&#44; and the congregation he faithfully served.<lb/>  Brethren&#33; rise and let us <sic>us</sic> offer the prayer of<lb/> our ritual for the repose of the pious dead.<lb/>  &#40;The long Hashcabah followed&#41;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
