<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF4_9</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_9_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_9_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_9_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_9_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_9_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_9_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_9_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_9_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_9_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_9_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_9_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_9_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_9_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_9_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_9_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_9_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>13 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Post Biblical history<lb/>
                29<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#34;Righteousness exalts a nation&#44; but sin is the<lb/> disgrace of peoples&#34;.  So wrote a pen guided by<lb/> inspiration&#44; while Judah and Israel dwelt in safety&#44;<lb/> every one resting under his vine and his fig tree.&#34;<lb/>  Very Truthful is the maxim in very deed&#44; and even as the first part<lb/> of it the rest has had its literal fulfilment&#93;sic&#33;&#93; in the history<lb/> of our ancestors&#44; so has its second part been too<lb/> painfully illustrated in their annals.  Shame&#44; accom&#45;<lb/>&#45;panied by sorrows and sufferings came to stay<lb/> in their midst&#44; when virtue had been turned away.<lb/>  The Temple remained still open before the total Judah&#39;s<lb/> dispersion&#44; but the ministers at the altar were<lb/> mostly corrupt&#59; pliant tools they were in the hands<lb/> of unprincipled men.  High priests were made<lb/> and unmade at pleasure&#44; and not rarely the heavier<lb/> by bag of gold won for its possessor the mitre<lb/> which had adorned the brows of Aaron.  The Tem&#45;<lb/>&#45;ple remained still opened before Israel&#39;s fatal fall&#44; but the vital breath<lb/> of religion had departed from it.  A superstitious<lb/> attachment to walls and floors and consecrated and vessels supplanted reveren&#45;<lb/>&#45;tial awe.  The Temple remained still open&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>but the rulers who were to bend the knee therein&#44;<lb/> like the humblest in Israel of their subjects&#44; showed contempt for<lb/> its worship.  The book of the Law which they<lb/> should have read to instruct and to exhort&#44; had changed<lb/> its living spirit into a dead letter.<lb/></p>
            <p>I confess that in calling back to mind the events&#44; which<lb/> followed the sudden termination of the reign of<lb/> Agrippa I&#44; my heart misgave me.  It is a<lb/> tale of sin and of disgrace&#44; which I would be compelled<lb/> to narrate&#44; and then&#44; alas&#63; so fearful are the disasters&#44;<lb/> so <sic>woful</sic> the distress and affliction&#44; which our<lb/> fathers endured&#44; that at the thought of them&#44; I<lb/> resolved determined me to touch lightly on a period of post&#45;bi&#45;<lb/>&#45;blical history&#44; so replete with horrors.<lb/></p>
            <p>The Governors sent by Rome to Judea after the<lb/> demise of Agrippa&#44; were greedy and inhuman and<lb/> indifferent to the religious susceptibilities of those<lb/> whom they governed.  Under Camanus&#44; one<lb/> of his soldiers keeping sentinel round the Temple&#44;<lb/> indecently insulted our people&#44; who flocked into<lb/> it to celebrate the Passover.  On another occa&#45;<lb/>&#45;sion&#44; a Roman soldier laid hold of the a scroll of the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Law and spitefully tore it into fragments&#44; uttering<lb/> vulgar curses.  Shortly after that&#44; some pilgrims<lb/> on their way to Jerusalem were cruelly set upon and<lb/> killed.  These unhappy untoward incidents caused encouraged outbreaks<lb/> and bloodshed&#59; for our ancestors finding no redress and<lb/> seeing themselves exposed to murderous attacks&#44; followed<lb/> the lead of political chiefs who were bent upon slaughter slaughter and<lb/> plunder.  Then the Roman governors would make order<lb/> a general slaughter massacre&#44; and turn a deaf ear to the en&#45;<lb/>&#45;treaties of myriads who prayed that the innocent<lb/> might be spared.  The pitiless Cumanus was<lb/> not at last recalled&#44; and the emperor Claudius banished<lb/> him from Rome&#44; but his successor Felix made the<lb/> Jews rue the moment they had asked for a change&#44; for in refined barbarity and cove&#45;<lb/>&#45;tousness the new governor left his predecessor far<lb/> behind.  The more insufferable must the presence<lb/> of that monster have been to our people&#44; because to indulge in his<lb/> profligacy he had lured the oldest daughter of Agrip&#45;<lb/>&#45;pa I into a desertion of her lawful husband.<lb/></p>
            <p>With a blush I acknowledge it&#58; None of the children<lb/> of the last king of Judea shed credit upon the religion<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>in which they were born.  His three daughters&#44;<lb/> Drussilla&#44; Berenice and Marianne became a<lb/> by word through their wanton behaviour&#59; his son<lb/> Agrippa II who might have proved a tower<lb/> of strength&#44; made no effort worthy of his maternal Maccabean<lb/> descent the Maccabees to help his unhappy fellow<lb/> believers.  When of age&#44; he was allowed by the<lb/> emperor of Rome large territories in Palestine. to rule<lb/> over  For them he cared&#59; to his reverences he mainly looked<lb/> with eagerness.  and Devoted to those who had placed him in power&#44; he finally he estranged himself<lb/> from the Hebrews&#44; and left his countrymen to their<lb/> sad fate.  Had the people whom Moses<lb/> and the prophets taught to trust in God&#44; leaned<lb/> then confidingly upon the arms everlasting Arms&#59; had they taken put on<lb/> righteousness for their shield as their armor&#44; disgrace and ruin would have been<lb/> averted&#44; but many seized the dagger which &#91;&#63;&#93; they remor&#45;<lb/> &#91;&#63;&#93; lentingly they &#45;selessly plunged into the hearts of their Jew&#45;<lb/>&#45;ish political opponents as well as the Romans&#44; and many in their despair relied on false Messiahs&#44;<lb/> who arose in various sections of the country and led<lb/> the credulous to destruction.<lb/></p>
            <p>At one time&#44; a certain Theudus persuaded multitudes<lb/> to carry all they possessed to the banks of the Jordan.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Joshua like he would divide the water and open for<lb/> Israel a way to conquest and freedom.  The deceiver and the deceived were slain by a troop of Roman horsemen.  At another<lb/> time&#44; an Egypptian Jew succeeded in gathering nearly&#44;<lb/> thirty thousand persons&#44; to whom he gave the assu&#45;<lb/>&#45;rance that as he stood upon the mount of Olives&#44;<lb/> the walls of Jerusalem below would fall down &#91;&#63;&#93; flat&#44;<lb/> down&#44; and he and his partizans would enter the capital in triumph&#44;<lb/> while Roman and her legions would be crushed.  Felix<lb/> attacked the imposter self&#45;deluded chieftain and his dupes&#44; and killed un&#45;<lb/>&#45;sparringly relentingly.  Josephus who justly deprecates the<lb/> frequent rising of pseudo&#45;Messiahs&#44; as the forerunners of calami&#45;<lb/>&#45;ties&#44; has nevertheless many a tale to relate about<lb/> certain supernatural signs of the approaching overthrow of Judea&#44;<lb/> of the burning of the Temple and the wide spread capti&#45;<lb/>&#45;vity.  Evidently our historian believed who prides himself on his clear understanding put implicit faith in evil<lb/> omens and wild prognostics.  He writes that a comet<lb/> in the shape of a sword was seen in Palestine for a<lb/> whole year&#44; previous to the final war.  Again&#58; On a night<lb/> of Passover all at once the sanctuary was lighted up<lb/> by invisible hands.  A brazen gate of the Temple&#44;<lb/> which it took twenty men to shut&#44; suddenly flew<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>wide open&#44; and it was with extreme difficulty<lb/> that strong people could close it again.  Shortly<lb/> after Passover at towards sunset&#44; chariots and a&#91;&#63;&#93;<lb/> cavalry appeared in the sky&#44; and on Pentecost<lb/> the priests heard a noise and a voice as of a<lb/> great army exclaiming&#58; &#34;let us depart hence&#34;&#63;<lb/>  But in the opinion of Josephus nothing was more<lb/> significant of the impending doom than the following<lb/> circumstance&#44; for which he seems to vouch.  Du&#45;<lb/>&#45;ring seven years&#44; an ordinary person&#44; called Jesus<lb/> son of Ananus walked the streets of the capital<lb/> and cried thus&#58; &#34;a voice from the East&#44; a voice<lb/> from the West&#44; a voice from the four winds&#44; a<lb/> voice against Jerusalem and against the Temple&#44;<lb/> a voice against the bridegrooms and the brides&#44; a<lb/> voice against the whole people.&#34;  The man<lb/> who gave forth those gloomy sounds&#44; would be some&#45;<lb/>&#45;time be beaten and not wince&#59; he would be arrested<lb/> and not say a word.  One day after the siege<lb/> had begun&#44; he passed by near where the engines were throw&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing out destructive missiles.  He then cried aloud&#58; &#34;Woe to the<lb/> people and to the holy house.  Woe unto me&#34; and a stone<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>struck him dead.  As usual with Jose&#45;<lb/>&#45;hus&#44; he ads his comments to his narrative&#44; reflecting upon<lb/> those who did not share his views and political<lb/> proclivities.  Admit&#58; the anti&#45;Roman party&#44; named<lb/> &#34;zealots&#34; and more disparagingly also sicarii and assassins did com&#45;<lb/>&#45;mit excesses unpardonable&#44; revolting.  To recall<lb/> them is to make the blood run cold congeal in our veins&#44; but it was not<lb/> the comet nor other prodigies the reported noise in the Holy place that foreshadowed the<lb/> def desperate resistance of those &#91;&#63;&#93; sworn enemies<lb/> of foreign masters.  and It was not the lamentations of a person crazed by grief that predicted the soul&#45;terrifying crisis.<lb/>  When Rome sent to govern Judea iniquitous men like<lb/> Felix&#44; Albinus and Florus&#44; the most peacefully inclined<lb/> must have predicted that a fore seen before hand the fire of popular indignation<lb/> with would which was about to irrepressibly burst forth into &#91;&#63;&#93; flames.<lb/></p>
            <p>If Rome had wished to madden a people into a hatred<lb/> which would stop short at nothing in order to reek wreak<lb/> vengeance upon the heathen stranger&#44; she could not<lb/> have accomplished her end more effectually than by<lb/> making Florus governor of the country&#44; once independent un&#45;<lb/>&#45;der Simon and John Hyrcanus thought&#44; to enrich himself&#44;<lb/> even if every Jew was reduced to beggary&#44; and every home<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>in Judea became desolate.  Shielded by the<lb/> friendship existing between his wife and Poppea<lb/> the wife of the infamous Nero&#44; then Roman emperor&#44;<lb/> he defied the people into savageness&#44; and laughed<lb/> at to scorn their attempts to self&#45;defence.  But the conflict<lb/> which could not long be put off&#44; was hastened by the<lb/> inveterate animosities of the Greeks of Cesarea.  In this<lb/> city there was a rich congregation of Hebrews.  A Greek<lb/> owned the ground round adjoining to the synagogue.  To protect the sacred structurre&#44; a large<lb/> sum was offered him to dispose of it his lot&#44; but he would<lb/> not accept any the highest price.  On the contrary&#44; to annoy<lb/> his neighbours&#44; he built low shops on the vacant spot&#44;<lb/> lot&#44; and made the entrance into the synagogue as<lb/> narrow as it would possibly be.  The Jews felt were incensed&#44;<lb/> and tried to stop the workmen.  Then Not succeeding they sent<lb/> Florus a present of eight talents&#44; &#40;about 8000 dollars&#41;<lb/> asking petitioning that he should would interfere and prevent their place<lb/> of worship from being blocked up.  Florus put the<lb/> money to his never enough&#45;filled purse the purse which was never filled enough&#44; and dismissed the<lb/> subject altogether from his mind.  To The Greek to add insult to injury&#44;<lb/> on a Sabbath as our people was crowding the Synagogue&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>a Greek openly mocked ridiculed the Jewish Jews and their worship.  A<lb/> fight ensued&#44; in which the Jews our people&#45;&#45;being few in number&#45;&#45;<lb/> were worsted.  A deputation that came before<lb/> Florus with complaints were cast into prison.<lb/>  As soon as The news reached Judea Jerusalem&#44; and anger and a<lb/> longing for revenge seized the multitudes.  Florus instead<lb/> of calming allaying the just burning indignation&#44; added fuel to the fire<lb/> by asking that seventeen talents be paid to him from out of<lb/> the public treasury&#44; in behalf of Rome.  The peace party&#44;<lb/> headed by many of the priests&#44; submitted to the humiliating unrighteous<lb/> exaction&#44; but as some had gone about ironically with<lb/> baskets asking lams for &#34;a man in a miserable condi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion&#44;&#34; meaning Florus the latter demanded the surrender of those who had<lb/> so mocked him&#44; that he might crucify them.  The<lb/> request could and would not be complied with.  At the<lb/> refusal&#44; Florus gave a signal&#44; and his troops spread<lb/> death terror everywhere&#44; kiling pillaging and outraging men&#44; wo&#45;<lb/>&#45;men and children.  Berenice&#44; daughter of the<lb/> late king Agrippa&#45;&#45;vicious as her character was&#45;&#45;still<lb/> melting with compassion for her coreligionists pren went before<lb/> Florus barefooted&#44; in token of humiliation&#44; imploring him<lb/> to let the carnage cease.  She hardly escaped being<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>herself given over to the loos soldiery.  Florus<lb/> then to fill the measure of popular irritation&#44; ordered<lb/> that as a token mark of submission the inhabitants of<lb/> Jerusalem should greet the entrance of two Roman<lb/> cohorts who that were passing through to go to Caesa&#45;<lb/>&#45;rea.  The prayers of the priests who supplicated the<lb/> people to yield for the sake of averting complete ruin&#44;<lb/> succeeded.  The Roman troops received a welcome&#44; which<lb/> they did not condescend to notice&#44; but treated with silent<lb/> contempt.  Aggravated by such a despicable conduct&#44;<lb/> the population hurled curses load and heavy against<lb/> Florus.  It was precisely what he the governor wished&#44;&#45;&#45;a pretext<lb/> to kill slay and plunder.  The military &#91;&#63;&#93; fell upon the<lb/> crowd.  In the pressure bodies were trampled on and<lb/> mangled&#44; and the Temple would have been attacked and<lb/> pillaged emptied out of its precious valuables&#44; if the war party&#45;&#45;the uncompromising zealots&#45;&#45;<lb/> had not quickly cut off every avenue&#44; and forced the<lb/> vile Florus and his Roman hirelings to beat a retreat.<lb/></p>
            <p>Agrippa II who was returning from Egypt<lb/> on learning of those disastrous events&#44; tried the<lb/> influence of his name to quiet the agitated<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>minds&#44; by holding out the hope of a change for<lb/> the better in a the possible appointment of a new<lb/> governor.  He delivered a long winded oration&#44;<lb/> descriptive of the colossal power of Rome&#44; which<lb/> had brought under mightier&#44; more famous<lb/> and more numerous peoples than the Jews.<lb/>  He dwelt at Cae with laid a great stress on the absurdity<lb/> of attempting to cope with such a power&#44; com&#45;<lb/>&#45;manding the wide world.  He advised urged entire<lb/> submission&#44; the prompt payment of tributes&#44; and<lb/> urged the necessity of showing satisfaction at being<lb/> allowed the possession of the Temple&#44; and the free<lb/> exercise of religious practices.  That lengthy<lb/> speech&#44; which I always read with increasing dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;gust&#44; because so servile to domineering Rome&#44; was<lb/> accompanied with tears&#44; in which Berenice joined.<lb/>  The people believed in their sincerity of those tears&#44;<lb/> and promised to follow the counsel.  But Agrippa<lb/> presumed too much on the patience of an his out&#45;<lb/>&#45;raged countrymen.  When he requested that they<lb/> should pay obedience to Florus&#44; as their present<lb/> governor&#44; good nature kindled into passion.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p>The men who had listened respectfully and<lb/> agreed to conform to the advice&#44; grew furious<lb/> They threw stones at the speaker&#44; and made<lb/> him hastily flee from their presence.<lb/>  In an essay by a very eminent Christian<lb/> scholar&#44; Agrippa II is represented as a man<lb/> deserving more than his father all the praise which the Talmudists have<lb/> bestowed on his father Agrippa I.  Perhaps&#44; the writer&#39;s<lb/> favorable opinion is based upon a passage in<lb/> the New Testament in which&#44; at the conclusion<lb/> of a speech&#45;&#45;in self&#45;justification by Saul of Tarsus&#44; called St. Paul who had been imprisoned by Felix&#44; Agrip&#45;<lb/>&#45;pa is credited with having said &#34;Almost thou persua&#45;<lb/>&#45;dest me to be a Christian&#44;&#34; but whether the state&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment be correct or not&#44; we that read the most the soul<lb/> stirring events in of our post&#45;biblical history with<lb/> profound anguish&#44; see in Agrippa II a<lb/> bad Jew&#44; a selfish flatterer&#44; and a dastardly heartless<lb/> traitor&#44; while with the Talmudists we still<lb/> proclaim call his father&#44; Agrippa I &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Thou art our brother&#44; thou art indeed our<lb/> brother.&#34;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
