<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF9_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1890-05" source="" attested="yes">May 1890</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_2_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. Fifth St.<lb/></p>
            <p>Philadelphia&#44; May&#47;90<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>For Nasso about prayers<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Profuse was each prince of the tribes in his gifts to the<lb/> Sanctuary.  The generosity was acknowledged by the<lb/> inspired legislator&#44; who rewarded it by a separate mention<lb/> thereof&#44; otherwise seemingly monotonous&#44; but I miss<lb/> an essential offering&#45;&#45;that which is represented by thanks<lb/> and praises to the Most High.  Why was that wanting&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Did our ancestors&#44; under the ministration of Moses&#44; ever hold a<lb/> public supplicatory worship&#63; Divine services of thanksgiving and supplications&#63;  A definite answer to this<lb/> question&#44; which has been often asked&#44; is not possible.<lb/>  If we take simply the Hebrew scriptures as our guide&#44; we<lb/> shall search in vain for the prayers&#44; constituting our fore&#45;<lb/>&#45;fathers&#39; divine service worship&#44; during the forty years of their encam&#45;<lb/>&#45;ping in wildernesses&#59; nor can we discover the trace of any such<lb/> prayer uttering a worship by the people at large&#44; till a num&#45;<lb/>&#45;ber of centuries later.  We do meet quite early in our<lb/> history with intreaties invocations offered to God by single indivi&#45;<lb/>&#45;duals.  Thus&#44; without having recourse to Talmudical infe&#45;<lb/>&#45;rences&#44; we clearly see that the founder of the Hebrew<lb/> nation&#44; made supplications to the Lord on several occa&#45;<lb/>&#45;sions&#44; and most prominently in the first book of the Law stands the petition of Abraham<lb/> on behalf of the sinful inhabitants of Sodom.  The example<lb/> of our the first patriarchs from Ur Chasdim&#44; must have been copied by his son&#44; who<lb/> is mentioned as having gone to solitarily meditate&#44; credited with meditating on the contemplation of nature&#44; or&#44; as<lb/> some render the expression &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Isaac went out to pray in the field towards evening time&#44;&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>and we learn that Jacob vowed made a solemn vow to the Almighty&#44; when<lb/> he left home to go among to the land of the strangers&#44; and he be&#45;<lb/>&#45;sought heavenly protection when returning home after<lb/> twenty years&#39; absence&#44; but fearing to meet his of&#45;<lb/>&#45;fended brother Esau.  Still those incidents&#44;<lb/> and similar ones of remote times&#44; are merely of a per&#45;<lb/>sonal not of a national character.  The first case instance<lb/> chronicled of an apparently united <sic>intreaty</sic> to the Lord is that of<lb/> the Israelites in Egypt&#44; for we read that when a tyrannic King had died their cry&#44;<lb/> or complaint&#44; went up to God by reason of the<lb/> bondage &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  But we are<lb/> left in total ignorance as to the nature and manner<lb/> of their supplications.  Our own minds<lb/> would suggest that after the Tabernacle had been<lb/> erected&#44; a public supplicatory worship was instituted by the<lb/> inspired leader of the tribes&#44; for admitting&#44; as we<lb/> are forced to acknowledge&#44; that it was not in their power<lb/> always to offer daily sacrifices&#45;&#45;demanding the possession<lb/> of a vast stock of animals yet nevertheless&#44; the existence of a<lb/> sanctuary&#44; and of priests and levites&#44; set apart to officiate&#44;<lb/> would seem to point to a devotional service of some kind.  But no<lb/> account distinct history account of it have the five books recorded.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>That the pure lips of Moses moved frequently in prayers we are<lb/> certain&#44; from for from the moment that his yearning<lb/> after the enslaved made him fear lest his interposi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion do harm rather than good&#59; as he exclaimed &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Wherefore &#40;O Lord&#41; hast Thou sent me&#63;&#34;<lb/> and through all the long and weary forty years of his<lb/> faithful ministration&#44; till he beheld from afar the approaching goal<lb/> of his wishes&#44; frequent was which he was not destined to enjoy the imploring of his soul for<lb/> guidance&#44; for pardon and mercy many a time ascended the heavens many a time.  But the archprophet<lb/> did not tell posterity whether the congregation also prayed&#44; whether at the convocations which<lb/> he was directed to appoint&#44; the people prayed unitedly thanked &#38; praised God.  We<lb/> may argue that they must have assembled for that purpose&#44; because<lb/> the very words &#91;Hebrew&#93; namely&#44; calling together for<lb/> holiness&#44; gives that our argument support&#44; even if we<lb/> lay aside whatever Rabbis or critics may have written<lb/> on the subject.  Still&#44; ours would be only a reasonable<lb/> supposition&#44; not a plainly stated fact to which we may cite as unquestionable.  However&#44;<lb/> in my mind what tradition invests that supposition<lb/> with an almost scriptural authority I will explain.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>If we turn to the opening of the fourth book of psalms<lb/>&#45;&#45;for all are aware that the Psalter because of its<lb/> high value has been divided into five books to make it correspond to the<lb/> Pentateuch&#45;&#45;if we turn to it&#44; we shall notice that the volumes begins with<lb/> a prayer breathed out by the arch&#45;prophet.  In lan&#45;<lb/>&#45;guage of deep pathos he describes the shortcoming<lb/> of human life as the effect of sin&#44; for whereas in for&#45;<lb/>&#45;mer ages to reach far beyond a hundred years was<lb/> nearly every one&#39;s lot&#44; now the score and ten only could<lb/> be attained&#44; and or by reason of strength four score years.<lb/>  The saintly suppliant calls upon Him who existed before<lb/> the mountains were brought forth and in whose eyes a<lb/> thousand years are like yesterday when it is passed<lb/> and a watch in the night&#44; to teach His people to<lb/> number their days&#44; so that they may apply their heart<lb/> to wisdom.  That invocation&#44; worthy of a conspicuous<lb/> place in that collection of soul&#45;stirring compositions&#44; which<lb/> are is ours spiritual wealth&#44; but which gentilism has largely borrowed<lb/> for its own use at devotional gatherings&#44; that prayer<lb/> of Moses the man of God&#44; doubtless had as its origin doubtless in a sad event in<lb/> our annals.  as its origin.  The decree had gone forth&#44;<lb/> the generation of adults that came out of Egypt must die in the wilderness&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>but the leader of unshaken faith&#44; he who firmly<lb/> believed that God turns man to contrition chastens for our ultimate good&#44; saying&#58; &#34;Return<lb/> ye children of man&#34;; the great teacher&#44; harbored no<lb/> fear.  God would still show His saving power to<lb/> the fathers&#44; and manifest His glory unto their children.<lb/>  Now&#44; is it too extravagant an idea to hold that<lb/> the same man of God were who so fervently besought<lb/> the Almighty for the sake of those he loved&#44; though<lb/> sinful&#59; is it now too unreasonable to think that he who<lb/> wished that Israel might consider the fleeting stages<lb/> of this existence&#44; and wisely prepare for a life hereafter&#44;<lb/> should have taught the tribes also to lay their sup&#45;<lb/>&#45;plications at the altar of the Most High&#44; petitioning<lb/> for forgiveness and for <sic>tranquillity</sic> of mind while on earth&#63;<lb/>  I judge deem it very rational so to think surmise judge hence I contend that it<lb/> is more than probable that long before the golden<lb/> ear of our history arose dawned when David&#44; and his gifted<lb/> associates&#44; Heman&#44; &#38; Asaph and Ethan and Jedulthan<lb/> of enriched us with the poetical effusions which re&#45;<lb/>sounded in the Jerusalem Temple&#44; our ancestors made<lb/> their devotions&#44; as instructed by the son of Amram and<lb/> Aaron his brother&#44; and the Levites and the elders&#44; in the Tabernacle round Sinai and Paran &#38; Kasoth.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>But there is a national prayer in the five lo books which&#44;<lb/> though not intended to be pronounced by the people&#44;<lb/> went up to God in unison of sentiments through the uninhabited wildernesses<lb/> in the days of Moses&#44; ere it was carried over to Palestine&#44;<lb/> it to remain with us during two captivities&#44; and it is be<lb/> still uttered whenever Israel gather to worship the One God.<lb/>  That prayer is chronicled in the section which we have<lb/> read this morning.  It is the holiest and the<lb/> most comprehensive in its conciseness&#45;&#45;the holiest be&#45;<lb/>&#45;cause it was reached down to us from heaven&#59; the<lb/> most comprehensive because it contains an entreaty<lb/> for whatever mortals essentially need here below.<lb/>  You understand that I allude to the threefold bles&#45;<lb/>&#45;sing the priests &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Verbal inspiration<lb/> dictated it&#44; for he who communed with the Lord was bid<lb/> to impart it to Aaron and his sons precisely as received.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  &#34;In this wise&#44; ye shall bless the children of Israel&#34;<lb/>  The first sentence having in the text three words&#44; im&#45;<lb/>&#45;plores God for the gift and preservation of health&#59; the<lb/> second containing five&#44; asks for understanding an enlightened illumined mind to pro&#45;<lb/>ceed aright&#59; the third comprising seven&#44; petitions for the<lb/> summary of all benedictions&#44; peace outwardly and inwardly.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>That prayer intensely Hebrew in diction and spirit&#44;<lb/> has been ever since and will&#44; to the end of time&#44;<lb/> hold prominence in Jewish worship.  To me it is<lb/> the swee a sweet reminder of I recall with profound emotions<lb/> early days&#44; when I heard that oldest and most sacred<lb/> of ordained prayers&#44; and I imagine yet to see fathers<lb/> laying their heads hands over the heads of their sons&#59; mo&#45;<lb/>&#45;thers over the heads of their daughters&#44; while the<lb/> Coharium at the Duchan changed in solemn impressive strains<lb/> words which have floated through the immense space<lb/> of ages&#44; unaltered and unimpaired&#44; just as God com&#45;<lb/>&#45;manded to be said by the undying progeny of him&#44;<lb/> on whose brows shone the token of his ministration<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Holy unto the Lord&#34;.  Touching was that<lb/> scene&#44; peculiar perhaps with Italian Jews&#44; for I have<lb/> not witnessed it elsewhere&#44; but in every city&#44; in every<lb/> town&#44; in every village the joyful solemnity of our<lb/> Biblical festivals is enhanced by the recital of<lb/> that same benediction.  Living miracle&#33;  The<lb/> indestructible lineage of those divinely privileged<lb/> to pronounce it&#44; state rehearse it still.  Its<lb/> discontinuance&#44; under the impression that only unsullied<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>lips are fit to utter it&#44; is an error&#44; into which<lb/> many have fallen&#44; who do not reflect upon the<lb/> closing verse.  The Cohen is no more the bestower<lb/> of the blessing than the reader of the Torah is the giver<lb/> of the Law.  The Cohen is simply the agent of the<lb/> Deity who vouchsafes to employ human means.  He<lb/> is the guardian of that benediction communicated by<lb/> the Supreme to Moses.  He call upon thrice invokes the name<lb/> of the Author of all happiness&#44; and God grants the<lb/> blessing.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            <p>To restore the usage of the Duchan service in our midst after many years<lb/> of its determined discontinuance&#44; might not be practi&#45;<lb/>&#45;cable&#44; but in the absence of those who have a right to<lb/> uplift their hands towards the people of God with words<lb/> of Divine love&#44; may their substitute be hearkened above.<lb/>  When he prays asks for the fruition of those gifts so precious&#44;<lb/> health&#44; good understanding and peace to all who<lb/> believe in the Universal Creator&#44; may he be answered&#44; as<lb/> promised by the psalmist &#34;The Lord is nigh to all<lb/> who call upon Him&#44; to all that call upon Him<lb/> in truth.&#34;<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
