<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF4_13</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_13_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_13_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_13_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_13_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_13_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_13_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_13_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_13_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_13_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_13_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_13_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_13_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Post Biblical<lb/>
                33<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>In giving at longer or shorter intervals an abridged account<lb/> of what happened among our people after the events told<lb/> in the book of Nehemiah&#45;&#45;with which Bible history<lb/> closes&#45;&#45;I have had one object principally in view.  I would<lb/> enable those whom I am bound to instruct&#44; to form an idea of<lb/> the causes which were long largely latently at work to bring about the overthrow of our poli&#45;<lb/>&#45;tical nationality.  As I believe in prophecy&#44; and as I saw<lb/> its finger point unerringly to the fatal consequences of our fathers&#39; de&#45;<lb/>&#45;sertion from duty&#44; I would show the origin of unequalled<lb/> sufferings and of a world wide spread dispersion.  For the fond&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness of copying heathen practices which called forth the burning<lb/> denunciations of our leaders during the existence of the first<lb/> sanctuary&#59; that mania passion mania for imitating gentilism which so saddened our faithful guides during the<lb/> second sanctuary&#44; but which the good illustrious Mattathias the of<lb/> Asmonean Modin changed for a time into a renewed love for Mosaic<lb/> laws&#44; that passion evil passion&#44; I say woke again and ran riot under the wicked Herod.<lb/>  Nothing Jewish was sacred with that destroyer of the Asmonean<lb/> family&#44; and vile hireling of pagan Rome&#44; who sat on<lb/> a Jewish throne.  And as he had defied religion&#44; and had<lb/> dared even to make and unmake high priests to seve serve his<lb/> purposes&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>so the conflicting parties that unhappily<lb/> arose in later years&#44; used the same foul means to reach<lb/> their unrighteous ends.  The man who was to minister<lb/> in the holy of holies should must further their nefarious schemes.<lb/>  His fitness for the solemn office was not studied.<lb/>  Lots were cast to choose him&#44; and the least qualified he<lb/> proved himself&#44; the more was he liked most because the more<lb/> readily he could readily become a toll in the hands of those who<lb/> had clothed him with the ephod and the mitre.<lb/>  The Mishnah hints at the low pitch to which the<lb/> station once held by Aaron had been reduced&#44; when it<lb/> writes that on the eve of the day of atonement the<lb/> high priest who was not familiar with the Bible had<lb/> a person appointed to read it for him.  But worse<lb/> than that is related by in Josephus.  A certain Phan&#45;<lb/>&#45;nias who had never known the first requisites of a<lb/> priest&#44; but who engaged in tilling the ground &#44;was<lb/> taken from the plough and mockingly placed before the altar&#44; to the<lb/> profound grief of all who ye respected yet the worship of God.<lb/>  But while I have thought it necessary th to<lb/> vindicate the dealings of the Lord with Israel&#44; and to prove the<lb/> predictions of our Moses and the prophets true&#59;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>while I would never cover up public offenses&#44; but<lb/> on the contrary I would always expose them in their naked <sic>uggliness</sic> for to the<lb/> abhorrence of the virtuous&#44; still I should have been false<lb/> to history and have wronged my people not to have by not having had I failed to<lb/> direct the attention of my hearers to deeds of unsurpassed<lb/> valor&#59; to a bravery which made the fall disruption breaking up of our na&#45;<lb/>&#45;tionality not a record of disgrace&#44; but the grandest sublimest of<lb/> all epic poems.  I specially desired that they young<lb/> might feel a noble pride on remembering that the<lb/> blood coursing in through their veins is the blood of <sic>heros</sic>.<lb/>  For the systematic persecution of ages may have humbled<lb/> to the dust some of the descendants of the fearless defenders<lb/> of home and country&#44; but the study of the past ought to<lb/> be even to such a lever of self&#45;exaltation convince all that manliness is the heritage of Hebrews.<lb/>  Jotapata has a historic name which electrifies our beings&#44; and<lb/> I have set it forth as an illustration of self&#45;denying greatness&#44; but<lb/> other cities in ancient Judea possess chronicles which<lb/> undying fame has written down traced in golden letters.  Let me speak<lb/> of Gamala in famous Galilee.  An odd city was that Gamala.  Situated on a<lb/> steep rock&#44; sloping down at on each and side&#44; and<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>having in the middle a rough ridge&#44; like<lb/> the hump of a camel&#44; from which the city&#44; derived<lb/> its name appellation&#44; &#40;Gamla&#41;&#44; it seemed to dare the approach say to the enemy&#58; &#34;I dare you&#34;<lb/> of an enemy  The Jews had built dug ditches around&#44;<lb/> to cut off approach&#44; and mines under the ground.  The inhabitants of that weird<lb/> spot&#44; made hardy by their surroundings&#44; were looked<lb/> upon as undaunted mountaineers.  From their midst<lb/> had gone forth the intrepid Judah the Gaulanite&#44; who<lb/> proclaimed it a sin it a sin that to pay taxes to a foreign enemy. was a sin<lb/>  Agrippa II&#45;&#45;a creature of the Romans&#45;&#45;had tried<lb/> in vain to bring again under his power sway that uncom&#45;<lb/>&#45;promising city.  which It had revolted against his power&#44; and its revolutionary revolutionary and whose example<lb/> he dreaded&#44; because of was a threat to menace menace to his own territories lying which lay close to by it.<lb/>  Vespasian brought to bear against it to bear on Gamala all that<lb/> military science could project.  The best legions best skif skilfully mar&#45;<lb/>&#45;shalled were ordered to level at at against it engines of des&#45;<lb/>&#45;truction.  King Agrippa emboldened by the assist&#45;<lb/>&#45;ance of Rome&#44; ventured out upon an eminence to exhort<lb/> the dwellers of Gamala not to attempt a useless<lb/> resistance&#44; but to submit to superior forces&#44; as<lb/> others had yielded.  The speaker received as the<lb/> wages of his advice&#44; a stone hurled by an archer from a high wall&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>and which broke his shattered broke the speaker&#39;s his right arm.  Vespasian<lb/> having who arrived at the expiration of seven months<lb/> during which Agrippa had been <sic>beseiging</sic> Gamala&#44; found the<lb/> <sic>belleaguered</sic> much considerably weakened&#44; but yet not cowed and inti&#45;<lb/>&#45;midated.  The inhabitants numbered only nine thou&#45;<lb/>&#45;sands persons&#44; and there were among them aged men&#44; wo&#45;<lb/>&#45;men and children&#44; who necessarily exhausted a large<lb/> portion of the provision.  This circumstance occasioned deep concern.<lb/>  Recognizing the impossibility to stand bear the brunt of<lb/> the military war machines of the Romans&#44; and anxious<lb/> to bring the <sic>seige</sic> to an end and prevent starvation&#44;<lb/> the defenders of Gamala retired from behind the walls&#44;<lb/> and took their stand where they might fight back<lb/> the invading army with a steady aim.  For the city<lb/> had narrow and winding streets&#44; its houses rose one<lb/> above the other on the declivity of the rugged hills&#44; and which&#44; seen<lb/> at a distance&#44; appeared as if sus hanging in the air.<lb/>  In those ill&#45;shaped and perplexing streets&#44; and on the tops of the hills where<lb/> those oddly queerly built houses stood&#44; the Jews awaited.<lb/>  The walls fell from which they had withdrawn soon gave away fell at the shocks of the battering rams&#44;<lb/> and the Roman cohorts rushed on into the city with wild shouts of<lb/> triumph. into the city  They met Judean swords<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>swords&#44; sharp and pointed.  They turned to the mount&#45;<lb/>&#45;ains&#44; Judean lances from above forced thrust them down into<lb/> ravines the valley.  They ran into houses&#44; but the upper ones<lb/> gave way by the weight of the steel clad Roman soldiers&#44; and those<lb/> underneath came tumbling with a crash&#44; and buried hun&#45;<lb/>&#45;dreds in their ruins.  The people of Gamala took<lb/> up the stones of their broken dwellings. to beat Like an avalanche they came to overwhelm their<lb/> assailants&#44; entangled in streets lanes and gorges from<lb/> which they could not find an issue.  Vespasian<lb/> himself&#44; who from a distant height had been an eye witness<lb/> of what happened&#44; was profoundly affected.  and Instinctively&#44;<lb/> and without being perceived&#44; came he drew nigh to mingle in the combat.<lb/>  He was exposed to imminent danger&#44; for  Javelins whizzed<lb/> on all sides.  The Roman general was exposed to imminent danger.  To screen himself protect his life form the missiles hurled<lb/> by the Galileans&#44; he ordered his few followers to keep<lb/> close to him and with their shields form a screen round<lb/> their heads against the storm of stones and lances.  At length&#44; the<lb/> fury of that storm tempest of darts abated&#44; and the Romans<lb/> retreated.  Terrible was the loss they sustained was terrible&#44; but<lb/> not less terrible was their vengeance.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>For Soon food became very scarce and water failed at Gamala.<lb/>  The feeble and the helpless moaned&#44; and those the men able<lb/> to bear with the sorest privations&#44; prepared to meet death<lb/> and while measuring arms with the heathens rather than<lb/> sink from hunger and thirst.  One morning day towards<lb/> the end of September of the year 67 before the at early dawn&#44; three Roman<lb/> soldiers with levers in hand crept unseen under a tower&#44;<lb/> and while Roman legions diverted the attention of the<lb/> Jews by a pretended feigned attack&#44; those soldiers loosened five struck away five<lb/> huge stones form that tower and fled away quickly fled.  Then the enemy by its<lb/> maneuvers attracted enticed the besieged to the weakened spot.<lb/>  The tower rolled down&#44; with its brave gallant defenders.  Titus<lb/> who gave the assault&#44; opened himself a passage into the city and<lb/> sez siezed a commanding by the aid of his cavalry seized a position which made him master<lb/> of the situation.  Cautioned by a former defeat&#44; he sur&#45;<lb/>&#45;rounded Gamala with consummate prudence.  The<lb/> Galileans rushed to arms.  Many A host of them hastened to take<lb/> refuge in a fortress on a summit of a rock&#44; where<lb/> their wives and children had gathered.  A whirlwind<lb/> blowing in their faces&#44; prevented their javelins from<lb/> being <sic>levelled</sic> at the Romans.  Made frantic by despair<lb/> those unhappy men took laid hold of the creatures they loved most and threw<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>them into the valley ravines below that the foe might not<lb/> add insult to injury.  Resistance became impossible&#44;<lb/> still&#44; struck but so likewise many but so also was submissive.  Many unsheathed their swords to strike down the advancing Romans and then<lb/> cast themselves headlong into precipices.  Many<lb/> sought death into caves&#44; where starvation consumed awaited<lb/> them.  All that could be found alive were massaredcred<lb/> by Titus and his father Vespasian.  They future emperors at the eternal city would<lb/> thus revenge the losses which a small despised city of<lb/> small in size and of few inhabitants had inflicted upon<lb/> the <sic>redoutable</sic> army sent by Rome to conquer unsub&#45; freedom<lb/>&#45;missive loving Judea.  Gamala&#44; like Jotapata&#44; remained<lb/> a monument of Latin vengeance.  But the deserted<lb/> hills which environed it&#44; told of the heroism of the<lb/> five thousands who had mounted their rugged crags<lb/> to hurl back the steel clad veterans of the proud<lb/> empire.  Joseph Salvador whose florid style suports gives<lb/> a high color historical description a high colour&#44;<lb/> thus concludes his narrative of the trials and daring<lb/> of Gamala.  &#34;Woe to nations whose hearts are<lb/> not touched by the resistance and fall of Gamala.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Generous deeds do not belong to the spot alone<lb/> in which they were enacted&#59; ages do not lessen their<lb/> grandeur.  In the memory of posterity&#44; the noble brave noble<lb/> dead resurrect resuscitate.  NOt without cause has glory&#44; gained<lb/> by &#91;&#63;&#93; bravery&#44; been called &#39;immortal&#39;&#34;.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
