<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Ezekiel, Jacob</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx3FF10_16</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Ezekiel, Jacob</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Morais, Sabato</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Cincinnati, OH</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1885-01" source="" attested="yes">24 January 1885</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx3ff10_16_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx3ff10_16_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx3ff10_16_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx3ff10_16_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx3ff10_16_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx3ff10_16_3v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 3 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Ezekiel &#38; Bernheim&#44;<lb/>
                Auctioneers.<lb/>
                Nos 134 Main and 31 Hammond Streets.<lb/></p>
            <p>Cincinnati&#44; Jan. 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 1885.<lb/></p>
                
            <p>My Valued Friend.<lb/></p>
            <p>As the Sabbath has passed and I feel like paying off<lb/> the debts due to my dear friends in the way of corresponden&#45;<lb/>ce&#44; considering you in the category&#44; I do not know what I<lb/> can do better than indite a few lines to you&#44; hoping they<lb/> may come to hand in due time&#44; and meet you our<lb/> dear Nina and every member of your dear family in the<lb/> full enjoyment of health. I peruse the weekly journals<lb/> as they appear&#44; and always find your name conspic<lb/>uous in all that tends to the welfare of our people and<lb/> the advancement of the true principles of our religion.<lb/> your time appears to be pretty much taxed in <del>writ</del> wri&#45;<lb/>ting for the press&#44; as well  attending the various institu&#45;<lb/> tions of learning. I trust the Ministers Meeting passed<lb/> off pleasantly at New York it being the first of the<lb/> series we must hope it will prove the harbinger of<lb/> mutual good&#45;will among our leaders&#44; which will<lb/> again unite us in the effort to make a more com&#45;<lb/>plete Union of American Hebrew Congregations&#44; and<lb/> place our institution of learning on a  firm basis.<lb/> I must at this point say that I was somewhat<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="2"/>
            <p>surprised&#44; and no less chagrined&#44; at your attitude to&#45;<lb/>ward our College&#44; and the idea advanced to form <lb/> a conservative Hebrew College in the East. I really<lb/> thought that past experience of &#34;Maimonides College&#34; and<lb/> <hi rend="underline">its</hi> <hi rend="underline">fate</hi> would have deterred another attempt to renew the<lb/> structure&#44; not but that I sympathised with that praisewor&#45;<lb/>thy institution during its existence. but the <del>the</del> utter im&#45;<lb/>practicability  at this time to renew the effort&#59; our<lb/> College has too strong a hold on the Israelites of this<lb/> country to &#94; be either supplanted or a rival institution in&#45;<lb/>augurated. The fruit which our College has <del>foun&#91;&#63;&#93;</del> ripened I<lb/> know must be admitted to be above all censure&#44;<lb/>well aware I am of the indiscreetness at times of its<lb/> President which we all admit&#44; but as &#94; I have written to<lb/> you on other <sic>occassions</sic>&#44; that Dr Wise will outlive his<lb/> enemies&#44; and the College must outlive him. I do hope<lb/> mean personal enemies&#44; for I know that personally<lb/> no one stands more exalted in the opinion of Dr Wise<lb/> than you do&#44; and I have no reason to suppose that it<lb/> is &#94; not visa versa&#44; indiscreet the Dr is&#44; and we all freely ad&#45;<lb/>mit it&#44; but the managers of our College will always<lb/> <sic>endeavour</sic> to keep it unsullied&#44; that the fruit we<lb/> pluck from it annually will  never cause us to thwart<lb/> nourishing it with all the energy and diligence that has<lb/> hitherto been bestowed upon it&#44; and I must freely say that<lb/> I was really surprised at your remarks concerning our <lb/>College. A &#34;Conservative College&#34; here what can you teach<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="3"/>
            <p>other than what we do. You have been with us and know<lb/> too well that no influence is brought to bear by any of<lb/> professors to divert or bias the minds of the students from the<lb/> teachings of our Sages of blessed memory but they are taught<lb/> from the original sources and their various commenta&#45;<lb/>ries and left to form their own conclusions when drifted<lb/>away from our institution into the world at large&#44; it<lb/> is  among the impracticabilities to undertake to ham&#45;<lb/>per the minds of our students with either reform or<lb/> orthodoxy the spirit of our age does not admit of it.<lb/> I only wish we had a graduate to fill the vacancy in<lb/> the Beth El&#45;Emeth Cong. I am  sure he would fill the posi&#45;<lb/>tion with credit to himself and honor to the Israelites of<lb/> Philadelphia. My dear and valued friend I have known<lb/> you long enough not to impeach your honesty in all you<lb/>write and say. I am truly aware that the rapid en&#45;<lb/>croachment made on your time cherished principles<lb/> of our blessed religion must be galling to you in the ex&#45;<lb/>treme&#44; all we can do is to remain steadfast to what we<lb/> think is correct&#44; and accept the situation we are placed<lb/> in. I am sure we could not have had any one more<lb/> <sic>antagonistical</sic> to our College and its President than<lb/> Dr Fred. De Sola Mendes. Look at his position now&#33; it is the<lb/> only way to get things right&#44; is by holding on&#58; as the late<lb/> governor Wise of Va once said at a convention in the<lb/> Secession times&#44; was &#34;to fight the Union in the Union<lb/> under the Stars and the Stripes&#34; not to <del>seceede</del> secede.<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="4"/>
            <p>therefore instead of encouraging Secession of Congregations<lb/> from our Union&#44; let its friends and enemies encour&#45;<lb/>age and strengthen the Union of American Hebrew<lb/> Congregations&#44; and by that means we can get good<lb/> men in its management&#44; and instead of some of<lb/> our Eastern Rabbis &#40;I will confine the number to a very few&#41;<lb/> <sic>endeavouring</sic> to popularize themselves&#44; let them en&#45;<lb/><sic>deavour</sic> to popularize the Union by adhering to it.<lb/> and influencing others to join it. No my valued friend&#44;<lb/> it is the dollars and cents taken annually from the<lb/> coffers of their Congregations that they wish to retain<lb/> <sic>there</sic> causes the one or two to use some dissatisfaction<lb/> with the College and its President as a pretext for to<lb/> withdraw from the Union. I think that I could name<lb/> a gentleman in New York that does not stand much<lb/> over six feet as one in that category. I know  it<lb/> has been a practice among our people for years&#44; that if<lb/> they are not pleased with the Parnass of their Congrega&#45;<lb/>tion&#44; to remain away from the Synagogue. The re&#45;<lb/>ligious services is but a secondary consideration&#44; and so<lb/> it is with Union and College&#44; as the President of the College is<lb/> <del>distasteful&#91;&#63;&#93;</del> distasteful to some they are down on the Union<lb/> and College as though the Union has no other motive than<lb/> the mere College to foster&#45;&#45; I hope to read your next article<lb/> taking the stand of Fred De Sola Mendes and go with us heart&#45; and hand<lb/> I fear  to have tired you with this long rigmarole of College dic&#45;<lb/>tion&#44; but it is from the impulse of my heart. May God bless you and<lb/> yours with health and life. And with love to all. I am<lb/> as ever. With sentiment &#38; high personal regard and esteem<lb/></p>
            <p>Yours very truly&#45;&#45;<lb/>
                Jacob Ezekiel<lb/></p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
