<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF3_16</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_16_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_16_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_16_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_16_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_16_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_16_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_16_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_16_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_16_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_16_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_16_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_16_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_16_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_16_7v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>A lecture for Sabbath Hachodesh.<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>A certain king had a son who after having been kept<lb/> as prisoner for a number of years among enemies&#44; was at<lb/> length rescued and restored to liberty.  The royal pa&#45;<lb/>&#45;rent overjoyed&#44; ordered that the event&#44; which had ren&#45;<lb/>&#45;dered him most happy&#44; should henceforward form<lb/> an era in his dominions&#44; from which all state docu&#45;<lb/>&#45;ments might be dated.  By this parable&#44; my<lb/> dear hearers&#33;  One of the Sages&#44; wished to explained the<lb/> spirit of the command&#44; which we have read this Sab&#45;<lb/>&#45;bath in the additional portion of the Law.  You may<lb/> have observed that the text twice uses the word<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;unto you&#34;&#44; in connection with the computing of<lb/> time from Nissan.  Moses and Aaron&#44; the former<lb/> destined to represent the governing power of the Hebrew<lb/> commonwealth&#44; and the latter its religious direction&#44;<lb/> received a divine instruction new to the world in<lb/> chronological reckoning.  The month when the<lb/> chosen children of the Lord would become free and<lb/> be invested with the rights of manhood&#44; must constitute<lb/> the main epoch in their annals.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Not to displace Teshri&#44; considered heretofore<lb/> as the season&#44; in which creation issued forth<lb/> from the hand of the Almighty&#44; and which must<lb/> still retain its importance&#44; but to be given precedence<lb/> as the starting point&#44; from which the true existence<lb/> of the Covenant&#45;people began&#44; namely&#44; their deliver&#45;<lb/>&#45;ance from bondage.  So that even Rosh Hashanah<lb/> or the Jewish New Year&#44; shall not be counted the com&#45;<lb/>&#45;mencement of the first month&#44; but of the seventh&#44;<lb/> because the greatest of all historical incidents to Israel<lb/> happened in Nissan.<lb/></p>
            <p>And how was each return of that memorable oc&#45;<lb/>&#45;currence to be celebrated&#63;  By a singular act.<lb/>  By the slaughtering of an animal&#44; roasting it entire&#44;<lb/> and leaving not a particle of it till the morning.<lb/>  A singular act&#44; my Brethren&#44; yet it summed up<lb/> the whole purpose of the Deity in His interposition<lb/> on behalf of the descendents of Abraham.  For&#44;<lb/> with us&#44; freedom is not the mere throwing off of<lb/> a yoke which bends the body&#44; but the rising<lb/> above error&#44; which cramps the soul&#44; the gaining<lb/> of the capacity to walk in the light of progress&#44;<lb/> which is the light of the universal God.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>In ancient Egypt was centered whatever degrades<lb/> humanity.  Egypt&#44; majestic in its exterior&#44; grand<lb/> for its achievements&#44; might nevertheless have been<lb/> fittingly compared to an edifice&#44; inviting to the<lb/> unwary through the superb architecture of its<lb/> porch.  But no sooner is the interior approached&#44;<lb/> then the breath is stifled by the foul air it exhales.<lb/>  The fifty gates leading to impurity&#44;&#45;&#45;to express<lb/> it in the hyperbolical language of some of the<lb/> Rabbis&#45;&#45;&#91;Hebrew&#93; those fifty gates may<lb/> have closed on many among our predecessors.  Hebrew<lb/> men and women&#44; notwithstanding the patriarchal<lb/> traditions&#44; tending to keep them undefiled&#44; may have<lb/> been drawn to the temples of brutalising idolatry&#44; which<lb/> a nation equally famous for the learning of its<lb/> priests&#44; as notorious for its credulity&#44; raised everywhere.<lb/>  Many of our ancestors&#44; may have been enticed into<lb/> those shrines.  The testimony of Ezekiel seems to prove<lb/> that evil surroundings were but too effective.  For&#44;<lb/> he exclaims&#44; in the name of the Lord.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>&#34;I said&#44; that I would pour out my fury upon<lb/> them&#44; to satisfy my anger against them in<lb/> the midst of the land of Egypt.  But I acted for<lb/> the sake of my name&#44; so as not to profane it before<lb/> the eyes of the nations&#44; in the midst of whom they were&#44;&#34;<lb/> and we know how prone was Israel of yore to<lb/> fall back into heathen practices.  But the un&#45;<lb/>&#45;compromising legislator&#44; inspired from above&#44; gave<lb/> a command&#44; which was meant to serve as an<lb/> axe to tear down the altars of falsehood.  The<lb/> lamb to which the Egyptians paid special ador&#45;<lb/>&#45;ation in the month of Nissan&#44; after the spring<lb/> equinox&#44; when the Sun had entered the constellation<lb/> called Aries or &#34;ram&#44;&#34; must be killed the very<lb/> evening preceding the redemption from slavery.<lb/>  Each Hebrew family must bring it to the slaughter&#44;<lb/> each member thereof must partake of its flesh&#44; lea&#45;<lb/>&#45;ving none uneaten&#44; thus to show that an object<lb/> of food cannot possibly be endowed with Divine<lb/> powers.  A streak of blood from that <sic>worshipped</sic><lb/> animal must mark the houses of those who would<lb/> soon go forth to battle against paganism.  And their<lb/> readiness for the holy undertaking&#44; must be signified&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>by the manner in which they ate the sacrifice of<lb/> Passover&#44; with their loins girded&#44; with their shoes<lb/> on their feet and with their staff in their hands&#44;<lb/> awaiting for the call of their leader&#44; giving a signal<lb/> for their onward march.<lb/></p>
            <p>Who could have supposed&#44; my Brethren&#33; that a ceremony<lb/> whose origin must be sought for in the opposition raised<lb/> to Egyptian mythology&#44; and in the mission entrusted<lb/> to the redeemed from bondage&#44; would&#44; twelve or thirteen<lb/> centuries afterwards&#44; be presented to the world&#44; as the<lb/> foreshadowing of a mystical event&#44; said to have then<lb/> been accomplished&#63;  Who could have imagined that an<lb/> observance purely historical&#44; not all at all dogmatical&#44;<lb/> not in the least connected with the theory of atonement<lb/> from for sin&#44; would be chosen as the ch corner stone of a<lb/> new system founded on the necessary death of a being<lb/> whose blood was to wash away transgressions&#63;  And<lb/> yet&#44; that untenable idea has spread far and wide<lb/> and we are stigmatised as a <sic>wilfully</sic> obstinate people&#44;<lb/> because we cannot admit it.  I&#44; however&#44; would<lb/> not have alluded to it this morning&#44; but for the reason<lb/> that&#44; like myself&#44; some among my hearers&#44; may at the<lb/> present season&#44; be the recipients of tracts&#44; aiming<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>to demonstrate that we are altogether lost&#44; because<lb/> we reject the belief in a vicarious sacrifice.<lb/>  It is argued that inasmuch as our dispersion prevents<lb/> the full performance of a part of the Law&#44; deemed<lb/> most essential&#44; we offend the Deity&#44; and forfeit His<lb/> grace&#44; by denying the efficacy of what He has grant&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed as an acceptable substitute&#44; namely&#44; the blood<lb/> of the lamb of <sic>God&#34;</sic>&#44; instead of immolated animals.<lb/>  Let me then tell very distinctly to every Israelite<lb/> who has not made this subject his study&#44; that<lb/> in no part of our Scriptures&#44; we are taught that sal&#45;<lb/>&#45;vation depends on oblations.  Even when the<lb/> sanctuary existed in all its glory&#44; and the ordained<lb/> high&#45;priest with his golden mitre&#44; on which sparkled<lb/> the words &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; stood between the people and<lb/> their Lord&#44; even then the confession which was in&#45;<lb/>&#45; variably to accompany the sin presentation of the offering for a sin unwittingly committed &#91;Hebrew&#93; as repeatedly expressed in the 4th chap of Leviticus and not<lb/> the blood streaming down from the sides of the altar&#44;<lb/> carried away the weight of human misdeeds.<lb/>  So true it is&#44; that when the mere shadow and zone<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>of the reality of the sentiments&#44; which the sacrifi&#45;<lb/>&#45;cial rites were intended to evoke&#44; remained&#44; pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;phets and psalmists&#44; exposed to view the hollowness<lb/> of an institution&#44; which had nothing to uphold it.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> The Rabbis &#91;&#63;&#93; themselves&#44; devoutly looking<lb/> for a restoration of our nationality as on the days that<lb/> the Temple raised its turrets on mount Moriah&#44;<lb/> still say in one of their legends&#44; that when Solomon<lb/> was about to build that structure&#44; God so spoke<lb/> to David &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Thy son intends to build<lb/> me a dwelling place for the presentation of offerings&#44;<lb/> but dearer than all sacrifices are to me the acts<lb/> of justice and charity thou fulfillest.&#34;  No&#58; Judaism<lb/> admits the efficacy of oblations laid on the altar with<lb/> feelings of gratitude for Divine blessings received&#44; but<lb/> it entirely discards the idea that its existence is de&#45;<lb/>&#45;rived from them&#44; or from any symbol assuming<lb/> to represent them.  Not the blood of slaughtered<lb/> sheep and oxen&#59; not the blood of an incarnate demi&#45;<lb/>&#45;god&#44; but our own blood&#44; when it quickens the heart&#44;<lb/> with virtuous emotions is most precious in the<lb/> sight of the Lord&#44; who asked us to love truth and peace.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>At all events&#44; its is very certain that the Passover<lb/> was simply a commemorative and not an expiatory<lb/> sacrifice&#44; hence&#44; the utter inappropriateness of the<lb/> use typically made of it by our gentile neighbors.<lb/>  But though the paschal lamb has ceased to be<lb/> the reminder of the past&#44; because the national<lb/> centre&#44; where it was to be brought and killed&#44; exists<lb/> no longer&#44; the momentous event that gave origin to<lb/> that ancient ceremony&#44; has not ceased from memory.  &#91;inserted above&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#93;<lb/>  For the people yet live&#44; who solemnize the night&#44;<lb/> when Moses gave the signal to march to the con&#45;<lb/>&#45;quest of right.  The unleavened bread&#44; ordered to be<lb/> eaten in all our habitations &#91;inserted above&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#93;&#44; suffices to recall the<lb/> mission undertaken&#44; to illuminate the pages of our<lb/> history&#44; that the remotest posterity may read and<lb/> plainly learn their duty.  Let us then&#44; my Brethren&#33;<lb/> sanctify the month of Nissan&#44; the first in order and<lb/> in rank.  And when the fifteenth day thereof arrives&#44;<lb/> the Matzah shall show us the arm of our Omni&#45;<lb/>potent King stretched forth to rescue us from a<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>bodily and spiritual imprisonment&#59; to uplift<lb/> us our lives above the pit of destruction&#44; many<lb/> a time dug out to bury us deep in.  Oh may<lb/> &#34;the feast of unleavened bread&#44;&#34; exercise over more<lb/> its weighty influence as of yore&#44; when its ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;proach was hailed with national delight.  May<lb/> it strengthen the bond of brotherly union&#44; may it<lb/> draw the hears to fathers closer to those of their<lb/> children&#44; and the hearts of children to those of their<lb/> fathers&#44; rendering Jewish homes&#44; holy houses&#44; and<lb/> even the tables on which the daily food is spread&#44;<lb/> an altar sacred to the Lord&#44; as the sanctuary of Moses<lb/> and of Solomon.  So may it be.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>A King had a son&#44; who&#44; having been kept long a prisoner among enemies&#44; was at<lb/> length set at liberty.  The overjoyed father ordered that the happy event&#44; be signalized<lb/> as an era in the history of his dominion.  In this manner have some of the<lb/> Hebrew Sages explained the preeminence accorded to the national festival the eve<lb/> of which we have just reached.  For&#44; in all reality&#44; it is an imperishable memento of the redemption of God&#39;s elect<lb/> from a soul crushing slavery.  Ancient Egypt had gained an attitude then unsurpassed yet in<lb/> it was centred whatever degrades humanity.  Egypt majestic in its exterior&#44; superbly great<lb/> in its material environments&#44; in its obelisks&#44; its pyramids&#44; its mausoleums which<lb/> have defied the rays of time&#44; might nevertheless be fittingly compared to stately edifice inviting in the<lb/> unwary&#44; but no sooner has the <sic>intterior</sic> been &#91;&#63;&#93; reached than the breath is stifled by the foul<lb/> air it exhales.  The fifty gates leading opening to the domain of impurity&#45;&#45;to express it in the hyperbolical<lb/> language of the Rabbis &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; those fifty gates may have closed in some<lb/> among our ancestors.  Hebrew men and women&#44; notwithstanding patriarchal traditions&#44; tend&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing to guard them against a defiling worship&#44; may have been drawn to the temples<lb/> of brutalizing idolatry&#44; which a people famous alike for the learning of its<lb/> priests and for scientific attainments still built up high.  The testimony circumstance of the woman Israelitish<lb/> mother married to an Egyptian&#44; whose son blasphemed and cursed God &#38; the testimony of Ezekiel go far<lb/> to prove that pollution had entered also the habitations of Goshen.  For&#44; the prophet<lb/> on the river Chebar so spoke in the name of his heavenly Master.  &#34;I<lb/> would have poured out my wrath on them in the midst of the &#91;&#63;&#93; of<lb/> Egypt.  But I acted for the sake of My name&#44; so as not to profane it<lb/> before the eyes of the nations&#44; in whose midst they were&#34; and history our own unbiased annals shows<lb/> how prone were the descendants of Abraham&#44; the friend of the One God&#44; whom he<lb/> proclaimed &#91;Hebrew&#93; the God of the heavens and the God of the earth&#44;<lb/> how apt they were&#44; I say&#44; to be lured away from the ancestral path.  Yet&#44; while<lb/> I do not hold up our forefathers in the aggregate as models of virtue&#44; as paragons of good&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness&#44; I neither picture them in the repulsive colors which some of the moderns<lb/> seem to take pleasure in portraying them.  The Divine selection for the<lb/> highest purpose&#44; proves that the pictures is very ill drawn.  Judah Hallevi&#44; a poet<lb/> by the grace of God&#44; may have allowed his genius too broad wide a scope when describing<lb/> the people chosen by the Creator as His herald of His unerring truths capable of<lb/> rising aloft in equal to the conception of lofty ideas&#44; but of that be an exaggeration it is false that they the redeemed of Egypt were a sink of vice&#44;<lb/> of ignorance and incredulity.  In a recent lecture I tried to show the contrary by evidences<lb/> which I consider irrefutable.  But I am asked&#44; if the redeemed of Egypt our progenitors were<lb/> capable of grasping to grasp &#38; propagate soul regimenting ideals&#44; why was the first command &#91;&#63;&#93;&#44; which<lb/> marked out their freedom&#44; one that to us must appears puerile.  And I unhesitatingly<lb/> answer the querist that singular ordinance which you set at naught&#44; summed up the purpose &#91;&#63;&#93; intention of<lb/> the Deity God in His &#91;&#63;&#93; interposition on behalf of our predecessors.  For&#44; with us liberty is not<lb/> the mere casting off of a yoke which bends down the body&#44; but the uprising of the mind&#44;<lb/> the to gaining the ability to walk of basking in the sun light of truth&#44; which is of our the right of God.  Our legislator<lb/> gave forth a statute&#44; meant as an axe to tear break down the altars of falsehood.  The<lb/> lamb to which the Egyptians paid special homage in the month of Nisan&#44; after the<lb/> spring equinox&#44; when the sun has entered the constellation called Aries&#44; or<lb/> &#34;ram sheep&#34;&#44; must be killed the n very evening preceding the deliverance from bondage.  Each<lb/> Hebrew family must bring it to the slaughter&#58; each member thereof must par&#45;<lb/>&#45;take of its flesh&#44; leaving none uneaten&#44; thus to show demonstrate that an object of food cannot<lb/> be possibly endowed with Divine powers.  But who could have supposed that a<lb/> ceremony whose origin must be sought for in the opposition raised to desire to expose the folly of<lb/> Egyptian mythology&#44; would&#44; twelve or thirteen centuries later&#44; be presented<lb/> to the world&#44; as the foreshadowing of a mystical event&#44; said to have then<lb/> been accomplished&#63;  who could have imagined that an observance purely<lb/> historical&#45;&#45;not in the least dogmatical&#44; not at all connected with the theory<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>of atonement from sin&#44; would be chosen as the cornerstone of a new system<lb/> founded on the necessary death of a an inexplicable being whose blood was to wash away<lb/> transgressions&#63;  And yet that untenable most absurd idea has spread far and wide&#44;<lb/> and &#91;&#63;&#93; men and fanaticism dared even to try and to engraft it on the Magna Charter of American rights&#44; and<lb/> we Jews are <sic>stigmatised</sic>&#44; as a <sic>wilfully</sic> obstinate people because we our reason will not<lb/> admit it.  I would not have alluded to this&#44; were it not that at the present season<lb/> churches resound with invectives because we reject the belief in a vicarious sacrifice.<lb/>  We are declared unpardonable offenders for denying what is said to have been supernaturally granted as an acceptable sub&#45;<lb/>&#45;stitute for sacrificial rites&#44; namely&#44; the blood of &#34;the lamb of God.&#34;  Let me tell with<lb/> all emphasis&#44; that in no part of our scriptures&#44; are we taught that salvation depends<lb/> on oblations.  Even when the Temple existed in all its glory raised its golden spires on Zions hills and the ordained high priest<lb/> with his golden adoring mitre&#44; on which sparkled the Heb words &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; stood between<lb/> the people and the adorable Lord&#44; even then the confession which was invariably to ac&#45;<lb/>company the presentation of the offering for a sin unwittingly committed &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> as repeatedly expressed in the 4th chapter of Leviticus the &#91;&#63;&#93; confession earned removed &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> the stains of &#91;&#63;&#93;.  Papal indulgence and absolutions never shamed disparaged disgraced Judaism.  So ture it is that<lb/> when that mere shadows and none of the reality sentiments&#44; which sacrificial rites were<lb/> meant to evoke&#44; remained&#44; prophets and psalmists exposed to view the hollow&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness of the institution.  In the Haftorah&#44; which would have been read this morning&#44; had<lb/> it not been the Sabbath preceding Passover&#44; Jeremiah explains&#58; &#34;Thus saith the Lord of<lb/> hosts&#44; add your burnt offerings to your sacrifices and eat the flesh thereof&#44; for I did not speak<lb/> to your fathers&#44; nor did I command them on the day which I brought them out of Egypt about burnt<lb/> offerings and sacrifices&#44; but only this I commanded them&#44; hearken to my &#91;&#63;&#93;<lb/> I shall will be your God&#44; and you shall be my people&#34;.  And who more pronounced than the<lb/> deep thinking Asaph&#63;  Let me quote him&#58; Gather together unto me my saints&#44; who make<lb/> a covenant with me by sacrifice....If I were hungry&#44; I would not tell thee&#44; for the<lb/> world is mine and the fulness thereof is mine.  Will I eat the flesh of bulls&#44; or drink<lb/> the blood of goats&#63;  Offer unto God the sacrifice of thanksgiving and pay the vows to the<lb/> Most High&#45;&#45;and call upon me in the day of trouble&#44; I will deliver thee and thou<lb/> shalt glorify me.  &#40;But to the wicked God saith....Thou givest thy mouth to evil&#44; and thy<lb/> tongue formeth deceit.  Thou sittest and speakest against thy brother&#44; thou slanderest thy<lb/> mother&#39;s son&#41;  Not the blood of slaughtered sheep and &#91;&#63;&#93;&#44; not the blood of an incarnate<lb/> demigod&#44; but our own blood&#44; when it quickens the heart&#44; with virtuous emotions<lb/> is most precious in the sight of the Lord&#44; who asked us to love truth and peace righteousness &#38; hate iniquity.<lb/>  At all events&#44; it is beyond a shadow of doubt that the Passover was only a com&#45;<lb/>&#45;memorative and not an expiratory sacrifice.  How very inappropriate then the<lb/> use typically made of it by our gentile neighbors&#33;  But through The Pas&#45;<lb/>&#45;chal lamb has ceased to be a reminder of the past&#44; yet the momentous event that<lb/> gave it origin&#44; has not been erased from memory.  For&#44; wonder of wonders&#44; the people&#44;<lb/> to whom Moses gave the signal to march to the conquest of right lives yet&#44; and it will<lb/> live to the end of until time be no more.  The unleavened bread&#44; suffices to recall the mission&#59; to il&#45;<lb/>&#45;lumine the pages of our eventful history &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Let us then<lb/> raise high the trophy of our heroism in facing all battles from heathen&#44; Christian and Moham<lb/>&#45;medan camps&#44; never flinching in our devotion to the Liberator of Israel.  Oh&#33; may<lb/> the feast of unleavened bread&#44; exercise once more again its weighty influence as of old&#44;<lb/> when its approach was hailed with delight.  May it strengthen the bond of our<lb/> brotherly union among dispersed Israel and render Jewish homes&#44; holy&#44; even the tables on which our food is<lb/> spread&#44; in as altars sacred to the Lord&#44; like in the sanctuary of Moses&#44; and the Temple of<lb/> Solomon.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
