<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF10_8</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1894-01" source="" attested="yes">1894</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_8_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_8_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_8_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_8_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_8_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_8_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_8_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_8_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_8_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_8_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_8_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_8_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>36<lb/></p>
            <p>94<lb/></p>
            <p>On Behar Sinai<lb/>
                About brotherly mercy<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>No doubt&#44; if American Jews were asked to<lb/> choose a sentence&#44; which pleases them best&#44;<lb/> in the portion of the Torah read this morning&#44;<lb/> they would agree upon that engraven molten on the<lb/> dear precious bell which from the Philadelphia state<lb/> House rung out in the sweetest tones a declara&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion of human rights &#91;Hebrew&#93;  &#34;Proclaim liberty<lb/> throughout the land unto all the inhabitants<lb/> thereof&#34;.  Nor would I consider the selection<lb/> inappropriate&#44; for&#44; urged by that motto&#44; pa&#45;<lb/>&#45;triots conquered peace with honor&#44; united discordant<lb/> elements into a powerful nationality and gave<lb/> the strictest strongest impulse to a progress<lb/> premotive of human comfort in and out of doors.<lb/>  A happy thought was that which suggested<lb/> so significant a passage from the Hebrew<lb/> Scriptures&#44; I prefer it decidedly to what Oliver<lb/> Cromwell is reported to have borrowed from an out&#45;<lb/>&#45;burst of anger hurled at his enemies by the ancient psalmist.<lb/>  For it is said that the Conqueror fiery lord protector thus incited his<lb/> followers to battle &#34;Lord &#34;Strive Thou O Lord against those that strive against me.  Fight Thou&#44; them that fight<lb/> me&#44; lay hold of shield and buckler and stand up to my defence.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>But neither of wars nor of victories&#44; am I now<lb/> moved impelled to speak.  Our section of Leviticus teems with<lb/> lessons of loving goodness not of bloodshed even in self defence for independence sake.  Those lessons They have arrested the atten&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion of political economists deep thinkers&#44; who wish the welfare<lb/> of communities&#44; and forced out the an acknowledgment<lb/> of the superiority of the Mosaic code not merely<lb/> above over that of Lycurgus of Sparta&#44; of Solen the Athenean&#44; of Theodosius<lb/> a Justinian&#44; but above over that of modern legis&#45;<lb/>&#45;lators.  In my mind three Hebrew words<lb/> in our Parasha are the summary of the Mosaic Divinely<lb/> sublime teachings &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; which words&#44;<lb/> interpreted in the vernacular&#44; read so&#58; &#34;Let thy<lb/> brother live with thee&#34;.  To act up to that<lb/> precept is to be an Israelite indeed.  The<lb/> common adage &#34;live and let live&#44;&#34; meaning&#59; &#34;don&#39;t<lb/> be of a grasping disposition&#59; don&#39;t try to become<lb/> such by injuring your neighbor&#39;s calling or<lb/> character&#44;&#34; is a maxim too narrow in its ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;plication to be set on a level par with the Biblical<lb/> doctrine&#44; that I have just quoted.  It may seem<lb/> liberal enough to some&#59; perhaps too liberal in<lb/> this age of unscrupulous competition&#44; but it falls<lb/> far below the mark&#44; when measured by a<lb/> Jewish standard as in the &#91;&#63;&#93; and oral Law&#44; of righteousness.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Our religion refuses to admit that adage as a<lb/> sound principle&#44; because it inculcates only a<lb/> negative goodness virtue according to it&#44; we should guard against<lb/> doing our fellow mortals harm&#44; it says&#44; whereas<lb/> Judaism demands of its adherents positive right&#45; beneficence.<lb/> &#45;teousness  We should strive to benefit help our fel&#45;<lb/>&#45;low creatures.  To abstain from lowering debasing our nature<lb/> as we would surely lower it&#44; by bringing ruin or shame on a brother&#44; is not<lb/> to be entitled to the name of virtuous.  To elevate upraise<lb/> our nature&#44; by furthering his our brother&#39;s welfare&#44; is to possess<lb/> a claim to a post of honor among the chosen<lb/> of God.  When I am told asked to let my<lb/> brother live with me &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; I understand<lb/> that I must not push him aside&#44; so that I<lb/> may walk more at large&#44; but that I must<lb/> make room for him&#59; that I must clear the<lb/> way of stumbling blocks which me prevent his<lb/> holding the station occupied &#91;Hebrew&#93; say<lb/> the Talmudists &#34;try to let him stay close to by thee&#34;.  And<lb/> when the prophet adds to that precept&#44; the words<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Thou shalt fear thy God&#44;&#34; I<lb/> realize this soul ennobling truth verity&#44; viz&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>I cannot consider that my life is acceptable<lb/> in the sight of the Universal Maker who gave<lb/> it&#44; simply because I do not covertly or by misuse it by<lb/> subtle cunning&#44; thrusting one of His God&#39;s creatures into<lb/> the back ground and taking up his place.  No&#44;<lb/> I learn that I can win the favor of my Lord and<lb/> Creator&#44; if I have endeavoured to keep my neigh&#45;<lb/>&#45;bor in&#44; when about to be cast out.  For&#44; I have<lb/> received a positive command to lay stronghold<lb/> of him that is falling into decay &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> so that we he may not sink under the weight<lb/> of his misfortune&#59; never waiting to inquire whe&#45;<lb/>&#45;ther the person who needs leaning on my arm for<lb/> support is a native of my city&#44; or whether he<lb/> hails from a foreign land &#91;Hebrew&#93;.<lb/>  Now I feel certain that every Jew will in theory<lb/> recognize&#44; as I do&#44; the sublimity of this doctrine of<lb/> our faith.  All with glory in knowing that Judaism<lb/> is the essence of humanity&#44; of equality and fra&#45;<lb/>&#45;ternity.  Philo Judeaus&#44; the world famous phi&#45;<lb/>&#45;losopher who lived at the beginning of flourished before the Christian<lb/> ear&#44; enamored with such a code of laws exclaimed&#58;<lb/> &#34;Are not those rules deserving of universal<lb/> reverence&#63;&#34;  And so we all admit them to be in the abstract.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>But how is it in practice&#63;  Do we carry out that<lb/> principle of our creed to the letter&#63;  If we do&#44; why then the<lb/> cry of anguish here&#44; and the din noise of revelry there&#63;  Why<lb/> the haggard looks of want in one place&#44; extravagance<lb/> and waste in another&#63;  If we did exemplify<lb/> the teachings of the inspired Moses in our daily walks&#44;<lb/> we would not alone light up the countenance which<lb/> troubles have darkened&#44; but we would also prove false<lb/> beyond peradventure&#44; as it is absolutely unjust&#44; the<lb/> charge brought against our people at large&#44; that<lb/> greed is the Jewish characteristic.   But<lb/> referring specially to a certain rule laid down in our<lb/> Parasha&#44; I wish to remark&#44; that if we were im&#45;<lb/>&#45;bued with the truth of the doctrine which I have<lb/> cited&#44; we would bridle the a passion for to growing rich<lb/> in haste by extortion.  Conceding&#44; for instance by way of illustration&#44; as we must now agree&#44;<lb/> that since money has become a staple of com&#45;<lb/>&#45;merce&#44; we may deal in it money&#44; as well as in any<lb/> other commodity&#44; we would nevertheless be chary<lb/> not to infringe upon the spirit of the law&#44; so forcibly<lb/> set forth in the lesson of this Sabbath &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; viz namely&#44; we would dread to demand of<lb/> our brother&#44; who has sank into a state of destitu&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion&#44; insurious interest for his loan.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Admitting that even what money lending&#45;&#45;a vocation which circumstances have brought<lb/> into disrepute&#45;&#45;may be carried out on with sentiments<lb/> of justice&#44; and with equity and deep consideration&#45;&#45;and<lb/> doubtless it is so performed abroad&#44; and here too in America too by some who are alive<lb/> to the dictates of the merciful law of Israel&#39;s God&#45;&#45;<lb/> still to them temptations a Jew ought always to a yielding to which disgraces our name and religion&#44; it were well that a Jew would set before his<lb/> let f before his mind mind in conjunction with what we have read&#44; also the 18th chapter of Ezekiel&#44;<lb/> in which the Seer on Chebar contrasts a life of right&#45;<lb/>&#45;eousness with that of unrighteousness its opposite.  According<lb/> to the prophetic description&#44; he alone shall live before the<lb/> Lord&#44; who has not wronged any&#44; has not held back<lb/> a pledge&#44; has never been guilty of cheating&#44; who has<lb/> given of his bread to the hungry and covered the<lb/> naked with a garment&#44; who has withdrawn his<lb/> hand not to hurt the poor by means of usury and<lb/> extortion.  Such one is &#91;Hebrew&#93; a just man&#44;<lb/> he shall live.  Better yet&#44; a Jew should inscribe on<lb/> the tablet of his heart that most sublime writing<lb/> left us in the 15th psalm of David.  There will a<lb/> Jew see portrayed the a soul wafted to the sacred<lb/> hill&#44; where the glory of God abides.  It is the soul of<lb/> a being who has acted with the strictest integrity&#44; ha&#45;<lb/>&#45;ving never soiled his hands with usurious money and corrupting<lb/> bribe &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Acting upon such the Mosaic Jewish principles&#44; we would not permit in&#45;<lb/> &#45;digence to become the lot of the worthy&#44; while the undeser&#45;<lb/> &#45;ving inherit affluence.  The knotty question&#44; the which<lb/> hard solution of which may one day overthrow society creates everywhere a restle restlessness threatening the<lb/> to its very foundations&#44; the question permanence of society&#44; the hard question which forces<lb/> communities upon the mouth of a volcano&#44; was square&#45;<lb/>ly met by the son of Amram&#44; and disposed of equi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tably&#44; when he wrote &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Let thy brother<lb/> live with thee.&#34;  There could not exist&#44; like at present&#44;<lb/> a shocking disparity between the idlers&#44; who roll<lb/> in wealth&#44; and the industrious who lack the comforts<lb/> of life&#44; if we rigidly adhered to the injunction of the<lb/> archprophet.  Capital and labor would cease to be<lb/> in open antagonism&#44; if the nerves and sinews of society<lb/> handicraft&#45;&#45;commanded the highest compensation remuneration<lb/> and were secured against casualties and the drainage<lb/> of one&#39;s resources consequent upon ill the ills that all<lb/> flesh is heir to.  The power that riches give&#44; would not<lb/> be centralized but diffused to the promotion of human<lb/> happiness and the avoidance of disturbing causes by<lb/> which republics and monarchies have been often con&#45;<lb/>&#45;vulsed.  But I do not intend inditing an essay on<lb/> political economy&#44;  which is out of my line and beyond my capacity.  A passage<lb/> in our Parasha elicited my few desultory remarks.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>According to that passage&#44; none who was an Israelite&#44;<lb/> could entail poverty on his household.  Why&#63; because<lb/> the soil was inalienable.  Let those listen to it the word&#45;<lb/>ing of that precept&#44; who are deaf to the sound of<lb/> their brothers&#39; woes&#59; let them listen to it whose only<lb/> aspiration is&#44; as Isaiah reproachfully tells them &#91;Hebrew&#93; to<lb/> join house to house&#44; field to field&#44; that no vacant spaces<lb/> be found &#44;and they shall remain sole masters of the land.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>  &#34;The land shall not be sold for ever&#44; for the land is mine&#44;<lb/> for ye are strangers and sojourners with me.  That is the all&#45;humanizing lesson of this morning&#39;s Parasha.  Aye&#58; to God<lb/> belongs the earth.  He is the supreme and everlasting owner&#44;<lb/> for His hands have made it.  We hold it at His divine<lb/> pleasure a limited time.  Such is the Mosaic doctrine.<lb/>  It condemns covetousness&#44; it denounces the insatiable&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness of our ambition to gain more and always more&#44; tho&#39;<lb/> we may by it drive a fellow mortal to the wall.  We are<lb/> all strangers&#44; wending our steps to a lasting existence&#44;<lb/> let us make our <sic>travelling</sic> companions live with us&#44; while<lb/> on the way.  We are sojourners bound to return to our<lb/> Father&#39;s house.  Let us pa make the passage easy<lb/> to others as well as to ourselves.  Even as I speak&#44;<lb/> a voice of lament reaches our ears from creatures under a flood<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>of affliction.  Let us dry with the worth warmth of brotherly<lb/> affection the streams of sorrow by which many who dwell<lb/> in our state have very nigh been whelmed.  Needless it is<lb/> to point out the awful trials which this week has brought<lb/> upon Pennsylvania.  May they have ceased and security be<lb/> restored.  But when humanity pleads for the suf&#45;<lb/>&#45;ferers&#44; let the adherents of the most human the religion<lb/> that lay deeply the foundation of humanity&#44; shall remember<lb/> &#38; act up to the commandment &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Let thy brother<lb/> live with thee.&#34;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
