<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF4_4</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_4_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_4_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_4_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_4_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_4_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_4_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_4_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_4_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_4_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_4_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_4_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_4_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_4_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_4_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_4_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_4_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Shabbat Ha&#45;Gadol<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;I the Lord change not&#44; therefore ye child&#45;<lb/>&#45;ren of Jacob are not consumed.&#34;  Is this<lb/> not&#44; my brethren&#44; a high privilege which we<lb/> enjoy my brethren&#45;&#45;we the indestructible witnesses of God&#39;s word&#45;&#45;<lb/> yearly to hail the season&#44; which verifies beyond<lb/> denial contradiction&#44; the unalterable promise of the Eternal&#63;<lb/>  Each time that it draws near&#44; we may well pon&#45;<lb/>&#45;flect der on the jubilant utterances of the arch&#45;prophet&#44;<lb/> who foresaw our destiny.  There never was a people<lb/> of antiquity so portentously drawn out of a grind&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing tyranny like so prodigiously&#44; as the descendants of Israel.  Never<lb/> was there a nation whom a heavenly light illumined<lb/> so inextinguishably&#44; that it did not become lost<lb/> in the labyrinths of dark ages of summer ignorance and brutality.<lb/>  The history of mankind fails to present a parallel<lb/> to that which strikingly illustrates the ceaseless<lb/> watching of the celestial Eye that neither slumbers nor<lb/> sleeps.  And the reason is obvious&#44; for as the<lb/> tribe of Levy was charged with the guardianship<lb/> of the outward symbols of outward religion&#45;&#45;the ark and the<lb/> altar&#45;&#45;Israel at large was set apart as custodians<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>of the inner spirit of religion&#45;&#45;the existence<lb/> and Oneness of God.  Hence the declaration of<lb/> which we are reminded in the Haftorah of this<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; great Sabbath.  &#34;I the Lord change<lb/> not&#44; therefore ye children of Jacob are not<lb/> consumed.&#34;  Still&#44; a perplexing<lb/> question often startles the thinker in when consider&#45;<lb/>ing the preference of Divinity given to Israel.<lb/>  Why did the Universal Creator single out a<lb/> few liberated slaves&#45;&#45;so to say&#45;&#45;as the depository<lb/> of civilizing ideas&#63;  Was not the whole hu&#45;<lb/>&#45;man race entitled to share with Israel the<lb/> advantages of being receiving at once a supernaturally enlightenment&#63;<lb/>  The solution of that query&#44; demand that we necessitates our<lb/> reflecting on man&#39;s nature.  None can deny<lb/> that parental propensities&#44; whether good or<lb/> evil&#44; will&#44; in all probability&#44; be reproduced<lb/> in their offspring.  That education&#44; early asso&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciations and surroundings&#44; may&#44; to a very great<lb/> extent&#44; encourage or check inborn inclinations&#44;<lb/> all will unhesitatingly admit.  But that those<lb/> inherited tendencies&#44; will in some measure at least&#44; reveal their<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>their existence&#44; daily experience demonstrates.<lb/>  Let us then cast a retrospective glance on the<lb/> moral condition of man in the early stages of<lb/> history.  It has been claimed by some Hebrew<lb/> authors&#44; that prophecy afflatus&#44; or a spiritual communion intercourse<lb/> with the Deity&#44; was originally intended by the<lb/> heavenly Maker&#44; as the prerogative of his the intellect&#45;<lb/>&#45;ual creatures He placed upon earth.  But man&#44; carried away by the<lb/> impulse of lower passions&#44; fell from the lofty<lb/> station&#44; he was designed to occupy.  A Single<lb/> individuals might rise superiorly&#44; and by a<lb/> life of unswerving righteousness reach up to<lb/> the understanding of the Almighty and draw<lb/> inspiration&#44; but that the bulk of mankind&#44; ha&#45;<lb/>&#45;ving inherited acquired a predisposition to worldliness&#44; should<lb/> stand in close connection communion with the all&#45;perfect<lb/> Lord&#44; was not possible.  It might be<lb/> argued&#44; that as every human being is a free<lb/> agent&#44; he possesses the ability of perfecting<lb/> his soul&#44; and befitting it for Divine communi&#45;<lb/>nion &#45;cation.  But though God has granted man liberty<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>of action&#45;&#45;and this is a leading principle in<lb/> Judaism&#45;&#45;He has not vouchsafed to endowed every reasoning<lb/> creature with the same powers&#44; hence we per&#45;<lb/>&#45;ceive that what one can accomplish easily&#44; another<lb/> finds very difficult.  A just God will surely recom&#45;<lb/>&#45;pense all according to their striving after right&#45;<lb/>&#45;eousness&#44; but rare are they whose spirituality<lb/> towers heavenward.  Now&#44; taking<lb/> Holy Writ as our guide&#44; we will discover that<lb/> the animal passions which the provoked the all sweeping flood&#44; had swept subdued<lb/> away&#44; were again engendered in subsequent ages&#44;<lb/> and they grew fast and ran riot.  Says<lb/> a tradition&#58; in the days of Nimrod&#45;&#45;the mighty hunter&#45;&#45;soul&#45;debasing<lb/> idolatry was enthroned&#44; and the pervading spirit<lb/> of the Universe went unrecognized &#91;Hebrew&#93; Amid it<lb/> the prevailing seething corruption&#44; one man succeeded<lb/> to remain <sic>incorrupt</sic>.  Not alone did he avoid<lb/> a morally infectious atmosphere&#44; but he lifted<lb/> himself far above it&#59; created around him<lb/> a region of healthful influences&#44; and by a<lb/> saintly example&#44; lessened the effects of a de&#45;<lb/>&#45;bauching grading polytheism.  Early training&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>which in others general acts powerfully&#44; left no visible trace<lb/> upon his searching mind.  He was reared where<lb/> paganism heathenism and its vices held sway&#44; but by an<lb/> extraordinary effort of the intellect&#44; he forced<lb/> truth out of error to appear before his vision&#44; and&#44; all aglow with his<lb/> grand discovery&#44; set up the banner of his a recovered belief&#44;<lb/> loftily.  Not inappropriately has<lb/> Abraham been called &#34;the father of the faithful.&#34;<lb/>  Better still is the title by which Isaiah designated<lb/> the son of Terah &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;the friend of God&#44;&#34;<lb/> for he laid out for posterity the course of actions in which<lb/> the Almighty delights.  The Rabbinical<lb/> aphorism that at three years of age&#44; the found&#45;<lb/>&#45;er of our people knew his Creator&#44; must be one<lb/> of those allegories in which the Talmudists in&#45;<lb/>&#45;dulge.  They may have wished to convey<lb/> the beautiful idea that Abraham&#39;s trust in<lb/> God was child&#45;like&#44; or that the infolding<lb/> of his extraordinary potent mind began at a very<lb/> early period of life.  Be that as it may&#44;<lb/> surely&#44; it was by a series of noble deeds<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>that our venerated patriarch forged the silvery<lb/> links of the spiritual silvery chain that bound his<lb/> soul to its heavenly author.  But to<lb/> make it man universally manifest that the<lb/> missionary of a world&#45;redeeming verity was<lb/> deserving of the selection&#44; Providence subjected<lb/> Abraham to crucial trial &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  When his<lb/> conduct demonstrably proved that he had served<lb/> his Maker with unselfish love&#44; and his fellow<lb/> mortals with disinterested kindness&#44; he heard the<lb/> same in speaking voice&#44; which had often com&#45;<lb/>&#45;forted his heart&#44; promise that from him a race <lb/>would spring up in whom all humanity would<lb/> eventually be blessed.  An ever living protest<lb/> it should be&#44; as it were&#44; against all manner<lb/> of falsehood&#59; the silent noiseless but effectual propagator<lb/> of civilizing truths.  Mankind could not<lb/> be reclaimed in a moment.  Not by a single<lb/> leap with the ladder of progress be mounted up.<lb/>  Ages must can alone work out a regeneration.  Phenomena<lb/> and wonders may perplex and terrify&#44; but they<lb/> cannot eradicate deep&#45;rooted errors.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>A heated imagination misguided fancy had peopled heaven and<lb/> earth with imaginary gods.  Only the example of a race<lb/> who&#44; amidst all changes&#44; cling unflinchingly to<lb/> one leading principle&#44; could carry force with it.<lb/>  Such was the designed mission of Abraham&#39;s<lb/> descendants.  Religiously set apart from<lb/> the rest of mankind&#44; they could treasure up the<lb/> knowledge&#44; which the righteous patriarch had<lb/> attained.  That knowledge&#44; handed down from<lb/> father to son&#44; prepared Israel for the heavenly<lb/> trust committed to their safe&#45;keeping at Sinai.<lb/>  Even amidst an abject bondage&#44; the conscious&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness of being the objects of God&#39;s care to a<lb/> high final purpose&#44; must have proved to the enslaved enthralled<lb/> a source of inextinguishable hope.  It is<lb/> recorded that when Moses first addressed the<lb/> fettered people enslaved in fetters they believed&#44; and understood that<lb/> the Lord had remembered them&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            <p>We may then exclaim with the Scriptures &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Far be iniquity from God&#44; and injustice from<lb/> the Almighty.&#34;  He did not exalt Israel<lb/> to rule.  The preference shown to the first&#45;born<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>was not to the detriment of the rest of God&#39;s<lb/> children&#44; but to the advantage of the latter.<lb/>  Because He loved His creatures&#44; He would<lb/> instruct them by means of such whose inherited<lb/> aptness fitted the mind for the sublime vocation.<lb/>  The wonderful redemption from Egypt&#44;<lb/> whose memorial anniversary we are about to celebrate&#44;<lb/> concerns therefore the whole human family.<lb/>  Let the enemies of positive religion scoff<lb/> and deny&#59; real civilization lies at the basis<lb/> of that code of laws&#44; which the enfranchised<lb/> bondmen of Mizraim received in the desert of<lb/> Arabia&#44; thirty five centuries ago.  And<lb/> here let me remark&#44; in passing&#44; that those<lb/> who&#44; disputing the authenticity of such a<lb/> revelation&#44; point to lives purely moral among<lb/> their own ranks&#44; are like persons who would<lb/> give the four&#45;wheeled carriage credit for having<lb/> conveyed them to their destination&#44; forgetting<lb/> the men who prepared the way and made<lb/> the journey possible.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Without the standard of morality unfolded raised as a beacon<lb/> on the summit of Horeb&#44; the path of social<lb/> rectitude would remain yet untrodden.  A<lb/> flood of light from above irradiated it for<lb/> ever&#44; and ours is the glory of having prevented<lb/> its extinguishment.  I emphasize this<lb/> sentiment&#59; it is our glory&#44; for we braved<lb/> contempt and did not surrender our charge.<lb/>  We girded our loins with faith&#44; and in the<lb/> face of engines of torture did not waver.  The<lb/> promise of God infused into us superhuman<lb/> vigor &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;I&#44; the Lord change not&#44; there&#45;<lb/>fore ye children of Jacob are not consumed&#34;<lb/>  The enemies of the truths which we have carried far<lb/> and wide at such a cost a terrible <sic>hazard</sic>&#44; might combine their<lb/> forces to annihilate us&#44; but the assurance of<lb/> our eternity and of a final acknowledgment<lb/> of the principles we disseminated steeled our<lb/> hearts and made of us <sic>heros</sic>.  Yes&#58; the Lord<lb/> will fling aside the covering cast over peoples&#44;<lb/> writes Isaiah and the veil spread over all nations writes Isaiah&#44; then<lb/> the tears shall be wiped from our eyes&#44; and<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>the rebuke of Jacob His people shall be taken away from<lb/> the whole earth.  When and how God&#39;s will<lb/> shall be thoroughly consummated&#44; we do not presume to<lb/> answer.  What mortal can be so arrogant as<lb/> to think that he can enter penetrate the secret counsel<lb/> of the Almighty&#44; and compel a revelation of<lb/> the means  by which the future shall crown<lb/> the past.  &#34;My thoughts are not like your<lb/> thoughts&#44; nor my ways like your ways&#58; Behold&#44;<lb/> as the rain cometh down and the snow from<lb/> heaven&#44; and returneth not thither&#44; but watereth<lb/> the earth&#44; and maketh it bring forth and bud&#44;<lb/> that it may give seed to the sower&#44; and bread<lb/> to the eater&#44; so shall be my word that goeth forth<lb/> out of my mouth&#44; saith the Lord&#44; it shall not<lb/> return unto me void&#44; but it shall accomplish<lb/> that which I please&#44; and prosper him whom<lb/> I have sent.&#34;  The declarations of the Most<lb/> High&#44; should sustain our hopes&#44; and the remem&#45;<lb/>&#45;brance of our mission should urge us on<lb/> ever to act conformably with the revealed Law&#44; commandments charges received.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>Brethren&#44; this day has been emphatically called<lb/> by the Sages &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;the great Sabbath&#44;&#34; because<lb/> it precedes the solemnization of an event which<lb/> should interest the whole human race.  And this<lb/> great day which&#44; for upward of three thousand years&#44;<lb/> has seen Israel at one time with manly steps&#44;<lb/> at others feebly&#44; because bent under a by reason of an oppressive burden&#44; of<lb/> oppression&#44; but still always proceeding towards the<lb/> goal of his destination&#44; is the monitor warning<lb/> us never to falter&#44; never cowardly to relinquish<lb/> the God&#45;given trust.  The echo of the parting words<lb/> of our last prophet resounds.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  &#34;Remember<lb/> ye the Law of Moses my servant&#44; whom I<lb/> commanded in Horeb for all Israel statutes and<lb/> ordinances.&#34;  Heed the words and you will be eternized&#44;<lb/> cast them aside and you will be lost in gentilism.<lb/>  But no&#58; We have God&#39;s unalterable promise&#58;<lb/> &#34;I&#44; the Lord do not change&#44; therefore ye child&#45;<lb/>&#45;ren of Jacob are not consumed.&#34;  When we shall<lb/> have passed away&#44; the latest generations will gather<lb/> their offspring round the family board on Passover night&#44;<lb/> and sing Hallelujahs to the ever living Redeemer of Israel.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
