<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF3_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_1_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_1_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_1_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_1_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_1_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>19</p>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>
                An explanatory lecture<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Dear Brethren&#33;  This is one of the four Sabbaths&#44;<lb/> preceding the festival of Passover&#44; on which an<lb/> additional portion of the law is usually read.<lb/>  For the instruction of those among my hearers&#44;<lb/> to whom the origin and design of that custom<lb/> are unknown&#44; I will offer a few explanatory<lb/> remarks thereupon.  The Mishna&#44; which<lb/> has embodied the Hebrew traditions&#44; relates that&#44;<lb/> while the Temple at Jerusalem existed&#44; messengers<lb/> were sent throughout Judea&#44; on the 1t day of<lb/> Adar&#44; to remind its inhabitants of a duty<lb/> incumbent on all&#44; without distinction of<lb/> class or station&#59; namely&#44; of the annual offering<lb/> of half a shekel.  That early proclamation<lb/> allowed every one sufficient time to bring<lb/> his tribute to the sacred treasury&#44; before the<lb/> opening of the ecclesiastical year&#44; which counted<lb/> from Nissan.  But in order to understand<lb/> why the performance of that national obli&#45;<lb/>&#45;gation was limited to the last&#45;named period&#44;<lb/> it is necessary to be acquainted with the object<lb/> of the half a shekel.  From the same<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>authoritative source we learn&#44; that the sacrifi&#45;<lb/>&#45;cial worship was entirely supported by it.<lb/>  And as upon the strength of a logical deduction&#44;<lb/> it had been established that the expenditure<lb/> of each revolving year&#44; should be defrayed by<lb/> a new offering&#44; and never by the surplus of<lb/> the preceding&#44; it became <sic>indespensable</sic> that<lb/> every Israelite&#44; cooperating to the maintenance<lb/> of the Temple service&#44; should accomplish that<lb/> duty without delay.  He could not have alleged<lb/> as a cause for his neglect his want of ability&#44; for&#44;<lb/> the <sic>smalness</sic>of the taxt would have scarcely<lb/> justified it.  But moreover&#44; the announce&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment made on the 1t of Adar tended to afford<lb/> ample time for procuring the scanty sum&#59;<lb/> so that every adult among Hebrew men might<lb/> be represented in the daily as well as all pub&#45;<lb/>&#45;lic sacrifices.  The wealthy could not boast<lb/> of a larger contribution to the furtherance of that<lb/> sacred end&#44; nor could the indigent complain that<lb/> he had no share in the service of the Lord&#59;<lb/> for&#44; agreeably to the first tribute levied by<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Moses&#44; wherewith the sockets of the sanctuary<lb/> and the books thereof were cast&#44; our<lb/> ancient authorities demanded only half a<lb/> shekel equally from every Israelite.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> It is only in commemoration of a usage &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> practiced during the existence of the Temple&#44;<lb/> that on the 1t day of Adar&#44; or upon the Sabbath<lb/> which precedes it&#44; an additional lesson from the<lb/> Pentateuch is recited&#44; allusive to the offering<lb/> of the half a shekel.  In fact the original<lb/> custom itself&#44; though no longer obligatory&#44; is<lb/> preserved among some Communities.  and Before<lb/> the opening of Nisan&#44; each individual tenders<lb/> to the Congregational treasurer&#44; an amount<lb/> equivalent to the amount of Hebrew coin for the<lb/> support of the Synagogue.<lb/></p>
            <p>The second Sabbath on which the law is read<lb/> out of two scrolls&#44; has been termed &#91;Hebrew&#93; because<lb/> the additional section&#44; commencing with that<lb/> word&#44; recalls to our memory the iniquitous<lb/> device of Amalek&#44; and indirectly announces<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>the approaching Purim&#45;&#45;a festivity occasioned by<lb/> the frustration of Jocheme concocted by a scion<lb/> of the same accursed race.  for&#44; Haman who<lb/> bore the appellation of Agagete&#44; probably<lb/> claimed a royal descent therefore as Holy Writ gives<lb/> room to im ply that by such a name the Amalek<lb/>&#45;ite Rulers were distinguished.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;And his king shall be higher than Agog&#34;<lb/>
                the additional portion recited on the third<lb/> Sabbath&#45;&#45;the one we observe this day&#45;&#45;is also<lb/> commemorative of usages connected with the<lb/> sacrificial worship.  Every member of<lb/> the house of Israel was enjoined to offer the<lb/> Parchal&#45;lamb&#44; but bodily impurities disqua&#45;<lb/>&#45;lified him until the 14th of the following<lb/> month for the performance of that rite&#45;&#45;Hence<lb/> to prevent his exclusion from a national service&#44; he sought his purification at the<lb/> commencement of Nisan with through the ashes of the<lb/> red&#45;heifer blended with spring water&#44; &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#45;<lb/> Thus&#44; by way of illustration&#44; a person who had<lb/> been in contact with a dead body&#44; on his<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>applying to the officiating priest&#44; he was<lb/> immediately set apart from his brethren<lb/> during an entire week&#44; and upon the third<lb/> and seventh day&#44; was sprinkled with the mixed<lb/> water by means of a bunch of hyssop.<lb/></p>
            <p>That purification&#44; which enabled him to cele&#45;<lb/>&#45;brate the Passover in its due season&#44; tended<lb/> also to impress him with the solemnity of<lb/> the occasion&#44; and the sanctity of the Temple.<lb/>  The red colour of the heifer&#44; and the scarlet<lb/> wool burnt together&#44; represented his former pollution&#44;<lb/> which precluded his joining in the national<lb/> festival&#59; the utter consumption of those<lb/> two objects indicated the necessity of removing<lb/> every trace of impurity before participating<lb/> in the service of the Lord&#59; while the cedar&#45;wood<lb/> and the hyssop intermixed therewith&#44; signified two<lb/> species of defilements&#44; a voluntary one as typified by<lb/> the natural height of the cedar&#45;tree&#44; as denoting<lb/> haughtiness and presumption&#59; and an accidental<lb/> one&#44; of which the small size of the hyssop was<lb/> a symbol&#44; but which alike needed thorough<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>cleansing ere the paschal lamb could be layd<lb/> laid on the altar of Israel&#39;s God.  During our<lb/> dispersion&#44; we do not require the same timely<lb/> precaution&#44; for &#34;we have neither a priest in his<lb/> office&#44; nor a Levite at his desk&#44; nor Israel in<lb/> his station&#34; yet&#44; we take pleasure in reverting<lb/> to the customs of our forefathers&#44; when they dwelt<lb/> upon their own land&#59; and if we cannot receive<lb/> as they a bodily purification&#44; we pray&#44; with<lb/> the words of our Aftorah&#44; that we may appear<lb/> on the ensuing festival before our heavenly Liberator&#44;<lb/> purged from all moral imperfections &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;And I will sprinkle clean water upon you&#44; and<lb/> ye shall be clean&#44; from all your filthiness and<lb/> from all your abominations will I cleanse you&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>The fourth Sabbath&#44; which invariably follows&#44;<lb/> without intermission&#44; that whereon the statute of con&#45;<lb/> touching &#45;cerning the red&#45;heifer is alluded to&#44; has been styled<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; or the month&#44; because on it we peruse<lb/> an extra chapter from Exodus&#44; that speaks par&#45;<lb/>&#45;ticularly of the importance of Nisan.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Its moment however&#44; is felt in our days as well<lb/> as in those of you&#59; because from that month<lb/> dates the constitution of our nationality&#44; and<lb/> are computed the various holidays enjoined<lb/> in Holy Writ are likewise computed.  We are not to quit out<lb/> homes at its beginning&#44; in order to throng the<lb/> habitation of the Lord on the fourteenth thereof&#44;<lb/> but it is incumbent on us to rid them of<lb/> every vestige of leaven&#44; that we may celebrate<lb/> the Passover in exact conformity with the<lb/> Divine direction.  Therefore we must deem it necessary<lb/> and proper to be early reminded of the forth&#45;<lb/>&#45;coming season&#44; for&#44; we can employ the inter&#45;<lb/>&#45;val in the gradual discharge of the multi&#45;<lb/>&#45;farious duties connected with it.  Now&#44; touching<lb/> the institution of reciting additional lessons are<lb/> the four Sabbaths to which I have hitherto<lb/> alluded&#44; I would observe&#44; that its antiquity<lb/> is warranted by the fact&#44; that it is recorded<lb/> by the contemporaries of the Mishnaic Sages&#59;<lb/> and that&#44; so sanctified by the time&#44; it has<lb/> been incorporated in the ritual of the Israelites&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>and is abided by wherever they congregate.<lb/>  But another practice universally adhered<lb/> to by our nation&#44; is the delivery of a sermon<lb/> on the Sabbath&#44; which immediately precedes the Passover&#44;<lb/> for&#44; although it has not been honored by<lb/> the recital of a particular section of the Penta&#45;<lb/>&#45;teuch&#44; still the title applied thereunto&#44;<lb/> has impressed on it special holiness &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;The great Sabbath&#34; meaning&#44; that day&#44; which&#44;<lb/> according to a certain tradition&#44; the terror of<lb/> God fell upon the persecutors of our ancestors&#44;<lb/> and they were suffered to gather home unmolested<lb/> the deified lamb of the Egyptians&#44; to slaughter<lb/> it on the altar of their heavenly Savior.<lb/></p>
            <p>In consequence thereof the good habit of expa&#45;<lb/>&#45;tiating on the wonders wrought in our behalf at<lb/> that season is prevalent among all Jewish<lb/> communities&#44; and it behooves the preacher<lb/> upon that Sabbath to recommend to his<lb/> audience a strict conformity with the<lb/> regulations prescribed both by the written<lb/> and oral law.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>From all the aforesaid you must have then<lb/> learnt&#44; my dear friends&#33; how solicitous<lb/> have been our Rabbis to recall at all<lb/> periods the reminiscences of the past.<lb/>  Those guardians of the vine brought out<lb/> of Egp Egypt&#44; and now cast among<lb/> the gentiles&#44; would preserve it by<lb/> rasin raising a fence around it&#44; and thus<lb/> far their zeal has been crowned with<lb/> success&#59; for such customs as those which I<lb/> we have cursorily explained&#44; though unessen&#45;<lb/>&#45;tial to the fundamental principles of Judaism by form<lb/> nevertheless by their universality&#44; a strong link that binds<lb/> together the scattered members of our race.<lb/>  When upon the same Sabbaths they read ad&#45;<lb/>&#45;ditional portions of the Pentateuch and listen to<lb/> the same instruction&#44; they are reminded of the<lb/> fact that they have a common extraction<lb/> and a common belief.  Let us then comply<lb/> with the enactments of our Teachers&#44; but let<lb/> the origin and design thereof be constantly<lb/> present in our minds&#44; so that their exercise<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>may call forth sentiments of brotherhood for<lb/> the outcasts of Judah&#44; and of unflinching<lb/> hopes in the deliverance of the Lord&#44; when<lb/> &#34;like the days of our coming forth from Egypt&#44;<lb/> He will show us <sic>marvellous</sic> things.&#34;<lb/>
                &#58;&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Oh Lord God&#33;  On this Sabbath that we have con&#45;<lb/>&#45;cluded the second book&#44; which Thou hast<lb/> inspired Thy servant Moses to write for<lb/> our instruction&#44; we pray that we may not<lb/> in vain have weekly read it.  Grant<lb/> that the miraculous deeds recorded therein<lb/> may may incite us to love and fear Thee.<lb/>  Grant that the character of the main<lb/> actor in the events registered in the same<lb/> volume&#44; may become our exemplar.<lb/>  That his faith&#44; and his zeal&#44; his attachment<lb/> to his people&#44; and his forbearance for their<lb/> rebellious&#44; may be to us a profitable study.<lb/>  Grant that the important laws contained<lb/> in it&#44; and which are destined to govern<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>the entire world&#44; may be deepened strike deep root in<lb/> our hearts.  We pray Thee also&#44; O<lb/> Lord&#33; to infuse in us a spirit of liberality<lb/> like unto that which moved our fathers to<lb/> enrich the sanctuary&#44; that dedicated to Thee<lb/> about this season of our year by their shepherd.<lb/>  Thus nobly prompted&#44; we likewise shall<lb/> speedily consecrate to thy holy name&#44; a<lb/> goodly habitation&#44; in which we shall offer<lb/> instead of steers&#44; supplications and praises.<lb/>  May this be thy will.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
