<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF10_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1892-01" source="" attested="yes">1892</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff10_2_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. Fifth St.<lb/></p>
            <p>Philadelphia&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>On charity some reflections<lb/>
                on the S of U. H. C.&#47;92<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>The style of one of our Talmudic Sages is <sic>epigramatic</sic>&#44;<lb/> so pointedly direct in its briefness.  Rabbi Sinla&#239;&#44; whom<lb/> I like to quote&#44; tells us that the Torah teaches the<lb/> virtue of benevolence in its first pages&#44; benevolence in its<lb/> last pages &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> For&#44; when the parents of the human race needed a cover<lb/> for their naked limbs&#44; God supplied it&#59; when the<lb/> archprophet lay himself down to die&#44; God buried him.<lb/>  From our Maker&#44; we must then learn lessons of charity.<lb/>  Now&#44; brethren&#44; to carry out those lessons out effectively&#44; Phi&#45;<lb/>&#45;ladelphia Jews agreed twenty four years ago upon the<lb/> creation of a society&#44; meant to supersede a number<lb/> of separate organizations.  Its history is well known&#59;<lb/> its workings are set to view in its yearly report.<lb/>  I confess that in reading the latest&#44; I felt pained.<lb/>  Let me not be misunderstood.  I dare not deny<lb/> the unfortunate necessity for an extraordinary ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;penditure&#44; during the last twelve month.  Much more<lb/> than Rabbi Sinla&#239; points out exhibits to view as an illustration exemplification of his<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>concise imparting teaching of goodness human sympathy&#44; our united Charities were called<lb/> upon to perform.  I&#44; who&#44; without holding any<lb/> official position in the association&#44; frequently<lb/> visit the building where our poor seek relief&#44; can<lb/> tell of pitiful scenes thou enacted and of wretched<lb/> misery there mitigated.  I do not begrudge<lb/> my necessitous brethren in want the sums that bought<lb/> them food to sustain life&#44; fuel to warm their bodies&#44;<lb/> that secured for them a shelter and warded off<lb/> sickness and death.  What occasioned in me<lb/> a painful sensation in perusing the report was a reflection on my<lb/> own self&#44; which I fancy to have noticed. in the report it.<lb/>  The woman who stands unequalled in the annals of<lb/> Philadelphia charity among Israelites&#59; the Jewess<lb/> whose death illustrated the mobility of her life&#59;<lb/> the godly Ellen Phillips&#44; who humbly worshipped<lb/> her Maker in this consecrated Tabernacle&#44; had often<lb/> listened to my appeals in behalf of the United<lb/> Charities.  Always open to kindly influences&#44; she<lb/> doubled in late years her original bequest to<lb/> the Society.  She felt that an enforced im&#45;<lb/>&#45;migration from among the down trodden of our race&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>demanded a larger income at the disposal of<lb/> those to whom a wise administration of our joint<lb/> beneficence is committed.  But she could not<lb/> possibly have wished that her munificent legacy might<lb/> be <sic>parcelled</sic> out in a few days among the custom&#45;<lb/>&#45;ary recipients of our alms.  I believe that<lb/> the large hearted benefactress&#44; had hoped to aid our<lb/> almoners in their allowance grants to deserving coreligion&#45;<lb/>&#45;ists&#44; by a judicious investment of the amount<lb/> which she entrusted to their care.  But<lb/> nothing was left of that amount.  Scarcely had her ten thou&#45;<lb/>&#45;sand dollars been deposited into the treasury&#44; when<lb/> a cry went forth&#44; that unless the Hebrew commun&#45;<lb/>&#45;ity hastened to the rescue&#44; the association would pu&#45;<lb/>&#45;blish to the world its inability farther to assist the<lb/> poor any farther more.  Had I not a just right cause to feel grieved&#59;<lb/> to fear that my pleading may have indirectly<lb/> done my sainted friend injustice&#44; by leading encouraging her to<lb/> a deed of generosity that <sic>yeilded</sic> so unsatisfactory<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>a result&#63;  But another state&#45;<lb/>&#45;sman in the latest report affected me unpleasantly.<lb/>  I read in it a recommendation to abolish the giving<lb/> the poor our the Passover bread to our poor.  A tendency to divest<lb/> all our institutions of a characteristic specifically<lb/> Jewish is seen but too clearly.  I lament it&#44; al&#45;<lb/>&#45;though acknowledging my powerlessness in that<lb/> respect.  In years past&#44; I did prevent the carrying<lb/> out of the same proposition&#44; which came now<lb/> strongly endorsed by the Board of government directors.  But time<lb/> and circumstances are not favorable to traditional<lb/> or Mosaic ordinances.  To substitute for the Matzot<lb/> the small coin&#44; which will purchase them&#44; is not<lb/> to keep alive the idea which I love.  Besides&#44;<lb/> it is our women who largely maintain the Judaic<lb/> spirit.  They make the home recall the <sic>marvellous</sic><lb/> history of God&#39;s people and the Torah.  The men&#44; pressed<lb/> by immediate want&#44; or by less justifiable motives&#44; may<lb/> spend the little they have received and leave their<lb/> wives and children deprived of the memorial bread.<lb/>  The argument that many abuse the facility with<lb/> which they can get the appetising Matzah&#44; is<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>not so valid cogent&#44; when we know that a vast deal<lb/> of imposition is practised in other directions ways&#44; which<lb/> have nothing Jewish to recommend them.  I have<lb/> the admission of persons who closely devote their<lb/> time to the needs of the Society&#44; that&#44; contrasted with<lb/> the thousands of yearly wasted on professional men&#45;<lb/>&#45;dicants&#44; the few hundred which the Matzoth<lb/> cost is are insignificant.  We do require<lb/> a reducing of the annual outlay by an economy<lb/> which will hold back the pauper and advance the<lb/> interests of the poor.  But let us not begin with<lb/> the cutting off of a single vestige that marks<lb/> out the organization as a Hebrew charity.  I heartily<lb/> hope that&#44; as the venerable president&#44; who has<lb/> surrendered his trust&#44; expressed it&#44; the society will<lb/> &#34;seek to elevate the station of its beneficiaries&#44; and make true men and women.&#34;<lb/> of its beneficiaries.&#34;  But to accomplish that<lb/> noblest of all objects purposes&#44; it should&#44; in all instances&#44;<lb/> insist upon the religious and secular education of<lb/> the offspring of the same beneficiaries.  That rule<lb/> ought to be enforced on persons who are Jews only<lb/> in so far as they are allowed to apply to Jews for assistance.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>During last winter&#44; I received a letter from an<lb/> unknown Christian.  I concerned a Jewish little<lb/> girl who hawked toys through our thoroughfares.<lb/>  I answered the communication and the gentleman called<lb/> on me.  He had been attracted by the child&#39;s manners&#44;<lb/> and had given her objects of dress and money.  He<lb/> offered me some&#44; which I refused&#44; to buy her clothes&#44;<lb/> as he imagined that destitution compelled one so young<lb/> to an exposure very dangerous&#44; because of her sex.  Our cor&#45;<lb/>respondence continued&#44; for I had promised to interest<lb/> myself with a view to withdraw the child from the<lb/> streets and send her&#44; where she could learn Hebrew and<lb/> English.  My efforts proved fruitless.  Her relatives<lb/> would have gladly accepted an allowance from our<lb/> United Charities&#44; but the child must not give the<lb/> hours that yield the <sic>covetted</sic> dollar to the school house.<lb/>  Ought persons so heedless of their children&#39;s real wel&#45;<lb/>&#45;fare&#44; successfully apply to Jewish charities for the<lb/> satisfaction of their wants&#63;  But they habitually do&#44;<lb/> and not a few with an manners which betray a<lb/> total disregard of the duty which parents owe their offspring.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Now&#44; conceding that it is easier to criticise shortcomings than to<lb/> discover a remedy the way to improvement&#44; granting that<lb/> the difficulty of administering charity judiciously and<lb/> effectively&#44; is very great&#44; recognizing even with<lb/> gratitude the endeavours of some who with unabated<lb/> zeal labor to do good and strive to correct faults and reform abuses&#44; I think<lb/> that in some respects&#44; it would not be arduous for the<lb/> trustees of our organization to act in perfect consonance<lb/> with its aim and scope.  Why the indigent who have<lb/> died&#44; shall have none to accompany them to the grave<lb/> with a prayer&#44; why the man employed engaged by the society<lb/> to prepare for the burial&#44; should not follow the needy<lb/> to their resting place&#44; as he attends the rich encased<lb/> in silver mounted handled and silver plated casket&#44; is a question which I have<lb/> often asked myself&#44; when in obedience to my<lb/> feelings I performed the last services over the remains<lb/> of my indigent brother or sister in faith.  The person&#45;<lb/>&#45;al interest which every one of you will evince in our<lb/> comprehensive institution&#59; your right to suggest<lb/> progressive measures&#44; will&#44; under God&#44; make it a<lb/> blessing to the unfortunates among our people<lb/> and an honor to the Hebrew community.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>In all sincerity&#44; I urge upon you&#44; brothers<lb/> and sisters in Israel to endow bestow your means generously&#44; prompt&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly and cheerfully on the society which&#44; above all<lb/> others&#44; lessens bodily suffering and the mental<lb/> agony which poverty brings on.  Humanity<lb/> claims it&#59; at your hand&#59; the religion which<lb/> you acknowledge demands it at your hands.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  &#34;Charity&#34; precedes &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;prayer&#34; in the<lb/> series of virtues that will win God&#39;s mercy.<lb/>  Let me not have spoken petitioned in vain that you will<lb/> exceed in bulk and in number former contributions.<lb/>  There are none in this congregation who cannot respond.<lb/>  While some have it in their power to bestow give hundreds&#44;<lb/> many can make a small donation.  This is the<lb/> maxim of the Sages of the Mishnah &#91;Hebrew&#93; The Bible calls<lb/> a large offering&#44; a sweet savor to the Lord&#59; a minor<lb/> offering&#44; a sweet savor to the Lord&#59; a handful of<lb/> flour&#44; a sweet savor to the Lord.  The intention is what<lb/> the Almighty accepts&#44; showering down on the giver<lb/> His loving kindness and mercy. the tokens of His approval and His blessing.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
