<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF12_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff12_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff12_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff12_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff12_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff12_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff12_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff12_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff12_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff12_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff12_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff12_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff12_1_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Memorial service for Abraham Adler<lb/>
                Late President of Hebrew free schools<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Dear children.  The occasion that has brought all of us together<lb/> is solemn but sad.  I will tell you what it is the reason for motiv cause of this large meeting very plainly&#44; so<lb/> that the youngest among you may understand what my<lb/> I mean speech.  I O don&#39;t know&#44; however&#44; why I was<lb/> chosen to speak in preference to other gentlemen bet&#45;<lb/>&#45;ter able to do the subject justice from their personal intimate<lb/> kno acquaintance with him about the person of whom I am about to<lb/> speak.  Perhaps the reason is because that they have heard that I am in the<lb/> habit of talking to children every week&#44; trying to make<lb/> them feel how&#44; after2 God&#44; I1 depend upon them for<lb/> the future of our holy religion in America&#59; how I<lb/> look forward to the time when they will grow to be<lb/> men and women&#44; and in their turn will do their utmost<lb/> to keep up that religion among us&#44; by their precept and example.  But<lb/> there may be another cause motive for the choice which the<lb/> directors of your schools have made.  They may have<lb/> heard been told that I love the language in which our people<lb/> offer their prayers to God&#44; and that I rejoice very very<lb/> much at each step taken to spread its knowledge&#44;<lb/> and that because I heartily rejoice at it&#44; therefore<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>I feel thankful to Israelites&#44; who work in any way shape<lb/> whatever or form in order to make our little ones familiar with<lb/> the Hebrew.<lb/></p>
            <p>Now my children&#44; I wish that you feel as I do towards a man who<lb/> labored hard to give you the advantage of learning that<lb/> which must be taught for the sake of Judaism and<lb/> must be held for ever among us in our midst&#44; you may at times have often noticed<lb/> a white haired&#44; tall&#44; pleasant looking gentleman&#44; come to your<lb/> schools.  He would address himself to you with kind<lb/> words&#44; reckon your number&#44; inquire after your improve&#45;<lb/>&#45;ments&#44; and occasionally sit down and examine boys and<lb/> gur girls in the reading and translating of the Bible.  That<lb/> good man will not visit you again.  Unfortunately he is<lb/> dead. I don&#39;t mean to say unfortunately to himself&#59; for<lb/> his soul which can never die&#44; is&#44; no doubt&#44; happy in the<lb/> recollection of the noble deeds performed while it was connected with<lb/> the body.  Nor do I I say &#34;unfortunately&#34; as a complaint against the will of God.<lb/>  It is always right.  I am sure certain that just as when the<lb/> Lord gives so when the Lord takes away&#44; He wants to grant<lb/> us blessings. which WE may not see immediately but which that they are real<lb/> blessings&#44; but we will in the by2 and bye1 find it out to have been real blessings and even if we don&#39;t<lb/> we have the assurance of reason and revelation that the Almighty so just &#91;&#63;&#93; us&#44; and<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>He will not afflict us but with for the object purpose of improving us&#44;<lb/> as a father who chastises his child to make him behave better&#44;<lb/> so that he may become grow to be a pleasure to himself and an honor to so&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciety.  But I call the loss which we have had lately a misfortune&#44;<lb/> because as I cannot look far into the future&#44; I think that<lb/> we could scarcely spare our dear friend and president Mr Abraham<lb/> Adler.  I think that we needed him greatly to help us<lb/> in carrying out an important object.  So active he was&#44;<lb/> so full of energy&#44; so willing to give and induce others to<lb/> give for the establishing of free Hebrew&#45;schools situated<lb/> in different parts of our city.  Why&#44; my dear boys and<lb/> girls&#44; he himself&#44; though old and very busy in the affairs of a large<lb/> store he kept&#44; got for us recently fifty subscribers&#44; so that we<lb/> might offer children who live far up town a chance to<lb/> receive sacred instruction.  It was only this week that I<lb/> spoke about2 our loss. to1 a lady who who takes a lively<lb/> interest in religious matters.  She told me from her own personal knowledge&#44; that whenever<lb/> the subject of Jewish schools of any kind was broached<lb/> in the presence of our late venerable friend&#44; he invariably listened<lb/> with attention&#44; and showed his readiness to lend assistance.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>I am positive that if he were living&#44; he would<lb/> grant us the benefit of his means and advice in to the promotion of the<lb/> plan which we wish to carry out.<lb/></p>
            <p>My children.  Philadelphia is a very large place.  People<lb/> suppose that there are about five thousand Jews living<lb/> in it.  But I believe that more than that number can<lb/> be met.  Particularly if we travel all over I mean in the outskirts of the town city&#44; and in the suburbs&#44; in Frankford and<lb/> in Germantown.  Now&#44; we want that hundreds of little<lb/> boys and girls settled there may get gain&#44; like yourselves the knowledge of<lb/> Hebrew&#44; and not alone of Hebrew&#44; but likewise also of the history of and<lb/> the rules of our religion.  We want furthermore to establish there sewing<lb/> schools&#44; as that which Mrs Van Beel very ably directs&#44;<lb/> and which is a pleasure to visit eve on Sunday afternoon.<lb/> as those kindly and effectively superintended by Miss Phillips and Miss Cohen<lb/>  We want to get up Sunday morning schools&#44; where short<lb/> prayers and portions of the Scriptures are read&#44; and short brief and early lectures may be are delivered on the history and characters of<lb/> the men of the Bible.  It is indeed very important that<lb/> we do all that&#44; because Judaism can alone be kept up only<lb/> by knowledge.  God forbid that you should be brought up<lb/> in ignorance.  See&#33;  We live among Christians&#44; who don&#39;t believe<lb/> in One undivided God as ourselves&#44; and don&#39;t observe the commandments<lb/> of the law of Moses&#59; they may talk you into your giving up<lb/> the beautiful path of Abraham the father of our people<lb/></p> 
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>and the holy ordinances of our prophets.  They may coax you<lb/> to change the Synagogue for the church&#44; and you not<lb/> knowing which is the right&#44; because you had not learnt<lb/> anything the truths of your religion&#44; you may forsake your parents<lb/> and go turn traitors to your your backs on their God.  You couldn&#39;t help it then&#44;<lb/> for you were never shown how the Almighty intended that<lb/> we Jews should by degrees bring the whole world to acknow&#45;<lb/>&#45;ledge that He is the only Being we must offer our prayers<lb/> to&#44; for He is the Creator&#44; and the Saviour kind Providence&#44;<lb/> the Forgiver of our sins and our Redeemer.  But we your elders must<lb/> help it.  We must have schools in plenty&#44; so that not<lb/> a child born of a Jewish father and mother in Philadel&#45;<lb/>&#45;phia shall have an excuse for not having learnt being acquainted with his<lb/> duties.  But to do it&#44; money is needed and persons who will<lb/> give their time and their hearts to the work are required.<lb/>  Our lamented friend Mr Abraham Adler&#44; could be spoken it to and he would have aided assisted us greatly materially&#44; for he was<lb/> very fond of laboring to that end.  And because he was so good you<lb/> should remember him with gratitude.  But do you know<lb/> how you can do his soul pleasure&#63; show thankfulness and procure the soul of your deceased friend gratification&#63;  By drawing the right deriving a proper ad&#45;<lb/>&#45;&#45;vantage of from the opportunity chance he has given you to learn&#59; by stu&#45;<lb/>&#45;dying much and behaving perfectly.  Oh&#33;  I cannot bear<lb/> to think of the discredit you would bring on his name&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>if after all his endeavours you should gain no know&#45;<lb/>&#45;ledge of our Bible and of its language&#44; because you wouldn&#39;t<lb/> pay attention&#44; or because you were unruly and your teachers had<lb/> to spend time in keeping you from mischief&#44; or&#45;&#45;what wold be a more general evil&#45;&#45;because your<lb/> bad conduct would so displease  the good people who take<lb/> an interest in the three schools now existing that they wouldn&#39;t<lb/> have anything more to do with them.  Never&#44; my children.  Honor<lb/> the memory of the venerable Abraham Adler by a regular<lb/> and punctual attendance&#44; by an excellent deportment and<lb/> by application to your task.  Honor his memory so&#44; and he who<lb/> is now in heaven enjoying his reward in the presence of God<lb/> who will pray that you may be blessed with minds to un&#45;<lb/>derstand the right&#44; and with hearts to practice it.  Your<lb/> future&#44; my dear children as men and women in Israel<lb/> was a matter of deep concern to our deceased friend.<lb/>  May he see from heaven that our rising generation<lb/> in Philadelphia will show prove their wisdom by walking<lb/> in the way of the Lord&#44; keeping his precepts&#44; his statutes<lb/> and testimonies and ordinances as He commanded<lb/> unto our fathers.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>And you good teachers instructors of these young creatures&#44; whom<lb/> Abraham Adler late President of this institution committed to your charge tuition&#44; permit me<lb/> to ask urge that you will not be discouraged by difficulties.<lb/>  Redouble your activity and perseverance.  Bear with<lb/> the faults of childhood&#44; and draw these little ones<lb/> by the rule of affection to the fountain of the God&#39;s Law.<lb/>  Make them love the word of inspiration and the lan&#45;<lb/>&#45;guage in which it has been transmitted.  Your<lb/> charge is a weighty as it is holy.  You are I must hope impressed<lb/> with its importance and sanctity.  You are well aware<lb/> that pecuniary remuneration cannot adequately repay<lb/> our public instructors teachers.  Their services are priceless have a value beyond price that of rubies.<lb/>  They are the guardians of religion&#44; Then women who labor for religion have been turned God&#39;s agents&#44; the sentients at the<lb/> citadel of truth&#44; or as the Talmud calls them &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;city watchers.&#34;  Be thus.  Reserve for us this ge&#45;<lb/>&#45;neration and yours will be the merit of which you may<lb/> boast in the allegorical language of the Rabbis.<lb/></p>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Those whom we have trained are replete with sacred know&#45;<lb/>&#45;ledge&#44; and rich in virtues.&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>And you respected directors of the Hebrew free schools<lb/> of Philadelphia&#44; you that have convened this meeting<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>to honor the your dead colleague&#44; continue to benefit the<lb/> living.  Much you have done&#44; and this large assem&#45;<lb/>&#45;blage proves testifies it.  But infinite more is still left<lb/> for you to accomplish.  I have hinted already at<lb/> yours self&#45;imposed and sublime undertaking.  You<lb/> are pledged to it&#44; you will not pause till it be car&#45;<lb/>&#45;ried out.  Like David of old each of you should vow not<lb/> to give himself rest&#44; till he finds places for spots for the dwelling service of the Lord&#44; ta&#45;<lb/>&#45;bernacles for the Mighty One of Jacob &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Schools are high altars to God&#44; colleges are sanctuaries<lb/> to the Most High.  For the knowledge therein early imbibed<lb/> is lasting in its effects.  The din of business may in after life<lb/> may hush the voice of conscience&#44; but it cannot deaden it&#59; the<lb/> tumult of the passions may drown its sound&#44; but it will<lb/> eventually rise powerfully strong and summon us back to the<lb/> path of righteousness.  May yours be the merit of having checked the progress of ungodliness&#44; and promoted the spread of piety&#59; may it be your<lb/> lot to have also restored to Philadelphia the priority hope supremacy to which it is entitled<lb/> for having first striven to uphold the faith by the dissemination<lb/> of sacred learning.  With all my heart I wish you God&#45;speed.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>And thou imparadised spirit of Abraham Adler&#44; accept<lb/> this religious communion to day as a token of appreciation<lb/> of thy noble deed while thou wast clothed in flesh.<lb/>  May our prayers be propitiatory of divine favor&#44; for<lb/> the remission of sin&#44; for the hastening of a more happier<lb/> propitious era to Judaism&#44; and for the redemption<lb/> of all who believe and hope in the salvation of<lb/> the one ever living and ever gracious Lord.<lb/>  Here follows the Hashcabah.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
