<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF7_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff7_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff7_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff7_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff7_1_2v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 1 sheet<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For a funeral<lb/></p>
            <p>Brethren.  All of us have been&#44; more or less&#44; inconvenienced&#44; at times&#44; by<lb/> the heat of the sun.  All of us have occasionally felt some unpleasant<lb/> sensations&#44; when the luminary of the day shoots forth its rays in the<lb/> summer season.  But were we deprived of its quickening powers a single<lb/> day&#44; how dismal&#44; how gloomy would then be the aspect of nature&#33;<lb/>  Nay more&#58; judging others by myself I may safely say&#44; that when the<lb/> sun goes far to warm regions remote from ours&#44; we forget the<lb/> discomforts partly experienced&#44; to remember the gratifications enjoyed<lb/> by reason of it.  We recall the smiling fields&#44; the rich harvest&#44; the<lb/> luscious fruits&#44; the refreshing drink&#44; the fragrant flowers&#44; the bright&#44;<lb/> the cheering sky.  Now&#58; the comparison which I am about<lb/> to draw suggested itself instinctively to my mind on Thursday last&#44;<lb/> when a note from one of the daughters of this venerable Jewess&#44; told<lb/> me that she was verging towards the close of her earthly career&#44;<lb/> and she would soon enter the world of spirits.  Doubtless&#44; for a<lb/> time her exceptionally prolonged existence here below&#44; must have been<lb/> a source of anxious solicitude to her children&#59; specially so to those<lb/> who saw and watched her constantly.  Holy was the duty con&#45;<lb/>&#45;sidered&#44; and sacredly it was performed&#59; yet unavoidably attended<lb/> with painful care and deep concern.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Nevertheless&#44; I venture to assert&#45;&#45;and I mistake human<lb/> nature greatly if I am at fault in the present instance&#45;&#45;I<lb/> venture to assert that all those to whom Rebecca A. Polack<lb/> gave birth forgot the worry felt&#44; only to think of the satis&#45;<lb/>&#45;faction of their mother&#39;s companionship&#44; only to remember<lb/> the pleasurable emotions at beholding her comforts&#44; and<lb/> the appreciation of her heart.  Gladly therefore would<lb/> they have borne with the increasing anxiety&#44; so that she<lb/> might have remained still longer in their midst.  But&#44;<lb/> as true as it is&#44; according to the assurances of science&#44; that<lb/> the earth in its divine&#45;appointed changes&#44; goes to meet the<lb/> sun&#44; while the latter remains in its central position&#44; so<lb/> true it is also&#44; that we all move on towards those who<lb/> have reached their destiny&#44; while they continue in the state<lb/> assigned to them by a merciful Lord.  The merits<lb/> which our deceased sister in faith acquired in the discharge<lb/> of the various obligations of life&#44; are best known to Him<lb/> who reckons our every deed&#44; and understands our secret<lb/> thoughts.  We do know of her industry&#44; and of her unex&#45;<lb/>&#45;celled domestic activity&#44; and we are certain of her<lb/> adherence to the ancestral injunctions&#44; and her fidelity to the<lb/> Unity&#44; with whose declaration Echad she gave up her last breath.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>But it is not of her whom my choicest phrases could<lb/> not benefit in the slightest degree&#44; nor my words of dispa&#45;<lb/>&#45;ragement&#45;&#45;if necessary&#45;&#45;could injure&#44; that I desired to speak.<lb/>  My humble remarks are intended for the surviving children<lb/> of this venerable mother in Israel.  They naturally<lb/> feel much grieved&#59; but the tears they may shed&#44; the laments<lb/> they may utter are not tears of remorse&#44; laments of self&#45;re&#45;<lb/>&#45;proach.  Many a child would wish to call back<lb/> the harsh expression&#44; the thoughtless act&#44; the rebuff that<lb/> wounded a parent&#39;s heart&#44; but too late is filial repentance<lb/> exhibited at the hour in which those who gave us exist&#45;<lb/>&#45;ence and education are enshrouded in a coffin.  The dead have<lb/> gone ot their destination&#44; and the living must reap the har&#45;<lb/>&#45;vest of their own planting.  But tears&#44; in this instance&#44;<lb/> do not flow from Marah&#44; from that bitter very bitter<lb/> fountain of compunction&#59; it is the sorrow of separation<lb/> that draws them forth&#44; not consternation at the dread of a<lb/> celestial punishment for negligence and undutifulness.<lb/>  Let then&#44; children of Rebecca Polack&#44; be comforted&#44; and<lb/> proceed in the career which will gain for you sterling<lb/> merits&#44; and gladden the spirit of the venerable departed<lb/> and propitiate for it heavenly blessings.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Make sacrifices for your fellow believers and for truth.<lb/>  Continue to be tender to the young&#44; reverent to the old&#44; com&#45;<lb/>&#45;passionate to all that suffer&#44; charitable to those who are<lb/> less fortunate than yourselves&#59; exercise the virtues extolled by<lb/> her prophets and Sages in your community and in your city.<lb/>  You shall thus approach step by step a perfectibility&#44; which<lb/> will afford you a foretaste of heaven while yet on earth.<lb/>  And Thou Eternal Lord&#44; pour down consolations on the bereaved.<lb/>  From Thee we receive existence&#44; and we dare not murmur<lb/> when that which is a gift at Thy hands is taken from us<lb/> again.  But to Thy handmaid Rebecca Polack Thou didst<lb/> deign to show exceeding goodness.  For Thou didst excep&#45;<lb/>tionally prolong her life&#44; so that she beheld the children<lb/> of the third generation.  They didst moreover surround<lb/> her with comforts&#44; and with descendants who can be point&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed to as respectful and respected Israelites.  Vouchsafe O Lord&#33; to<lb/> forgive the trespasses of the deceased they loved well&#44; and<lb/> grant to her the reward Thou has reserved for the<lb/> upright who serve Thee with singleness of thoughts<lb/> and purity of heart.  So may it be.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
