<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF4_5</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_5_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_5_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_5_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_5_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_5_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_5_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_5_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_5_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_5_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_5_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_5_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_5_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>23</p>
            
            <p>On the 7th day of Pesach<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>
                Formulated largely from a Hebrew rendition<lb/>
                of a German sermon by Jellinek<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;The Lord will fight for you&#34;.  The<lb/> scriptural portion designated for this festive day&#44; and<lb/> in which the words that I quoted occur&#44; unfold a vision scene<lb/> unique in its character.  Africa and Asia&#45;&#45;the most<lb/> conspicuous parts of the world in the days of antiquity&#45;&#45;<lb/>are drawing against each other a sharp line of demarcation. against each<lb/> other  South of the map&#44; known to the an&#45;<lb/>&#45;cients&#44; lies the famous land country of the pyramids&#44; proud<lb/> of her Nile&#44; &#91;Hebrew&#93; of her soothsayers learned priests &#91;Hebrew&#93; of art and the skill of the to enduringly<lb/> embalmers of her deified dead.  Her countless gods&#44;<lb/> like her mausoleums&#44; tell a tale of human brutalization.<lb/>  North&#45;East lies the desert of Arabia with its moutnain<lb/> pointing heavenward&#45;&#45;that Sinai&#44; hallowed to spiritual<lb/> liberty&#44; from whose peak a flood of light streamed forth to irra&#45;<lb/>&#45;diate the mind of a missionary a newly spiritually created nation.  One one<lb/> side are cities for men&#39;s dwelling&#45;&#45;Succoth&#44; Elthom&#44; Pi&#45;<lb/>&#45;hahiroth&#59; on the other&#44; a sea is surging up&#44; and on<lb/> its horizon a wreath of smoke points the way onward&#59;<lb/> a streak column of red fire illumines the path.  The panora&#45;<lb/>&#45;ma changes and an army and a cavalry are is seen&#44;<lb/> and further on a throngs of an affrighted peoples.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>and in their midst a man venerably majestic man who towers high&#44;<lb/> &#38; waves a staff before which nature bows obediently.<lb/>  Hushed is&#44; of a sudden&#44; the trampling of soldiers ready<lb/> for the fray&#59; the prancing of the horses is heard<lb/> no more.  Angry billows have dragged into the abyss<lb/> the rider and his steed&#44; and from afar the <sic>joyouful</sic><lb/> strains of a liberty song reverberate &#91;Hebrew&#93;  Could<lb/> the inventive genius of poetry have created from &#91;&#63;&#93; pictured depicted a scene<lb/> more striking vividly than the one which that historical episode presents&#63;<lb/>  In Behold in it&#44; my brethren&#44; you are made typically to<lb/> behold past and future struggling for supremacy.<lb/>  The Africa &#38; Asia&#45;&#45;Africa her past is despotism&#59; the irresponsible exercise<lb/> of power over the powerless&#59;  Asia&#58; her the future is is law&#44;<lb/> the recognition of a Lord of compassion&#44; who com&#45;<lb/>&#45;mands visible and invisible ministers of His will<lb/> to stand by the oppressed.  This struggle<lb/> which our section of the Pentateuch symbolizes&#44; con&#45; is old&#44; but it<lb/> has not died&#44; it con&#45;<lb/>&#45;tinues yet&#44; because the highest aspirations of our human&#45;<lb/>&#45;ity remain yet unfulfilled.  To our fathers&#44; Moses<lb/> said this day&#58; &#34;The Lord will fight for you&#44; and<lb/> you shall be silent&#34; and God performed has the pro&#45;<lb/>mise made by inspiration has ever had its &#91;&#63;&#93; has been performed performance.  He God accomplished it<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>in times of old yore and in the middle ages&#59; and yea&#44; He<lb/> fights for us on even now.  A still.  The war was and is waged&#44;<lb/> is not for the conquest of territory&#44; but for that of<lb/> ideas which in all reality govern guide a nations life like that of the indivi&#45;<lb/>&#45;dual.  It is The war peaceful war is unobstensibly noiselessly noiselessly carried on through the faithful&#44; whom the arch&#45;<lb/>&#45;prophet bade to proceed undauntedly.  They waver not in their <sic>lawyalty</sic> to religious precepts to the standard.  The Lord marshals then &#91;Hebrew&#93; under the lead of the Sovereign Lord.  In like manner Even<lb/> as the rising spring battles against winds and rain to rid<lb/> the earth of storms noxious vapors&#44; and prepare the sky for the balmy<lb/> breeze and the ground for the smiling looks verdure which it gives&#44;<lb/> to Israel&#45;&#45;the spring&#44; as it were&#44; of religious nation&#45;<lb/>&#45;alities the first produce of God&#39;s planting&#44; as Jeremiah<lb/> calls it&#44; &#91;Hebrew&#93; helped by the Master above&#44; strives to dissi&#45;<lb/>&#45;pate the clouds which darken human men&#39;s intellects&#44; and<lb/> to make the world ready for the acceptance of luminous<lb/> and soul&#45;quickening truths.  &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;The Lord will<lb/> fight for you&#34; cried out Moses to allay our fathers&#39;<lb/> fears&#44; and infuse the courage of national a progressive resolve.<lb/>  For as Isaiah expresses it&#44; they were sent forth as witnesses<lb/> of a saving God.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  But Jewish the liberals in Judaism deny it&#44; &#38; the prejudiced among Am all classes of &#91;&#63;&#93; progressives all shades of opinion&#44; malign Judaism.  In the name of truth&#58; But Is the Lord<lb/> in by whose presence breathing the archprophet offered reassur&#45;<lb/>&#45;ance to the &#91;&#63;&#93; undying our still ministering at the altar of faith people&#44; a tribal God&#44; who cares for none except his votaries&#44; a Bel&#44; a Dagon or a Cheurosh&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Well&#58; In the vision of the burning bush that never consumed&#44; a fitting type of Israel&#39;s perpetuity&#44; the &#34;I am&#34; He declared<lb/> His eternity and immutability&#45;&#45;sublime attributes<lb/> but insufficient to draw all humanity to the<lb/> footstool of His fatherhood.  But when inspired mes&#45;<lb/>&#45;sengers proclaimed Him &#34;the all aglow with inspiration the fire of inspiration the fire of inspiration ascended the height of ascended the heights the Lord prophecy &#38; saw God enthroned as on high as God of the world.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; not of one single people&#59; the as Ruler of<lb/> the Universe&#44; whose eyes watch nations&#59; as He who<lb/> judges peoples all with equity&#44; He who loves justice<lb/> and cares for the stranger&#44; then it became demon&#45;<lb/>&#45;strably palpable manifest that Israel had been chosen as<lb/> the repository of ideas tending predestined to harmonize mankind and constitute it a family.<lb/>  For in our law&#44; our prophets and our hagiographa<lb/> those enunciations are met&#44; and ours is the par&#45;<lb/>&#45;donable pride of having preserved those books jealously kept such teachings for<lb/> generations yet unborn.  Nay&#58; It was by the spirit<lb/> of that all&#45;embracing fatherhood that Moses avenged<lb/> wrong and wrought deliverance &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;Thou<lb/> shouldst know that the earth belongs to God&#34; was the his charge to<lb/> Pharaoh.  In the same spirit the Sages wrote that<lb/> every moral step in advance made by Israel is God&#39;s triu&#45;<lb/>&#45;mph.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  But ene&#45;<lb/>&#45;mies of light have arisen. at all times on our days<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Not unlike the Syphon of Egyptian mythology<lb/> whose perogative it was to conquer by striking in enemies forced into the<lb/> dark&#44; so have the Treitschkes and the Mars and<lb/> the Ragozins and the Rohlings and the Drumonds and<lb/> others of that ilk&#44; joined impiously hand to terrify<lb/> us into the darkness of inactivity and then heap shame<lb/> upon us as obscurantists&#59; as haters of mankind.  You all may re&#45;<lb/>&#45;member how a short time since ago the infamous attempt<lb/> was made by a would be Hebrew scholar of the gentile persuasion&#44; to prove from<lb/> our literature that the blood accusation&#44; which has but<lb/> too often turned our Passover bread into an actual too real<lb/> bread of affliction to prove I say that the accusation of our murdering a Christian in honor of &#91;Hebrew&#93; the feast of freedom receives strong support.<lb/>  And when that atrocious imputation was irrefutably contradict&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed by Christians &#38; Jews.  Cabbalistic books were ransacked and misquoted<lb/> to prove true what is an unmitigated rank malignant false&#45;<lb/>&#45;hood.  Enemies of light&#33;  Why not cite the<lb/> very prince of traditions&#63;  Even Rabbi Akiba&#44; the mar&#45;<lb/>&#45;tyr&#44; who of our faith.  He wrote &#91;Hebrew&#93; Man &#45;not alone Israel&#45;&#45;&#34;Man is beloved for he was created in<lb/> the image of God&#34;&#44; and mark it well&#58; Akiba was a Hebrew of the<lb/> Hebrews&#44; he who to keep alive the last spark<lb/> of Jewish patriotism is reported to have enlisted&#44; in at a far advanced age&#44;<lb/> in the ranks of Bar Cocheba&#44; that he might strike deal a<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>struggling blow at tyrannical Rome.  When Can you cite one that fought for<lb/> country and religion who has uttered a sentiment more<lb/> grandly liberal than that Semite&#63;  But then<lb/> we are not Aryans&#45;&#45;whatever that epithet may<lb/> mean to avowed believers of in one Creator and hence to in the unity<lb/> of races.  Say our antagonists&#58; &#34;The same marked distinction broad line drawn in the<lb/> days of Moses between Asia and Africa&#44; exists now<lb/> between Aryanism and Semitism&#44; the former means signifies ad&#45;<lb/>&#45;vancement&#44; the latter retrogression.&#34;  So the adversa&#45;<lb/>&#45;ries of the ancient faith preach and publish&#44; and<lb/> they point to certain distinguishing peculiarities as characteris&#45;<lb/>&#45;tical of our people&#39;s isolation.  What are those singular manifestations of exclusiveness&#63;  Enter their &#91;&#63;&#93;<lb/> the homes of the most conservatives.  What meets<lb/> your eyes at the very door&#44; ye accusers&#63;  A Mezuzah.<lb/>  Is that an distinguishing mark evidence of exclusiveness tribalism&#44; of<lb/> ill&#45;will against the outside world&#63;  &#34;The Lord is one&#44;<lb/> you shall love the Lord with all your heart and soul and<lb/> might&#34;.  Is not that the identical lesson which the<lb/> man of Nazareth you hold as the embodiment of divine<lb/> perfection taught the taunting inquisitively tempting badgering lawyer who asked him<lb/> about the greatest commandment&#63;  What have the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Rabbis added to it which impairs its beauty&#63;<lb/>  Why&#44; they declared that to cleave to God is to stir<lb/> oneself and go about doing good&#44; sanctify our energies to the service of goodness&#59; not to pray long and<lb/> undergo privations&#44; but to sanctify existence by instilling copy<lb/> the Most High in His acts of providential mercifulness&#44;<lb/> ad and forgiveness&#44; to model our conduct after that of<lb/> Abraham in cherishing kindness for all creatures and the friend of God&#44; rearing altars&#45;&#45;when the incense of beneficence ascends heavenward.<lb/>  Or later&#44; if you so prefer&#44; the most orthodox synagogues.  What Will<lb/> will you have but the sounds of invectives &#38; imprecations offend your &#91;&#63;&#93; ears&#63;  Alas&#33; that in some churches even<lb/> in America the Jew is called &#34;perfidious &#38; accursed&#34; hence the case of a Jewish child used &#91;&#63;&#93; to death by a Christian lad&#44; before &#34;good Friday&#34;. will echo forth from the &#91;&#63;&#93; of supplication &#34;the Lord is nigh unto all that call<lb/> upon Him&#44; to all that call upon Him in truth&#44;&#34; and through the<lb/> voice of supplicants will respond to this benediction out of<lb/> the Rabbinical ritual &#34;Hear&#44; O Lord&#33; hearest the prayer<lb/> of every month.&#34;  This same liturgical sentence was instanced by<lb/> a Portuguese Sage to a King to show the spirit of our creed at a period of history&#44; when controversies between<lb/> parish and Christian scholars often took place&#44; to were encouraged &#38; listened to by Kings.<lb/> show the spirit of our creed.  And the Talmudists in their<lb/> figurative language&#44; tell us that a house of Jewish<lb/> prayer must have be surrounded by windows&#44; that is&#44; the hen must pe&#45;<lb/>&#45;netrate&#59; the sun&#44; representing God&#39;s benefaction&#44; re&#45;<lb/>flected through all His creatures Thy dwelling place&#44; &#38; so according to all there the stranger calleth to you for&#34;  Do  not smile<lb/> at the legend of the same Talmudists&#44; that when Egypt<lb/> sunk into the bottomless sea and ministering angels<lb/> broke forth into joyous songs&#44; they were thus rebuked<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>&#34;Creatures of my making are perishing away and<lb/> you attune your voices to hymns&#63;&#34;  I read in that pa&#45;<lb/>&#45;rable a sublime lesson of magnanimity.  We shall<lb/> leave to God the vindication of right&#44; and deem it<lb/> offensive to the Deity to be glad when our enemy<lb/> falls.  This idea is farther carried out by our<lb/> olden preceptors in the regulation which shortens the<lb/> recital of the Hallel upon this seventh day of the Pass&#45;<lb/>&#45;over&#44; whereas on all other Biblical festivals it is read<lb/> in its entirety.  And what object could the wise men<lb/> who selected the prophetic portions for each occasion&#44; have<lb/> had in view in choosing for the conclusion of our present<lb/> holidays the splendid masterly oration of Isaiah&#44; in which he<lb/> depicts a reign of righteousness and peace&#44; and of<lb/> knowledge of God&#44; filling the whole earth as the<lb/> water which covers the sea&#63;  What&#44; but to fasten on<lb/> our minds the glorious doctrine of a final unity of<lb/> all races&#44; by the recognition of the fatherhood of God<lb/> and the brotherhood of man&#45;&#45;the interest aspirating of<lb/> Jewish prophets&#63;  Barter not&#44; I pray you&#44; brethren&#44;<lb/> those glorious sentiments underlying your religion&#44; for<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>the vapid liberation of the age.  The Lord will<lb/> fight for you&#44; but only when you will not exchange<lb/> Him for the evanescent popularity&#44; for the grati&#45;<lb/>&#45;fication of a prurient wish to be considered eman&#45;<lb/>&#45;cipated by the miscalled &#34;free thinkers&#34;.  &#34;The Lord<lb/> will reign for ever and ever&#44;&#34; was the closing enun&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciation of the immortal song which echoed forth<lb/> this day from shore to shore&#44; and you daily pray<lb/> for the establishment of that kingdom universally recognized.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Through you will the Almighty<lb/> have a throne in every heart&#44; for Isaiah wrote<lb/> it&#58; &#34;I&#44; the Lord have called thee in right&#45;<lb/>&#45;eousness and held thee strongly by the hand&#44; and<lb/> preserved thee&#44; and made thee a covenant&#45;people&#44;<lb/> a light of nations&#34;.  The Lord shall<lb/> </p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
