<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF3_6</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_6_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_6_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_6_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_6_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_6_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_6_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_6_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_6_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_6_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_6_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_6_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_6_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_6_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_6_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_6_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_6_8v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_6_9r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff3_6_9v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>15 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>An explanatory lecture<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  The theme to which the section of this Sabbath<lb/> draws our attention&#44; is of such magnitude that to attempt to<lb/> compass it within the circumscribed limits of a single lecture&#44;<lb/> would be futile.  That portion of the book of Genesis which<lb/> we have just perused&#44; opens with the narrative of the vicissitudes<lb/> of a man&#44; whom whether we regard simply as an individual of the human race&#44; or as the founder of a nation&#44;<lb/> or as a simple individual&#44; we may justly call eminently<lb/> great.  In him the philosopher will admire that<lb/> masterly mind&#44; which through a concatenation of effects and their<lb/> causes&#44; could unravel the primary cause that gave<lb/> being and impetus to uncreated nature.  The moralist<lb/> will discover in his character those traits which will&#44; as long<lb/> as mankind reveres virtue&#44; excite universal encomium.<lb/>  And he who loves faith&#44; will behold it exemplified&#44; in all its<lb/> purity&#44; in the life of Abraham.  In what light soever<lb/> we contemplate the object under our observation&#44; we shall<lb/> find that to discourse briefly on his rare qualities&#44; would be<lb/> both derogatory and unbecoming&#59; for were we even to confine<lb/> our strictures to the very first sentence with which his<lb/> history commences&#44; ample scope would be offered for detaining<lb/> you long within these sacred walls.  It would in that case&#44; in order to form<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>a connecting link&#44; be needful to allude to that which<lb/> tradition has handed down&#44; concerning the father of our<lb/> people&#44; to investigate the motives which prompted his<lb/> aged parent to emigrate from his native land&#44; and<lb/> then to dilate upon the injunction of the Most High&#44;<lb/> the obedience to which&#44; severed Abraham from his connections&#44;<lb/> and rendered him an exile.  We will then this morn&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing deviate from our customary method&#59; we will not<lb/> assume to produce a well concocted address&#44; for&#44; as I have<lb/> said&#59; to follow coherently the events recorded in our Parash&#39;a<lb/> and expatiate thereupon&#44; would be too extensive a task&#59; and to<lb/> endeavour to do so cursorily would be doing injustice to the topic&#59;<lb/> but&#44; we shall solicit your attention to a few desultory<lb/> remarks on sundry passages which require elucidation.<lb/>
                Our <sic>Rabbies</sic> in the Talmud commenting on the incident<lb/> when Abraham repaired to Egypt&#44; made use of the following<lb/> sentence &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Let every man pay due respect to his<lb/> wife&#44; fo because it is on her account that blessing rests on his house&#44;<lb/> for&#44; it is written that unto Abram He did good for her sake&#34; We will<lb/> examine what relation bears their maxim bears to the circumstance to which<lb/> it had reference.  Holy Writ records that<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>while Abraham dwelt in Canaan&#44; a raging famine constrained<lb/> him to move to another country.  This action which to every<lb/> one of us must appear not alone justifiable but proper&#44; has<lb/> nevertheless called forth the loud censure of a learned expositor.<lb/>  He maintains that in quitting the land which God had ordered<lb/> for his habitation&#44; Abraham committed a grievous sin&#44; and that more&#45;<lb/>&#45;over he&#44; very indiscreetly&#44; exposed his wife&#39;s reputation for&#44; he ought to have<lb/> confided in the Lord&#44; to whom nothing is impossible and remained in Beth El&#44; where he had erected an altar in honor to the Eternal.  So this and he<lb/> adds&#44; that this such a want of faith in the patriarch&#44; was punished by the long<lb/> captivity of his progeny&#59; but the opinion of that ancient<lb/> writer is clearly gainsaid by the Rabbins&#44; who number this very<lb/> circumstance among the trials&#44; to which it pleased the Deity&#44;<lb/> that Abraham should undergo&#44; ere he designated him &#34;his servant<lb/> and friend&#44;&#34; and surely He who had promised to bestow on him<lb/> every spiritual good&#44; would have2 not1 led him to sin&#59; for He<lb/> loveth righteousness&#44; and never abnadoneth his pious ones. but<lb/> Now&#44; my friends&#33; although the patriarch was commanded to dwell in<lb/> Canaan&#44; at no time was he forbid to betake himself<lb/> elsewhere temporarily&#44; and the Bible itself attests&#44; that<lb/> his intention was to remain in Egypt only till the abatement<lb/> of the scourge which afflicted Canaan &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Abram went down to Egypt to sojourn there&#44; for the famine was severe in<lb/> the land&#34;; besides to jeopardize<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>one&#39;s life&#44; and trust to miracles for the issue is not demanded by<lb/> the religion which says proclaims &#34;You shall live by my statutes&#34;&#44;<lb/> and to which sentences our Teachers wisely add &#34;And you shall not fo in any wise <sic>emperil</sic> your lives through them.&#34;<lb/>  To charge Abraham with pusillanimity&#44; would be to deny<lb/> facts&#44; for without demur he staked his existence&#44; when by<lb/> so doing he could rescue the persecuted and humble the<lb/> persecutors&#44; and although his own safety was not involved<lb/> in the affray&#44; he magnanimously faced peril for the<lb/> sake of his fellow&#45;beings&#59; but in the case under discussion&#44;<lb/> he would have endangered himself and his household&#44;<lb/> while and he rendered service to none&#59; therefore we sincerely believe<lb/> that rather than a culpable act&#44; Abraham&#39;s determin&#45;<lb/>&#45;ation was alike judicious and righteous&#59; judicious&#44; because he<lb/> averted an impending evil&#44; and righteous&#44; because&#44; as he<lb/> understood the trust committed to him by the Almighty&#44;<lb/> he would have forfeited it&#44; by a diverse demeanor.<lb/></p>
            <p>Having thus striven to clear our patriarch of the first<lb/> imputation laid against him&#44; we will proceed to examine<lb/> if the argument on which the second accusation has been based&#44;<lb/> is fully borne out by the context&#59; and verily we<lb/> must acknowledge that it has the semblance of truth&#44;<lb/> but we ought&#44; my friends&#33; in pronouncing a judgment to<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>practice great circumspection&#44; for it is not rarely that<lb/> appearance is deceptive&#44; and if collateral circumstances<lb/> were always properly weighted&#44; we might arrive at a<lb/> different conclusion.  It has been said&#44; that Abraham<lb/> resorted to <sic>opprobius</sic> means in order to escape death&#44; and<lb/> that he should have preferred the latter to the disgrace of<lb/> his own consortium.  This reasoning certainly seems plausible&#44;<lb/> but he who argued in this manner&#44; forgot that the outrage<lb/> which Sarah might have received at the hands of the<lb/> Egyptians&#44; would have not in any degree have lessened&#44; if Abraham<lb/> was slain&#44; nay&#44; the risk and the injury would have been greater<lb/> when left unprotected&#44; whereas if he lived&#44; he might by some<lb/> stratagem deliver her from the power of the lawless and restore her to herself.  And in<lb/> fact&#44; it is the opinion of both ancient and modern commentators&#44;<lb/> and among others that of the celebrated Professor Luzzato of<lb/> Padua&#44; that by calling Sarah his sister &#40;in which he spoke<lb/> the truth&#44; for such she really was&#41; Abraham imagined<lb/> that that people might prefer infer that he had brought her thi&#45;<lb/>&#45;ther with the design of marrying her to some nobleman of the<lb/> land&#44; and then when asked for his consent&#44; he would temporize until<lb/> he might safely return whence he came&#59; but that he was<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>frustrated baffled in his device&#44; for no one of the chiefs and princes<lb/> dared to offer her his hand&#44; for fear of the king&#44; who<lb/> would not have suffered any other man to possess a woman<lb/> whose beauty contrasted so strikingly with that of the<lb/> females of his own race&#44; and that harboring under that such apprehension they consequently forced deemed it best<lb/> to commend her before Pharaoh&#44; to whose sent for her without further inquiries palace she was forthwith conveyed.<lb/>  But they who carp at every thing and every body will not concur<lb/> in this view&#59; they will object to this exculpation on biblical ground&#59;<lb/> they will presume to condemn Abraham by his own words&#59; but<lb/> let us see however notice how they can support their position.  The patriarch<lb/> spoke thus to his wife &#34;Say I pray thee&#44; that thou art my<lb/> sister&#44; in order that it may be well to with me for thy sake&#44; and my<lb/> soul live because of thee&#34;  It was selfishness&#44; exclaim our<lb/> antagonists&#44; he sought to preserve his life&#44; and enrich<lb/> himself at the expense of her honor&#59; for what else could&#44;<lb/> the first part of the verse just cited&#44; signify&#44; but a reprehensible eagerness<lb/> for wealth&#63;  Yet I may venture to assert&#44; that such<lb/> an inference displays either ignorance or disregard of the nature<lb/> of the <sic>hebrew</sic> language.  Were I to prove by quotations that<lb/> Holy Writ is wont first to pronounce a sentence in general<lb/> terms&#44; and immediately after to particularize it&#44; I should<lb/> exhaust your patience by the immensity of their numbers<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>but in order that my affirmation may not appear vague&#44;<lb/> I shall produce a few instances.  In the book of Deuteronomy<lb/> we are strongly warned against exercising cruelty towards animals&#44;<lb/> &#34;Thou shalt not see the ass of thy brother&#44; or his ox fall down by<lb/> the way and hide thyself from them&#59; thou shalt lift them up<lb/> again&#34; defining with the last words&#44; the duty generally expressed<lb/> before&#44; when it said bid us&#44; &#34;not to hide our eyes from them&#59;&#34; elsewhere<lb/> we are told that to exact usury from our co&#45;religionists&#44; is a<lb/> heinous crime&#44; and in that case the command &#91;&#63;&#93; thus &#34;Thou shallt<lb/> not lend upon usury to thy brother.&#34;  This might have been<lb/> deemed sufficient to restrain us from <sic>practising</sic> it in any guise&#44;<lb/> but the Scripture specifies it by adding &#34;utter usury of money&#44;<lb/> of victuals or of whatsoever might be loaned.&#34;  In another<lb/> page of the heavenly volumes we are prohibited when we<lb/> meet with a bird&#39;s nest&#44; to take the dam with her young&#44; and the<lb/> expression then used is as follows &#34;Thou shallt send the dam<lb/> away and take the young with thee&#44;&#34; in order that it may<lb/> be well with thee&#59; and thou mayest prolong thy life&#34;&#44; explaining<lb/> with the end of the sentence what <sic>preceeds</sic> it&#44; namely&#44; the good<lb/> thou shalt derive from thy obedience to this law&#44; will be&#44; length<lb/> of days.  And in like manner must the words of Abraham<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>be interpreted.  The advantage accruing from thy proclaiming<lb/> thyself my sister said he to Sarah will be that I shall not be wantonly<lb/> killed but&#59; far be a thought of venality from him who pe<lb/>&#45;remptorily refused to appropriate to himself the least of that which<lb/> he had wrestled from the hands of the spoilers&#59; far be a mercenary<lb/> design from him who generously gave the tenth of his own<lb/> acquisition to the priest who ministered Ch to the Most<lb/> High&#59; but&#44; why&#59; does not the very construction of the sentence<lb/> justify our interpretation&#63;  If the truth was on the side of<lb/> those who dissent from our opinion and he meant to signify that not alone he should eschew danger&#44; but accrue acquire wealth&#44; through munificent gifts ought not the text to<lb/> be transposed&#44; and read so &#34;Say&#44; I pray thee&#44; that thou art my<lb/> sister&#44; so that I may live for thy sake&#44; and that it may be<lb/> well with me because of thee&#34;&#63; but that it is not so worded&#44;<lb/> is the strongest evidence of what we have hitherto endeavoured<lb/> to demonstrate.  Nor is the fact that Abraham gained<lb/> materially by this incident&#44; a refutation of our argument&#44; for<lb/> it is obvious from the maxim of the Rabbins which I prefaced<lb/> to my remarks&#44; that they refer the sixteenth verse of the<lb/> twelfth chapter of Genesis&#44; to the Lord and not to Pharoah&#59;<lb/> According to their rendering&#44; that verse is an antithesis to<lb/> the succeeding one&#44; namely &#34;Unto Abraham He &#40;God&#41; did<lb/> good&#44; but unto Pharaoh he plagued&#44;&#34; hence comes their<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>aphorism &#34;Let every man pay due respect to his wife&#44;<lb/> because it is on her account that blessing rests on his house<lb/> for&#44; it is written that Abram was <sic>benefitted</sic> through Sarah&#34;<lb/>  This opinion of our Sages has been endorsed by the learned<lb/> Abarbanel&#44; who strives to corroborate it by pointing to<lb/> the words occurring in the text.  He maintains that if<lb/> Pharoah was the donor the phrase &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;And he gave him sheep&#44; and<lb/> oxen&#34; etc&#44; ought to have been written instead of &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;And he had<lb/> sheep&#34; and so forth&#44; which might denote that they were his property<lb/> previous to that period&#59; but if we even agree to the more general<lb/> acceptation of that verse&#44; and admit that Pharoah is<lb/> the subject of the proposition&#44; it will reflect no ignominy<lb/> on the irreproachable character of the patriarch&#44; if the<lb/> monarch of Egypt&#44; unsolicited&#44; bestowed on him some presents.<lb/>  In repairing to that country&#44; Abraham had sought to<lb/> rescue himself and his household from the pangs of starvation&#59;<lb/> in concealing his right claim on Sarah&#44; he aimed at<lb/> his self&#45;preservation and that of her honor&#44; but in no manner<lb/> he ever debased himself because of worldly preferments&#44; and<lb/> of his designs were frustrated&#44; we must assign the cause<lb/> to Him who disposes otherwise than what man proposes&#59; for&#44; to try his<lb/> faith the Almighty suffered him not&#44; to remain where he<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p><sic>he</sic> had met abundant subsistence&#44; and whereas he had<lb/> imagined to shield his wife&#39;s reputation from danger&#44; she<lb/> was on the contrary suddenly taken from him.  Yet&#44; &#34;as the eye<lb/> of the Eternal watches them that fear him&#44; &#38; those who trust in<lb/> his mercy&#44; to deliver their soul from death and to maintain<lb/> them alive in the famine&#59;&#34; so were Abraham and his beloved<lb/> partner supported by the might arm of the Lord&#44; and he<lb/> commanded his angel to encompass them that they might not<lb/> be scathed.  And now&#44; my friends&#33; that I<lb/> have so far labored to exonerate the father of our people<lb/> from the two imputations laid against him&#44; namely&#59;<lb/> his having quitted the land of promise without the expressed<lb/> consent of the Lord&#44; and his having egotistically exposed<lb/> his wife to dishonour&#44; I need not dwell any longer to disprove&#44;<lb/> what has been averred&#44; that the servitude of Egypt was<lb/> the consequence of Abraham&#39;s guilt&#59; but&#44; as touching the cause<lb/> of that event&#44; authors vary greatly in their notions&#44; I shall<lb/> very briefly signify my idea on that subject.<lb/></p>
            <p>I believe that the bondage which our ancestors suffered<lb/> in the country of the Pharoahs&#44; was not a punishment<lb/> for any previous delinquency&#44; but a decree of the Omnipotent&#44;<lb/> for a wise and benevolent design.  He foresaw that if the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>descendants of Abraham had increased and striven in the land<lb/> of their nativity&#44; they might gradually become identified with<lb/> the aborigines&#44; and forget the tradition of that Unity which<lb/> has been jealously preserved by the patriarchs&#59; and he therefore<lb/> deemed it necessary&#44; for the sake of mankind at large and for<lb/> the glory of his name&#44; that Israel should undergo exile and<lb/> thraldom.  In a place where they were considered strangers&#44; they<lb/> would have remained aloof from the idolatrous denizens&#44; and<lb/> the persecutions to which the latter subjected them&#44; would<lb/> prove the strongest safeguard against imbibing their baleful<lb/> principles.  Israel purified in the crucible of very severe trials&#44; would<lb/> be fitted for the reception of those tenets which were to spread<lb/> light and eternal life among all the offspring of Adam.<lb/>  And God would also be extolled alike through their medium as through their stupendous deeds&#59; for&#44; when<lb/> He would stretch forth his powerful arm to liberate his enslaved people&#44;<lb/> and the laws of nature would become subservient to his will&#44; human<lb/> wisdom would stand aghast&#44; and they who denied his existence&#44;<lb/> his power and his watchful providence&#44; would be forced to confess<lb/> that He is the Creator&#44; the Almighty and the Saviour.<lb/></p>
            <p>This I judge&#44; if man can presume to scrutinize the device of<lb/> the Lord&#44; is the principal cause of the Egyptian bondage and of the<lb/> wondrous deliverance therefrom&#59; and not&#44; as some have supposed&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p>the consequence of a sin which Abraham entailed on his<lb/> posterity&#44; for&#44; the immortal spirit from above never animated a being<lb/> more faithful to his God&#44; more dutiful to his family&#44; more<lb/> beneficent to his fellow&#45;men&#44; more generous towards every one&#44;<lb/> more devoted to the cause of truth&#44; than the venerated Founder<lb/> of our nation.  On him is deservedly bestowed the need of praise<lb/> awarded by our Sages&#44; when they said&#44; that Abraham was the<lb/> type which Isaiah had in his mind in his sublime description of<lb/> the man who shall even stand high in the presence of God&#59; which<lb/> is &#34;he that walketh uprightly&#44; and speaketh righteously&#44; he that<lb/> despiseth the gain of oppressions&#44; that shaketh his hand from holding<lb/> of bribes&#44; that stoppeth his ears from hearing of guilt&#44; and shutteth<lb/> his eyes from seeing evil&#34; May he ever be also our prototype&#44;<lb/> the exemplar which we will strive to copy&#44; for then the<lb/> epithets used by the prophet shall justly beseem every one of<lb/> us.  &#34;Listen now Thou art O Israel my servant&#44; O Jacob whom I have<lb/> chosen&#44; O the seed of Abraham my friend&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>
                O Shield of Abraham&#33;  It is by this epithet that thy children<lb/> daily address thy throne.  With their faces towards that<lb/> part of thy world&#44; whence that righteous man&#44; charged<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="14"/>
            <p>with a glorious mission&#44; was summoned&#59; they exalt<lb/> as they recall to their minds thy divine declarations on<lb/> behalf of his future generations.  When for thy sake<lb/> he suppressed filial tenderness and the love for the land of<lb/> his birth&#44; and went to an unknown clime&#44; Thou didst comfort<lb/> his heart by the assurance that his trials would yield an ever&#45;<lb/>&#45;lasting good.  He did not murmur when famine<lb/> made him again roam abroad&#44; for&#44; his faith sustained him&#44;<lb/> and because of that&#44; he saw thy hand strike him who was ready<lb/> to tarnish his honor.  His meek spirit did not swell<lb/> with pride when by his own hand valour he struck down crushed the<lb/> oppressors&#44; for&#44; he labored in thy name&#44; and to save the<lb/> innocents&#44; was his highest recompense.  When an appalling<lb/> vision terrified his mind&#44; and his prophetic eyes viewed unutterable<lb/> suffering&#44; the cause of which he could not comprehend&#44; he<lb/> silently received that fiat&#44; because he knew that thy ways<lb/> are righteousness.  And what promptitude did he not evince<lb/> when at the age of nearly a hundred&#44; he was bid to subject his<lb/> body to writhing pains&#33;  On the &#34;self&#45;same day&#34; he obeyed that<lb/> injunction and was seated with thy covenant.  Many O Lord&#33; were<lb/> the trials which he for thy sake exultingly underwent&#44; and the<lb/> merit he acquired&#44; has been entailed on his posterity.  Thou<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="15"/>
            <p>didst promise to be to them a protecting God.  Father&#33;<lb/>  The days of our pious ancestor did not exceed those of his<lb/> contemporaries&#44; so that he might experience the <sic>fulfilment</sic><lb/> of thy declaration&#44; but from the supernal habitation where<lb/> his soul is imparadised&#44; he beholds it even this day through<lb/> the breadth and length of Thy world.  Grant O God&#44; that<lb/> through his merits we may ever live in thy presence&#44; as<lb/> the worthy children of one so faithful.  Grant that when<lb/> the period of our probation shall expire&#44; and in accordance<lb/> with the prophecy&#44; the remnant of thy people shall have<lb/> been tried as gold is tried&#44; we may still invoke Thy name<lb/> in the beauteous Zion as our only God&#44; the shield of Abraham.<lb/>  Amen.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
