<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF7_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_2_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>On Parashat Vayesheb<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Joseph was sold for a slave.  They found his<lb/> feet in fetters&#44; his body was laid in irons&#44; until<lb/> the time that his own word came to pass&#44; when<lb/> the will of the Lord purified him&#34;.  So reads a<lb/> record left of one of the noblest of human characters.<lb/>  The description will be found in a writing which<lb/> offers a bird&#39;s eye view of the history of our peo&#45;<lb/>&#45;ple&#44; from the patriarchal ages to the conquest of<lb/> Palestine.  You may feel curious to know<lb/> the author of that short but comprehensive pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;duction.  Well&#58; it has come down to us posterity anony&#45;<lb/>&#45;mously&#44; but I see in that composition the master&#45;<lb/>mind glowing with devotional thoughts.  The versatile<lb/> genius of David must have penned it.  The aim of<lb/> that crowned shepherd of old had been to prepare<lb/> an imposing service for the Temple which he longed<lb/> to hand raised to the God of salvation.  To that<lb/> end his fertile imagination enriched Israel&#44; and by<lb/> means of Israel the whole civilized world&#44; with<lb/> sublime effusions&#44; best fitted as a communion between<lb/> earthly creatures and their Divine Maker heavenly Creator.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>I mean&#44; the Tehillim&#44; or Tehilloth&#45;&#45;that<lb/> matchless collection of praises&#44; prayers and hymns<lb/> chastening but cheering&#44; humbling the spirit&#44; yet<lb/> lifting it high to the head&#45;spring of comfort.<lb/>  David&#39;s righteous ambition to be the poet laureate<lb/> of the King of Kings showed itself first&#44; when<lb/> the ark of the covenant&#44; long exiled and kept<lb/> away form the Mosaic Tabernacle&#44; was brought to hailed in<lb/> the new capital of Israel and enshrined under the veil.<lb/>  You remember the narrative of that soul&#45;stirring<lb/> incident.  An enthusiastic reception was to<lb/> have been given to an object worthy of<lb/> the most profound reverence.  All the tribes&#44;<lb/> like a swelling stream&#44; overleaping its banks&#44;<lb/> had flowed into Jerusalem.  For the ovation was<lb/> emphatically national.  Not to &#91;&#63;&#93; a mortal<lb/> being&#44; preeminent for his warlike exploits&#44; or<lb/> universally famous for his political influence<lb/> had that countless multitudes gathered together.<lb/>  Not to pay homage to David&#44; the victor of hundred<lb/> battles&#44; the ally of powerful rulers&#44; but to greet<lb/> the quickening word of the Supreme&#45;&#45;the ten command&#45;<lb/>&#45;ments of Sinai&#45;&#45;had the immense concourse assembled under the shades of Zion.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>The son of Jesse&#44; the greatest in Israel&#44; mingled<lb/> with the lowliest&#44; in acts of devotional joy.  His<lb/> ardor was not dampened by the taunting reproaches<lb/> of the proud daughter of the house of Saul.  What<lb/> Michael ridiculed as derogatory to regal dignity&#44;<lb/> David deemed most honorable.  For the once fugi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tive and persecuted could&#44; with deep&#45;felt sincerity&#44; say&#44;<lb/> &#34;His is the happiest day of my life.&#34;  In time of<lb/> affliction he had vowed to glorify his celestial Deli&#45;<lb/>&#45;verer&#44; and now&#44; the Monarch whose friendship east&#45;<lb/>&#45;ern potentates sought&#44; now&#44; he that dwelt in a palace<lb/> which the renowned craftsmen of Phoenicia had built&#44;<lb/> could not rest&#44; while his eager wish remained unful&#45;<lb/>&#45;filled &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;I will not let my eyes sleep&#44; nor my eyelids<lb/> slumber&#44; till I find a seat for the Eternal&#44; a<lb/> Tabernacle for the might One of Jacob.&#34;  So had<lb/> David promised&#44; and the consummation of his desire<lb/> loomed high.  The man who had shed blood in fighting<lb/> his people&#39;s battles was not suffered by the Deity<lb/> to rear a Sanctuary in Him whose appellation is Adonai Shalom&#44; the Lord of peace&#44; but David but he foresaw its erection<lb/> at no distant period.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>He beheld the glistening spires towering heaven&#45;<lb/>&#45;ward in the city&#44; which he had captured from the insulting<lb/> Jebusite and and had chosen as the metropolis of his<lb/> kingdom.  For that David the son of Jesse had accumulated treasures&#44;<lb/> for that he had drafted models and plans&#44; and in<lb/> anticipation of that important event&#44; he thus hailed<lb/> the entrance of the ark of the testimony into Jerusalem.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Rise O Lord&#33; for Thy resting place&#44; Thou and Thy<lb/> oracle&#44; the sign of Thy omnipotence.  Thy priests<lb/> shall be clothed in righteousness&#44; and Thy devout ones<lb/> shall sing&#44; &#39;for the sake of David Thy servant&#44; do<lb/> not reject Thy <sic>annointed</sic>&#39;&#34;.  That was the address of<lb/> welcome from the throne to the glorious comer&#91;&#63;&#93;.  Then the skilful musi&#45;<lb/>&#45;cians and glowing poet appointed the Levites&#44;<lb/> whose prerogatives was to make the habitation of<lb/> God vocal with the strings of their instruments<lb/> and their sacred songs.  For that purpose David<lb/> composed and doubtless arranged harmoniously&#44; the<lb/> psalm where the historical character which forms<lb/> the central figure in our Pentateuchal section is fittingly described<lb/> in the language of my text.  &#91;Hebrew&#93; Joseph was sold for<lb/> a slave.  They forced his feet in fetters&#44; his body was laid<lb/> in irons&#44; until the time that his own word came to pass&#44;<lb/> when the will of the Lord purified him.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>I say that the inspired bard wrote it then&#44; not&#45;<lb/>&#45;withstanding the verbal discrepancy existing in that same<lb/> composition&#44; as registered in the 16th chapter of the<lb/> first book of Chronicles&#44; and the 105th psalm.<lb/>  I hold that David is the author of that production&#44;<lb/> which he intended to be alternately chanted in its<lb/> various readings.  For no effusion of his genius could<lb/> he more appropriately have given to the Levites to<lb/> sing in the national worship&#44; than that which<lb/> briefly narrated the sufferings of the exemplary son<lb/> of Rachel&#44; and his abiding trust in Almighty God.<lb/>  Aye&#58; well he wrote it &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;the will of the Lord puri&#45;<lb/>&#45;fied him&#34;.  It is the crucible of trials that we<lb/> show of what size and what mettle our spirit<lb/> is made.  Joseph sold for having spoken frankly&#59; Jo&#45;<lb/>&#45;seph imprisoned for having overcome scorned to yield to a fearful<lb/> temptation&#44; was passing through an ordeal&#44; whence<lb/> he would issue forth sublimely perfect.  His<lb/> history plainly related as Moses received it&#44; was<lb/> to the ancient tribes&#44; and will continue ever to be&#44;<lb/> a lesson which all the maxims of moralists and<lb/> the sentences of philosophers cannot equal.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>That lesson which speaks volumes of truths&#44; pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;cious to man in every relation of life&#44; as a<lb/> child&#44; as a brother&#44; as a father&#44; as a citizen&#44; or<lb/> as a titled official&#44; is in our portion of the Pen&#45;<lb/>&#45;tateuch more particularly directed to youths in<lb/> a subordinate condition.  Not exactly like Joseph&#45;&#45;<lb/> reduced to mere chattel&#45;&#45;but still subject to the will<lb/> of another who has the right to command.  Let<lb/> them study the demeanour of that Hebrew lad.  It<lb/> may reconcile many a rebellious will to orders<lb/> considered imperious&#44; and therefore resisted.  It will<lb/> teach that a dependent station cannot degrade<lb/> him who fills it with a keen sense of duty&#44; and<lb/> with singleness of purpose.  Joseph did not expect<lb/> a remuneration for his arduous labors&#44; but his heart<lb/> told him that obedience to those who have a claim<lb/> to our services is virtue&#44; and to promote their inte&#45;<lb/>&#45;rest is righteousness.  He did not grow impa&#45;<lb/>&#45;tient because he could not at once exchange drud&#45;<lb/>&#45;gery for a less toilsome and more congenial office.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Nor did he sit and repine over his hard fate&#44;<lb/> but proceeded with alacrity&#44; certain that his ser&#45;<lb/>&#45;vices&#44; if valuable&#44; would be rewarded with confidence.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;And the Lord was with Joseph&#44;&#34; we read&#44; for<lb/> God is always with the well&#45;principled and the<lb/> diligent.  The slave became the virtual ruler of<lb/> the house&#44; because his master took notice of that unswer&#45;<lb/>&#45;ving fidelity which challenges respect.  To that<lb/> unimpeachable honesty&#44; I judge&#44; the youth owed<lb/> his escape from the effects of a false accusation.<lb/>  And when a prisoner&#44; without a cause&#44; still his<lb/> industry&#44; tampered the severity of his condition.<lb/>  It would not be difficult for any one of<lb/> us to trace the want of success in the lives of<lb/> many individuals to an opposite conduct&#59; to<lb/> restlessness under a wholesome restraint in early<lb/> years.  The experience of my hearers will<lb/> help me in the assertion that Americans may<lb/> look back and have a just cause to attribute a<lb/> failure in their undertakings to a spirit of<lb/> mistaken independence&#59; to a confusion of ideas&#44;<lb/> darkening the intellect&#44; so that it cannot discover<lb/> between social freedom and moral obligations.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>But I have spoken to day mainly to instruct a<lb/> young brother&#44; who needs our encouragement&#44; our<lb/> sympathy and counsel.  Deprived of paternal<lb/> support&#44; and doubtless necessitated soon to go<lb/> out into the world and earn his bread by the<lb/> sweat of his brow&#44; he should be shown here&#44; in<lb/> the dwelling of Israel&#39;s God&#44; the way he must<lb/> follow to obtain favor and rise by his own merits.<lb/>  Joseph is a fitting model to any&#44; and specially<lb/> to a child&#44; who may be thrown among strangers.<lb/>  Seeing the children of the wealthy enjoy leisure&#44;<lb/> and himself tied down to work&#44; he may occasionally<lb/> feel as if Providence had been unkind to him.  We<lb/> must this day give the lad the assurance that he<lb/> will have no cause to despond by reason of that dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;parity&#44; that a better future awaits the industrious<lb/> than the heir of riches&#44; that he will proffer by<lb/> his exertions&#44; that the Almighty will bless his ef&#45;<lb/>&#45;forts&#44; if the heart accompanies them&#59; if the drift of his<lb/> endeavours is not to gain opulence and swell high with<lb/> popular praise&#44; but to do right &#38;c &#38;c &#38;c ...<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
