<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF5_20</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_20_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_20_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_20_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_20_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_20_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_20_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_20_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_20_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_20_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_20_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_20_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_20_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Post Biblical<lb/>
                63<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>History has recorded that even after the pitiless procla&#45;<lb/>&#45;mation of expulsion had gone forth&#44; Abarbanel had not<lb/> relinquished all hopes to work upon the feelings of the king<lb/> and queen and induce them to revoke the iniquitous edict.<lb/>  He knew that Isabella was not hard&#45;hearted by nature&#44; if she<lb/> was made a bigot by education&#44; while experience had made it almost<lb/> assured to his mind him that Ferdinand could be softened at the sight<lb/> of gold.  Accordingly&#44; he secretly arranged that an audience<lb/> might be given him together with a few influential friends.<lb/>  In language which Abarbanel knew well how to choose&#44; the<lb/> great diplomatist and financier&#44; pointed out the irreparable<lb/> loss that Spain would sustain by the banishment of a class<lb/> of people that had enriched it the country as merchants and<lb/> <sic>benefitted</sic> it by a practical application of sciences&#59; a people that<lb/> reflected honor on the peninsula by their cultured intellects and<lb/> who loved it passionately as the home of their ancestors as the<lb/> cherished spot where lay the bones of generations of Jews&#44;<lb/> ever ready to make sacrifices for their native hearth country.<lb/>  Then with keen judgment and tact he added at the last that as a<lb/> demonstration of the affection which Jews bore Spain&#44; they<lb/> would pour into its treasury three hundred thousand gold<lb/> ducats for the privilege of living and dying there.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Isabella&#44; not inherently cruel&#59; Ferdinand insatiably greedy&#44;<lb/> wavered.  They looked at each other indecisively.  They were about<lb/> to <sic>yeild</sic>&#44; when Torquemada&#44; the inquisitor general&#44; who must<lb/> have heard that Abarbanel and his friends had been given an granted a private<lb/> audience&#44; rushed into the hall&#44; hiding under his Dominican<lb/> cloak a crucifix.  He seized it&#44; raised it aloft and with a<lb/> fierce countenance cried out&#44; &#34;Judas Iscariot sold his master<lb/> for thirty pieces of silver&#44; your highnesses are about to<lb/> sell him for three hundred thousand ducats pieces of gold.  Here<lb/> he is&#44; take him&#44; barter him away.&#34;  With that&#44; the savage<lb/> priest&#44; whose insolence ought to have met with a withering<lb/> rebuke&#44; threw the crucifix upon a table and went out&#44; thus<lb/> putting an end to the pending negotiations.  For&#44; Isabella was terror struck<lb/> at the denunciations of the man who held in his hand the strings of her heart.<lb/> in his hand Her confessor would not grant her absolution.  She<lb/> would be doomed to a hereafter of everlasting torments.  No&#58; Catholic<lb/> Spain must not harbor infidels.  Prescott in his elegantly<lb/> written history of Ferdinand and Isabella&#44; referring to the expul&#45;<lb/>sion&#44; says that by &#34;a deed so unwise and impolitic&#44; Spain lost the<lb/> most industrious and <sic>skilful</sic> portion of her subjects.&#34;  And in<lb/> a narrative which tears the soul of the reader&#44; the American historian pictures<lb/> the sufferings of the exiles while in search of an asylum&#44; which<lb/> refined barbarity denied them.  Abarbanel in his preface to a<lb/> his comment on Daniel utters this Jeremiah&#45;like lamentation.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>&#34;I am the man who saw affliction&#44; after having seen<lb/> my people in its greatness.  My own eyes did see its increasing<lb/> prosperity&#59; the height it had attained&#44; its glory&#59; all which<lb/> it had achieved.  My eyes followed it in all its phases.<lb/>  It was became splendid.  Who would have believed what has happened&#63;<lb/>  I call heaven and the Lord Divinity as witnesses of this truth.  In the<lb/> year that our splendour vanished&#44; there were in the kingdom<lb/> of Spain three hundred thousand of my people&#44; every one of<lb/> whom owned estates worth amounting altogether in the aggregate to more than thirty millions gold<lb/> ducats&#45;&#45;a wealth <sic>ammassed</sic> alas&#33; to the ruin of its possessors.  For&#44;<lb/> after four years from the awful event&#44; the exiles were reduced to ten thousand were poverty<lb/> stricken&#44; stripped of their all&#59; a target to robbers&#44; rolling in<lb/> their own blood.  Bitterly do I weep&#59; my spirit is broken by<lb/> reason of the devastation and desolation.  My heart trembles&#59; I<lb/> drag myself on the ground which I tread upon.&#34;  A<lb/> number of the unfortunate refugees reached Italy and sought<lb/> a home in Naples&#44; where Ferdinand II. reigned.  That Prince<lb/> showed them kindness.  Abarbanel and his family had also<lb/> gone there in quest of a shelter.  The illustrious exile found<lb/> a measure of comfort in resuming his favorite writings.<lb/>  But again he was drawn out of the privacy that he yearned<lb/> for. The Neopolitan king being told of his presence&#44; requested<lb/> that he would serve him&#44; as he had served Alfonso V of Portugal<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>and the ungrateful Ferdinand and Isabella.  Abarbanel dared<lb/> not refuse and he accepted the an office in the financial treasury department.<lb/>  But adversity accompanied him there also.  For&#44; Charles VIII. of<lb/> France made war against Naples and conquered it.  Abarbanel&#44;<lb/> loyal to the son of Ferdinand who had succeeded his father&#44; at&#45;<lb/>&#45;tended the dethroned Prince in Sicily&#44; as partner of a life of sorrow. in<lb/> Sicily  The French had confiscated all he possessed&#44; and<lb/> unhappy Abarbanel a wanderer all alone forlorn and disconsolate&#44; left exchanged<lb/> after a time Sicily for Corfu.  because Meanwhile his children unable to provide for their<lb/> parent and for themselves&#44; had scattered about.  He&#44;<lb/> Left alone&#44; he however did not&#44; continue long in Corfu&#44; but longing anxious for quietness after<lb/> so stormy an existence&#44; he passed on to Monopoliz&#44; a small<lb/> town not far from Venice&#44; where he remained eight years<lb/> absorbed in the studies which alone afforded him pleasure respite<lb/> and earned for him eternal renown.  At the instance of<lb/> his son Joseph he was subsequently induced to come out of his retirement and<lb/> settle in Venice.  Inscrutable are the ways of Providence.<lb/>  The Republic on the Adriatic&#44; knowing what an expert Abarbanel<lb/> was in diplomacy&#44; requested that he would undertake to settle<lb/> a dispute litigation it had with Portugal&#44; concerning certain distant colo&#45;<lb/>&#45;nies and the trade derived from them.  His diplomatic will statesmanship<lb/> was put again to the test and&#44; regardless of the treatment which<lb/> he had received when in his native home at Lisbon&#44; he settled the<lb/> dispute contest agreeably to both the contestants disputants.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>  Of his three sons&#44; the illustrious distinguished father might well have<lb/> been proud.  Judah&#44; the oldest&#44; called in Italian &#34;Leon&#44;&#34; gained<lb/> distinction as an eminence as a physician&#44; but more so by means of his<lb/> scientific researches.  His celebrity however&#44; is principally based<lb/> upon a work which he entitled &#34;Dialogues on love&#34;; Dia<lb/> &#45;loghi d&#39;amore.  I confess that it being in my mother<lb/> tongue&#44; I felt very curious to read it.  But owing to my<lb/> unacquaintance with ignorance of philosophy in general and with of that of<lb/> Plato in particular&#44; I failed to appreciate a book discussing<lb/> the attractiveness of metaphysical ideas.  But the production which I did not prize non&#45;Jewish Italian<lb/> scholars however have greatly valued&#44; that book that so that so that through their favorable opinion it has<lb/> undergone translations in several languages&#44; even in Hebrew.<lb/>  Profess Graetz holds that &#34;Leon Abarbanel was much<lb/> more highly accomplished&#59; richer in thoughts&#59; in every way<lb/> more gifted than his father.&#34;  Possibly so&#44; but I am not fa&#45;<lb/>miliar with the writings of the son&#44; and I have acquired some<lb/> acquaintance with those of the parent&#44; that I highly appreciate.&#45;&#45;an author greatly exceedingly esteemed by me.<lb/>  My affection for Judah Abarbanel has its origin not in his<lb/> Dialogues on love&#44; but in the anguish that he heroically endured for the<lb/> sake of his religion.  When the agonizing hour of the expulsion<lb/> from Spain arrived&#44; Ferdinand of Castile determined that&#44; if his<lb/> minister and financial adviser preferred poverty&#44; exile and<lb/> suffering to baptism&#44; the son&#44; who had <sic>developped</sic> extraordinary<lb/> talents&#44; should be forced to remain in Spain.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>to accomplish his design&#44; he ordered that Judah Abarbanel&#39;s<lb/> little child&#44; one year old&#44; named Isaac&#44; after his grandparent&#44;<lb/> be abducted&#44; thinking that it would be the sure means of<lb/> preventing the departure of the father&#44; who would try make any sacrifice to secure<lb/> the recovery of his boy.  An intimation of the wicked plan was<lb/> obtained in time and Judah Abarbanel entrusted the babe to a<lb/> nurse&#44; charged to take it him to Portugal.  He himself would<lb/> not venture there&#44; because of the treatment which his own<lb/> father had received under John II.  He preferred to accom&#45;<lb/>&#45;pany his broken&#45;hearted parent to Naples&#44; hoping that the<lb/> child would escape the attention of the authorities in Lisbon.<lb/>  Whether treachery on the part of the nurse&#44; or government spies did the foul<lb/> wrong&#44; John II was told that one of the seed of Abarbanel<lb/> was in his kingdom.  He kept the child as a hostage&#44; ex&#45;<lb/>pecting that his father would soon follow.  Frustrated in that<lb/> object&#44; the boy was finally baptised and baptism of the boy Abarbanel boy was made to afforded ba the beholders pleasure.  Like Edgar Mortara of<lb/> Italy Papal Rome in our days&#44; the lad was reared in the bosom of the Catholic Church.<lb/>  A Hebrew elegy which the afflicted father composed is dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;tressful in the extreme.  I will translate two or three lines&#58;<lb/> Apostrophising his child&#44; the unfortunate father exclaims&#58; &#34;I hope&#44; oh hope deferred&#33;  Why dost thou my sweet darling delay<lb/> to come&#63;  Why wilt thou crush the heart of him that has begotten<lb/> thee&#44; thrusting arrows into my reins&#44; darkening the sun&#44; clouding the stars<lb/> of my existence&#44; stealing sleep from my eyes&#44; so that I know not<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>whether I should to rise up&#44; or lie down.  Ah&#33;  I dream of the my return.<lb/>  I see thy image&#45;&#45;O how delightful my hope lot&#33;&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>Joseph Abarbanel&#44; the second son of Don Isaac&#44; combined with<lb/> the knowledge of the medical art that of general literature.<lb/>  He settled in Ferrara and reached a very old age&#44; in the enjoyment of universal esteem.  Samuel the third<lb/> son of Don Isaac was only nineteen years&#44; when his father<lb/> fled to Naples.  And as his parent could not bestow upon<lb/> the youth&#39;s education the necessary attention&#44; he was<lb/> sent to Salonica&#44; where he gained surpassing capacities&#44; the<lb/> exercise of which procured for him fame and riches.  One<lb/> of his contemporaries&#44; Samuel Usque who had escaped from<lb/> the inquisition at Portugal&#44; alluding to that third son of<lb/> Don Isaac&#44; writes in his history entitled &#34;Consolation for the sorrows of Israel&#34;  &#34;That scion of Abarbanel<lb/> possesses a threefold glory&#45;&#45;greatness in learning&#44; greatness<lb/> in lineage&#44; greatness in affluence.&#34;  And the same author<lb/> lavishes praises upon that an same Israelite&#44; whom he portrays as<lb/> a generous and public benefactor.  However&#44; in my<lb/> mind the father of the three distinguished sons excelled them all.<lb/>  Not simply because of his facile pen so very prolific&#59;<lb/> not even for the honor which he shed upon his people<lb/> and his faith by his a broad understanding of the art of govern&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment&#44; but because when confronted by the alternative<lb/> either to enjoy life&#44; opulence and power as a pretended convert<lb/> to Christianity&#44; or to face tribulations and death in exile&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>he chose the latter&#44; that he might remain true<lb/> to Judaism.  Born to be a majestic figure in<lb/> the country of his birth among the celebrities of that wonder&#45;<lb/>ful age of learning&#44; perfidy&#44; ingratitude and religious hatred<lb/> made Isaac Abarbanel a wanderer&#44; among strangers&#44; needy<lb/> and broken in spirit.  Scarcely had the allotted scriptural three<lb/> score years and ten arrived&#59; when the strain of exceedingly extremely<lb/> sore trials&#44; told upon his system.  He died in at Venice&#44; just after having completed his seventy<lb/> first year&#44; at Venice but the Israelites of Padua&#44; who<lb/> could boast of a flourishing community and of men in its<lb/> midst of great calibre&#44; begged of their <sic>Venitian</sic> coreligion&#45;<lb/>&#45;ists the privilege of having the Sephardic Sage and<lb/> illustrious diplomatist statesman&#44; who had created an epoch&#44; interred<lb/> in their choice burial place ground.  His sons had the remains of<lb/> their immortal father carried there&#44; amidst the universal la&#45;<lb/>&#45;mentations of Italian Jews.  But even after its decease&#44; the<lb/> body of that glorious son of Israel was denied rest&#44; for<lb/> a conflict between some Italian cities within the gates of Padua<lb/> overthrew houses and fields and with them the cemetery in which<lb/> the bones of Don Isaac Abarbanel lay buried.  Still&#44; I remember<lb/> to have read that recently while excavations were being made&#44; the<lb/> working men found a tombstone&#44; which they imagined to have<lb/> been placed over what was mortal of our greater brother in faith.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>Nay&#44; his body may have been lost&#44; but his spirit lives and<lb/> breathes love within all for the religion that cost him such<lb/> sufferings.  Could his undying soul address us now&#44; it<lb/> would urge us to hold fast on the belief we inherited&#44;<lb/> even&#44; on the Sephardic liturgy memorials&#44; historically grand.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
