<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF8_3</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1888-01" source="" attested="yes">1888</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_3_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_3_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_3_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_3_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_3_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_3_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_3_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_3_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_3_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_3_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_3_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_3_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>119</p>
            
            <p>On the bull fight at Celaya &#40;Mexico&#41;<lb/> in honor of Easter Sunday. 88<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  Last Thursday in reading the morning<lb/> papers&#44; I fully realized the meaning of a sentence in<lb/> Hosea&#44; as Rabbinically commented on.  The prophet<lb/> so addresses his contemporaries &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;O Israel&#44; rejoice not according to after the manner of other people&#39;s pleasure.&#34;<lb/>  By what are Hebrew festivities distinguished&#63;  Ask<lb/> some Talmudists&#44; and the answer returned is by no means in but truth not<lb/> a message concocted by national vanity always repre&#45;<lb/>&#45;hensible&#44; not a fabricating a groundless boast deserving public cen&#45;<lb/>&#45;sure&#44; but a reply as is based on the unshaken found&#45;<lb/>&#45;ations of history.  Hebrews celebrate their holidays<lb/> conformably to the dictates of a religious sentiment and<lb/> a national instinct&#59; precisely as the sages express<lb/> it &#91;Hebrew&#93; neither wholly ascetically&#44; nor wholly materially.  They do not devote the time en&#45;<lb/>&#45;tirely to ascetic devotional practices&#44; like anchorites&#44; nor do they<lb/> <sic>yeild</sic> it like sybarites altogether to the cravings of the palate<lb/> and the gratification of the senses.  Hebrews<lb/> understand that God has endowed His creatures with<lb/> an intellectual soul which does needs spiritual food&#44;<lb/> but they are alive to the fact that He has also given<lb/> them bodily promptings&#44; which dare not be overlooked.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>That correct impression&#44; the idea that it becomes as to attend to both those wants&#44; strengthened by the experience lessons<lb/> of ages past&#44; leads observant Israelites aright.  Thus&#44; prayers and<lb/> thanksgiving&#44; meditations and righteous resolves do not<lb/> prelude a family repast richer than ordinarily on holiday&#44; accord&#45;<lb/>ing to God&#39;s gifts bounties&#44; and an agreeable interchange of<lb/> friendly visits.  Necessary as the Synagogue un&#45;<lb/>&#45;doubtedly is to keep alive quicken the nobler part of our being&#45;&#45;<lb/>our Divine aspirations&#45;&#45;&#44; still the home pleasurable gatherings at home and<lb/> the kindly intercourse abroad&#44; are essential&#44; as highly it directly<lb/> preeminently calculated to foster domestic affections and human<lb/> sociability.  Perhaps&#44; the festival in which<lb/> those many healthful features combine and are most clearly set to view&#44;<lb/> is the last&#44; just solemnized throughout Israel&#44;<lb/> and I have but profound pity for my brethren born in<lb/> the faith&#44; who find it more sensible to spend the<lb/> evening of the fourteenth of Nisan at a soir&#233;e&#44; than<lb/> in raising attuning our children&#39;s hearts to sing hymns and psalmody to in honor of the Redeemer of<lb/> the oppressed.  I grieve over those who let every day<lb/> of the Passover week glide by unnoticed and unhonored disowned.<lb/>  Without claiming the gift of prophecy&#44; I predict that the<lb/> progeny of such&#44; reared to look on the memorials of a mar&#45;<lb/>vellous post as sheer stolidity&#44; will shape their future<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>in a mould neither godly nor blissful.<lb/></p>
            <p>But my object this sabbath is not to offer admonish.<lb/>  Deeply as I lament the growing evil to my faith&#44; result&#45; menace against our religion&#44; offered<lb/> &#45;ing from by the heedlessness of some whom I would delight<lb/> to acknowledge as believing brethren loyal Hebrews&#44; I must forbear<lb/> chiding&#44; when I simply wish to explain.  Last Sunday<lb/> was Easter&#44; invariably held on the first day of the week<lb/> after the full moon of Nisan.  The celebrated renowned French<lb/> Orientalist&#45;&#45;Joseph Ernest Renan&#45;&#45;whom none will<lb/> accuse of holding traditional Judaism in undue reverence&#44;<lb/> wrote this&#58; &#34;The establishment of the Church can have<lb/> a meaning significance only by a reference to in connection with the Synagogue&#44; which<lb/> existed already in countries bordering on the Mediterranean&#44;<lb/> when Paul and the other apostles took up their mission.&#34;<lb/>  All know that the feast of the unleavened bread was then common to<lb/> the followers of the new creed as to those of the mother<lb/> belief.  In conformity with Pursuant to the example of the founder<lb/> of Christianity&#44; as reported in the New Testament&#44;<lb/> the celebration continued at the same time&#44; till policy<lb/> dictated a separation&#44; not contemplated by the man<lb/> of Nazareth&#44; and not at all conducive to the moral<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>advantage of his adherents.  After various at&#45;<lb/>&#45;tempts at a final break with Mosaism&#44; in order to<lb/> open a channel for the inflowing of gentilism&#44; the<lb/> Synod at Anteochia&#44; in the middle of the fourth cen&#45;<lb/>&#45;tury&#44; issued this injunction&#58; &#34;If any head of the church&#44;<lb/> bishop&#44; priest or deacon shall dare after this decree<lb/> is made known&#44; to act at pleasure&#44; misleading peoples<lb/> and disturbing churches&#44; by keeping the pascha or Pesach &#40;feast&#41; with<lb/> the Jews&#44; this holy synod adjudges him from now a<lb/> stranger to the Church&#44; and as one who is not only<lb/> himself a sinner&#44; but one who lays a stumbling block<lb/> in the way of many.&#34;  Easter of heathen origin&#44; sup&#45;<lb/>&#45;planted then the Jewish Passover.  But Now&#44;<lb/> fellow Israelites&#44; consider at what cost Christianity<lb/> severed every connection with the religion from which<lb/> it sprung.  I have no reference to shall say nothing of novel dogmas bewildering<lb/> defilling repugnant to reason&#44; ever t as the coexistence of a triune god&#44; nor of ceremonies inexplicable as the<lb/> transubstantiation.<lb/>  I have no desire indeed to cast reflections on my neigh&#45;<lb/>&#45;bors&#39; belief.  My feelings and the teachings I have im&#45;<lb/>&#45;bibed demand that I shall respect those who ho&#45;<lb/>&#45;nestly hold doctrinal opinions to which my mind<lb/> cannot assent.  But I feel justified in<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>asserting that&#44; viewed even from a moral standpoint&#44;<lb/> the severance did not benefit society at large as intended.  The<lb/> ethical code which Christianity borrowed from Ju&#45;<lb/>&#45;daism and on which it claims to have improved&#44;<lb/> does not while it on improving did improve holy theists immensely&#44; it did not altogether effectually guard its own followers altogether from from a taint of heathenish<lb/> indulgences.  Greek and Roman rude practices<lb/> of a rude character still cling to them.  I have often protested in<lb/> the name of our religion&#45;&#45;which is humanity&#45;&#45;against<lb/> games in which the brutal side of human nature<lb/> is shamelessly exhibited&#44; but last on Thursday morning in reading<lb/> what happened at Celaya in Mexico last Sunday&#45;&#45;<lb/> Easter Sunday&#45;&#45;I was asked myself whether this is the enlightened 19th century of the Christian era&#44; so horrified I was.  It The shocking event must have<lb/> attracted your attention.  The festival which the<lb/> Christians of early ages celebrated with us by eating<lb/> the commemorative &#34;bread of affliction&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93; and by singing<lb/> hosannas to the heavenly Liberator&#44; was devoted there<lb/> to a barbaric sport of pagan origin&#44; to a fight between men savagely<lb/> trained men and infuriated bulls.  What ensued you<lb/> have learned.  Even convicts must participate in<lb/> the cruel pasttime horrid diversion&#44; because it is national&#44; forsooth&#33;<lb/> and try to make good their escape&#44; set the spot enclosure<lb/> where thousands had gathered on fire.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>It soon devoured the lives of helpless women and<lb/> children&#44; while the horrid animals enraged beasts rendered more<lb/> fierce by the crackling of the flames and by the<lb/> unbearable heat&#44; gored many of the spectators to death.  A carnage was perpetrated.  Report<lb/> tells that &#34;the best society was in attendance&#44;&#34; but<lb/> the worst society in Israel would not conceive think it<lb/> possible conceivable to so thus observe one of our festivals.  Such<lb/> a catastrophe under such revolting circumstances<lb/> would be a impossibility&#44; it<lb/> could never occur among &#34;the people of the God<lb/> of Abraham&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Rightly Fervently we may<lb/> repeat with fervor the daily prayer of our the olden ritual &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Blessed be our God who created us to attest His<lb/> glory and separated set us apart from those who are in<lb/> error&#44; and gave us a true Law&#44; in which He im&#45;<lb/>&#45;planted a life eternal.&#34;  Deny it who will&#44;<lb/> but the Torah has been the salt that kept our<lb/> hearts undecayed.  The more who we shall ponder<lb/> on it&#44; and the closer we shall observe cleave to it&#44; the gentler&#44;<lb/> the kinder will our nature be.  Not as a boast<lb/> I say so&#44; but in acknowledgment of deep gra&#45;<lb/>&#45;titude to the heavenly Being&#44; who inspired our<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Moses and our prophets&#44; and endowed our<lb/> Sages with wisdom to instruct us nobly.<lb/>  Far be from me to gainsay what is patient.  The<lb/> moral legislation of Sinai has taken a deep root<lb/> among our fellow creatures of a newer creed.  There<lb/> are Christians&#44; who shrink with horror equally<lb/> as ourselves at the sight of the brutality I have<lb/> described.  There are Christians overflowing with<lb/> compassion&#44; even for lower creatures animals&#59; men and women<lb/>&#45;&#45;innumerable&#45;&#45;ever ready to lend a helping hand<lb/> to elevate and protect and alleviate sufferings&#44; but<lb/> what is generally titled &#34;Christian Charity&#34; is by<lb/> priority of birth&#44; Jewish.  This I am anxious<lb/> to impress upon all&#59; I must and to assure my young fellow believers that<lb/> no improvement can be made on the guiding principles of the faith which<lb/> teaches that &#91;Hebrew&#93;  God&#39;s <sic>trhone</sic><lb/> stands on righteousness and justice&#44; and that loving kindness<lb/> and truth will stand before His face enjoy the radiance of God&#39;s countenance&#44; or as the Rabbis<lb/> put it &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;the precepts<lb/> were intended only to humanize the earthly creatures.&#34;<lb/>  To this fact broad minded non&#45;Israelites have often<lb/> testified&#44; and none perhaps more emphatically willingly<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>than the eminent jurist&#44; whose demise elicited<lb/> expressions of sorrow in our courts&#44; on Wednesday last&#44; and whose panegyric will be pronounced today<lb/> Benjamin Harris Brewster was alike genial and<lb/> liberal&#44; and whenever occasions presented themselves to<lb/> do us justice&#44; he eagerly seized them.  Standing Raised loft&#45;<lb/>&#45;ily in his legal profession so that he by natural talents&#44; so as to deservedly popularly win the position<lb/> of attorney general of Pennsylvania&#59; enjoying at<lb/> one time the confidence of the President of the<lb/> United States&#44; who appointed him counsellor in<lb/> the interest of the Republic&#44; loyal lawyer Brewster<lb/> did not refuse grow proud and deny the use of his talents capacities in behalf<lb/> of institutions of burning and beneficence.  Rich<lb/> in expressions&#44; graceful in diction&#44; flowery in style and<lb/> witty withal his eloquence was sought after&#44; and the Israe&#45;<lb/>&#45;lites of this city enjoyed it as well as others appreciatively availed themselves therewithof.<lb/>  I can recall the time when he spoke at banquets<lb/> in aid of the Hebrew Education Society&#44; and he<lb/> was heard also acceptably at the hall monthly entertainments of the Young Men&#39;s<lb/> Hebrew Association.  I gladly own our indebtedness<lb/> to the noble hearted departed citizen of Philadelphia&#44; now departed from our midst&#44;<lb/> and pray that his generous instincts may secure for<lb/> his soul the bounties of heaven in the of beatitude world of forgiveness and bliss.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
