<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF1_8</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_8_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_8_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_8_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_8_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_8_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_8_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_8_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_8_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_8_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_8_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_8_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_8_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>7 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>On the occasion of 4 Bar Mitzvah<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>The occasion is extraordinary.  It must call forth some remarks.<lb/>  I do not believe that the history of this Congregation&#44; can point<lb/> to that what the circumstance we have witnessed to&#45;day&#44; I mean&#44; the addition<lb/> of four lads on one Sabbath to the number of God&#39;s worship&#45;<lb/>&#45;pers.  At all events&#44; I&#44; who have long been connected with it&#44;<lb/> do not remember a similar instance.  I am glad it has happened&#44;<lb/> and I give free expression to my feelings&#44; because the hope founded<lb/> upon the teaching of our experienced Rabbis receives obtains confirm&#45;<lb/>&#45;ation thereby &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Every union formed for the sake of honoring God&#44; is destined to<lb/> remain.&#34;  He unusual increase accession just received&#44; augurs well<lb/> for the continuance of our sacred institution.  It will be<lb/> preserved&#44; and with it will be effected the object of the<lb/> worship&#44; which is neither the temporal support of any one<lb/> individual&#44; nor the gratification of the personal ambition<lb/> of a few&#44; but most unqualifiedly and truly the pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;motion of practical righteousness.  In that light it has been viewed<lb/> by the good men of past ages&#44; and so I do trust and<lb/> pray it may ever be regarded in Israel.<lb/></p>
            <p>Simeon the just&#44; a member of the great synod once<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>presided over by Ezra the priest placed worship as<lb/> the central pillar&#44; on which the world of Judaism firmly<lb/> rests.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Torah&#45;&#45;the knowledge of the holy law&#45;&#45;&#44; and Gemehet Chassa&#45;<lb/>&#45;dim acts of beneficence&#45;&#45;stand each by the side of Abodat<lb/> divine service&#44; and set off its real worth.  What is it&#44; my<lb/> Brethren&#63;  What is in very deed this assemblage in a<lb/> peculiar spot which we keep up at the cost of time and<lb/> means&#63;  What&#44; but a monitor&#44; a constant reminder<lb/> of our dependence on the Almighty&#44; and of our community<lb/> of origin and interests&#63;  But can utterances emanating from<lb/> persons whose minds are void of the understanding of the<lb/> Sinaic instruction&#44; and whose hearts are closed against cha&#45;<lb/>&#45;ritable instincts be termed a worship&#63;  It could no more<lb/> be asserted that <sic>wilful</sic> ignorance and unkindness can offer<lb/> a holy communion&#44; than to say be said that learning means piety&#44;<lb/> and alms giving doled out is a most acceptable divine service.  No&#44; unless the<lb/> places where Israelites meet to pray serve to enlighten the<lb/> attendants into the path of religious duties&#44; and to soften<lb/> their feelings&#44; or to say it&#44; as Simeon the just was accusto&#45;<lb/>&#45;med to express it&#44; unless Torah&#45;&#45;the knowledge of the Law&#44;<lb/> and Gemehet Chassadim&#45;&#45;died of goodness&#44; stand side by side<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>With the Abodah&#45;worship&#44; the latter cease to be of any<lb/> appreciable value.  We must then by that our religious<lb/> union be deserving to remain by showing itself a &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> To do it&#44; gold is unavoidably needed&#44; but not to such a<lb/> degree as to deter the honest working&#45;man from contributing<lb/> effectually to that end.  for&#44; he who bestows the little<lb/> he can spare from after having supplied his legitimate wants&#44; to maintain the<lb/> worship&#44; but gives more largely than of money his time&#44;<lb/> his thoughts&#44; his feelings to the promotion furtherance of that glorious<lb/> object&#44; may be said to have <sic>mightly</sic> sustained Judaism.<lb/>  Now&#58; I think&#44; I do not misplace my confidence when I<lb/> look to our first Bar Mitzvah as a future contributor to the<lb/> preservation of our institution.  Only He who apportions<lb/> to each of us a lot&#44; which His wisdom judges best&#44; knows<lb/> whether the means at the disposal of our newly quali&#45;<lb/>&#45;fied Cohen&#44; will be ample and proportionately devoted<lb/> to the maintenance of the Synagogue&#44; but arguing from<lb/> surroundings&#44; I have cause to believe that his presence and<lb/> his anxiety to practically carry out the purpose of Synagogue<lb/> attendance will be unlimited by circumstances.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>About the three who succeeded him&#44; no anticipations can<lb/> be approximately formed.  My prayers are for them&#58; aye&#58;<lb/> more than my prayers&#44; my soul&#39;s yearnings are for their<lb/> healthful growth as palm&#45;trees in the courts of our Lord.<lb/>  Ever since the establishment which has fostered those lads<lb/> was opened&#44; I set my hopes within its walls.  I expected<lb/> that form there&#44; the teachers of American Israel would<lb/> issue forth&#44; according to the aphorism &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Away from the outside influences which&#44; at times&#44; pervert<lb/> the studious and righteous dispositions of our children&#59; brought<lb/> up to feel understand that all they enjoy is not&#44; as our sons and<lb/> daughters consider it&#44; a matter of course&#44; a thing that can&#45;<lb/>&#45;not be otherwise&#44; but rather a gift from the Source of<lb/> beneficence daily bestowed&#44; they might have become the fittest<lb/> to impart Judaism in its purity.  So far I have met<lb/> with disappointments.  Some did proceed from that Int<lb/> Institute&#44; who in the ordinary walks of life commend them&#45;<lb/>&#45;selves to our esteem&#59; some are pursuing with intelligence<lb/> and conscientious industry the course laid out for their<lb/> apprenticeship&#44; but scarcely any can be pointed to that<lb/> chose for their calling the ministry of the Lord&#44; studying<lb/> the interests of Judaism&#44; and laboring to uphold its time&#45;honored<lb/> standard.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>But aside from that&#59; the inmates of that asylum coming from various sections of the land&#44; have<lb/> scattered to different parts of the land&#44; thereof&#44; and they will be likely<lb/> still to leave our midst&#44; thus disabling f me from judging<lb/> personally whether they will be supporters of the Divine<lb/> worship by natural and spiritual agencies.<lb/></p>
            <p>Nevertheless&#44; while I dare not form an opinion about the<lb/> selection of my three young brothers&#39; future course in life career&#44;<lb/> I must exhort them to turn to good account the advantages<lb/> possessed&#44; to study assiduously&#44; depending on my assurance<lb/> that if they or nay of their school&#45;mates decide upon<lb/> a choice which will supply our sacred desks with readers&#44;<lb/> and our pulpits with preachers&#44; the facilities for effecting<lb/> their arm will be forthcomin held out.  And may the<lb/> God of Israel guide those three lads of our faith with His counsel.<lb/>  May He who cast a shield round their lives existence&#44; when they stood<lb/> a target to the arrows of misfortune&#44; ever deliver them from<lb/> the onslaught of sin&#44; so that a well spent life existence may en&#45;<lb/>&#45;title them to the honor they have sought to day.  May they<lb/> feel that humbleness in childhood is a ladder to exaltation<lb/> in manhood&#44; and so believing&#44; endeavour to ascend each<lb/> step till they reach the topmost happiness<lb/> and the sanctification of the name of the Lord.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>And may&#44; my brother Cohen to whom the privilege<lb/> of blessing has been given&#44; see the realization of<lb/> our Rabbis&#39; saying &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; that whosoever needs Divine<lb/> assistance and prays that it may be showered down<lb/> upon others&#44; he will obtain it first.  May our<lb/> Bar Mitzvah exercise his prerogative not merely by<lb/> conforming with an outward form observance&#44; but by having always<lb/> a benediction in his heart for all the creatures of the<lb/> earth.  May he notably hold it for the benefactors<lb/> of his early days&#44; and the his unwavering friends<lb/> in after&#45;life&#59; even his parents who hope that his<lb/> even temperament and good disposition may have<lb/> enabled them to have offered Judaism a staunch<lb/> supporter&#44; doing honor to the house of Israel&#44; and<lb/> glorifying their One God.<lb/>  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
