<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF13_5</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_5_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_5_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_5_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_5_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_5_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_5_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_5_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_5_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_5_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_5_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_5_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_5_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>5th lecture on Immortality.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  The reverence in which Rabbi Akiba has been<lb/> deservedly held by a nation who remembered his checkered<lb/> life&#44; his surpassing learning&#44; and his death as a martyr<lb/> to freedom and religion&#44; led gave universality of a practice based upon<lb/> one of his sayings.  That illustrious Sage had expressed<lb/> the opinion that twelve months is the period of trials&#44;<lb/> when needed&#44; for a spiritual purification beyond the grave is 12 months.<lb/>  The support to that opinion&#44; as borrowed from the last<lb/> sentence but one of Isaiah&#44; may be declared extremely weak.<lb/>  It is in fact more a kind of mnemonical contrivance&#59;&#45;&#45;as frequently used among Rabbis&#59; a reminder of the view set<lb/> forth more than a proof in its favor.  Still&#44; all congregations<lb/> of Israel&#44; in deference to the authority of the man&#44; have<lb/> agreed to observe a twelve month&#39;s mourning.  And In in the<lb/> belief that the soul&#44; while undergoing atonement feels enjoys a foretaste<lb/> of heaven by the public praises of the Lord&#44; by charitable and<lb/> pious deeds&#45;&#45;when emanating from the living it dearly fondly loved&#45;&#45;<lb/> our people have accepted the custom of reciting the Kaddish&#44;<lb/> of distributing alms&#44; and making offerings for the maintenance<lb/> of the worship&#44; during the stated period.<lb/></p>  
            <p>I may&#44; not inappropriately I judge&#44; explain&#44; that the<lb/> &#34;Kaddish&#34; which is in the main an acknowledgment of<lb/> God&#39;s power to hasten the time when His Divine will rule<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>will be recognized throughout the world He created&#44;<lb/> an admission of our inability ever adequately to extol<lb/> His holy name&#44; and of His goodness on which alone our<lb/> welfare depends&#44; as in nearly all Chaldaic&#45;&#45;the language mostly spoken<lb/> by our ancestors in the days and country of its composition.  It has been<lb/> chosen&#44; because of its comprehensiveness&#44; as a substitute for the<lb/> recital of the whole&#44; or part of the Hebrew ritual&#44; which<lb/> every Israelite in the year of his mourning might not<lb/> have been competent to read aloud in public.  But to<lb/> entertain the idea that we do the spirit of the departed<lb/> pleasure by a hurried repetition of it&#44; and the absence of<lb/> acts of goodness and benevolence religiousness&#44; is a serious mistake.<lb/>  I hold that only a devout and intelligent rehearsing of<lb/> the Kaddish during twelve&#45;&#45;or eleven months&#44; as general usage will<lb/> have it&#45;&#45;accompanied invariably with deeds of self&#45;denial and benevolence&#44;<lb/> in honor to the memory of the dear ones that have gone hence&#44;<lb/> may be to them a cause of spiritual gratification.  But<lb/> if anything needs reform&#44; the prevailing habits in the time<lb/> of mourning surely demand it.  We must banish as<lb/> irrational and derogatory to our faith the thought that<lb/> a listless attendance at the Synagogue&#44; and the mumbled<lb/> utterance of an occasional invocation to the Deity&#44; is what<lb/> may draw the disembodied soul nearer to its Celestial Source.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Nor can the supplications made for the perfect rest of deceased<lb/> relatives&#44; gladden the latter&#44; when the hearts of the survivors<lb/> are enchained to worldly cravings and to selfishness.  The<lb/> institution of the Hashkabah&#44; as Jews of the Sephardic ritual call it&#44; or Haz&#45;<lb/>&#45;kareth Neshamoth&#44; as those of the Ashkenaz term it&#44; has an<lb/> ancient origin.  But its antiquity cannot ensure its efficacy&#44;<lb/> when so long as the object to be reached is ignored.  In the 12th chapter<lb/> of the 2d book of the Maccabees&#45;&#45;which I confess&#44; however&#44; to be<lb/> of uncertain authority&#45;&#45;we find that after the battle at<lb/> Jamn&#233;&#44; the adherents of Judah&#45;&#45;the lion&#45;hearted&#45;&#45;while about to bury their<lb/> brethren who had died in battle&#44; discovered in the sacks of<lb/> the slain things which the enemy had consecrated to idols.<lb/>  At that sight&#44; the faithful betook themselves to prayer&#44; en&#45;<lb/>&#45;treating the Lord that those who had departed from earth<lb/> in sin might meet forgiveness in heaven.  But the<lb/> Asmonean general exhorted all to avoid falling into the<lb/> same transgressions and&#44; having asked from each per&#45;<lb/>&#45;son an equal sum&#44; sent it to Jerusalem that expiatory<lb/> sacrifices might be offered.  I learn then that the pure conduct<lb/> of the living then and their deeds of piety must be joined<lb/> to their petitions for the deceased&#44; in order to procure the<lb/> latter ethereal exaltation.  So I have a right to interpret the teachings<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>of later Rabbis in connection with the opinion of their<lb/> predecessor&#44; the famous Akiba Ben Joseph.<lb/></p>
            <p>Those of our philosophers&#44; who&#44; in homage to the memory<lb/> of one so great&#44; have accepted his views&#44; reason thereupon<lb/> in a manner which to me&#44; appears sensible and satisfact&#45;<lb/>&#45;ory.  Joseph Albo&#44; noted principally for his opposition<lb/> to Maimonides the formulated creeds of Maimonides&#44; and who in his book<lb/> has reduced Jewish fundamental doctrines to three&#44; namely&#59; the<lb/> existence of a Creator&#44; an inspired Law revealed legislation&#44; and reward and punish&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment for human actions&#44; argues thus&#58; we all are naturally<lb/> wedded to habits we have long contracted and closely followed.  Such<lb/> feelings can be noticed even in infants.  For on being weaned<lb/> and supplied with more substantial and varied food&#44; a young<lb/> child will nevertheless crave and cry for its mother&#39;s milk.  And<lb/> there is scarcely any of us who has not experienced a degree<lb/> of uneasiness at a change of residence&#44; or of companions<lb/> and of surroundings&#44; though the change be for the better.<lb/>  Now&#58; the soul through its close association with the<lb/> body may receive a shock by the total entire separation.  Not<lb/>&#45;withstanding its thorough emancipation from the confinement<lb/> of a perishable tenement&#44; it may possibly feel somewhat<lb/> like a prisoner who&#44; in coming out of his cell&#44; cannot at<lb/> once face the bright sun and walk at its light steadily<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>and erect.  It takes sometime to accustom oneself<lb/> to any new mode of living.  The saying of the Tal&#45;<lb/>&#45;mudists that the disembodied spirit ascends and descends<lb/> for twelve months&#44; may allegorically signify the sen&#45;<lb/>&#45;timent I have just expressed.  But it is rational<lb/> to infer that in proportion to the control which the soul<lb/> has exercised&#44; by its elevated thoughts and lofty aspirations&#44;<lb/> over the body during their union&#44; so will be its facility to<lb/> leave behind the recollection of things mundane&#44; and enjoy<lb/> the companionship of the righteous blessed and the contemplation<lb/> of the Essence of Goodness.  On the contrary&#44; in the same ratio<lb/> as the soul was under the dominion of low cravings and<lb/> appetites&#44; so will its difficulty be to wring itself upward<lb/> to a purely ethereal existence.  Albo inclines to<lb/> think that a mighty struggle will ensue.  Devoid of<lb/> the means by which it formerly gratified long habits&#44; that<lb/> is&#44; deprived of the agency of the limbs&#44; the soul of the unright&#45;<lb/>&#45;eous will be at war with itself.  An intense hankering<lb/> after pleasures which can no more be satisfied&#44; and a<lb/> yearning for a bliss which it is yet unfit to enjoy&#44; will oc&#45;<lb/>&#45;casion torments severer than the cutting of sharp swords&#44; or<lb/> the burning of fire.  But the righteous man who&#44;<lb/> during a terrestrial existence was moderate in his desires&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>who learnt to subdue his passions&#44; who acted like a<lb/> servant knowing the character of his Master for justice<lb/> and mercy&#44; and striving to initiate Him&#44; so as to be<lb/> kept in a charge mutually agreeable&#44; such a man can&#45;<lb/>&#45;not be exposed to a contest harrowing to the soul.  He<lb/> had very night prepared here below for the change which<lb/> would take place above.  Seven days or a month to the<lb/> <sic>furtherest</sic> extent will suffice him to recover from the shock<lb/> of the separation&#44; and thenceforth the delights of a<lb/> new and higher existence will be shared and valued&#44; as<lb/> priceless treasures stored up by the Almighty Creator.<lb/>  That is the meaning which the Talmudists intend to convey<lb/> when they picture the different pleasures attending a life<lb/> hereafter&#44; and culminating with in the wearing of a crown<lb/> and basking in the splendour of the Divinity.  Material<lb/> is unavoidably the language they employ in their des&#45;<lb/>&#45;cription&#44; but under cover of similes and metaphors and similes lies a<lb/> fund of wisdom&#44; which claims our study and medi&#45;<lb/>tation.  But what has a greater title to our attention<lb/> is the lesson that the purer had been our conduct<lb/> the calmer and sweeter will be the passage be from<lb/> the mortal to the immortal.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Brethren.  In pursuance of a promise made in<lb/> my last lecture&#44; I have offered some slight information<lb/> on what one of our most celebrated Sages and one of our accredited philosophers have<lb/> advanced&#44; regarding the state of the soul in the world to<lb/> come.  I have simply brought before your minds understanding&#44; what<lb/> mine has assented to.  I do not urge its acceptance adoption<lb/> as infallible&#44; for what&#44; to me&#44; seems the most reason&#45;<lb/>&#45;able of conjunctures&#44; you may perhaps reject&#44; and obtain<lb/> your support from authorities equally great eminent as those<lb/> I have cited.  My aim&#44; however&#44; has not been to<lb/> secure your adhesion to this or that opinion in meal matters<lb/> of a metaphysical nature&#59; about particulars which must<lb/> always remain in the domains of speculation&#44; logical<lb/> perchance&#44; but still mere speculations.  I have rather<lb/> sought to confirm your belief in the truth of immortality&#44;<lb/> a spring of human virtues&#44; a fountain of consolation&#44; a flow&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing stream to whose placid water we trustingly commit<lb/> ourselves when weary of trials&#44; sure to be carried at length<lb/> to golden fields of joyous harvests.  And I have had also in<lb/> view the commending of a better method of evening our reverence<lb/> for the dear departed&#44; more sensible&#44; more beneficial to them and<lb/> and to us than that pursued heretofore by the multitude&#44; more<lb/> calculated than it the &#91;&#63;&#93; bare recital of an occasional revocation to edify&#44; exalt and ennoble our feelings.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>I now stop.  I shall declare well spent the hours<lb/> at during which I pondered on this and the other too two<lb/> subjects of my series&#44; if the little I was able to<lb/> say thereupon has strengthened the youths of my<lb/> congregation in the leading doctrines of our religion.  If&#44;<lb/> as they go forth treading a path often beset with<lb/> difficulties&#44; they will see God everywhere&#44; find His<lb/> unerring Guide in the uttterances enunciations of Sinai&#44; and derive<lb/> courage from the hope of a blissful genial transformation<lb/> into an angelic existence.  I may never rejoice in the<lb/> evidences of my teachings&#44; but I feel that every senti&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment of piety I shall have awakened&#44; every wish I I shall have excited to cast<lb/> off wrong and embrace right&#44; to abhor make falsehood and<lb/> hypocrisy odious and love honest and truth I shall have incited loveable&#44; such of those sentiments will be an advocate<lb/> in my behalf before the throne judgment seat of our<lb/> Creator&#44; our Father Legislator&#59; and the all&#45;saving God.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
