<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF32_3</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet></placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_3_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_3_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_3_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_3_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_3_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_3_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_3_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_3_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_3_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_3_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_3_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff32_3_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>7 pages on 3 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>A lecture for the three weeks<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Oh that my grief were thoroughly weighed&#44; and my &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> calamity laid in the balances together&#44; for&#44; now it would be<lb/> heavier than the sand of the sea&#44; therefore are my words confused.&#34;<lb/>  But however deep be the sorrow with which recent events<lb/> have furrowed my soul&#59; although to disburthen the weight&#44;<lb/> which&#44; like an incubus&#44; oppresses my whole being&#44; might<lb/> temporarily assuage the harrowing feelings I experience&#44; yet<lb/> I forbear giving vent to complaints which might ill&#45;<lb/>become this time and place.  Friends&#33;  It is not of my political<lb/> sympathies with the hapless country of my birth&#44; that I<lb/> shall discourse&#44; lest I transcend the limits assigned to my<lb/> vocation.  In silent solitude I shall bemoan the fate<lb/> of her&#44; which I mightily love&#44; though she has proved to my<lb/> brethren ever ungracious.  But I will raise a loud and<lb/> bitter cry to lament those of Israel&#44; who&#44; deluded by men&#45;<lb/>&#45;dacious lips offered their lives and substance solely to rivet<lb/> their chains.  From the bowels of the earth&#44; drunk with<lb/> their precious blood&#44; their spirits arise before my bewildered<lb/> mind&#44; and I hear a voice which exclaims &#34;O Thou who<lb/> art too pure to behold evil&#44; and canst not look on iniquity&#45;&#45;<lb/>why lookest Thou upon them that deal treacherously&#63;&#34;<lb/>  Alas&#33; my beloved hearers&#33; that these days which sadden our<lb/> hearts&#44; with the memory of our former national disasters&#44;<lb/> should also have been to us the herald of future tribulations&#33;  When<lb/> our eyes were hopefully turned towards the sea which had<lb/> already wasted over joyful tidings&#59; when anxiously2 we1<lb/> expected to learn that the hand which had robbed a<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>mother of her young&#44; had been for ever paralyzed&#44; we heard&#44;<lb/> with horror&#44; that that scourge of Israel has acquired more<lb/> virulence.  Hitherto its fierceness had been felt by a<lb/> few thousands of our unhappy brethren&#44; immediately exposed<lb/> to its flagellation&#59; henceforth it may tear the hearts together<lb/> with the flesh of tens of thousands.  &#34;Oh&#33; that my head<lb/> were waters and mine eyes a fountain of tears&#44; that I<lb/> might weep day and night for the slain of the daughter<lb/> of my people&#33;&#34;  Undauntedly had they entered the arena<lb/> to purchase with their blood the security for their<lb/> fellow&#45;believers.  Supported by so inspiring a hope&#44;<lb/> many had torn themselves away from all they held dear<lb/> on earth&#44; to brandish the sword of salvation&#59; tender mothers<lb/> had exhorted their sons to ennoble Judah&#39;s race in the<lb/> sight of the nations&#44; and by deeds of valor earn their freedom.<lb/>  And now they sit desolate and disconsolate.  &#34;Is there<lb/> a grief like their grief&#63;&#34;  They sacrificed the existence<lb/> of those they had tenderly nurtured and reared&#44; of those<lb/> they loved above themselves&#44; only to pamper the ambition<lb/> of traitors.  The bright prospects which had&#44; three<lb/> months since&#44; illumined the horizon of Israel&#44; had suddenly<lb/> vanished.  The seductive promises which throughout a<lb/> vast peninsula&#44; had made Jewish breasts leap with joy&#44;<lb/> have been ruthlessly violated&#59; nothing remains to comfort<lb/> them&#44; not even a shadow of glory&#44; for&#44; will history record<lb/> with honor the names of such&#44; whom the world regards<lb/> as aliens&#63;  Aye&#44; the spot where they fell victims<lb/> of perjury&#44; is unknown to all.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>No stone distinguishes these mortal remains from that<lb/> mas of mangled bodies heaped like carcasses&#44; in the<lb/> Italian charnel&#45;house.  No humble stone which a<lb/> mother&#44; a widowed wife&#44; or an orphan may bedew with<lb/> the sacred tears of undying affection&#33;  Say not&#44; my<lb/> friends&#33; that such are the necessary concomitants of all<lb/> wars&#44; for&#44; that painful thought may otherwise be<lb/> relieved under other circumstances by the reflection that a great and noble end was<lb/> achieved&#59; but&#44; whatever benefit may accrue from the sud&#45;<lb/>&#45;den termination of hostilities&#44; to my native land &#40;if any can<lb/> rationally be anticipated&#41; her Hebrew denizens will not<lb/> &#91;&#63;&#93; participate therein.  The sword of Damocles has been suspended over<lb/> their heads&#44; by the promotion of their arh arch&#45;foe.<lb/>  &#34;Oh that my head were waters&#44; and mine eyes a fountain<lb/> of tears&#44; that I might weep day and night for the<lb/> slain of the daughter of my people&#34;&#44; because &#34;when<lb/> I looked for good then evil came&#44; when I waited for light&#44;<lb/> there came darkness.&#34;  Fascinated by specious<lb/> appearances&#44; I had&#44; at times&#44; viewed in the struggle of<lb/> a freedom&#45;loving people nation&#44; the realization of my<lb/> ideal.  I imagined to see the monster of persecution<lb/> fall prostrate before the progress of civilization&#44; like Dagon<lb/> before the ark of the true God.  I had wheedled myself<lb/> into the belief that the incestuous coalition of Church and<lb/> state&#44; would be sundered by the stalwart arm which<lb/> was to hew down the stanchion of oppression&#44; and I<lb/> had then prognosticated days of <sic>tranquillity</sic> for the residue<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>of Judah&#44; until the redeemer shall come to Zion&#59; but I<lb/> awoke from that glowing vision&#44; to the sad reality of<lb/> approaching coils.  The bitter cup is not yet<lb/> to be removed from our lips&#59; an irritated Deity has<lb/> doomed us to drink it to its dregs.  Never&#44; my<lb/> beloved hearers&#44; has this <sic>woful</sic> season&#44; the anniversary<lb/> of Israel&#39;s first and second dispersion&#44; cast over my spirits<lb/> the gloom which now pervades them&#59; for&#44; whereas<lb/> in former years I sought some consolation in the remem&#45;<lb/>&#45;brance that there existed generous countries ready<lb/> to receive our exiles and offer them the choicest of<lb/> blessings&#45;&#45;liberty and equality&#59; now my agitated mind<lb/> detects but a disguised falsehood under the enunciation<lb/> of those glorious principles.  Liberty for the many&#44;<lb/> restrictive laws for the few&#59; equality for one caste<lb/> of citizens&#44; proscription for another.  Would that<lb/> this dismal picture were overdrawn&#44; but though I<lb/> fain would persuade myself that it is the offspring<lb/> of my perturbed thoughts&#44; daily occurrences will<lb/> manifest the contrary.  Wherefore ought we at this<lb/> mournful period&#44; to lament the desolation of our temple&#44;<lb/> our protracted captivity&#44; and unparallelled suffering.<lb/>  When the dreadful ninth of Ab&#44; arrives&#44; the day<lb/> in which twice hordes of barbarous nations <sic>levelled</sic><lb/> our glory with the earth&#44; every child of Israel ought in<lb/> fasting and humiliation to beseech Almighty<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>God to look pitifully on the flock of his pasture&#44;<lb/> which the wolves devour&#44; and speedily for his name&#39;s<lb/> sake gather them to his paternal fold.  Men<lb/> who pretend to read the times&#44; may discover the signs<lb/> of our national emancipation in the present boasted<lb/> enlightenment&#44; but verily I tell you&#44; that they are<lb/> false prophets.  Unless divine interposition<lb/> restores us to our pristine state&#44; the name of<lb/> Hebrew&#44; just as one of our doleful poets writes&#44; will<lb/> ever be <sic>synonimous</sic> with reproach.  But the<lb/> golden era promised by an <sic>inffabble</sic> Lord&#44; will never<lb/> dawn as long as we cling to the delinquencies which<lb/> have occasioned our dispersion.  While disunion and<lb/> enmity are rampant&#44; while a grovelling spirit sows<lb/> the seeds of discord&#44; to reap therefrom a petty dominion&#44;<lb/> both the hand of men and God will be against us&#44;<lb/> as it was against our fathers.  Brethren&#33;  I do<lb/> not wish to sadden your hearts&#44; but recent events portend<lb/> calamities to Israel&#39;s household&#59; Let us then&#44; like the<lb/> wayfarer&#44; who wraps his body envelops his mantle himself lightly around hisself<lb/> mantle mantle as the tempest approaches&#44; let us&#44; I say&#44; draw<lb/> closer to each other in mutual protection&#44; &#38; let us more&#45;<lb/>&#45;over encircle ourselves with the mantle which we donned in Horeb&#44;<lb/>&#45;&#45;our holy Torah&#45;&#45;&#44;and He who neither slumbers nor<lb/> sleeps&#44; may avert from us national sorrows&#44; for&#44; &#34;the<lb/> Lord will not cast us off for ever&#44; but though he has<lb/> caused us grief&#44; yet He will have mercy according to his abundant goodness&#34;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>O Lord&#33; have mercy upon us&#44; O Lord&#33; have mercy upon<lb/> us&#44; for we are exceedingly filled with contempt.  How<lb/> long shall the penalty of former trespasses be enforced<lb/> upon us&#63;  Hast Thou utterly rejected Judah&#44; hath thy<lb/> soul loathed Zion&#63;  Why hast Thou smitten us and Behold the city in which thy<lb/> there is no healing for us we looked for peace&#44; and have Divinity visibly dwelt&#44; trampled on by haughty and<lb/> us no good&#44; for the time of one&#44; and behold trouble unrelenting fanatics&#33;  Behold the servants who take<lb/> delight in her stones&#44; and revere her dust&#44; bow in<lb/> contrition near the sacred spot whence their sacrifices&#44;<lb/> like sweet savour&#44; ascended the heavens.  From one<lb/> end of the globe to its opposite end&#44; thy exiled children<lb/> turn devoutly towards the shrine of thy ancient oracles&#44;<lb/> and thrice daily pray for their restoration.  Although<lb/> their soul cleaveth unto the earth and they have been<lb/> sold like cattle to the slaughter&#44; yet they have not<lb/> forgotten Thee&#44; neither have they forsworn thy covenant.<lb/>  But for thy sake have they been killed continually&#44;<lb/> and have preferred <sic>opprobium</sic>&#44; to the abandonment<lb/> of thy law.  Awake to their help O God&#33; cast not2<lb/> them1 off for ever&#44; but speak comfortably to their<lb/> hearts&#44; cry unto them that their salvation is night<lb/> that their inequity is pardoned&#44; that Thou will be<lb/> a wall of fire round about them because of the enemy<lb/> and the oppressor&#44; and a glory in their midst for<lb/> ever and ever.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
