<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF4_5</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_5_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_5_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_5_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_5_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_5_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_5_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_5_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_5_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_5_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_5_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_5_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_5_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>For Sabbath Vayer&#225;<lb/>
                on the Haftorah.<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  We have&#44; this morning&#44; made the acquaintance of<lb/> two women of Israel.  Their positions in life are is unlike&#44; but<lb/> both of them are equally worthy of our esteem.  We shall know<lb/> them more intimately&#44; after having taken a mental survey<lb/> of the habitations they occupy.  In the dwelling of the one&#44; the<lb/> traces of poverty are everywhere discernible.  Gaunt visages<lb/> meet our eyes.  A widow and her two youthful sons are the<lb/> inmates of that humble abode dismal dreary spot place.  The appearance of the mother&#44;<lb/> betrays intensity of grief.  Destitution had followed bereavement.<lb/>  And now a calamity was is impending over her household&#44; the<lb/> thought of which harrows her very soul.  A pitiless<lb/> creditor demanded her two children&#44; as bondmen&#44; in payment of his<lb/> claims.  The hopes of a brighter future so soothing to her maternal heart will be<lb/> blighted.  Deprived of her only comfort&#44; she must will pine away<lb/> in solitude.  Her appeal to the courts of justice would<lb/> avail nothing.  The kingdom of Israel under whose rule<lb/> she lived&#44; had cast aside the merciful laws of the Mosaic code.<lb/>  It mattered not that according to the divine revelation&#44; no Hebrew<lb/> man could be permitted to be sold to servitude&#44; even for a short period of<lb/> time&#44; unless he had committed a high crime.  Those in<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>authority trampled on religion&#44; and no redress could be<lb/> obtained for wrongs suffered.  Since the unfortunate<lb/> schism&#44; in the days of Rehoboam&#44; which had divided the people<lb/> of God into two distinct sections&#44; the conduct of the princes of<lb/> the house of Israel encouraged a laxity of principles among all<lb/> classes.  The subjects vied with their monarchs in doing<lb/> inequity.  Therefore we hear Amos inveigh against that<lb/> corrupt kingdom&#44; because in it the righteous were enslaved<lb/> for the sake of money.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  But despite the<lb/> general depravity&#44; a few remained unpolluted.  They were<lb/> principally individuals who belonged to the school of the prophets.<lb/>  The merit of having founded that institution of sacred learning is<lb/> ascribed to Samuel.  That faithful servant of the Lord<lb/> sought&#44; in all likelihood&#44; to counteract by it the ill&#45;effects of<lb/> the abuse of power in which priests and high officials indulged.  For&#44; in<lb/> that school a rigid discipline taught self&#45;denial for the love<lb/> of God&#39;s word&#59; and while the minds of its attendants became elevated<lb/> by the cultivation of the arts of poetry and song&#44; abhorrence for ido&#45;<lb/>&#45;latry and idolaters was instilled into them.  That in the<lb/> course of ages degeneracy crept even into the holy precincts<lb/> of that establishment&#44; cannot be denied.  Nevertheless many<lb/> did issue from it&#44; fully armed to battle for the Lord.  Many who<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>braved the displeasure of potentates&#44; who preferred a<lb/> life of constant privations&#44; to the relinquishing of their mission.<lb/>  The history of which chronicles the recreancy of a Zedekiah<lb/> son of Canaanah&#44; recounts records also the undaunted demea&#45;<lb/>&#45;nour of a Micarah son of &#91;&#63;&#93;.  And we all have<lb/> read of Obadiah&#44; who jeopardized his existence by stealthily<lb/> feeding in a cave one hundred of the disciples of Samuel&#44;<lb/> whom the wicked Jezebel had doomed to destruction.<lb/>  Now&#44; my Brethren&#33; We may not choose to credit the legend<lb/> which represents the widow with two sons of our Haftorah&#44;<lb/> as the wife and children of the righteous man I have just mentioned&#59; but<lb/> we must believe that the deceased copartner of that Hebrew<lb/> woman&#44; who illustrated his fidelity to the principles imbibed<lb/> in the school of the prophets.  Addressing Elisha&#44; she<lb/> exclaimed in anguish of spirit.  &#34;Thy servant my husband is<lb/> dead&#44; and thou well knowest that thy servant did fear<lb/> the Lord&#34;  In her misery the memory of the upright religious conduct<lb/> he had followed&#44; was her solace.  For&#44; she felt assured that the<lb/> loving&#45;kindness of God will be shown to the offspring of those<lb/> who keep His covenant&#44; and observe His statutes in sincerity<lb/> of heart.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>She complained because of men&#39;s cruelty&#44; but she looked trustingly<lb/> for help to that beneficent Being who works wonders through<lb/> human agency.  Her faith proved her salvation.  The<lb/> sequel of my narrative is familiarly known.  A supernatural<lb/> deed performed by Elisha&#44; obtained for her ten&#45;fold more than<lb/> she needed to pay her heartless creditor.  Poverty was by2 a heavenly<lb/> power chased1 way to make room for competence and comfort.<lb/>  Dear hearers&#33;  It is not at all probable that any of my sisters within reach of my<lb/> voice&#44; have ever been so sadly situated as the widow of whom<lb/> I have spoken.  The dread of being constrained to <sic>yeild</sic> one&#39;s child&#45;<lb/>&#45;ren to slavery&#44; cannot&#44; thank God&#44; be experienced in this land<lb/> of freedom.  But some may at times have grieved by reason of<lb/> their inability to adequately provide for their young offspring.  Let<lb/> the faith which delivered a mother and her two orphaned sons&#44; be<lb/> their stay.  In that particular instance a miracle became was<lb/> necessary requisite&#44; because men had ceased to <sic>practise</sic> the merciful in&#45;<lb/>&#45;junctions of the Law.  In our age it would be unnecessary.<lb/>  The sufferings of the bereaved awaken the liveliest sympathies.<lb/>  A spirit of universal brotherhood which the religion of the Sinai<lb/> breathes&#44; stirs pervades is gradually stirring up the human breast.  Means are ceaselessly<lb/> resorted to to in order that sorrow may be alleviated&#44; and that<lb/> the hapless may not be exposed to want&#44; and despair shame.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> The spreading of the book of books among nations&#44; has offered a more com&#45;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>&#45;prehensive view of charity.  The promise made in that heavenly<lb/> volume to the upright&#44; has being fulfilled&#44; through the workings of real charity.<lb/>  &#91;&#63;&#93;&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>  &#34;The Lord will not suffer the soul of the righteous to famish.&#34;<lb/>  But let us now it is time we should turn our attention to the other object presented<lb/> to our view consideration.  In the dwelling of the woman of Israel&#44; who<lb/> residing at Shunem&#59; signs of affluence&#45;&#45;gratefully enjoyed&#45;&#45;<lb/> are visible.  The stranger receives in it a cordial welcome&#59;<lb/> and very often a man of venerable appearance will might be seen&#44; bend&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing his way thither to take enjoy a meal.  But the character which<lb/> distinguish that personage&#44; has become known to his generous<lb/> hostess.  It does not then suffice her any longer that the prophet<lb/> Elisha be a guest at her table.  He must be provided supplied<lb/> with a room in her habitation&#44; where he and his attendant<lb/> may remain at perfect ease.  She obtains her husband&#39;s consent&#44;<lb/> and a chamber is purposely built and suitably furnished.<lb/>  Such much consideration signal thoughtful kindness&#59; so peculiar an instance of hospitable<lb/> reception&#44; arouses in the man of God a strong desire to si&#45;<lb/>&#45;gnify by some act his appreciation and thankfulness.  He<lb/> therefore inquires whether his influence with the King or the<lb/> general in chief might not promote her interest and relieve<lb/> him&#44; in part&#44; of his indebtedness.  Mark well the answer&#44;<lb/> my respected sisters&#33;  &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;I dwell among my<lb/> own people&#34;.  How simple&#44; and how expressive withal&#33;<lb/>  But I verily believe it is as rare a reply&#44; as rare were the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>virtues of the woman who gave it.  Many&#44; a great many<lb/> would gladly have accepted the offer.  Just think&#58; if I being<lb/> on familiar terms with crowned heads&#59; of to &#91;&#63;&#93; in the same<lb/> circle with the highest kin magnates of the land.  What bright pros&#45;<lb/>&#45;pects&#33;  To bask in the sun&#45;shine of royal favors.  To be<lb/> numbered among a privileged few.  But those anticipations<lb/> at which the hearts of thousands of women would have swelled<lb/> immeasurably&#44; had no charm for our modest Shunamite.<lb/>  She had no ambition to step beyond her own sphere.  Let it<lb/> not be imagined that her preference for a life of simplicity<lb/> emanated from a consciousness of her emptiness for a loftier<lb/> station.  No&#44; for&#44; Holy Writ styles her &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;A great<lb/> woman&#34;; and her whole course as described in our Haftorah<lb/> and in a subsequent chapters proves her intelligent&#44; self&#45;re&#45;<lb/>&#45;liant and sagacious.  But she wished to continue in her position&#44;<lb/> because it enabled her to do good unostentatiously and with much great<lb/> efficacy.  She set no value upon the acquaintance of rulers<lb/> and princes&#44; because she loved her home&#44; and the pure joy it<lb/> affords.  And she would not risk barter them for the fleeting pleasures<lb/> attended with heart&#45;burnings&#44; and for pleasures which breed extravagance and<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>irregularity of habits.  A noble type of a Hebrew<lb/> wife.  So&#44; at least&#44; I consider it.  Others&#44; however&#44; look there&#45;<lb/>&#45;upon in a different tight.  To lose the opportunity of<lb/> shining among people of high tone&#44; they regard a sheer folly.<lb/>  To expect&#44; they say&#44; that the ladies of our days will share the<lb/> ideas held by the women of scores of centuries ago&#44; is to<lb/> ignore the changes which society has undergone.  Neither<lb/> the manners nor the mode of living of the ancients would suit<lb/> our times&#44; and they who would attempt to imitate them such&#44;<lb/> would deservedly expose themselves to ridicule.  Why<lb/> then propose intimate that the retiring habits of our mothers might safely becomingly be followed<lb/> up by their daughters&#63;....&#91;&#63;&#93;&#44; my friends&#33; incited by<lb/> a wish to condemn or censure I would show how a blind<lb/> adherence to fictitious rules made by society&#44; has tarnished<lb/> much of the lustre of the Jewish character.  I would prove<lb/> that if some of my sisters in faith had&#44; like the Sunamite&#44;<lb/> answered to the promptness of feminine vanity &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;I dwell among my own people&#44;&#34; their homes would<lb/> now be happier.  But it was not my intention design to utter<lb/> denunciations.  I felt interested in the lesson of the<lb/> prophets designated for this Sabbath&#44; and I thought it might<lb/> not be altogether unprofitable for you to listen to my some<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>explanatory remarks.  My task is preformed.  It rests<lb/> with you to judge whether my efforts have been advantageously<lb/> or uselessly p employed.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
