<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF4_8</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1893" source="" attested="yes">1893</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_8_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_8_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_8_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_8_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_8_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_8_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_8_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_8_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_8_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_8_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_8_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_8_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_8_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_8_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_8_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_8_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>An exegetical lecture on Vaer&#225; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  You may have heard both Hebrews and Gentiles<lb/> repeatedly ask&#58; &#34;How could the King of Egypt resolve<lb/> to loosen the chains that bound Israel&#44; if he was not<lb/> the master of his own actions&#63;  Do we not read<lb/> in the Scriptures that God had hardened Pharaoh&#39;s<lb/> heart&#63;  Was he not then a tool in the hand of<lb/> the artificer&#63;  How could he alter his course&#44; when<lb/> the means by which he might accomplish the task&#44;<lb/> were withheld from him&#63;  To solve these im&#45;<lb/>&#45;portant questions&#44; it is necessary to understand&#44; how a<lb/> sinful being can atone for his misdeeds&#44; and propitiate<lb/> the grace of God.  When man looks back<lb/> on his past conduct and feels that he has acted<lb/> in opposition to the will of the Almighty&#59; when<lb/> this retrospective examination awakens self&#45;reproach<lb/> and a strong desire to amend the evil done&#59; when<lb/> forgiveness is sincerely petitioned for&#44; and righteousness<lb/> becomes the highest aspiration of the once fallen creature&#44;<lb/> he then can be called a true penitent&#44; for of him Eze&#45;<lb/>&#45;kiel says &#34;when the wicked man turneth away<lb/> from his wickedness that he hath committed.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>and doth that which is lawful and right&#44; he shall<lb/> save his soul alive&#44; because he considerth and turneth<lb/> away form his transgressions that he hath committed&#44;<lb/> he shall surely live&#44; he shall not die.&#34;  Mark&#44;<lb/> my Brethren&#33; &#34;because he considereth&#44; he turneth away&#34;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  his repentance is not the effect<lb/> of fear&#59; nor does the increase of suffering compel<lb/> him to relinquish his sinful habits&#44; but compunction<lb/> actuates him.  He considers that the path he has<lb/> trodden&#44; is hated by the Lord&#44; and he gladly avoids it.<lb/>  But there are men who will desist from sinning&#44;<lb/> but who will not never repent.  Not because<lb/> they have not been endowed with freedom of will&#44;<lb/> but because they misapply that divine gift.<lb/>  Such are those who deny God.  Those of whom our<lb/> Sages have written &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;the impious even on the verge of death will not<lb/> repent.&#34;  They refuse to admit their accounta&#45;<lb/>&#45;bility to a higher authority&#44; and how can they discover<lb/> in their actions anything reprehensible&#63;  Should<lb/> one endeavour to withdraw them from their sinful<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>way&#44; he would only succeed in calling down upon<lb/> himself their ill&#45;will.  They do not acknowledge<lb/> a Supreme Ruler of the universe&#44; and how could<lb/> the admonitions of a human instructor find access<lb/> into their hearts&#63;  His words will appear un&#45;<lb/>&#45;meaning&#59; his denunciations will excite their derision.<lb/>  Were he even so supernaturally gifted&#44; that he could<lb/> confirm his teaching by miracles&#44; the unbelievers<lb/> might marvel&#44; but still persist in their incredulity.<lb/>  Their corrupt minds would fancy to discover in the<lb/> wonders they witness&#44; the effect of some natural causes&#44;<lb/> which a dexterous hand knows how to apply.<lb/>  For&#44; to draw such an inference would appear to<lb/> them more sensible than to arrive at the conclusion<lb/> that an Almighty Being has given to2 nature existence1<lb/> by his immeasurable wisdom&#44; and he can by the<lb/> same wisdom&#44; invert the laws of nature&#44; when necessary<lb/> to teach mankind justice and truth.<lb/></p>
            <p>Should the miracles that the unbelievers behold&#44;<lb/> affect them personally with great severity&#59; should<lb/> a life of ease&#44; change through them into one of<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>bitter treats&#44; the sufferers may seem humbled&#44; but<lb/> their subdued appearance is not the consciousness of<lb/> guilt&#59; it is the result of the extreme pain they endure.<lb/>  For&#44; no sooner shall it have abated&#44; than they will<lb/> relapse into their former habits.  They will charge them&#45;<lb/>&#45;selves with cowardice&#44; and obdurately follow again<lb/> an evil course.<lb/></p>
            <p>Now&#44; my hearers&#44; what I have said in plain language&#44;<lb/> that I might be well understood&#44; will furnish every one of<lb/> you with a ready answer for him who might cavil<lb/> about the causes of Pharoah&#39;s obstinacy.<lb/></p>
            <p>God&#44; before whose vision the future must necessarily<lb/> be open as the present&#44; knew that the Ruler of<lb/> Mizraim would not <sic>yeild</sic> of his own accord to the request<lb/> of Moses.  And this fact He communicated to his<lb/> inspired servant at the outset&#44; when He asked him<lb/> to assume the mission of liberating Israel.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;I know that the king of<lb/> Egypt will not suffer you to go&#44; unless by a strong<lb/> hand.&#34;  Repeated chastisements of a fearful<lb/> nature&#44; might at last force him into an unwilling<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>compliance&#59; yet he would cling to his errors.<lb/>  His mind and that of his subjects would remain<lb/> unimproved.  But the Almighty who would<lb/> teach all coming generations that tyranny is a<lb/> hateful sin&#44; hardened the heart of Pharoah&#44; that<lb/> he might endure what he could not have naturally<lb/> borne any longer&#44; until he acknowledged his crime<lb/> and the justice of the divine decree.  For even<lb/> so we hear him exclaim after the <sic>inflinction</sic> of the<lb/> eighth plague &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;I have sinned against<lb/> the Lord your God and against you.&#34;  But<lb/> contrast&#44; my Brethren&#33; this utterance with the<lb/> response he made to the first demand of Moses.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> he then arrogantly said &#34;Who is the Lord&#44; that I shall<lb/> hearken unto his voice to send Israel free&#44; I know not<lb/> this Lord&#44; neither will I let Israel go&#34;; implying that<lb/> he could not believe in the existence of an avenging<lb/> God whose ears were open to the cry of those he tyrannized<lb/> over&#44; and that he could not so be daunted by threats&#44;<lb/> as to give liberty to a race of men whose toils enriched his land.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>And if you will moreover consult the Hebrew text you<lb/> will perceive&#44; as I once before explained at large&#44; that<lb/> not until the sixth plague&#45;&#45;that of the boils&#45;&#45;<lb/> had been brought upon Egypt&#44; does the phrase &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;the Lord hardened the heart of Pharoah&#34;&#44; occurs.<lb/>  During all the preceding strokes we read &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Pharoah&#39;s heart hardened&#34; or &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Pharoah<lb/> made his heart obdurate&#34; and similar expressions.<lb/>  But in addition to this fast&#44; proving that the su<lb/> <sic>stubborness</sic> of the king of Myraim was for a long<lb/> period occasioned by his inherent wickedness&#44;<lb/> the concurrent testimony of history shows that it<lb/> was so generally understood and admitted by the people<lb/> of ancient days.  Thus&#44; when the ark of the Lord was cap&#45;<lb/>&#45;tured by the Philistines&#44; and they desired to return it<lb/> with tokens of repentance&#44; they were exhorted to do<lb/> so by their priests in the following language &#34;Why will<lb/> ye harden your heart&#44; as the Egyptians and Pharoah<lb/> did hea harden their heart&#33;&#34;  Yes&#44; the unbending<lb/> will of the King of Myriam made him stand a series of disastrous<lb/> events&#44; which would have broken the spirit of any<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>one less persistent in evil rather than loosen the chains of his bondsmen but when total ruin<lb/> stared in his face&#44; and he would have <sic>yeilded</sic> to avert<lb/> it&#44; then a superhuman strength was given him<lb/> that he might receive the full measure of his<lb/> iniquities.  Accordingly we read in the lesson of this<lb/> Sabbath &#34;For now I might have stretched forth my<lb/> hand&#44; and smitten thee and thy people with pestilence&#44;<lb/> and thou wouldst be cut off from the earth&#44; and but in<lb/> very deed for this cause have I raised thee up&#44; for to show<lb/> in thee my power&#44; and that my name might be declared<lb/> throughout all the earth&#34;.  Twofold was the object<lb/> which the universal Judge would compass by hardening<lb/> the heart of Pharaoh&#59; firstly&#44; He would continue as He<lb/> had begun to suit the punishment to the nature of the<lb/> crime committed &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  The water of the Nile had<lb/> been redeemed with the blood of innocent babes&#44; therefore<lb/> it ran blood for seven consecutive days&#44; to the sorrow<lb/> of all the Egyptians.  The latter sought to extend and<lb/> <sic>embelish</sic> their country by the hardship of a whole race<lb/> of men&#44; therefore was their country laid waste by<lb/> vile reptiles.  They had bowed their head at the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>throne of fulsome objects&#44; they were therefore tormented<lb/> by loathsome objects insects.  They had inhumanly torn<lb/> the flesh of the offspring of Jacob&#44; therefore were<lb/> they torn by ferocious beasts.  They had dispossessed Israel<lb/> of what their ancestor Joseph had legally acquired&#44;<lb/> therefore their own riches consisting of herd &#38; flock was consumed by a pestilence.<lb/>  They had denied God a power over nature&#44; therefore He<lb/> changed its order that they might be chastised by a substance<lb/> the lightest in nature&#44; even the soot of the furnace.  And<lb/> when their pertinacious will began to flag He lent it<lb/> vigour that they might witness not only his boundless<lb/> power&#44; but the justice of his ordinances&#44; the heavenly<lb/> compassion He bestows on the oppressed&#44; and the destruction<lb/> He reserves for the oppressors.  Secondly&#58; He would<lb/> teach generations yet unborn&#44; that He alone is everlasting&#44;<lb/> all&#45;mighty and all&#45;wise&#59; for when they shall<lb/> be told of the <sic>marvellous</sic> deeds wrought in Egypt&#59;<lb/> how a land on which the heavens never rain was<lb/> ravaged by violent hail&#44; how the locust that had<lb/> never before visited the Egyptian coast&#44; turned that<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>fertile province into a barren soil&#59; how the sky where<lb/> the Sun reigns in all its brightness was impenetrably<lb/> darkened for three consecutive days&#59; how in one night<lb/> those who had embittered the lives of the first&#45;born<lb/> children of God&#59; saw death cut off their own first&#45;<lb/>born&#44; they shall learn that as clay in the potter&#39;s<lb/> hand&#44; so is all mankind is the hand of their<lb/> great Maker&#59; that He judges the universe with righteous&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness&#44; and people with rectitude &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> that if he allows the wicked to live&#44; it is to accomplish<lb/> thereby some ultimate good.  If he calls hence the pious<lb/> in the spring of life&#44; it is to shield them under the wings of<lb/> his mercy&#44; against the day of wrath&#59; that the unworthy<lb/> may long enjoy his bountiful gifts&#59; but their latter end<lb/> will be endurable misery&#44; that his faithful ones<lb/> may bear trials and persecution&#44; but interminable a<lb/> glory which is never obscured awaits them.  Such&#44; my<lb/> dear hearers&#33; was the design of the Almighty when He<lb/> hardened the heart of Pharaoh&#44; and delivered us from slavery&#44;<lb/> and such lessons it is our duty to instill into the minds<lb/> of our children.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>But you will ask&#58; &#34;&#91;Hebrew&#93;&#34; Who stood in the<lb/> counsel of the Lord&#63;&#44; that he may tell us with cer&#45;<lb/>&#45;tainty why events which appear to us as clashing<lb/> with our ideas of justice happen in the world&#63;  No one&#44;<lb/> not even his inspired messengers could explain to us<lb/> what only pure spirits can comprehend&#44; but when<lb/> our own history&#44; and the laws of nature attest the<lb/> wisdom&#44; the benignity&#44; and the long&#45;suffering of<lb/> the Most&#45;High God&#44; should we not argue from them<lb/> that even what is too recondite for our thoughts<lb/> springs from a fountain of goodness and mercy&#63;<lb/>  Should we not put on the armour of faith the armour<lb/> of faith&#44; and instead of destroying the fence of our<lb/> mind by investigations too audacious&#44; meekly petition<lb/> the Lord&#44; like the Royal shepherd &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;O God&#33; send Thy light and Thy truth that they might<lb/> may guide me&#63;&#34;  We will&#44; my friends&#33;  Like our fathers<lb/> who believed in the Lord&#44; when crushed to the earth with<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>unutterable afflictions&#44; we will believe in Him&#44; &#91;&#63;&#93;<lb/> to his commands&#44; and hope in await for his temporal and<lb/> eternal salvation now and evermore.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
