<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF3_13</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_13_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_13_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_13_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_13_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_13_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_13_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_13_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_13_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_13_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_13_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_13_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_13_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>In behalf of the Alliance<lb/>
                for the Sabbath before Purim.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  It is the Sabbath preceding the<lb/> joyful feast&#44; principally instituted to renew<lb/> friendship by mutual gifts&#44; and to please<lb/> Israel&#39;s God by being gracious to the poor.<lb/>  In a circular which I have received from the Presi&#45;<lb/>&#45;dent of that section of the &#34;Union of American Congre<lb/>gations&#44;&#34; called the Board of Delegates on civil and<lb/> religious rights&#44; the attendants at this Synagogue<lb/> are recommended to hallow the forthcoming occasion&#44;<lb/> by contributions donations to the Alliance Isarelite Univer&#45;<lb/> selle.  To explain what that assocaition means&#44;<lb/> and what its claims are&#44; would be to say that<lb/> which has been said on pulpits and written<lb/> in journals again and again.  A child<lb/> has heard before this that an organization looking aiming<lb/> to at the protection of Jews&#44; is located in the capital<lb/> of France&#44; and has it branches wherever our people<lb/> congregate.  But not all seem to<lb/> be acquainted with the circumstance that a branch<lb/> of it exists in Philadelphia&#44; and is in direct com&#45;<lb/>&#45;munication with the parent society&#44; and that therefore<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Philadelphia Israelites act independently of<lb/> the representative body which has reminded us<lb/> of our duty.  Indeed&#44; judging from the num&#45;<lb/>&#45;ber of subscribers and donors&#44; one would think<lb/> that in a population of ten or twelve thousand&#44;<lb/> only a very small fraction of it is aware of the<lb/> fact which I have just stated.  Yet&#44; I hold<lb/> that every Jew and Jewess ought to know it&#44; and<lb/> knowing it ought yearly to remit two Dollars&#44; and<lb/> each returning Purim a gift which can be spared<lb/> without stealing for by reason of it one&#39;s own family.<lb/></p>
            <p>My advocacy of the Alliance is not the outgrowth<lb/> of an enthusiasm&#44; which stirring events awaken&#44; but<lb/> which dies off when the existing causes have somewhat subsided.<lb/>  It is the result of serious&#44; even painful reflections.<lb/>  I love Israel for its heroic sacrifice on the<lb/> altar of Monotheism.  Had my people become<lb/> Christian where the creed in the Trinity prevails&#44;<lb/> and Mohammedan in countries where Islamism is<lb/> dominant&#44; the suffering it bears would long since<lb/> have come to an end.  The Jew has preferred<lb/> what no other nation under the sun has ever chosen&#45;&#45;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>stripes and public contempt to a change of<lb/> religious principles.  But who can deny that<lb/> the effect of deep humiliation has been ignorance<lb/> and a moral retrogression&#63;  Joyfully as I admitting<lb/> that the evil is not so desperate as to baffle the at&#45;<lb/>&#45;tempt of rooting it out&#59; gladly acknowledging that<lb/> only where persecution has been systematically car&#45;<lb/>&#45;ried on by governments&#44; and has&#44; in consequence&#44; been<lb/> continual and unrelenting&#44; only then the Jew has<lb/> sunk low&#44; still a momentous question presses us.<lb/>  Whoever wishes for the redemption of brethren enslaved<lb/> in fetters of degradation&#44; and for the vindication of a pure Judaism&#44;<lb/> must aid in towards the solution of that weighty question.<lb/>  By what means shall a new spirit be infused<lb/> into the Jew whom deadening influences have made<lb/> incapable of manly thoughts and vigorous deeds&#63;<lb/>  I answer&#58; by education&#59; education unhampered by<lb/> the prejudices which adverse circumstances have<lb/> fostered&#59; education broad and far&#45;reaching&#44; education&#44;<lb/> secular not less than religious.  If any<lb/> of us has ever doubted the necessity of an extensive<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>instruction far beyond that of <sic>rudimental</sic> Hebrew&#44;<lb/> recent incidents must have corrected his false<lb/> impressions.  We were brought face to face<lb/> with an emigration&#44; which has disclosed a state of<lb/> general decay decline.  Oppressive Russia has for centuries<lb/> compelled a seclusion that was attended with nar&#45;<lb/>&#45;rowness of ideas and occasionally with indications of semisavageness.  Still&#44;<lb/> what we have seen in the Jew of Northern Europe&#44;<lb/> we would witness&#44; in a worse form&#44; in our brethren<lb/> of Northern Africa&#44; if language and habits did not<lb/> debar an influx from that quarter of the world into<lb/> America.  The sight might be perhaps more star&#45;<lb/>&#45;tling owing to the results of a more brutal persecution.<lb/></p>
            <p>Six months ago the Alliance commissioned an intelli&#45;<lb/>&#45;gent Israelite to go to Fez&#44;&#45;&#45;a city which during<lb/> the middle ages had givne our race eminent scholars.<lb/>  That coreligionist was to ascertain by personal in&#45;<lb/>&#45;spection the condition of the Jewish population in<lb/> that city of Morocco.  After having accomplished<lb/> his task&#44; the commissioner sent a report to the cen&#45;<lb/>&#45;tral committee at Paris&#44; from which I gathered<lb/> the information that I am about briefly to set before my hearers.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Fez is divided into new and old.  The old is<lb/> inhabited by over one hundred thousand Mussulmans&#44;<lb/> some among whom have become civilized by having<lb/> <sic>travelled</sic> in Europe and America&#44; and having learnt<lb/> commerce and letters.  Others&#44; who remain there sta&#45;<lb/>&#45;tionary&#44; are lazy&#44; illiterate and fanatical.  Very few<lb/> Israelites however can be found in that section of the town&#44;<lb/> and as they are principally merchants&#44; they come<lb/> in contact exclusively with the best portion better class of the<lb/> population and are receive a kindly treatment.<lb/></p>
            <p>The new Fez&#44; which contains the palace of the<lb/> emperor&#44; has also the &#34;Mellah&#34;&#44; or Ghetto of the<lb/> Jews.  Nothing can be lower&#44; nothing can be<lb/> more calculated to rob man of his dignity than<lb/> the state of abjection which our people have there<lb/> to endure.  They are obliged to walk barefooted.<lb/>  In winter&#44; when the roads continue for months<lb/> in mud and filth&#44; the wretched brethren can scarcely<lb/> carry themselves from place ot place in quest of a livelihood without plunging<lb/> a knee deep into the mire.  In summer&#44; their feet<lb/> blister under the rays of a sun which nearly scorches<lb/> the ground.  This barbarous rule is often the cause of<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p><sic>of</sic> severe diseases to those who must obey it.<lb/>  The &#34;Mellah&#34; comprises a number of buildings<lb/> three or four stories high&#44; divided into what New&#45;<lb/>&#45;Yorkers would call &#34;flats.&#34;  As many as thirty<lb/> families will sometime be huddled up in such a<lb/> building.  The consequences may be well need not be told&#59; they can easily be imagined.<lb/>  Of the fifteen or twenty thousand Jewish residents&#44;<lb/> a small number are in easy circumstances&#44; enga&#45;<lb/>&#45;ging in foreign traffic&#44; and keeping large stores&#59;<lb/> the most follow different trades&#44; and mechanical pur&#45;<lb/>&#45;suits&#44; earning barely enough for their daily support&#44; while very many live altogether on charity.<lb/></p>
            <p>The character of the Jew is generally that of a timid&#44;<lb/> servile man&#44; destitute of knowledge&#44; except that<lb/> of rudimental Hebrew and the history of the Bible.<lb/>  The character of the Jewess is that of a woman reared<lb/> in ignorance&#44; hence submissive to man&#39;s will and<lb/> whims.  She is married&#44; with or without her consent&#44;<lb/> in childhood&#44; and not infrequently divorced and married again<lb/> before she has fully grown up.  Syangogues are plenti&#45;<lb/>&#45;ful&#44; but decorum is wanting absent.  Schools are abundant&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>but teachers few and unequal to their all important<lb/> charge.<lb/>
                Such is the picture drawn by the <sic>traveller</sic>&#44; and of which I have given the outline.  It is not flattering&#44; yet it is<lb/> one out of the many&#44; &#40;Alas&#33; too many&#41; which might<lb/> be set to view and shock our feelings.  But we<lb/> should know how far Jewish existences is being cankered&#44;<lb/> so as to apply the proper remedies.  In order<lb/> to lift up our brother above his degraded self&#44; we<lb/> must instruct him in the spirit of the scriptures&#44;<lb/> in the language of the country he lives in&#44; in the arts and<lb/> sciences of modern times.  In order to force raise up our sister<lb/> in faith from the sink of debasement into which<lb/> she has been lowered&#44; we must lead her by the hand&#44;<lb/> as it were&#44; to places where she will learn that God<lb/> intended her to nurture her offspring not bodily alone&#44;<lb/> but morally and mentally.  Gentilism&#44; whether it<lb/> be Christianity or Mohammedanism will always despair<lb/> the cringing Jew&#44; who bares the his back to the lash&#44;<lb/> because he is devoid of that knowledge which gives character<lb/> and a dignified bearing.  To impart that is our bounden<lb/> duty&#44; and then&#44; only then we shall have acted justly toward<lb/> our brother&#44; and have vindicated our glorious religion.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>That mission the Alliance has assumed.  It will<lb/> plant better schools in Fez&#44; as it has raised established them<lb/> in other African cities&#44; and in Asia&#44; and in Europe.<lb/>  But its one thousand seven million thousand &#38; 300 pupils should be increased to over<lb/> one million within this year.  How much have the free&#44; intelligent enlightened<lb/> and wealthy Hebrews of America exerted themselves to&#45;<lb/>&#45;wards the accomplishing of that object&#63;  Through&#45;<lb/>&#45;out the Union&#44; Philadelphia and <sic>Pittsburg</sic> are<lb/> the two cities in which branches of the parent<lb/> society exist.  The list of our own subscribers shows<lb/> now two hundred and forty nine names&#44; representing<lb/> less than five hundred Dollars to be annually remitted<lb/> to an organization encircling almost the entire<lb/> globe&#44; and whose continuance unhappy circumstances<lb/> have made indispensably essential to Judaism.<lb/></p>
            <p>But not to complain have I come to day.  To secure<lb/> tokens of a warm sympathy for a grand cause have I have<lb/> spoken.  Brethren.  It is the Sabbath before Purim.<lb/>  Let not the ensuing week elapse&#44; without your having<lb/> sent a gift present to the Alliance.  The treasurer Simon<lb/> Muhr&#44; or myself&#44; will be happy to receive and publicly<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>to acknowledge what your hearts prompt you<lb/> to offer fraternally on the joyful season&#44; which<lb/> I wish may bring to you all contentment and peace. and happiness.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
