<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF13_3</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_3_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_3_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_3_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_3_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_3_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_3_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_3_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_3_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_3_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_3_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_3_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_3_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>3d lecture on Immortality.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  When last Fall I announced my in&#45;<lb/>tention to deliver a course of lectures on God&#44; Reve&#45;<lb/>&#45;lation and Immortality&#44; I foresaw that the difficulty<lb/> of the subjects I had chosen&#44; and the necessity<lb/> of presenting&#44; every now and then&#44; questions of the<lb/> day which might be instructive and of interest&#44;<lb/> would occasion intervals between our lecture of the<lb/> series and the next in order.  Still&#44; I expressed<lb/> the hope&#44; that those intervals would not be very too<lb/> frequent&#44; nor very far apart.  I had anticipated<lb/> concluding the course before Passover arrived.  But<lb/> national&#44; Congregational and personal causes prevented<lb/> the realization of my expectations.  They led me<lb/> to speak oftener than I had supposed on topics<lb/> having no connection with those which belong to<lb/> the promised series.  But the season is now far advanced.<lb/>  Before summer sets in I b must bring to a termina&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion what I have left unfinished.<lb/></p>
            <p>In resuming my task and proceeding further with the third<lb/> subject&#44; I wish to recall to your minds the arguments I adden brought<lb/> forward in support of to the belief in a life hereafter.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>I quoted the Bible as due to its sanctity&#44; but I<lb/> laid more stress on the suggestions of human Reason.  I tried<lb/> to disprove the theory of some materialists that what<lb/> we call &#34;the soul&#34; is nought else than the workings of our nervous sys&#45;<lb/>&#45;tem.  I said that our sentiments&#44; our aspirations&#44; our the<lb/> lofty conceptions of which we are capable cannot<lb/> arise form any physical sensation&#44; that the invi&#45;<lb/>&#45;sible Spirit stirring within us must of necessity be a separate<lb/> entity independent of our body&#44; that it must there&#45;<lb/>&#45;fore live when its agents&#45;&#45;our limbs&#45;&#45;shall dissolve<lb/> into their primitive elements&#44; and that God who<lb/> breathed it into us can and will transform it<lb/> into a higher existence.  But as the indes&#45;<lb/>&#45;tructibility of the soul cannot be shown by the<lb/> sense of vision or of touch&#44; we may&#44; for want of any<lb/> clearer test&#44; illustrate our point by way of analogy.<lb/>  When we see that not a single atom in the universe can ever<lb/> be reduced to absolute nothingness&#44; it is logical to<lb/> infer that the noblest of God&#39;s creations&#45;&#45;the Soul&#45;&#45;will<lb/> not be annihilated.  This momentous question which has frequently often<lb/> engaged the attention of learned Israelites&#44; has been treated<lb/> in our days in a book of quite small in size&#44; but fraught with instruction&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>and which a book&#44; the little of which that I could well understand&#44; I have found exceedingly useful.  A Polish<lb/> Jew&#44; noted for his works on Astronomy&#44; metaphysics&#44; and<lb/> mathematics is the author.  H. S. Slomimsky argues<lb/> from the eternal laws which govern matter to those which<lb/> are&#44; most likely&#44; to govern the spirit.  I will re&#45;<lb/>produce a few and the very simplest among the many<lb/> and profound thoughts which he advances with consum&#45;<lb/>&#45;mate abilities&#44; and a perfect mastery of the Hebrew lan&#45;<lb/>&#45;guage.<lb/></p>
            <p>A chemist may decompose a substance into invisible<lb/> parts&#44; still not the smallest particle of it will have<lb/> been lost.  A piece of pure silver may be made so<lb/> to mix with sulphuric acid as to leave no trace of itself&#59;<lb/> yet it exists in the sulphur&#44; and the chemist can<lb/> draw it out entirely by a process known to him.  We all&#44;<lb/> without being skilled in sciences&#44; may alter the form of<lb/> things in nature.  We all may change fluids in a<lb/> manner which will seem to have deprived them of<lb/> existence&#44; but they are only transformed&#44; for the time<lb/> being&#44; into another substance.  Thus&#44; by the application<lb/> of heat&#44; water will turn into steam&#44; but this will<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>change again into moisture&#44; which spreading<lb/> through the air atmosphere will become fog or clouds and then<lb/> rain&#44; or fluid&#44; as at first.  Nor is it too water<lb/> alone that undergoes those transformations and suffer<lb/> no waste&#44; but also whatever is capable of being<lb/> dissolved into a liquid.  For instance&#44; if quick silver is<lb/> heated to a temperature will which will make cause it to rise<lb/> upward like vapors&#44; when it meets a current of cold<lb/> air it will come down in the shape of small balls of<lb/> quick&#45;silver&#44; as originally.  Sometime the substance<lb/> so decomposed by heat will be absorbed into another sub&#45;<lb/>&#45;stance and will assume a new shape and unalterable form.  For example&#58;<lb/> A large wax candle after burning a while will seem<lb/> to dwindle away and get entirely consumed&#59; yet in<lb/> reality the fire has produced no such a thing as a<lb/> consumption.  We can prove it as follows&#58; Let us put that a candle inside of within a<lb/> glass vessel lightly closed on all sides&#44; but filled<lb/> before hand with enough air to make the candle burn&#59;<lb/> let us then weigh the glass&#44; after the candle is gone alto&#45;<lb/>&#45;gether&#44; and we shall find that its weight is equal<lb/> to that of its own self and of the wax candle which<lb/> had been put inside.  The air in the vessel will<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>have grown heavier&#59; that is&#44; the candle has mixed<lb/> with it and with the fine powder and moisture at the<lb/> bottom of the glass.  Again&#58; nothing appears so<lb/> annihilating in its process like as Decay in vegetation.  We have thou&#45;<lb/>&#45;sands of diverse species of productions which at one time are in<lb/> bloom and fresh&#44; and then are withered and rotten.<lb/>  The spring&#45;sea works on fruits and flowers and they thrive&#59; when<lb/> winter comes arrives they decline for the want of genial heat.<lb/>  Now&#58; what has in truth been taking place&#63;  Simply a<lb/> change.  The natural component elements of those productions&#44; which<lb/> kept them soundly together have gradually separated&#44; and fruits and<lb/> flowers&#44; which we consider dead&#44; have become dear not a waste but rich food<lb/> for the seed buried in the ground&#44; and which&#44; at the proper in due season<lb/> time will rise in its perfection to supply our food wants and gratification as heretofore.<lb/></p>
            <p>We may then logically argue that since real destruction<lb/> does not happen in any thing which God has formed&#44;<lb/> but that only a transformation or an absorption has<lb/> been going one&#44;&#44; so will reckon &#91;&#63;&#93; that the soul&#44; which is the sublimest<lb/> of God&#39;s creation&#44; will likewise undergo such a change as fitting to its<lb/> ethereal nature&#44; and survive the body which it animated.<lb/>  But many ask&#58; &#34;How can will a spiritual essence exist se&#45;<lb/>&#45;parately&#63;  We can understand that what is material may<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>take another material shape&#44; but the soul is a <sic>subtile</sic><lb/> substance which eludes excludes the idea of form&#44; as it does<lb/> that of space and touch.&#34;  This question my brethren&#44; rises from our<lb/> ignorance of what we call &#34;material.&#34;  Thus&#44; deep researches<lb/> have discovered that Light is a <sic>subtile</sic> substance filling expanding through all<lb/> the immensity of space&#44; yet invisible and incapable of being touched.  Lumi&#45;<lb/>&#45;nous bodies are not so naturally do not send forth their rays by an inherent force&#44; by but by a motion<lb/> they receive from the light surrounding them&#44; which motion&#44;<lb/> like the waving of the air which produces sounds&#44; when<lb/> it reaches the retina of the eye produces vision.  So<lb/> that light is distinct from the sun&#44; as the Bible itself<lb/> teaches&#44; by telling us that light was created on the first<lb/> day&#44; and the sun&#44; or the most luminous body&#44; on the fourth.<lb/>  Now&#44; light and its action&#44; may not inappropriately<lb/> be likened to the soul and its qualities.  One might<lb/> have <sic>tought</sic> that light and luminous bodies are the same&#44;<lb/> and that when the latter do not exist&#44; the existence of the<lb/> former is an impossibility.  But science assures us<lb/> that the such a supposition would be faulty.  Why then can&#45;<lb/>&#45;not then our soul live apart from our limbs&#44; on which it works&#44;<lb/> as light exists independent of the sun&#44; which is its principal agent&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>You must have become convinced that it would be<lb/> folly to declare possible only what falls under our<lb/> senses&#44; and is comprehensible to our minds&#44; and impos&#45;<lb/>&#45;sible what is otherwise.  For we know that light<lb/> is an entity&#44; but who can we point to the place of its dwelling&#63;<lb/>  We are aware of the power of Caloric or heat&#44; of its pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;sence in all created objects&#44; yet the essence thereof is hidden<lb/> from us&#44; and likely will so remain.  What shall<lb/> we say of Electricity&#63;  Inquire of the most skilled in sciences&#44;<lb/> of men who can use natural forces in a thousand ways&#44; re&#45;<lb/>quest them th to define the cause which at reason why the approach<lb/> of certain metals will produce a magnetic shock&#44; and they<lb/> will answer that they have tested the effects&#44; but they<lb/> cannot explain the internal causes.  Aye&#58; not alone<lb/> the causes&#44; but the manner in which those forces operate<lb/> we can never comprehend.  How are light and heat com&#45;<lb/>&#45;municated&#63;  In which way does electricity pass from<lb/> one material substance to the other&#63;  Those forces do exist&#44; and<lb/> the result we noticed continually&#44; though we may fail<lb/> to bestow on them the consideration they deserve.  And like<lb/> them so does the soul exist and we behold it in the very capacity<lb/> of man to invent&#44; to design&#44; to arrange&#44; to judge and to feel.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>True&#44; the law of analogy which we have invoked in our in&#45;<lb/>&#45;vestigations has not furnished a mathematical proof.<lb/>  That we can never secure on a question to metaphysical.<lb/>  One understanding is necessarily limited.  In trying to stretch<lb/> it beyond its assigned bounds&#44; we can only help ourselves<lb/> by drawing inferences.  It is the process we follow in<lb/> all our meditations.  For instance&#58; If we see that oil<lb/> being lighter in weight than water&#44; rises above it&#44; we<lb/> judge that the same principles governs all similar sub&#45;<lb/>&#45;stances.  Now&#58; we have met many things in nature<lb/> comparable to a union of the soul with the body.  From<lb/> them we have formed our criterion.  Whoever persists in<lb/> asking for more is like one who wishes to find have a<lb/> positive definition of the workings of a sense where it does not exist.<lb/>  Suppose that a person born blind should ask to be informed<lb/> how we can see light and colours.  He will be told that he sense of sight is somewhat like the sense of hearing&#59; that as by<lb/> motions in the air a noise is created which strikes the ear&#44; and we<lb/> hear&#44; so by the vibrations of rays the eye is touched and we see.<lb/>  But though the illustration will serve to give an idea of the truth&#44; the blind per&#45;<lb/>son will never be able tangibly to feel that the fact is as<lb/> we have explained it.  We all are totally blind about the nature<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>of a life hereafter&#44; but then we have the assurances<lb/> of sound reason&#44; the promises of the good book&#44; and the<lb/> innate consciousness that Divine justice and mercy demand<lb/> an existence beyond the grave.  The opaque body now inter<lb/>venes &#45;cepts our view&#44; but it is will be cast off&#44; we shall gain when its course is run&#44; and a flood of<lb/> ethereal light shall irradiate our undying selves. and<lb/> We shall see the King of glory the Universe dispense a new life&#44; and<lb/> lasting joys and a crown of unfading glory.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
