<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF4_15</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_15_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_15_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_15_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_15_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_15_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_15_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_15_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_15_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_15_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_15_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_15_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_15_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_15_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_15_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_15_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_15_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Post Biblical<lb/>
                35<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>The events which brought upon the throne in quick<lb/> succession three shortlived Roman emperors&#44; affected&#44; in a<lb/> measure&#44; the political condition of affairs in Judea.<lb/>  Vespasian&#44; who was about to lay <sic>seige</sic> against Jeru&#45;<lb/>&#45;salem when he heard the news that Nero had died<lb/> by his own hands&#44; suspended operations for a time.<lb/>  He ordered his son Titus&#44; to go to Rome and present his<lb/> homage and that of his army to the new emperor Galba.<lb/>  Titus set off accordingly&#44; but having journeyed as far as Greece&#44;<lb/> learned that Galba&#44; after a reign of only seven<lb/> months had been murdered by a party who preferred<lb/> Otho&#44; and that the latter was elected Ruler.<lb/>  It is not impossible that Titus saw in the unsettled<lb/> state of things government at home a chance for his father<lb/> to wear the crown.  He quickly returned hastened back to Judea<lb/> to tell report what had happened at Rome.  Mean&#45;<lb/>&#45;while it was reported the news spread abroad that Vitellius&#44; who com&#45;<lb/>&#45;manded the Roman legions in Germany&#44; had fought<lb/> Otho&#44; overcome all opposition and sat himself upon<lb/> the throne.  The hour had now struck for<lb/> Vespasian to gratify his cherished ambition.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>He was the idol of the army and with<lb/> his faithful soldiers on his side he felt certain<lb/> of success.  The legions in Judea and Syria pro&#45; saluted<lb/> &#45;claimed him emperor&#44; and his friends at Rome<lb/> prepared to support the choice with drawn swords.<lb/>  Vitellius was fought against and killed and<lb/> he who had won many battles in the East&#44; re&#45;<lb/>&#45;ceived the imperial mantle from the Senate in<lb/> the West.  But Vespasian in beco&#45;<lb/>&#45;ming chief of a vast empire&#44; had not forgotten<lb/> that his military honor was pledged to the con&#45;<lb/>&#45;quest of that small but indomitable people in<lb/> a corner of Western Asia.  He clothed with his<lb/> power Titus&#44; and ordered bid him not to pause till<lb/> the Jews were humbled to the earth.  The young<lb/> general performed the paternal injunction but<lb/> too well.  To our sorrow and shame be it said&#44;<lb/> our ancestors helped the enemy by their internal<lb/> quarrels&#44; and dishonesty. conduct.  The question was<lb/> not how to thrust back the foreign heathen by a united resistance but<lb/> how to make this or that party&#44; which in<lb/> turn contended for the mastery&#44; gain the day.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>The sacred Temple had become a battle field and<lb/> where the voice of priests was raised to bless Israel&#44;<lb/> where Levites sang Davidic psalmody&#44; profanity<lb/> and blood shed shocked the <sic>worshippers</sic>.  Simon<lb/> son of Giorus jealous of the influence which John<lb/> of Giskala exercised over a vast large number of the zea&#45;<lb/>&#45;lots&#44; had responded to the call of a faction&#44; that in&#45;<lb/>&#45;vited him to Jerusalem.  A third party had arisen<lb/> under the lead of Eleazar&#45;&#45;the man who had declared<lb/> it a crime to pay foreign tributes.  The capital<lb/> of Judea was in a <sic>wofully</sic> deplorable state&#44; when<lb/> the Passover of the year 70 of the vulgar era came<lb/> near.  Titus aided by King Agrippa II and other<lb/> allies resolved to carry out his father&#39;s command order command.<lb/>  The helmeted steel clad legions&#44; marched gathered from Alexandria&#44; from<lb/> Cesarea&#44; from different places marched under his command with<lb/> the most rigid discipline.  They were made to halted on the historic<lb/> hill Biblically called &#34;Gibeah of Saul.&#34;  From thence<lb/> the turrets of the Temple might be seen at a looming up.<lb/> distance Jerusalem was not far&#44; and Titus&#44; followed<lb/> by six hundred fearless soldiers&#44; attempted a feat of bravery.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>He went forth to study the surroundings<lb/> and determine where best to attack.  He The gallant general met<lb/> with no one&#44; till he had drawn nearer&#44; then the<lb/> gate of a Temple&#45;tower burst open&#44; and a shower<lb/> of javelins poured upon him.  Our people had<lb/> united to give the son of Vespasian such a reception<lb/> as he Rome might long remember.  How he That Titus fought his<lb/> way out of that storm of arrows&#44; can only must appear a<lb/> miracle.  Would that our fathers had interpreted that the<lb/> singular incident as a sign from above of the danger they<lb/> ran before a man <sic>superhumanly</sic> delivered&#33;  They might<lb/> then have discovered their fatal errors&#44; and joined<lb/> forces to battle for country and religion.  But they&#44;<lb/> on the contrary&#44; imagined to have read a good omen.<lb/>  Titus had fled for his life.  A happy sign prognostic&#33;  They would yet send<lb/> his legions flying back to Rome covered with confusion.<lb/>  Ill&#45;founded hopes&#33;  Passover arrived&#44; and<lb/> a countless number of Jews multitude from both sides of the<lb/> Jordan and even from beyond the Euphrates flocked to<lb/> the holy city&#44; impelled by the memories of the days<lb/> of national gladness&#44; when&#44; as told said by Isaiah&#44; the<lb/> festival was ushered in with a joyful heart&#44; and at the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>sound of the flue by those who hastened to the moun&#45;<lb/>&#45;tain of the Lord.  But now sorrow and wailing awaited the<lb/> pilgrims&#44; for&#44; as they sided with nay of the three<lb/> contending parties&#44; so they would they be harassed set upon by the others&#44;<lb/> and openly or secretly feel the dagger of the sicarii or assassins.<lb/>  Still&#44; though the unity so good and so pleasant for<lb/> brethren to dwell in&#44;&#45;&#45;a unity which&#44; if brought about<lb/> at first&#44; might have accomplished wonders&#45;&#45;was un&#45;<lb/>&#45;happily wanting&#44; nevertheless the conquest that Titus eagerly as&#45;<lb/>&#45;pired to achieve was neither quickly not easily effected. nor easily<lb/> We may search in vain the pages of history for<lb/> a parallel to the five days&#39; terrific fight in<lb/> the month of Iyar or May of the year 70.  That alone will<lb/> stand&#44; while time exists&#44; as a testimony of a valor<lb/> which nothing could daunt.  It The struggle at Bezetha and Acra brings to light<lb/>the daringness not of a few but of hosts of Hebrews<lb/> that courted death to in the effort to throw dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;order and dread among the closed ranks of their<lb/> enemies.  I find no pleasure in the description of<lb/> human slaughter&#44; else I could tell vividly show how the unfailing<lb/> aim of Jewish archers pierced through the ranks and files<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>and filled them with corpses&#44; how Jewish<lb/> shrewdness outwitted strategic skill&#44; how Jewish<lb/> intrepidity set engines of war on fire&#44; how the<lb/> general in chief&#45;&#45;Titus himself&#45;&#45;was forced to<lb/> measure arms with Jewish combatants&#44; who would<lb/> have struck at his life.  But I forbear&#59; not however without<lb/> asking such as deny our people courage&#44; to read<lb/> the events of the year 70 of the vulgar ear&#44; and<lb/> say whether the deeds of our ancestors at the <sic>seige</sic> of<lb/> Jerusalem deserve the title of heroism.  But<lb/> matchless boldness could not overcome famine&#44; and<lb/> its horrid attendant&#45;pestilence.  The Talmud men&#45;<lb/>tions three rich men&#44; Nakdimon&#44; Calva Sabua&#44; and Zizith<lb/> Kesath&#44; who vowed to supply Jerusalem with suffi&#45;<lb/>&#45;cient provision to last over twenty years&#44; but unfortu&#45;<lb/>&#45;nate internal wranglings&#44; which caused destruction of<lb/> food&#44; inimical fires that consumed it&#44; and an im&#45;<lb/>&#45;mense population superadded to the ordinarily<lb/> large number that devoured it&#44; put it within reach of Rome to<lb/> complete in a few months what might have defied cost<lb/> her power a score of fatiguing years.  Soon the besieged were<lb/> reduced to put gnaw the very leather of their sandals&#44; the fastenings<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>of their shields&#45;&#45;so desperate was the hunger.  The<lb/> scenes pictured in the book of Kings at the seige of<lb/> Samaria were reenacted with still greater horrors. more intense severity.  Nor<lb/> was there an Elisah to foretell predict a forthcoming salvation.  A Jewish<lb/> mother&#45;&#45;once wealthy&#45;&#45;crazed by starvation roasted her infant.<lb/>  The soldiers attracted by the smell demanded a portion<lb/> of the meal.  They fled horrified when told of what<lb/> flesh that repast had been prepared.  Then&#44; again&#44;<lb/> the rite of burial&#44; always so sacred among Jews could<lb/> no longer be performed&#44; when the <sic>seige</sic> became more<lb/> pressing.  The dead were heaped together in within the<lb/> houses&#44; or left buildings breeding poisonous vapors&#44; or were left to decompose in the streets.  Yet&#44;<lb/> the thought of laying down the arms was indignantly<lb/> chased away.  Titus bid Josephus more than once<lb/> try his eloquence to persuade his countrymen into<lb/> a surrender.  Our historian raised on a height from<lb/> which he could be heard&#44; but which could not be easily<lb/> reached by the listeners&#44; harangued the people.  His well<lb/> rounded periods and his erd erudite arguments&#44; received<lb/> as an answer response a round of curses and a volley of<lb/> stones.  His coreligionists could not forgive one who boasted of a lineal descent form the Maccabees his enjoying<lb/> Roman favors&#44; while the besieged suffered untold agonies.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>One by one they saw the walls of Jerusalem<lb/> yield to the battering rams of the foe&#44; and bury beneath<lb/> the rain the choicest and most gallant of their war&#45;<lb/>&#45;riors.  Thinned in their ranks&#44; famished and<lb/> sick&#44; still they still disputed every inch of ground&#44;<lb/> and reddened it with the blood of the assailants.<lb/>  But now the summer of the year 70 had set<lb/> in&#59; thirst tormented our soldiers&#44; and the <sic>seige</sic> fast<lb/>&#45;ened upon them with a violent pressure.  They All that could fight<lb/> had rallied in the fortress Antonia&#44;&#45;&#45;so called by Herod<lb/> in honor of his friend Marc Antony&#45;&#45;a stronghold<lb/> which communicated with the Temple through an<lb/> underground passage.  So long as the holy edifice<lb/> remained&#44; the heart of the national heart beat hope&#45;<lb/>&#45;fully.  Many an unfulfilled prediction was uttered to<lb/> cheer the defenders of that fortress.  It was a key<lb/> to the sanctuary of Israel&#39;s God&#44; the stranger could<lb/> not come to its possession so it was believed.  But after five days<lb/> of a desperate resistance&#44; the fortress Anotonia was<lb/> stormed&#44; and levelled razed to the ground.  It was then the<lb/> seventeenth of Tammuz&#44; the beginning of the three<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>saddest weeks in our annals.  The worship<lb/> of at the Temple ceased.  On the morrow&#44; before<lb/> the dawn had flung aside the veil of night&#44; the<lb/> Romans fell upon the Jewish sentinels.  A panic<lb/> ensued&#44; but soon our people was up to fight drive back<lb/> the assailants.  The latter grew furious by reason of at<lb/> the unexpected repulse&#44; and their general became im&#45;<lb/>&#45;patient in his eagerness to crush under the iron<lb/> heel of Rome&#44; a country which had so long dared<lb/> her redoutable armies.  Where the fortress<lb/> Antonia had stood lifted its turrets&#44; Titus raised embankments<lb/> from which to level his engines against the<lb/> Temple.  The Jews unsuccessful in their attempt<lb/> to dislodge the enemy&#44; set on fire with their<lb/> own hands a portico in the Temple&#44; which<lb/> connected with the spot where the fortress Antonia<lb/> had stood.  They thought thus to harass the Romans&#44;<lb/> but these in revenge set fire on another portico.<lb/>  Then the Jews filled an enclosure with combusti&#45;<lb/>&#45;bles&#44; and pretending to flee away lured into it the<lb/> Romans&#44; who many of whom perished in the flames which suddenly<lb/> burst forth.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>In vain had the battering rams beaten against<lb/> the Western Wall of the Temple&#44; in vain had the<lb/> engines tried to undermine the foundations of<lb/> the Northern gates.  The Jews would hurl back<lb/> the missiles&#44; hurl down the soldiers in their escalades&#44; they would<lb/> even seize the Roman Eagle from the standard<lb/> bearers and flaunt it defiantly.  Titus cut<lb/> to the quick by a resistance that baffled all<lb/> his military skill&#44; ordered that the gates of the<lb/> Temple be set on fire.  No sooner had the<lb/> blazing torches been applied&#44; than the silver plates<lb/> heated up&#44; the wood kindled&#44; the whole exterior<lb/> of the Sanctuary flamed up as a vulcans.  The<lb/> Jews saw the awful circle of fire closing around<lb/> them&#44; but did not move.  They stood paralyzed<lb/> by the terrific sight&#44; not a hand was stretched<lb/> forth to quench that conflagration.  Through<lb/> the whole night and the next day it raged<lb/> and went on consuming.  Titus at length ordered<lb/> that it be extinguished&#44; and that through the<lb/> gates now reeking&#44; a path be opened for the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>advance of his legions.<lb/></p>
            <p>I shall not continue this day a description already<lb/> too harrowing to Jewish hearts.  In my next lecture&#44;<lb/> I shall depict the final burning of the house of<lb/> our God&#44; the heroism of its defenders&#44; and the<lb/> utter desolation of Judea widowed of her Lord the shekinah<lb/> bereft of her children.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
