<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF2_4</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1863" source="" attested="yes">1863</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_4_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_4_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_4_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_4_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_4_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_4_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_4_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_4_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_4_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_4_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_4_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_4_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_4_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_4_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_4_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_4_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>14 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>A discourse for the 3d anniversary<lb/>
                of the 7th st Synagogue<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#34;O come&#44; let us prostrate ourselves&#44; &#38; bow down&#59; let us kneel before the Lord&#44;<lb/> our Maker.&#34;<lb/>
                Bright were the hopes&#44; which some among you&#44; my<lb/> beloved hearers&#33; harbored just three years ago&#44; when we first<lb/> entered this sanctuary with psalmody.  The structure<lb/> was imposingly beautiful.  They who had supervised its<lb/> erection&#44; sought in every appliance of the architectural<lb/> art&#44; the promotion of the design held in view.<lb/></p>
            <p>This stately edifice was to become a centre of attraction.<lb/>  The child of Israel who but rarely attuned his heart to the<lb/> national prayers&#44; would thenceforth watch constantly<lb/> at the portals of so noble a mansion.  Even he who<lb/> had heretofore refused to blend in sacred communion with<lb/> his fellow&#45;believers&#44; would be irresistibly drawn towards this<lb/> sightly spot.  The removal of our Congregation from<lb/> a building tottering with old&#45;age to one that well became<lb/> the changes of time and our general requisitions&#44; was<lb/> deemed to prove very auspicious.  The accession of number&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>would add material as well as spiritual strength<lb/> thereto&#44; and the prosperity which had attended the former<lb/> Synagogue&#44; would be exceeded by that of the latter.<lb/>  Such were the anticipations&#59; but truth demands that<lb/> we should inquire how far they have been realized.<lb/>  I therefore welcome you&#44; my friends&#33; in our consecrated dwelling&#44;<lb/> for&#44; we will together dispassionately search into the important question&#44;<lb/> which the recurrence of the season suggests to our minds.<lb/>  The experience of three years shall be our guide.  Its<lb/> steady light will not fail us&#44; and we shall be enabled<lb/> to submit to our impartial scrutiny the result of those<lb/> expectations so eagerly entertained at the opening of<lb/> that period.  The comeliness of<lb/> this house would swell the number of constant <sic>worshippers</sic>.<lb/>  So it was sanguinely imagined&#58; Well&#59; if the attendance<lb/> on the Sabbath&#45;morning were a just criterion&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>a slight progress in that direction might be admitted.<lb/>  We are gladdened every week by the presence of some of<lb/> our brethren&#44; who were wont to appear in the courts of the<lb/> Lord&#44; only at the celebration of high festivals.  But is<lb/> the duty of tendering public homage to our divine Benefactor<lb/> restricted to that time&#63;  Does His mercy reach us merely<lb/> at intervals&#44; that we should consider it unnecessary to<lb/> extol His name in unison of hearts&#44; safe at stated periods&#63;<lb/>  Are not His favors &#91;Hebrew&#93; renewed with every morning&#45;<lb/>dawn&#44; constant as the return of the grand luminary that<lb/> cheers the life of man&#63;  Whence then proceeds our disregard<lb/> for His service&#63;  Jointly&#44; my beloved hearers&#33; we<lb/> gather the abundance of His goodness&#44; and unitedly we<lb/> should also offer Him thanks&#44; when we lie down and when<lb/> we rise up.  As His providence is unending&#44; so<lb/> our adoration should be unlimited.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>That would indeed be a reform much to be commended&#44;<lb/> for&#44; it would&#44; in a remarkable degree&#44; distinguish this<lb/> house of prayer form the former.  But the<lb/> architectural beauty of our Tabernacle&#44; has not hitherto<lb/> affected the change.  The influence which was to<lb/> prove so salutary has not been felt even on the occasions&#44;<lb/> when public worship in the established usage of this Con&#45;<lb/>&#45;gregation.  I forbear to cite the instances&#44; when<lb/> ten Hebrews could not be found to hold communion<lb/> with the God of Israel before these holy shrines.  When ten<lb/> Hebrews could not be found to have said&#44; &#34;O let us come&#44; prostrate ourselves &#38; bow down&#44; let us kneel before<lb/> the Lord our Maker.&#34;<lb/>  While I therefore rejoice at the improvement exhibited in<lb/> the attendance of the service on the Sabbath&#45;morning&#44;<lb/>&#45;&#45;greatly to be attributed to our sister&#39;s zeal&#45;&#45;I cannot but<lb/> deprecate the indifference of our brother&#39;s in faith&#44; to an<lb/> obligation&#44; the performance of which ought to be constant.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;It is our bounden duty to<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>address our Maker every day.&#34;  The Sabbath we should<lb/> entirely devote to Him&#44; but we ought unceasingly to raise<lb/> our hearts to the Celestial Being&#44; upon whose mercy we<lb/> depend for every breath we draw.  It is a fatal radical mistake<lb/> to suppose that we may best evince our gratitude to our<lb/> Benefactor by the secret utterance of the soul.  No&#44; God does<lb/> delights in the sincere expressions of our lips.  And as<lb/> our prayers are designedly of a national character&#44; it<lb/> behooves us to address His throne in consonance both of<lb/> voices and minds.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> The orisons of the assembled faithful&#44; are at all times wafted heavenward.<lb/>  Is it&#44; my friends because some of our Gentile neighbors<lb/> convene together for worship only at the revolving of<lb/> each week&#44; that we must copy the example&#63;  Shall<lb/> the pioneers of religion retrograde&#63;  We should&#59; rather<lb/> strive to follow as a pattern&#44; those we taught how to pray&#44;<lb/> in that which is worthy of imitation.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>It would be well&#44; that we were equally assiduous<lb/> in our attendance&#44; irrespective of the inclemency of the<lb/> weather&#44; or the distance of the place.  It would be well<lb/> that we were equally punctual to the appointed<lb/> hours for devotional exercise.  It would be well&#44; that<lb/> a feeling of awe would deter us&#44; as it debars them&#44; from<lb/> entering the habitation of the Lord&#44; with an air of levity<lb/> or self&#45;importance.  It would be well that a sense<lb/> of propriety would induce us&#44; as it prompts them&#44; to<lb/> occupy our repsective seat until the divine service is<lb/> concluded.  It would be well that we&#44; like them&#44;<lb/> would demurely listen to the word of instruction&#44; though<lb/> offered with much frequency.  Then would this sightly<lb/> dwelling be a glory to the Most High&#44; because signa&#45;<lb/>&#45;lized by the decorum and sanctity prevailing therein.<lb/>  And who can say&#44; but that at the tidings of a place<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>so eminently calculated to impress and edify the<lb/> mind&#44; our brother who has ever remained a stranger<lb/> to it&#44; might also seek its holy precincts and be<lb/> refreshed at the fountain that gushes forth from the<lb/> Rock of Israel&#63;  Such a result&#44; my beloved hearers&#33;<lb/> would be the noblest success attained in this new Sy&#45;<lb/>&#45;nagogue.  Not alone would we realize the hopes<lb/> entertained at its dedication&#44; but likewise receive an<lb/> adequate reward from Him&#44; we led served with faithfulness.<lb/>  For&#44; we have been taught&#44; that to convert the vile man into<lb/> a precious object&#44; is to be the friend and representative of<lb/> God Almighty &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  But&#44;<lb/> Not the symmetry of the edifice&#44; not the skillfully<lb/> carved timber and the polished marble&#59; but the heart that<lb/> burns with love for the ancestral belief&#44; may under Providence accomplish<lb/> that desirable end.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Three long years have elapsed since this sl fane has been<lb/> reared&#44; yet&#44; they whom we long to greet within its walls&#44;<lb/> still continue to refuse their presence.  They saw<lb/> it&#44; and expressed admiration&#44; but its beauty gratified<lb/> the eye&#44; it did not impress the mind.  Hence&#44; to this day<lb/> they reject the holy communion of their brethren.  They<lb/> will not come&#44; prostrate themselves&#44; and bow down&#44; they will not kneel before the Lord their<lb/> Maker.<lb/>  Say then&#44; my friends&#33;  Where shall we seek for the proofs<lb/> of the advancement&#44; which has attended our removal hither&#63;<lb/>  Certainly not in the material means at our disposal.<lb/>  The idea that in order to possess a structure of superior<lb/> appearance&#44; many would have lavished on it their gifts&#44; has<lb/> proved erroneous.  Its additional requirements awakened<lb/> not a liberal spirit.  We were at one time reduced<lb/> to great straightness&#44; and to replenish our treasury conceived new<lb/> plans and adopted them&#44; but they have hitherto<lb/> been inefficacious.<lb/></p>
            <p>To excuse this prevailing indifference&#44; the charge of<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>improvidence has been laid against the administrators of<lb/> our Congregational revenue&#44; but conceding even that<lb/> some of their acts were unwarranted by our condition&#44;<lb/> ought we therefore to have suffered the decay of an<lb/> institution once so flourishing&#63;  Ought not a noble pride<lb/> to have stirred us up to deeds of generosity and restored us<lb/> to the high position we held in the Community of Israel&#63;<lb/>  I also often lamented in my heart the effects of a rash<lb/> undertaking&#44; but I would unhesitatingly offer this day a<lb/> portion of my scanty means&#44; for its ultimate completion.<lb/>  It avails us naught now to censure or criminate&#44; we<lb/> must correct the evil&#44; and prevent its extension.<lb/></p>
            <p>Charity commands enjoins it.  Self&#45;respect imperatively demands<lb/> it.  If your neighbour bends under a weight that<lb/> baffles his strength&#44; you surely do not abandon him to his<lb/> fate&#44; because of his inconsiderate act&#44; how much more<lb/> solicitous ought you then to be in aiding an object&#44; whose<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>downfall would bring many to shame and disgrace the<lb/> name of Israel&#33;  Remember &#34;that the palace is<lb/> not for man&#44; but for the Eternal God&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  To Him are your gifts&#59; for<lb/> the maintenance of His holy service are your boons.<lb/>  King David treasured immense sums of silver2 and gold1<lb/> as a token of affection to the house of the Lord &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; you are requested<lb/> to give but a slight portion of your superfluities.  The<lb/> heavenly Being who has prospered the works of your<lb/> hands&#44; requires wishes of you&#44; as a return for His boundless<lb/> goodness&#44; only a small token of your gratitude&#44; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;let there be food in my house&#34; He exclaims<lb/> by the mouth of His prophet.  Deny it not&#44;<lb/> my Brethren&#33; to the Author of your existence&#44; to<lb/> the Guardian of all your substance.  Upon his<lb/> altar&#44; to which you will repair on the morrow<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>to vow again your allegiance&#44; lay on the morrow munificent offerings.<lb/>  What you have lent for the rearing of His sanctuary&#44;<lb/> <sic>yeild</sic> cheerfully for its support.  What you may<lb/> have perchance reserved as a bequest thereto&#44; give now<lb/> liberally&#44; which is the hour of need.  Think&#44; my<lb/> friends&#33; what satisfaction it will create in your minds&#44;<lb/> what lustre it will shed on your name&#44; what unction<lb/> it will lay on your soul to feel that you were the<lb/> stanchion of the house of the Lord our God&#59; and you<lb/> will vie with each other in acts of pious generosity.<lb/>  But however meritorious such a conduct will be&#44; we<lb/> should deem it as only one token of our homage to<lb/> the Almighty.  To endow a place for public worship<lb/> and rarely visit it&#44; is an sinful as it is unpardonable inconsistency.<lb/>  The Possessor of all things does not require our exact from his creatures costly presents&#44;<lb/> though He favorably accepts the thoughts that have prompted<lb/> them.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  An altar of earth is as precious<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p>in His sight as the most gorgeous Temple&#44; provided the heart<lb/> is poured forth at its shrine.  It would by far profit us<lb/> more that we invoked His name in an humble dwelling&#44;<lb/> than we lavished gold upon the establishment of a<lb/> deserted fane.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  The best exponent<lb/> of the love we bear our celestial Protector&#44; is our communion<lb/> with Him.  But&#44; It must be constant&#44; it must be spiritual<lb/> it must elevate us to Him and arouse godly sentiments in the<lb/> mind of others.  Can you not&#44; my dear hearers&#33; so serve<lb/> the Lord your beneficent Creator in this sightly tabernacle&#63;...Yes&#44; you<lb/> will.  Each of you will&#44; by his devout demeanour<lb/> and liberal spirit&#44; show his fellow&#45;believers an example<lb/> worthy of imitation.  Each of you will&#44; by words that carry<lb/> persuasion&#44; draw hither the indifferent and the disaffected&#59;<lb/> and whereas the past failed to realize the anticipations<lb/> entertained&#44; the future will witness the independent<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="14"/>
            <p>stability of our Synagogue&#44; the increase of its attendants&#44;<lb/> their improved demeanour within its hallowed walls&#44;<lb/> and the reclaiming of our erring brothers&#44; who&#44; burning<lb/> with devotion will say to each other &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;Oh&#33; come&#44; let us prostrate ourselves<lb/> and bow down&#44; let us kneel before the Lord&#44; our Maker&#44;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;For&#44; He is our God&#44; and we are the people of his pasture<lb/> and the flock of his hand&#44; yea&#44; this day if ye<lb/> will hearken unto his voice&#34;  So may it be&#44; and<lb/> our eyes behold it.  May the Dweller in heaven breathe<lb/> into us a new spirit&#44; that we may serve Him with<lb/> one consent&#44; and observe his morals laws&#44; and cere&#45;<lb/>&#45;monial ordinances&#44; as He commanded for a guidance<lb/> unto all the generations of Israel.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
