<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF5_14</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_14_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_14_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_14_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_14_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_14_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_14_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_14_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_14_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_14_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_14_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_14_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_14_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Post Biblical<lb/>
                57.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>When I shall be no longer among the living&#44; some<lb/> kind hand may collect such writings of mine&#44; as<lb/> are not unworthy of being preserved.  Among them&#44;<lb/> I would wish that the Post Biblical lectures&#44; which&#44;<lb/> at longer or shorter intervals&#44; I delivered here&#44; during se&#45;<lb/>&#45;veral years on Sabbath mornings&#44; be submitted to<lb/> the perusal of my Philadelphia brethren&#44; in book a permanent<lb/> form shape.  The wish may sound like an assumption&#44; arrogance most<lb/> especially now&#44; since Professor Graetz&#39;s exhaustive work<lb/> on that subject&#44; is being abridged in English&#44; under the<lb/> auspices of the &#34;Jewish Publication Society of America.&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>But&#44; disclaiming any not intending to draw a comparison&#44; savoring of presumption&#44;<lb/> I may be allowed to say that my unpretentious addresses&#44;<lb/> in the form that I gave them&#44; could be read by the young of<lb/> our people to some advantage.  I have resisted all along<lb/> the flattering request of well meaning persons&#44; and with com&#45;<lb/>paratively few exceptions&#44; have declined publishing what<lb/> I had penned&#44; for&#44; my morbid sensitiveness might<lb/> not have stood adverse criticism&#44; but I know from<lb/> experience that the considerateness often denied to the<lb/> living&#44; is accorded to the dead.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>To day I shall resume&#44; what illness and other motives<lb/> compelled me to interrupt&#44; for a much longer period<lb/> than usual heretofore.  In speaking of French<lb/> Jews in the Middle Ages&#44; I described&#44; on various<lb/> occasions&#44; the marked difference existing between<lb/> those who lived in the South and their coreligionists<lb/> who had made their home in the North.  I showed<lb/> how the latter&#44; whose noblest Chief was the great<lb/> Solomon Isaaki&#44; or Rashi of Troyes in the XI cen&#45;<lb/>&#45;tury of the common era&#44; were looked upon regarded&#44; in general&#44;<lb/> as very staunch adherents of Rabbinism&#44; entirely free<lb/> from the admixture of the Philosophical notions&#44; then<lb/> in vogue.  That a determined opposition to ideas con&#45;<lb/>&#45;flicting with the plain teaching of Holy Writ and<lb/> the traditions of the Synagogue&#44; should have led<lb/> a member of those French Jews in the XIII century&#44;<lb/> to wage war against a giant of intellect&#44; the world renowned Maimoni&#45;<lb/>&#45;des&#44; proves beyond doubt&#44; their earnestness and uncompromising<lb/> character.  We must deeply regret the violence<lb/> of the attack&#44; notably so&#44; when since the object fought<lb/> against&#44; was an Israelite upon the like of whom<lb/> we may never look again&#44; and we cannot<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>sufficiently lament the sad consequences of the on&#45;<lb/>&#45;slaught&#44; when we remember that the arm of the<lb/> Catholicism church was finally invoked&#44; to and that church and the Roman its church publicly burned the writings<lb/> of the immortal Sage of Cordova&#44; and with them other<lb/> precious volumes of our sacred national literature.  But<lb/> deploring what happened&#44; we dare not deny the sincerity<lb/> of the assailants.  It was acknowledged by some Spanish<lb/> Jews&#44; distinguished in various high walks of life&#44; for they<lb/> also recognized the danger of trying to reconcile the<lb/> irreconcilable&#44; namely&#44; the soul directing and spirit<lb/> quieting lessons of Moses and the prophets with the<lb/> misguiding and audacious perplexing theories of a philosophy&#44; which <sic>cameleon</sic><lb/>like&#44; changes its colors continually.  The greater<lb/> the man&#44; the greater his error.  had Maimonides fore&#45;<lb/>seen that what he deemed indisuptably correct&#44; as<lb/> the emanation of individuals for ages universally esteemed them infallible&#44;<lb/> would one day be set aside as incorrect&#44; he might<lb/> have avoided an evil which needs rooting out even<lb/> at present.  I refer to a mania for turning and twisting<lb/> words of the Bible and Talmudical maxims in order to force<lb/> them into an agreement with a distorted philosophy.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Let me repeat&#44; what I may have declared before.<lb/>  I would not detract a single iota from the merits<lb/> of Moses Ben Maimon.  In the horizon of Jewish liter&#45;<lb/>&#45;ature&#44; the Rabbi philosopher shines as a star of first magnitude&#44; but<lb/> unintentionally&#44; he led astray some who wished to<lb/> walk at his light.  Among his devoted fol&#45;<lb/>&#45;lowers&#44; Jews in South France were numerously count&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed.  They Those Hebrews coreligionists of ours&#44; dwelt principally in Provence&#44; congre&#45;<lb/>&#45;gating largely in Bagnoles&#44; Perpignan and Avignon&#45;&#45;<lb/>Avignon the city&#44; so celebrated in Church history&#44; as<lb/> the enforced residence of several Popes and anti Popes&#44;<lb/> and chronicled in ritual Judaism&#44; as the possessor of having a holidays&#39; liturgy<lb/> of its own.  In those parts of France&#44; metaphy&#45;<lb/>&#45;sical researches accompanied the study of the Scrip&#45;<lb/>&#45;tures and Talmud.  Towards the end of the<lb/> XIII century&#45;&#45;perhaps in 1290&#45;&#45;was born at<lb/> Bagnoles a man who earned high a wide reputation&#44;<lb/> because of his rare and varied talents.  The name<lb/> which he bore in Hebrew&#44; was Levi Ben Gershon&#44;<lb/> or Ralbag&#44; according to the initial letters of his name.  But<lb/> he is better known among the learned under<lb/> the appellation of Gersonides.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>He was doubly fortunate&#44; in receiving early and care&#45;<lb/>ful instruction from his own father and in possess&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing enough of this world&#39;s goods to enable allow him<lb/> to seek knowledge&#44; unhindered by the necessity<lb/> of going in quest of a livelihood.  Confessedly&#44;<lb/> a voluminous writer&#44; some of he was not so fortunate in the perpetuation of his productions&#44; for some were<lb/> lost to posterity&#44; but very many of them en&#45;<lb/>&#45;gage to this day the attention of scholars.<lb/>  And deservedly so&#44; for his comments upon a<lb/> number of scriptural books&#44; though speculative in many instances&#44; reflect a searching<lb/> mind&#44; resolved to arrive at its own independent<lb/> conclusions&#44; regardless of what renowned authors<lb/> may have said before.  Hebrew as the language<lb/> which that Southern Frenchman exclusively used&#44;<lb/> but he had gained a thorough acquaintance with<lb/> foreign works&#44; such as Aristotle and Averroes<lb/> had given the world of letters.  His Gersonides&#39; familiarity<lb/> with them&#44; enabled Gersonides him to compose a book<lb/> on &#34;Right Logic&#34; Hekesh Ha&#45;Gashar&#44; another<lb/> on the &#34;science of the number&#34; or mathematics&#44; and<lb/> to qualified him also to controvert&#44; at times&#44; certain<lb/> views advanced by Greek and Arabian celebrities.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Do I hold up then Levi Ben Gershon as a Jew&#44; whom<lb/> we may trustingly follow&#63;  Not at all.  I<lb/> respect his extensive knowledge&#44; I honor his<lb/> candor in the presentation of his ideas.  I am<lb/> thankful for his exertions&#44; which have illus&#45;<lb/>&#45;trated books of Holy Writ&#44; f and for his kindly<lb/> sentiments towards persecuted brethren&#44; in less<lb/> auspicious sections of France than where he was born.  But I could<lb/> not unqualifiedly recommend the productions of that Jew&#44; as<lb/> I would those of his Northern countrymen&#44; Rashi and<lb/> his grandsons&#44; Isaac&#44; Samuel and Jacob&#44; or as<lb/> I would readily recommend those of the Southern Kimchi&#45;family.<lb/>  In fact&#44; I am amazed&#44; when studying the<lb/> pages of his principal work&#44; that it should<lb/> have found any circulation.  When we call<lb/> to mind the deep sensation which the Moreh<lb/> Nebuchim&#44; or &#34;teacher of the perplexed&#34; by Mai&#45;<lb/>&#45;monides created&#59; how it divided Israel into two<lb/> hostile camps&#59; how the great Cordovan&#44; after<lb/> his death demise&#44; was pronounced a heretic&#44; for having<lb/> occasionally tried endeavoured to explain away what is supernatural<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>in some Scriptural narratives&#44; I am perfectly<lb/> astounded at seeing that work&#44; beyond com&#45;<lb/>&#45;parison freeer in thought&#44; should not have<lb/> been put under ban. aroused angry disputes.  True&#44; two Spanish<lb/> authors&#44; Shene Tob Flaquevier&#44; and Hasda&#239; Kres&#45;<lb/>&#45;kas&#44; criticised it unsparingly&#59; the former calling the<lb/> book&#44; which Gersonides had entitled Milchamoth Ashem<lb/> &#34;Battles for the Lord&#44;&#34; &#34;Battles against the Lord&#44;&#34; still<lb/> Gersonides found also staunch defenders was spared the effects of what must have been considered his temerity.  To give an<lb/> instance of our &#91;&#63;&#93; on writer&#39;s boldness&#44; I will<lb/> limit myself this morning to quoting a sentiment<lb/> as met in the preface&#44; reserving for another time occasion my re&#45;<lb/>&#45;marks on the book itself.  He says&#58; &#34;No doubt&#44;<lb/> many will reject our words&#44; as strange to their<lb/> understanding&#44; not because they have arrived at<lb/> their convictions by researches&#44; or by considering reflecting on<lb/> the controlling principles of Judaism&#44; but simply<lb/> because they inherited their ideas from their parents.<lb/>  Not for such have we written.  To them is one<lb/> enough to believe&#44; without trying to known<lb/> why they believe.&#34;  And after having highly eulogising<lb/> Maimonides for having opened the way to<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>profound investigations&#44; he continues&#58; &#34;We<lb/> swear by Truth&#44; that we were not would never be held back from<lb/> introducing such topics&#44; as we present in this<lb/> book&#44; because fools&#44; who consider themselves<lb/> wise&#44; are unused to deep inquiries.&#34;  The lan&#45;<lb/>&#45;guage is forcible&#44; but not commendable.  It is<lb/> not the language which the inspired moralist styles wis&#45;<lb/>&#45;dom.  &#34;With the lowly is abides wisdom&#34; Wisdom abides with lowly&#34;&#44; or when he praises<lb/> the sweet lips of the righteous&#44; which increase learning &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Nor does it the language agree with the sensible aphorism of the Rabbis&#58;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Despise no man&#34;.  But Gersonides&#44; who so<lb/> admired Maimonides&#44; ought to have imitated that Sage&#44;<lb/> who&#44; in a letter to a fond pupil&#44; tells him that&#44; according to<lb/> the dictum of Israel&#39;s preceptors&#44; knowledge is<lb/> a crown to its possessor&#44; but humility is the com&#45;<lb/>&#45;pletion of virtues&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
