<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF5_19</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_19_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_19_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_19_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_19_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_19_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_19_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_19_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_19_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_19_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_19_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_19_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_19_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Post Biblical<lb/>
                62.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>When several years ago&#44; I laid out a plan to occasional<lb/>&#45;ly deliver here post&#45;Biblical lectures&#44; from the sacred desk&#44; at intervals shorter or longer intervals&#44;<lb/> no translation of Professor Graetz&#39;s most comprehensive<lb/> work existed in a language familiar to me.  In my<lb/> Ignorant of the German in which the great author wrote&#44;<lb/> I imagined that I could be of some use by sketching in English<lb/> what I knew of the life work of a number among of our most eminent<lb/> sages and philosophers&#44; unknown to with which the generality<lb/> of my hearers were unacquainted.  But with the issuing of the latest volume of issued<lb/> Graetz&#39;s history in the vernacular by our Publication Society&#44; my endeavours in that direction<lb/> have become altogether unnecessary.  For&#44; that volume<lb/> covers a period much nearer to our times&#44; than I had<lb/> reached&#44; and all can read there extensively what I would<lb/> present only with comparative brevity.  Still&#44; I<lb/> have a wish to gratify myself this once and possibly also<lb/> hereafter by describing a few of the characters among<lb/> our celebrated predecessors just as the literary my knowledge<lb/> that of I possess of them suggests to my mind.  One<lb/> that I fondly love will be the subject of my discourse<lb/> this morning.  All may have heard of Don Isaac<lb/> Abarbanel&#44; or Abrabanel&#44; or Abravaneli&#44; as he has been<lb/> variously called in various countries.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>But not all are aware of the depth amount of gratitude our<lb/> indebtedness to that illustrious Jew of the 15th century.<lb/>  The title &#34;Don&#34; attached to his name&#44; shows tells us his country<lb/> and his rank.  He was a great distinguished personage living in Spain.<lb/>  It is not clearly stated what led him his ancestors&#44; or<lb/> his own parents parents&#44; perhaps&#44; to quit Spain and<lb/> settle in Portugal.  Religious persecutions which broke out at<lb/> intervals may have caused it&#44; for&#44; we read that one of<lb/> his predecessors&#44; Samuel Abarbanel&#44; sought &#91;&#63;&#93; his escape<lb/> from the burning caldron of the Inquisition into the<lb/> baptismal fount.  We first meet Isaac Abar&#45;<lb/>&#45;banel in his native home at Lisbon&#44; as a banker of<lb/> high repute.  Alfonso V. who resigned in Portugal&#44;<lb/> having heard of the exceptional abilities of his Jewish<lb/> subject&#44; appointed him&#44; minister of finance.  Like<lb/> Chasda&#239; Aben Maprut and Samuel ABen Nagrela of<lb/> former ages&#45;&#45;patrons of Hebrew learning and defenders of<lb/> their race&#45;&#45;Abarbanel utilized his political influence and the<lb/> large means at his command to the social and intellectual<lb/> advantage of his coreligionists.  So eager was he to<lb/> be of service to those who shared his belief that in one<lb/> instance&#44; when two hundred and fifty Jewish prisoners<lb/> of war were carried from Algiers to Portugal Abarbanel&#44; who realized that<lb/> his personal contributions were too inadequate to purchase their ransom&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Abarbanel <sic>travelled</sic> abroad to collect in quest of what was needed<lb/> for that purpose and entered also for that purpose into correspondence<lb/> with a certain Yechiel of Pisa&#45;&#45;a very rich and<lb/> and public spirited Italian&#44; the Rothschild of Tuscany<lb/> in the 15th century&#45;&#45;who helped very greatly.<lb/>  Ominous Most unfortunate for Abarbanel was the death or&#44; as some relate&#44; the abdication of of Alfonso V.  For&#44; his son<lb/> John II&#59; adopted a course altogether at variance<lb/> with that which his royal parent had followed.  In<lb/> order to rule despotically&#44; unchecked by the wise inter&#45;<lb/>&#45;vention of acknowledged statesmen&#44; he determined to<lb/> rid himself by cruel death of all whom his father had consulted and<lb/> trusted.  Isaac Abarbanel was among the intended<lb/> victims of John&#39;s wicked design.  He was Having been summoned<lb/> to the palace and suspecting no foul play&#44; he would have gone&#44; if a friendly<lb/> voice had not whispered a word of caution&#44; which<lb/> warded off the imminent danger.  Abarbanel hotly hastily<lb/> pursued fled the country&#44; leaving behind all his pos&#45;<lb/>&#45;sessions&#44; which were unmercifully confiscated.  Hotly<lb/> pursued by soldiers on horse back&#44; he succeeded never&#45;<lb/>less to reach Castile in safety&#44; but exhausted and<lb/> destitute.  However&#44; the Rabbinical maxim may<lb/> fittingly apply in this case &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>&#34;He is only is poor&#44; who lacks understanding.&#34;  The fame<lb/> of Don Isaac Abarbanel had preceded his arrival in<lb/> Spain.  His coreligionists who enjoyed there wealth&#44; and<lb/> high positions&#44; encouraged the new comer in a substantial<lb/> manner to devote his mind time to occupations most congenial<lb/> to his nature and for which his mind was superbly equip&#45;<lb/>&#45;ped.  In Toledo Abarbanel began in all earnestness to<lb/> weild handle the pen&#44; that which he had already employed in Lisbon&#44; and which immortalized his name in the world<lb/> of letters.  And here I may be permitted to re&#45;<lb/>&#45;mark that I dissent from Professor Graetz&#39;s judgment<lb/> of the spirit underlying&#44; Abarbanel&#39;s writings.  Without accepting as un&#45;<lb/>&#45;questionably correct all the ideas which our Spanish Jew expositor<lb/> advanced in his very many and diversified works&#44; I hold that<lb/> our German Jew historian has done him injustice.  How could<lb/> a writer&#44; whose standard was the Torah and the traditions&#44; do<lb/> otherwise than come to different conclusions than different from those at which authors like<lb/> Gersonides&#44; commentators like Narboni&#44; or philosophers like<lb/> Maimonides in his Mor&#233; Nebuchim&#44; had arrived&#63;  Pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;fessor Graetz laments complains that Abarbanel was too or&#45;<lb/>&#45;thodox.  He says&#58; Abarbanel &#34;was not tolerant enough<lb/> to listen to a liberal view of Judaism and its doctrines.&#34;<lb/>  But how could he with harmonize with persons who denied<lb/> God&#39;s special providence &#91;Hebrew&#93; and who wrenched and twisted the<lb/> Biblical text most unscrupulously to make it agree with prevailing notions&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Indeed&#44; it was that great Sephardic Jew who freed<lb/> us from the shackles which many of his predecessors<lb/> voluntarily put on in their servility to Aristotle the<lb/> Greek and Averroes the Arabian.  Defects in<lb/> in Abarbanel&#39;s literary productions can be detected.<lb/>  He is too diffuse&#44; where he might have been concise.<lb/>  His speculations on the approaching advent of the Messiah are chi&#45;<lb/>&#45;merical.  His interpretations of the Scriptures&#44; are&#44; at times&#44;<lb/> far fetched&#59; but what none can gainsa contract contradict<lb/> is that his style flows ever smoothly&#44; that his mastery<lb/> of the Hebrew is unsurpassed&#44; that he is thoroughly<lb/> honest and open minded in his expressions&#44; and evinces a quickness<lb/> in writing that few could imitate.  It seems al&#45;<lb/>most incredible that in less than four months&#44; he<lb/> could comment four books of the Bible&#45;&#45;Joshua&#44; Judges and<lb/> the two books of Samuel even if&#44; as Professor Graetz&#39;s asserts&#44; he utilized Latin works on the same subject.  But grateful as all<lb/> who love sacred literature must feel to Abarbanel&#44; the<lb/> obligation which we Jews owe him has its main foun&#45;<lb/>&#45;dation in the memory of the infinite services he rendered<lb/> us&#44; in his splendid character and in his having suffered<lb/> terribly for the sake of our religion&#44; while one word might have<lb/> kept him in power&#44; in affluence and undisturbed peace.<lb/></p>
            <p>Like Alfonso of Portugal&#44; Ferdinand of Spain resolved to<lb/> avail himself of the administrative abilities of his newly acquired subject.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Abarbanel was invited to Madrid to fill the office<lb/> of Minister of finance.  Dur In that capacity&#44;<lb/> during eight consecutive years&#44; he made the royal<lb/> treasury swell with gold&#44; and in by performing his duty<lb/> faithfully towards his king&#44; he stood as became a tower of<lb/> defence to his brethren&#44; whom malice and envy tried to<lb/> injure.  But Ferdinand of Aragon had wedded<lb/> Isabella of Castile&#44; the priest ridden and bigoted.  Could<lb/> she tell at the confessional that her kingdom was the most Catholic&#44;<lb/> the <sic>stanchest</sic> devotee to the Chruch&#44; while Mohem&#45;<lb/>&#45;medans and Jews lived there and prospered&#44; <sic>weilded</sic> power<lb/> and half held exalted stations&#63;  She believed not That<lb/> question was a pang to her <sic>shrivelled</sic> soul.  She vowed<lb/> that if the rule of Moslem ceased in Spain she would<lb/> purged the land of all infidels.  After obstinate battles on both sides Granada fell&#59; the Moors&#44;<lb/> on whose Spanish domains&#44; Jews has shed rays of inextinguishable<lb/> light&#44; for nearly eight hundred years&#44; were finally van&#45;<lb/>&#45;quished.  The cross had made forced the crescent to sink in<lb/> the <sic>Ibernian</sic> horizon.  Triumphantly amid popu&#45;<lb/>&#45;lar acclamations&#44; Ferdinand and Isabella made their<lb/> entry into their new possession.  But to the Hebrews<lb/> the joyful shouting of the conquerors&#44; was the knell which sounded<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>announced their death.  Islamism was not as hateful to<lb/> Catholic Spain as Judaism was.  For&#44; the Koran admits<lb/> that the Galilean preacher had been a great apostle&#59;<lb/> but Jews reject him and the creed which he is alleged<lb/> to have founded.  Should they be suffered to pol&#45;<lb/>&#45;lute a kingdom cleansed of the followers of Moham&#45;<lb/>&#45;met&#63;  From the halls of the magnificent Alhambra&#44; the<lb/> murderous edict issued forth.  Within three months<lb/> every one who denies the trinity must leave the country&#44;<lb/> without daring to carry along the riches that that industry he has they gathered&#44; but which must now<lb/> revert to the throne.  Abarbanel writes as follows in<lb/> his preface to the comment of the first book of Kings&#58;<lb/> It &#34;I was at court when the decree was proclaimed.  I<lb/> exhausted my persuasive powers of persuasion in addressing the King&#44;<lb/> beseeching him thus.  &#39;Deliver us O our Sovereign&#33;  Turn<lb/> not away form your loyal subjects.  Ask of us silver<lb/> and gold&#59; every son of Israel will give them for the country<lb/> he loves.&#39;  I then looked to my friends&#44; whom the king<lb/> favored&#44; that they might intercede for my people.  Those<lb/> high officials earnestly prayed for the recalling of the<lb/> fearful mandate.  But as the odder which is said to close<lb/> its ears against the charmer&#44; so the king remained un&#45;<lb/>moved.  For&#44; the queen sitting on his right&#44; urged him on<lb/> with her loquacious tongue to be firm in his purpose.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Alas&#33; vain were our endeavours.  The peace I had<lb/> sought&#44; the ease I hoped for vanished away.  Anguish<lb/> supplanted them.  As the distressful news spread fast&#44;<lb/> Jews trembled and mourned&#44; for sn since Judah had lost<lb/> his country and roamed abroad among strangers&#44; such<lb/> horrors had not been felt.  But in the face of the<lb/> dreadful calamity&#44; we encouraged one another.<lb/>  Let us bear it&#44; brethren&#44; rather than be turn traitors to the<lb/> faith which our enemies outrage and revile.  Whether we<lb/> shall live or die&#44; let us not be false to the covenant.<lb/>  Move on under the Lord&#39;s banner.  Then three hundred thou&#45;<lb/>&#45;sand moved on journeyed towards Portugal&#44; some towards Navarre&#44;<lb/> but only the gloom of misery accompanied them every&#45;<lb/>where&#44; famine&#44; pestilence and sword walked before them.<lb/>  Those who trusted their lives to the waves&#44; sunk into bot&#45;<lb/>&#45;tomless seas deeps&#44; some were consumed in ships set on fire&#44; others<lb/> were sold to slavery.  The rigorous judgments of heaven attended<lb/> their footsteps.  Of the many that went forth few only<lb/> were left to tell the horrid tale.  Ah&#33; with the Scripture we may<lb/> cry.  &#39;We have perished&#44; all we have been lost&#44; all of us have been lost&#44;&#39;<lb/> but with the Scripture still we repeat&#58; let the name of the Lord still be blessed.&#34;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
