<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF3_12</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_12_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_12_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_12_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_12_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_12_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_12_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_12_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_12_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_12_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_12_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_12_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_12_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>12th lecture on<lb/>
                Post&#45;Biblical history.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  We are not about to celebrate Hanuccah&#44; but my historical series<lb/> requires that I shall speak of the events incidents which gave ori&#45; fired up<lb/> &#45;gin the zeal of heros sainted men and gave origin to the semifestival of the Temple re&#45;Dedication.  I will do so be&#45;<lb/>&#45;cause necessary to the thread of history comprehension of the the chain of events which I have been sometime engaged to in realting but I will proceed with as<lb/> much brevity as consistent with as the intelligeblenessnce of the<lb/> subject well admits.  I know that my audience can dispense with<lb/> detailed accounts&#44; and can fill up supply present omissions with<lb/> that which has been narrated to them at length on other occasions.<lb/>  In this lecture which I delivered last&#44; I told of the treasure of one man&#44;<lb/> who became a backbiter and an informer&#44; and thus<lb/> brought a worthy minister of God into disrepute&#44; and<lb/> endangered the honor of his religion&#44; and jeopardised<lb/> the welfare of his people.  But that man was&#44;<lb/> after all&#44; a stranger to the high&#45;priest whom he tried to<lb/> injure.  We may surmise that some personal grudge or jea&#45;<lb/>&#45;lousy stirred up Simon the Benjamite to acts deeds of treachery infamy.<lb/>  But Still such feelings&#44; unjustifiable in any human being&#44;<lb/> would not be expected in persons of supposed to lurk in the breasts of creatures in whose veins the same parental blood and flows.<lb/> lineage  Onias III was however so unfortunate enough as to<lb/> find that those who had been nurtured by his mother&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>and fed and cared for by the same loving father&#44; plot&#45;<lb/>&#45;ted to supplant him and bring cause his grey hairs to be down with sorrow to the grave.<lb/>  A proverb in that Scriptural book&#44; which deserves to be<lb/> framed in gold&#44; says that a lad will disclose even in<lb/> his boyish actions whether his doings future conduct will be right<lb/> and proper.  Joshua&#44; the brother of Onias showed early<lb/> in life an unjewish turn of mind&#44; when he exchanged<lb/> a name of which he might have felt proud&#44; for<lb/> that of the fabulous hero of the Argonautic expedition&#45;&#45;the Greek &#34;Jason.&#34;  And the<lb/> sequel proved that hollow were his professions of<lb/> adherence to the belief in the Unity&#44; for that the priestly mitre he longed to put on wear he intended as a shield against the arrows of an outraged nation&#44; &#38; that he would not<lb/> scruple stepping into power by trampling under foot the<lb/> holiest institutions of his ancestral faith.<lb/></p>
            <p>Seleucus King of Syria had died&#44; and a suspicion lay<lb/> on Heliodorus&#44;&#45;&#45;the official courtier whom he had trusted&#45;&#45;&#44; of having poisoned<lb/> his master&#44; to seize the crown.  There was none<lb/> at the time likely to oppose the usurper.  Demetrius<lb/> son of Seleucus was then kept at Rome&#44; as a hostage.<lb/>  Antiochus&#44; a brother of the late king&#44; having left Italy&#44;<lb/> was <sic>travelling</sic> in Greece&#44; and no doubt Heliodorus<lb/> had no doubt taken precautions to gane gain the army on<lb/> his side.  The news of the usurpation spread<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>abroad and reached Antiochus while he was staying at Athens.  He at their tindings he sudden Suprred by ambition&#44; he hastened to<lb/> Syria&#44; and by with the aid of foreign soldiers fought Heliodorus&#44;<lb/> slew him and assumed the government under the title of<lb/> Antiochus IV.  He bore also that the surname of Epiphanes&#44; meaning &#34;the<lb/> illustrious&#44;&#34; but which in truth he could only claim that epithet of ferocity &#38; fanaticism were<lb/> synonymous with greatness.  It was to this king&#44; that<lb/> Jason came&#44; as an ambassador if feigning to present the respects<lb/> of the Hebrew nation.  The deceitful messenger Our ancestors had received a generous treatment from Antiochus III and his son Seleucus had not<lb/> been honorably hostile to them&#44; but the deceitful self&#45;constituted ambassador knew<lb/> well that the dissipated ruler craved for gold&#44; and that that the new ruler he addressed was of a different temperament.  Dissipated and greedy he craved for gold&#44; but<lb/> while his treasury was and sought it in vain in his exhausted treasury.  Jason insinuated himself into<lb/> the good grace of the new monarch&#44; and offered to raise<lb/> the Jewish tribute to about half a million of Dollars every<lb/> year&#44; if his older brother Onias should be stripped of<lb/> the sacerdotal authority&#44; and he himself be made high clothed with it.<lb/>  priest Then as an earnest of his willingness to please the Syrian ruler potentate&#44; the traitor pledged hisself word to give devote a<lb/> large sum towards building in Jerusalem a gymnasium<lb/> and an academy.  In the first&#44; exercises abhorrent to<lb/> the purely chaste religion of Moses were to be intro&#45;<lb/>&#45;duced&#59; in the second&#44; the philosophy of the school of<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Epicurus was to supersede the study of the Law<lb/> and traditions.  Nothing better than that<lb/> could meet with the views of a pof potentate sovereign steeped<lb/> in vice and heathenism.  Jason&#39;s unrighteous scheme&#44;<lb/> was therefore carried out in full.  Onias was<lb/> transported to the capital of Syria&#44; so as not to<lb/> be a hindrance to the consummation of the devised plan. devised<lb/> The youths of Israel soon learnt were but too apt to learn how to rival their idolatrous<lb/> neighbors in public sports and in the subtle &#38; speculation &#38; subtle knowledge<lb/> of the Greeks.  The Temple was deserted&#44; and the<lb/> teachings of the Hebrew Sages despised.  Three<lb/> years the impious Jason thus defied God and grieved<lb/> to death the faithful ones among our people.<lb/>  He had the royal sanction and support&#44; and he had the besides<lb/> young a strong element in Judea on in his side favor.  For our so many of our boys<lb/> and girls were charmed with a change that broke<lb/> the <sic>monothony</sic> of a life under Biblical and Rabbi<lb/>&#45;nical restrictions.  But in an unlucky hour  The old cry which &#91;&#63;&#93; the wrath of the inspired Ezekiel sounded again&#58; &#34;We will be like other nations.&#34;<lb/> and Jason was the man to gratify a prurient wish for reviva imitation.  What&#44; if the pious raised their<lb/> heads in horror at his sending gifts to the Olympic games&#44; so long as he was allowed to wield the sway.  But in an unlucky hour for himself&#44; Jason sent to pay the tribute to<lb/> Antiochus IV&#44; a younger brother&#44; who like the oldest<lb/> was called Onias&#44; but who had taken the more euphonious Grecian<lb/> name of Menclaus.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>The Syrian King was just then preparing to go to wage war<lb/> against Egypt&#44; and naturally he felt the want<lb/> of larger resources to defray the expenses of the company.<lb/>  Menclaus was not ignorant of the way by which his<lb/> perfidious brother relative had won power.  The teaching<lb/> that Jason had practised&#44; served as a pattern for his one<lb/> near relative akin to copy.  Menclaus assured<lb/> Antiochus of an additional sum of three hundred<lb/> thousand dollars&#44; if he should be raised to the high&#45;<lb/>priesthood and Jason be set adrift.  The King<lb/> of Syria thirsted for gold.  To him who had lived<lb/> long enough in Rome to grow unscrupulous about the<lb/> means of obtaining his accomplishing a purpose&#44; Menclaus appeared a<lb/> now preferable better tool than Jason.  Accordingly&#44; he<lb/> deposed the latter and ordered that his younger brother should<lb/> wear the mitre and breast plate the ephod &#38; breast&#45;plate.  But Jason was not<lb/> Onias who rather <sic>that</sic> plunge his country into civil war&#44;<lb/> allowed himself to be divested of the sacred office he worthily filled&#44; and chose to live in exile and obscurity.  Jason resisted his brother&#39;s<lb/> pretentions demands&#44; with the drawn sow sword.  Menclaus was<lb/> too feeble to attempt entering venture unaided upon the field of battle.  The<lb/> reprobate had reckoned upon a schism which he might create&#44;<lb/> but on discovering his dangerous situation&#44; harried back to Antiochus<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>and requested an army to back his pretensions.  To induce secure<lb/> Antiochus to a ready compliance&#44; the atrociously wicked Jew promised<lb/> that once installed into his office&#44; he would use his au&#45;<lb/>&#45;thority to surrender his land to Jupiter and Venus mythology&#44; and chase<lb/> away from thence Adona&#239; and the Torah.  Now began<lb/> the time that tried men&#39;s souls.  Judaism or Gentilism&#59;<lb/> unyielding morality&#44; or a pliant code of ethics&#59; that was the burning<lb/> question.  I shall not relate th eper&#45;<lb/>&#45;fidy of Menclaus in robbing the sanctuary of its precious<lb/> vessels and selling them to heathens to pay the an exhorbitant<lb/> tribute as the price of his apostacy. bribe of iniquity.  I shall not describe<lb/> the indignation which that sacrilege aroused&#44; and the<lb/> manly protest of Onias III from the place of his<lb/> exile banishment&#44; and which protest remonstrance cost the good man his life.<lb/>  I will cast a veil over the unnatural contest between<lb/> Jason and Menclaus&#44; when Antiochus was reported to<lb/> have died in fl fighting Egypt&#44; and I will refer you<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>to the second book of the Maccabees for a narrative of<lb/> the wretched end of the two detestable brother apostate brothers.  But<lb/> I must say a word in honor of the heros who did not<lb/> flinch before the engines of tortures.  Antiochus<lb/> Epiphanes had reso reasons to believe that the Jews favored<lb/> the Egyptian cause and looked anxiously for the down&#45;<lb/>&#45;fall of Syria and its aggressive ruler.  Our coreligionists<lb/> in North Eastern Africa could not have concealed their hatred<lb/> of a King who had encouraged Jason and Menclaus in<lb/> their &#91;&#63;&#93; deed&#44; of injury&#44; who ground down the inhabitants of Pales&#45;<lb/>&#45;tine with exactions&#44; and treated a tributary nation as me&#45;<lb/>&#45;nial slaves.  Upon the battle ground field Antiochus must<lb/> have met in Alexandria Memphis and elsewhere many Hebrews<lb/> <sic>levelling</sic> their arrows against at his mercenary soldiers.<lb/>  And when he moreover was told that Jerusalem had shown<lb/> signs of gladness at the tidings of his death&#44; he grew<lb/> impatient with revenge.  To wreak it&#44; he beseiged<lb/> the capital of Judea&#44; stormed it&#44; and for three days<lb/> let vented his fury&#44; slaughtering away till the streets swam<lb/> with in blood.  Through it the maddened king<lb/> waded and opened his way to the Temple.  He resolved<lb/> to pollute what Jews held as Hebrews considered sacred.  Impure beasts<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>were seethed on the fire of the golden altar&#44; and the holy courts besmeared with the loathsome flesh of the swine.<lb/>  To render the situation still more unbearable&#44; he left as<lb/> governor of Judea a certain one Phillip&#44; a man of a ruffianly&#44; ruthless<lb/> and and rapacious. disposition.  Then he sanguinely under&#45;<lb/>&#45;took a second campaign against Egypt.  He had<lb/> humbled Palestine to the dust&#59; if he could only subjugate<lb/> the proud kingdom upon the Nile&#44; his name would be dreaded<lb/> in the East Orient.  Pont Antiochus IV committed the same error<lb/> into which Antiochus III had fallen.  He forgot to<lb/> reckon an outside power that stood in every King&#39;s way&#44;<lb/> and dictated terms which dared not be refused.  Alexandria<lb/> was very nigh within the grasp of the Syrian ruler potentate&#44; when<lb/> he received a message from Rome couched in these terms&#58;<lb/> &#34;Antiochus shall not make woe on the Ptolemies.&#34;  The<lb/> commissioner who presented the missive was happened to be an old<lb/> friend whose intimacy the <sic>combatting</sic> king ruler had enjoyed<lb/> during his stay in the eternal city.  Antiochus fancied relying<lb/> on that circumstance fancied that he might evade the<lb/> danger of a denial reply answer question.  But the Roman drawing a circle<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>on the sand with the point of his staff forbid<lb/> Antiochus coming close to him before having assented to<lb/> the order of the senate.  In utter confusion &#38; humiliation Epiphanes&#44;<lb/> &#34;the illustrious&#44;&#34; stammered out &#34;I will.&#34;  It has<lb/> been written that the wrath of a king is a herald of death.<lb/>  To our fathers it proved death&#44; but also resurrection.  Antiochus<lb/> retraced his steps from the spot whence he had imagined to re&#45;<lb/>&#45;turn covered with glory.  Judea lay in his way.  Upon it he<lb/> would exhaust his deep&#45;seated rancour and thus allay his mortification.<lb/>  Israel shall be no more a religion and a people.  Extermination<lb/> or Grecianism must now be the alternative.  The Abrahamic<lb/> covenant&#44; the Sabbath&#44; the dietary laws are an insult to civi&#45;<lb/>&#45;lization&#44; let none be so rash as to observe them.  The money<lb/> for Temple worship&#44; shall replenish the empty coffers of the<lb/> ruling sovereign.  And to execute this satanic decree&#44; Appollonius<lb/> was charged to spread terror around by fire and sword.  But<lb/> the extreme evil brought its wholesome cure.  When tender women suffered themselves to be thrown<lb/> from a high tower with their circumcised infants tied round their necks&#44; rather than<lb/> live in sin&#59; when men venerable for their age and character&#44; allowed the rack to tear<lb/> their bodies&#44; rather than let a desecration of the Law pollute their souls&#44; then a spirit<lb/> which had seemed irreconcilibly extinguished hopelessly quenched&#44; flashed up anew.  Metoism tolled.  Men buckled on the armour to strike for their civil and religious rights upon Zion hills the ban&#45;<lb/>&#45;ner of freedom waved&#44; set up by pure hands patriotism&#44; pious ardor and<lb/> the love of Truth.</p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
