<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF4_9</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_9_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_9_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_9_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_9_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_9_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_9_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_9_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_9_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_9_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_9_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_9_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_9_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_9_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_9_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_9_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff4_9_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>An exegetical discourse<lb/> on Haftorat Vaera<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  A deceased friend&#44; to whose opinion I listened<lb/> deferentially&#44; said to me once that in order to confirm Israelites<lb/> on their belief&#44; the Pastor ought to mingle socially with his<lb/> flock&#44; and seek opportunities by which to offer the wavering a<lb/> wholesome advice&#44; and explain points in the religion which<lb/> need elucidation.  By which saying&#44; my valued friend meant&#44;<lb/> that a preacher ought not to limit himself to the lessons<lb/> imparted from the pulpit&#44; but he should supplement them<lb/> by others&#44; taught in the course of easy conversation.  For the latter may leave a deeper impression&#44; than a set discourse&#44; necessarily formal in its character.  But<lb/> it must be candidly admitted that the occasions on which<lb/> the Jewish minister can combine popular instruction with<lb/> familiar intercourse&#44; are extremely rare.  The topics in which<lb/> he will be engaged when visiting the members of his congre&#45;<lb/>&#45;gation will vary&#44; of course&#44; according to the disposition and men&#45;<lb/>&#45;tal capacities of each individual&#44; but as a rule&#44; they do not<lb/> have any bearing upon subjects tending to spiritual im&#45;<lb/>&#45;provement.  The days when a Rabbi was specially em&#45;<lb/>&#45;ployed as the mentor of a Hebrew household&#44; remain<lb/> only in the memory of a few.  The days when a Rabbi<lb/> was almost oraclelarly consulted touching cases of conscience&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>and the right understanding of Biblical or Talmudical<lb/> sentences&#44; are not likely to revive in our midst.  Nay&#44; a<lb/> sense of delicacy will urge now a pastor to avoid such dis&#45;<lb/>cussion&#44; for ignorance of the laws&#44; and negligence of the<lb/> precepts are unfortunately so <sic>wilfully</sic> kept&#44; that a remark<lb/> ingenuously made&#44; a word dropped unguardedly may<lb/> be interpreted a deliberate insult offered in a man&#39;s own<lb/> private dwelling.  Not so&#44; however&#44; when the pulpit is<lb/> the medium through which popular instruction is conveyed.<lb/>  What emanates from it will never be construed into pers&#45;<lb/>&#45;nalities&#44; and even if it must unavoidably be less flowing<lb/> and less effective than a friendly interchange of religious<lb/> thoughts&#44; it will have the merit of reaching a multitude&#44;<lb/> prepared&#44; in all likelihood&#44; to hera hear some distasteful<lb/> truths.  Without&#44; therefore&#44; setting aside any opportunity<lb/> by which to strengthen our fellow&#45;believers on the doctrines<lb/> &#38; tenets of our faith&#44; I judge&#44; that&#44; as we are at present constituted&#44;<lb/> this place is the fittest and most acceptable for its pur&#45;<lb/>&#45;pose.  The waters of life flowing therefrom&#44; will not&#44; I<lb/> trust&#44; turn into waters of Merebah&#44; filling some with<lb/> displeasure&#44; and giving others the pains&#44; and heart&#45;burnings<lb/> of censure undeserved.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>The prefatory observations&#44; just made&#44; were elicited&#44; my<lb/> dear Brethren&#44; from by the Haftorah of this Sabbath.  Study&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing it&#44; in connection with the chapter succeeding it&#44; I la&#45;<lb/>&#45;mented within myself&#44; that the practice of devoting an hour<lb/> every day to the reading of Holy Writ&#45;&#45;as suggested by<lb/> one of Israel&#39;s nobblest daughters&#45;&#45;Grace Aguilar&#45;&#45;in some<lb/> of her excellent writings&#45;&#45;was not usually followed.<lb/>  Much of our time is frittered away in pursuits&#44; unimportant&#44;<lb/> if not trivial&#44; but that which would afford a thorough acquain&#45;<lb/>&#45;tance with the imparting of God and his prophets&#44; and hence<lb/> the ability to confound the unbeliever infidel&#44; does not occupy our<lb/> minds.  Indeed&#44; I readily believe&#44; that were it not for<lb/> this holy institution&#45;&#45;the Synagogue&#45;&#45;some of our young<lb/> offspring would know as much of the book that lies at<lb/> the foundation of the religion we have inherited&#44; and when we are<lb/> sworn to perpetuate transmit to posterity&#44; as of the laws of Confucius a Zoroaster.<lb/>  Parents&#44; nowadays are so <sic>wholy</sic> engaged in the engrossing<lb/> object of running after wealth&#44; that they cannot<lb/> halt in their course&#44; and inquire whether those who must<lb/> perpetuate their names&#44; have acquired any knowledge<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>of the volumes&#44; which will enable them to remain<lb/> intelligently within the fold.  But let me not be<lb/> this morning profuse in the dispensation of rebukes.<lb/>  And since it is from the here that popular instruction must<lb/> reach all&#44; let me rather crave your attention to some<lb/> scriptural explanations.<lb/></p>
            <p>The effusions of Ezekiel which&#44; as a model of ornate<lb/> and flowery style&#44; delight the lover of literature&#44; possess<lb/> a still stronger attraction to him that goes in search after<lb/> truth.  They mirror forth the power of diverse inspiration.<lb/>  The hand of time has marked twenty three centuries on the<lb/> world&#39;s dial&#44; since the priestly bard spoke&#44; but the whole<lb/> universe may wax old&#44; and wear out like a garment&#44; yet<lb/> the words he uttered will stand unaltered.  We have heard<lb/> him this Sabbath foretell the downfall of a kingdom<lb/> once famous&#44; and glittering with the stars of achieved<lb/> glories.  From the land of the North&#44; whither the son<lb/> of &#91;&#63;&#93; was early taken captive&#44; his far&#45;reaching eye<lb/> surveys the majestic Nile.  It sees it deserted of<lb/> the huge dragon that ruled it.  The prophet&#39;s vision<lb/> dives deeper still&#44; when lo&#33; all the countless denizens<lb/> of the swelling river&#44;&#45;&#45;dragged irresistibly after the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>watery monster&#45;&#45;are drawn to a dry land&#44; there to<lb/> meet an invetil inevitable death.  You understand&#44; my<lb/> Brethren&#33; the application.  That people who had often<lb/> proved to our credulous fathers&#44; when struggling mightily<lb/> against Assyria and Babylon&#44; a &#34;staff of reed&#44; which<lb/> breaks under the hand that leans on it&#34; for support&#44; that<lb/> treacherous people&#44; must bear the weight of their inequities.<lb/>  Pharaoh and his subjects will be chased away ignominiously<lb/> from their territories.  During forty years they who boasted<lb/> of their greatness prowess&#44; will be subjected to a foreign power&#44;<lb/> imposing humiliation and banishment.  And though at<lb/> the end of that period&#44; the term of national degradation would<lb/> also expire&#44; yet they who trod again the native soil<lb/> would never regain attain the height from which they had<lb/> been hurled down.  We read &#34;I will restore the captivity<lb/> of Egypt&#44; and cause them to return to the land of Pathros<lb/> &#40;Tebaides&#41;&#44; but they shall be there a lowly kingdom&#34;<lb/>  And what is here foretold in general terms&#44; is expressed in<lb/> the next chapter pointedly and definitely.  &#34;A prince out<lb/> of the land of Egypt shall rise no more&#34; &#40;XXX 13.&#41;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Now&#44; I am not in possession of the records from<lb/> which to show&#44; beyond dispute&#44; that how and when the<lb/> first prediction was accomplished.  While unbelievers&#45;&#45;ever<lb/> busy to throw discredit upon the pages of inspiration&#45;&#45;fli<lb/> flatly deny that it ever became a relia reality&#44; ancient<lb/> history relates that during the period specified by<lb/> Ezekiel&#44; the Ethiopians&#44; having made an inroad into the<lb/> country of Myraim&#44; held it entirely under subjection.<lb/>  Still&#44; I am unable through a defect in Chronological<lb/> accounts to ascertain whether the event to which I have<lb/> reference is identical with that foreseen by the priestly<lb/> bard.  Strongly inclined as I feel to think that the<lb/> two incidents tally exactly&#44; I would not venture upon<lb/> an assertion damaging the cause of truth&#44; even in the to defend Holy<lb/> Writ from the aspersions of infidelity.  But what I can&#45;<lb/>&#45;not state with precision regarding the first prediction&#44;<lb/> I am qualified to say touching that which follows it&#44;<lb/> &#34;A prince out of the land of Egypt&#44; shall use no more.&#34;<lb/>  From the day in which the indomitable Nebuchadnezzar<lb/> set his iron heel upon nations&#44; and crushed dynasties&#44;<lb/> even to this day&#44; the land proud of her sages and states&#45;<lb/>&#45;men&#44; gave birth no more to a Ruler from the Coptic&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>or the original Egyptian&#44; extraction.  Persian&#44; and<lb/> Macedonian&#44; and the world renowned Ptolemies&#44; and<lb/> Roman &#91;&#63;&#93;&#44; sat&#44; in turn&#44; upon the <sic>shyning</sic><lb/> thrones of hte Pharaohs.  The Saracenes and the Mame&#45;<lb/>&#45;lukes mastered the land of the pyramids&#44; and chose a<lb/> king from their midst.  But a prince from the land<lb/> of Egypt arose <sic>weilded</sic> not &#91;&#63;&#93; the sceptre.  Finally&#44; the seat of learning&#44;<lb/> the focus of science&#44; the she that had legislated for and<lb/> taught the known world&#44; sunk into a viceroyalty of<lb/> the Turkish empire.  And through so checkered a history&#44;<lb/> the word of inspiration stood firm&#44; it defied time and all<lb/> its vicissitudes.  In later days the effort has been made<lb/> to redeem redeem that a once famous country from her state<lb/> of objection.  All haver to her present ruler&#44; Il Ismael<lb/> Pacha&#44; and his late parent Abraim&#44; who have strove mi&#45;<lb/>&#45;ghtily to rescue from Extinction the cradle of ancient know&#45;<lb/>&#45;ledge&#44; but if d she does rescuscitate&#44; it be will only<lb/> be the skeleton of her former self with new flesh and<lb/> sinews and a vital spirit gotten from the mart of Euro&#45;<lb/>&#45;pean civilization.<lb/></p>
            <p>Let now skeptics tax their inventive faculties to disprove<lb/> what prophecy has traced on adamant with a pen dipped in inspiration.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Will they dare gainsay what twenty three hundred years<lb/> attest in a single accord of voices&#63;  What power was that<lb/> which tore asunder the veil hiding the future&#63;  What<lb/> keen eye penetrated the unknown&#63;  Was it human<lb/> discernment&#59; the wisdom drawn from earthly surroundings&#63;<lb/>  Did that succeed in <sic>unravelling</sic> events&#44; which brought<lb/> on the scene of the world nations yet uncreated&#63;  Ah&#33;<lb/>  my Brethren&#33; Learn Study to learn&#44; and to draw treasures<lb/> from the store of inexhaustible knowledge.  Ponder well&#44;<lb/> and you will discover that man&#39;s sharpest reasonings&#44; when<lb/> set up in open antagonism to God&#39;s word are comparable<lb/> to that statue which had a golden head&#44; but feet of<lb/> clay.  It drops down at the first blow.  Vain<lb/> are the endeavours of the skeptics to prop make it with the rise and stand<lb/> a staff borrowed from chance. upon &#91;&#63;&#93;.  Your great prop&#44; change O infidels&#33;<lb/> chance can never account for incidents succeeding each other in<lb/> <sic>marvellous</sic> unity.  Was it indeed men chance that a tribe<lb/> still existing&#44; and number&#44; possibly&#44; a million of human<lb/> beings&#44; distinct in their dialect&#44; in their features&#44; and<lb/> in their habits&#44; should not to this day raise a ruler<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>from their ranks.  A chance that the Copts&#44; who<lb/> are noted for their shrewdness and abilities should not<lb/> sit again upon the throne&#44; which their ancestors&#44; the<lb/> Pharaohs had made illustrious&#63;  Never&#44; my Brethren&#33;<lb/>  We have learnt to believe that there is a Providence meet<lb/> meting out to nations as well as individuals their<lb/> due.  That God ranks high and brings low.  We have<lb/> learnt that they who have despoiled and consumed<lb/> the house of Jacob&#44; kindled with their own hands the<lb/> fire that extinguished their wit and their glory begot their<lb/> existence.  We that have seen our persecutors face<lb/> to face&#44; and outlived them all&#44; believe that&#44; as<lb/> the prophet Zachariah declares &#34;Whosoever toucheth<lb/> &#40;us&#41; you&#44; toucheth the pupil of His eye&#44; or to say it<lb/> in the language of our Haftorah &#34;The Lord will<lb/> execute judgments against all who plunder us<lb/> around&#44; so that it may become known that He<lb/> is the Lord our God.&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>&#40;This discourse was continued at considerable length&#44;<lb/> addressing a Bar Mitzv&#225;&#44; in the course of which&#44; the<lb/> legend of B. J. Ben Lakish and Elijah and the Messiah&#44;<lb/> founded on the sentence &#34;To day if ye obey His voice&#44;&#34; was alluded to.&#41;<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
