<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF11_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_1_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>7 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>&#91;&#63;&#93;<lb/>
                A few words about the law<lb/>
                of Bassar Bechalab &#40;meat &#38; milk&#41;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>An attendant of this Synagogue&#44; whose signature was<lb/> not appended to the note I received&#44; asked on Monday<lb/> last&#44; that I would make to day the Seventh and<lb/> eighth verses of the 18th Chapter of Genesis the topic<lb/> of a discourse.  By referring to the place cited&#44; I dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;covered the object which prompted the request.  For&#44; the<lb/> Biblical narrative speaks of the moral which Abraham<lb/> prepared for the three strangers&#44; he hospitably entertained.<lb/>  The person who addressed me&#44; doubtless wishes to understand<lb/> how the prohibition of using promiscuously meat and<lb/> any milky substance can be reconciled with the doing of the<lb/> founder of our race.  We are told that he took cream<lb/> and the flesh of a calf&#44; and set all before his guests&#44; and<lb/> they did eat.  I might settle the question immediately<lb/> at rest&#44; by remarking that the rule we now observe<lb/> is an institution posterior to the patriarchal times.  Hence<lb/> Abraham could no more keep it than the command&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment of not intermarrying among blood relations&#45;&#45;<lb/> a precept of infinitely greater moment thant that at issue&#45;&#45;<lb/>against which he acted&#44; when he took Sarah&#44; his<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>half&#45;sister for a wife.  But the answer&#44; though<lb/> quite sufficient&#44; might be considered curt&#44; and if<lb/> not so unfavorably interpreted&#44; it might perhaps be looked<lb/> upon as an <sic>skilful</sic> evasion.  To prevent a construction&#44; which<lb/> in any way I would deprecate&#44; I shall possibly be<lb/> compelled to repeat myself.  Some among my audience<lb/> may remember a discourse I once delivered upon that<lb/> same subject&#44; in compliance&#44; I think&#44; with the expressed<lb/> wish of another member of this Congregation.<lb/></p>
            <p>I have not referred at all to that composition of mine&#59;<lb/> for&#44; besides its having been delivered recited before a large assembly&#44;<lb/> I lent the manuscript&#45;&#45;from which I then habitually read&#45;&#45;<lb/>to several friends for perusal.  But as loth as I am<lb/> to rehearse words that have been already heard&#44; I may<lb/> unavoidably present ideas very similar to those I advanced<lb/> on a former occasion.  I shall&#44; however&#44; do so concisely.<lb/>  It is generally known that the prohibition technically<lb/> called &#34;Bassar bechalab&#34; draws its origin from a<lb/> Scriptural sentence written twice in Exodus and once in<lb/> Deuteronomy.  It runs thus&#58; &#34;Thou shalt not seeth the<lb/> kid in its mother&#39;s milk.&#34;  Guided by the light<lb/> of our judgment&#44; we would arrive at the conclusion that the ordinance<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>aims to instill humane feelings into our breasts towards<lb/> even the brute creation&#59; and that it bears analogy<lb/> to the precept forbidding to plough the ground with<lb/> an ox and an ass&#44; because the two animals are unequal<lb/> in strength&#44; and to others prescriptions having evidently the same<lb/> tendency.  Accordingly&#44; the application of the<lb/> rule to all quadrupeds&#44; seems perfectly logical.  So<lb/> did the ancients agree to apply it&#44; and so the writings of<lb/> unbiassed authors testify.  For&#44; our predecessors believed<lb/> that Holy Writ often speaks in general terms&#44; depending<lb/> on tradition for a full explanation of its ordinances.  As<lb/> in the present instance&#44; where the act of seething is simply<lb/> forbidden&#44; not withstanding that the eating and making<lb/> any other use thereof must be included in the prohibition&#44;<lb/> and as we are orally taught.  Maimonides&#44;<lb/> however&#44; entertains an entirely different opinion about<lb/> the object of the statute.  Because the sentence<lb/> in which it is conveyed&#44; occurs two twice in a chapter<lb/> relating to the institution of our holidays&#44; he argues<lb/> that very probably heathen nations&#44; were wont to boil<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>a kid in its mother&#39;s milk and either offer or eat it<lb/> at the festivals in honor of some of their false deities.<lb/>  That he inspired Lawgiver&#44; anxious to separate Israel<lb/> entirely from idolaters&#44; repeatedly cautioned against copy&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing one of their practices&#44; as to say&#58; when you appear before<lb/> your Lord do nothing like the rites of gentilism.<lb/></p>
            <p>The celebrity which the Rabbi aforenamed deservedly enjoys&#44;<lb/> led many to embrace his views as the most acceptable.<lb/>  To me they seem open to serious objections&#44; but in order<lb/> not to enlarge upon a theme I have discussed before&#44; I will<lb/> merely remark&#44; that inasmuch as Moses in the book<lb/> of Deuteronomy connected that statute with those concern&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing animals and fishes from which we must abstain loathe&#44; and<lb/> not with the laws relating to heathen customs&#44; we receive from<lb/> that circumstance a semi&#45;proof against the idea held by<lb/> Maimonides&#44; and in favor of that which I have put forth.<lb/>  I mean&#44; that the Divine Legislator desired us to consider<lb/> the act of eating a kid in its mother&#39;s milk in itself<lb/> an abomination to the Lord&#59; ignoring the cause that<lb/> may or may not have given rise to the prohibition.<lb/>  Now my Brethren&#33; if we accept the oral interpretation&#44;<lb/> supported by logical deductions which extend the rule to all four footed animals&#44; suckling<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>their young&#44; &#40;in the same manner as the commandment<lb/> of not killing an ox or a sheep with its young offspring in one day<lb/> bears a wider meaning than the literal text presents&#41;<lb/>  If we agree that to avoid&#44; by all precautions&#44; feeding on the<lb/> flesh of an animal together with the milk of its mother&#44;<lb/> or of any substance derived from it is by the spirit of the Bible obligatory&#44; we will<lb/> respect the scruples which influenced the Rabbins.<lb/></p>
            <p>The fear that we might unintentionally transgress the law&#44;<lb/> made them hedge it in with numerous fences.  Their motive was pure.  Zeal for their Master impelled them so to act.  I may<lb/> be free to say that as to the regulations of culinary utensils&#45;&#45;<lb/> adding difficulties to our household arrangements&#44; the mater&#45;<lb/>&#45;ials employed by our forefathers may possibly have occasioned<lb/> the restrictions.  The character of their vessels may have<lb/> been such&#44; as to imbibe and retain fluids&#44; differing from<lb/> many now in use&#44; which are harder and less impregnable apt to absorb moisture.<lb/>  But neither do I arrogate to myself the authority of<lb/> acting contrary to setting aside the general practice&#44; nor could i consistently<lb/> encourage its abolition abrogation.  This much I have said in<lb/> answer to the request made in writing by a fellow&#45;believer&#44;<lb/> who probably may wishes to follow the usages of our people<lb/> intelligently.  Should the querist seek fuller inform&#45;<lb/>&#45;ation&#44; I will look for and willingly lend the copy of a<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>more elaborate discourse upon that subject.  Still&#44; I believe conceive that<lb/> what I have briefly stated meets the question without<lb/> evasion or equivocation.  Not that I anticipate flatter myself to have brought<lb/> conviction to minds prejudiced against traditional expositions&#44;<lb/> but that I hope to have shown that the law I we have<lb/> considered this morning stands in the main on logical grounds&#44;<lb/> and that by obeying it we follow a Mosaic injunction&#44;<lb/> according to its sense&#44; and we will acquire merit thereby<lb/> in the sight of the heavenly Legislator.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
