<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF8_9</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1889-11" source="" attested="yes">November 1889</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_9_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_9_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_9_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_9_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_9_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_9_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_9_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_9_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_9_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_9_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_9_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_9_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>123</p>
            
            <p>On the explosion next door to the<lb/>
                Synagogue Nov.&#47;89<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>It must have been in the year 1858&#44; or there&#45;<lb/>about&#44; that in a lecture aiming to influence the<lb/> Mickv&#233; Israel Congregation in a special direction&#44;<lb/> I instanced as an illustration of my topic King David.  I<lb/> showed how the man destined to exchange the<lb/> shepherd&#39;s crook for a royal sceptre&#44; thankful<lb/> because of the success he had personally met&#44;<lb/> and of the victories he had achieved in behalf<lb/> of his nation&#44; wished tangibly to prove his gra&#45;<lb/>&#45;titude to the Disposer of human events.<lb/>  He had built for himself a spacious habitation<lb/> suiting royalty&#44; but the place of God&#39;s wor&#45;<lb/>&#45;ship was still very plain and of small di&#45;<lb/>&#45;mensions.  The son of Jesse lamented that the<lb/> ark in which the ten commandments were<lb/> enshrined&#44; had only a pavilion for its dwelling&#44;<lb/> while he&#44; who owed his elevation to the hea&#45;<lb/>&#45;venly author of those commandments&#44; moved<lb/> at ease in a palatial mansion.  Fain would<lb/> the recipient of Divine favors have raised<lb/> a stately structure in honor of the Most High&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>had not Nathan the prophet dissuaded<lb/> him and promised the <sic>fulfilment</sic> of his<lb/> heart&#39;s desire by means of his progeny.  Impelled<lb/> by that Biblical example&#44; I drew the at&#45;<lb/>&#45;tention of my hearers to the fact that not a<lb/> few among them had risen from lowliness<lb/> to affluence&#44; and that in a like manner as David&#44;<lb/> they had reared for their comfort commodious<lb/> homes&#44; while their house of prayer had remained continued<lb/> for over three quarters of a century in a spot<lb/> which time and surroundings had rendered un&#45;<lb/>&#45;fit for the holy purpose.  Naturally&#44; some<lb/> of the elderly members of this Congregation&#45;&#45;<lb/>most of whom have been since summoned away<lb/> from earth&#45;&#45;deprecated the scheme of a removal which I ad&#45;<lb/>&#45;vocated urged.  To the Cherry St. Synagogue&#44; their<lb/> parents had taken them in the days of child&#45;<lb/>&#45;hood&#59; within its walls they were first called<lb/> to the Law upon reaching their religious ma&#45;<lb/>&#45;jority&#59; round the humble building whose<lb/> remains we have preserved and put beneath<lb/> this structure&#44; clustered many reminiscences<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>sacredly joyful&#44; or devotionally sad.  It<lb/> pained some of our men and women to leave that<lb/> building&#44; and I <sic>sympathised</sic> with their feel&#45;<lb/>&#45;ings.  But the necessity for a removal change became<lb/> imperative.  All know the issue.  In May of<lb/> 1859&#44; the corner stone of this comely edifice<lb/> was laid&#44; and in June of 1860&#44; it was dedicated<lb/> to the glory of Israel&#39;s God.  At a an early stage<lb/> of its early history&#44; when the needs thereof<lb/> were not adequately supplied&#44; and I inef&#45;<lb/>&#45;fectually urged preached a liberal policy in order to<lb/> free it from humiliating encumbrances&#44; a female<lb/> friend of mine to whom I expressed my regrets&#44;<lb/> charged me with having occasioned what I com&#45;<lb/>&#45;plained of.  That good Jewess was already<lb/> advanced in years&#44; and she had parted reluc&#45;<lb/>&#45;tantly with the old Synagogue&#59; hence her reproof at the mention of our financial decline.  Moreover&#44;<lb/> it must be admitted that although the edifice<lb/> we erected here&#44; exceeds the former by far in ele&#45;<lb/>&#45;gance and imposingness&#44; the improvement in the<lb/> locality was not very perceptible.  It was scarcely<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>perceptible appreciable from the start.  Our representatives<lb/> who chose it&#44; understood well its object&#45;<lb/>&#45;ionable points&#44; but they considered the spot<lb/> central&#44; and accessible to our congregants&#44;<lb/> both North and South of our city.  How<lb/> the Hebrew population of Philadelphia has<lb/> spread during the period that we have<lb/> met here to worship&#44; all can easily see.<lb/>  The idea which prompted the selection has not<lb/> had therefore a full realization.  That we<lb/> hold our own&#44; and that&#44; with rare exceptions&#44;<lb/> we miss the legal number to perform Divine<lb/> services at other times and hours besides the<lb/> mornings of Sabbaths and holidays&#44; is indeed<lb/> a source of gratulation.  But if happily&#44;<lb/> despite drawbacks&#44; our number has not<lb/> diminished&#44; the surroundings of our house<lb/> of prayer have deteriorated beyond what<lb/> might have been originally anticipated.<lb/>  Where dwellings stood&#44; factories have sprung<lb/> up.  We are almost encompassed by them.<lb/>  It was to protect ourselves from a noise<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>which made the voice of the speaker nearly<lb/> inaudible&#44; that we raised a brick wall<lb/> on the Northern side at a considerable expense<lb/> which we could then ill afford&#44; and we regret&#45;<lb/>&#45;fully darkened in a measure our own building.  But if<lb/> we shielded ourselves thus&#44; in a measure&#44; from<lb/> an unpleasant neighbor&#44; we could not ward<lb/> off a greater evil that has already twice<lb/> threatened us with severe consequences.  A<lb/> year ago&#44; on a Sabbath day&#44; an explosion<lb/> of some combustible materials&#44; shook this edi&#45;<lb/>&#45;fice&#44; while I was reading the Law&#44; causing a<lb/> panic&#44; which I could hardly check.<lb/>  Fortunately&#44; no harm befell us&#44; but where the<lb/> accident happened one person was fatally<lb/> wounded injured.  Last Monday afternoon the same<lb/> occurrence&#44; in a more serious form&#44; was attended<lb/> with sorrowful results.  Our city papers have<lb/> reported it in details.  I will not distress my hear&#45;<lb/>&#45;ers by an account of a painful nature&#44;<lb/> but the interests of our Sanctuary and the safety<lb/> of those who worship therein demand of us<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>prompt action.  We cannot prevent the<lb/> rattling of cable cars&#44; or the hammering on wood<lb/> and stone&#44; disturbing us particularly in summer<lb/> when our doors &#38; windows are open&#44; but we must guard<lb/> against what may shatter our building and<lb/> imperil our lives.  Upon hearing of the me&#45;<lb/>&#45;lancholy event&#44; I lost no time to seek our<lb/> acting President and urge that he will consult<lb/> municipal authorities and ask the perempt&#45;<lb/>&#45;ory removal of too dangerous a laboratory next<lb/> to our Synagogue.  We are not prepared<lb/> to leave it&#44; because some ones&#44; recklessly<lb/> and unpardonably&#44; use explosive substances but it is<lb/> the bounden duty of the Mayor of Philadelphia<lb/> to make our conventions on this spot free<lb/> from the least danger.  I have deemed<lb/> it advisable to refer to the subject&#44; in the<lb/> hope that any one in our religious body weild&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing influence may exercise it to aid our re&#45;<lb/>presentative in bringing about the immediate<lb/> removal of an object likely to spread destruction.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>I am aware that in the mind of some of my<lb/> constituents&#44; the speediest way to rid ourselves<lb/> of annoyances&#44; is would be to quit these premises and<lb/> build a synagogue in a more eligible locality.<lb/>  But were the suggestion even feasible&#44; I still<lb/> would not be prepared to advocate its acceptance.<lb/>  I am free to confess that I apprehend a<lb/> change of place&#44; which may force or foist<lb/> in a change breeding disunion&#44; and divesting<lb/> this congregation of its venerable aspect.<lb/>  Very night thirty years have passed over our<lb/> heads peacefully&#44; if not prosperously from a<lb/> material point of view&#44; since we entered this<lb/> minor sanctuary with psalmody.  Notwith&#45;<lb/>&#45;standing that our services are capable of impro&#45;<lb/>&#45;vement in several instances&#44; nevertheless<lb/> I may presume to say that conservatism&#44;<lb/> looking to the maintenance of our faith&#44; through<lb/> faithful instruction&#44; has continued to be our aim.<lb/>  We might have accomplished more with larger<lb/> means at our command&#44; but the activity of<lb/> some of our men and women in the line of a<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>sensible progress has not abated.  I do<lb/> not feel certain that the changes which I fear<lb/> would benefit those whom we wish to elevate&#44;<lb/> but certain sure I am that innovations would create<lb/> difficulties which we have hitherto successfully<lb/> avoided.  But independent of ritual con&#45;<lb/>&#45;siderations&#44; I would deeply lament a repetition<lb/> of what I remonstrated against at the time of<lb/> the raising of this structure.  For I have always<lb/> contended that the only method to pursue in<lb/> erecting a house of God&#44; is to be able in all<lb/> honesty to inscribe upon each stone and brick thereof&#44;<lb/> &#34;This belongs to the Lord&#34;.  Experience should<lb/> teach us&#44; besides&#44; how an opposite course might<lb/> drag us to the verge of dissolution.  For whatever<lb/> be our shortcomings congregationally&#44; we would<lb/> never repudiate our indebtedness to individuals<lb/> any more than to corporations&#44; or compel the abandonment of one&#39;s just claims&#44; to relieve our burden.  Rather<lb/> disperse than hold together as a religious orga&#45;<lb/>nization by irreligious means&#59; by the violation<lb/> of the eighth commandment of the Decalogue.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>No&#58; we are not ready to part with<lb/> this holy edifice&#44; though its environments<lb/> detract of its imposingness&#44; but we must<lb/> use every endeavour to let our devotion&#45;<lb/>&#45;al gatherings remain undisturbed&#44; for<lb/> to worship God tranquilly is our right&#44; as<lb/> law abiding citizens of the commonwealth<lb/> of Pennsylvania.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
