<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF1_9</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_9_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_9_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_9_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_9_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_9_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_9_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_9_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_9_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_9_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_9_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_9_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_9_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>The three crowns<lb/>
                an address specially for a Bar Mitzva boy<lb/>
                who was a Cohen<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> The three crowns by which a Mishnic Sage symbolized<lb/> three powers in Israel&#44; shone with oriental brightness.  The Law&#44;<lb/> priesthood&#44; and royalty wore those <sic>jewelled</sic> diadems.  The<lb/> highest among men made obeisance to the Law.  She had<lb/> sent forth freedom order&#44; her attendant&#44; to establish give stability to the social order compact<lb/> and promote the social weal.  Upon honesty she looked with bestowed her<lb/> gracious smiles&#59; at her frowning wickedness was covered with<lb/> shame.  In a spacious chamber of the Temple&#44; whose<lb/> floor of marble stones equal in size and in shape singled it<lb/> out&#44; sat the crowned Law.  She opened her mouth with<lb/> wisdom&#44; and the dictates of truth reason flowed from her lips.<lb/>  You have recognized in her&#44; O fellow&#45;believers&#33; the ancient<lb/> council of our people&#44; the Sanhedrin&#44; shielding the indivi&#45;<lb/>&#45;dual from wrong&#44; bringing the right to light&#44; crushing with<lb/> a ponderous blow the evil&#45;doer&#44; banishing disputes&#44; and guard&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing against encroachments the treasures of national traditions.<lb/>  The diadem adorning that august Senate was answering<lb/> rectitude&#59; the exemplifying of the Divine rule by which the<lb/> guilty poor found no leniency because of their poverty&#44; nor<lb/> the culpable rich judicial connivance by reason of their wealth.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>A fitting representative of the law of God&#44; that<lb/> supreme tribunal of Israel commanded reverence&#44; and ranked<lb/> foremost among our authorities in the days of yore.<lb/></p>
            <p>The second crown sparkled on the brows of priesthood.  Of the<lb/> twelve tribes set apart as custodians of a humanizing religion&#44;<lb/> one family had alone been vested with a power inalienable<lb/> and most exalted.  A close communion with God was vouch&#45;<lb/>&#45;safed solely to Aaron and his descendants.  Their feet could tread<lb/> the spot&#44; which none other dared enter.  And in their hands<lb/> a sacrificial atonements on the outer altar&#44; and the offering burning of<lb/> incense upon the golden altar inlaid with gold within&#44; became a sweet savor to the<lb/> Lord.  The defilements which separated man from his associates&#59; the<lb/> impurities which debarred from admission into the Sanctuary&#44;<lb/> their sacerdotal aspersions washed away.  Distinct in appearance&#44;<lb/> and in apparel the privileged household stood between the Al&#45;<lb/>&#45;mighty Bestower of blessings&#44; and the recipients of His loving&#45;<lb/>&#45;kindness.  They put His name upon the children of Israel&#44;<lb/> and drew down a heavenly influence.  And when the dreaded<lb/> morning arrived&#44; on which the officiating Pontiff penetrated the<lb/> veil that had the holy of holies&#44; and prostrate at that shrine<lb/> made fervent entreaties for his land and for his people&#44; the crown<lb/> of priesthood became grew truly resplendent&#59; so luminous&#44; that all eyes turned<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>towards it as to a sun diffusing light and warmth.<lb/>  The third crown was set upon royalty.  It became well the war&#45;<lb/>&#45;rior and statesman&#44; who sung immortal lays on the melodious<lb/> harp.  The scions of the Davidian stock&#44; whose statement arms<lb/> defended the ancestral heritage&#44; wore it with dignity.  They added<lb/> lustre thereto when the throne subserved the worship&#44; and lent<lb/> influence to the courts of justice.  The brilliancy of that diadem<lb/> radiated then to in all directions.  Multitudes gazed admiringly upon<lb/> the object that mirrored forth righteousness.  A halo of glory<lb/> surrounded the king who rendered his power the staff leading<lb/> securely to the rich fields of national prosperity.  Regal prerogatives so<lb/> nobly beneficently exercised must have endeared the possessors to every<lb/> heart endowed with feelings&#59; must have raised them in every<lb/> mind that correctly thought capable of thinking aright.<lb/></p>
            <p>But the three crowns for which the Mishnic Sage bespeaks<lb/> universal acceptance&#44; often forfeited their claims to respect.<lb/>  The Law cast at times its whole weight on the balance of<lb/> inequity.  It did not spurn the bribe which dim the eyes<lb/> of wisdom&#59; it did not raise uplift the glaive axe to strike crime defiantly<lb/> looking down from every high places.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Of all the numbers of the national council&#44; who<lb/> summoned a prince of the Asmonean race before the bar of justice&#44;<lb/> one only dared meet the looks of sternly to confront the imperious ruler.<lb/></p>
            <p>And how tarnished the crown of priesthood did become&#44; when a<lb/> Jason&#44; &#38; an Alcimus placed it upon their heads&#44; history has<lb/> deploringly described.  The golden plate upon which &#34;holiness<lb/> to the Lord&#34; was inscribed&#44; far from representing the meekness<lb/> of Aaron&#44; that loved peace&#44; and followed it&#44; loved all creatures&#44;<lb/> and suasively won them over to a soul&#45;redeeming faith&#44; represented ambition<lb/> and strive&#44; Grecian ungodliness&#44; and shameless immorality.<lb/>  What need I say of the crown of royalty&#44; which has not<lb/> already been written with a pen dipped in righteous wroth by<lb/> our prophets and annalists&#63;  The instances in which it retained<lb/> its brilliancy are the exception&#59; the occasions whereon it lost<lb/> eveyr spark of the original lustre&#44; are the rale.  Against some<lb/> pure&#45;hearted Josiahs&#44; a score of infamous Jeroboams can be set<lb/> off.  And a Herod in later ages did more to draw hatred and<lb/> contempt upon the regal diadem&#44; than Simon the benefactor<lb/> and the ethnarch of the Jews&#44; or any o the Maccabeans ac&#45;<lb/>&#45;complished to gain for princely authority the esteem of<lb/> their countrymen.<lb/></p>
            <p>But the Sage of the Mishna knew that power engenders<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>haughtiness.  He felt that however responsible&#44; sacred and<lb/> elevated may be the office with which mortals are invested&#44; corruption<lb/> hems it around.  He could but acknowledge that the Sandhedrin<lb/> who administered the law in Israel&#44; commended themselves to the<lb/> reverence of the community.  Perspicuity in judgment&#44; extensive<lb/> a learning an thorough knowledge of Sinaic nature varied and extensive insight broad experience&#44; the performance of duties con&#45;<lb/>&#45;tinued and onerous&#44; must surely entitle to tokens of deference.<lb/>  So likewise he admitted that the ministry&#44; whom God Himself<lb/> had ordained&#44; and through whose agency He promised the remission<lb/> of sin&#59; the Jewish priesthood&#44; delegated from on high&#44; and de&#45;<lb/>&#45;manding for its functions of long training&#44; a body without blemish<lb/> and a mind free from earthly cares&#44; ought to have inspired<lb/> awe and veneration.  And not less than either&#44; the <sic>annointed</sic><lb/> of the Lord&#44; who stood at the breach in the time of danger&#44; and<lb/> averted it by courage and sagacity.  The chief Executive&#44; called<lb/> a King&#44; who exercised illimitable authority to quell seditions&#44;<lb/> and restore <sic>tranquillity</sic> in Zion&#44; was to have called forth sentiments<lb/> of profound respect.  But the Mishnic Sage was could not blind ignore<lb/> to the fact that those three powers too frequently abused&#44; brought<lb/> disgrace upon the country of Israel&#44; and heinously offended the Deity.<lb/>  He must have then have asked himself in the language of the Psalmist&#63; When the<lb/> foundations are being torn down&#44; what can the righteous do&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Is there not society verging at such a junction on the brink of ruin&#63;  Are Where can they no means be found any by which<lb/> it may be still upheld&#63;  If the crowns on which the commonwealth should<lb/> glory presents exhibit only stains and ineffaccable spots&#44; when shall may<lb/> we look for another which may emitting a shining light&#63;<lb/>  And the mind beheld of the olden Sage was shown a crown exceeding all in brightness.  A<lb/> crown of private virtues which the humblest individual may put<lb/> on to the deliverance and exaltation regeneration of the community.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>  R. Simeon writes&#58; &#34;We recognize three crowns&#44; that of the law&#44;<lb/> that of priesthood&#44; and that of royalty&#59; but the crown of a<lb/> good name is vastly their superior&#34; to th&#91;&#63;&#93;.&#34;  It is not dependent<lb/> on a human or even a divine investiture.  Whoever wishes it can<lb/> adorn himself therewith.  Unbending uprightness places<lb/> it at one&#39;s disposal.  For the man social being who never stooped to<lb/> meanness.  The man being who can bear himself heat aloft in the con&#45;<lb/>&#45;sciousness of having pursued a line of conduct honorable and<lb/> philanthropic will be acknowledged the King of virtue glorious nature&#39;s nobleman.<lb/>  He confers upon the commonwealth the greatest good.<lb/>  An example of unflinching rectitude.  Like a sweet&#45;scented plant&#44; which<lb/> diffuses its fragrance beyond the spot wherein it has grown&#44;<lb/> so do the just spread beyond further than their own circles their distinguished qualities.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>The world may perchance be tardy in ad confessing its indebtedness so such.<lb/>  For while many will agree to ostracize an Arestides because<lb/> of his overshadowing probity&#44; few will may be willing to set him up<lb/> at once as a pattern of righteousness worthy of being copied.  But a high character&#44;<lb/> though silent is self&#45;asserting.  It compels recognition admiration and<lb/> imitation.  It wears a crown studded with sparkling gems&#44; sed shed&#45;<lb/>&#45;ding it rays upon myriads.  Even vice is forced to bend the<lb/> knee before that nobility.  The hypocritical who feigns inno&#45;<lb/>&#45;cence&#44; and dissemble in order to cover up depravity&#44; pays a tribute to<lb/> the real virtue they does not possess.  They brands their own<lb/> demeanour with the stigma of reproach&#44; while professing<lb/>to do homage to goodness.  And a good name&#44; which raises its possessor to the height of the social edifice&#44; which he acts well his part in life&#44; has still a powerful hold upon his mind&#44; when all which is terrestrial vani shes apace.  I think that the moralist&#44; who<lb/> declared in the same sentence the superiority of a good name to<lb/> precious ointment&#44; and the day of death to that of one&#39;s birth&#44;<lb/> intended to impart this grandest of lessons truth.  The hour of depar&#45;<lb/>&#45;ture from earth by to in him who has deservedly enjoyed a reputation<lb/> for sterling honest and sincere piety is frequent with delights&#44; a herald of glories ineffable<lb/> and unfading in comparison of which the pleasures pomp and honor and most exalted positions of this probationary world&#44; from<lb/> the hour we were ushered in to its very last&#44; are but phantoms.<lb/></p>
            <p>Yes&#33; law&#44; priesthood and royalty may demand obeisance.  A good<lb/> name receives it spontaneously.  The august Sanhedrin&#44; holding<lb/> in hand the scales of justice&#59; the majestic priest approaching in spotless<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>white&#44; ministering before the sacred depository of the ark of the covenant&#44; the monarch bearing the<lb/> destiny of a realms on his sceptre the hilt of his sword a wave of his sceptre may hope for an eternity of<lb/> glory only if they exercised power only for the public weal&#59; and never<lb/> for their own aggrandizement&#44; but that being who&#44; treading the hum&#45;<lb/>&#45;blest walks of life&#44; gathered the crown of a good name&#44; will<lb/> move on with surer steps towards the unknown future&#59; be&#45;<lb/>&#45;cause preceded by indubitable righteousness&#44; followed by the<lb/> v richest blessings of a multitude.<lb/></p>
            <p>That is the crown with which I most earnestly wish eagerly desire that you<lb/> my dear young brother&#45;&#45;Bar Mitzva&#39;&#45;&#45;be decked.  The oil of<lb/> sanctity power poured whilom upon the head of your ancestors<lb/> has not lost all its perfume.  It clings yet in a measure to the family of<lb/> Aaron.  Because you retain it&#44; you are given preeminence<lb/> in some of our retinal observances.  And you will have the right<lb/> to pronounce&#44; in the words of Israel&#39;s God&#44; a threefold benediction upon<lb/> the house of your brethren.  Let the lips that utter it be<lb/> purified sevenfold.  The lava in to which you seek resort to be cleansed&#44;<lb/> shall be honesty of purpose.  If the knowledge of your<lb/> sacerdotal descent&#44; can add fervor to your devotions&#44; a stronger<lb/> incentive to deeds of exemplary probity and enlarged humanity&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>cherish it.  If it is incapable of breathing into your<lb/> soul&#44; holy aspirations&#44; cease to glory in a high extraction&#59;<lb/> direct your thoughts to the future that you may gain a crown<lb/> infinitely superior to that which your predecessors ore in the<lb/> days of antiquity&#59; even the crown of a good name.<lb/></p>
            <p>Fortunately you are not left unaided in your striving for<lb/> that <sic>inperishable</sic> acquisition.  From all your surroundings<lb/> a voice of encouragement resounds.  You are quickened by hearts<lb/> that yearn after righteousness.  You are guided by minds&#44; which<lb/> the rays of pure faith has have illumined.  You cannot go astray.<lb/>  With such instruction&#44; and such an example you can never forswear<lb/> yourself.  My mental vision follows you through a straight path&#44; <lb/>marked by parental footsteps.  You proceed onward with a manly<lb/> gait.  You halt&#44; to gather a precious object within your reach.<lb/>  It is the crown of a good name.  Your brows an is adorned there&#45;<lb/>&#45;with.  Society beholds it and pays you obeisance.  The<lb/> house of your brethren praise her that gave you nurture&#44; and<lb/> him that early offered early &#91;&#63;&#93; fathers&#39; counsel.  This congregation of the<lb/> faithful&#44; exult in your noble traits of character.  Jacob<lb/> rejoices&#44; Israel is exceedingly glad.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
