<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF5_13</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_13_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_13_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_13_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_13_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_13_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_13_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_13_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_13_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_13_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_13_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_13_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_13_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET.<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; 189<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Post Biblical<lb/>
                56<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>The biographical sketch of Solomon Ben Addereth<lb/> of Barcelona the Spanish Rabbi of whose life&#45;work<lb/> I spoke last&#45;&#45;in the course of my Post Biblical lectures&#44; requires a supplement and I shall<lb/> present it this day morning.  Among the worldly learned of his<lb/> time&#44; a degree of restiveness at religious rules was<lb/> being manifested in Spain of the middle ages.  Not unlike in our own days&#44; Jewish<lb/> men talked inconsiderately about the uselessness of<lb/> ritualism.  This One would say&#58; &#34;It Surely it is not necessary<lb/> to place some scriptural sentences against our door&#45;<lb/>posts&#44; in order to be reminded of God&#39;s absolute Unity.<lb/>  Our reason shows that a division of power&#44; implies<lb/> insufficiency in some&#44; who have a share in that power&#44; to act<lb/> singly&#44; whereas harmony in nature proclaims the<lb/> Creator All&#45;mighty.  Another would tell sophistically argue that we<lb/> can better raise our soul to a higher plane&#44; best by con&#45;<lb/>&#45;sidering its wonderful faculties and not than by remain&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing inactive upon the seventh day.  A third<lb/> would allegorize and declare that the prohibition<lb/> to kindle fire upon the Sabbath&#44; was meant simply<lb/> as a warning against stirring up the fire of contention&#59;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>while not a few&#44; following the system of Philo<lb/> the Alexandrian&#44; tried to explain every thing in<lb/> the Pentateuch&#44;&#45;&#45;history&#44; doctrines and ordinances&#45;&#45;&#44; as<lb/> types and figures&#44; suitably to a fantastic philosophy<lb/> then in vogue and not yet extinct yet altogether.<lb/>  It is easily seen perceived that by such a procedure&#44; Ju&#45;<lb/>&#45;daism would be reduced to a shadow.  Stripped<lb/> of ceremonialism&#44; which which is designed to keeps the spirit thereof<lb/> alive ever present in the minds of its votaries&#44; all abstract<lb/> ideas&#44; advanced by theorists&#44; could never preserve<lb/> the religion of Moses alive among the disciples of the<lb/> archprophet.  Indeed&#44; it was this over philo&#45;<lb/>&#45;sophising itching of our Hellenistic brethren&#44; that<lb/> finally estranged them from our God and people.<lb/></p>
            <p>Ben Addereth foresaw at a glance the inevitable outcome<lb/> of a growing indifference to the precepts&#44; still he<lb/> hesitated to exert himself in a manner that<lb/> might he conceived probable likely to hold back the <sic>treatening</sic> evil.  At one<lb/> time&#44; conscious of the influence of his name&#44; he<lb/> inclined to put under ban all books&#44; apt to under militate<lb/> &#45;mine against the conservation of the faith.  At another&#44; he resolved to forbid<lb/> young persons from reading books on philosophy.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Again&#44; fearing such a study&#44; he sought to prohibit<lb/> it more generally still.  This mind&#45;wavering<lb/> of the Barcelona Rabbi Sage&#44; was not calculated to strength&#45;<lb/>&#45;en orthodoxy&#44; but it had a cause&#44; and that cause<lb/> deserves respect.  Like his illustrious preceptor&#44;<lb/> Moses Nachmanides&#44; he Ben Addereth feared to offend the memory<lb/> of the greatest Rabbi that Spain produced.  Had<lb/> not Maimonides penned volumes upon philosophy&#44;<lb/> logic and metaphysics&#63;  Was it fit for that a Barce&#45;<lb/>&#45;lona Rabbi should indirectly even to declare&#44; then writings left<lb/> by the famous Cordovan&#44; dangerous and unholy&#63;  Ben<lb/> Addereth shrunk from what he deemed a reflection<lb/> on the character of his illustrious celebrated predecessor.<lb/>  But while he was thus a prey to conflicting thoughts&#44;<lb/> a great scholar&#44; hailing from Germany arrived in Spain.<lb/>  Asher Ben Jechiel&#44; like the bulk of his Jewish<lb/> countrymen&#44; had known Moses Ben Maimon only<lb/> as a Talmudist of unsurpassed abilities.  He<lb/> felt scandalized on learning that the author of a<lb/> most exhaustive work on ritual laws&#44; had made<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Aristotle&#44; Avicenna and Arderoes subjects of<lb/> deep meditations.  He experienced no hesitancy in<lb/> urging Ben Addereth jointly to launch an anathema<lb/> against books that diverted the minds of Hebrew<lb/> youths from the written and oral Law.  In Ger&#45;<lb/>&#45;many&#44; he had been an eye witness of the love and<lb/> devotion of Rabbinists to the cause of Israel&#44; and for<lb/> that alone would he labor.  His The brightest illustration of devotion to the faithful&#44; was that set by his own teacher.  Meir<lb/> of Rottenberg had preferred to die in a dungeon<lb/> and lie unburied&#44; to having his congregation ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;posed to the rapacity of a brutal populace&#44;<lb/> that demanded exorbitant sums as the prize of<lb/> his deliverance.  In Germany&#44; he Asher had seen the what sore trials<lb/> which tested the unflagging attachment of Jews to Juda&#45;<lb/>&#45;ism.  For&#44; the antisemitism of Germany&#44; which now<lb/> takes the shape of calumny to make as odious<lb/> and to socially to ostracise us&#44; in the middle of<lb/> the thirteenth century&#44; when Asher Ben Jechiel<lb/> lived&#44; had recourse to plunder and murder&#44; in order<lb/> to gain its iniquitous purposes.  I belive that<lb/> our brethren of the Ashkenazic ritual have a<lb/> record of martyrs hewn down unmercifully by the axe of the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>gallant &#34;Knights of the Cross&#44;&#34; who sped on to the<lb/> conquest of the &#34;Holy Sepulchre&#44;&#34; through rivers of<lb/> innocent blood&#44;&#45;&#45;the blood of thousands who refused<lb/> to turn traitors to their fathers&#39; belief creed.  The pupil<lb/> of Meir of Rottenburg&#44; as Pastor of a large commun&#45;<lb/>&#45;ity&#44; trembled at the sword which hung on over the head<lb/> of his flock.  Fain&#44; would he have jeopardised his<lb/> existence to save that of his people&#44; but unable it did not lie in<lb/> his power to work out salvation.<lb/>  To avert the imminent peril fate of his teacher and predecessor&#44; he fled with his wife<lb/> and their eight sons.  They wandered together from city to<lb/> city&#44; in search of safety.  They reached Italy&#44; but<lb/> feared to remain&#44; lest they be extradited&#44; for were they<lb/> not&#44; forsooth&#44; fugitives from royal justice&#44; and did not then a German emperor side with the Italian Ghibellins to win a kingdom&#63;  Parents<lb/> and children travelled further journeyed further in their self&#45;imposed exile&#44; and inclined to settle in<lb/> South France&#44; but Asher may must have heard of the fame<lb/> of Ben Addereth.  He would visit the renowned Tal&#45;<lb/>&#45;mudist in his home.  At Barcelona&#44; the two kindred spirits may<lb/> have counselled together and planned a method&#44; then<lb/> prevailing&#44; to hinder the spread of a learning&#44; which<lb/> they considered hurtful to Judaism.  The <sic>excomu&#45;<lb/>&#45;nication</sic> went forth.  None shall dare study Greek science<lb/> and Greek philosophy&#44; who has not reached at least his<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>twenty fifth year&#44; and that rule shall be<lb/> enforced during the next half a century.  But<lb/> beyond Barcelona&#44; and possibly Toledo&#44; the harsh mea&#45;<lb/>sure does not seem to have gained a foothold.<lb/>  In Spain&#44; in Italy and in South France&#44; lovers of<lb/> general learning wide culture arose to antagonise the anathema.<lb/>  In the last named country especially&#44; science and<lb/> philosophy found a vigorous defender in a youth&#44;<lb/> master of an incisive style.  Jedajah Happenini<lb/> of Bezier&#44; wrote with a wonderfully facile pen.<lb/>  He made more than one stroke of that pen cut the<lb/> knot with which some a well meaning but mistaken piety&#44; would tie up the wheel<lb/> of progressive studies.  That French Jew pleaded<lb/> with his Spanish contemporary senior of Spain in behalf of unrestricted<lb/> knowledge.  In his unbounded admiration for Mai&#45;<lb/>&#45;monides&#44; he so concluded his book called &#34;Investigations<lb/> into the world&#34; Oh &#34;O my mind&#44; shape thy course<lb/> in every direction&#44; after that which Moses son of<lb/> Maimon has indicated.  For the last was he&#44; yet the greatest<lb/> among the School of Gaonic teachers&#59; incomparable since<lb/> the closing of the Talmud.  By doing thus&#44; ye thou wilt<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>discover the secrets of science and religion&#44; and learn to<lb/> fear the Lord God.&#34;  Ben Addereth may have<lb/> felt some a qualm of conscience&#44; when addressed by<lb/> a forcible opponent reasoner.  Not so Asher Ben Jechiel&#44; for<lb/> to a contemporary fond of metaphysics&#44; he said&#58; &#34;We<lb/> are not learned in your kind of logic&#44; thank God for it&#44; be&#45;<lb/>&#45;cause experience has demonstrated that it robs us<lb/> of the fear of the Lord.&#34;  It would be an error&#44; however&#44;<lb/> to suppose that he who spoke so deprecatingly of<lb/> logic&#44; was illogical in his writings.  On the con&#45;<lb/>&#45;trary&#44; he largely possessed the qualities which con&#45;<lb/>&#45;stitute a clear sighted headed&#44; even minded author.  For the German Rabbi<lb/> having taken up his residence in Toledo as ecclesiastical chief&#44; disseminated<lb/> knowledge by productions evening of vast erudition and <sic>systematic&#45;<lb/>&#45;cally</sic> designed and laid lucidly laid out.<lb/>  They are principally Talmudical&#44; but invaluable&#44; as<lb/> aids to the understanding of decisions arrived at by<lb/> the Sages in their varied discussions.  A Remarkable<lb/> &#91;&#63;&#93; incident is that which shows the traits which distinguishing the father&#44;<lb/> were inherited by to be reflected in the life of each of his numerous children.  None can<lb/> too highly estimate the mental strength of the eight<lb/> sons of our Asher.  For they excelled in several<lb/> departments of Biblical&#44; and Talmudical and Cabbalistic lore.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Most notable was the third son&#44; Jacob&#44; who has<lb/> left behind the obvious luminous proofs of splendid his capacities in the &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> At the beginning of or &#34;Four rows&#34;  Early in the present century&#44; a scho&#45;<lb/>&#45;larly Christian&#44; the possessor owner of rare works&#44; donated<lb/> to the Turin royal library more than one thousand volumes&#44;<lb/> some printed&#44; others in manuscript.  Among the<lb/> latter&#44; were found seventy six Hebrew epitaphs&#44; which<lb/> an ancient <sic>traveller</sic> had copied from tomb stones in a burial<lb/> ground at Toledo&#44; in Spain.  Published in Prague fifty<lb/> years ago&#44; at the instance of the untiring Professor Luzzatto&#44;<lb/> I was enabled privileged to read those inscriptions&#44; as they stood over upward of<lb/> five hundred years ago&#44; upon the tombstones graves of Asher Ben<lb/> Jechiel&#44; of some of his children&#44; grand&#45;children and<lb/> respective wives.  The elegists did not indulge in exag&#45;<lb/>&#45;gerations&#44; when bestowing on the distinguished dead the<lb/> tribute due to sterling piety and exceptional activity in<lb/> the field of religious knowledge.  And if the report be<lb/> true&#44; that during an outbreak in the kingdom of Navarre&#44;<lb/> several of that prominent family sanctified the name<lb/> of Israel&#39;s God by suffering martyrdom&#44; we must hold the<lb/> memory of those saintly beings in the deepest veneration.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>I may not inopportunely&#44; I think&#44; conclude this<lb/> sketch&#44; by quoting a few of the sentiments in Asher<lb/> Ben Jechiels last will.  Let them serve as a clear<lb/> demonstration that strict orthodoxy and liberal views<lb/> can be and are closely allied.  The following I have<lb/> read the following among other recommendations of the father to his<lb/> children&#58; &#34;Be heartily sincere and true with every body&#59; with<lb/> those even who do not belong to our religion...show<lb/> a courteous demeanour to all....Be heedful not<lb/> to excite to anger a person of another belief....<lb/> Do not speak evil of any person&#59; mock and<lb/> vilify no human being...If one addresses you un&#45;<lb/>&#45;becomingly&#44; give no rude answer...Put none to<lb/> shame&#59; do not abuse the powers you may possess...<lb/> Never cease to make friends&#59; avoid making a<lb/> single enemy....Be the first to greet your<lb/> neighbors&#59; be they the adherents of any faith....<lb/> Make not gold the main object of your exist&#45;<lb/>&#45;ence&#44; for that longing is idol worship&#45;&#45;a heathen<lb/> religion&#34;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
