<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF10_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_2_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>on Parashat Shemot &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>
                This lecture was recast&#44; enlarged and<lb/>
                improved upon considerably in &#91;&#63;&#93; 96<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  A friend sent me lately a short time ago a touching story<lb/> to read.  Written originally in Sanskrit&#45;&#45;a language<lb/> no longer spoken&#44; but still used among peoples of India<lb/> in their public worship&#45;&#45;it had been translated into<lb/> faultless English.  The story purported to show how<lb/> exquisitely tender&#44; even towards even dumb animals&#44; are the<lb/> feelings of nations&#44; whom we consider uncivilized.<lb/>  I gladly admit&#44; to the honor of all my fellow mor&#45;<lb/>&#45;tals&#44; that sentiments of humanity are not the<lb/> peculiar passion of any sect or denomination.<lb/>  I hold that they are untrue to nature&#44; &#39;s imparting&#44;<lb/> who cruelly treat lower creatures.  A forcible reminder<lb/> of the instinct of compassion implanted by the beneficent<lb/> Creator in our breasts&#44; is the sentence of the pslamist<lb/> so which observant Israelites often repeat in their prayers&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;The Lord is good to<lb/> all&#44; and His mercies are over all His works.&#34;  Not<lb/> less forcible is the Rabbinical illustration of that<lb/> Scriptural passage.  I will present it.  Many among my audience have heard of the compiler of the Mishnah.  When we<lb/> search through Talmudical literature&#44; we shall find<lb/> that none stands higher than Judah the Prince&#44;<lb/> Chief of the colleges which flourished in Tiberias about the 3rd century of the vulgar era.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>In his life time he that sage was extolled for the exercise<lb/> of rare virtues&#44; and succeeding generations have<lb/> encircled his memory with a halo of sanctity.  They<lb/> have called him Rabbenu Hakkadosh&#44; &#34;our Rabbin<lb/> the holy&#44;&#34; because by his influence piety and activity<lb/> the Mishnah or the oral Laws was were collected and formulated.  Never&#45;<lb/>&#45;theless&#44; with an impartiality deserving of all respect&#44;<lb/> the Talmudists tell us that the bodily ailments to<lb/> which Judah the Prince became subject&#44; were a<lb/> punishment for an act of his harshness towards a poor<lb/> beast.  On one occasion a calf about to be led to the slaughter house&#44;<lb/> once hid its head under the folds of the Rabbi&#39;s gar&#45;<lb/>&#45;ments&#44; and piteously gave a pitiful cry as if to beg for life&#44; but<lb/> the Sage roughly chased it away&#44; saying &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Go<lb/> to&#44; thou wast born to be killed&#34;.  I shall not<lb/> cite the legend of the lamb&#44; which&#44; having strayed<lb/> from the flock in quest of water to look for a stream where to quench its thirst&#44; Moses gently car&#45;<lb/>&#45;ried it back in his arms to the fold&#44; and heard on the<lb/> way a Divine assurance that his compassionate<lb/> soul fitted him as shepherd of God&#39;s chosen flock.<lb/>  All are familiar with that sweet parable from<lb/> the Medrash&#59; while the aphorism &#34;A righteous man<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>knows the soul of his animals&#34; and the other in the Tal&#45;<lb/>&#45;mud &#34;To trouble beasts&#44; is prohibited by the law&#44;&#34; are<lb/> household words among Jews.<lb/>  Yet&#44; notwithstanding that kindness towards the brute crea&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion&#44; ought to be a criterion to judge of one&#39;s refined nature&#44; still it is very<lb/> Yet it is possible to meet instances of deep an extravagant at&#45;<lb/>&#45;tachment to irrational beings and of brutality towards<lb/> reasoning creatures.  The very peoples from whose<lb/> classical writings the touching story sent to me<lb/> for perusal was taking proves my assertion.  There<lb/> exists among the Hindoos a class distinction&#44; such<lb/> impassable barriers between men and men&#44; such fiery<lb/> walls separating keep holding far apart the children of One God from each so far apart&#44;<lb/> other&#44; as to reduce many to a pitiable condition&#59; to<lb/> a state inferior to that of beasts.  Witness&#44; the Pariahs and the Sudras.  Nations<lb/> that who cannot rise to the Biblical conception of a sole an<lb/> God created man and woman omnipotent whose plastic hands created the first parents power that breathed into existence the first parents from whom all intel&#45; sentient<lb/> &#45;ligent beings have sprung&#59; nations who believe that<lb/> that different portions of the human race have issued<lb/> from different parts of the body of their false<lb/> deities&#44; will bye the force of a fatal logic declare some as superior by through an irre&#45;<lb/>&#45;vocable law of nature&#44; and will shun others as<lb/> doomed by an inexorable fate to drudge in constant degrada&#45;<lb/>tion.  Now I ask you to turn away<lb/> from that scene offensive to religion&#44; and contemplate<lb/> the sight which your faith opens before your vision this morning&#44;<lb/> O coheirs of the Torah.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Observe it well that you may judge of value prize its<lb/> resplendent beauties.  A lad reared among an excep&#45;<lb/>&#45;tionally privileged class caste&#44; is surrounded by the object of ro&#45;<lb/>&#45;yalty solicitude.  Wealth&#44; power uninhibited can reach him streams for him&#44; a princely crown lies<lb/> within his reach.  The love of pleasure&#44; inherent<lb/> in youth&#44; whispers acceptance&#44; the fond caresses of a<lb/> foster&#45;mother bid it&#44; but compassion has transformed that lad&#39;s nature.  A voice within his soul<lb/> which he cannot silence&#44; urges him on to deeds<lb/> of heroic self&#45;denial.  He tears himself from<lb/> Palatial splendour to seek the hovels of misery has no charm for him.  Where the groans of slavery cry for help&#44; there he hastens.<lb/>  He leaves behind an aristocracy of egotistical learning&#44;<lb/> that he may to go with outstretched arms to the lowly<lb/> and that he may lift them to a moral elevation.  You have<lb/> recognized your generous deliverer&#44; the hater of<lb/> castes&#44; the lover of equality&#44; the champion of<lb/> liberty&#45;&#45;your Moses who&#44; to shield the defenseless&#44;<lb/> threw aside a sceptre and seized a shepherd&#39;s<lb/> staff.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  I was reading this week<lb/> the life of our inspired liberator and legislator written<lb/> by a Jew of Alexandria nineteen hundred years<lb/> ago.  The perfect close similarity between his thoughts<lb/> and those of our Sages struck me forcibly.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Philo&#44; who knew nothing of post&#45;biblical litera&#45;<lb/>&#45;ture&#44; and probably knew the Bible Holy Writ only through<lb/> the medium of the sp Septuagint Greek translation&#44;<lb/> remarks substantially that if we we examine matters solely to<lb/> find out truth&#44; and not to learn what opinions this or that per&#45;<lb/>&#45;sons entertains&#44; we will discover that a well skilled<lb/> shepherd can become a perfect leader of men.  For&#44;<lb/> though some may laugh at the idea&#44; still noble splendid undertakings things can<lb/> ripen into perfection by means of small agencies.<lb/>  The Talmudists in their turn&#44; commenting on a sen&#45;<lb/>&#45;tence of the psalms which runs thus &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;the Lord tries the righteous&#34;&#44; remark that as the<lb/> life of a shepherd had schooled David for the throne&#44;<lb/> and Amos for a prophetic errand&#44; so did it prepare<lb/> Moses for the grandest of human missions&#44; for the<lb/> creation lead of a priestly people created not to rule&#44; but to<lb/> teach world&#45;redeeming truths verities.  Face to face<lb/> with God&#39;s nature&#59; in the vast fields which proclaim<lb/> the goodness of a Providential Father&#44; in the soli&#45; silent<lb/> &#45;tude of a the wilderness which inspires reverential awe<lb/> for the Creator&#44; the son of Amram&#44; wrapt in meditation&#44;<lb/> saw justice&#44; humanity and justice mercy stand before his soul.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Then the eyes that could not bear to look upon<lb/> iniquity&#44; read as in the pages of a an open volume&#44; unfolded<lb/> before his vision&#44; the history of ages past and the events of<lb/> the future.  He read the patriarchal creed&#44; the and under<lb/> forthcoming salvation &#45;stood its full grandeur he read the vicissitudes of the people<lb/> he yearned for&#44; their eternity upon earth.  Always<lb/> small like a thorn bush amidst a forest of trees&#44;<lb/> always exposed to the fire of gentile opposition&#44;<lb/> but always unconsumed.  Confronted with<lb/> an inexplicable phenomenon&#45;&#45;a bush which melting flames<lb/> did not devour&#45;&#45;the shepherd would learn the cause<lb/> of that wonder&#44; but he comprehended was made to grasped the secret of<lb/> a more stupendous marvel&#44; the phenomenal<lb/> existence of Israel&#44; through their belief in that God<lb/> whom the pilgrim of Ur Chasdim discovered and his<lb/> <sic>descendants</sic> <sic>worshipped</sic>&#44; through their acceptance<lb/> of a heavenly Torah revelation.  For the voice at the sound of<lb/> which the countenance of the greatest of men mortals fill<lb/> in deep humiliation spoke of Abraham the faithful&#44;<lb/> of Isaac and Jacob the tried adorers of the author of the<lb/> universe.  It spoke of the mountain at the foot of which<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>the redeemed of from a crushing bondage would receive be lifted heavenward by an im&#45;<lb/>&#45;parting unparalleled&#44; in the books of antiquity&#45;&#45;a the<lb/> model after which the most famous among<lb/> modern nations would shape their legislation.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> But now Moses who was wont to form the cen&#45;<lb/>&#45;tral figure in the annals of civilization&#44; Moses<lb/> after whom the Law was called &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44;<lb/> because he suffered ere he could muster the<lb/> armies of the Lord&#59; he suffered to keep the<lb/> standard bearers of the Torah at their posts&#44; now<lb/> Moses has caused to commands no more no longer the reverence of his<lb/> beneficiaries.  These are taught a novel religion&#58; pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;phetism it is called termed&#45;&#45;the doctrine that the prophets after<lb/> Moses were the pronounced enemies of Mosaism&#59; that they<lb/> knew not of or cared nothing for incidents and tenets which<lb/> assigned to Israel a religious preeminence&#59; that the lat&#45;<lb/>&#45;ter prophets abhorred the sacrificial rules and ceremonial<lb/> percepts enforced in the five books&#59; that those pro&#45; seers<lb/> &#45;phets entertained moved midst larger views&#44; entertained broader aspirations.  This<lb/> doctrine has&#44; in late years&#44; were immense popularity&#44;<lb/> not because it is clothed in the majesty of Truth&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>for it is illusory&#44; shadowy&#44; but because it is fathered<lb/> by writers of renown&#44; and because it pleases the worldly<lb/> in our ranks&#44; to whom Sabbath&#44; festivals&#44; dietary laws<lb/> and restrictive matrimonial rules&#44; are have become irksome.  Hence<lb/> the clamor for a the necessity of denationalising Judaism&#44;<lb/> and effecting a fusion with some Christian denomination.<lb/>  Let Jeremiah&#44; one of the latter prophets give the novel<lb/> new fangled doctrine the lie.  So he speaks in the<lb/> concluding sentences of the Haftorah of this morning.<lb/>  &#34;Thus says the Lord.  I remember for thy sake the kind&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness of thy youth&#44; the love of thy espousals&#44; thy<lb/> going after me in the wilderness into through a land which<lb/> was not sown.  Israel is hallowed unto the Lord&#44; he is<lb/> the first fruit of His produce.&#34;  What can such enun&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciations mean&#44; if they are not an emphatic avowal of our<lb/> Divine selection&#44; and an inferential recognition of re&#45;<lb/>&#45;gulations concerning &#91;&#63;&#93; ceremonialism&#63;  What logic can<lb/> explain them otherwise than as an unbroken covenant<lb/> between the Lord who sent the son of Amram to make<lb/> as free that we might be enlightened in the wilderness<lb/> of Sinai&#44; and between ourselves&#44; to the end of time&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Do we even need the other passage of Jeremiah<lb/> which says that if the ordinances of the sun&#44; moon<lb/> and stars shall be removed&#44; then the seed of Israel<lb/> shall cease to be a nation for ever&#63;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> No&#58; study&#44; o youths of my people&#44; study that you<lb/> may be not lured away from the faith which the<lb/> noblest of God&#39;s creatures imparted to your ancestors.<lb/>  You owe Moses gratitude for his abnegation&#44; for<lb/> his devotion to your cause&#44; for his sublime example.<lb/>  Evince your thankfulness by your adherence to his<lb/> behests&#44; proceeding form deep knowledge&#44; from the<lb/> conviction that the descendants of the patriarchs must<lb/> be merciful towards irrational beings&#44; loving to all<lb/> sentient beings&#44; social and progressive in the com&#45;<lb/>munities among whose in whose midst they live&#44; but always reli&#45;<lb/>&#45;giously&#44; always Israelites eternally known and acknow&#45;<lb/>&#45;ledged as believing Israelites.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
