<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF1_24</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_23_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_23_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_23_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_23_2v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 1 sheet<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            <p>Dear Bar Mitzvah.  If you have paid attention to the<lb/> portion of the Bible which we have read out of the five<lb/> books books of Moses&#44; and to the last chapter of Isaiah&#44;<lb/> always recited on the day of the New Moon&#44; you will<lb/> have learnt two things&#44; that you ought this early to<lb/> learn.  For though you are not now but a lad&#44; you hope to grow<lb/> to be a man.  And as a son of Jews&#44; you have made us<lb/> understand this morning that you intend to remain in<lb/> the Congregation of Israel.  Well&#44; my young brother&#44; you<lb/> will have learnt to avoid ambition&#44; and hate hypocrisy.<lb/>  Korah who figures so notoriously in our Parasha may<lb/> not have been radically a bad man.  He certainly believed<lb/> in God.  He believed also that the Almighty had<lb/> saved our people from slavery to make them holy by the<lb/> practice of wholesome laws&#44; for&#44; he indirectly acknowledged<lb/> that in his speech &#91;Hebrew&#93;  But Korah had a fault which<lb/> has led many to the pit of destruction.  He was ambi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tious.  I don&#39;t mean to say that he wanted to rise in the<lb/> world by his own industry and <sic>perseverence</sic>&#44; for&#44; that is<lb/> a kind of ambition&#44; I cannot recommend to you and all<lb/> those of your age.  but he was dissatisfied with what<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>with what he had&#44; and to gain what he<lb/> craved for&#44; he did not stop to consider the consequences.<lb/>  Korah though that his cousins had no right to be<lb/> privileged characters&#45;&#45;as he no doubt called Moses and Aaron.<lb/>  According to his ideas&#44; the one ought not to have been<lb/> chief of the nation&#44; nor the other a high&#45;priest.<lb/>  If a ruler was wanted&#44; and a minister needed why&#44; he<lb/> could answer for both offices.  He was&#44; in his eyes&#44; as<lb/> good as his two relatives.  Perhaps better.  Such being<lb/> his fancy&#44; Korah managed by his talk to win a number<lb/> of persons over to his views&#44; and he might have created<lb/> a revolution&#44; in which not only Moses and Aaron&#44; but<lb/> many more might have lost their lives.  Of course&#44; a<lb/> just God would not allow that ambition to succeed.<lb/>  An earth quake was made to open a grave for Korah and his<lb/> followers.  In that instance the intervention of the Al&#45;<lb/>&#45;mighty was clearly seen&#44; as it was so always with while<lb/> our nation remained under the government of God&#39;s chosen<lb/> servants&#59; but when your mind will be able to look<lb/> into the events which constantly happen more closely&#44;<lb/> you will find out that even now the Almighty<lb/> prevents the ambition&#44; which is hurtful to his creatures to<lb/> prosper.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>He does not accomplish it by what we would term a<lb/> miracle&#44; but nevertheless He does it openly enough for<lb/> those who have intelligence to understand.  Therefore I have<lb/> taken advantage of an occasion&#44; which must have a deep<lb/> impression&#44; to address you&#59; and the portion of the day sug&#45;<lb/>&#45;gested my remarks.  I warn you&#44; my brother&#44; against a<lb/> feeling the working of which instead of setting you up high&#44;<lb/> as you might hereafter imagine&#44; would surely cause<lb/> your downfall.  Labor then to the best of your abilities to<lb/> procure an honorable standing in society&#44; but never never<lb/> to try to rise upon the ruin of your fellow&#45;creatures.<lb/></p>
            <p>But the lesson from the prophets gives you also a valuable<lb/> advice.  In the days of Isaiah Jews existed who brought<lb/> presents to the Lord&#44; just as the heathens laid gifts on the<lb/> altar of their idols.  they felt sure that by it they<lb/> received absolution&#44; and could commit all sorts of sin.  Besides&#58;<lb/> no body would credit that they did wrong&#44; since they<lb/> showed so much zeal for the Temple.  But the servant<lb/> of God&#44; angry because of such falsehood&#44; tells the people<lb/> that those who pretend to be religious by sacrificing an<lb/> ox&#44; while they stealthily strike down a man&#59; by presenting<lb/> a meat&#45;offering&#44; while they slyly eat pork&#44; shall pay<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>for their hypocrisy with their lives.  For&#44; He<lb/> who dwells in heaven&#44; needs none of our gifts&#44; yet He<lb/> takes pleasure in such as are of an humble spirit&#44; and<lb/> who obey His word.  My Brother.  Take into consideration<lb/> also alike the second as the first teaching of the day.  Be<lb/> even now&#44; which is a solemn hour in your existence&#44; con&#45;<lb/>&#45;secrated to your faith.  It bids you keep watch over<lb/> your heart&#44; so that it may not swell with unrighteous<lb/> sentiments&#44; hurtful to mankind.  It asks you to check<lb/> your appetites that you may not break through rules<lb/> designed to supply you with a sound body in a<lb/> sound mind.  Promise then that you will be an Israelite<lb/> not in name but in practice&#44; not in the Synagogue alone&#44;<lb/> but everywhere&#44; so that through your agency also may<lb/> be verified the sentence we have perused.  Far off islands shall<lb/> see the glory of our God.  None will rejoice more than myself&#44;<lb/> who place my confidence in our guileless youths&#44; and none will<lb/> be more amply repaid than your parents who feel that a responsi&#45;<lb/>&#45;bility of the heaviest character is laid on them&#44; and that before it<lb/> be performed acceptably to our Maker&#44; times&#44; means and pleasure<lb/> must be sacrificed.  Let your recognition of their self&#45;denial be obedience to<lb/> the law.  And may your righteous intention be blessed.  &#38;c&#38;c&#38;c.<lb/>  &#40;This address was lengthened considerably in the same plain language.&#41;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
