<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF13_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_1_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>For Sabbath Ytr&#243;<lb/>
                It was altered &#38; lengthened &#38; corrected<lb/>
                in 1892 for &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <p>40</p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>It is a wonder of God&#44; that communities do not break<lb/> loose of all restraints&#44; and run riot.  The Christian<lb/> Church nourishes cormorants&#44; who after having been richly<lb/> fed&#44; bite the hand which afforded gave &#91;&#63;&#93;.  The Jewish<lb/> church gives birth to brings up ravagers&#44; who sally forth with ham&#45;<lb/>&#45;mer and axe to tear down the fortress which Moses has<lb/> built.  Say&#44; friends.  From whom shall the people learn the way<lb/> leading to righteousness&#44; since men appointed to teach it&#44;<lb/> are fast falling back&#63;  For my part&#44; I entertain<lb/> decided opinions.  Paradoxical as it may seem&#44; I honestly<lb/> think that to relieve the simple&#45;hearted from a state of per&#45;<lb/>&#45;plexity&#44; when in search of religion&#44; the voice of the pulpit<lb/> ought to be <sic>stiffled</sic>.  The young not hearing the sound<lb/> of heresies with audacious constancy&#44; might be less apt to<lb/> grow skeptic.  The germs seeds of harassing doubts&#44; might<lb/> not then be implanted&#44; where piety should drop sweet<lb/> nectar refreshing the soul.  But how can our<lb/> children be now supported in a belief essential to society at<lb/> large&#44; and to their individual happiness&#44; when preachers of<lb/> the new and of the old creed&#44; combine forces to batter down<lb/> the bulwark of morality&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>The Decalogue&#44; whose very first sentence introductory of the all&#45;important subject&#44; a renowned<lb/> French statesman lately declared to surpass in majesty of<lb/> diction all that Demostenes or Cicero ever wrote&#44; the De&#45;<lb/>&#45;calogue hitherto recognized as the prime factor in civiliza&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion&#44; is now decried as antiquated and barabarous.  The Christ&#45;<lb/>&#45;ian levels at it his sharp arrows&#44; because &#34;the ten com&#45;<lb/>&#45;mandments are but a string of negatives&#34;.  I quote the<lb/> words of the pampered divine.  The Jew bespatters it with<lb/> mire because the God of Sinai pronounces Judgment a&#45;<lb/>&#45;gainst the offspring of sinners.  We have arrived at<lb/> this unfortunate pass.  To defend the dearest interests of<lb/> mankind&#44; we must keep ever awake&#44; and guard against<lb/> external and internal assaults.  Reasonings direct and<lb/> forcible&#44; we must oppose to seductive arguments.<lb/>  Well then&#58; What else than negatives could freed slaves&#44;<lb/> who had seen learned priests&#44; and mighty kings bow to<lb/> all created nature&#45;&#45;save before the Creator of nature&#45;&#45;&#44;<lb/> have been imparted taught&#63;  The celestial Deliverer did not<lb/> ask that those He had elevated should accept dogmas&#44; not<lb/> even that of His eternal existence&#44; but He demanded that<lb/> they should not lower the manhood&#44; to which His outstretched arm<lb/> had raised them&#44; at the shrine of material objects.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>An open&#44; a solemn condemnation of heathenism&#44; and of<lb/> the atrocious practices it encouraged&#44; was absolutely<lb/> needed&#44; and the address which thundered out of Sinai&#44;<lb/> denounced perjury and bloodthirstiness&#44; incest licentiousness and theft&#44;<lb/> defamation of characters and lust of gain.  For&#44; the<lb/> land of pyramids and <sic>hyrogliphics</sic> whence Israel issued&#44;<lb/> and the country of commercial merchant princes in whose neighborhood&#44;<lb/> they were about to live&#44; reeked with the burning of incense<lb/> to infamous vices.  Israel should not be overpowered<lb/> by the fumes of profane libations.<lb/></p>
            <p>But is the Decalogue in its every aspect&#44; only &#34;a string<lb/> of negatives&#34;&#63;  Did the God who formed a new nation<lb/> to clothe it in holiness&#44; have but warnings to give&#44; as the<lb/> sacerdotal robe&#63;  Verily&#58; The Christian divine&#44; would&#44; in the<lb/> ardor of his fiery eloquence&#44; have consumed two commandments enun&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciated at Horeb.  They stand side by side.  They look<lb/> at each other with a positive understanding.  &#34;Remember<lb/> the Sabbath&#45;day&#34; &#34;Honor thy father and thy mother&#34;.<lb/>  The recognition of a prime Mover in all that sustains<lb/> and gladdens the world&#44; and of the necessity of devoting a<lb/> time exclusively to His worship&#44; is not a mere check&#44; as flippantly<lb/></p>
            
            <p><pb n="5"/>
                said of negative precepts&#44; upon brutal propensities.<lb/>  It is spirituality&#44; which Hebrews alone could grasp<lb/> even that early.  The acknowledgment that the same<lb/> great Mover of all things&#44; set the angels to watch over<lb/> our infant frames&#44; and to work out in beautiful harmony&#44;<lb/> instincts which distinguish the higher from the lower<lb/> animals&#59; that those vigilant guardians custodians and laborers<lb/> have an imprescriptible claim to our reverence&#44; can&#45;<lb/>&#45;not be styled as sentiment suiting a barbaric state.  It is<lb/> nobility&#44; nobly represented.  But I go further and<lb/> assert&#44; that each of the negative eight&#44; has in some<lb/> other page of the heavenly legislation an equivalent<lb/> positive.  A single sentence in Deuteronomy contains<lb/> three &#34;The Lord thy God thou shalt fear&#44; Him thou shalt<lb/> serve....by His name thou shalt swear&#34; And is not<lb/> the injunction &#34;Thou shalt love the stranger&#44;&#34; in juxta&#45;<lb/>&#45;position to the prohibition &#34;thou shalt not kill&#44;&#34; since<lb/> foreign enemies prisoners were slaughtered by pagans without<lb/> compunctions&#63;  And the rigor with which female<lb/> chastity was guarded&#44; and the obligation of daily paying<lb/> the operatives daily their wages&#44; and that of subjecting a<lb/> false witness to the punishment his malice wished aimed to have inflicted&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>and the duty to bless the Lord for benefits obtained&#44;<lb/> are all these not statutes of a positive character&#44; agree&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing with negatives in the Decalogue&#63;<lb/></p>
            <p>But I have imposed trespassed on your patience&#44; my hearers.  I<lb/> might have at once quoted the golden rule&#44; and thus<lb/> have hurled a stone&#44; which dashes to fragments the<lb/> high turret from whence a christian divine sought to<lb/> attack the ten utterances of Sovereign Wisdom.  &#34;Thou<lb/> shalt love thy neighbor like as thyself&#34; possesses an earn&#45;<lb/>&#45;est positiveness&#44; unexcelled by any system of religion&#44;<lb/> since Moses was bid to write it down.  The ordinance<lb/> has not been embodied in the Decalogue&#44; but it is the ideal luminary standards of Judaism<lb/> splendidly evolved therefrom to its full orb and extent.<lb/>  False is then the assertion with which a Christian minister<lb/> covers an ill&#45;concealed skepticism&#44; that &#34;in the New<lb/> Testament for the first time appeared the injunction &#34;thou<lb/> shalt&#34;&#44; and that &#34;man should therefore graduate from the<lb/> condition in which the negatives ruled&#44; and come under the<lb/> influence of the positive and higher law&#34;.  To presume so<lb/> thus to impose on human credulity&#44; and subtly to challenge the<lb/> origin of the Sinaic proclamation&#44; is to strike at the very<lb/> foundation heart of social morality.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>And thou&#44; impious Jewish preacher&#44; that hast entered a<lb/> thy protest against that proclamation&#44; because it threatens to fetters<lb/> thy children with the chords of thy sins.  Say now&#58; Shall<lb/> thy example rear scoffers&#44; deniers of a Being&#45;the archi&#45;<lb/>&#45;type of virtue&#45;&#45;and not entail on thy offspring misery&#63;<lb/>  How could the Lord better protect thy own from the le&#45;<lb/>&#45;prosy of the soul&#44; than by showing thee in advance&#44; the<lb/> suffering which thy uncleanness would bring through con&#45;<lb/>&#45;tagion&#63;  How could the Lord better shield nations<lb/> from ruin&#44; than by sending an austere messenger to<lb/> human households and terrify parents into an upright<lb/> demeanour&#63;  For sure as besotted drunkards will beget<lb/> dullards&#44; and the debauched will engraft low passions<lb/> upon their seed&#44; so will crimes rising from a disbelief in<lb/> a ubiquitous Providence occasion force down along disasters and <sic>woful</sic><lb/> calamities.  The Almighty Himself cannot prevent<lb/> the downfall of republics or kingdoms&#44; when homes sink<lb/> into the slough of corruption.  For&#44; communities are an ag&#45;<lb/>&#45;gregate of individuals&#44; whose conducted is moulded at the<lb/> fire&#45;sides.  When Rectitude is chased from there&#44; the<lb/> overthrow of the social edifice is inevitable.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Merciful was the caution.  From the source of good&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness alone could the second commandment have proceeded.<lb/>  It told fathers and mothers this all essential lesson.<lb/>  The happiness of your posterity lies in your hands.<lb/>  If you stoop before images&#44; either graven on metals<lb/> or stamped upon paper&#44; your sons and daughters will<lb/> bend still lower and their moral growth will be<lb/> stunted.  If you live up to Truth&#44; stand up for<lb/> Truth&#44; the image of your pure souls will beam forth<lb/> in the very looks of your children&#44; and they will in<lb/> turn impress on their descendants the dignity of an<lb/> honest manhood&#44; the sublimity of a righteous existence&#44; the<lb/> felicity of virtue.  But God must be the ideal&#44; as<lb/> expressed in the opening words of the Decalogue.  The Deli&#45;<lb/>&#45;verer of the oppressed&#44; the Avenger of offended justice&#44; the<lb/> Recompenser of every deed&#44; shall have a throne shrine in your<lb/> homes as in the Sanctuary.  And you are the two<lb/> cherubim above whom the Divinity must hover.  Then you<lb/> may feel at rest.  For though it is written&#44; that &#34;a jealous<lb/> God visits the inequities of parents on the children&#44;&#34; we have<lb/> also been promised that &#34;the tender&#45;kindness of the Lord<lb/> continues everlastingly with those who fear Him&#44; and<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>His goodness to their children&#39;s children&#59; even with those<lb/> that keep His covenant and remember His statues by ob&#45;<lb/>serving them.&#34;  To the instruction derogatory of the Deity&#44;<lb/> and unworthy of our attention&#63;  Oh&#33; that it were<lb/> thoroughly understood&#44; and sedulously acted upon&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <p>I sincerely congratulate you&#44; O brother Bill&#44; on the significant coincidence.<lb/>  The first time that you were invited to bless your Maker in a solemn assembly&#44;<lb/> you have thanked Him before and after having heard a portion which narrates<lb/> the most important event in the annals of mankind.  You have heard from whom<lb/> you have descended&#44; and what is your mission as the child of the covenant.<lb/>  Abraham who walked erect at a bright light&#44; when all else groped in darkness&#44;<lb/> foresaw that his seed would grow to be keeper of a belief destined to knit the creatures<lb/> of the earth together.  Moses still higher than Abraham&#44; stretched his vision<lb/> further.  He foresaw that to preserve that belief in its purity&#44; wise laws<lb/> must be ordained and enforced.  And the God of Abraham and of Moses deigned<lb/> Himself to proclaim these laws&#44; calling upon us to be the guardians thereof.<lb/>  This day&#44; to you so memorable&#44; you have been told that event&#44; but you have also<lb/> learn its signal attending consequence.  You were made a priest of the One living Lord.  You will<lb/> be henceforth known as such&#44; not by the garments you wear&#44; but by the<lb/> actions you perform.  when you will resist temptations &#40;alas&#33; never so powerful<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>as now&#41; and be an Israelite without pull&#91;&#63;&#93;&#44; showing your<lb/> faith in devoting your time not simply to gain wealth&#44; but to burden<lb/> the sphere of your usefulness in the social family&#44; and specially amidst<lb/> the house of Jacob.  When your professions and your practices will exactly<lb/> tally&#44; you shall be the minister of the God of Sinai&#44; a glory to<lb/> your ancestry&#44; an honor to parents and grandsires who have built upon<lb/> you fond hopes&#44; and&#44; shall I add a consolation to me&#63;  Yes&#58; a comfort<lb/> to one of God&#39;s servants to know that his ministry has not been<lb/> barren of some goodly fruits.  For as often as I address your<lb/> coevals&#44; I reproach myself on the abortiveness of my labors.<lb/>  Oh may you grow&#44; according to my wishes&#59; physically vigorous&#44;<lb/> but morally gigantic&#44; as a cedar of Lebanon&#44; planted in<lb/> the courts of our Lord&#44; expanding its fragrant branches&#44; to<lb/> the delight of all beholders.  So may it be.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
