<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF3_9</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_9_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_9_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_9_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_9_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_9_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_9_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_9_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_9_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_9_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_9_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_9_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_9_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_9_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_9_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_9_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_9_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>9th lecture on Post&#45;Biblical<lb/>
                History<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  I have briefly spoken of the sects<lb/> which have existed&#44; and&#44; in a measure&#44; still exist<lb/> among our people.  The circumstance that<lb/> Judaism did not&#44; in this instance&#44; escape the fate<lb/> of other religions&#44; is to be regretted.  Nevertheless I<lb/> may say&#44; to the credit of Israel&#44; that since Ezra and his<lb/> co&#45;workers effected the revival of the monotheistic belief<lb/> by the dissemination of the Mosaic books&#44; no departure<lb/> from the cardinal point of the Torah took place among<lb/> those who claimed the name of &#34;Jews.&#34;  However widely they<lb/> may have differed&#44; at any time&#44; on ritual questions&#44; they<lb/> have always been remained a unit about the total exclusion of<lb/> apotheosis&#44; or the transferring of the adoration due to<lb/> the One all&#45;creating God to created beings.  Alexander<lb/> of Macedonia had gained a title to the goodwill of the<lb/> inhabitants of Palestine&#44; and they did evince a proper appre&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciation of his kind treatment after his conquest of the<lb/> Persian empire.  But Alexander the victor of thousand battles&#44; could never draw forth<lb/> from our ancestors what he obtained from other peoples.<lb/>  Neither when nations lay prostrate at his feet&#44; nor when he<lb/> lay powerless in the cold arms of death&#44; could the Macedonian<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>bring the believers in Adona&#239; upon their knees in acts<lb/> of impious worship.  The ambitious Monarch had<lb/> indeed aspired to such honors&#44; and to make himself<lb/> certain of deification&#44; he demanded that his body should<lb/> be carried from Babylon&#44; where it had breathed its last<lb/> into the Temple of Jupiter&#45;Ammon in the desert of<lb/> <sic>Lybia</sic>.  This last will and testament of the mighty dreaded<lb/> hero was set aside by the men who had been charged<lb/> with its performance&#44; yet&#44; in Alexandria&#44; a stately<lb/> edifice&#44; adorned with Oriental magnificence&#44; received the<lb/> remains of the proud mortal&#44; and at its shrine mul&#45;<lb/>&#45;titudes offered adoration.  Jews did not swell<lb/> that servile throng.  Jews did not&#44; because they dared<lb/> not&#44; bend before crowned dust&#44; but Jews respected the<lb/> memory of Alexander with human dignity.  They respected it<lb/> by keeping faith to their oath of allegiance.<lb/></p>
            <p>Many are the stories related in Talmudical books about<lb/> conversations held between Alexander the Great and some<lb/> of the Sages of his time.  He used to propound to them<lb/> queries&#44; to which he sought a ready answer.  On one<lb/> occasion he asked&#58; &#34;Who do you think is a wise man&#63;&#34;<lb/>  And the reply was&#58; &#34;he that can foresee what will happen.&#34;</p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Had the inquisitive king endeavoured to follow the healthful lesson&#44;<lb/> his end would have been different&#44; and his vast empire<lb/> might have had permanence.<lb/></p>
            <p>All my hearers know how Alexander the Great died after<lb/> a night&#39;s debauch&#44; and how his boundless dominions&#44;<lb/> over which he had set Perdiccas&#44; his favorite general&#44;<lb/> as regent&#44; became the battle&#45;field where his lieutenants<lb/> fiercely contended for supremacy.  Palestine&#44; however&#44; had<lb/> been assigned by common consent&#44; to Laomeden&#44; who was<lb/> to levy a tribute in trust for the future emperor.  But the<lb/> new governor had a neighbor stronger and more scheming<lb/> than he himself was.  Ptolemy Soter to whose lot Egypt<lb/> had fallen&#44; looked covetously across the Red Sea to that<lb/> region whose stones Moses had declared to be like iron for<lb/> building with&#59; to that land of plenty made fruitful by<lb/> the former and latter rains in due season.  Not suc&#45; Having failed<lb/> &#45;ceeding in compassing Laomedon by cunning promises&#44;<lb/> Ptolemy openly fought him and conquered.  By this<lb/> change of fortune the Jews were placed in a position not<lb/> unlike that which had called forth the anger of Alexander<lb/> some fifteen years before.  But this time&#44; no priest<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>arrayed in his sacred robe&#44; went forth to meet the assail&#45;<lb/>&#45;ant.  Our ancestors refused voluntarily to transfer their allegiance<lb/> to the usurper.  A hard seize ensued.  Josephus<lb/> in his Antiquities is the authority for the report that<lb/> Judea could not have been easily taken&#44; if Jews had<lb/> been less scrupulous about their laws.  Ptolemy had<lb/> noticed that every seventh day the beleaguered did not<lb/> sally forth and offer resistance.  It was the Sabbath&#44;<lb/> and our unwisely&#45;pious forefathers would not carry<lb/> arms even in self&#45;defence.  The wily Greek<lb/> stormed Jerusalem on the Sabbath day&#44; and delivered to<lb/> murder and rapine a population that <sic>wofully</sic> mis&#45;<lb/>&#45;understood the religion&#44; which commands to live by<lb/> the Law.<lb/></p>
            <p>We are apt to pity our predecessors&#39; simplicity.  As to<lb/> ourselves we are rid of such notions as would hinder us<lb/> to from shielding our bodies from danger.  We do not need require a<lb/> direct order of another Matthalhias the Asmonean&#44; as our<lb/> fathers did at a later period&#44; to prevent a recurrence of<lb/> the scenes enacted by Ptolemy.  Would to God that in cast&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing off ideas incompatible with the spirit of the Sinaic<lb/> revelation&#44; we had not thrown over likewise as a burden&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>what is perfectly consonant with the spir object<lb/> of that Divine enunciation&#44; to rush headlong after<lb/> our unruly dispositions&#33;  The Sabbath would still<lb/> be a sign of the covenant between the Lord and Israel&#33;<lb/>  Pardon the digression.<lb/></p>
            <p>Ptolemy Soter irritated at the opposition he had met&#44;<lb/> carried as captives to Egypt a hundred thousand Jews.<lb/>  But he did not long follow the cruel policy which had<lb/> characterized his conquest.  He relented&#59; either because<lb/> a second sober thought impressed him favorably with our<lb/> people&#39;s fidelity to principles&#44; or because he needed the<lb/> service of trusty men.  In fact&#44; history relates tells that<lb/> the King of Egypt confided the superintendence of<lb/> some of the most important localities in his domains<lb/> to thirty thousand Hebrews&#44; and to induce many more<lb/> to emigrate of their own accord&#44; he offered exceptional<lb/> privileges.  The statement of the Talmudists that<lb/> millions of our coreligionists settled in the ancient country land<lb/> of the Pharaohs&#44; and that in Alexandria alone more<lb/> Jews could be found that in Goshen in the days of Moses&#44;<lb/> may be an exaggeration&#44; but doubtless their number<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>became by degrees very extensive.  A friendly<lb/> intercourse opened between the learned of our faith and<lb/> those among the heathens who were in at the service court of Ptolemy.<lb/>  For the latter encouraged the cultivation of arts and literature.<lb/>  A Greek named Hecateus took lessons from a certain<lb/> Hezekiah of the tribe family of Cohen&#44; and wrote a history in<lb/> which he spoke highly of the Jews and their institutions&#59;<lb/> of their industry and activity.  After mentioning<lb/> that they also served honorably in the army&#44; he recorded<lb/> the following interesting incident&#44; as illustrative of Jewish<lb/> good sense.  A very robust and stout&#45;hearted<lb/> Israelite happened to be with the troops that went on<lb/> na expedition round the neighborhood of the Red&#45;Sea.<lb/>  A soothsayer having requested that the soldiers would<lb/> halt till he had observed the flight of a bird&#44; and deci&#45;<lb/>&#45;ded whether they should advance or retreat&#44; an arrow<lb/> at once whizzed through the air and killed the bird.<lb/>  The Jew had sent it off.  Such an act was deemed<lb/> outrageous&#44; and the <sic>skilful</sic> archer would have shared<lb/> the fate of the animal&#44; but for his clever remark.<lb/>  He took Having Taking up the dead bird and he said&#58; &#34;Friends&#44; if this bird had possessed<lb/> the power to predict the future&#44; he surely would not have<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>come in the way of Mishullam the Jew.&#34;  The argu&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment was unanswerable.  No one attempted a refuta&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion.<lb/></p>
            <p>But independent of the testimony of Hecateus&#44; the favorable<lb/> condition of our predecessors in Egypt&#44; and notably in<lb/> Alexandria&#44; is frequently alluded to in the volumes of our<lb/> traditions.  Using Employing a Greek term&#44; the Rabbis de&#45;<lb/>scribe a Basileke&#44; meaning an immensely large edifice structure<lb/> used as a  Synagogue&#44; in which hundreds of thousands<lb/> could be <sic>accomodated</sic>.  It was divided into many<lb/> compartments&#44; where different guilds sat.  There was<lb/> the Weavers&#39; guild&#44; the goldsmiths&#39; guild&#44; the silversmiths&#39;<lb/> guild&#44; the journeymen&#39;s guild&#44; and somewhat similarly to the trades<lb/> unions of our own days&#44; each guild helped its members<lb/> to find work and earn a decent livelihood.  It cannot<lb/> surprise any one therefore to learn that Ptolemy Soter<lb/> should have manifested a wish to secure a translation<lb/> of the laws which religiously governed his numerous and useful He&#45;<lb/>&#45;brew subjects&#44; and that under his son and successor Ptolemy<lb/> Philadelphus&#44; that version should have been completed&#45;&#45;<lb/>though a vast deal connected with the so&#45;called Septuagint<lb/> rendering of the Bible must be looked upon as fabulous&#45;.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>What must astonish us&#44; however&#44; is to hear that<lb/> the Egyptian Jews should have set up a Temple&#44; after the model of that in Jerusalem and<lb/> offered therein animal sacrifices.<lb/></p>
            <p>Were it in accord with my purpose&#44; I would explain<lb/> at some length&#44; the supposed origin&#44; the continuance&#44;<lb/> and closing of that same Temple.  But as my aim is to give<lb/> the attendants at this synagogue&#44;&#45;&#45;especially the young&#45;&#45;<lb/>some information on their history&#44; as an incentive to<lb/> their searching still further the volumes of our post&#45;<lb/>Biblical literature.  I will simply say this&#58; a Judean<lb/> called named Onias&#44; who ought to have been raised to the<lb/> high&#45;priesthood&#44; seeing himself deprived of his rights&#44; left<lb/> his country and took up his abode in Egypt.  At<lb/> Heliopolis&#45;&#45;a city famous for an altar devoted dedicated to the wor&#45;<lb/>&#45;ship of the Sun&#45;&#45;Onias met with a welcome from his core&#45;<lb/>&#45;ligionists.  Having procured the permission of one of the<lb/> Ptolemies&#45;&#45;which of them it is impossible now to ascer&#45;<lb/>&#45;tain&#45;&#45;he built a sanctuary that lasted form two to three<lb/> hundred years.  The distance which separated the Holy<lb/> Land from Mizraim&#44; led many of the Jewish inhabitants of the<lb/> latter place to visit that house&#44; and worship in its courts.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Our people progenitors in Palestine regarded it as unlawful&#44; and<lb/> justly so&#44; for it opposed the intention of our inspired<lb/> Legislator who would made us gave us to understand that only one central spot of national<lb/> worship be allowed should exist.  Still&#44; our Sages never accused<lb/> the Egyptian Jews of having severed themselves from<lb/> their religion and people.  We may notice in the Talmud<lb/> an inclination to palliate rather than condemn the action<lb/> of Onias and his adherents.<lb/></p>
            <p>Now&#44; without nay <sic>pretence</sic> to more zeal or bitter judgment than<lb/> our sainted preceptors&#44; I venture the opinion that both the cir&#45;<lb/>&#45;cumstances I have just narrated were very injurious to the<lb/> interests of Judaism.  The Greek translation of our<lb/> sacred books&#44; caused a neglect of the study of the original&#44; and<lb/> opened paved the way for the admission of ideas entirely at variance<lb/> with the written and oral Law.  This result was recognized and<lb/> deprecated by some of our ancient chroniclers&#44; who put down in<lb/> their diaries that on the 8th of Tebeth&#44; when the Septuagint<lb/> version was made&#44; darkness began and continued for three days<lb/> to overspread our sky.  Again&#58; the erection of Onian temple&#44;<lb/> engendered a degree of estrangement&#44; which rendered the Egyptian<lb/> Jews proverbially self&#45;sufficient and haughty.  I do not<lb/> deny that from Hellenistic Congregations&#45;&#45;as that community<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>of our brethren was called&#45;&#45;men issued forth deserving<lb/> of an everlasting remembrance.  The literary and personal merits of Philo Judeas alone&#44;<lb/> would be enough to cover up the faults of some of his countrymen<lb/> and fellow&#45;believers&#44; yet&#44; Philo himself fell into the<lb/> error of making up what will never blend together&#45;&#45;<lb/> the philosophy of Pythagoras and Plato with the ho narratives<lb/> of the Bible and the teachings of our Prophets.  The great scholar<lb/> committed that error because he did not draw his knowledge<lb/> from the pure source of the Hebrew Scriptures and ancestral tradi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tions.  That Philo remained a loyal Jew and a modest<lb/> man&#44; despite his surroundings&#44; I am grateful for&#44; but many<lb/> of less note and less firmness in belief fell off from our ranks&#44; for want of the right a proper<lb/> support.<lb/></p>
            <p>This lecture which is indeed inadequate to the importance of the sub&#45;<lb/>&#45;ject discussed&#44; would be still more defective&#44; if I closed it with&#45;<lb/>out a word of counsel.  American Jews whose situation<lb/> bears some resemblance to that of the Jews I have described&#44;<lb/> ought to copy what was right in our forefathers under the<lb/> Ptolemies&#44; and shun what was wrong.  To choose mechanical<lb/> professions&#44; and avoid much the seductions of traffic&#44; was commendable&#44; to neglect the<lb/> Bible in the language we received it&#44; was reprehensible.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>May the Hebrews of this country&#44; and particularly those I<lb/> address&#44; learn from a deeper study into the history<lb/> of Hellenism&#44; how very necessary it is for Israelites<lb/> to seek to attain a thorough comprehension of the volumes entrusted<lb/> to our safe&#45;keeping.  For as that a devotional steadfast and diligent meditation on the<lb/> scriptures did prove in the past the strongest cement<lb/> to our brotherhood&#44; so it will be to the end of time the<lb/> agent of our eternization and our greatest best defence&#44; our spiritual glory.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
