<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF6_25</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_25_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_25_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_25_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_25_2v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 1 sheet<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For a funeral<lb/></p>
            <p>Not as an interloper&#44; encroaching upon the rights and<lb/> official prerogative of a brother Israelite&#44; I stand by the side<lb/> of this coffin&#59; but as a friend&#44; complying with the expressed wish<lb/> of members and commercial connections of the family&#44; whose good<lb/> will I have enjoyed for a long series of years.  To comfort<lb/> the bereaved is always a solemn duty&#59; to show fraternal sympathy<lb/> when fellow creatures are in affliction is to give evidence of a heart<lb/> that beats Jewishly.  For&#44; what religion better than that which<lb/> we profess&#44; teaches that to be compassionate is to be god&#45;like&#63;<lb/>  Indeed&#44; the highest attribute of the Almighty Himself&#44; according<lb/> to the imparting of Moses&#44; is compassion &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; And our<lb/> sages tell us that the commandment to cleave to the Lord means<lb/> to exercise our best feelings&#59; or loving kindness towards those who<lb/> look for our tender consideration.  Now&#44; as I contemplate<lb/> the melancholy scene here presented&#44; I am reminded of circum&#45;<lb/>&#45;stances which must draw forth our sympathies.  Unfortunate<lb/> it is at all times to be compelled to part for ever on earth with<lb/> those whom we love or respect&#44; but more unhappy still it is to<lb/> see death enter in rapid succession the dwellings of the same<lb/> family.  That such has been the sad experience of those who<lb/> now lament the loss of our brother in faith&#44; L. I&#44; I need not say&#59;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>nor will I speak of it&#44; lest I intensify sorrow instead of<lb/> offering condolence.  But while in other instances the ter&#45;<lb/>&#45;restrial departure was not attended with lingering sufferings&#44;<lb/> and the terrors of a prolonged disease&#44; in the present case days<lb/> and weeks which lapsed into months brought anxiety<lb/> and agony and the final anguish of the dissolution.<lb/>  The more grievous is the reflection&#44; because I learn that&#44;<lb/> in a measure&#44; exceeding paternal affection occasioned the<lb/> sickness which has ended so fatally.  The tidings<lb/> that a daughter far away lay seriously ill&#44; the<lb/> desire to hasten to her&#59; the privations and fatigue en&#45;<lb/>&#45;dured&#44; while her life was almost despaired of&#44; all<lb/> of that may have induced or aggravated the bodily<lb/> prostration which removed a father from the midst<lb/> of his household&#44; before he had reached old age.<lb/></p>
            <p>And here I may bestow a meed of praise upon the de&#45;<lb/>&#45;ceased&#44; without the fear of being taxed with partiality.<lb/>  Bereaved of the companion of his youth&#44; when he<lb/> most required her cooperation and the maternal care of<lb/> his offspring&#44; L. I. bent his energies upon train&#45;<lb/>ing his motherless children&#44; and supporting each of them<lb/> by his own unflagging industry.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>For the sake of the religion which I represent&#44; and<lb/> which you all share with me&#44; I am glad to know<lb/> that his difficult task was partly eased by the du&#45;<lb/>&#45;tifulness of his daughters&#59; but how onerous&#44; at all<lb/> events&#44; it must have been till those whom his wife left<lb/> orphans&#44; could grow and do for themselves&#33;  That he<lb/> was successful&#44; it must have been a source of satisfact&#45;<lb/>&#45;ion&#44; as it will surely be a merit in the sight of the<lb/> Most High&#44; who rewards our exertions tending to a<lb/> good purpose.  What ought I now<lb/> to say in the name of the God of Israel to the progeny<lb/> of the departed&#63;  Pray for him&#63;  Well&#58; prayers are<lb/> always becoming&#44; and the soul is imparadised when invo&#45;<lb/>&#45;cations are made understandingly and in all sincerity&#44;<lb/> but more than invocations I must recommend a conduct<lb/> which will reflect credit upon both the deceased parents&#59;<lb/> industry accompanied inseparably with uprightness&#44; social<lb/> usefulness by a perfect identification with whatever<lb/> leads to the advantage and honor of their belief and<lb/> their country.  Children of L. I.&#44; be a unit<lb/> in the pursuit of that object&#59; help one another to at&#45;<lb/>&#45;tain it&#44; and you will deserve the approval of all the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>right&#45;thinking and the blessing of your heavenly Maker.<lb/>  And now let us offer <sic>intreaties</sic> for the Israelite who was sum&#45;<lb/>&#45;moned to give an account of his doings upon earth earlier<lb/> than he would have anticipated in the ordinary course<lb/> of human wants&#59; too soon for the sons and daughters&#44; whose<lb/> protector and staunchest friend he was.  Let us petition<lb/> the Lord that the physical ailments he resignedly under&#45;<lb/>&#45;went may have proved the crucible which cleansed<lb/> away all dross&#44; and left behind only what is pure and pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;cious in the presence of the Almighty.  So that the sentence<lb/> of Holy Writ may be fulfilled in him &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;He has delivered his soul from passing through<lb/> destruction&#44; and his immortal spirit shall behold the light.&#34;<lb/>  And we brethren who are about to celebrate the most so&#45;<lb/>&#45;lemn period of our year&#44; let us prepare fittingly for<lb/> the communion with the Lord in His holy house.  When<lb/> the hour of sun set on the great day of atonement shall<lb/> have struck&#44; our names will be sealed in the book of life&#59;<lb/> a life free from bereavements&#44; a life of advantage to our&#45;<lb/>&#45;selves and others&#59; a life exemplary challenging the esteem<lb/> of our fellow&#45;mortals&#44; and gaining the enjoyment<lb/> of an unreproaching conscience.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
