<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF13_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff13_2_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>2d lecture on the immortality<lb/>
                of the soul.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  In my introductory lecture on the Immortality of the soul&#44;<lb/> I made the Bible alone speak.  I know well that the<lb/> thoughtful deep&#45;thinking&#44; who look for more than the teachings lessons of inspiration<lb/> to support their belief&#44; would not rest satisfied simply with some<lb/> allusions to a hereafter&#44; casually met in Holy Writ.<lb/></p>  
            <p>Besides&#44; most of my audience may have been already acquainted<lb/> with the Scriptural passages I selected&#44; so that what was said by<lb/> me&#44; did not create through its newness any deeper impression about the truth<lb/> that I seek to establish.  But the honor high respect we owe<lb/> the book which is our guide&#44; demanded that I should<lb/> let It be heard first&#44; in vindication of the spirituality it<lb/> breathes.  For the bare mention in the Pentateuch of<lb/> man having received the image of his Maker&#44; excludes the<lb/> suspicion of Materialism&#44; and clearly defines the ethereal<lb/> essence of the soul and its indestructibility.<lb/></p>
            <p>The great Maimonides began his philosophical work by showing<lb/> that the image which man bears is the intelligent spirit<lb/> which constitute his a real superiority.  And as the Creator<lb/> is incorporeal and eternal&#44; so must likewise must be the soul which<lb/> partakes of the divine essence.  But this doctrine which<lb/> the Sage of Cordova explained and upheld with that burning<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>which has rendered him famous in all succeeding generations&#44;<lb/> the doctrine of Immortality which has found opponents<lb/> but also strong defenders in the numerous various schools of heathen<lb/> Greece&#44; is discussed and fought against in &#34;Protestant<lb/> Europe&#34; in our own age days.  The same theory of<lb/> atoms or molecular attractions of which I spoke and which I <sic>combatted</sic> in reference<lb/> to the creation of the world is brought forth by Materialists<lb/> regarding the unseen faculties of the soul.<lb/></p>
            <p>No philosopher who lays claim to that title will hold<lb/> that the body&#44; which is matter formed of different parts&#44;<lb/> and divisible into different elements is the source of<lb/> our thoughts and volition.  It is acknowledged that an absurdity<lb/> to imagine that a mass of flesh cut and shaped in numerous<lb/> ways&#45;&#45;wonderfully indeed&#45;&#45;but still <sic>cupable</sic> to perform only material<lb/> functions&#44; possesses the power to judge of what is good and<lb/> true&#44; to love and to hate&#44; to rejoice and to grieve.  Even<lb/> skeptics put down as preposterous the notion that bones<lb/> and blood and sinews and ligaments can conceive abstract<lb/> ideas.  But it is assumed by physiologists have assumed that<lb/> there exists in the brain&#45;&#45;which is the centre of our<lb/> nervous system&#45;&#45;certain substances indescribably fine&#44;<lb/> which some called atoms&#44; or molecular forces.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>When our nerves receive impressions from outward objects&#44;<lb/> a communication is opened at once&#44; as by electricity&#44; with the<lb/> brain.  Then the cerebral atoms are set in motion and their groupings<lb/> produce thought&#44; wish and will.  The theory is ingenious.<lb/>  At all events&#44; it can neither be proved nor disproved&#44; so<lb/> very little we know of this curious piece of pulp encased<lb/> within our skull.  But let us admit that theory.<lb/>  The atoms&#45;&#45;whatever these may be&#45;&#45;react upon the nerves&#44;<lb/> and create sentiments and aspirations&#44; not unlike invisible<lb/> air which&#44; touching the chords of an eolian harp&#44; creates<lb/> soft music.  But I contend that it would be just as<lb/> reasonable to assert that the wind gives the music&#44; as to say<lb/> that a shake of the supposed atoms wakens dormant feelings and<lb/> desires.  Unless man&#39;s foreknowledge of causes and their<lb/> effects had well arranged the box and stretched the chords inside&#44;<lb/> so that the air might work thereon&#44; no sweet notes would<lb/> issue forth.  So also if something above the material<lb/> had not prepared the brain for the association of these<lb/> supposed animalcular forces&#44; the outward sensation of the<lb/> nerves would be incapable of evoking a single thought.<lb/>  That something must be the result of a wisely designed<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>act of a Mind all&#45;foreseeing and all&#45;mighty&#45;&#45;that is God.<lb/></p>
            <p>But has the Atomic theory settled the question&#63;<lb/>  Granted that we have discovered an internal power which<lb/> stirs up our sentiments&#44; have we therefore found out the soul&#63;<lb/>  How can we explain the existence of abstract ideas&#63;  What<lb/> connection is there between a sudden vibration of some cere&#45;<lb/>&#45;bral atoms and the feelings that draw us spontaneously<lb/> to virtue and withdraw us from vice&#63;  What identity<lb/> has it with our reverence for goodness&#44; and our abhorrence<lb/> of wickedness&#63;  Supposing atoms to be indivisible and<lb/> imperceptible&#44; they still belong to our physical composition&#59;<lb/> they are particles&#44; however fine&#44; of dissoluble concrete matter&#44; but our<lb/> sentiments have nothing material&#44; they are psychical.<lb/>  To controvert this belief which I entertain&#44; physiologists<lb/> point to the dependence of our reasoning faculties upon<lb/> the state of the brain.  They argue thus&#58; Man in a<lb/> normal condition uses his mental powers to a purpose&#44; but<lb/> no sooner does a disease or a blow affect the head internally inwardly<lb/> than the mind loses its balance.  Man becomes then<lb/> incapable of unfit to forming a sound judgment&#44; consequently what<lb/> we call the soul is not an entity in itself&#44; but a<lb/> part&#44; or parts identical with the brain.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>I am not prepared altogether to confound soul with<lb/> mind&#44; though a close affinity must exist between<lb/> them.  I have said &#34;I am not prepared&#44;&#34; I should rather<lb/> have made the confession that I am unable disqualified to settle a<lb/> question that rises up spontaneously&#44; so that I may vindicate Divine<lb/> Justice.  for if happiness hereafter should be proportionate<lb/> only to the attainments of the a broad intelligence&#44; scanty might<lb/> be the lot apportioned to the simple&#45;hearted&#44; who&#44; without<lb/> having mounted high intellectually&#44; have evenly followed<lb/> Right&#44; as God gave them to understand Right.  But<lb/> waiving that question&#44; I deny that the brain and the spirit<lb/> within us are the same.  I insist that they are distinct.<lb/>  To illustrate my point&#44; I resort again to my first com&#45;<lb/>&#45;parison.  The strings of the eolian harp create no music<lb/> by themselves&#59; the air in motion does not give out pleasing<lb/> notes&#59; it is an the intellectual faculty of the mechanic which regulates before<lb/> hand cause and effect&#44; that brings about the harmony of the sending forth<lb/> melodious sounds.  Now&#44; the musical box where the chords<lb/> were cleverly arranged gets broken or impaired.  Must it there&#45;<lb/>fore be confidently declared that the power which had prepared<lb/> it is also destroyed&#63;  Can that which does not partake of<lb/> the a material nature be shattered and crushed&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>No&#58; it exists.  It exists in its ethereal state&#44;<lb/> it only lacks the means to visibly work.<lb/>  The brain is the medium by which the soul ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;hibits its faculties.  When the former is injured&#44; the<lb/> latter remains quiescent.<lb/></p>
            <p>You will ask&#58; May it not happen the same after the<lb/> death of the body&#63;  Since it is through our bodies and our<lb/> senses that the working of our spirit is discernible&#44; might<lb/> not the soul continue in a state of inactivity or of stupour&#44;<lb/> so to speak&#44; when our physical organism is broken up&#63;<lb/>  I reply to this query&#44; pr by propounding another.<lb/>  What would we think of a person who has never <sic>travelled</sic><lb/> beyond his city limits&#44; but who nevertheless felt positive that<lb/> in every part of the globe days and seasons are alike&#44; or<lb/> that one equal law rules supreme everywhere&#63;  Would we not consi&#45;<lb/>&#45;der him rash and presumptuous&#63;  Reflect one a moment&#44; my<lb/> hearers.  If a babe at the hour of its birth&#44; could have suf&#45;<lb/>&#45;ficient understanding and we addressed it thus&#58; &#34;Your eyes<lb/> will open to a bright light&#44; which you will contemplate and<lb/> rejoice at&#59; your powers will develop <sic>marvellously</sic>&#44; you<lb/> will feel altogether differently from now&#44;&#34; he would answer<lb/> &#34;From my present condition&#44; I should argue that such a thing<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>cannot take place&#44; still a contradiction does not become<lb/> one so ignorant as myself.&#34;  We are less than inferior to babes.<lb/>  We are embryos&#44; as it were&#44; destined to be born to a life of<lb/> spirituality.  Who will dare to say that because here be&#45;<lb/>&#45;low we needed flesh and  blood and bones and sinews for<lb/> our operations&#44; that it must be so in a higher sphere of<lb/> action&#63;  History is not barren of instances&#44; proving that<lb/> even while clothed in a body very imperative in its demands&#44; per&#45;<lb/>sons have been met found so absorbed in intellectual meditations&#44; as to<lb/> forget&#44; for a time&#44; their earthly wants.  And yet how puny<lb/> our contemplations&#44; when contrasted with those of beings freed<lb/> form the importunate cravings of a perishable matter&#33;  Of<lb/> beings set amidst transferred to the realms of heavenly Intelligence to realizeing in all its complete fulness<lb/> extent the beauty loveliness beauty of human Goodness honesty goodness and Truth&#44; and the glory of<lb/> the Parent of love&#33;  For to that end must the Creator<lb/> have implanted within us a longing for our perfectibility&#59;<lb/> each of His creatures striving after it in his studies&#44; in his<lb/> calling&#44; in his multifarious relations duties of life&#44; but no one<lb/> attaining it because it lies beyond our terrestrial reach.<lb/>  Is the spirit soul which still incites us onward to be defeated<lb/> in its aspirations.  When the turning point is gained&#44;<lb/> must it remain inert because plunged &#91;&#63;&#93; into lethargy&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Far be from the Author of man a grievous injustice&#44; from<lb/> our Sovereign Lord&#44; impotency.  He who said to the<lb/> light &#34;be&#34; and it was&#44; can and will create a life for<lb/> the spirit adequate to its needs and aspirations.<lb/></p>  
            <p>I cannot can better conclude my second lecture on Immortality<lb/> than with the words effusion of our sublime poet and philosopher&#44;<lb/> Solomon Ben Gabirol.  &#34;Incomparable o God is Thy power&#44; for Thou<lb/> madest a light of vivid brightness issue from Thine own re&#45;<lb/>fulgence.  Thy hands and Thy divine implements brought it. forth<lb/>  When it came forth Thou didst let a spirit of Wisdom knowledge rest on it&#44; and<lb/> didst call it Soul.  Flames Flashes of an intellectual fire have been<lb/> its generating powers&#44; and that fire burns within it.<lb/>  Incomparable is Thy wisdom for having set laid the soul upon the solid<lb/> foundations of understanding&#44; so that it can never be<lb/> shaken.  It must abide perpetually&#44; in a manner myste&#45; hidden<lb/> rious to from our vision&#44; yet indestructible.&#34;<lb/>  &#40;Free translation from &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#41;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
