<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF7_23</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1882-03" source="" attested="yes">March 1882</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff7_23_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff7_23_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff7_23_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff7_23_2v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 1 sheet<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For a funeral<lb/></p>
            <p>Wherever we turn&#44; death stares us in the face.  We<lb/> see in every direction&#44; the ravages it occasions.  Yet&#44;<lb/> we act as if we alone were proofs against its fatal<lb/> strokes.  Perhaps wise Providence has it so ordained&#44;<lb/> alike for our own good&#44; and for the welfare of society.<lb/>  Did Should we suffer our minds long to contemplate the<lb/> bereavements&#44; which our neighbors have sustained.  Did Were<lb/> we to dwell on the thought&#44; that the evil which has<lb/> this day happened to our fellow&#45;being may befall us<lb/> on the morrow&#44; we might become unfit for the discharge<lb/> of our various duties&#44; and live a constant death in the<lb/> fear of an approaching death.  Bu though the<lb/> grave may have closed o&#39;er the remains of infants and<lb/> of youths&#44; and we barely noted the occurrence.  Not&#45;<lb/>&#45;withstanding that we may have accompanied the<lb/> aged to their final homes&#44; and continued unaffected&#44; still<lb/> our feelings will be aroused at the startling tidings&#44; that<lb/> a mother has left for ever the innocent creatures&#44;<lb/> under her guide and affectionate vigilance&#44; that the<lb/> sweet hopes of a husband were dashed against the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>stones of the consuming pit&#59; aye&#58; that a home was<lb/> rendered desolate&#44; because its leading spirit vanished<lb/> away.  Then we are pained at heart&#59; and together<lb/> with our instinctive sympathies for the afflicted&#44; will<lb/> blend the distressing apprehension that we also<lb/> perchance may be made to endure a similar calamity.<lb/>  Such sentiments must needs prevail at this melancholy hour&#44;<lb/> destined to witness a separation as <sic>woful</sic> as the<lb/> sorrows it brings in its train are numerous and grievous.<lb/>  Yesterday a week ago&#44; I visited my deceased friend&#44;<lb/> dwelling yonder&#44; and gratified at the filial attention of<lb/> all his offspring&#44; I bestowed a meed of praise upon<lb/> his eldest&#44; who administered to the relief of to the hapless<lb/> father.  Today I am called upon to offer consolation<lb/> to that same son&#44; destitute of his main comfort.<lb/>  Mrs Elias De Casseres&#44; while enlivening her surrounding&#44;<lb/> and giving imparting thereto a moral tone&#44; was marked by the<lb/> Destroyer as its precious victim.  Three days sufficed<lb/> it to change one healthy&#44; young and dignified<lb/> mien into an inanimate corpse.  A short period<lb/> it was&#44; working the misery of years.  For&#44; how<lb/> shall five children thrive without maternal care&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>How shall he whose energies are necessarily bent on<lb/> acquiring the means to support his dear charges&#44; supply<lb/> the place of her that regulated the household&#44; and aided<lb/> her life&#39;s copartner in his pursuits&#63;  The trials which<lb/> the Lord has laid upon you&#44; bereaved family&#33; are severe.<lb/>  But I would have spoken selfishly&#44; if only to express<lb/> my condolance.  I do desire you should know the<lb/> feelings I entertain as a friend&#44; but I am more<lb/> anxious you should benefit from my words as a<lb/> messenger of our religion.  To you&#44; mother of<lb/> departed&#44; our faith directs itself&#44; and bids you rise above<lb/> your grief.  You must summon fresh courage powers&#44;<lb/> and with an activity surpassing your age&#44; labor for the<lb/> growth of those tender plants&#44; alas&#33; so early deprived<lb/> of their natural culture.  Teach the progeny of<lb/> your daughter to love her memory&#44; and practically to<lb/> show reverence to her whose loss we all bemoan&#44; by<lb/> a conduct eliciting universal commendation.  Join<lb/> the father in his efforts to do that which will<lb/> be acceptable to the living&#44; and refreshing to<lb/> the soul of her that has departed died.<lb/>  And you disconsolate husband&#44; look up to God<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>for strength and fortitude.  Your heart has been lacerated&#44;<lb/> but He wounds and his hands heal up.  The urgency of<lb/> your duty should keep you erect amidst crushing sorrow.<lb/>  Your manhood must not <sic>yeild</sic> to the pressure of<lb/> adverse circumstances.  For the sake of the sainted one<lb/> you loved&#44; and for the sake of those she bore unto you&#44; sup&#45;<lb/>&#45;press every sentiment which might impeded the accom&#45;<lb/>&#45;plishing of your important task.  Do it well&#44; my friend&#33;<lb/> and you beloved children of Elias Caroline De Casseres&#33;  You are unable<lb/> fully to realize the misfortune you have suffered.  But<lb/> you can understand&#44; that hte mother so fond of each and<lb/> all of you&#44; has gone from your midst.  Try by your affec&#45;<lb/>tionate behaviour to solace your father in his trouble.<lb/>  He needs all the devotion of which you are capable.<lb/>  Be certain that the tokens of your attachment&#44; combined<lb/> with your improvement at the school&#44; your obedience<lb/> at home&#44; and your kindness to one another&#44; will prove<lb/> the greatest comfort he shall receive on earth&#44; beside<lb/> that which he draws from the blessed belief that<lb/> points to immortality.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
