<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF4_22</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_22_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_22_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_22_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_22_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_22_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_22_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_22_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_22_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_22_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_22_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_22_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_22_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Post Biblical<lb/>
                42<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#43; could the spirit of Gamliel II have assumed a bodily<lb/> form&#44; what a withering rebuke they would have recieved&#44; who&#44;<lb/> a few days ago&#44; offended the memory of the Sage&#44; and defied<lb/> Judaic rules&#33;  A dead Rabbi&#45;&#45;so named&#45;&#45;whose corpse clothed in a<lb/> superb official robe&#44; casketted in satin2 and silver1 artistically wreathed<lb/> with floral tributes unique in their costliness&#44; was a sight<lb/> to excite the wrath of a the real Rabbi&#44; who ordered to be<lb/> interred in striking exceptional plainness.  But we have lost the simple<lb/> habits that so beautifully distinguished our people&#44; and another<lb/> Gamliel might have tried in vain to prevent the a show in the<lb/> Newark synagogue.  In Jammia such senseless pageantry<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>So distant are the intervals which I allow between<lb/> each lecture of mine on post biblical history&#44; that nearly<lb/> always I find it necessary to refresh the memory<lb/> of my hearers&#44; by alluding to the subject treated in<lb/> the preceding one&#44; before I deliver another.  When I<lb/> last spoke of the schools flourishing in Judea&#44; I sketched<lb/> very briefly the life&#45;work of Jo the successor of<lb/> Johanan Ben Zaccka&#239;&#44; the founder of an academy<lb/> of sacred learning lore in Jammia.  I did not dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;guise the fact that Gamliel II had shown at<lb/> times a temper apparently unbecoming of the cha&#45;<lb/>&#45;racter of a spiritual guide&#44; but I called summoned history<lb/> to my support and defended the Sage from the<lb/> charge of self&#45;will and pride of office.  I spe&#45;<lb/>&#45;cially proved his absence freedom from all ostentation by<lb/> citing the directions he left concerning the simplicity of his own burial&#44; when<lb/> funerals were universally unwarrantably made public occasions for extravagant<lb/> display. &#43; But with the death of Gamliel II would not be allowed&#44; after the demise injunction of the great chief man<lb/> the prestige of the Jammia college&#44; who had presided over its famous school of learning.  Now as to the latter&#44; its prestige for the reten&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion of which the the President thereof Gamliel had been so tenacious&#44; as to incur the<lb/> displeasure of his colleagues&#44; died also away. soon vanished at the decease<lb/> of the great chief. of its chief<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>For days the deepest gloom and<lb/> sorrow began followed.  Our ancestors must have believed<lb/> that the Syro&#45;Grecian monster&#45;&#45;Antiochus Epi&#45; that the whole weight of national sins of ages past had been laid upon them&#44; that<lb/> &#45;phanes had resurrected in the person of the they would now be irrecoverably crushed&#59; that the Torah was doomed<lb/> hateful Hadrian. to perish together with Israel.  The persecution about the year<lb/> 130 of the vulgar era&#44; enacted by that Roman Hadrian&#44;<lb/> emperor&#44; precluded the possibility of meeting<lb/> to study and keep up the knowledge of the<lb/> written and oral Law.  Disobedience to this was the commandments of Sinai<lb/> was imposed on penalty of death.  Those who dared<lb/> the imperial edict&#44; and in spite of it taught<lb/> and practised the Mosaic ordinances&#44; were flayed<lb/> alive&#44; and endured other manner of tortures too harrowing<lb/> to be described.  Indeed&#44; some of the Rabbis&#44; noticing<lb/> that the dread of the executioner led many to<lb/> desert the faith&#44; advised the suspension of all<lb/> religious statutes&#44; till more suspicious terms arrived&#44; limiting their recommendation to the ob&#45;<lb/>recommending only to observe &#45;servance of the rules which<lb/> prohibited under all circumstances&#44; idolatry<lb/> incest and murder.  In Talmudical writings<lb/> this awfully soul&#45;trying period is known by the name<lb/> of &#91;Hebrew&#93; the period of compulsory apostasy.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Simeon who should have succeeded his father in<lb/> the presidential chair at the Academy of Jammia&#44;<lb/> had miraculously escaped death.  He hid away in<lb/> parts unknown&#44; perhaps in Babylon&#45;&#45;then Parthia&#45;&#45;&#44; where<lb/> an immense population of Jews had lived since<lb/> the first destruction of the first Temple.  Happily&#44;<lb/> the murky clouds lowering over the heads of our people&#44; scattered away&#44; the persecution for conscience sake&#44; set in incited by the<lb/> hateful Hadrian&#44; did was not continue long of very long duration.  A just God<lb/> &#34;whose eyes are too pure to behold inequity&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93; avenged our cause and the would be philosopher&#44;<lb/> who tyrannized over our people a remnant of Israel the seed of Abraham&#44; perished expired amidst<lb/> insufferable bodily pains&#44; which his pretended stoi&#45;<lb/>&#45;cism could not allay.  The ascending of<lb/> Antoninus&#44; deservedly called &#34;pious&#44;&#34; upon the<lb/> throne at Rome&#44; was a joyful event to down<lb/> trodden Israel.  The new emperor&#45;broad minded<lb/> and cultured&#45;&#45;had rescinded the cruel mandate of<lb/> his predecessor&#44; and allowed the Jews to follow<lb/> their ancient creed and disseminate their learning.<lb/>  The Talmud naturally sees in Antonius a benefact&#45;<lb/>&#45;or&#44; and surrounds his name with a legendary<lb/> drawn from the minds appreciative of the worth of the good &#38; great sovereign<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>All hopes of recovering retrieving regaining political independ&#45;<lb/>&#45;ence had fled&#44; since the last ineffectual struggle<lb/> under Bar Cocheba&#44; and the bloody massacre at Bither&#44;<lb/> but the facility received now obtained to make the Bible<lb/> and the traditions imperishable&#44; was a boon which<lb/> our progenitors valued beyond all price.  The<lb/> schools reopened&#44; and a2 wider scope&#59; and a1 fresher<lb/> vigor impulse was imparted to given them.  Simeon had<lb/> returned from his place of concealment at as soon as the<lb/> tidings of brighter prospects for the future of Ju&#45;<lb/>&#45;daism had reached his ears.  He had gone He went to Jammia&#44; that he might with a view to<lb/> revive the glory of the spot associated with the<lb/> honored name of his parent&#44; but the most illustrious<lb/> Sages of his time&#44; who had outlived the persecution&#44;<lb/> had established an academy in a city called<lb/> Obsha.  Simeon discovered perceived that the supremacy<lb/> once enjoyed by Jammia could not be recovered&#44;<lb/> and he joining his colleagues in Obsha was acknowledged in Obsha as chief by reason of his descent lineal descent from Hillel.  Before<lb/> I cease speaking of the school of learning&#44; founded by through<lb/> the zeal of Johanan Ben Zaccka&#239;&#44; and celebrated deserted abandoned in<lb/> Talmudical annals the days of Simeon&#44; I must quote a saying of the<lb/> teachers who were wont to gathered there to impart sacred knowledge.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>That saying reveals the right true estimation<lb/> in which manual labor work&#44; however humble&#44; was<lb/> held by our preceptors of old.  We read&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  The Rabbis of Jabn&#232; used conversationally to make such<lb/> remarks as these&#58; to one another &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;I am a<lb/> creature of God&#44; and so is my neighbor&#59; my calling<lb/> is in the city&#44; he has his own in the country.  I<lb/> rise early to see to my affairs&#44; and so does he.<lb/>  In the same manner as my neighbor &#40;a plain<lb/> laborer in the fields&#41; does not get grow proud over his vo&#45;<lb/>&#45;cation&#44; so ought I never to become haughty<lb/> because of mine.  One You might say&#58; Why&#44; I earn<lb/> vast amounts&#44; he earns only a small sum.<lb/>  Let such a one Remember that God does did not promise to re&#45;<lb/>&#45;gard the rich because he can make who could bring in a large offering to the Temple&#44;<lb/> more than the poor who offered little.  The heart must<lb/> be right &#40;principles must be correct&#41; to receive a Divine approval.  It means&#58; Let us understand it&#58;<lb/> work is honorable&#44; if pursued with honesty and<lb/> diligence.  The horny hands of him who handles holds the<lb/> hoe and the pick axe are is as valuable to society<lb/> as that of the extensive merchant who puts down<lb/> the account of goods exported or imported&#44; or even of that<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>of him who sits in the hall of legislation and<lb/> writes laws for a people&#39;s government.  All workers are necessary to the mainte&#45;<lb/>&#45;nance of civilized communities.  None are despi&#45;<lb/>&#45;cable&#44; but the hangers on and idlers hangers on and the false.<lb/>  None but those who fold their arms in idleness&#44; and look up for miracles to <sic>ammass</sic> gold.  Beautifully did the last president of the Jammia<lb/> college illustrate in one of his maxims the<lb/> principles rules that should guides the creatures of<lb/> the earth in their intercourse.  Simeon Ben Gam&#45;<lb/>&#45;liel says&#58; &#34;the world exists through the exercise<lb/> of three virtues&#59; truth&#44; justice and peace&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Truth is the secret spring of success individually<lb/> and nationally&#44; but when accompanied with a<lb/> sense of justice&#44; which demands that we should do to<lb/> others as we wish to be done by&#44; and with the<lb/> still gentler sentiment of &#45;&#45;peace&#45;&#45;inspiring self control and self&#45;denial<lb/> for the sake of promotion union&#44; then our homes<lb/> are safer than if guarded by armed helmetted dreaded soldiers&#44;<lb/> then are our countries are protected&#44; better than by<lb/> a standing armies.  Did the character of Simeon<lb/> son of Gamliel II&#44; who the sage man who taught so<lb/> well&#44; illustrate exemplify his preaching&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Studying it&#44; I found that the Sage possessed<lb/> deep sagacity a keen intellect&#44; enabling him to grasp a penetrate into abstruse questions&#44; in<lb/> all its bearings&#44; that he was very learned as a scholar&#44;<lb/> and profound as a thinker&#44; but I discovered also<lb/> that&#44; being human&#44; he was fallible.  Hence&#44; his pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;sidency was not free from trials of his own creation.<lb/>  With truth and justice he was girded&#44; but he lacked<lb/> the splendid ornament&#44; which so embellished the<lb/> character of his ancestor Hillel&#45;&#45;peace&#59; a dis&#45;<lb/>position to wave the right privileges due to his lofty station&#44;<lb/> in order to conciliate opponents ensure peace.  Like his father<lb/> he seemed to have entertained an exaggerated opinion<lb/> of the dignity of his station office&#44; as the recognized chief.<lb/>  The respected which he claimed and and resolved<lb/> to receive at all hazards in his official public capacity&#44; awakened against him to a degree&#44; the<lb/> antagonism which his parent had aroused drawn upon him&#45;<lb/>&#45;self.  But to speak of that and of other<lb/> events connected with the life of Simeon of Jam&#45;<lb/>&#45;mia&#44; would be to narrate history in full&#44;<lb/> while whereas I simply mean to trace some some short faint outlines simply for<lb/> the instruction of youths&#44; that they may learn understand how<lb/> knowledge kept our people alive.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>I may nevertheless appropriately remark that<lb/> in more than one respect Simeon illustrated the<lb/> Rabbinical adg adage&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;the child is the re&#45;<lb/>&#45;production of his parents.&#34;  He caught the spirit<lb/> of his immortal father.  Gamliel II had rebuked extravagance<lb/> at funerals&#44; as a waste and a burdensome task tax<lb/> upon the living&#44; and had sought to put an end to<lb/> it by his last will and testament.  His son told<lb/> us that &#34;good people do not need a monument over<lb/> their graves.  &#91;Hebrew&#93; their words will eternize them.&#34;<lb/>  To my mind The sentence of Simeon stands in fiery<lb/> letters before my minds eyes as often as a melancholy duty<lb/> takes me to Jewish cemeteries&#44; and I lament the vast<lb/> sums sunk there in marble and bronze.  Rain and<lb/> wind&#44; snow and frost will wear out the most stately<lb/> mausoleums.  Posterity may be unable to decipher<lb/> even the names once engraven thereon&#44; but words that<lb/> charity dictates and take a practical shape in the support of<lb/> institutions for the relief of the sick and the aged&#44; for<lb/> the protection of the fatherless and the outcasts&#59; words<lb/> of wisdom which promote the knowledge of industry&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>counsel thriftness&#44; temperance&#44; change vile soul&#45;debasing taverns into<lb/> soul ennobling workshops&#59; words of religion which further the<lb/> cause of learning in schools and seminaries and<lb/> colleges&#44; they are memorials perpetual glorious&#44; everlasting<lb/> here and in another world.  The men who have<lb/> effectually spoken those words will never die&#44; though<lb/> only a plain stone marks out to his offspring<lb/> the spot where his mortal remains were depo&#45;<lb/>sited.  Let me say it in the comforting<lb/> language of the psalmist&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;The generation of<lb/> the upright shall be blessed....&#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Unto the<lb/> upright there ariseth light in darkness&#34;......&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;The righteous shall be in eternal remembrance.&#34;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
