<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF18_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff18_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff18_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff18_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff18_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff18_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff18_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff18_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff18_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff18_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff18_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff18_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff18_2_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>A lecture for Pekud&#233;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#34;Moses saw looked upon all the work and behold they did had done it as the<lb/> Lord had commanded&#44; even so had they done it&#44; and Moses blessed them.&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  A long time must have been spent in preparing<lb/> the materials for building in the wilderness the moveable<lb/> sanctuary&#44; which accompanied the Israelites throughout their<lb/> journeys.  The scene which the workmen presented<lb/> as they were busily engaged in performing their respective prescribed<lb/> undertaking task&#44; not for temporal gain&#44; but to serve their<lb/> people and their God&#44; must have been cheering to the<lb/> inspired leader.  But can any one suppose that labors<lb/> so varied and so numerous&#44; were finished all at the same<lb/> time&#63;  That the women who wore the scarlet yarn&#44; and<lb/> the smiths who made gold and silver plates&#44; and they<lb/> who manufactured utensils for the altar&#44; for the table<lb/> of the shoe&#45;bread&#44; fastenings&#44; and knobs and hooks<lb/> and nails&#59; others who tanned leather&#44; and extracted oil<lb/> for the sacred ointment&#59; in short&#44; that all employed in<lb/> getting ready the requisites for the Tabernacle and<lb/> the worship held therein&#44; completed their tasks undertakings together&#63;<lb/>  Is it not more reasonable to suppose believe that different objects<lb/> were terminated upon at different days periods&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>And yet&#44; we do not find that Moses took public<lb/> notice of the holy work&#44; until it was perfect in its<lb/> every par.  &#34;Moses saw looked upon all the work&#34;.  No one<lb/> appears to have received a separate acknowledgment for<lb/> quickness or industry displayed.  Shall we learn<lb/> from that circumstance&#44; recorded in our section&#44; that we<lb/> must wait till an enterprise has been brought to<lb/> a successful issue&#44; before we pronounce a judgment<lb/> about the merits of those engaged in connected with it&#63;  But<lb/> imagine that one of the workmen had disappointed<lb/> the prophet&#39;s expectations&#44; would it have been just to<lb/> deny the rest the deserved praise commendation&#63;  Let us reflect.<lb/>  In human affairs&#44; we often meet with a failure&#44;<lb/> because of the many persons engaged in carrying them<lb/> to a final termination.  And as the more extensive is<lb/> the enterprise&#44; the larger is generally the number of<lb/> individuals needed to promote its success&#44; so the chances of a<lb/> failure are proportionately greater.  The labor<lb/> must&#44; of course&#44; be divided.  One is entrusted with<lb/> that part of the undertaking&#44; another with a depart&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment entirely different.  Now&#58; we know that all<lb/> ought conscientiously to work in concert for a common end&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>that all should agree to cooperate with singleness<lb/> of purpose&#44; in order that the main object be reached.<lb/>  But does it always follow&#63;  Do most people act so&#63;<lb/>  Do we not frequently perceive&#44; on the contrary&#44; that the<lb/> work of one will far with that of another&#63; that private<lb/> views&#44; personal ambitions&#44; greed&#44; pique&#44; passions&#44; make of<lb/> those who should have been hearty colaborers&#44; jealous<lb/> competitors&#44; open adversaries&#63;  Even if one is not<lb/> led by unkind motives to stand in another man&#39;s way&#44; he<lb/> still may wish to secure the largest share of praise credit.  And<lb/> to win it&#44; he will permit to himself a latitude&#44; not admit&#45;<lb/>&#45;ted in the original agreement.  He will break through go beyond exceed<lb/> the limits he ought to have respected&#44; trespassing upon<lb/> a province which was not his won&#44; and thus occasioning<lb/> a hitch&#44; a break&#44; not easily remedied repaired in the presentation<lb/> of the joint enterprise.  Observe Mark now the wisdom of Moses.<lb/>  He bestows no special laudation. upon any.  The general<lb/> alacrity diligence must have afforded him delight.  The daily inspection<lb/> of the work must have revealed to his mind the sentiments<lb/> actuating the individuals occupied in it&#59; still yet he wantsed<lb/> for the final result&#44; for the moment which should prove<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>beyond a shadow of a doubt that every one has kept<lb/> to his legitimate task&#44; that no possibility of a failure&#44;<lb/> by reason of the untrustiness of any man may arise.  Then<lb/> he expresses his full approbation.  &#34;Moses saw looked upon all the<lb/> work and behold they had done it as the Lord had commanded&#44;<lb/> even so had they done it&#44; and Moses blessed them.&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>Observe again&#58; The prophet did not note down the artistic<lb/> finish of the labor&#44; but its exact conformity with the ori&#45;<lb/>&#45;ginal plan.  Moses never lost sight of the end of so<lb/> many generous efforts.  The erection of a Sanctuary with<lb/> objects of significant form was to impress his people<lb/> with the wholesome idea that a Sovereign Being dwelt<lb/> in their midst&#59; that He condescended to accept their offerings<lb/> and listen to their confessions.  But that like the Taberna&#45;<lb/>&#45;acle for the service of God&#44; which so many separate parts<lb/> constituted a magnificent whole&#44; so the diverse members<lb/> of Israel&#39;s family who <sic>worshipped</sic> in it&#44; formed an entire<lb/> Union for a purpose designed by the Supreme.  They<lb/> deserved credit so long as they directed their endeavours<lb/> to one goal&#44; and this was held preeminently in the thoughts<lb/> of the humblest and of the loftiest&#44; all being coworkers in the<lb/> grand enterprise.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>But what was the nature of the approval which<lb/> the Arch&#45;prophet bestowed&#44; when he became convinced that<lb/> perfect harmony had reigned among the laborers in a common<lb/> cause&#63;  Did he eulogize their conduct&#44; lavish encomiums<lb/> on one for having accomplished what demanded little skill<lb/> but immense patience&#44; on the perfect another for the style of a<lb/> delicate workmanship&#63;  Let us hear how he expressed himself<lb/> on the subject.  &#34;Moses looked upon all the work&#44; nad behold<lb/> they had done it as the Lord had commanded&#44; even so had they<lb/> done it&#44; and Moses blessed them.&#34;  To such artifices&#44; raised<lb/> above themselves&#44; caring not for worldly honors&#44; but for<lb/> the glory of the great Master&#44; the most exalted praises<lb/> would have sounded vapid&#44; out of time and place.<lb/>  Moses knew the feelings that prompted the completion of<lb/> each one&#39;s task&#44; he highly valued the unanimity which<lb/> had prevailed&#44; but he deemed silence upon that subject<lb/> the best token of appreciation.  There are&#44; my friends&#44;<lb/> actions which impress us so deeply with their nobility&#44;<lb/> that a recognition thereof by spoken words may seem<lb/> almost an offence.  A blessing rises upon our lips&#44; and<lb/> that we spontaneously give.  Moses blessed the<lb/> workmen.  He declared what they had finished&#44; divine.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Or&#44; as the Rabbis explain&#44; the prophet&#39;s benediction was<lb/> that the spirit of the Creator might rest on the<lb/> work performed.  For it was deserving of that visible<lb/> sign of God&#39;s favor&#44; a benediction for which the laborers<lb/> yearned&#44; and which they prized all above all rewards.<lb/>  Dear brothers and sisters in faith&#33;  We have no Taber&#45;<lb/>&#45;nacle to set up&#44; but we have many sanctuaries to<lb/> strengthen&#44; to support&#44; to enlarge.  They need our united<lb/> efforts without rivalry&#44; without a thought to personal<lb/> exaltation.  Wherever the name of the One God is taught&#44;<lb/> and the book whose contents had given us eternity is<lb/> imparted&#44; there a sanctuary raises its spires domes above the clouds.<lb/>  Wherever the Israelites meet to thank the Doer of wonders<lb/> that they live as testimonies evidences of His word&#44; there a Sanctuary<lb/> exists in glorious height.  Both should command our labor<lb/> we in any manner we can render it.  Some schools<lb/> demand encouragement&#44; our periodical visits may offer<lb/> it&#59; others the advantage of experience&#44; our constant<lb/> attendance may benefit them.  But I hear this one say&#58;<lb/> &#34;Let men and women who enjoy a place of distinction&#44; make<lb/> it their business to call where children learn the Hebrew Alphabet.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>That one will cry&#58; &#34;Can I allow myself to be thrust<lb/> into a corner with a primer in hand&#44; while my inferior<lb/> in knowledge impart higher instruction&#63;  I have no<lb/> interest in obliging the president&#44; in pleasing the directors.<lb/>  If I take part in the work&#44; I must have my say.<lb/>  The committees shall not slight me&#59; let them under&#45;<lb/>&#45;stand that I am not destitute of self&#45;respect&#59; I shall<lb/> not exert myself and remain in obscurity.&#34;  But is it<lb/>; so that we can contribute to the completion of righteous<lb/> undertakings&#63;  Say&#58; how many Bezabels and Aholiabs are<lb/> named in connection with the raising of the Tabernacle&#63;<lb/>  Had our fathers and mothers considered so much their self&#45;<lb/>respect&#44; as we term it&#44; the house of the Lord would have<lb/> never been set up.  None would have split wood and<lb/> drawn water&#44; who deemed themselves capable of carving or<lb/> guilding.  He who was assigned carpentering may have been<lb/> an adept in engraving&#59; the females who &#91;&#63;&#93; goat&#39;s<lb/> hair may have been able to make the ephod with which<lb/> to robe the high&#45;priest.  But one thought was the<lb/> motive power of that sublime enterprise&#59; to sink one&#39;s<lb/> personality into the natural cause.  Who greater<lb/> than Moses&#63;  Yet you must have noticed that&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>when all the objects were brought to him in their per&#45;<lb/>&#45;fection&#44; and the day arrived for putting them together&#44; and<lb/> present to the Congregation a building for the worship<lb/> in all its magnificence&#44; the prophet did not shrink<lb/> from the meanest of labors.  He performed them all.  With<lb/> the same alacrity that he spread the golden curtain over<lb/> the ark of the covenant&#44; he filled the basin with water&#44; he<lb/> lighted the candles&#44; and fastened the boards and the pillars<lb/> with hooks.  Hence our lesson tells us &#34;Moses finished<lb/> the work.&#34;  Which his people had accomplished after months<lb/> of ceaseless and join application&#44; he terminated in a manner by showing<lb/> the equal value of their efforts in the sight of that God&#44;<lb/> whose messenger he was&#44; and to whose honor he bent to<lb/> perform every task.  It is so&#44; brothers and sisters&#44;<lb/> that we must act&#44; if we do wish that our sanctuaries<lb/> be reared and perpetuated.  Judaism says to all of<lb/> us &#34;You are not expected to complete the work&#44; but you dare<lb/> not exempt yourself from it.&#34;  Let me in the language<lb/> of the Scripture exhort you all&#44; &#34;the weak must say<lb/> I am powerful.&#34;  Yes each of us can contribute mightily<lb/> to the stability of organizations which I call our sanctuaries.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>&#40;This lecture was continued at some length&#44; urging<lb/> the attendants at the Synagogue&#44; but specially<lb/> the young to joint exertions to spiritually elevate<lb/> its status&#44; and render it a seat of glory to the Divinity&#41;<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
