<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF3_11</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_11_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_11_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_11_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_11_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_11_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_11_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_11_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_11_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_11_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_11_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_11_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff3_11_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 3 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Sabbath before Purim &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>
                on the Alliance<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#34;The Jews had light&#34;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>  Brethren.  Let us be thankful for every sign of a<lb/> soul&#45;illumining progress.  The sentiment of charity inborn with<lb/> the people&#44; whom the ancients have deservedly called<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#45;&#45;the coheirs of mercy&#45;&#45;is assuming<lb/> among American Jews&#44; a more cordial form brighter aspect than<lb/> heretofore.  All sentient beings are prompted<lb/> to relieve want when men hunger&#44; or women and<lb/> children shiver with cold.  The sight of<lb/> human suffering arouses within us our breasts a wish to<lb/> lessen it by personal exertions.  But many who<lb/> will stretch forth a helping hand to prevent fellow<lb/> creatures sinking from sheer destitution&#44; or acute from prostrating<lb/> diseases&#44; will often refuse assistance&#44; when the object<lb/> of pity is not under their immediate vision&#44; or when<lb/> its does needs do not appeal to their corporeal senses.  If an active<lb/> cooperation is asked towards <sic>benefitting</sic> the lowly<lb/> by opening a new path which may lead to the gaining<lb/> of self esteem and self&#45;dependence&#44; those individuals&#44;<lb/> considered otherwise charitable&#44; will withhold it&#44; because<lb/> their minds are unable to grasp the progressive idea.<lb/>  Charity bears in their conception a certain defined limitation.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Some time ago&#44; when I undertook to popularize<lb/> the &#34;Universal Jewish Alliance&#34;&#44; I urged its<lb/> claims in the presence of a wealthy coreligionist<lb/> of New York&#44; known for his labors in beneficial<lb/> Societies.  My pleading met with a repulse&#44; for<lb/> the reason that poverty among Jews is on the<lb/> increase in the United States.  He whom I addressed<lb/> could not be argued into a realization of the facts&#44;<lb/> that to provide for the mental elevation of the ab&#45;<lb/>&#45;ject among our race is real philanthropy&#44; even if<lb/> our beneficiaries be dwell thousands of miles away.  The<lb/> New Yorker insisted that American money&#44; as he termed it&#44; ought<lb/> not to leave this side of the Atlantic&#44; to aid in&#45;<lb/>&#45;stitutions in foreign lands.  I rejoice that such<lb/> a narrow thought is not shared by all my<lb/> brethren.  Last year&#44; the twenty fifth an&#45;<lb/>&#45;niversary of the parent Association in Paris&#44; inau&#45;<lb/>&#45;gurated a promising future for the Alliance&#44; both<lb/> in our neighboring city and elsewhere.  The Union<lb/> of all Congregations to the same one identical purpose&#44; which I<lb/> had advocated in a writing was not effected&#44; through owing to<lb/> unfortunate communal jealousies still in existence.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Nevertheless&#44; a considerable sum gathered from separate<lb/> religious bodies&#44; testified to the interest which<lb/> Israelites on the Western shores of the Ocean&#44; take<lb/> in those of our faith who are very nigh brutalized by persecu&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion on the Eastern continent.  New branches<lb/> of the Organization were formed&#44; and a circular&#44; issued<lb/> on behalf of this Congregation&#44; <sic>yeilded</sic> a satisfactory<lb/> amount.  The mind&#45;cramping idea that&#44; because<lb/> with the increase of the Hebrew population&#44; the<lb/> demand on our charity increases&#44; we should not cast<lb/> a fraternal look beyond the bounds of this country&#44;<lb/> has no hold on the righteous&#45;thinking.  It was<lb/> a source of satisfaction to me recently to receive from<lb/> the far West&#44; by means of a brother&#45;Israelite&#44; whom<lb/> Philadelphians well remember to respect&#44; an attest&#45;<lb/>&#45;ation of philanthropy&#44; so that through the<lb/> branch on the Pacific coast affiliated to ours&#44; we<lb/> reckon now over four hundred annual subscribers.<lb/>  That the figure is still small&#44; all must admit.<lb/>  We ourselves should furnish more than thirty five<lb/> contributors to the furtherance of a great national cause.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Surely&#44; the six organized congregations&#44; besides<lb/> ours&#44; ought to present a fairer show.  And here<lb/> I may say&#44; in passing&#44; that though I was not<lb/> made aware that cards would be distributed in my<lb/> name soliciting subscriptions&#44; I am gratified at<lb/> having obtained a number of responses.  Some&#44;<lb/> however&#44; will persistently contend that the request is an injustice to<lb/> the indigent in our own midst.  These have a primary<lb/> title to our consideration.  Undoubtedly so.  I have<lb/> not forgotten the Rabbinical maxim &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;the poor of your city have precedence<lb/> to those of others.&#34;  Nor can I ignore the melancholy<lb/> fact that the employment question is every day beset<lb/> by severer with more serious difficulties&#44; and as&#44; despite all new schemes&#44;<lb/> the cry of the unemployed reaches our ears&#44; we<lb/> dare not turn away pitilessly.  But we&#44;<lb/> American Hebrews&#44; may broaden our charity on one<lb/> side&#44; without necessarily restricting it on another.<lb/>  No parallel can be drawn between the demands on<lb/> our coreligionists abroad and on ourselves.  There&#44;<lb/> countries are ever crowded with a Jewish population&#44; not<lb/> one tenth of which will earn a bare sufficiency subsistence.</p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>There the avenues to industry are few and narrow&#44;<lb/> handicraft goes unrewarded&#44; and to augment the<lb/> misery&#44; every attempt to rise socially&#44; meets with<lb/> <sic>insuferable</sic> political hamperings impediments.  Yet&#44; the burden<lb/> of relief dispensing relief is carried principally by our European<lb/> fellow&#45;believers&#44; and to no insignificant an appreciable extent also<lb/> by the Universal Jewish Alliance.  We are<lb/> accustomed to hear that Roumania promises our people&#39;s<lb/> emancipation&#44; and perjures herself&#59; that she denies<lb/> human rights and banishes journalists who denounce<lb/> the iniquity.  Russia we have long regarded<lb/> as the political scourge of mankind.  Like Gog of the Scriptures<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; she is looked upon &#91;Hebrew&#93; as the huge cloud<lb/> overcasting the horizon of modern civilization.  But<lb/> we seldom contemplate countries&#44; before which even cruel<lb/> Roumania and Russia lose their ferocity&#59; countries where<lb/> our men are robbed completely of their manhood<lb/> by brutal brutal subjection&#44; our women of every sense of<lb/> self&#45;respect by an artfully enforced ignorance&#45;&#45;<lb/> Morocco the mind brutalising degrading empire&#44; Persia the<lb/> heart&#45;crushing&#44; Arabia the soul&#45;withering&#33;<lb/>  Shall we&#44; the free&#44; the cultured&#44; the affluent&#59;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Yes&#44; Aye&#58; the rich&#44; by way of comparison shall we make no<lb/> effort to recall our brothers and sisters to the<lb/> knowledge of their national past&#44; that they may<lb/> strive to map out for themselves a noble future&#63;<lb/>  The subject of my pleading is not new.  It is thread<lb/> bare&#59; so repeatedly I have discussed its merits&#44; that<lb/> I each time I approach it&#44; I apprehend falling into self&#45;plagarism.  I<lb/> rejoice at having been the medium to of opening a current<lb/> of fraternal sympathy between many Americans<lb/> and their Jewishly patriotic fellow&#45;religionists<lb/> abroad&#44; but I have not stronger colors with which<lb/> to portray the Alliance and render it more at&#45;<lb/>&#45;tractive&#44; than to describe it as ever&#45;&#45;the educational<lb/> lever of down&#45;trodden Israel.  During the late<lb/> contest between <sic>Servia</sic> and Bulgaria&#44; a regiment<lb/> belonging to the latter was commanded by Jewish<lb/> captains.  In an interview&#44; Prince Alexander addressed<lb/> them in German.  They answered correctly.  Questioned<lb/> as to the place where they had learned that language&#59;<lb/> they replied&#44; in Vienna and <sic>Leipsig</sic>.  &#34;Do you know Can you speak<lb/> the Bulgarian language also&#63;&#34; asked the prince&#59; asked<lb/></p> 
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>&#34;Yes&#44; Sire&#44; all of us&#34;.  &#34;you mean those who move<lb/> in a higher social circle&#44;&#34; interrupted the prince.  &#34;No&#44;&#34;<lb/> they rejoined &#34;all of us.  We are Israelites&#44; and for our<lb/> instruction the Universal Alliance has established schools&#44;<lb/> where both sexes are taught the language of the<lb/> countries we live in&#44; besides the French.&#34;  But<lb/> my brethren&#44; it is the knowledge of a self respect which will<lb/> ultimately compel popular respect&#44; that we&#44;<lb/> my brethren&#44; should appreciate in the teachings<lb/> of a far&#45;wide&#45;extended organization.  Slow is the pro&#45;<lb/>cess&#44; but not profitless&#59; painful the task but not<lb/> thankless&#44; expensive but with God&#39;s blessing destined<lb/> to yield precious fruits in a generation alive to a sense<lb/> of human dignity.  You can win the merit of<lb/> having assisted in that glorious resurrection.<lb/>  Let me incite in you a wish to act philanthropically<lb/> by setting to view two personages preeminent in the<lb/> promotion of that sublime object.  Baron Maurice<lb/> De Hirsch&#44; who in late years has covered the deficit<lb/> of the expenses incurred by the Alliance&#44; be the sum<lb/> small or large&#44; and his far&#45;sighted and beneficent<lb/> almoner&#44; Chevalier Emanuel Veneziani.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>The former who&#44; twelve years ago&#44; donated two hundred<lb/> thousand dollars towards the founding and <sic>maint&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing</sic> of schools in the Orient&#44; has now projected the<lb/> establishing of industrial schools in Galicia&#44; devoting<lb/> to the scheme twenty thousand dollars annually.<lb/>  His almoner has gone to the spot to draw plans<lb/> and supervise the work with his vast experience and<lb/> sagacious skill.  Those two illustrious Israelites re&#45;<lb/>&#45;calling the exhortation of Jeremiah &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Remembering Jerusalem the Lord from after have determined likewise to build<lb/> and let Jerusalem come up on your minds&#34;<lb/> in the holy city rows of houses to shelter indigent<lb/> families of our faith deserving of succour.<lb/></p>
            <p>Let your liberal Purim gifts to the Alliance O Americans&#33; en&#45;<lb/>&#45;courage that Maecenas and his faithful asso&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciate.  Let them De Hirsch and Veneziani hear that from Philadelphia<lb/> proceeded the free will offerings of brethren&#44; who<lb/> heartily wish that all Jews may have light<lb/> and Joy&#44; and gladness triumph and honor&#44; in the land<lb/> of their habitations. &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
