<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF11_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_1_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_1_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_1_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_1_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_1_8v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_1_9r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_1_9v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_1_10r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff11_1_10v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>16 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>An explanatory lecture<lb/>
                on Shemot Bo<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <p>7<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>History repeats itself.  This truism which the events of every&#45;day&#39;s<lb/> life prove illustrate&#44; is brought to my mind quite often&#44; and that in a striking<lb/> manner.  For&#44; I perceive that how the identical questions put by the<lb/> fathers are asked by their children.  Must I then accept the<lb/> inevitable and repeat also myself&#63;  It may be irksome to<lb/> those more rather advanced in age who have heard me before.  Shall I<lb/> leave the query unanswered&#63;  It would be a disregard of duty.<lb/>  I judge the middle course the most advisable.  To simplify while<lb/> reasoning&#59; to condense when explaining.  This plan I will<lb/> follow to&#45;day.  My intended discourse has reference to a<lb/> transaction which marked the departure of our ancestors from<lb/> Egypt as read in our Parasha&#44; and which a number of years ago I tried to present<lb/> in an aspect&#44; I consider fair&#44; and free from the blemishes that<lb/> others have discovered in it.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  The belief that God&#44; whose every word way<lb/> is pure righteous&#44; would commend an act&#44; clashing with the<lb/> principles of morality&#44; is repugnant to my very nature.<lb/>  Hence I readily accepted the opinion of an ancient<lb/> author&#44; touching a passage which occurs in the narrative<lb/> of the Divine revelation in the vision of the a burning&#45;bush.<lb/></p>
            <p>Glad&#44; that his interpretation had removed whatever<lb/> seemed objectionable in it&#44; I did not critically examine<lb/> whither it stood altogether on tenable ground.<lb/>  So that&#44; whereas according to a great number very many of our<lb/> commentators&#44; the Israelites were ordered to borrow from at the time<lb/> the Egyptians of their liberation &#34;vessels of silver and vessels of gold and garments&#34;<lb/> which they did not intend mean to return&#44; I adopted the idea<lb/> that they were bid enjoined to ask as presents&#44; whatever things<lb/> soever they required wished for.  The verb &#91;Hebrew&#93; employed in<lb/> the text&#44; can be made to favor that rendering&#44; and I<lb/> preferred it&#44; because I conceived that I saw therein a<lb/> vindication of the character of our ancestors&#44; and likewise<lb/> a defense to Biblical Divine ordinances.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>But a deeper searching into the same passage&#44;<lb/> convinced me that I had allowed my feelings too<lb/> strong a preponderance over my judgment.<lb/>  In whatever light I considered the command&#44; I could&#44; after upon<lb/> mature reflection&#44; find no other construction&#44; but than that<lb/> generally given to it.  I first compared<lb/> its wording&#44; as with a page we read last last Sabbath<lb/> with that which describes our forefathers in the act<lb/> of seeking from their former masters objects of value.<lb/>  There I saw it found it obviously stated that &#34;the Lord gave the<lb/> people favor in the sight of the Egyptians&#44; and<lb/> they lent unto them.  &#34;&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> The learned expositor&#44; whose opinion views I had eagerly<lb/> embraced&#44; must have perceived detected in that sentence a<lb/> refutation to his own version&#44; for he strives to explain<lb/> it away.  But his ingenuity fails to carry with it<lb/> a great weight.  The verb &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; when formed<lb/> as in the verse I have just quoted&#44; cannot be possibly<lb/> be translated otherwise than &#34;to lend&#34;.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>We meet with it once more in Holy Writ&#44; and<lb/> then&#44; by common consent&#44; only that meaning is attached<lb/> to it.  Listen&#58; my frien As the mother of Samuel presented<lb/> her long wished&#45;for child to Eli&#44; she thus expressed<lb/> herself.  &#34;For this child have I prayed&#44; and the Lord hath<lb/> granted my petition&#44; which I asked of Him&#34;.  &#34;And<lb/> I also have lent him unto the Lord&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> She could not correctly have said that she had given him<lb/> entirely to God&#44; for he if we judge from our text&#44; being neither not a Priest nor a Levite&#44;<lb/> was disqualified from ministering in the Tabernacle abiding in the Tabernacle &#38; ministering at the altar.<lb/>  She therefore purposed to signify&#44; that she <sic>yeilded</sic> her<lb/> son partially unto the Lord&#59; fitting him by education<lb/> as a laborer for the cause of religion&#44; though he would<lb/> still belong to and serve his natural parents.  I am aware<lb/> that another expression of that righteous pious mother&#44; appears<lb/> to contradict my interpretation.  For&#44; she said that she<lb/> would defer to carry her child unto the presence of the<lb/> Lord&#44; until he was weaned&#44; after which period&#44; he would should<lb/> &#34;abide there for ever&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;; but the subsequent<lb/> history of Samuel proves beyond dispute&#44; that her<lb/> tending to say&#44; supporting themselves in a passage in Chronicles&#44; he was a Levite<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>expression had no reference to his remaining permanently<lb/> in the Sanctuary&#44; but rather to the godly life he would<lb/> always lead.  In fact&#44; if it is true that Samuel was reared<lb/> in Shiloh near where the ark of the covenant stood&#44; it can&#45;<lb/>&#45;not nevertheless be asserted that he continued there in that sacred spot&#44;<lb/> after when he grew to manhood.  It is recorded that<lb/> after he had judged Israel in their different cities&#44;<lb/> he returned to Ramah&#44; &#34;for there was his house&#34;.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  And furthermore&#59; on the day that<lb/> Saul went in quest of the asses&#44; which his father<lb/> had lost&#44; he asked for the Seer in the land of Zuph&#44;<lb/> the place of his birth.  Now&#44; my Brethren&#33;<lb/> Having shown that Hannah purposed by the word<lb/> she used&#44; to convey solely the idea of lending&#59; I have<lb/> virtually proved that the Egyptians also purposed<lb/> to lend&#44; and not to grant as donations the objects they<lb/> gave unto Israel&#59; for in both cases is the word verb identi&#45;<lb/>&#45;cally formed.  In one as in the other&#44; it stands in the<lb/> same conjugation&#44; and is governed by the same rules.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>But apart from this observation&#44; which they will<lb/> best appreciate&#44; who are versed in Hebrew Grammar&#44;<lb/> I was induced by another consideration&#44; to discard the<lb/> opinion that our forefathers&#44; asked as gifts what their<lb/> masters possessed.  The latter may have suspected that<lb/>&#45;&#45;if permitted at all to to leave Egypt&#45;&#45;their bond&#45;<lb/>&#45;men would not voluntarily come again to servitude&#59;<lb/> but the request of Moses had simply been&#44; that they<lb/> might go the distance of three day&#39;s journey&#44; and hold<lb/> worship to their God.  Their inspired leader knew well&#44; that to leave demanded the manumission of the slaves&#44; and their departure from the country they had enriched&#44; would have been instant death to himself&#44; and a general slaughter&#44; perhaps of all who could bear arms among the Hebrews.  Only on the strength of the re&#45; character<lb/> &#45;peated demand of of the request made by their champion&#44; the Israelites might<lb/> have received as a loan&#44; what they represented as<lb/> necessary&#44; during the feast they contemplated celebrating&#44;<lb/> and in honor of the occasion&#59; but I believe that even at<lb/> the last hour&#44; and after so many sore trials&#44; the Egyptians<lb/> could scarcely have been led to part with their riches&#44;<lb/> in order to endow with the same&#44; men whom they<lb/> regarded infinitely their inferiors.  Besides&#59;<lb/> to apply for them as presents&#44; would have been to confirm<lb/> the suspicion already entertained of an intended flight.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>For&#44; &#34;why should the Hebrews&#45;&#45;if they expected<lb/> to return after the lapse of a few days to their<lb/> former thraldom&#45;&#45;&#44;require objects that <sic>graceously</sic><lb/> the person and dwelling of the free&#63;  So must<lb/> the Egyptians have naturally reasoned&#44; when<lb/> solicited to give away their own substance.  And<lb/> we know for certain that &#91;&#63;&#93; did not none was found so basely treacherous as to disclose<lb/> to the oppressors of his brethren&#44; the true motive<lb/> of his Moses&#39; mission&#59; nor was it this revealed&#44; till until his various encampments<lb/> in the wilderness revealed it unto them alarmed the slave&#45;holders.<lb/>
                From all the aforesaid&#44; I arrived at the conclusion&#44;<lb/> that our ancestors obtained what they desired carried away&#44; by<lb/> asking it merely as a loan.  Now&#44;<lb/> my Brethren&#33;  This conclusion may be startling<lb/> to you&#44; as it was at first painful to me.<lb/>  But if you will give it your serious thoughts&#44;<lb/> you will agree that is so only in appearance.<lb/>  We should not forget under what circumstances<lb/> our predecessors made their request.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>If incited by &#91;&#63;&#93; greed&#44; they had endeavoured of their own accord to gain<lb/> through deception&#44; what they could not reach by fair<lb/> means&#44; or&#44; if they had even been so impelled by a<lb/> sense of the wrongs done them&#44; when forced to labor<lb/> without compensation&#44; we might pronounce their deed<lb/> a an unmitigated fraud.  But it was the man who spoke to<lb/> them in the name of God&#44; that directed their every<lb/> action.  He who had seen witnessed their utter humiliation&#44; and grieved<lb/> at their suffering&#44; bid them&#44; by inspiration&#44; with his inspired lips&#44; to resort to<lb/> a strategy measure whereby that they might not leave in destitution an<lb/> ungrateful country&#44; which owed them its advancement<lb/> in commerce and arts.  He told them that a higher<lb/> Power&#44; to whom all belongs&#44; permitted them an action<lb/> unlawful in ordinary circumstances&#44; so that without divulging his design&#44; they might<lb/> be virtually repaid for the unrequited work of ages&#44;<lb/> and for property they could not carry away along&#44; but which<lb/> was theirs by right of inheritance&#44; as lineal descendants<lb/> of Joseph&#44; the deliverer of Egypt.<lb/></p>
            <p>We may reasonably suppose that at the hour&#44; when<lb/> the chains fell loose from off their arms&#44; and<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>they hailed the approaching dawn of freedom&#44;<lb/> the Israelites would not&#44; in all likelihood&#44; have<lb/> delayed their departure&#44; to seek their former masters<lb/> either for silver or for gold.  But a command they<lb/> dared not disobey&#44; pointed out to them the predeter&#45;<lb/>&#45;mined course&#44; which they were destined to pursue.<lb/></p>
            <p>But has it never occurred to your minds&#44; that<lb/> many several had been the opportunities in which our<lb/> forefathers could&#44; at their ease&#44; have enriched them&#45;<lb/>&#45;selves with the wealth of their task&#45;masters&#44;<lb/> if prompted by dishonesty&#63;  Who&#44; for instance&#44;<lb/> would have opposed them&#44; on that terrific night&#44;<lb/> that when every Egyptian house lamented a dead&#44; if transgressing the ordinance received&#44; and stealthily lending their own houses before &#91;&#63;&#93; morning they had seized on<lb/> the precious things&#44; which their incessant toils<lb/> could not procure for them&#63;  Nay more&#59; during<lb/> the three days that the sun refused to shed its<lb/> rays upon the land of oppression&#44; what&#44; but the<lb/> fear of a God &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;who hateth fraud&#34;&#44; could<lb/> have prevented the oppressed from storing away against<lb/> their forthcoming liberation&#44; whatever laid before their<lb/> illumined vision&#63;&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>Indeed&#44; it strikes me that the Psalmist may<lb/> possibly have alluded to this fact&#45;&#45;worthy<lb/> of being remembered.  When&#44; recounting the wonders of<lb/> the Lord in the land of Ham&#44; he says &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;He sent darkness and made it<lb/> impenetrable&#44; but they relle rebelled not against<lb/> his word&#34;.  Meaning&#44; that the people of God&#45;&#45;men&#45;<lb/>&#45;tioned in a preceding sentence&#45;&#45;did never not harbour<lb/> the unrighteous thought of <sic>profitting</sic> of the occasion&#44;<lb/> by which they might&#44; without being detected&#44; have<lb/> taken away the spoil of their enemies.<lb/></p>
            <p>Such a demeanour&#44; my dear hearers&#33; must prove<lb/> to all unprejudiced minds&#44; that what bears the<lb/> semblance of deception&#44; was practised by our progenitors&#44;<lb/> only that they might perform a heavenly injunction.<lb/>  I have advisedly said&#44; that bears the semblance of<lb/> deception&#44; because&#44; while a similar proceeding in<lb/> our customary dealings would be reprehensible&#44; agree&#45;<lb/>&#45;ably to the teaching of the scriptures &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;the wicked man borrows&#44; and does not pay&#34;;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>When it is authorized by Him&#44; from whom all<lb/> we possess springs forth&#44; it ceases to be an artifice&#44;<lb/> and becomes a lawful action.  For it was the<lb/> God of justice&#44; the God in whose law it&#39;s written&#44;<lb/> &#34;Ye shall not steal&#59; ye shall not deal falsely&#59;<lb/> ye shall not lie one to another&#34;&#44; that righteous God&#44; I say&#44;<lb/> it was&#44; who would not suffer the progeny of<lb/> Abraham to go forth in indigence&#44; when they who<lb/> had embittered their lives&#44; and robbed them of their<lb/> children luxuriated in affluence.<lb/></p>
            <p>But you may still offer objections.  You may<lb/> deprecate not the power of the Supreme to do as<lb/> He wills with his creatures&#44; but the manner in which<lb/> it had been exercised in that particular instance.<lb/>  You may fear that the impression it left was&#44;<lb/> that &#34;the end justifies the means.&#34;  Not so&#44; my<lb/> friends&#33; not so.  Picture to your mind a people<lb/> who have for years been cruelly treated&#44; but whose cause an<lb/> extraordinary man undertakes to avenge.<lb/></p>
            <p>By repeated strokes he succeeds in wresting the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p>persecuted from the hand of the persecutors&#59; and<lb/> as he is about to lead them forth into the path of free&#45;<lb/>&#45;dom&#44; he so addresses them.  &#34;Brethren&#33;  To&#45;morrow<lb/> your afflictions will be at an end.  I ask of you<lb/> not to return evil for evil.  You may not&#44; because<lb/> so long denied the right of gaining wealth&#59; indulge<lb/> now in plunder and rapine&#44; but you may endeavour<lb/> to obtain by a stratagem a portion of the substance<lb/> which&#44; through your hardships your foes have acquired.<lb/>  This course I recommend&#44; as the surest to save you from want&#44; and as that which best accords<lb/> with my future plans.&#34;  Do you not think<lb/> that they who should be so directed&#44; would regard the<lb/> command as another judgment by which the wicked<lb/> were to be visited&#44; rather than an incentive to fraudu&#45;<lb/>&#45;lence&#63;  And if it is so my friends&#33; with what greater<lb/> force must this reasoning apply to our case&#44; in<lb/> which God Almighty himself orders that the hitherto<lb/> wretched and helpless&#44; should be the instruments of<lb/> his wrath against the pitiless and the tyrannical&#63;<lb/>  He had promised to deliver Israel from the fiery<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="14"/>
            <p>furnace in which they had been cast.  They<lb/> should not lift as spear&#44; nor unsheath a sword&#44;<lb/> He would fight their battles&#59; but when victorious&#44;<lb/> He would commission them&#45;&#45;so long despised&#45;&#45;<lb/> to draw from the vanquished&#44; the means of attaining<lb/> temporal exaltation.  This was not for sooth<lb/> a lesson in cunning&#44; but a warning even to<lb/> those whom the Mo Omnipotent had signally bene&#45;<lb/>&#45;fitted&#59; a caution against their abusing the power<lb/> they might gain&#59; an intimation that whatsoever<lb/> they might hereafter possess&#44; would be theirs only<lb/> in trust.  For God is the author of human glory&#44;<lb/> the source of human strength&#44; and the Lord of wealth.<lb/>  He can bring the <sic>heighest</sic> to the lowest ebb of<lb/> degradation&#44; and He will&#44; if He so chooses&#44; accom&#45;<lb/>&#45;plish it by the agency of those whom we imagined&#44;<lb/> we could oppress with impunity.<lb/></p>
            <p>Let us open the Scriptures&#44; and there we shall find<lb/> that frequently when a deed of mercy is recommended&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="15"/>
            <p>or an unkind act reprehended inveighed against censured&#44; the heavenly<lb/> Legislator adds this sentence &#34;Remember that thou<lb/> wast a servant in Egypt.&#34;  But what<lb/> moral influence&#44; I ask&#44; would these words possess&#44;<lb/> if at the very hour of their redemption&#44; our<lb/> fathers had been impressed with the belief that<lb/> a deceitful dealing is no offence&#63;  Forbid it<lb/> God&#33;  The thought is itself is a blasphemy.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;False lips are<lb/> an abomination unto the Lord&#44; but they that<lb/> deal truly are his delights.&#34;  Woe unto him<lb/> who should look into the book that holds the<lb/> subtle and the hypocrite to reprobation&#44; for a<lb/> defense to his crafty practices&#33;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;I say&#44; an untimely abortion is happier better than he.&#34;<lb/>  Let us&#44; my Brethren&#33; acknowledge our ignorance&#44;<lb/> if we are unable to reconcile some biblical passages<lb/> with the ideas of eternal justice implanted in<lb/> every breast.  But let us not represent&#44; or consider<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="16"/>
            <p>them as sanctioning what reason and religion<lb/> repel.  Wherefore&#44; my hearers&#33; if I have<lb/> failed to draw your assent to my opinion touching<lb/> the question at issue&#44; and your approval of the<lb/> manner in which I have advanced it&#44; think<lb/> me at fault&#44; and the pages of inspiration free<lb/> from blemish&#59; for &#34;the words of the Lord are pure<lb/> words&#44; as silver tried in a crucible of earth&#44; purified<lb/> sevenfold&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93; and we also read &#34;&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;The ways of the Lord are<lb/> right&#44; the just shall walk in them&#44; but the<lb/> transgressors shall stumble thereon.&#34;  May<lb/> we ever be reckoned among the former&#44; and may<lb/> we eschew the arrogance of the latter.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
