<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF2_20</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1876" source="" attested="yes">1876</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_20_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_20_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_20_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_20_2v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 1 sheet<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For the 1st anniversary of the young men&#39;s<lb/></p>
            <p>Hebrew association of Philadelphia.<lb/></p>
            <p>Ladies and Gentlemen&#33;  Ordinarily Generally&#44; the farce concludes<lb/> the performance.  This evening a freak of our manager<lb/> has made it first in order.  I guess it was done on<lb/> purpose.  That head&#45;piece of his is brimful of shrewdness.<lb/>  &#34;Let us put the company in good humor.  They will be<lb/> more willing to lend their ears to the serious portion of the exer&#45;<lb/>&#45;cises.&#34;  So must have reasoned to himself that man Wise<lb/> the Steine&#44; I mean&#44; the Stone&#44; on which whereon our insti&#45;<lb/>&#45;tution was founded about a year ago.  I am sure he didn&#39;t<lb/> mean any offense.  But as he was once a child&#44;&#45;&#45;and he<lb/> knows who we are all children of an older growth&#45;&#45;he<lb/> thought he would coax us into learning.  I remember<lb/> well&#44;&#45;&#45;though nearly two score years and ten have rolled away<lb/> since&#45;&#45;&#44; I remember well when a Hebrew Alphabet was<lb/> put into my hands.  It contained large and small letters<lb/> printed on paste&#45;board&#44; upon the top part of which the picture<lb/> of an angel figured conspicuously.  My little eyes being in<lb/> sympathy with that spiritual babe&#44; caught something<lb/> rolling out of the outstretched wings.  I had not been<lb/> mistaken.  They were sugar&#45;plumbs.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>That signet quickened my reflective organs.<lb/>  I soon gained an acquaintance with our twenty two letters.<lb/>  I say thus merely by way of illustration&#44; believing that<lb/> our manager by so oddly arranging the programme<lb/> wished to give those who will render our entertainment<lb/> instruction&#44; a chance to be attentively heard.  I only<lb/> regret that with all his reputation for sagacity&#44; our<lb/> friend fell into a huge error.  He chose the wrong person<lb/> for the play.  I am so accustomed to public speaking<lb/> on grave subjects&#44; that my attempt to excite a dispo&#45;<lb/>&#45;sition to risibility must needs a dead failure.  I<lb/> shall not try my hand at it.  But as I am up&#44; and some&#45;<lb/>&#45;thing has preliminarily to be said&#44; according to promise&#44; I will relate a short<lb/> story.  There was once a Rabbi who held a<lb/> high position.  But notwithstanding his acknowledged<lb/> abilities and good character&#44; he did not enjoy popularity.  The<lb/> community thought him too austere&#44; too jealous of his authority&#44;<lb/> and too un<sic>yeilding</sic> to measures which others proposed.<lb/>  The charges were not unfounded.  The olden Sage asserted<lb/> that his conduct sprang simply from a consciousness of<lb/> his religious duties.  But whether that was so or not&#44; his<lb/> brethren who judged him by the result consequences of his exceeding strictness&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>could not well suppress the antipathy entertained<lb/> against a teacher&#44; who drove away the people repelled scholars from the<lb/> seat of learning&#44; rather than impel them to seek it.<lb/>  On one occasion&#44; when he used his power with undue severity&#44;<lb/> public feelings were wrought up to such a pitch&#44; that a<lb/> younger&#44; but more genial Rabbi was selected to supercede<lb/> the stern preceptor.  The utility of that measure decision strike of jealousy revolutionary movement became<lb/> at once evident.  Whereas formerly many had kept aloof<lb/> from the college&#44; now so large became grew the attendance that<lb/> an extraordinary number of benches had to be provided.<lb/>  The day upon which the new ecclesiastical chief was<lb/> installed into office&#44; formed quite an epoch in the annals<lb/> of traditional Judaism.  Ladies &#38; Gentlemen&#33;<lb/>  It is the hope of a similar result which suggested the<lb/> literary entertainment to which you have been invited.<lb/>  I emphatically disclaim the idea of drawing a compari&#45;<lb/>&#45;son between my insignificant self and Rabbi Gamliel&#44;<lb/> the second.  But I have during the last twelve months&#44;<lb/> as a presiding officer&#44; and as a member spoken so<lb/> repeatedly before this association&#44; and always to very<lb/> little purpose&#45;&#45;owing perhaps to a lack of social ame&#45;<lb/>&#45;nities and of tact on my part&#45;&#45;&#44; that aware of my<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>incapacity to lengthen its life and give it strength&#44;<lb/> I heartily commend a change in the base of our operations.<lb/>  All look confidently to other men for the concocting of useful<lb/> plans and for a wise direction.  My colleagues celebrated<lb/> for their discernment and persuasive eloquence can offer them&#44;<lb/> and they may moreover bring the popularity enjoyed to bear<lb/> upon the furtherance of a worthy object&#44; which has been left<lb/> hitherto to lag behind.  Why shall there not be among amidst<lb/> a Jewish population of at least ten thousand an institution&#44;<lb/> to which our youths may be drawn for mutual improvement&#63;<lb/>  A central point whence kindly influences may proceed and become<lb/> visible in a closer intercourse among the co&#45;heirs of the same<lb/> Divine Law&#44; and the possessors of the same rich literature&#63;<lb/>  Where&#44; I say&#44; Israelites irrespective of laying aside ritual differences&#44; will<lb/> learn to appreciate and respect one another&#63;....But I<lb/> am admonished to cease.  The sharp eye of our manager is on<lb/> me.  Our understanding was that I would make a few intro&#45;<lb/>&#45;ductory remarks and retire.  I beg his and your pardon&#44; and<lb/> draw quickly back&#44; but not without extending a cordial greet&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing to the assemblage that has honored us with their presence&#44;<lb/> and wishing sincerely that the Hebrew Association of Philadelphia<lb/> may by the exertions of prominent individuals&#44; add lustre to<lb/> our city&#44; and cement the bond of union among our people.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
