<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF3_17</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_17_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_17_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_17_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_17_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_17_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_17_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_17_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_17_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_17_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_17_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_17_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_17_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Post Biblical Lecture<lb/>
                17th<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  Our traditional laws do not favor woman&#39;s<lb/> sovereignty.  In Biblical times Hebrew females did occupy pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;minent stations&#44; but only one&#44; who usurped the<lb/> power&#44; became queen.  However&#44; the reign of Athaba&#44;<lb/> daughter of the impious Ahab King of Israel&#44; and wife of<lb/> the degenerate Jehoram King of Judah was cut short.<lb/>  The An outraged people arose and placed aided by the righteous priests set the crown upon<lb/> the head of Joash&#44; who had escaped from the mur&#45;<lb/>&#45;derous slaughter perpetrated by his unnatural cruel grand&#45;<lb/>mother.  In post&#45;biblical times&#44; the royal<lb/> consort of John Hyrcanus might have been allowed<lb/> to act as regent&#44; in conformity with her husband&#39;s last<lb/> will&#44; if her wicked unnatural son Aristobulus had not cast his mother<lb/> into a prison and made proclaimed himself King of Judea.  But the wi&#45;<lb/>&#45;dow of Alexander Janneus&#44; whose history I cursorily briefly<lb/> related in my last lecture of the course&#44; was certainly the<lb/> acknowledged queen of Judea our people.  Still&#44; I am inclined<lb/> to believe that she was so but nominally and not absolutely&#44; and that she let<lb/> the Sanhedrin&#44; or&#44; as we would term it&#44; the national Parlia&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment&#44; govern the country.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>The speech from the throne&#44; if she Alexandra delivered<lb/> any&#44; must have been a mere rehearsal of what<lb/> that authoritative body suggested.  For nine<lb/> years Alexandra the wife of Janneus reigned in comparative tranquility.<lb/>  As she could not officiate in the capacity of high&#45;<lb/>priest&#44; she clothed with the sacerdotal garments the<lb/> older of her two sons&#44; Hyrcamus&#44; so named after his<lb/> grand&#45;father.  But her second son Aristobulus<lb/> was not unlike his uncle who bore the same name.<lb/>  Ambitious and haughty he did not scruple employing using<lb/> foul means to gratify attain his passions wicked ends.  Although<lb/> his father had made it a parting request that<lb/> the Pharisees should be used treated with their highest<lb/> respect&#44; Aristobulus showed a preference for the<lb/> discarded Sadducees.  Unfortunately&#44; he was<lb/> given a strong motives for espousing the cause<lb/> of the dissenters.  The Pharisees failed to show exercise the moderation and forbearance which would have softened asperities.  Not satisfied<lb/> with having recalled from exile those of their sect&#44; who<lb/> had been banished under the last administration&#44;<lb/> they were harsh and&#44; in some instances&#44; cruel unforgiving towards<lb/> their former opponents.  They demanded the execution of<lb/> officials who had put to death many of their adherents.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>At Irritated by that&#44; Aristobulus convened together some of the most<lb/> distinguished among the Sadducees&#44; and called upon the queen.<lb/>  The deputation complained to her of the indignities to which<lb/> men a people who had been her husband&#39;s staunch friends were<lb/> subjected.  Cunningly it the spokes of men dwelt on the services rendered<lb/> to her family in the past by a sect now given over<lb/> to their enemies adversaries.  The haughty Aristobulus went so<lb/> far as to make his mother understand feel&#44; that she&#45;&#45;a female&#45;&#45;had<lb/> no right to the throne&#44; while Alexander Janneus had<lb/> left two sons.  Alexandra was worked up to the<lb/> highest pitch of excitement.  Gratitude Fear and and maternal indulgence&#44;<lb/> fear and distrust struggled within her breast.  At length she<lb/> agreed to a compromise.  The Sadducees should exercise <sic>weild</sic><lb/> some power.  A number of fortresses&#44; far away from<lb/> the capital&#44; should be placed to under their guardianship&#44;<lb/> and serve afford them military occupations&#44;&#45;&#45;a kind con&#45;<lb/>&#45;cession&#44; but an unwise measure.  The queen<lb/> soon fell sick to die.  The thought of losing her&#44; whose<lb/> motherly womanly tenderness had been stronger than exceeded her royal<lb/> discretion&#44; did not trouble the ambitious Aristobulus.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>He stole away from Jerusalem to raise troops<lb/> an army among his partisans&#44; and prepare to<lb/> dispute the claims of his elder brother Hyrcamus<lb/> to the Judean kingdom.  The anxious mother noticed<lb/> his absence&#44; and inquired into the cause.  She was<lb/> not long to learn that Aristobulus had left quitted her<lb/> side in her last moments to go and stir up sedition&#44; that he had already<lb/> collected a large force army and seized important fortresses.<lb/>  It was then that Alexandra discovered the effect of<lb/> her weakness.  In the hopes of checking her son in<lb/> his daringness&#44; she consented to have his wife and<lb/> children kept as hostages in the castle of Baris.<lb/>  But she the queen was too then very near her end and unable to act with unabated unflagging<lb/> energy.  To a deputation of the Pharisees&#44; headed by<lb/> Hyrcanus&#44; the queen she said that her body had grown<lb/> too weak&#44; and her mind too weary to be of any further help.<lb/>  Still she felt satisfied at knowing But&#44; she added&#44; that her departure from earth was eased by the knowledge that she was leaving<lb/> behind a nation strong and rich.  The dying woman<lb/> spoke the truth as people generally understand it&#44; but<lb/> not the truth&#44; as it really is.  A nation like an individual is strong&#44; when<lb/> held up by virtue.  It is rich when supported by wisdom.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Those two essential qualities were sadly wanting<lb/> in the two princes&#44; on whose conduct the destiny<lb/> of the country largely depended.  Hyrcanus was<lb/> inactive and easily led inveigled away.  Aristobulus was rest&#45;<lb/>&#45;less and unyeilding domineering.  Immediately upon the death<lb/> of their mother&#44; civil war broke out.  But the<lb/> army under Hyrcanus fraternized with that led on<lb/> by the more soldierly Aristobulus&#44; and the latter soon<lb/> became master of the situation.  An agreement<lb/> was then entered into by which the elder son of<lb/> Alexandria&#44; glad to live quietly in the exercise of the priest&#45;<lb/>&#45;hood&#44; relinquished his right to the crown in behalf<lb/> of the her younger son.  The mutiny to ratify the treaty<lb/> took place in the Temple&#44; amidst a large vast con&#45;<lb/>&#45;course of people&#44; and with great solemnity.  The two<lb/> brothers embraced with apparent security.  To strength&#45;<lb/>&#45;en the bonds of domestic affection&#44; the only daughter<lb/> of Hyrcanus was promised in marriage to the oldest<lb/> son of Aristobulus.  Uninterrupted peace might<lb/> now have been the lot of Judea&#44; if a vile writch&#91;sic&#63;&#93;<lb/> had not disturbed it by his deep&#45;laid scheme of<lb/> self&#45;aggrandizement.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Hyrcanus had a pretended friend&#44; called Antipater.<lb/>  History is not clear about the descent of that man&#44;<lb/> but likely he had issued from one of the most influential<lb/> Idumean families&#44; whom John Hyrcanus had compelled<lb/> to become adopt the Jewish faith.  Antipater was possessed of wealth and<lb/> learning&#44; but also of an smooth evil tongue and a wicked<lb/> heart.  He knew well the characters of the two<lb/> scions of the Asmonean race&#44; for he had been brought<lb/> up in their association.  He hated Aristobulus and<lb/> determined to use Hyrcanus as his tool to accomplish this purpose.  A fresh<lb/> quarrel between the two brothers might facilitate his object.<lb/>  For he aimed at raising his own house upon<lb/> the ruins of that created by the illustrious Mat&#45;<lb/>tathias of Modin.  Accordingly&#44; he Antipater spread reports prejudicial<lb/> to Aristobulus wherever and whenever he could.<lb/>  To the leading Jews&#44; he would say that the government<lb/> was insecure&#44; so long as the person at the head of it<lb/> did not belong to their party.  To Hyrcanus he would<lb/> say that life was in danger&#44; so long as the person who had forced<lb/> himself into power&#44; had a strong army at his back.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Hyrcanus refused to listen to treasonable language.<lb/>  Weeks and months and years were spent by the wily<lb/> Idumean in trying to arouse ill&#45;feelings in the a mind<lb/> unwilling to suspect wrong.  But not without<lb/> reason has the book of books repeatedly cautioned us against<lb/> the workings of a smooth deceitful tongue sharper than arrows&#44; keener than the keenest steel.  Antipater haras&#45;<lb/>&#45;sed his dupe into a belief of approaching evils perils&#44; and<lb/> into the necessity of fleeing to a place of safety.<lb/>  In the darkness of night&#44; Hyrcanus was almost<lb/> carried away from Jerusalem and en brought to Petra<lb/> in Arabia.  Its king&#44; Aritas&#44; with whom Antipater<lb/> had had previously entered into secret negotiations&#44; pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;mised an army to fight Aristobulus&#44; and face him in the antici&#45;<lb/> to pation of recovering a number of cities which the<lb/> parent and grand parent Maccabeans had captured from the<lb/> Arabians.  Again&#44; civil war raged fiercely.<lb/>  Aristobulus have being out numbered&#44; retreated within the forti&#45;<lb/>&#45;fications situated round the Temple.  A narrative full<lb/> of sorrow and shame and sacrilege is that connected with this pe&#45;<lb/>&#45;riod of our history.  One brother&#44; aided by foreign hea&#45;<lb/>&#45;thens&#44; closely besetting the other brother&#44; who had been<lb/> compelled to take refuge within the precincts of the dwelling of God.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>The Talmud did not overlook such enormities.  It<lb/> has recorded in all its hideousness the iniquity of which<lb/> our people became then guilty.  For&#44; while the besieged&#44; who<lb/> were mostly Sadduccees&#44; sent over the walls&#44; behind<lb/> which they were entrenched&#44; rolls of gold to buy animals<lb/> for that the sacrificial worship might not be neglected&#44; those who lay the <sic>seige</sic>&#44; mostly profes&#45;<lb/>&#45;sing Pharisaism&#44; often kept the gold given in good<lb/> faith for a holy purpose.  Fraud was one day made<lb/> more execrable by an act which horrified every Jew<lb/> who had not yet sold his faith to unprincipled infamous <sic>parti&#45;<lb/>&#45;zanship</sic>.  Instead of the expected lambs&#44; the impure<lb/> swine was cast over let down where the Sanctuary stood.<lb/>  Another day&#44; the infatuated mob committed a murder<lb/> deserving of the punishment calamities dire chastisement which unhappily was fast<lb/> coming upon the land of our fathers.  An Israelite&#44;<lb/> called Onias&#44; enjoyed the reputation of being a saint.<lb/>  It is said that one year Passover was drawing nigh&#44;<lb/> and the bitter rain falling in March and so needed for to supply with water the pilgrims flocking to<lb/> Jerusalem with water was wanting.  Onias made a circle upon the<lb/> ground&#44; and stood there in supplication till copious showers poured down.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>He The pious Israelite loved his religion and country&#44; but to avoid the grievous sight which met him now on<lb/> all sides&#44; the pious Israelite he had hidden himself<lb/> into a cave.  He was sought after&#44; and dragged<lb/> out of his secret shelter.  &#34;Pray for us&#34; cried the excited<lb/> populace.  &#34;Since thou art so much liked by the Lord&#44; that<lb/> He unfastened the flood gates of the sky at thy request&#44; utter<lb/> let a course against Aristobulus and his followers&#44; that<lb/> they may be exterminated.&#34;  And the righteous man<lb/> prayed thus&#58; &#34;O Lord God of universe&#33;  Since those in whose<lb/> midst I now stand are thy people&#44; and those who<lb/> are besieged are thy priests&#44; I beseech Thee not to<lb/> hearken to either against to the injury of one another.&#34;  He had<lb/> scarcely finished when he fell dead by the under pelting stones.<lb/>  thrown at him Josephus tells us that Providence avenged deeds so<lb/> horrible by a hurricane&#44; which destroyed all the produce and  brought on the<lb/> suffering of famine.  But a still severer punishment calamity was waiting Judea.  Legions<lb/> and cohorts knocked at her gates.  Devastation preceded them&#44; dispersion was at their heels.  At the end of a hundred years&#44; the independence<lb/> which Mattathias and his heroic sons bled for was forfeited by their un&#45;<lb/>&#45;worthy descendants.  What the unity of the five heroic brothers conquered&#44;<lb/> the shameless <sic>dissentions</sic> of unbrotherly brothers lost.  We shall see hereafter<lb/> how the house of Antipater&#44; propped up by Rome was lifted up&#44; and how<lb/> it fell in its own turn&#44; to rise no more.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
