<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF21_3</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet></placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff21_3_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff21_3_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff21_3_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff21_3_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff21_3_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff21_3_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff21_3_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff21_3_4v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>6 pages on 3 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>For Parashat Shemini<lb/>
                about the prohibition of eating oysters.<lb/></p>
            
            <p>134</p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>I have no wish to animadvert on the actions of any<lb/> of my hearers.  They who knowingly feed upon objects&#44;<lb/> which the Mosaic code forbids&#44; and still claim to be<lb/> the adherents of that legislation&#44; need not be shown<lb/> the inconsistency.  It rests with themselves to reconcile<lb/> their habitual practice with their avowed professions.<lb/>  But I have heard that among my brethren some fall<lb/> short in their obedience to the dietary laws&#44; and believe<lb/> they do not violate any of the injunctions set forth in<lb/> the lessons of Leviticus we have recited this Sabbath.<lb/>  Those of my coreligionists I would fain afford some information<lb/> which may correct an error of judgment&#44; and be the means<lb/> of preventing further transgressions.<lb/></p>
            <p>I observe that the sentence&#44; which prohibits Israelites to eat<lb/> of certain fishes&#44; employs various expressions to apparently<lb/> signify the same ordinance.  It reads as follows&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;All that have not fins and scales<lb/> in seas and in rivers&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;of all that move in the<lb/> water&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;And of all living things that<lb/> are in the water&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;they are an abomination to you.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>A slight reflection will bring home to our minds the<lb/> conviction that the seemingly unnecessary repetition was<lb/> intended to explain il in all its bearings the design of the<lb/> legislator.  We are first told that the Hebrew people<lb/> must  consider as loathsome for food any fish found in<lb/> large bodies of water&#44; lacking the requisite marks just&#45;<lb/>&#45;named.  But lest persons argue that only such creatures<lb/> are meant by the statutes&#44; which enable us by their size<lb/> to perceive whether they are deficient of the prescribed signs&#44;<lb/> and that whatever is so small as to render it impossible<lb/> for us to ascertain its exact conformation&#44; cannot be under&#45;<lb/>&#45;stood as pertaining to that nomenclature&#59; in other words&#59; lest<lb/> persons permit themselves diminutive creatures with which<lb/> lakes and ponds abounded&#59; the sentence next cautions us against<lb/> partaking of anything that moves in the water&#44; whether<lb/> it be of huge or of little dimension&#44; until we have positively<lb/> learnt that it possesses the required tokens.<lb/></p>
            <p>So far the Bible extended its prohibition to every kind of<lb/> <sic>acquatic</sic> animals inhabiting the water&#44; and wanting of<lb/> fins and scales.  But there exists in nature creatures<lb/> that do not necessarily abide or move in water&#44; yet they<lb/> will not thrive except in places where water flows.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>To that nature we may consider to belong that beb being<lb/> furnished with a bivalve shell&#44; and known by the name of oyster.<lb/>  Has the Mosaic code left any direction applicable to its case&#63;<lb/>  Is it included in the family of fishes and forbidden&#44; or excluded<lb/> from it and permitted&#63;  I believe that our Bible has been<lb/> very explicit concerning it&#44; when it stated in the last part<lb/> of our sentence &#34;any living thing which is in the water&#44; shall<lb/> be an abomination unto you.&#34;  I shall not now<lb/> launch into a disquisition touching the character of the<lb/> aforenamed creature.  Naturalists have differed widely with<lb/> regard to it&#44; and it would be presumption on my part to treat<lb/> the subject on from a scientific point of view.  I know that while<lb/> some have confidently asserted that the oyster is motionless&#44;<lb/> and that it adheres with tenacity solely to stones and rocks<lb/> by the water&#44; others have brought forth their observations and<lb/> experience as proofs that it is endowed with locomotion&#44; and<lb/> it has the power of throwing itself backwards and forwards in<lb/> the water by sudden jerks.  To me the words of<lb/> Holy Writ are amply sufficient for the rejection of that<lb/> animal for our aliment.  Because it clearly comes in the<lb/> category of living things which are in the water&#44; and which Moses<lb/> declared unfit for the use of Israelites&#44; by an emphatic repetition<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>in general terms of the ordinance at issue.  &#34;Whatever has<lb/> no fins and scales in the water&#44; that shall be an abomination<lb/> unto you.&#34;  But aside from the plain<lb/> unvarnished words of the text&#44; tradition&#44; I think&#44; has a right<lb/> to be consulted in the premises.  I say in the present instance&#44;<lb/> as in all other instances&#59; a practice which has been uni&#45;<lb/>&#45;versally accepted among Hebrew communities&#44; bears with<lb/> it the stamp of high authority.  Now&#58; I have not once<lb/> read or heard that Jews observant of the ancestral religion deem<lb/> it lawful to feed on shell&#45;fish&#59; nor have I ever seen&#44;<lb/> save in cases of rapidly failing health&#44; a consistent Israelite<lb/> act as if he regarded the eating of oysters quite permissible.<lb/>  So perfect a conformity to the observance among our coreligio&#45;<lb/>&#45;nists dispersed in innumerable countries&#44; could not have<lb/> been brought about except by oral tradition instruction from father<lb/> to son.  This is not denied by the teachers of the<lb/> new school.  Their preaching that we may freely sa&#45;<lb/>&#45;tisfy our appetites with whatsoever natured created for<lb/> food&#44; does not emanate from any objection to the traditio&#45;<lb/>&#45;nal rendering of our text&#44; but from an aversion against all<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>ceremonial laws.  They desire to abrogate the statutes we<lb/> have perused this morning in Leviticus&#44; on the same principle<lb/> by which the disciples of another creed were guided&#44; when they<lb/> wrote.  &#34;There is nothing from without a man&#44; which entering into<lb/> him&#44; can defile him.&#34;  But I direct my words to men<lb/> and women&#44; who have not cast off the salutary yoke of the<lb/> law.  I speak to Hebrews who have not made common cause with<lb/> the changelings&#44; but who still believe that what the son of<lb/> Amram proclaimed an abomination&#44; does defile the soul.  Them<lb/> do I exhort to exercise some self&#45;restraint which cannot fail<lb/> to be beneficial to the moral as well as to the spiritual weal of<lb/> their offspring.  To them I say&#58; you have hitherto been noted<lb/> for your attachment to the precepts&#44; be not now inveigled by<lb/> specious reasonings.  Let not your houses heretofore kept Jewishly<lb/> be defiled&#59; let not your table formerly free from pollution be<lb/> sullied&#44; by presenting thereon to your children and guests what<lb/> the Mosaic code prohibits.  The ordinance I have urged is not<lb/> simply a Rabbinical fence to prevent trespassing on the written law&#44;<lb/> but a prescription obviously deducible from the text.  Act then<lb/> consistently.  Continue Put not a stumbling block in the way of<lb/> the rising generation.  Continue to prove the light&#44; and they will<lb/> also &#34;keep the commandments precepts&#44; the statutes and ordinances commanded to our<lb/> fathers.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
