<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF19_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff19_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff19_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff19_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff19_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff19_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff19_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff19_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff19_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff19_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff19_2_5v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            <p>The character of Elisha&#44; brought to our notice&#44; in the<lb/> Haftorah of this Sabbath&#44; has come down to posterity&#44; shrouded<lb/> in a veil of marvels.  Of all individuals&#44; who succeeded<lb/> the greatest of prophets&#44; in the leadership of Israel&#44; the<lb/> son of Shaphat&#44; stands foremost in the way of the miraculous.<lb/>  Sacred history ascribes to him faculties never met in any one<lb/> man&#44; however endowed with an inspired genius.  To Elisha<lb/> have been attributed&#44; a mind&#44; that could dive into the future&#44; a<lb/> power which could control the elements&#44; and an influence<lb/> that extended over life and death.  Now&#44; we hear his voice<lb/> predict a victory&#44; anon&#44; foretell a defeat.  At one time&#44;<lb/> we see him defy the tides&#44; and cross a river dryshod&#44; at<lb/> another&#44; we are shown how his hand draws foulness out<lb/> of a spring of water with a measure of salt.  Again&#58; he<lb/> rises indignant and human life becomes extinct&#44; he stretches<lb/> his body over the dead&#44; and life is restored.  Some of<lb/> the boldest thinkers&#44; among modern and ancient writers&#44; have<lb/> not scrupled to intimate&#44; that Elijah&#39;s disciple&#44; had learnt in<lb/> schools&#44; which flourished at that period&#44; in the holy land&#44;<lb/> what was hidden from the multitudes&#44; and he performed<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>deeds&#44; considered in his days&#44; absolute miracles&#44;<lb/> but which were the result of arts as then discovered&#44; and<lb/> of science as then <sic>developped</sic>.  To accept that opinion<lb/> unconditionally&#44; would be heresy&#59; to deny that it may&#44;<lb/> in part&#44; contain the truth&#44; would be to judge rashly.<lb/>  A note&#45;worthy feature in Judaism is that nature is<lb/> made always to occupy a prominent station.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  She is never<lb/> banished away from sight&#44; to leave the entire room to<lb/> the supernatural.  Those who read the Scriptures thought<lb/>&#45;fully&#44; will discover the working of God&#39;s hand&#45;maid even<lb/> among the most wonderful events.  Thus&#44; for instance&#44; the<lb/> path which the Red&#45;Sea offered to the liberated tribes&#44; was<lb/> opened by an east&#45;wind&#44; which the Author of Nature caused<lb/> tremendously to blow during the whole night.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  The<lb/> manna&#44; which fed our fathers&#44; in uninhabited regions<lb/> fell with the night&#39;s dew&#44; and was kept by it until<lb/> the morning&#44; as under a cover.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  Nay&#58; the delivering<lb/> of the Decalogue was accomplished through as scene&#44;<lb/> in which fire presented to the eye&#44; whe the words which<lb/> the air impressed upon the ear &#43; As it is written&#58;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;These words the Lord<lb/> spoke unto all your assembly on the mountain&#44; from the midst of<lb/> the fire.&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>&#43; The idea which seems to be borne out by the text&#44; is advanced by Hertz Wessels.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Let me&#44; however&#44; be very explicit&#44; that I may not be<lb/> misunderstood.  Our religion does admit the possibility of<lb/> having received from Him who is all&#45;mighty&#44; extraordinary<lb/> powers.  No one who reverences the memory of Moses&#44; the<lb/> lawgiver&#44; will refuse to believe that men were <sic>marvellously</sic><lb/> endowed&#59; but our religion admits also that natural means&#44;<lb/> and a knowledge of their application will prove very effective<lb/> even in accomplishing stupendous works.  I hope&#44; there&#45;<lb/>&#45;fore&#44; that I am not expressing an opinion heretical&#44; or<lb/> dangerously arrogant&#44; when I venture to assert that the learning<lb/> acquired by Elisha&#44; may have been his co&#45;worker in some<lb/> of the wondrous he acts he performed.  That a thorough<lb/> acquaintance with the laws of Hygiene&#44; may have become<lb/> a strong agent in effecting the care of a Syrian general.  That<lb/> his familiarity with the properties of minerals and vegetables&#44;<lb/> may under providence have enabled him to remove injurious qualities from<lb/> both food and drink in time hour of want.  That his profound study of the healing<lb/> art&#44; may have combined with his superhuman gift in<lb/> resuscitating the infant son of his generous hostess.  For&#44;<lb/> this is the striking difference between our belief&#44; and that<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>of other people.  We make the possession of<lb/> wisdom&#44; an indispensable attendant of inspiration&#59; as<lb/> the Sages have taught us by saying &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Prophetic spirit can rest only on the wise&#45;hearted&#59;&#34;<lb/> while&#44; according to the teachings of the books we reject&#44;<lb/> the most illiterate can be invested with powers equal to<lb/> those given to the son of Amram.  None of our chosen<lb/> men&#44; were illiterate fishermen.  From Abraham to<lb/> Malachi&#44; from David to Nehemiah&#44; all the leading<lb/> characters in our Bible&#44; evinced superior understanding&#44;<lb/> keen discernment&#44; and a well cultivated mind.<lb/>  Nor was their mission to astonish the world by miracles&#44;<lb/> but to educate&#44; to improve and exalt.  And if in<lb/> the prosecution of their holy task&#44; they did at times per&#45;<lb/>form what will ever remain unexplained to our finite<lb/> reasons&#44; they did not do violence to nature&#44; when ac&#45;<lb/>&#45;complishing supernatural acts.  The driving of impure<lb/> spirits into the bodies of unclean animals&#44; or the reviving of human bodies&#44; that had decayed in their grave&#44; are is<lb/> not numbered among their astounding achievements.<lb/>  This much I felt necessary to say&#44; in order to correct an error har&#45;<lb/>&#45;bored by some&#44; who&#44; being Jews&#44; have not a right<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>conception of Judaism.  There is a tendency to confound<lb/> things&#44; and jump at conclusions.  Persons incapable<lb/> of drawing a distinction between a religion which admits<lb/> the possibility of miracles&#44; and another which has set<lb/> thereupon the foundations of its whole structure&#44; will<lb/> place in one and the same category eternal truths and<lb/> unfathomable mysteries&#59; liberal doctrines and proscriptive<lb/> dogmas.  They will blend and jumble together Sinai<lb/> and Calbary&#44; a man&#45;god and a godly man&#44; they<lb/> will contend that a mystic veil covers the history of<lb/> all beliefs&#44; and they will incredulously will they turn their back<lb/> upon our volumes&#44; as they cast aside the directions of<lb/> a &#34;new testament.&#34;  Ah&#33; my Brethren&#33;  Learn once<lb/> the art of winnowing&#44; and separate the chaff from the<lb/> wheat &#91;Hebrew&#93; Understand rightly and judge maturely.<lb/>  Your religion is not a myth&#44; but a manual of<lb/> duties.  You are nowhere commanded&#44; to give credence<lb/> to wonders&#44; but you are everywhere bid to live up to<lb/> the rales of a health&#45;&#45;and mind&#45;&#45;preserving law.  You are<lb/> not assured of salvation&#44; if you belief believe in things super&#45;<lb/>&#45;natural&#44; but if you will act as nature and nature&#39;s God dictates.  This<lb/> teaching&#44; which underlies the books of Moses&#44; is borne<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>out by the preaching of individuals&#44; whom we call pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;phets&#44; not because they made us stand aghast by at<lb/> miracles executed&#44; but because their lips purified by a heavenly<lb/> fire breathed words of goodness&#44; an of charity&#44; of truth.<lb/>  We revere them&#44; though they came to us divested of<lb/> all mystery.  Samuel and Isaiah&#44; Micah and<lb/> Jeremiah &#91;Note&#58; Hebrew inserted above the names listed&#93;&#44; the fearless messengers of the Most High&#44; speak<lb/> to us yet&#59; we hear the their undying spirit addresses to us a language which appeals to the<lb/> understanding&#44; and wins the heart.<lb/></p>
            <p>But even the character of the man&#44; who figures con&#45;<lb/>&#45;spicuously in our Haftorah&#44; through by reason of miracles&#44; exemplified<lb/> the principles upon which our religion stands.  I could cannot<lb/> not but refrain to from contrasting the first utterance recorded in the life<lb/> of Elisha&#44; with an expression often made by the author<lb/> of our neighbor&#39;s creed.  Elijah passed through the field&#44;<lb/> which the son of Shaphat was tending.  The mantle cast<lb/> towards him&#44; indicated the wish that he might exchange<lb/> husbandry for the ministry of God.  The youth felt<lb/> instantly the holy influence.  Ready to follow the great<lb/> Master who had chosen him for his successor&#44; he asked a<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>favor &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Let me go&#44; I pray thee&#44;<lb/> and kiss my father&#44; and my mother.&#34;  Of the man of<lb/> Nazareth we read&#44; that he renounced nature&#39;s obligations&#44;<lb/> when assuming his mission.  Pointing to his adherents&#44; he<lb/> is said to have exclaimed &#34;Behold&#44; my mother and my brothers.&#34;<lb/>  I have no intention to cast obloquy upon my neighbor&#39;s our the<lb/> belief that any of my fellow&#45;mortals may honestly hold&#44; but I desire to teach Israelites to discriminate&#44; and<lb/> feel mark where superiority lies.<lb/></p>
            <p>But not to allow my thoughts too wide a range&#44; I will<lb/> remark observe that what we have perused this morning<lb/> reflects the noble instincts which stirred Elisha to act.<lb/>  The widow for whose support he miraculously provided&#44; was<lb/> the wife of a self&#45;sacrificing man&#59; of a man who had<lb/> died in poverty&#44; while striving spiritually to enrich his<lb/> Hebrew fellow&#45;being.  He had bequeathed nothing save<lb/> the memory of his self denial&#44; and of devotion to his a sacred<lb/> calling&#59; but what cooked the deep sympathy of Elisha&#44;<lb/> did not not soften the heart of a pitiless creditor.<lb/>  The sons of the righteous one who had died&#44; would have been<lb/> made to pay their father&#39;s indebtedness&#44; in menial abhorrent slavery&#44;<lb/> had not the <sic>the</sic> prophet been providentially commissioned<lb/> to spare a mother the keenest sorrow.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>And profound gratitude mingled with tender compassion in<lb/> the bosom of Elisha.  The thought that she who had<lb/> built and set apart a room in her habitation&#44; where he and<lb/> his attendant might be hospitably entertained should suffer<lb/> the intensity of anguish&#44; because of her bereavement of an only child&#44; drew from his soul a fervent prayer&#44;<lb/> which was heard in ascended the heavens&#44; to the joy of a previously distressed parent.<lb/>  I leave aside what is supernatural in those events&#44; but I have<lb/> recalled what is conformable with the sentiments instilled<lb/> by nature&#44; that all my hearers&#44; may copy the goodly<lb/> model.<lb/></p>
            <p>Specially&#44; and suitably can I instruct you &#43; by that means&#44;<lb/> my brother Bar Mitzvah.  For compassion and gratitude<lb/> are two virtues which circumstances&#44; connected with your early<lb/> life&#44; ought to have strongly awakened in your breast.<lb/>  It is when we ourselves have endured trials&#44; that we can most<lb/> sensibly feel for others exposed to the same.  And without say&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing ought that might cause you pain&#44; I will exhort<lb/> you to keep alive the memory of the past&#44; and as you found benefactors&#44; when events<lb/> beyond your control&#44; brought you to <sic>straitness</sic>&#44; before<lb/> you found benefactors&#44; so do you&#44; my dear young friend<lb/> &#43; an inmate of the Foster Home.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>show active sympathy&#44; when the Almighty gives<lb/> it in your power&#44; towards all who undergo privations.<lb/>  But gratitude must have an altar with ever&#45;burning<lb/> incense in your heart.  For&#44; Elisha met in the<lb/> house of the generous Shumanith a chamber with a bed&#44;<lb/> and a table&#44; a chair and a lamp&#44; but you have met in<lb/> the hour of need&#44; a home with numerous comforts&#44; a school<lb/> of instruction&#44; and friends willing and anxious to aid you<lb/> in becoming good and useful&#44; honored and happy.  May<lb/> you ever be thankful&#44; and illustrate the sentiments cherished<lb/> by a conduct &#91;&#63;&#93; agreeable to the lessons imbibed.  May<lb/> you become a true type of an Israelite&#59; intelligently religious&#44;<lb/> wisely beneficent&#44; and ready to sacrifice self&#45;interest to<lb/> duty&#44; even like Abraham and like Elisha&#44; a portion<lb/> of whose histories you were privileged to rehearse this<lb/> day&#44; which is to you&#44; solemn and memorable.<lb/></p>
            <p>&#40;This address to the Bar Mitzvah was continued at some length&#41;.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
