<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF1_11</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_11_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_11_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_11_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_11_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_11_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_11_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_11_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_11_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_11_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_11_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_11_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_11_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For two Bar Mitzv&#225;<lb/>
                on<lb/>
                Parashat Chay&#233; Sar&#225;h<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> The rich and the poor have met together&#44; the<lb/> Lord made them all&#34;.  Brethren&#33;  It is my wish<lb/> and my prayer&#44; that the occurrence of this day&#44; may<lb/> be intended as an acknowledgment of that Biblical<lb/> truth.  Two youths have presented themselves<lb/> in this holy house&#44; and have in the same language<lb/> offered thanks to God.  But their station in life<lb/> is not alike.  He who first blessed the name of<lb/> the Lord&#44; is lowly&#44; deficient in earthly goods&#44; and bereft<lb/> of a father&#39;s tender care and love.  The one who<lb/> followed him is the inmate of a luxurious home&#44;<lb/> the child of wealth&#44; and the object of parental en&#45;<lb/>&#45;dearments.  Yet both declared asserted that they are the<lb/> joint&#45;heirs of an inestimable treasure.  Both de&#45;<lb/>&#45;clared to possess the means which will secure equally<lb/> to them endurable happiness.  Is it really so&#63;<lb/>  Have the rich and the poor in Israel a common heritage&#63;<lb/>  A patrimony which supplies all with an unfailing<lb/> support&#63;  What say ye&#44; my young hearers&#63;<lb/>  I fully agree with the two Bar Mitzv&#225; in their<lb/> open declarations.  Do you also assent to it&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Is the law that Moses commanded us&#44; valued as<lb/> an inheritance by you&#44; who will soon form a congre&#45;<lb/>&#45;gation in Jacob&#63;  Let me rejoice in the assurance<lb/> that your warm hearts beat high still for your<lb/> religion and your people.  Not many years have<lb/> elapsed&#44; since you first ascended this pulpit&#44; and<lb/> publicly avowed that the word of God is the sole guide to<lb/> human prosperity felicity.  Is that your present conviction&#63;<lb/>  You must pardon me&#44; if my expression betrays any<lb/> distrust in your firmness of purpose.  Sad experience<lb/> has taught me caution.  Too often have I seen the<lb/> professions of youth&#44; belied ere manhood had been<lb/> reached.  Some whom I imagined would have<lb/> grown to do Judaism honor&#44; evince by their daily actions&#44;<lb/> utter contempt for its ordinances&#59; while others that<lb/> I prepared for the day on which they attained religious<lb/> majority&#44; now disdain to be reckoned as members of<lb/> the Synagogue.  This is indeed a gloomy picture&#44;<lb/> but not one which has been designedly overdrawn.<lb/>  I have delineated simply that which he that has<lb/> eyes to see can attest to be a palpable fact.<lb/>  Yes&#44; I am deeply grieved at so great a dereliction among the rising generation&#44; but<lb/> thank God I have not lost all faith in my Brethren.  The cause<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>of religion will triumph&#44; though&#44; like among the<lb/> army of Gideon&#44; only three hundred could be found&#44;<lb/> that did not bend the knees to Baal.  To you&#44;<lb/> my young brothers friends&#44; do I look&#44; if not with the san&#45;<lb/>&#45;guine expectation of former years&#44; with anxious hope<lb/> at least.  To you I look for the success of that holy<lb/> cause.  Your minds are open to healthful impressions<lb/> your feelings strike a sympathetic chord at the appeals<lb/> of the forsaken religion of Sinai.  Let not&#44; I pray you&#44;<lb/> let not the dictates of self&#45;interest change your noble en&#45;<lb/>&#45;thusiasm into a chilling indifference.  Keep its flame<lb/> vivid and bright.  Suffer not ambition or avarice to<lb/> extinguish it from within your breasts.  I hail&#44; my<lb/> dear friends&#33; the day on which I see the increase of your<lb/> number&#59; for despite many disappointments&#44; I delight<lb/> in thinking that the disaffection of some&#44; will be counte&#45;<lb/>&#45;racted by your staunch adherence to the belief of<lb/> our fathers.  This Sabbath especially has<lb/> inspired me with fresh hope&#44; for&#44; as I said&#44; on it<lb/> a Biblical truth has been clearly illustrated.<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;The rich and the poor have met together&#44; &#40;to acknow&#45;<lb/>&#45;ledge&#41; that the Lord hath made them all&#34;<lb/>  The religion of Israel does not&#44; like that of heathens&#44;<lb/> admit of different castes&#44; entrusted with a partial<lb/> knowledge of human duties.  No&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Universal enlightenment is its prin ruling prin&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciple.  Hence it is that the humblest among our brethren&#44;<lb/> not less than the highest&#44; expected to perform the<lb/> commandments of the Lord.  None needs plead<lb/> ignorance&#44; for the light that shone upon Horeb<lb/> illumined all&#44; and by all can Judaism be faithfully<lb/> and intelligently represented.  Raise then your head<lb/> with manly dignity&#44; my young brother&#44; who are humbly<lb/> situated.  The religion you have acknowledged this day&#44;<lb/> has dignified exalted your existence.  It has conferred upon<lb/> you the right of equality.  You Morally and spiritually&#44;<lb/> you are inferior to none.  Your future actions&#44; and<lb/> not the worldly goods your parents have gathered&#44; will<lb/> exalt you enhance your position on earth.  They will glorify your Creator&#44; and give<lb/> your soul immortality.  Only be sincere and<lb/> steadfast in your declarations.  You should consi&#45;<lb/>&#45;der the event you have celebrated&#44; as the first<lb/> step to a career of usefulness and honor.<lb/></p>
            <p>You are now lacking what others may possess<lb/> in abundance&#44; but the Father of the fatherless did not forsake you.  He did<lb/> prepare for you the requisite comforts of life.<lb/>  A home where you meet sympathy&#44; consideration and<lb/> timely aid was open to receive you.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>I can appreciate the loss you have early sustained.  It was severe and irreparable.  But friends and<lb/> relatives&#44; most affectionate and kind are still with<lb/> you.  Their arms are stretched forth to help&#59; and<lb/> they will&#44; under Providence&#44; lead you to a path where<lb/> industry obtains its reward.  Let this thought<lb/> animate you&#59; let it inspire you with gratitude<lb/> to God&#44; and with a powerful desire to mount high<lb/> up on the social ladder.  You may yet acquire<lb/> influence and wealth&#59; for&#44; it has been authoritatively written &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;The hand of the diligent shall be made bear rule&#44;&#34; &#38; else&#45;<lb/>where rich.&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;The hand of the diligent shall be made maketh rich.&#34;  But....Remember this day&#59; forget<lb/> not nor be ever ashamed of your lowly extraction.  The section you have<lb/> read&#44; gives you instruction.  We find recorded<lb/> therein a circumstance worthy of your notice.<lb/>  It is the following<lb/> Eliezer saw that his undertaking was about to<lb/> be crowned with success.  The family of Rebecca<lb/> had offered him a generous hospitality.  Their demea&#45;<lb/>&#45;nour toward him denoted respect.  He might<lb/> then have represented himself as a greater personage.<lb/>  He might have said&#44; that he was a confidential<lb/> friend&#44; as a messenger charged by Abraham with<lb/> an errand which he would et entrust to no other inferior man.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>He might have exhibited a pardonable pride at his being<lb/> thought deemed of so much consequence.  But what were<lb/> the words with which Eliezer opened his speech&#63;<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;I am the servant of Abraham.&#34;<lb/>  His humility <sic>equalled</sic> his fidelity.  In all<lb/> the walks of life&#44; let it be your future endeavours&#44;<lb/> to exemplify those noble traits of human character.<lb/>  Humility &#38; fidelity to God and man.  And you my young brother&#44; whom<lb/> the Almighty has so greatly blessed.  You the<lb/> only surviving son of fond parents.  You who<lb/> are being reared with the tenderest care and surrounded<lb/> with joys&#59; what sentiments&#44; but those of gratitude<lb/> ought now to fill your breast&#63;  The exertions you made<lb/> to conquer overcome a national timidity&#44; in order to perform a<lb/> a religious practice is laudable.  You have gratified<lb/> thereby those you owe a debt that can never be paid&#44; and<lb/> shown some disposition to righteousness.  But<lb/> much greater exertions than that will be necessary&#44;<lb/> to <sic>fulfil</sic> what the law of our God commands.  The<lb/> best manner in which you can express gratitude for the favors enjoyed&#44;<lb/> will be by your future efforts in to conquering sin.<lb/>  Your happy condition in life exposes you to enticements&#44;<lb/> which are not held out to youths in needy circumstances.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>The love of pleasure may lead you astray.  The<lb/> felicity you will have to overreach others in the<lb/> pursuit of gaiety and fashion&#44; may lay a snare<lb/> to your feet.  Be on your guard.  Beware of<lb/> false friends.  Avoid those that advise a departure<lb/> from the religion you have openly avowed this day&#44;<lb/> in order to satisfy the cravings of the flesh.<lb/>  Restrain your appetites and the lust of gain.<lb/>  Give to God what is God&#39;s.  The days he set apart for His worship.<lb/>  You may by so doing&#44; discover perhaps&#44; that the<lb/> heap of gold&#44; which will so please gratify your eye&#45;sight&#44;<lb/> had grown a little lower&#59; but you will then stand higher<lb/> before your heavenly Creator&#44; before your fellow&#45;men&#44;<lb/> and in your own estimation.  Thus you will<lb/> show a thankful heart for the benefits enjoyed<lb/> in early years.  Thus you will prove the sincerity<lb/> of your utterance before the Lord&#44; and before this Con&#45;<lb/>&#45;gregation of your brethren.  And now I conclude<lb/> with a prayer that your future may be as joyous as<lb/> the past&#44; but also with an exhortation to follow the<lb/> example pointed out also to you in the portion<lb/> you have rehearsed.  The relatives of Rebecca<lb/> were loth to part with her so unexpectedly&#44; and<lb/> they asked of Eliezer that she might remain with them<lb/> a short space of time.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>But the faithful servant could not consent&#44;<lb/> lest he break the promise made to his master.<lb/>  &#34;Do not delay me&#44;&#34; he2 exclaimed &#91;Hebrew&#93;1<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; since the Lord hath prospered Thy<lb/> way.&#34;  The Lord and not his foresight&#44; or<lb/> his wisdom sagacity.  The Lord and not his well arranged matured<lb/> plans.  Him alone he recognized as the author<lb/> of his success&#44; and in Him he confided for the speedy<lb/> cons realization of Abraham&#39;s dearest wish.  My Brother&#33;<lb/>  Keep the scriptural incident fresh in your memory&#44;<lb/> and let your conduct be formed after its mould it be standard of your conduct.<lb/>  When prosperous in your undertakings&#44; see the hand<lb/> of God that showers down blessings.  Attribute to the<lb/> Director of human events the abundance affluence you may enjoy&#44;<lb/> and the honors which may be in store for you.<lb/>  Then humility will beautify your existence.  You<lb/> will be religious and virtuous&#44; you will be charitable<lb/> and kind&#59; you will profoundly feel and demon&#45; obviously illustrate<lb/> &#45;strate that by our actions&#44; was exhibited this day&#44; that what you have tacitly acknowledged this day&#44; viz&#44; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;The poor and the rich have met together&#44; the<lb/> Lord hath made all of them all.&#34;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
