<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF8_8</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>New York, NY</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1889-09" source="" attested="yes">22 September 1889</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_8_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_8_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_8_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_8_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_8_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_8_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_8_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_8_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_8_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_8_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_8_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_8_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For the consecration of Synagogue<lb/>
                Moses Montefiore in Harlem<lb/>
                Sep 22nd 1889<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  No one who has the honor of<lb/> the Jewish religion at heart&#44; can sufficiently<lb/> deprecate the unprecedented increase of<lb/> meeting rooms for the ostensible purpose of<lb/> public worship.  In Philadelphia they<lb/> multiply disproportionately to their want&#44;<lb/> and I&#44; knowing that&#44; almost reproach my<lb/>&#45;self for lending my countenance to such<lb/> irregular assemblages.  The <sic>defence</sic> which<lb/> I am <sic>allege</sic> is nevertheless clear.  As I<lb/> am powerless to prevent what I consider an<lb/> evil&#44; I seek its mitigation by a brotherly<lb/> counsel in occasional addresses.  Failing<lb/> to break up what not infrequently has local<lb/> prejudices for its origin&#59; what injures the interests<lb/> of properly organized and decorously conducted<lb/> synagogues&#44; I try to influence for good men<lb/> and women whom I must own as members<lb/> of my race.  By approaching them with<lb/> kindness&#44; I may hope to ward off a national<lb/> stigma&#45;&#45;Hillul kashem&#45;&#45;the profanation of the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>name of God&#44; which shames Israel at<lb/> large.<lb/></p>
            <p>From all which I can gather&#44; the object that<lb/> I regretfully see in the city of my princi&#45;<lb/>&#45;pal exertions&#44; exists also in New York&#44; and<lb/> it has a wider field for its mischievous<lb/> operations&#44; by reason of the population of<lb/> foreign Hebrews flocking <sic>therin</sic> conti&#45;<lb/>&#45;nually.  Most painfully noticeable<lb/> is the circumstance I lament at the forth&#45;<lb/>&#45;coming solemn season of our year&#44; when<lb/> places ill&#45;according with the dignity of<lb/> the Divine services are chosen&#44; and persons<lb/> unqualified to stand as Shelich&#232; Zibbur&#45;&#45;<lb/> officiating ministers at the sacred desk&#45;&#45;<lb/> offer propitiatory prayers and benedictions.<lb/>  Now&#44; brethren&#44; it is heartfelt satisfaction<lb/> to me to know that the religious body<lb/> hearing a name deservedly revered where&#45;<lb/>&#45;soever the outcasts of Judea dwell&#44; is not<lb/> to be reckoned among objectionable associations&#44;<lb/> with high&#45;sounding titles&#44; but having nothing<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>to support their claims.  The &#34;Moses Monte&#45;<lb/>&#45;fiore&#34; is a legitimate Kehal Adona&#239;&#45;&#45;&#34;Congre&#45;<lb/>&#45;gation of the Lord&#34;&#45;&#45;founded upon the laudable<lb/> wish to build up intelligent &#34;Conservatism&#34; in<lb/> a spot of the great metropolis of free America&#44;<lb/> where Israelites visibly grow very numerous.<lb/>  The venerable &#34;residue of Israel&#34;&#44; to whom the<lb/> glory belongs of having first unfurled the<lb/> banner of the Torah in &#34;new Amsterdam&#34;&#44; even<lb/> before &#34;liberty was proclaimed throughout the<lb/> land unto all the inhabitants thereof&#34;&#44; Shearith<lb/> Israel&#44; I mean&#44; could not anticipate the affi&#45;<lb/>&#45;liation of my coreligionists in Harlem.  A<lb/> great distance hindered it&#44; while the advisability<lb/> of precluding the formation of discreditable<lb/> gatherings by a becomingly constituted assem&#45;<lb/>&#45;blage&#44; must elicit the approval of the old&#45;<lb/>&#45;est Sephardic congregation in the United States.<lb/>  Naturally&#44; my gratification increases because<lb/> the order of service adopted by my brethren<lb/> who now consecrate this building is that of the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>school historically famous&#59; the school from<lb/> which sprung poets who nobly sang to<lb/> the Lord&#59; Sages who drew at the fountain<lb/> of the traditions&#44; and formulated a Syna&#45;<lb/>&#45;gogal ritual.  In the absence of a uniform<lb/> liturgy for the myriads of Israel&#44; whose lot<lb/> Providence has cast in these favored regions&#44;<lb/> that one according to which our Abarbanels&#44;<lb/> our Aboabs&#44; our DeVegas prayed&#44; must be<lb/> preferred to either the Ashkenazic in its lengthy<lb/> and obscurely worded additions&#44; or to the diminu&#45;<lb/>&#45;tive hybrids of &#34;Reform&#44;&#34; often born of igno&#45;<lb/>&#45;rance of the Hebrew language and heresy.<lb/>  Besides&#44; the general characteristics of the<lb/> Spanish and Portuguese manner of <sic>worshipping</sic><lb/> are dignity and decorum&#44; traits inherited<lb/> and not forced out by a compulsory silence<lb/> which is death to congregational worship.<lb/></p>
            <p>But I have not accepted the invitation<lb/> to participate in these ceremonies with the<lb/> view of disparaging some and sounding the<lb/> praises of others.  Empty talk would<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>be mine&#44; if I did not improve the solemn<lb/> occasion by some suggestive thoughts.<lb/>  My Brethren.  What means the dedication<lb/> of an edifice to the Lord&#63;  I understand by<lb/> it the opening of a spiritual intercourse<lb/> between the universal Ruler who vouchsafes<lb/> to let a heavenly ray rest thereupon&#44; and<lb/> His subjects who head before the Shechinah&#44; and<lb/> acknowledge the Divine government.<lb/></p>
            <p>To that ethereal communion the archprophet<lb/> must have alluded in his golden preaching&#44;<lb/> which is eternally recorded in the book whose<lb/> perusal the faithful are about to complete.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Thou hast exalted the Lord<lb/> this day&#34;......&#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;And the Lord<lb/> has exalted thee this day.&#34;  How is that<lb/> mutual glorification effected&#63;  Say our Biblical<lb/> expositors&#58; when Israel declare &#34;the Lord is our<lb/> God&#44; the Lord is One&#34;&#44; the holy spirit &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> hovering around them responds&#58; Who is like<lb/> Israel the One devotional nation upon earth&#63;&#34;<lb/> When Israel exclaim&#58; &#34;Who is like Thee among<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>the mighty O Lord&#33;&#34;&#44; the holy spirit echos<lb/> forth&#58; &#34;Happy thou O Israel&#33;  Who is like thee a<lb/> people saved by the Lord&#63;.&#34;  True&#59; Israel<lb/> are not alone the beneficiaries of the Almighty<lb/> extolling His name.  Even peoples who bow<lb/> to brutish fetishism mean to magnify the<lb/> Monarch of time&#59; so teach the Talmudists &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; but Israel slav and in Malachi<lb/> we read &#34;from the rising of the sun&#44; even unto unto its<lb/> setting my name is great among the gentiles&#44;&#34;<lb/> but Israel stand closer to the Rock of all ages&#44;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> By the law of heredity and by voluntary<lb/> consecration the seed of the patriarchs has chosen<lb/> to cleave to the living Redeemer.<lb/></p>
            <p>Brothers and sisters in Israel.  Will the tendency<lb/> of your organization be luminously to prove<lb/> true that assertion of our seers and sages&#63;<lb/>  Will this structure promote a blissful end&#63;<lb/>  Will the men and women of my race enjoy<lb/> here the spiritual communion with the Shechinah&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>that strengthens the weak in faith&#44; and<lb/> sends them hence to their daily walks of life<lb/> invigorated to pursue right&#63;  Will a stream<lb/> of consolation flow here in time of adversity&#44;<lb/> a spring of celestial joy be found in time of<lb/> prosperity&#63;  Will this structure be a cement<lb/> to the bond of Union which has uninterruptedly<lb/> kept Israel together through untold vicissitudes&#45;&#45;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#63;  For that I fervently pray.<lb/>  Again&#58; I rejoice at being assured that in this<lb/> building an instrument of moral elevation has<lb/> been stored away to be called into daily requisition.<lb/>  I refer to the teaching of the Torah which the<lb/> young will receive&#44; and of the language dear to<lb/> the adherents of the Torah.  The Jew who eager&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly wishes the perpetuity of the religion of Sinai<lb/> and of a monotheistic worship free from gentile<lb/> admixture&#44; must prepare&#44; in advance of the syna&#45;<lb/>&#45;gogue itself&#44; a spot in which our offspring<lb/> will meet and learn the eventful history of<lb/> their people and the manner of unitedly<lb/> singing to the glory of the Most High who<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>watched over the preservation of their people.<lb/>  Mark it my brethren.  In our outpourings on<lb/> the great day of Atonement&#44; we often petition<lb/> God to pardon us for the sake of our guileless<lb/> school children &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Let us care for them&#44; and God&#39;s blessing will<lb/> be ours.  Let us care for them&#44; because in accord&#45;<lb/>&#45;ance with the precept and example obtained&#44; they<lb/> will become either our builders or our destroyers.<lb/>  May the creatures issuing from the diligent super&#45;<lb/>&#45;vision of &#34;the Congregation Moses Montefiore&#44;&#34; rise<lb/> like central pillars in the religious edifice of an intelligent &#34;conservatism.&#34;  May the impres&#45;<lb/>&#45;sion created by the consecration of a house of God&#44;<lb/> stir up the hearts of many Jewish inhabitants<lb/> of Harlem to <sic>enrol</sic> their names among the<lb/> attendants at the worship tendered here to the<lb/> Almighty&#44; and among the practical supporters<lb/> of the religious tuition imparted to the young.<lb/>  Then will the entreaty of the Psalmist be fulfilled&#59;<lb/> our sons growing like plants well tended in their<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>youth&#44; our daughters becoming like polished<lb/> corner stones that sustain and beautify the<lb/> Temple of the One God.  &#34;Oh happy the<lb/> people who shall fare thus&#44; happy the peo&#45;<lb/>&#45;ple whose God is the Lord&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#40;Here followed a conservative prayer&#41;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
