<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF5_5</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_5_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_5_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_5_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_5_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_5_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_5_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_5_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_5_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_5_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_5_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_5_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_5_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_5_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_5_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_5_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_5_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Post&#45;Biblical<lb/>
                on Babylonian Schools<lb/>
                48<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Many lectures I have delivered from time to time&#44; with<lb/> the object of giving affording my hearers some slight information<lb/> on matters of a date&#44; later than that at which the<lb/> Hebrew Bible ends.  Naturally&#44; I directed the mind<lb/> all the while to Palestine&#44; as the country&#44; which&#44; viewed<lb/> from both a religious and a historic standpoint&#44; has<lb/> a primary claim to our consideration.  I spoke of its<lb/> people and of its sages&#44; of its struggle for independence<lb/> and of its schools for the spread of traditional learning.<lb/>  Now I have arrived at a period&#44; in which Palestine<lb/> sinks from our sight view&#44; and another country rises up and commands our<lb/> attention.  Professor Graetz has sensibly written&#44;<lb/> that Babylon became a second mother to Israel.<lb/>  Although the emigration of our ancestors there&#44; was<lb/> forced by the arms of the invincible Nebuchadnezzar&#44;<lb/> nevertheless the situation of the exiles soon took on<lb/> favorable turn.  From Ezra and Ezekiel&#44; who<lb/> lived in Babylon&#44; we learn that certain districts<lb/> had been assigned to the Jews.  There they dwelt un&#45;<lb/>&#45;molested&#44; and enjoyed the right of self&#45;government.<lb/>  Of course&#44; at the outset the loss of country was<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>keenly felt.  We have an evidence of it&#44;<lb/> in the psalms which doubtless belong to that<lb/> period&#59; specially in the 137th&#44; where the poet<lb/> gives vent to the terrible wish that the young babes<lb/> of Babylon might be dashed against a rock.<lb/>  But deep hatred against the destroyer of Palestine&#44;<lb/> gradually made room for sentiments of a mild nature&#59; so much<lb/> so that the next generation of Jews born in Babylon&#44;<lb/> became warmly attached to it.  When that land<lb/> was subjected to Cyrus King of Persia&#44; and this ruler<lb/> issued his famous proclamation&#44; allowing our people<lb/> to go back to Palestine&#44; not quite fifty thousand<lb/> availed themselves of the royal permission&#59; the very<lb/> largest number remained behind.  Unfortunate&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly&#44; history is silent about internal affairs among<lb/> these vast multitudes who preferred the borders of the stranger to the<lb/> ancestral home&#59; but a most valuable letter from to the Rabbis of Kirwan in Egypt Africa a<lb/> Sage&#44; called Sherira&#44; who lived in the tenth century<lb/> of the vulgar era&#44; to the Rabbis of Kirwan in Egypt throws considerable light upon<lb/> the subject.  The tradition that Jehojachin<lb/> King of Judah&#44; who was captured by Nebuchadnezzar&#44;<lb/> being joined by his fellow&#45;prisoners&#44; had taken along<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>from the Holy Land stones and ground and built there&#45;<lb/>&#45;with a Synagogue in Babylon&#44; may be exaggerated&#44;<lb/> but we must admit that at some period&#44; not definitely<lb/> stated after the banishment which we do not find definitely stated&#44; places of worship&#44;<lb/> colleges with their Presidents&#44; and Judges of Jewish<lb/> courts existed among our people beyond the Euphrates.<lb/>  The superiority Perhaps the supremacy justly given ascribed accorded to national institutions<lb/> in Palestine after the restoration under Zerubabel&#44; may<lb/> have caused similar institutions elsewhere to remain<lb/> unknown&#44; or to be little noticed&#44; but to deny that<lb/> religion and learning were cultivated in Babylon<lb/> centuries before the fall of the second Temple and before<lb/> the extinction of Palestinian schools&#44; would be to<lb/> contradict facts.  To prove it this assertion&#44; we may simply<lb/> recall the circumstance that Hillel I.&#44; who lived a<lb/> number of years previous to the founder of Christianity&#44;<lb/> was by no means ignorant&#44; when he <sic>journed</sic> from<lb/> Babylon to study under the illustrious chiefs of the<lb/> schools of Judea.  Like Hillel&#44; so&#44; many other pursued a Jewish<lb/> education at home&#59; some coming afterwards to perfect<lb/> themselves and obtain Rabbinical privileges in the land of Israel.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Now&#44; having freely acknowledged all this&#44; we<lb/> may also confess that institutions of learning in<lb/> the cities between the Euphrates and the Tigris&#44;<lb/> did not gain their great renown&#44; until two<lb/> pupils of Judah the Prince went there&#44; in the third<lb/> century of the common era.  Abba was the<lb/> name of one&#59; the other was called Samuel.  But before<lb/> I proceed further&#44; I may as well give an idea of the<lb/> principal places in Babylon populated then at that time by our<lb/> ancestors.  Nahardea&#44; lying on the river Euphrates&#44;<lb/> was a very large city.  There To it the gifts collected abroad<lb/> for Palestine in aid of the Temple and its Divine ser&#45;<lb/>&#45;vice were collected sent&#44; and from thence those volun&#45;<lb/>&#45;tary contributions were forwarded at the end of every<lb/> year.  On the south of Nahardea&#44; stood a city<lb/> called Firuz&#45;Shabar&#44; said ot have had full ninety<lb/> thousand Jews.  Not very far from it was<lb/> Pumbaditha&#44; mostly populated inhabited by Israelites&#44;<lb/> be much so to a degree that it went by the name of Golah&#44;<lb/> or&#44; as we would term it &#34;a centre of the emigration&#34;.<lb/>  Some miles off&#44; lay Sara&#44; on the river of the same<lb/> name&#44; and known by some as Matha Mahasia.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>On the river Tigris&#44; was Mahuza&#44; in which many<lb/> of our people also congregated.  The Talmud inci&#45;<lb/>&#45;dentally alludes to those main points of Jewish<lb/> activity&#44; and the student cannot help noticing<lb/> how the dwellers differed in character in accordance<lb/> with the nature of their dwelling places.  Thus&#44; Pum&#45;<lb/>&#45;baditha&#44; noted for its gorgeousness and luxuriousness&#44;<lb/> living&#44; abounded in Jews addicted to pleasure and<lb/> not over honest.  Sura offered the very opposite<lb/> aspect&#44; so that a Sage told his children to they should prefer<lb/> to lie on the dung&#45;hills of Sural&#44; than in the man&#45;<lb/>&#45;sions of Pumbaditha.  But in process of time&#44;<lb/> those cities became famous in Rabbinical literature&#44;<lb/> by reason of the great masters who taught there.<lb/></p>
            <p>Abba occupies a high rank among the greatest.  He was one of<lb/> the many who <sic>travelled</sic> from Babylon&#44; or Parthia as<lb/> it actually was then&#44; for the purpose of extending his<lb/> knowledge in Palestine.  He sat at the feet of Judah&#44;<lb/> the immortal Sage who formulated the text of the Mish&#45;<lb/>&#45;nah.  Endowed with bright talents with a retentive<lb/> memory&#44; and a heart full of overflowing with the milk of human kindness&#44; he drew<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>towards himself the love and appreciation<lb/> of his preceptor.  To whom could &#34;our&#34; teacher the<lb/> holy&#34; commit the charge of disseminating abroad<lb/> the knowledge of all the traditions better than<lb/> to his trustworthy pupil&#63;  Abba returned<lb/> to Babylon&#44; splendidly equipped with learning&#59; rich<lb/> in erudition.  Arrived at Nahardea&#44; and being<lb/> unknown&#44; he temporarily accepted the office of<lb/> Methurgeman&#44; whose duty it was in ancient time days<lb/> to explain in the vernacular tongue to the attendants at the college the<lb/> Hebrew text read by the President.  One day It happened once that Abba inter&#45;<lb/>&#45;preted once the text in a manner different from the usual.<lb/>  Having been asked about it found fault with&#44; and having answered that<lb/> he had often rendered it so before a renowned Rabbi<lb/> in Palestine&#44; his identity was discovered.  Then the<lb/> President pained at having engaged so distinguished a scholar so<lb/> distinguished for a subordinate calling&#44; apologised and<lb/> would not suffer him any more to act in that capacity.<lb/>  A story is told that the Exilarch&#44; or the<lb/> appointed Governor of all the Jews in Babylon&#44; cal&#45;<lb/>&#45;led by us &#34;Rosh Galutha&#34;&#44; chief of the captivity&#44;<lb/> gave Abba a political position&#44; making him a<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Kind of overseer&#44; or provision&#44; commissioned<lb/> to see to the honesty of general provision dealers. &#91;&#63;&#93; But<lb/> the Exilarchs&#44; who prided themselves on being of<lb/> a lineal descent from David&#44; were not all except&#45;<lb/>&#45;ional characters.  Being clothed with an almost<lb/> irresponsible power authority&#44; many of them took advantage of it their power&#44;<lb/> and exacted bribe.  Abba who disdained to yeild conjure<lb/> to at wrong&#44; endured trials through the abuse of<lb/> power&#44; but virtue and scholarship could not be crushed by arbitrariness.  Those endowments received at length<lb/> their reward.  He Abba became illustrious by his exer&#45;<lb/>&#45;tions in behalf of Judaism.  He might have<lb/> been raised to the Presidency of the college in Nahar&#45;<lb/>&#45;dea left vacant by the death of its former chief&#44;<lb/> but he would allow chose to let that honor to be reserved for<lb/> his friend and colaborer&#44; Samuel.  He preferred open&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing a school at Sura&#44; whose Jewish population<lb/> stood most in need of wholesome instruction.<lb/>  The number of his listeners&#44; increased immensely&#44; and<lb/> the veneration in which the teacher in Babylon<lb/> was held&#44; equalled that paid to Judah the Prince<lb/> in Palestine&#44; for as the latter was called &#34;the Rabbi&#34;<lb/> by way of eminence&#44; so was his pupil called &#34;Rab&#44;&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>which represents the same title.  The hours of<lb/> his tuition were so wisely regulated&#44; as not to<lb/> prevent hinder agriculturalists and mechanics from fol&#45; in<lb/> &#45;lowing their vocations.  During two months of<lb/> the year&#44; in Adar and Elul&#44; a rehearsal of the<lb/> studies took place&#44; and public lectures were delivered.<lb/>  Abba&#39;s activity was felt far and wide&#44; and the<lb/> reputation of his report that he used his own means in for the support<lb/> of poor students&#44; increased his popularity exceedingly.<lb/>  His fame reached the ears of Artaban King of<lb/> Parthia&#44; and between the two a respectful friendship grew sprung up.<lb/>  On one occasion the gentile monarch sent the Hebrew<lb/> Sage a precious gift&#44; and the recipient sent in return<lb/> a Mezuzah&#44; or the scroll of parchment to be affixed<lb/> to our door&#45;posts.  In answer to the inquiry about the<lb/> strange present&#44; Abba said that while the royal gift<lb/> needed watchers lest it be stolen&#44; his own presented<lb/> watches over those who possess it&#44; for it keeps alive the memory of the promises of<lb/> God to the righteous are inscribed in it and it is &#91;&#63;&#93; is an incentive to virtue.  Scholars<lb/> know how diligently&#44; affectionately and effectually Rab<lb/> taught during twenty eight consecutive years&#59;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>scholars are aware that his decisions on ritual<lb/> questions were found wise and have been universally accepted&#44; and that to<lb/> him also we are indebted for the composition of several<lb/> prayers.  But omitting any reference to all that&#44; in<lb/> order to be brief&#44; I will show nevertheless how one who<lb/> was firm and determined&#44; always preferring principles to expediency&#44;<lb/> still exemplified in his character the Rabbinical maxim that<lb/> humility becomes a mortal better than all other other noble<lb/> traits however noble.  When Abba saw from a distance people<lb/> who would rise before his presence&#44; he chose a byway turned round about<lb/> to avoid the meeting.  When about to in the act of entering the college&#44;<lb/> he noticed  the crowd ready to listen lend attention to his words&#44; he would say to<lb/> himself in the language of the Scriptures &#34;Though human<lb/> greatness reach up to heaven the sky&#44; it will suddenly vanish&#44;<lb/> and those who saw beheld it will cry &#39;Where is it&#39;&#34;&#63;  Persons<lb/> who studied for a mere literary curiosity&#44; he did not<lb/> chase away as unworthy of his consideration.  He encouraged them&#44; hoping that learn&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing would lead to practice.  It was the<lb/> misfortune of Rab to have been married to a wife<lb/> peevish and self&#45;willed.  He bore patiently with her&#44;<lb/> and tried to soften her temperament by anticipating<lb/> her wishes&#44; and buying objects that she might like.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>He was not successful.  One of his sons having grown up<lb/> and having discovered how contrary his mother was&#44; acted<lb/> with such a shrewdness&#44; &#91;&#63;&#93; which enabled him to please<lb/> his father unknowingly of to the woman who might<lb/> <sic>has</sic> stood in the his way.  But as soon as Rab detected<lb/> the artfulness to which his child resorted&#44; he forbid<lb/> it peremptorily.  Candor and truth he loved&#44; though he might suffer in the exercise thereof.  The death of one so mentally<lb/> exalted&#44; yet so meek&#44; so useful important in the community yet so unselfish&#44;<lb/> occasioned a universal mourning among his people.<lb/>  A famous Palestinian Sage on hearing the sad tidings&#44;<lb/> rent all his garments&#44; and exclaimed &#34;The man<lb/> of whose superiority I must have stood in awe&#44;<lb/> has gone.&#34;  We after fifteen sixteen centuries may still<lb/> exclaim &#34;The memory of the righteous is a blessing.&#34;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
