<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF12_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_1_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_1_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_1_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_1_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff12_1_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>13 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <p>For Sabbath Beshalach<lb/>
                including<lb/>
                some pertinent remarks on the<lb/>
                character of Ab Finzi<lb/>
                late Shamosh<lb/>
                of the Congregation<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#34;He called the name of the place Massah and<lb/> Memb&#224;h&#44; because of the <sic>quarelling</sic> of the children<lb/> of Israel&#44; and because they tempted the Lord&#44; saying&#58;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Is the Lord among us&#44; or not&#63;&#34;  Then<lb/> came Amalek&#44; and fought against Israel in Rephidim.&#34;<lb/>  These two sentences apparently disconnected&#44; gave the<lb/> imaginative minds of our ancient Teachers&#44; full<lb/> scope for adding another parable to the sl rich<lb/> store of the Talmudical allegories.  Hear it&#44; my brethren&#33;<lb/>  A man had a son&#44; whom&#44; from pure affection&#44; he bore covered in his<lb/> arm&#44; and conducted carefully every where.  If the<lb/> child&#44; expressed the desire to possess a certain object&#44;<lb/> the kindly father promptly procured it.  And that<lb/> he did not once&#44; but many times.  The son&#44; however&#44;<lb/> accustomed to being so pampered&#44; forgot even the<lb/> presence of him&#44; who afforded all the pleasures enjoyed.<lb/>  While immediately under paternal protection&#44; he inquired<lb/> of an acquaintance&#44; whither he knew where his father<lb/> could have gone.  He was looked upon as demented&#44;<lb/> for&#44; it was naturally inferred that only insanity<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>could have prompted &#91;inserted above&#58; inated suggested&#93; the question&#59; but the parent<lb/> provoked to anger&#44; loosened his hold.  The son<lb/> fell.  Left undefended&#44; he was bitten by a dog.<lb/>  That is the parable.  The following is the interpretation<lb/> thereof.  &#91;Inserted above&#58; You readily understand the<lb/> application.&#93;  The benevolent father represents Al&#45;<lb/>&#45;mighty God.  The ungrateful son typifies Israel.<lb/>  The slaves of Egypt had been set at large.  Their<lb/> Divine Liberator cast His powerful shield around<lb/> their existence.  The heavens were made to mi&#45;<lb/>&#45;nister to their comfort.  Benign clouds accom&#45;<lb/>&#45;panied the enfranchised bondmen in their journeys.<lb/>  They guided&#44; illumined&#44; and shaded the arid paths<lb/> they trod.  The sky daily rained down their<lb/> nutriment&#59; and winged &#91;&#63;&#93; swiftly descended<lb/> to offer the favored of the Lord a delicious repast.<lb/>  For&#44; as the archprophet sung when describing the<lb/> love of God for His redeemed people&#59; &#34;He encircled<lb/> him&#44; He watched him&#44; He guarded him as the<lb/> apple of His eye.&#34;  But after his necessities<lb/> had been so as amply provided for&#44; Israel grew<lb/> wanton.  He incredulously asked &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>  &#34;Is the Lord among us&#44; or not&#63;&#34;  The outraged<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Father&#44; removed then His protecting shield.  The<lb/> froward son was exposed to the onslaught of Amalek<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; that enemy&#44; who&#44; as his names denotes&#44; sought<lb/> to lick&#44; like a dog the blood of sinful Israel.<lb/>  Dear Brethren&#33;  You have clearly understood the lesson<lb/> purposed to be conveyed in the figurative language of<lb/> our Sages.  Punishment is at the heels of sin.  So<lb/> long as we lean upon the arm of God for support&#59;<lb/> and acknowledge His omnipresence&#44; we are safe.<lb/>  Our wants will be fulfilled&#44; and mishaps averted.  But<lb/> the instant we relinquish faith&#44; and throw doubts<lb/> on the existence of an ever watchful Providence&#44; then<lb/> we ourselves stir up the evil that will befall us&#59;<lb/> that Amalek&#44; who smites2 and attacks1 &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;all<lb/> the feeble&#34;&#44; those who are of little faith&#44; those who<lb/> waver about their religious convictions&#44; and skeptically<lb/> ask &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Is the Lord among us or not&#63;&#34;<lb/>  This truth which pervades the pages of Holy Writ&#44;<lb/> is illustrated&#44; according to the opinion of our Rabbins&#44; by<lb/> the proximity of the two sentences I have quoted from our Parasha.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>And as we read how Israel of yore became<lb/> guilty of incredulity nt notwithstanding the<lb/> constant miracles witnessed&#44; we will be apt to censure<lb/> their demeanour.  We will even venture to assert that<lb/> it would be impossible for us&#44; under similar cir&#45;<lb/>&#45;cumstances to commit a trespass of that character.<lb/>  Now&#44; I will not palliate the offence perpetrated<lb/> by our ancestors.  It was heinous&#59; and their inspired<lb/> leader deemed it so&#44; when he exclaimed &#34;Why chide ye<lb/> with me&#44; wherefore will ye tempt the Lord.&#34;&#63;  But<lb/> the occasion which prompted it was such that as apt to<lb/> tried men&#39;s souls.  Hunger and thirst are ill&#45;advisers.<lb/>  When keenly felt they will very nigh drive to madness.<lb/>  An entire people&#44; <sic>travelling</sic> through inhospitable<lb/> regions&#44; lacked water.  They ought&#44; you say&#44; to have<lb/> trusted in their celestial Liberator.  They ought to<lb/> have prayed&#44; instead of murmuring.  They ought to<lb/> have supplicated&#44; rather than imperiously demand.<lb/>  For&#44; whatever man enjoys here below is but a gift from<lb/> the Creator and Ruler of nature. It is even so.<lb/>  But after all what they asked for&#44; was indispensable<lb/> to sustain life.  I judge that their sin would have<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>been tenfold more grievous&#44; if they had complained for<lb/> want of luxuries.  If they had upbraided Moses&#44; and<lb/> tempted the Lord&#44; in order to obtain a spacious dwelling<lb/> in the wilderness&#44; chariots and horses and a train of<lb/> attendants.  Yet&#44; many of us&#44; will utter reproachful<lb/> words against the Almighty&#44; though possessed of an<lb/> overabundance of the goods of the world.  Let a<lb/> scheme from which we anticipated to realize much<lb/> prove abortive&#44; and we become perfectly oblivious of<lb/> all the divine gifts hitherto received.  We forget then<lb/> that if the sky does not pour down manna&#44; nor<lb/> does the word drive quails to our direction&#44; that we may<lb/> gather then with ease&#44; a rich table is spread out<lb/> for us every morning.  We forget that whereas our<lb/> ancestors fed mainly upon one substance&#44; we can<lb/> lay our head on a variety of provisions.  That whereas<lb/> our forefathers pitched rude tents in a howling desert&#44; and<lb/> were surrounded by inimical tribes&#44; we dwell in<lb/> commodious&#44; and oftentimes gorgeous habitations&#44; and<lb/> stand not in dread of a lurking foe.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>The priceless blessings we enjoy&#44; but to which<lb/> they were strangers&#44; are lost sight of&#59; and incited<lb/> by ignoble feelings&#44; we despondingly ask &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Is the Lord among us or not&#63;&#34;  Why have other men&#39;s<lb/> efforts been crowned with success&#44; and ours have<lb/> earned for us only disappointments&#63;&#34;  Brethren&#33;<lb/>  Has not the bulwark of your faith been occasionally<lb/> set upon by disbelief&#63;  Have you not&#44; when failed<lb/> in some of your designs thus tempted the Lord&#63;<lb/>  Would I could think that at no period of your exis&#45;<lb/>&#45;tence the shadows of skepticism darkened the regions<lb/> of your intellect&#33;  That you have always felt the<lb/> arm of the Lord environ your existence&#44; and<lb/> you have cleaved thereto despite deluded hopes&#33;<lb/>  But I should add falsehood to flattery&#44; if I described you<lb/> so righteous.  For&#44; I know that some of you amid the fraction<lb/> of numberless blessings&#44; murmur and bewail their fate.<lb/>  They would&#59; be the first to stigmatize our predecessors as<lb/> unbelievers.  To declare that the assault of Amalek&#44; was a<lb/> requital well meted out.  But they do not reflect upon their<lb/> own wavering.  They do not reflect upon the unjust claims<lb/> they lay for to a double portion of celestial boons.  They<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>heed not&#45;&#45;because it applies to themselves the<lb/> lesson&#44; which teaches that&#44; punishment is at the heels<lb/> of sin&#44; and none is so severe as that caused by ingratitude.<lb/>  To use a phrase&#44; which thick books revered by the<lb/> gentiles have borrowed from the Talmud &#34;they behold<lb/> the mote in their brother&#39;s eye&#44; but consider perceive not<lb/> the beam in their own eyes.&#34;  Yes&#44; Dear hearers&#33;<lb/>  Ere we cast obloquy on our neighbor&#39;s conduct&#44;<lb/> let us consult our feelings and tendencies&#44; examine<lb/> how we would have acted if placed under circumstances<lb/> precisely alike.  Then we will learn to be more<lb/> charitable in our judgment towards our fellow&#45;mor&#45;<lb/>&#45;tals&#44; more contented with our lots&#44; more grateful<lb/> to Providence.  Never will we&#44; because our plans<lb/> were frustrated&#44; skeptically cry &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Is the Lord among us or not&#63;&#34;.<lb/>
                But though comparatively few are they who<lb/> so govern their conduct&#44; still the human family<lb/> maintains its dignity through its righteous<lb/> members.  We all have met with such in our<lb/> walks of life.  To them would I direct your attention.<lb/>  They are the beacon&#44; on which I would fain you look&#44; when<lb/> tossed upon a sea of misgivings and misapprehensions.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>God who employes humble means to accomplish<lb/> noble ends&#44; placed one of those shining lights<lb/> before your vision&#44; in the character of your late<lb/> faithful servant.  While yet clothed in<lb/> flesh&#44; I contemplated him in silent admiration.<lb/>  While that which was mortal&#44; laid before us&#44;<lb/> I respected his injunction&#44; and forbore to rehearsed not his praise.<lb/>  But now that he has exchanged the material for<lb/> the spiritual&#44; I may exhibit his demeanour as<lb/> a model&#44; which you should copy.  Forgive&#44;<lb/> O sainted being&#44; thy minister and friend&#44; if he<lb/> trespasses against thy modesty&#44; by showing this<lb/> people thou hast loved&#44; how they should live and die.<lb/>  For&#44; rare is the example thou set forth.  Its presen&#45;<lb/>&#45;tation may be fruitful of good results.<lb/>  Abraham Finzi was a bright illustration of the<lb/> Rabbinical maxim that &#34;man&#39;s character elevates<lb/> his position.&#34;  In his youthful year&#44; he had acquired<lb/> a high reputation and a competence.  When he<lb/> chose America for his abode&#44; he did not imagine<lb/> that to act as sexton of the congregation Mikve<lb/> Israel&#59; would be for him an acceptable occupation.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>But fortune refused to smile on his commercial<lb/> enterprises.  His industry and unsurpassing probity<lb/> did not save his substance.  Reverses swept it<lb/> away.  Bowing to the will of the Disposer of all<lb/> wants&#44; he then exclaimed&#44; &#34;the Lord gave&#44; and the Lord<lb/> hath taken away&#44; may the name of the Lord be<lb/> blessed.&#34;  Everything was not lost.  His intellect<lb/> had been cultivated.  His manners were polished.<lb/>  Surely&#44; the elegance of his penmanship&#44; and his ability<lb/> as a computist&#44; must needs command a lucrative<lb/> situation.  But an infirmity early contracted&#44; grew<lb/> worse with advancing age.  A difficulty in hearing<lb/> precluded the possibility of his earning a liberal<lb/> subsistence by his knowledge.  Our lofty&#45;minded<lb/> coreligionist did not therefore sink into despair.  Trusting<lb/> in that God&#44; on whose arm the whole creation hangs<lb/> for support&#44; he bore residudl resignedly many<lb/> privations&#44; until it was your good fortune&#44; O my<lb/> congregation&#44; to secure the services of one so faithful&#44;<lb/> so courteous&#44; so estimable&#44; so purely religious.<lb/>  With what ease he moved about&#33;  With what precision<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>he discharged his multifarious duties&#33;  How even<lb/> his temper in any emergency&#33;  How bland his<lb/> language with all&#33;  But the virtue of<lb/> <sic>of</sic> my deceased friend&#44; was not fully <sic>developped</sic>&#44;<lb/> until the inscrutable decree of the Omnipotent sentenced<lb/> him to lie upon the couch of sickness for three<lb/> long years.  I have advisedly said &#34;the virtue&#44;&#34;<lb/> for that word implies strength.  Not htat of the body&#44; in<lb/> which the irrational creatures far exceed the rational&#59;<lb/> but that of the soul.  That strength which enables<lb/> man to endure tortures without a murmur.  That<lb/> strength which enables man to bear with an<lb/> unruffled spirit&#44; a sore disease to which he knows<lb/> there is no cure.  That strength&#44; which familiarizes<lb/> man with death.  Such strength Abraham<lb/> Finzi fully possessed.  In the paroxysms of<lb/> his dispen distemper&#44; hed he did not once turn<lb/> to his ministering angel&#45;&#45;the devoted wife&#45;&#45;<lb/> and despondingly ask &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Is the<lb/> Lord among us or not&#63;&#34;  Never&#58; he called<lb/> of a God who afflicts&#44; but comforts&#44; to be at<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>his right hand&#44; that his faith might be sustained.<lb/>  Thou has gone to thy eternal home&#44; O patrons of<lb/> virtue&#33; but the sufferings thou borest on earth<lb/> will yield blessings&#44; if we thy survivors&#44; well<lb/> learn therefrom to practice righteousness.  Aye&#44; my<lb/>dear hearers&#33; let us study that character&#44; for&#44; it<lb/> contains a treasure of useful knowledge.  Let us<lb/> reflect therein&#44; though we did not meet it in<lb/> the highest walks of life&#44; for&#44; it is nevertheless<lb/> exceedingly noble.<lb/>
                And you&#44; my dear Bar Mitzvah&#44; ponder on the<lb/> life I have faintly delineated.  You may derive<lb/> healthful instruction.  Imprint this truth on<lb/> your mind&#44; my beloved young friend.  To be happy&#44; is<lb/> to be good.  Riches and the applause of the<lb/> world are things to be desired&#44; but in the hour<lb/> of trials they will be powerless.  Religious principles<lb/> alone will then assuage our sorrows&#44; infuse within<lb/> us a calm&#44; a celestial serenity.  With the deepest<lb/> sincerity I wish you an existence free from all<lb/> ailments&#44; a prosperous career&#44; the exaltation of<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p>your standing&#44; and the perpetration of your<lb/> name.  But if it be the will of your Father<lb/> in heaven to try your faith&#44; remember the lesson<lb/> I have placed this day before your vision.<lb/>  I have an almost sure guarantee that you will<lb/> cling to religious principles&#59; for&#44; parental precept<lb/> inculcates them&#59; parental example will give them<lb/> stability.  Waver not.  Be aware of those who are<lb/> wise above the law.  Keep within its holy bounds.<lb/>  You will never then incredulously ask &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Is the Lord among us or not&#63;&#34;  You will see your<lb/> God every where.  You will see Him above and below.<lb/>  You will see Him in every step in advance you<lb/> will take towards the improvement of yourself and<lb/> your fellow&#45;mortals.  You will see feel Him in<lb/> your guileless heart&#59; you will have Him ever present<lb/> before your pure soul.  And prompted by gratitude<lb/> for the beneficent God&#44; who made you live to see<lb/> enjoy this gladsome day&#44; your lips will spontaneously<lb/> sing the praises of Him&#44; who is the source of<lb/> happiness&#44; the Lord of the living and of the<lb/> dead&#44; the hope&#44; and Saviour of his people Israel.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
