<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF3_7</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1895" source="" attested="yes">1895</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_7_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_7_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_7_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_7_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_7_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_7_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_7_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_7_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_7_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_7_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_7_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_7_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>On the 44th anniversary<lb/>
                of my ministry<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>A long time has rolled away since what I am<lb/> about to tell happened.  The Jewess upon whom<lb/> I called was pious. and She certainly was the child of had been reared by devout parents.  Following their footsteps she honestly believed that<lb/> her conduct had always been measured by the square<lb/> and compass of religion and probity.  She said to me in the<lb/> course of conversation&#58; &#34;I do not think that if I were<lb/> to begin life over again&#44; I would act differently from<lb/> what I have acted in the past.&#34;  To express doubts on her<lb/> convictions&#44; might have been rude&#44; still I ventured<lb/> to refer to a Rabbinical sentence&#44; while disclaiming<lb/> any intention to apply it in that to her particular instance ease.<lb/>  In my mind&#44; however&#44; the maxim of Hillel is fraught<lb/> with wisdom and I quoted it &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Do not trust thyself till the day of thy death.&#34;<lb/>  Later Talmudical Sages cite illustrations&#44; confirmatory of the sound&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness of that aphorism&#44; notably the history of John<lb/> Hyrcanus&#44; the Asmonean&#44; who after eighty years of<lb/> staunch adherence to the written and oral Law&#44; be&#45;<lb/>came a Saducee&#44; or a member of a Jewish sect&#44;<lb/> &#45;&#45;during our second commonwealth&#45;&#45;that denied the traditions and a hereafter.  My<lb/> good sister in faith&#44; had occasion to realize before<lb/> passing away from earth&#44; that she had been hasty<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>in supposing herself above human shortcomings.<lb/>  For&#44; no unlike Eli of old&#44; she leniently overlooked her child&#45;<lb/>&#45;ren&#39;s growing defects to a degree that they all&#44; disre&#45;<lb/>&#45;garding her personal example&#44; became morally dead<lb/> to the religion that she loved.  As to my own self<lb/> I hold so fast on the maxim of Hillel.  Having grown old&#44; I take cast a glance of on the past&#44; and firmly believe that much of what I said<lb/> and did&#44; ought to be recalled&#44; if it were possible&#44; and<lb/> I even stand in dread of dying with the loss of that<lb/> which I imagine to have largely measurably gained.  It is not<lb/> of course&#44; wealth that I so fear to be gradually deprived of&#44; because that<lb/> I never craved for&#59; nor can I at my age and in my<lb/> avocation hope to <sic>ammass</sic> it.  In fact&#44; it were<lb/> sheer folly on my part to seek it&#44; noticing how<lb/> too often riches left behind are the main origin of a<lb/> sundering apart of the holiest family ties&#59; how by<lb/> reason of riches left behind&#44; the fatal state pictured<lb/> by Micha is brought about &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.....&#34;a son reviling his father&#44; a daughter<lb/> her mother&#44; how a man&#39;s enemies are those reared<lb/> in his own house.&#34;  And who wiser than Koheleth<lb/> who in his peculiar philosophy assures us<lb/> that no pleasure is secured by the owner of abund&#45;<lb/>ant riches&#44; beyond that of looking at them &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; I have never collected the possession of<lb/></p> 
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p><sic>of</sic> vast means.<lb/></p>
            <p>It is an open secret&#44; and I dare allude to it<lb/> now that I have just entered the forty fifth year<lb/> of my service in the Mickv&#232; Israel Congregation&#44;<lb/> it is an open secret that if I had loved gold more and my work in<lb/> Philadelphia less&#44; I might&#44; in a measure to a certain degree at least&#44;<lb/> have gratified my ambition.  To some perhaps<lb/> it is not unknown that when circumstances<lb/> affected my congregation injuriously from a financial<lb/> stand point&#44; I acted inconsiderately.  What I fear<lb/> then is not my inability to bequeath that which my<lb/> offspring may enjoy with much ease and comfort.<lb/>  I rather apprehend forfeiting public respect for a consistent which I fancy to have won by<lb/> a demeanour consistent with my ministerial pledge.  To stand the pressure which every<lb/> day urges one on to deviate form an even course&#44; is<lb/> an effort almost superhuman.  We have witnessed<lb/> of late changes in people&#39;s minds which I would<lb/> have deemed impossible.  To contemplate them<lb/> is the lashing of my very soul.  Am I not unjustly<lb/> apprehensive&#63;  for Mark well&#44; my brethren&#58; what I deprecate some of you may have<lb/> read last month in the report of a case of a Christian<lb/> clergyman in our city.  Having presented his resignation<lb/> as for being charged with the cause of a too slender an attendance at the worship&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>a prominent member of the Church arose and said&#58;<lb/> &#34;I intend voting for the acceptance of that resignation.....<lb/> A new pastor will be an attraction.&#34;  There is no<lb/> denying that the presbyterian was unconsciously<lb/> the mouth piece of my own people.  Whence shall<lb/> I derive the moral strength resisting the prurient imperious<lb/> wish for ever new attractions in the Synagogue&#63;  I ask it<lb/> of those who remember a past&#44; forty four years long.<lb/>  I ask it&#44; not out of to elicit any feelings akin to pity&#44;<lb/> for&#44; attached as I really am to Philadelphia and<lb/> the Mickv&#233; Israel Congregation&#44; I still recoil<lb/> at the idea of being held at sufferance.  I ask<lb/> it for the sake of the cause which needs firm&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness in those sworn to uphold it&#44; so as to prevent<lb/> its drifting away into nihilism&#44; such as stares us now<lb/> in the face.  With the moral help of such coreli&#45;<lb/>&#45;gionists of mine&#44; I may hope to pass away un&#45;<lb/>&#45;accompanied by the charge of defection and pusillani&#45;<lb/>&#45;mity.  But my brothers and sisters in faith<lb/> who still cherish for me kindly thoughts can evince<lb/> it besides in a manner most acceptable to my<lb/> heart.  I do not remember that during my unusually<lb/> long protracted incumbency&#44; I have petitioned for a personal<lb/> favor&#44; but now that I cannot naturally respect<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>a much longer continuance in the midst of<lb/> those whom I have tried to serve the best I could&#44;<lb/> I do <sic>intreat</sic> them for a token of regard.  It is full nine<lb/> years since I conceived the necessity of upbuilding<lb/> in America a Judaism&#44; that might prove a<lb/> bulwark against the attacks of external and in&#45;<lb/>&#45;ternal enemies.  An theological institution should use in New<lb/> York&#45;&#45;a city preeminent in number and opulence<lb/> among our brethren&#45;&#45;.  The teaching imparted communicated should<lb/> not be <sic>onesided</sic>&#44; but broad&#44; still recognizing the fide&#45;<lb/>&#45;lity due to Mosaism and Rabbinism&#44; a teaching con&#45;<lb/>&#45;scientious but not servile to any school&#44; however<lb/> venerable for its age.  A teaching&#44; as stated in my preamble to the Constitution&#44; by which the Bible is impartially imparted and Rabbinical literature faithfully expounded.  My planting has not been un&#45;<lb/>productive&#44; notwithstanding that the time devoted to its<lb/> cultivation was comparatively short and the means at the<lb/> command of my coagents are inadequate.  A youth who<lb/> entered the chambers of learning&#44; in &#34;the Jewish Theological<lb/> Seminary&#34; as soon they were opened&#44; stood last summer a search&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing examination in many branches of Biblical and<lb/> Rabbinical knowledge&#44; and was declared competent<lb/> to preach understandingly the religion of Sinai and<lb/> to guide a school in Syracuse where boys and girls of<lb/> our faith are taught the language and history of<lb/> Holy Writ.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Even before Joseph Herman Hertz graduated with honors in his<lb/> Alma Mater and in the Columbia college&#44; with<lb/> honors the Mickv&#233; Israel Congregation was given a test<lb/> of his mental capacities and pleasing delivery.  It is<lb/> not impossible that shortly another of his fellow students<lb/> may occupy the pulpit in a synagogue at Buffalo&#44; and<lb/> loth as I am to extol the work of my hands&#44; I may<lb/> venture to predict that several whom I admitted in the<lb/> institution in later years&#44; will not disappoint my<lb/> eager expectations and grieve my heart.  But the twenty six matriculated<lb/> attendants&#44; a number of whom have a home in the insti&#45;<lb/>&#45;tution proper&#44; while a n umber thereof receive a sti&#45;<lb/>&#45;pend&#44; because of their lowly condition in life&#44; call for<lb/> a more generous recognition of my undertaking.<lb/>  Philadelphia responded at the very outset to my appeal.<lb/>  Mrs Catharine Kaas gave the first impulse which the<lb/> noble hearted Miss Ellen Phillips seconded with a numi&#45;<lb/>&#45;ficent sum.  I shall not deny that New<lb/> York with her Pizas&#44; her Jacob H. Shiff &#38; her Ferdinand Sulzberger&#44; Baltimore<lb/> with her Jonas Friedenwald&#44; Pittsburg with her J. D.<lb/> Bernd&#44; have also given aid and countenance so indispen&#45;<lb/>&#45;sable to an undertaking as important as that which I conceived in the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>nature of a safeguard against most destructive ten&#45;<lb/>&#45;dencies&#44; an undertaking demanding constant watchfulness and exceed&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing generosity.  I have recently been met with the pain&#45;<lb/>&#45;ful reflections.  It is said by not a few that the wheel of commerce<lb/> is clogged&#44; and that by reason of it patrons feel constrain&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed to become subscribers&#44; thus reducing to one half their<lb/> former contributions&#44; while some of the latter are obli&#45;<lb/>&#45;ged to withdraw their assistance altogether.  I will<lb/> not act in a manner&#44; which my brethren may<lb/> interpret as a price of proud arrogance.  I will not tell<lb/> my Philadelphia coreligionists.  Do&#44; dear Fellow believers&#44;<lb/> you must make a small sacrifice and lay it on the altar&#44; which<lb/> I have erected for the <sic>sactification</sic> of our ancestral<lb/> faith&#44;k but without presuming to demand&#44; I may<lb/> petition for the permanence of the Jewish Theologic&#45;<lb/>&#45;al Seminary.  The Talmudists&#44; in one of their parables<lb/> tell us that the lips&#44; whence the Torah was wont to<lb/> issued forth when alive moving in life&#44; will reecho forth forth the tuition and joyfully smile in the grave&#44;<lb/> when others equally sincere imparting it upon earth.  Who<lb/> knows but that when I shall moulder in the grave<lb/> dust&#44; some whom I have taught will take up<lb/> my incipient work and with more learning&#44; unaba&#45;<lb/>&#45;ted zeal and steadfast determination will give Israel in Ame&#45;<lb/>&#45;rica a Samuel&#44; an Elijah&#44; the saviours of <sic>imperilled</sic> Israel Judaism.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>That is my supplication to god and my entreaty to<lb/> you&#44; dear brethren after having stood at the &#91;&#63;&#93;<lb/> without flinching and flagging four and forty four long<lb/> years.  To you my young brother Bar Mitzvah &#38;c<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
