<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF12</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff12_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff12_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff12_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff12_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff12_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff12_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff12_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff12_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff12_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff12_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff12_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff12_1_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff12_1_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff12_1_7v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>A discourse on the mission of<lb/>
                The Messiah<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  The wish I expressed not long since at<lb/> the conclusion of one of my discourses&#44; has prompted<lb/> several of my hearers to submit to my judgment<lb/> questions of grave importance.  Each of them has<lb/> an equal claim on my serious meditation&#44; but motives<lb/> that need not be explained&#44; impel me to give pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;cedence to one latterly offered.  You may perhaps<lb/> be startled at hearing that a member of the Jewish<lb/> household&#44; should have asked &#34;whether we believe in<lb/> a personal redeemer&#44;&#34; since we continually pray for<lb/> his advent&#44; but if you will bear in mind in relation<lb/> with the subject&#44; the dogma of a redemption from<lb/> eternal perdition&#44; through the agency of a man&#45;god&#44;<lb/> preached by the apostles of another creed&#59; you will<lb/> agree with me that the query apparently para&#45;<lb/>&#45;doxical when emanating from a child of our faith&#44;<lb/> is nevertheless pertinent&#44; and well deserving of our<lb/> consideration.  It does not imply&#44; if I argue<lb/> correctly&#44; a doubt as to the <sic>fulfilment</sic> of the glorious<lb/> predictions concerning Israel&#44; but a desire to learn whe&#45;<lb/>&#45;ther the messenger of happy tidings to the outcasts of<lb/> Judea will be&#44; by reason of the appellation it bears&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>identical in anywise with him whom the opponents of<lb/> Judaism style their redeemer.  Let me then&#44; my friends<lb/> in order to dispel any error which may have been con&#45;<lb/>&#45;ceived on this score&#44; emphatically assert that both<lb/> in temporal as in spiritual concerns&#44; Israel recognizes one<lb/> sole Redeemer&#44; the Most High God Creator of the hea&#45;<lb/>&#45;ven and the earth.  To cite authorities in corroboration<lb/> of this truth would be supererogatory&#44; for it stands proved<lb/> beyond refutation&#44; by the words of every prophet who<lb/> wrote for our instruction &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Thou O Lord art our Father&#44; Thy name is Our Redeemer<lb/> from everlasting&#44;&#34; exclaims Isaiah&#44; when petitioning<lb/> for the restoration of our nationality&#59; and by the<lb/> mouth of the inspired Hoshea&#44; the Eternal said &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;I will deliver them form the power<lb/> of destruction&#44; I will redeem them from death.&#34;  Let<lb/> therefore no shadow of doubt ever be harbored in a<lb/> Jewish mind&#44; as to the true author of human salva&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion.  Let the oft repeated lesson of our seers be ever remem&#45;<lb/>&#45;bered &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;There is no Saviour but me.&#34;<lb/></p>  
            <p>Yet&#44; to renounce the expectation of a Messiah&#44; because<lb/> we are taught to rely solely upon God for our redemp&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion&#44; would be a denial of what we consider a<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Divine declaration.  Yes&#44; we must believe that as<lb/> Providence raised a Moses to lead us forth to freedom<lb/> and that as He infused into Zerubabel and his right&#45;<lb/>&#45;eous colleagues devotion for the cause of their brethren&#44;<lb/> enthralled in the land of the stranger&#44; so will He&#44; when<lb/> our mission is fulfilled by our dispersion endow a mortal with the<lb/> mental&#44; moral and spiritual qualifications&#44; whereby<lb/> he will be enabled to unfurl the banner&#44; around<lb/> which will rally all the outcasts of Israel from<lb/> the four corners of the earth.  Him did the son<lb/> of Amoz foresee&#44; and call &#34;a a redeemer that shall<lb/> come to Zion&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;and to those who turn<lb/> from their transgression in Jacob.&#34;  Him did Ezekiel<lb/> behold with a celestial eye&#44; when he predicted the<lb/> acumen of the house of Joseph with that of Judah&#44;<lb/> under one shepherd and one shepherd and one king.<lb/>  &#34;&#91;Hebrew&#93;&#34;  But neither the<lb/> former nor the latter prophets ascribed to the foreshadowed<lb/> personage the attributes which have been assigned<lb/> by his followers to the character of the man of<lb/> Nazareth.  To construe the term &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Redeemer&#34; into that signification&#44; would betray<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>a total ignorance of the sacred language&#44; for&#44; who<lb/> does not know that although when applied to God&#44;<lb/> it frequently means&#44; the Deliverer of our souls&#44; as &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;He redeemeth thy life form destruction&#44;&#34; never&#45;<lb/>theless it has been variously employed in Holy Writ&#44; so<lb/> that under its title sometimes is he represented&#44; on<lb/> whom devolved the duty of rescuing his relative from<lb/> penury distress&#44; for instance &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;And his redeemer nigh unto him&#44; shall come&#44; and redeem<lb/> what &#91;&#63;&#93; his brother hath sold&#34;; at others he that in<lb/> the days of yore deemed it a point of honour to avenge<lb/> the death of a <sic>kinssman</sic>&#44; as &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;And the assembly shall judge between the slayer&#44;<lb/> and between the <sic>revenger</sic> &#40;properly the redeemer&#41; of blood&#44;<lb/> but who&#44; I say&#44; that is at all conversant with the Hebrew&#44;<lb/> has not learnt that the sense which that word mostly<lb/> conveys&#44; is a&#44; liberator from oppression&#44; so that of<lb/> Solomon it is written&#44; &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;He will<lb/> deliver their life from vexation and violence&#44; and their<lb/> blood will be precious in his eyes&#34;&#44; and of the Almighty<lb/> Protector of Israel&#44; we read &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;He<lb/> redeemeth him form the hand of him one that is stronger<lb/> than he&#63;  Besides&#44; in the chapter&#44; where<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>the sentence I have quoted occurs&#44; the inspired man<lb/> depicts the effect of sin&#44; only with respect to our resto&#45;<lb/>&#45;ration.  He points out the causes of its delay&#44; acknow&#45;<lb/>&#45;ledges the justice of the punishment&#44; and concludes with<lb/> the consolatory promise of our final return to the<lb/> pristine glory&#44; not through our inherent merits&#44; but<lb/> by the mercy of God&#44; who will &#34;put on charity as<lb/> a breastplate&#44; and as a helmet of salvation upon his<lb/> head&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  It is therefore&#44;<lb/> my dear Brethren&#33; palpably demonstrated&#44; that the<lb/> predicted redeemer&#44; will not supersede&#44; so to speak&#44; the<lb/> Omnipotent Creator&#44; by assuming His Divine attributes<lb/> in blotting out human trespasses&#44; but will be only<lb/> invested with the power of consolidating the disjoint<lb/> members of Israel into one compact body.  This idea<lb/> theologically correct&#44; is further <sic>developped</sic> by the<lb/> writings of Ezekiel&#44; for&#44; he says &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;And David my servant shall be a prince over them for<lb/> ever&#34; purposing to signify&#44; not that the monarch long<lb/> deceased will rise form his grave&#44; to <sic>weild</sic> the scepter anew<lb/> but that what his genius and religious zeal achieved&#44; will<lb/> be likewise accomplished by one of his own lineage&#44; for&#44;<lb/> tradition asserts that the Messiah will infallibly prove his descent<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>from the progeny of Jesse.  This assertion&#44; will in our<lb/> present condition&#44; seem untenable&#44; but when we<lb/> reflect that not only sundry of our ancient Sages&#44;<lb/> but even an author of celebrity who lived later than five<lb/> centuries ago&#44; could exhibit his pedigree&#44; as a branch<lb/> of the Davidian stock&#44; we will accept with favour<lb/> what our Teachers have handed down to us upon<lb/> this subject.  Now&#44; the facts hitherto ad&#45;<lb/>&#45;vanced&#44; ought to convince all my hearers that<lb/> to ascribe to the man whom God will appoint as the<lb/> future leader of his people a supernatural mission&#44; is<lb/> unwarrantable and contradictory of the holy scriptures.<lb/>  But in order to substantiate my statement also by<lb/> Rabbinical authority&#44; I will transcribe what Maimo&#45;<lb/>&#45;nides wrote towards the end of his treatise on Kings.<lb/>  &#34;Imagine not&#45;&#45;says the justly renowned philosopher&#45;&#45;that the King Messiah will be de&#45;<lb/>&#45;manded to perform extraordinary deeds &#38; wonders&#44;<lb/> or change the aspect of the world by calling the<lb/> dead to life&#44; or by similar prodigies&#44; for&#44; it is<lb/> not so&#58; witness it the conduct of Rabbi Akibah<lb/> who was a very eminent Sage of the Mishnah&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>and yet he became a staunch adherent of Bar Cochab&#224;&#44;<lb/> because he regarded him as the true Messiah&#44; though<lb/> the Rabbis required of him neither a sign nor a mi&#45;<lb/>&#45;racle.  But the whole truth is the following&#59; that<lb/> our law is unalterable in all its parts&#44; nothing must<lb/> be added to nor taken away from it&#59; so that if a<lb/> descendant of David&#44; thoroughly versed therein and of pious<lb/> habits&#44; respecting both the written precepts and their<lb/> oral exposition&#44; were successful in enforcing the execution<lb/> of the same upon Israel&#44; and in securing their national<lb/> <sic>tranquillity</sic> by his victories&#44; we n be may would be justified<lb/> in supposing him to be the Messiah.  However&#44; what<lb/> will unquestionably proved him so it&#44; is his ability to<lb/> reconstruct the Temple&#44; to restore Israel into their land&#44;<lb/> and bring thereby the world at large to the knowledge<lb/> of the Unity of God&#44; as it is predicted &#34;For then<lb/> will I turn to the peoples a pure language&#44; that they<lb/> may all call upon the name of the Lord&#44; to serve Him<lb/> with one consent &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Such will&#44; my dear Brethren&#44; be the commission en&#45;<lb/>trusted to the redeemer that is to come to Zion.<lb/>  His nature will not partake of the divine&#44; more<lb/> than that which is intellectually vouchsafed to mortals<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>by the only source of wisdom&#59; his rule will be<lb/> temporal&#44; his dominion in the country of his forefathers.<lb/>  He will be what his name precisely denotes &#91;Hebrew&#93; Messiah&#44;<lb/> that is&#44; the one&#44; <sic>annointed</sic> with the oil&#44; which erst consecrated<lb/> alike the regal as the sacerdotal office.  By<lb/> that epithet were recognized all the Hebrew monarchs&#44;<lb/> in it gloried the royal shepherd&#44; and by special<lb/> grace it likewise adorned the name of that mighty<lb/> Ruler of Persia&#44; who arose a benefactor and liberator<lb/> of the Babylonian exiles &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Thus sayeth<lb/> the Lord to his Messiah Cyrus&#34; intimating by it<lb/> that the earthly grandeur he was to attain&#44; would<lb/> be the reward due to his magnanimous demeanour<lb/> towards the residue of Judah.  But not once&#44;&#45;&#45;even<lb/> by the confession of gentile scholars&#44;&#45;&#45;has that term been<lb/> employed in Holy Writ to testify an ethereal and<lb/> yet terrestrial being&#44; sent or spontaneously come to offer himself a vicarious sacrifice.<lb/>  Therefore it came to pass m b that the rack and the stake&#44;<lb/> the caldron of the inquisition and the auto da f&#233;s could<lb/> never force out of the lips of the Jewish outcast an avowal&#44;<lb/> which would have changed his life of unheard of suffering<lb/> into an honored existence.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>The volumes unfolded before his eyes taught him that<lb/> &#34;to the Lord our God belong mercy and forgiveness&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  From the redeemer whose advent he<lb/> prayed for&#44; he did not expect the remission of his ini&#45;<lb/>&#45;quities&#45;&#45;which heartfelt repentance alone can expiate&#45;&#45;&#44;<lb/> but freedom from oppression&#44; and a high position among<lb/> the family of nations&#44; as when Judah and Israel dwelt<lb/> peacefully together in the land of the patriarchs.  The<lb/> world mistook that unwavering firmness for in&#45;<lb/>&#45;flexible obstinacy&#44; and poured on its possessor the<lb/> vial of contempt&#44; but he bore it&#45;&#45;and what has he<lb/> not borne&#33;&#33;&#45;&#45;as a heavenly dispensation&#44; still looking<lb/> intently forward to the time when &#34;the redeemed of the<lb/> Lord shall return&#44; and come with singing unto Zion&#44;<lb/> while everlasting joy shall crown their heads&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  My beloved Brethren&#33;<lb/>  For the consummation of that happy event we also<lb/> daily pour forth our supplications.  We have not&#44;<lb/> thank God&#44; joined the new Hebrew band&#44; who laugh<lb/> to scorn the idea of cherishing a hope so long deferred.<lb/>  We believe that even if it tarries in its <sic>fulfilment</sic>&#44; we must <lb/>await for him it &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; because the mouth of<lb/> the Lord hath spoken.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#45;&#45;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>But while holding fast on the divine declaration&#44; it<lb/> would be a fruitless and unreasonable end endeavour<lb/> to speculate about the means by which Providence<lb/> will work out his design.  It may be by the light<lb/> He will cast shed upon the gentiles.  It may be by<lb/> the arts of peace and human conditions&#44; it may perad&#45;<lb/>&#45;venture be by wars and fierce struggles&#44; but that<lb/> should not engross our thoughts.  Let our mind be<lb/> rather occupied in improving ourselves and the intelligent<lb/> creatures among whom our lot has been cast.  Surely&#44;<lb/> my friends&#33; what was to Daniel closed up and sealed<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; can never be revealed to us.  The<lb/> Rabbins themselves greatly deprecated the attempt&#44; l<lb/> when they said by remarking that &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;The mind of those what<lb/> determine when the captivity is to end&#44; will be <sic>harrassed</sic>.&#34;<lb/>  Let us then trust with child&#45;like faith to the Director<lb/> of sublunary occurrences&#59; and when disdainfully regarded<lb/> by fallible men&#44; comfort ourselves with the words which<lb/> the unerring God inspired his chosen servant to<lb/> utter in his name &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>&#45;&#45;&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;As the rain cometh down&#44; and the snow from heaven&#44; and<lb/> returneth not thither&#44; but watereth the earth&#44; and<lb/> maketh it f bring forth and bud&#44; that it may give<lb/> seed to the sower&#44; and bread to the eater&#59; so shall be my<lb/> word that goeth forth out of my mouth&#58; it shall<lb/> not return unto me void&#44; but it shall accomplish<lb/> that which I please&#44; and it shall prosper him for<lb/> whom I have sent it&#34;.  So may it be&#44; Amen<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
