<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF6</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1890-05" source="" attested="yes">May 1890</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff6_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff6_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff6_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff6_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff6_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff6_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff6_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff6_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff6_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff6_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff6_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff6_1_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff6_1_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff6_1_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff6_1_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff6_1_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>13 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. Fifth St.<lb/>
                Philadelphia&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>86</p>
            
            <p>On the sect of Bene Israel in India<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>May&#47;90<lb/></p>
            <p>My address to day will simply be a piece of historical in&#45;<lb/>&#45;formation&#44; which I presume is new to most of my hearers.<lb/>  But before beginning with it&#44; I think it necessary to say<lb/> that I have been officially urged by an officially letter during this week&#44; to make<lb/> complaints of the conduct of some who attend worship in<lb/> our Synagogue.  I am assured by the writer that their practice to come<lb/> and go at pleasure&#44; to speak talk audibly loud to sing out of time &#38; out of tune&#44; but specially<lb/> the habit of a number of children to move restlessly and<lb/> noisily while the religious exercises are being performed&#44;<lb/> cause annoyance to those who wish to join quietly in the prayers and<lb/> listen to the discourse.  To The congregation know that to find fault is as distasteful<lb/> to me as it must be to the persons who have occasioned<lb/> the reproof&#44; therefore I shall will not dwell upon it.  Hoping<lb/> that my few well meant words will effect a needful<lb/> correction&#59; begging all to assist me in imparting dignity to the Divine services&#44; I shall proceed to speak on a subject that<lb/> may prove of some interest.<lb/></p>
            <p>In the East Indies&#45;&#45;now under the sole dominion of Great<lb/> Britain&#44; a religious sect has existed for dating many centuries<lb/> back.  The name which it bears&#44; and the practices<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>to which that its members adhere to are strong evidences of its de&#45;<lb/>&#45;scent.  It is closely Jewish&#59; not by adoption like the Falashas<lb/> of Abyssinia&#44; whose features show an foreign traces of an origin foreign to our race&#44; but<lb/> by direct lineage extraction descent&#59; for I learn that ages and the adoption acceptance<lb/> of foreign the manners and customs prevalent among the aborigines&#44; have not essentially al&#45;<lb/>&#45;tered the Jewish looks of those distant brethren of ours.<lb/>  But how did it happen that in old times&#44; the remote days of antiquity&#44; a colony of<lb/> our people settled in so far off a Asiatic country&#63;  This question<lb/> has been answered in various ways&#44; but just as<lb/> unsatisfactorily as that which regards the Jews who an&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciently took up their homes in China.  The &#34;Bene<lb/> Israel&#44;&#34; or children of Israel&#44; as the original oldest Hebrews<lb/> in India like prefer to call themselves&#44; have their own story to<lb/> tell.  We will hear it.  They say&#58; &#34;Our ancestors came<lb/> here about eighteen hundred years ago to avoid per&#45;<lb/>&#45;secution.  But misfortune followed their steps&#44; for the<lb/> ships in which they had sailed were wrecked on the<lb/> Indian ocean&#44; and only seven men and seven women<lb/> were saved.  Homeless and destitute&#44; the few survivors<lb/> would surely have died of hunger and sicknesses&#44; if<lb/> they had not found procured a living and a shelter in by<lb/> hard work toil.  They took to farming and principally<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>to olive pressing&#44; and because they would never labor do servile work<lb/> on the Sabbath&#44; they went by the name of Shanv&#225;r<lb/> Telis &#40;which means in the Hindu language &#34;the <sic>saturday</sic> ol oilmen&#34;&#41;.  Now&#59;<lb/> as every one can see&#44; this account is exceedingly <sic>meagre</sic><lb/> and open to doubts&#44; still the further testimony of<lb/> history proves that the Bene Israel have in all reality<lb/> an identical descent extraction with us ours&#44; though we may not<lb/> be able to discover the why and when they left the land<lb/> of our fathers&#44; nor trace their line of travel from Palestine<lb/> to a spot of whose very existence they scarcely could have<lb/> had a knowledge notion.  They Irrespective of their strong Jewish type&#44; denoting their lineage&#44; they have uniformly preserved<lb/> rites and ceremonies ordained in the Mosaic code.  They<lb/> have had always in common with us the New Year &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> in Tishri&#44; and the day of atonement &#91;Hebrew&#93; on the 10th of that<lb/> month&#44; and the Passover &#91;Hebrew&#93; in Nissan.  None needs<lb/> wonder that in the lapse of so many ages&#44; they forgot<lb/> some of the holidays&#59; that they misplaced or misunderstood others&#44; and<lb/> could not recall the ceremonials connected with&#44; nor<lb/> even the names of those which they did keep&#44; but<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>which they knew only in the language they ordinarily<lb/> spoke.  The Hebrew had become entirely dead to them&#44;<lb/> and as they were cut off altogether from every associa&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion with their coreligionists in Western Asia&#44; or Europe in Rome&#44; nothing but a miracle<lb/> could have prevented a difficult result.  Do we not<lb/> ourselves perceive how mischievously the decline of<lb/> Hebrew learning acts on our observances&#63;  How Do I not but too often find that some of<lb/> the young generation would find it have difficulty to in pronouncing<lb/> the Biblical titles of the festivals of the Lord&#44; not to say<lb/> that they would be are unable to recite the simplest sentence<lb/> out of our Scriptures&#63;  It cannot be therefore only a matter of surprise<lb/> to us that what we deliberately bring about by <sic>wilful</sic> neglect&#44;<lb/> circumstances beyond human control occasioned among the<lb/> Bene Israel of Hindustan.  They During hundreds of years they<lb/> received no teaching whatever in the Law. and traditions  The<lb/> mere tradition of their origin hindered their merging into<lb/> gentilism.  To their praise it must be said that<lb/> a great factor in their distinct preservation&#45;&#45;the same which often in our<lb/> history has operated before to our advantage&#44; as the Rabbis<lb/> express it &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> I mean a great factor was the obedience of the women to ordinances handed<lb/> down by the ancestors.  It is stated that in the year<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>900 of the Christian era&#44; a certain David Rahabi<lb/> journeyed from Cochin of Malabar in search of the<lb/> Bene Israel.  He was prompted by a strong wish to<lb/> better the mental and spiritual condition of his forlorn<lb/> coreligionists.  Having heard of them&#44; he determined to become<lb/> their instructor and guide.  Arrived at their settlements&#44;<lb/> the good man noticed that the Bene Israel retained but a<lb/> faint recollection of the Torah&#59; that they performed many<lb/> of its rules mechanically&#44; simply as olden inherited habits&#44; whose the<lb/> sense of which they could not give&#59; that they possessed<lb/> no ritual whatever&#44; but that on all occasions they<lb/> repeated over and over again &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> or our declaration of faith&#59; and that such was the whole<lb/> extent of their knowledge of acquaintance with Holy Writ and its language.<lb/>  David Rahabi felt convinced that the Bene Israel<lb/> were in reality what they called themselves&#44; still to<lb/> try them&#44; he brought one day to some of their women diffe&#45;<lb/>&#45;rent fishes which he asked them to cook prepare in the<lb/> same dish.  The women looked&#44; and having detected<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>a number that had no fins and scales&#44; they refused<lb/> to comply with the request&#44; saying that they had<lb/> never mixed the permitted pure with the prohibited impure.  Strength&#45;<lb/>&#45;ened in his views&#44; as to the genuineness of the descent<lb/> of the people he was anxious to elevate&#44; the zealous<lb/> Jew of Malabar went about teaching&#44; and chose<lb/> three youths whom he trained in Hebrew reading.<lb/>  He let the continual monotonous recital of the Shemag be<lb/> dropped&#44; and showed how to conduct a regular wor&#45;<lb/>&#45;ship.  Unfortunately&#44; his generous tuition soon ceased.<lb/>  Either out of jealousy of his influence over the Bene<lb/> Israel&#44; or for other motives unexplained&#44; an Indian Chief<lb/> murdered David Rahabi&#44; and the Bene Israel were<lb/> left to under the leadership of the three he had measurably<lb/> taught.  They watched over the improvements which<lb/> he had introduced&#44; but they these had not taken sufficient<lb/> root to remain inalterable unaltered.  As one generation succed&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed another&#44; steadfastness of principles yielded to tempt&#45;<lb/>&#45;ations&#44; and marriages out of the Jewish pale were productive<lb/> of sore evils&#59; for the offspring of such misalliances fell<lb/> into heathenish habits.  Nevertheless&#44; the majority kept<lb/> firm and Providentially a number of Jews from Malabar&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>possessing more than an ordinary acquaintance with<lb/> versed in our sacred learning&#44; arrived at different intervals in<lb/> different settlements and &#91;&#63;&#93; spread there the knowledge<lb/> of the Scriptures&#44; according to the text.  The records from<lb/> which I have gathered my information&#44; makes special<lb/> mention&#44; with high praise&#44; of a Rabbi Solomon Salem Shurrabi&#44;<lb/> whose personal exertions in Bombay to reform improve his bre&#45;<lb/>&#45;theren&#44; were unremitting and attended with noble results.<lb/>  He is described as a man of commanding appearance and<lb/> intelligent looks&#44; a man esteemed by all and listened to deferent&#45;<lb/>&#45;ially.  To He served his congregation twenty years for<lb/> a <sic>tifle</sic>&#44; not to let them feel under obligation&#44; while<lb/> earning his daily livelihood as a book&#45;binder&#44; and still<lb/> utilizing every moment in favor behalf of his people in<lb/> multifarious capacities&#44; as readers and preacher at<lb/> the Synagogue and as officiating minister in various other<lb/> religious rites and ceremonies.  Familiar with the Hindustani<lb/> and Marathi languages&#44; he had no difficulty<lb/> in communicating useful learning to those who<lb/> had forgotten the Hebrew and the precepts promulgated<lb/> in it.  When Solomon Salem Shurrabi died in 1856&#44;<lb/> he left a void which was not filled&#44; but which widened<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>greatly&#44; because Christian missionaries took ad&#45;<lb/>&#45;vantage of the absence of his powerful influence&#44; to in&#45;<lb/>&#45;sinuate themselves into the favor of the weaklings<lb/> and the wordly.  Promises of temporal promotions are<lb/> apt to silence in the ambitious&#44; the voice of conscience.<lb/>  The Bene Israel are mostly poor mechanics&#44; or olive<lb/> pressers&#44;&#45;&#45;Saturday oilmen&#45;&#45;Shanvar Telis&#44; small like their ancestors&#44; hired of narrow trusts of land&#44; earn&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing in all their callings very small wages.  Many<lb/> of them have arisen in the army and wear decorations won<lb/> by their bravery.  It is also stated that during the<lb/> Sepoy outbreak in 1851 and 58&#44; Jews in the military<lb/> ranks distinguished themselves for their loyalty to the<lb/> English government&#44; and one Moosageen or Moses<lb/> Israel&#44; a commissioned officer&#44; was personally set upon<lb/> and his family threatened with imminent danger&#44; be&#45;<lb/>&#45;cause he would not join in the meeting.  But if&#44; as<lb/> soldiers&#44; some have reached distinction attained eminence&#44; in the ordinary<lb/> walks of life&#44; the Bene Israel remain in a very humble<lb/> condition.  Hence the offers which that the Church makes<lb/> to converts&#44; are snares into which the unwary may<lb/> be easily caught&#44; and they are entrapped.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>Education&#59; broad education&#44; is a mighty impulse to<lb/> self&#45;respect compelling social progress.  If&#44; for instance&#44;<lb/> the Bene Israel of Bombay for instance were not hampered in<lb/> every way by municipal rules against attaining a lofty<lb/> degree of religious and secular learning&#44; if the facilities<lb/> to exercise their natural faculties were placed within their<lb/> reach&#44; they might frown down the evil counsels wily schemes of pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;pagandists.  It certainly was worth the while of the<lb/> public spirited and good hearted in among the Hebrews&#44;<lb/> to try to bring into play the lever of human elevation.<lb/>  Accordingly In 1875 a modest school was started and<lb/> supported by voluntary contributions.  But too un&#45;<lb/>&#45;equal to the wants of a large constantly increasing attendance that<lb/> institution was.  It might have been closed alto&#45;<lb/>&#45;gether for by reason of insufficient means&#44; had not<lb/> an organization in England&#44; and a philanthropic<lb/> family in India&#44; readily come to the rescue.<lb/>  The Anglo&#45;Jewish association sought after by the<lb/> school President&#45;&#45;Mr Hyam Samuel Kehimker&#45;&#45;and<lb/> the Sassoons&#45;&#45;the Montefiores of the East Indies&#44; were<lb/> kind and liberal on all occasions&#44; responded to the appeal.<lb/>  In 1881 a larger and fitter school was opened&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>and the testimony of prominent Jews and Christians<lb/> who grace it with their presence each year at<lb/> the examination season&#44; and express to the students<lb/> words of encouraging gratulations&#44; holds out the hope<lb/> of the intellectual preservation of those distant bre&#45;<lb/>theren in our fold.  In a pamphlet which<lb/> I lately forwarded to my address&#44; the aforenamed<lb/> Hyam Samuel Kehimker writes&#58; &#34;The charities<lb/> of many European&#44; American&#44; and Asiatic mil&#45;<lb/>&#45;lionaires are truly catholic and princely&#44; and the<lb/> Bene Israel community consisting of about 10&#44;000<lb/> souls earnestly look for patronage which will<lb/> tend to elevate the intellectual&#44; social&#44; and moral<lb/> condition of this isolated and neglected branch of<lb/> Israel&#44; steeped as it is in the ocean of ignorance<lb/> both secular and religious.&#34;  The pleading is strong&#44;<lb/> and should evoke a response even from those who do<lb/> not reckon their riches by the million&#44; but I will not<lb/> urge it&#44; for wide as my sympathies are&#44; embracing<lb/> the whole house of Jacob&#44; wherever Providence<lb/> destined its members to scatter&#44; still I feel&#44; with<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p>the Rabbis that those nearest to us have a primary<lb/> claim to our benevolence &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  I need not say to my hearers&#44; how<lb/> a generous spirit must now be evinced towards<lb/> the exaltation of the lowly of Israel in the city of<lb/> Philadelphia.<lb/></p>
            
            <p>&#40;This address was concluded with a few words of<lb/> exhortations to a Bar Mitzvah&#41;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
