<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF5_10</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_10_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_10_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_10_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_10_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_10_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_10_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_10_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_10_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_10_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_10_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_10_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_10_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_10_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_10_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_10_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_10_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>13 pages on 6 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Post Biblical lecture<lb/>
                53<lb/>
                Spanish French School<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>The Ibn Tibon family<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>It is sometime since I undertook to resume my<lb/> post biblical lectures&#44; and really when before the<lb/> heated term of last summer set in&#44; and I began<lb/> to speak of the eminent scholars&#44; who flourished<lb/> in France in medieval ages&#44; I had intended to fol&#45;<lb/>&#45;low up my brief account of the famous world renowned Rashi<lb/> and of the exceedingly meritorious Rudak or David<lb/> Kimchi&#44; by a short biography of more such worthies&#44; &#34;belong&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing to that country.  But the necessity of making<lb/> my discourses suit solemn and festive seasons and as well as current events&#44;<lb/> prevented what I will endeavour now to do at<lb/> intervals&#44; not quite so far apart as I permitted to<lb/> to elapse heretofore.  I wish to make mention of a<lb/> a French family in France whose members have distinguished signalised<lb/> themselves in one particular.<lb/></p>
            <p>At Granada&#44; once a famous city of Southern Spain&#44;<lb/> was born Judah Aben Tibon in the twelfth century<lb/> of the vulgar era.  What causes may have induced<lb/> him early in life to emigrate to Lunel&#44; in South France&#44; we have<lb/> not heard.  Very probably&#44; some political agitation.<lb/>  For&#44; let me say here&#44; in passing&#44; that they are in error<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>who imagine that in Spain&#44; even in the days during the dominion of the<lb/> liberal Moors&#44; who cultivated and fostered know&#45;<lb/>&#45;ledge and appreciated our people&#39;s state of culture&#44; Jews enjoyed<lb/> perfect freedom&#44; fearing neither prejudice nor<lb/> ill will.  The idea that in the Ibernian penin&#45;<lb/>&#45;sula our predecessors fared as well as we whose<lb/> fortunate lot was cast in the United States of<lb/> America now fare is simply absurd.  Not infrequently in&#45;<lb/>&#45;ternal dissensions&#44; jealousies among Arabian tribes<lb/> and envy of Hebrew talents and Hebrew influence&#44;<lb/> brought on persecution and voluntary exile.  A<lb/> glance at the history of the time will convince us<lb/> of that fact.  Judah Aben Tibon having<lb/> taken up his residence in Lunel&#44; exercised there<lb/> the medical profession with distinction.  In that<lb/> calling&#44; followed almost everywhere effectively<lb/> by adherents of our religion&#44; while magic arts and<lb/> quackery were the senseless appliances of gentiles&#44;<lb/> Judah Aben Tibon earned more than a competence.<lb/>  His large means he employed to communal advantage&#44;<lb/> so that by a commendable generosity&#44; he secured from<lb/> local authorities a privilege of inestimable value.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>He prevented the odious personal tax&#44; imposed in<lb/> other localities upon every Jew.  It is also<lb/> narrated that our Judah gained an enviable refu&#45;<lb/>&#45;tation as an author.  To this Maimonides bore<lb/> witness&#59; for&#44; writing to Samuel&#44; son of Judah Aben<lb/> Tibor&#44; the illustrious sage of Cordova so expressed him&#45;<lb/>&#45;self thus&#58; &#34;We had already heard of the honorable and wise<lb/> Chief&#44; Judah your father&#44; of his scholarship and the<lb/> terseness of his style&#44; both in Arabic and Hebrew.<lb/>  Men of good parts and high repute standing from Granada told<lb/> us so.&#34;.  I have also read likewise that he was sought<lb/> by many who relied on his quick perception and<lb/> calm judgment&#44; for an opinion about the merit of their literary<lb/> works.  His own productions in the sacred language<lb/> have been lost&#44; but arguing from stray paragraphs<lb/> and passages occasionally met&#44; we may be justified<lb/> in ascribing to him cleverness in handling the Biblic&#45;<lb/>&#45;al tongue.  The highest service&#44; however&#44; which<lb/> the Israelite of who settled at Lunel rendered literature&#44; consists in<lb/> his translations.  Had not his pen run rapidly&#44;<lb/> works books of vast importance might have never become<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>known to us&#44; after the Arabic ceased to be the<lb/> vernacular among a portion of our people&#44; or in<lb/> countries where that language was never understood. at no time spoken.<lb/>  Thus&#44; for instance&#44; the first labors in Jewish philosophy from<lb/> a man&#44; whom the world of letters delights to honor<lb/> this year&#44;&#45;&#45;the one thousandth of his birth&#45;&#45;&#44; might<lb/> have been cast into the pit of oblivion.  Saadiah<lb/> of Fayum in Egypt&#44; whose writings are being<lb/> collated for publication&#44; would not have taught<lb/> posterity&#44; as he did instruct us in that noble volume of his&#58; &#34;Creeds<lb/> and Opinions.&#34;  If for nothing more than for having<lb/> made us acquainted with the offspring of a master<lb/> mind that raised the School of Sura to its pristine<lb/> glory when invited to preside over it&#44; we owe Judah Aben Tibon infinite thanks.<lb/>  But he laid us under obligation by his version of<lb/> other Arabian works&#44; on theology&#44; on Grammar and<lb/> a variety of subjects.  We must not&#44; nevertheless&#44;<lb/> forget the man&#44; who inspired our Judah to take<lb/> up the pen of the Scribe and who financially supplied<lb/> what the learned translator needed.  Meshullam<lb/> Ben Jacob was the Maecenas&#44; deserving of remembrance&#44;<lb/> and some of his relatives acted in concert to that<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>laudable end.  All honor to them and to the<lb/> agent of their scholarly liberal disposition.  Judah<lb/> Aben Tibon had an heir worthy of his sire.  Like the<lb/> celebrated father&#44; so the son Samuel widened the<lb/> boundaries of our learning.  He had studied well at<lb/> home&#44; during his youth.  Having reached manhood&#44;<lb/> his mind bent in a new direction.  He determined<lb/> to launch into commercial schemes&#44; in order to get<lb/> quickly rich.  Samuel Aben Tibon&#44; so learned<lb/> in Jewish lore&#44; appeared to have forgotten the salu&#45;<lb/>&#45;tary advise of the author of Proverbs&#58; &#34;Do not worry to<lb/> grow affluent&#34; and the other maxim of the same in&#45;<lb/>&#45;spired writer&#58; &#34;He who is in haste to become opulent<lb/> will not remain guiltless.&#34;  He lost in his<lb/> mercantile pursuits what he had put into them&#44;<lb/> and would have sunk into penury&#44; had not his father<lb/> come to his rescue.  His losses&#44; however&#44; proved our<lb/> gain&#44; for the unsuccessful merchant&#44; closed his<lb/> ledger&#44; which showed a continual deficit&#44; to open<lb/> the books out of which he would afford us a wealth<lb/> of knowledge.  His unbounded admiration of<lb/> Maimonides&#44; led him to undertake a translation into<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Hebrew of almost everything which the immortal<lb/> Rabbi wrote in Arabic.  If he was not very<lb/> felicitous in some of his rendering&#44; we must attribute<lb/> it to the difficulty in which he met encountered in reproducing<lb/> terms and expressions foreign to our sacred tongue.<lb/>  At all events&#44; Maimonides himself highly appre&#45;<lb/>ciated the efforts of the French Israelite.  Fortunately&#44;<lb/> some of the correspondence between the enthusiastic<lb/> translator and the illustrious author is still extant.<lb/>  I will quote a passage&#44; which may be of interest.<lb/>  In a letter&#44; sent from Lunel to Cairo&#44; making inquiries<lb/> about certain sentences expressions phrases occurring in the famous original of<lb/> the famous Moreh Nebuchim &#34;the teacher of the per&#45;<lb/>&#45;plexed&#44;&#34; Samuel Aben Tibon evinces a strong inclination<lb/> to personally consult the writer.  Maimonides<lb/> answers&#58; &#34;Regarding your idea of visiting me&#44;<lb/> let me say at once&#44; that you will be the most<lb/> welcome among all comers.  I shall greatly rejoice<lb/> in your company&#44; for I indeed desire to see you&#44; more<lb/> than you may desire to see me&#44; though the accomplish&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing of your wishes must be attended with the dangers<lb/> &#40;after having delivered this lecture&#44; I was shown Maimonides&#39; letter in Mrs Magnus<lb/> outline of P. B.&#41;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>of a sea voyage.  Still&#44; I must tell you&#44; even give<lb/> you counsel for your sake&#44; not to venture on the jour&#45;<lb/>&#45;ney&#44; for you will gain nothing by it&#44; except seeing<lb/> my face and receiving whatever attention it may be<lb/> in my power to show.  The expectation to derive in&#45;<lb/>&#45;formation on science&#44; or to remain alone with me any<lb/> time by day or by night&#44; I dare not encourage&#44;<lb/> for the reasons which I will now set forth.  I live<lb/> some miles away from Cairo&#44; where the Sultan has<lb/> his residence.  I must visit him daily at an early<lb/> es hour.  Should anything hail him or his children<lb/> or his wives&#44; I cannot leave Cairo.  I must keep most<lb/> of the time at the palace&#44; where some offices not<lb/> infrequently consult me&#44; regarding their own health.<lb/>  In short&#44; I go to Cairo each day.  If all goes right&#44;<lb/> I come back home after twelve o&#39;clock&#44; very much<lb/> exhausted.  I find crowds of people&#44; Jews and Gentiles&#44;<lb/> of every standing in society a motley company waiting<lb/> for my return.  I alight from my horse&#44; wash&#44; beg to<lb/> be excused till I take a light mean and go to my<lb/> office to prescribe&#44; according to different diseases.<lb/>  So it continues till late at night.  Sometime till<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>long after midnight&#44; when I lie down perfectly<lb/> jaded out&#44; so that I can hardly speak.  In a word&#44; my<lb/> fellow Israelites cannot confer with me &#40;as such&#41; except on the<lb/> Sabbath.  The the Congregation&#44; or most of them seek me<lb/> after the morning service.  I direct them how to proceed<lb/> during the week.  Then they read in my presence till noon.<lb/>  Some do not arrive till the afternoon services.  Now&#58;<lb/> I wanted to let you know all this&#44; and I only told you in<lb/> part what you may see&#44; if&#44; with the help of God&#44; you<lb/> do come&#44; after having finished the work which you<lb/> have undertaken for the benefit of our brethren.  Come<lb/> then to make inquiries&#44; but not to anticipate instruction&#44;<lb/> for my time is exceedingly limited.&#34;  This interesting<lb/> communication&#44; offering us an insight into the life work<lb/> of Maimonides as court physician in Egypt&#44; to which country he had immigrated&#44; is followed by directions which he gives<lb/> the translator&#44; concerning certain points and the books which<lb/> he ought to consult in preference to all others.  I have<lb/> not learned whether the two ever met&#44; but I know that<lb/> a vast deal of Samuel Aben Tibon&#39;s time was devoted<lb/> to rendering into Hebrew the Arabic productions issued<lb/> from the pen of his ideal philosophical author.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>More happy than Samuel in his diction was his son Moses in his<lb/> versions.  A perfect Arabist&#44; he translated into classical<lb/> French&#44; as spoken in the middle ages&#44; a number of books<lb/> on medical science.  But what to Israelites would be<lb/> inestimable&#44; if extant&#44; is a work in Hebrew by Moses<lb/> Aben Tibon&#44; explanatory of Talmudic legends&#44; parables<lb/> and hyperboles.  I say inestimable&#44; for&#44; too often have<lb/> Rabbinical sayings&#44; which&#44; very possibly&#44; were designed<lb/> to convey deep meaning&#44; or point a moral&#44; served the ene&#45;<lb/>&#45;mies of Judaism &#40;to our shame mostly apostates&#41; to set<lb/> our Sages into ridicule and make us blush at the interpretation<lb/> of their strange sayings&#44; or bold figures of speech.<lb/></p>  
            <p>I cannot conclude my sketch&#44; referring to works in Arabic&#44;<lb/> without making special mention of a coreligionist of our own time&#44; suc&#45;<lb/>&#45;cessful in his wonderful effort.  Solomon Munk&#44; who<lb/> replaced Ernest Benan&#44; as Professor of Semitic languages in<lb/> the &#40;Royal Academy&#41; college of France&#44; was struck blind&#44; when he just as he had un&#45;<lb/>&#45;dertaken to give us a faultless rendition of the most celebrated<lb/> labors of Maimonides.  Through the help of devoted friends&#44;<lb/> who read out the original&#59; who wrote under dictation&#44; and<lb/> who revised proofs&#44; Munk&#44; that had already won<lb/> high distinction by his erudite works&#44; astonished<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p>the world&#44; by issuing from the press in three<lb/> volumes with abundant copious annotations and<lb/> scholarly illustrations&#44; the Moreh Nebuchim<lb/> in perfect modern French.  All Let us honor<lb/> to the memory of one so persevering&#44; under a<lb/> trial which would have deterred many from<lb/> even easier tasks.  All honor and We owe gratitude<lb/> to the Israelite&#44; who sustained by his trust<lb/> in God&#44; and by pious resignation to the Divine<lb/> will&#44; <sic>benefitted</sic> us&#44; while seeking comfort in a he sought relief to his<lb/> terrible privation&#44; by in serving the cause of Hebrew<lb/> literature.<lb/></p>
            <p>&#40;The concluding part of this lecture&#44; which has reference to the good and<lb/> learned Munk&#44; was lengthened by a sense of deep felt sympathy and admi&#45;<lb/>ration for the translator of le guide des egar&#233;s.&#41;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
