<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF11_3</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_3_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_3_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_3_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_3_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_3_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_3_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_3_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_3_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_3_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_3_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_3_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_3_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_3_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_3_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_3_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff11_3_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>14 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>27</p>
            
            <p>An explanatory lecture about eating meat &#38; butter<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>My brethren&#33;  A few weeks ago I was asked&#44; how I could reconcile<lb/> the action of Abraham our father&#44; recorded at the commencement<lb/> of this weeks&#39; Parash&#225;&#44; with the ordinance which forbids not only<lb/> the preparing of animal food with any milky substance&#44; but the<lb/> partaking separately thereof at the same meal.  My reply was<lb/> the simplest and most unsophisticated.  I said&#44; that when the<lb/> patriarch offered simultaneously to the three supposed wayfarers<lb/> the flesh of a tender calf and cream&#44; no law had yet interdicted it.<lb/>  My querist however did not appear satisfied&#44; but argued that if<lb/> the prohibition&#44; as now existing&#44; was really of divine origin&#44; the<lb/> angels who are supernal intelligences&#44; ought to have paid it<lb/> proper regard&#44; though it had not been communicated to<lb/> human beings.  I then rejoined that the celestial messenger<lb/> having assumed a corporeal aspect&#44; had necessarily to conform<lb/> with the usages prevailing among the men of that age.  But as<lb/> while engaged in the subject&#44; my attention was suddenly diverted from<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>it&#44; I have deemed it fit to resume its discussion for general<lb/> instruction.  I will therefore&#44; ere I proceed&#44; admit with all<lb/> candour&#44; that the law in question does not&#44; according to its literal<lb/> construction&#44; allow the wide scope given it by the Rabbins.<lb/>  That they extended it for wise purposes I am fully convinced&#59; that<lb/> in this as in many other instances the Teachers of Israel aimed at<lb/> guarding against too close a familiarity communion with the gentile world&#44;<lb/> is my firm opinion&#44; but while my respect for their pious intentions<lb/> urges me to counsel a strict adherence to their prescriptions&#44; when<lb/> I undertake to explain the import of the Biblical injunction&#44;<lb/> I must be guided chiefly by the light which the context throws<lb/> upon it.  Lend me then your kind attention.  Three times in<lb/> the Pentateuch a sentence occurs which has been thus rendered<lb/> in the vernacular &#34;Thou shalt not seethe the kid in its mother&#39;s<lb/> milk.&#34;  But if we refer to the passage wherewith it<lb/> is connected&#44; we shall perceive that twice in the book<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>of Exodus it immediately follows the command of offering to<lb/> God the first ripe fruits of the land.  This fact has sug&#45;<lb/>&#45;gested the idea that the prohibition had in view the prevention of<lb/> a custom exercised among the ancients at the harvest&#45;season.<lb/>  It is not improbable that the heathens considered it meritorious<lb/> to offer them at the shrines of their numerous idols&#44; also the firstlings<lb/> of their cattle&#44; boiled in the milk drawn from their mother.<lb/>  But Holy Writ which deprecate any assimilation with gentile practices&#44;<lb/> does therefore express itself in these terms &#34;The beginning of the<lb/> first ripe fruits of thy land&#44; thou shalt bring to the house of the<lb/> Lord thy God&#44;&#34; that is&#44; whereas other people present the increase of<lb/> their soil to the false deities&#44; with whose altars the earth is replete&#44;<lb/> thou&#44; who worshippest One only God&#44; shalt convey your solely<lb/> to the place He has chosen to hallow with His Divinity.<lb/>  Nor shalt that token of your gratitude to Providence be accom&#45;<lb/>&#45;panied with a rite which the heathens performs at that period.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>That shalt not take the young from under its parent&#44; and<lb/> prepare it as food with the very milk that nature had<lb/> provided for its sustenance &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#45;&#45;The law of Sinai&#44; my dear friends&#33; which<lb/> designs to render us human even towards the dumb creation&#44;<lb/> contains various directions to that effect.  For example&#58;<lb/> we are forbid to slaughter on the same day an animal with<lb/> its offspring.  Likewise we are emphatically warned not to<lb/> <sic>to</sic> seize upon the dam while hatching her young.  Not<lb/> to plough the ground with two animals of unequal strength<lb/> bound together.  And other precepts of the same character&#44;<lb/> will be found interspersed throughout the heavenly pages.<lb/>  Now&#44; I conceive that the prescription touching the case at<lb/> issue&#44; has the identical tendency as the above.  Although<lb/> we have been permitted the destruction of animal life for<lb/> our nutriment&#44; as well as for the divine service&#44; we should<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>not do so with wanton recklessness.  It might be thought that<lb/> since the kid had been killed&#44; it matters not what sort of<lb/> liquid is used in dressing it&#44; but the deliberate action of drawing<lb/> for that purpose its mother&#39;s milk&#44; betokens a want of that<lb/> tenderness of feelings which ought to harbour in the human breast.<lb/>  Hence&#44; I believe to have arisen the prohibition so written in the<lb/> Pentateuch &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  But that ordinance&#44;<lb/> in order to effect the object of the Legislator&#44; must needs bear a general<lb/> application.  It cannot possibly be restricted to the mere case<lb/> contemplated in the text.  Therefore have the Rabbins asserted<lb/> that not only the newly born goat&#44; but all other animals are<lb/> included in the Biblical behest.  Nor let any one suppose that<lb/> the idea they have advanced is a bare assumption&#44; for it is&#44; on<lb/> the contrary&#44; a truth supported by scriptural authority.  We could<lb/> cite many instances in which the law is evidently meant to<lb/> be general&#44; though specifically stated&#44; but one will suffice<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>our purpose.  Among the statutes registered in the twenty first<lb/> chapter of Exodus we read the following&#58; If a man openeth a<lb/> pit or diggeth a pit&#44; and covereth it not&#44; so that an ox<lb/> or an ass falleth therein&#44; the owner of the pit shall pay&#44; he shall<lb/> return the equivalent money to the owner of the animals &#34;Can it&#44; my<lb/> friends ever be imagined that because the inspired writer framed<lb/> the ordinance in those words&#44; the sentence applies exclusively to the<lb/> injury effected by that particular cause and to those particular objects<lb/> therein mentioned&#63;  Will it not&#44; on the contrary&#44; be readily under&#45;<lb/>&#45;stood that any detriment occasioned to our neighbour&#39;s property<lb/> by heedlessness evinced in a manner similar to that pointed out<lb/> in the cited passage&#44; would subject the offender to the same<lb/> penalty&#63;  It being most undoubtedly so&#44; we must arrive&#44; by<lb/> the same process of reasoning&#44; at the conclusion that whether<lb/> an Israelite prepares for food the flesh of a kid or that of any<lb/> other suckling animal with the milk of its parent&#44; his trespass<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>is equally grievous.  Now&#44; my Brethren&#33;  It was to preclude<lb/> the possibility of our infringing unwittingly on the divine behest&#44;<lb/> as well as to raise a higher barrier between the gentile practices and<lb/> our own&#44; that the Sages have extended the prohibition to the mixture<lb/> of any meat with a milky substance.  In deference to the righteous<lb/> aim they had in view&#44; have all their restrictions&#44; upon this score&#44; been<lb/> accepted every where by the people of Israel&#44; and we possess unmis&#45;<lb/>&#45;takable evidences that as far back as at least nineteen centuries<lb/> ago the belief had already been rooted in the mind of our nation&#44;<lb/> that to contravene the Rabbinical directors in this respect&#44; would<lb/> be tantamount to violating the scriptural command.  For&#44; Onkelos<lb/> the Roman proselyte&#44; who wrote during the beginning of the<lb/> vulgar era&#44; translated the verse &#91;Hebrew&#93; in the<lb/> Chaldaic language &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Ye shall not eat meat<lb/> with milk&#34; showing that a universal practice had attached<lb/> that sense wide sense to the original prohibition.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>This much I have said to prove my querist and my audience<lb/> at large&#44; that to advance as an argument against the divinity<lb/> of the statute&#44; the circumstance that the angels who visited<lb/> Abraham did not heed it&#44; is to misapprehend and confound<lb/> facts.  First&#58; because the action of the patriarch was not in<lb/> direct antagonism to the ordinance&#45;&#45;according to its literal signification&#45;&#45;<lb/> as revealed in after&#45;ages at Sinai.  Secondly&#58; because were it<lb/> even conceded that it was so&#44; my elucidation must have demon&#45;<lb/>&#45;strated that God intended it simply to convey a lesson of humanity<lb/> to the creations of the earth&#44; and consequently as2 such his1 tuition<lb/> had no weight whatever with respect &#34;to the supernal beings whose<lb/> dwelling&#45;place is not with the mortals&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> The following allegory of the Talmud will further illustrate my<lb/> position.  When Moses ascended mount Sinai to commune<lb/> with the Lord&#44; the angels who surround His throne asked why<lb/> had a son of man been so greatly favored.  They were answered<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>by the Omnipotent that he had been commissioned to receive form heaven<lb/> and impart to earthly beings a code of laws.  At this the Seraphic host observed<lb/> that the perishable inhabitants of the world&#44; could not certainly<lb/> be worthy of obtaining so precious a token of celestial regard.<lb/>  But to silence the opposition&#44; the son of Amram rehearsed the<lb/> Decalogue before the adverse spirits&#44; and thus conclusively showed<lb/> that those only in whose heart lurks an evil propensity can need<lb/> tenets that control the passions and govern the will &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            <p>But in order to complete my disquisition&#44; I must refer also to<lb/> the sentence in Deuteronomy&#44; where the prohibition under discussion<lb/> occurs for the third time.  In that instance Holy Writ joins<lb/> it with the rules concerning the quadrupeds and fishes which<lb/> are not permitted as food to the Hebrews.  It seems that<lb/> in recapitulating the laws of Leviticus&#44; the inspired leader of<lb/> our ancestors sought to impress us more deeply with the object<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>of those peculiar observances.  Wherefore had after having recalled to<lb/> mind the love of the Eternal for the descendants of Jacob&#44; he concluded<lb/> this &#34;ye shall not eat of any thing that dies of itself&#44; thou shalt<lb/> give it unto the stranger that is in thy gates&#44; and he may eat<lb/> it&#44; or thou mayest sell it unto an alien&#44; for thou art a holy<lb/> people to the Lord thy God&#58; thou shalt not seethe the kid in<lb/> its mother&#39;s milk.&#34;  He purposed thereby to signify that not<lb/> because nay principle of morality was involved in the <sic>fulfilment</sic> of<lb/> those enactments were they enjoined on us&#44; but because they were to<lb/> stand as characteristic marks to prove us the missionaries of<lb/> the Most High &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  And although the blending<lb/> of the flesh of a young animal with the milk of its parent could<lb/> not be placed in the category of those viands which were forbid<lb/> by reason of sone some inherent impurity&#44; yet&#44; as our abstinence from<lb/> it serves to distinguish us from other people&#44; we should loathe it<lb/> equally as the flesh of a diseased carcass.  Hence have the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>two prohibitions been designedly connected together in the same<lb/> passage &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#45;&#45;.<lb/></p>
            <p>And here I will seize the opportunity offered to point out the<lb/> grievous error into which those Israelites fall&#44; who maintain that<lb/> they may sit with impurity at tables laden with viands indis&#45;<lb/>&#45;criminately prepared&#44; provided they do not partake of the<lb/> flesh of animals declared unclean in the Scriptures.  I will not<lb/> dwell at present on the regulations which a well&#45;founded tra&#45;<lb/>&#45;dition has laid down for slaughtering the cattle&#44; and extracting<lb/> the blood so repeatedly and so emphatically forbidden in the<lb/> sacred pages&#44; but I will ask whether the passage I have just quoted<lb/> from the fifth book of Moses&#44; is not a sufficient warrant against<lb/> our feeding on the flesh of animals that have not undergone a careful<lb/> examination&#58; Does not common sense&#44; irrespectively of any<lb/> Rabbinical tuition tell us&#44; that if a think that dies of itself is<lb/> prohibited to the Hebrews&#44; that which is liable to die through<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p>some inward disorder&#44; must be comprised in the same rule&#63;  But<lb/> how can we convince ourselves that we are not swallowing what<lb/> God has pronounced an abomination to us&#44; unless we have previously<lb/> ascertained its perfection&#63;  Say&#44; can we be sure of not violating the<lb/> decree of our Supreme Legislator&#44; when we join at meals those who<lb/> do not scruple to eat the most noxious and sickness&#45;breeding diet&#63;<lb/>  No&#44; my friends&#33;  To be true to our mission we must abide by the<lb/> salutary directions of our wise preceptors.  They have afforded us the<lb/> means of guarding against transgression.  Their writings contain what<lb/> will amply suffice to discover if the object we have destined for<lb/> our aliment is fit for him who is bound by the law of Sinai &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>  And as we attend to their instruction&#44; we shall promote both our<lb/> physical and moral health.  We may not always escape the<lb/> distempers to which human creatures are subject&#44; but we shall<lb/> avert numerous infirmities&#44; while we shall also bear within us<lb/> the satisfaction&#44; that we have not presumptuously deviated from<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="14"/>
            <p>the line of our religious duties.<lb/></p>
            <p>And in order to avoid sinning even from ignorance&#44; I would recommend<lb/> exceeding caution in trusting the individuals who furnish Israelites with<lb/> animal flesh&#59; for not <sic>unfrequently</sic> have they been detected in the act<lb/> of abusing our confidence.  I am aware that the our safest defense from<lb/> such dishonest dealings&#44; is the supervision of our brethren&#44; whose office<lb/> and interest it is to guard their work against being counterfeited.  But<lb/> as they are not ubiquitous&#44; nor are they all acting in concert for the wel&#45;<lb/>&#45;fare of the Community&#44; it behooves us to exercise our own judgment and<lb/> thus foil the schemes of the deceivers.  And let us pray that from<lb/> hence forth and ever more&#44; the boast of every Israelite who resides within<lb/> our borders may be the same as that in which the prophet of old glorified before<lb/> his God&#44; to wit&#44; &#34;behold my soul hath not been polluted&#44; for&#44; from my<lb/> youth up even till now&#44; have I not eaten of that which dieth of itself<lb/> or is torn in pieces&#44; neither came there any abominable flesh into my<lb/> mouth&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> So may it be.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
