<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF7_29</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff7_29_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff7_29_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff7_29_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff7_29_2v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 1 sheet<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>A funeral<lb/></p>
            <p>&#34;He has humbled my power on the way&#59; He has shortened my<lb/> days.&#34;  This lament which one of the Hebrew psalmists<lb/> uttered&#44; might have been set forth by our coreligionist now<lb/> lying dead.  Many were the grievous vicissitudes which<lb/> he experienced during a life not reaching up to the<lb/> allotted term.  But to allude to the instability of<lb/> fortune&#44; to cite social and domestic changes would be to<lb/> recall circumstances of a painful character.  I shall not<lb/> add to the distress of the bereaved.  I will rather<lb/> obey my natural instincts and speak a few words<lb/> that may afford some comfort.  It must be a source<lb/> of satisfaction to the sorrowful wife to feel that<lb/> she strengthened herself to bear all the mutations under&#45;<lb/>&#45;gone.  It is a soothing reflection to know that she<lb/> was a helpmate indeed to her husband when sorely tried.<lb/>  Who but the all&#45;seeing God could have perceived the<lb/> mental efforts of a woman in feeble health&#59; her strenuous<lb/> endeavours to lighten the burden of the man bent under<lb/> the weight of afflictions&#63;  When she so taxed her powers&#44;<lb/> she did not imagine that she would survive him&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>who seemed hale and robust&#44; but the Disposer<lb/> of human events kept her alive for a beneficent<lb/> purpose.  He would that she might receive some<lb/> reward on earth&#44; ere she joins the companion of her<lb/> existence in heaven.  The only child of the widow<lb/> will henceforth bestow the fulness of filial devotion<lb/> on her aged mother.  I am assured that evi&#45;<lb/>&#45;dences of tender love were never wanting.  It was<lb/> a disinclination on the part of the father to leave<lb/> a city&#44; where so many reminiscences and affections<lb/> clustered that prevented his married daughter from<lb/> personally caring for her parents.  Israel Jacobs<lb/> would not <sic>exhange</sic> Philadelphia even for the<lb/> place in which his daughter resided.  We can<lb/> best appreciate the feelings which actuated our<lb/> coreligionists and sympathise therewith&#44; when we<lb/> behold round this coffin a respectably raised<lb/> progeny&#44; an offspring forming the second generation<lb/> that issued from our lamented fellow&#45;believer.  For<lb/> here were those grand children born who bear<lb/> his family name&#44; and here they bid fair to rise and<lb/> do his memory credit.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>It greatly pained the daughter whose husband&#39;s<lb/> interests retain her in the West&#44; to be deprived of the<lb/> satisfaction of dwelling in the East.  She was thus<lb/> forcibly prevented from waiting immediately upon her<lb/> parents&#44; but no just person will consider a fault<lb/> what circumstances beyond one&#39;s control and a sense<lb/> of conjugal duties absolutely demanded.  Let us<lb/> then condole with the bereaved mother and child&#44; and<lb/> offer them the assurance that whatever method they<lb/> will adopt hereafter to afford each other comfort&#44;<lb/> will give us also veritable pleasure.<lb/></p>
            <p>But another reflection should be a source of ineffable<lb/> consolation to the mourners.  Israel Jacobs was<lb/> an unsophisticated Jew.  He believed in and adhered<lb/> to the precepts of the Law with child&#45;like faith.<lb/>  As such his recompense will be high&#44; for though our<lb/> religion does not oppose a searching into the origin and<lb/> object of its tenets&#44; nay&#44; it encourages investigation&#44; because<lb/> it can stand the light of criticism&#44; yet to serve the<lb/> Lord with singleness of the heart as a youth obeying his<lb/> parents because he has implicit confidence in their<lb/> wisdom and experience&#44; is according to my mode of thinking&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>a merit worthy of eternal bliss.  I do not wish to<lb/> assert that my coreligionist was sinless.  It may not be<lb/> impossible that those who knew him intimately&#44; had<lb/> detected glaring faults and imperfections&#44; but I simply<lb/> mean that he did not share in the flippant incredulity<lb/> of the age&#44; the pretentious belief of men and women<lb/> who fancy to have learned enough to justify their offen&#45;<lb/>&#45;sive indifference to ancestral ordinances.  May the<lb/> fidelity of Israel Jacobs be the key unfastening for<lb/> his soul the portals of everlasting happiness.  May<lb/> it prove a source of constant consolation to those who<lb/> mourn for his loss&#44; and become an incentive to his<lb/> descendants to follow righteousness.  God grant<lb/> that the virtues he practised may be his advocates<lb/> before the judgment seat of the Most High&#44; that<lb/> his shortcomings may be forgiven by the Lord of<lb/> mercy&#44; and that his spirit may experience the hope<lb/> realized hope of the Psalmist &#34;As for me I shall<lb/> see Thy face through righteousness&#44; I shall be satisfied<lb/> when I awake in contemplating Thy &#40;Divine&#41; likeness.&#34;  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
