<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF3_5</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_5_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_5_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_5_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_5_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_5_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_5_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_5_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_5_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_5_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_5_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_5_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_5_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>5th lecture on<lb/>
                Post&#45;biblical history.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  We are now entering into the actual<lb/> domains of post&#45;biblical history.  Venerable for its<lb/> antiquity&#44; and venerated for its reformatory work&#44; is the<lb/> Congress that met under the leadership of the most<lb/> illustrious of Hebrew Scribes.  A halo of sanctity<lb/> encircles the brows of Ezra&#44; and each of his coadjutors&#59; for<lb/> to them Judaism owes the creation of soul&#45;exalting and soul&#45;<lb/>delivering institutions.  In the lecture&#44; which I designed<lb/> as an introduction to my present series&#44; I referred to the<lb/> Talmudical legend that gives the first Judeans&#44; exiled to<lb/> Babylon&#44; the credit of having erected a Synagogue in<lb/> a city to whereto they had been transported.  Indeed&#58; some<lb/> critics have ventured the opinion that lawful places of<lb/> worship besides the central Temple existed in Palestine proper&#44; before the conquest<lb/> of Nebuchadnezzar.  I am bold enough to acknowledge that I entertain very strong doubts on<lb/> that point the correctness of such views.  I am&#44; on the contrary&#44; forcibly led to believe<lb/> that Synagogues are the results of wise deliberations taken<lb/> by the men who constituted the august assembly&#44; called<lb/> Keneseth Ha&#45;gedolah.  To them is due a reform&#44; whose<lb/> high purposes we ourselves&#44; even this day&#44; have cause to appreciate.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>The Temple Sanctuary founded by Zerubabel had been<lb/> rebuilt and consecrated.  Its altar reeked with the<lb/> blood of daily burnt&#45;offerings.  But the Temple&#45;service<lb/> and its atoning powers&#44; conbibuted contributed very too scantily<lb/> to the moral and intellectual elevation of the masses.  Three<lb/> times only during the year&#44; the male portion of a scattered<lb/> population bowed at the holy shrine in the metropolis.<lb/>  Conceding that on those the occasion of those national festivals&#44;<lb/> instruction accompanied the sacrifices&#45;&#45;though the Penta&#45;<lb/>&#45;teuch ordered simply a Septennial public reading of the<lb/> Law&#45;&#45;still we still cannot avoid admitting that a teaching<lb/> received at long intervals could not possibly suffice to<lb/> keep up the knowledge of human deities.  True&#58; the<lb/> inspired legislator had not left Israel destitute of the<lb/> means which would prevent stagnation.  Moses had<lb/> opened a source of ever fresh instruction&#44; when he had<lb/> demanded of parents the instilling of the precepts into<lb/> the tender minds of their children&#44; even &#34;to that they should speake of<lb/> them the word of God&#44; when sitting in the house&#44; when walking by<lb/> the way&#44; when lying down&#44; and when rising up.&#34;  But<lb/> the great Synod understood well the causes of past short&#45;<lb/> backslidings &#45;comings&#44; and the urgent need of providing against their recurrence.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>It felt that to insure the permanence of the faith&#44; despite<lb/> the surrounding dangers&#44; new and more direct measures than heretofore must be resorted to.<lb/>  What the Sanctuary at Jerusalem and each family hearth had<lb/> failed to accomplish prior to the Babylonian captivity&#44; Sy&#45;<lb/>&#45;nagogues will bring about.  Rabbinism must try to effect<lb/> what the reform for which Prophetism labored mightily&#44; but<lb/> in vain.  Knowledge must be widely diffused&#59; popu&#45;<lb/>&#45;larized.  It will be sowed broadcast&#44; when plain&#44;<lb/> unpretending buildings&#44; not <sic>rivalling</sic> the magnificence of<lb/> the Temple in its outward magnificence&#44; but supplementing its national object&#44; shall<lb/> thickly fill the cities of Judea.  There Holy Writ<lb/> shall be read on Sabbaths and Holidays in the original&#44; translated and explained<lb/> in the vernacular&#45;&#45;Hence the Chaldaic paraphrases&#44; which<lb/> form a prominent feature in post&#45;biblical literature.  There<lb/> also some prayers of a common character shall be recited in a<lb/> language easily understood&#45;&#45;Hence the origin of the Hebrew<lb/> liturgy&#44; which in its essentials is substantially the same among<lb/> all Jews.  There meetings shall be held with great frequency&#44;<lb/> to enable persons of different pursuits in life to attend at one time<lb/> or at another&#45;&#45;Hence the practice of perusing a chapter from the<lb/> Torah on Mondays and Thursdays.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Such were the reforms advocated and carried out by<lb/> the men of the famous Keneseth Ha&#45;gedolah.  And thus<lb/> did they endeavoured to ward off decay from their religion<lb/> and people.  But more than that did our Sepherim<lb/> did for the perpetuation of Judaism.  They collected many of<lb/> the prophetic and hagiographal writings&#44; still in a<lb/> floating state&#59; redeemed shielded them from any any possible fear of<lb/> being lost&#44; and began the formation of the sacred canon&#44; which<lb/> is the fountain&#45;head of an exhaustless knowledge.  And an&#45;<lb/>&#45;xious that the spirit of the five books of Moses be preserved&#44;<lb/> they enacted rules and regulations according with suiting the changes in<lb/> the social and political state condition of our fathers.  To this Ne&#45;<lb/>&#45;hemiah had already set an example&#44; when in order to remove the temp&#45;<lb/>&#45;tation of trafficking with foreign merchants&#44; he command&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed that the gates of Jerusalem be shut from sun&#45;set<lb/> on the eve of the Sabbath to the following night.<lb/></p>
            <p>But to fully enter into the sentiments feelings which animated<lb/> the one hundred and twenty men&#44; who for very nigh<lb/> two centuries watched in turn over the interests of their<lb/> nation and country&#44; we must reflect on the maxims<lb/> which they never ceased to inculcated.  They are these&#58; &#34;Be<lb/> careful in judging&#59; raise many disciples&#59; and set up a peace for the<lb/> Law.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>I surmise that the President&#44; or the most influential<lb/> among the members of the Synod&#44; addressed his colleagues<lb/> with those aphorisms&#44; as a reminders of Solemn obli&#45;<lb/>&#45;gations.  He first recommended extreme caution in con&#45;<lb/>&#45;demning or acquitting the litigants.  The Judeans were<lb/> allowed the exercise of self&#45;government by Persian Kings.<lb/>  That prerogative carried with it the power of making issues such<lb/> ordinances as were conducive to the social meal&#44; and to the observance<lb/> of the faith.  The enjoyment of that privilege was naturally<lb/> prized above all things by a people so jealous as ours about<lb/> their rights.  But it became very imperative that individuals<lb/> vested clothed with authority should <sic>weild</sic> it with a thought<lb/> solely du directed to the triumph of justice.  A preju&#45;<lb/>&#45;dice&#44; or an error might prove doubly disastrous.<lb/>  It might expose the Jewish tribunal to contempt&#44;&#45;&#45;thus<lb/> demoralising the entire community&#45;&#45;and it might invite<lb/> the heathen foreigner as an arbitrator&#44; who&#44; taking advan&#45;<lb/>&#45;tage of internal disaffections&#44; would work the ruin of<lb/> the commonwealth.  You can now appreciate<lb/> the deep significance of the first maxim.  The<lb/> second&#44; which bid the wise Sopherim to educate<lb/> a large number of pupils and increase disciples&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>reechoed the noble sentiment&#44; once expressed by<lb/> the greatest of men&#44; when he exclaimed&#58; &#34;Would that<lb/> all the people of the Lord were prophets&#33;&#34;  Learning<lb/> shall not be confined to a few&#44; nor to a privileged<lb/> caste.  The humblest whom nature has endowed<lb/> with talents&#44; shall receive encouragement and<lb/> promotion.  Their acquirements shall be put to<lb/> the service of the national cause.  So thought<lb/> the far&#45;sighted members of a truly reformatory congress.<lb/>  During the first Temple&#44; priests and levites were<lb/> the custodians of the Law&#44; and they applied its<lb/> ordinances&#44; as cases arose&#44; in accordance with the oral<lb/> instruction of their preceptors.  But soon the<lb/> appointed sentinels became guilty of desertion.<lb/>  The cast the Torah behind their backs&#44; to rush headlong<lb/> after unlawful gain.  The prophets with their<lb/> fiery enthusiasm often burnt the faithless to<lb/> the quick&#44; and exposed their vices pollutions to public<lb/> disgrace.  But to save a people from destruction community from a moral decline more<lb/> is needed than simply to lay bare the vices of those<lb/> who are seated in high positions places.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Ezra and his synod understood appreciated this well truth&#44; therefore<lb/> they provided an extended recommended urged education&#44; an education reaching all classes<lb/> of society&#59; for an education much wider in its scope<lb/> than that once under the direction of priests or even of as imparted in the schools of the prophets.<lb/>  Colleges presided over by men of the people&#44; whose culture<lb/> and winning manners could induce the young willingly indiscriminately<lb/> to come and listen&#44; began their work in Judea&#44; agreeably to the<lb/> second injunction of the Keneseth Ha&#45;gedolah&#44; &#34;raise many<lb/> disciples&#34;.  But the third of their maxims is the<lb/> most important in its consequences.  The Sopherim<lb/> were to &#34;set up a fence for the Law.&#34;  Real wisdom<lb/> lies in reserving the facilities for guarding against the commission of<lb/> sin&#44; not in punish commensurately punishing sinners.<lb/>  The same system which sensible parents pursue in the<lb/> training of their children&#44; should be followed by legis&#45;<lb/>&#45;lators.  A vast deal of the evil which is brought con&#45;<lb/>&#45;stantly to light and creates scandal would be prevented&#44;<lb/> if a fence were set up for municipal or federal laws.<lb/>  Regarding Respecting the applicability of that aphorism to<lb/> the religious conduct standard of Israelites&#44; I may cite an<lb/> illustration which current events suggest.<lb/></p>
            <p>Moses and the prophets have emphasized the necessity<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>of keeping holy each seventh day of the week.<lb/>  That commandment does not exclude holiday wor&#45;<lb/>&#45;ship on other days.  We know&#44; on the contrary&#44; that<lb/> Rabbinically every morning and evening a public ser&#45;<lb/>&#45;vice ought to be offered.  But now a very weighty<lb/> question rises.  The Sabbath of Moses and the pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;phets is neglected by a large number of Jews&#44; who<lb/> do not meet their brethren in faith in a Synagogue<lb/> at any time during the week.  On the first day&#44;<lb/> however&#44; they are unoccupied&#44; not voluntarily&#44; but by<lb/> compulsion.  For&#44; that day is devoted  by a semi&#45;<lb/>polytheistic majority to a worship recalling the supposi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tious divinity of a man&#45;god.  Ought the leisure<lb/> imposed on the monotheistic minority be then devoted by the latter<lb/> to a convocation which will virtually become a substitute<lb/> for the Scriptural Sabbath&#63;  The Doctors who stand<lb/> in heir of the ancient Sopherim have to decide.  Were<lb/> I one&#44; I would if asked&#44; answer &#34;No&#34;; and base my refusal<lb/> on the ground that teachers in Israel must set up a<lb/> fence for the Law.  Tu unitedly sing the praises of<lb/> the Lord&#44; and hear pulpit exhortations is not only allowable&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>but becoming on a Sunday as on any day of the week&#44;<lb/> but when Israelites who do not otherwise assemble for<lb/> prayer and instruction request to have these on the same day and at<lb/> the same hours consecrated to prayer and instruction by<lb/> an anti&#45;Judaic church&#44; a consent would  be the lending of<lb/> a hand for breaking the Law.  It would be the gradual erasing<lb/> of the Decalogue from the memory of the next generation<lb/> and the paving of the way to <sic>apostacy</sic>.  Sunday services&#44;<lb/> as proposed&#44; are not a direct violation of the written sta&#45;<lb/>&#45;tute&#44; yet they are&#44; under circumstances&#44; an insidious enemy<lb/> of the Torah.  The disciples of the Sages&#44; who are con&#45; continue<lb/> &#45;scientiously wise faithful will raise a high fence to hinder the<lb/> approach of that foe.  They will never permit a con&#45;<lb/>&#45;vocation bearing likeness to the Sabbath&#44; upon Sundays.<lb/>  Oh&#33; may the sentiment which pervaded the sainted fathers twenty three<lb/> centuries ago&#44; when they established Synagogues&#44; be carried out by their successors.<lb/>  May the minor sanctuaries intended to preserve Judaism&#44; through the join in&#45;<lb/>&#45;vocations and mutual teachings of the believers in One uncreated God&#44; remain for<lb/> ever a rallying point to the children of our race.  May we learn there to<lb/> defend what Ezra the greatest of our Scribes&#44; and Nehemiah his zealous co&#45;<lb/>&#45;worker&#44; and all the men of the Keneseth Ha&#45;Gedolah guarded against destru&#45;<lb/>&#45;ction.  May the spirit of Judaism hover above dwell within us when we in our coming in and in our going out<lb/> of the house of our God Lord now and evermore.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
