<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF8_4</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff8_4_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff8_4_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff8_4_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff8_4_2v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 1 sheet<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For a funeral<lb/></p>
            <p>Some of the Hebrew Sages of old&#44; believing that<lb/> not a single letter of the five books of Moses can be<lb/> dispensed with&#44; ingeniously tried to discover a meaning&#44; not<lb/> expressed in the text&#44; in whatever&#44; according to their views&#44;<lb/> might seem superfluous.  I am free to acknowledge<lb/> that I do not approve altogether of such a system&#44; knowing<lb/> that it often occasions a straining of the literal sense.<lb/>  But on hearing of the decease of this our coreligionist&#44; I was<lb/> forcibly reminded of the teaching of those ancient Sages&#44; in<lb/> connection with the fifth commandment of the Decalogue.<lb/>  They thought that it might have been worded more<lb/> concisely in the original&#44; but that by saying &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Honor thy father and thy mother&#44;&#34; the heavenly Legislator<lb/> had in mind other beings entitled to respect&#44; not named in<lb/> the sentence&#44; but closely allied to ones parents&#59; such as&#44; for<lb/> instance&#44; the oldest son in the family.  Now&#44; I ho&#45;<lb/>&#45;nestly declare that in my experience&#44; derived from a per&#45;<lb/>&#45;sonal acquaintance with the congregation I have long<lb/> served&#44; I have not met with a better illustration of<lb/> the observance of that unexpressed ordinance of Holy Writ&#44;<lb/> them among the children of Mayer and Fanny Arnold.<lb/>  They have honored the eldest son in the household&#44; and<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>their deference has proceeded from a high apprecia&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion of his character.  They early learned that he had the<lb/> ability and the will to counsel and help and comfort those<lb/> with whom he had shared the good effects of maternal<lb/> care and paternal solicitude.  Endowed with a mental<lb/> acumen&#44; which showed him the full scope of fraternal<lb/> duties&#59; possessing a degree of culture which raised him<lb/> above the average of man in the mercantile walks of<lb/> life&#44; he could supply the place of his sainted father<lb/> and mother&#44; and he did become in the days of trial&#44; a<lb/> moral support to his younger sisters and brothers.<lb/>  That he acted his part nobly in that capacity&#44; the an&#45;<lb/>&#45;guish pictured on the countenances of relatives whom I saw&#44;<lb/> when the sad tidings of the demise arrived here&#44; testifies.  The<lb/> tears shed were drawn from the memory of deeds&#44; which fasten<lb/> still more closely the ties of nature.  But a family<lb/> grief is sacred&#44; I dare not intrude upon it.  They who<lb/> have lost a veritable friend in Simon W. Arnold&#44; would not<lb/> wish that I should harrow their feelings wit ha narrative<lb/> of events&#44; when his tender regard and affection were best evinced.<lb/>  But they will experience a melancholy satisfaction to hear<lb/> that his activity among his people in the city that beheld<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>his growth from childhood to a well <sic>developped</sic> manhood&#44;<lb/> is still kindly remembered.  For&#44; it is true&#44; beyond quest&#45;<lb/>&#45;ioning&#44; that when the defective system of dispensing alms<lb/> among the poor&#44; elicited the considerate thoughts of some lead&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing Jews in Philadelphia&#44; our lamented fellow&#45;believer labored<lb/> steadfastly in conjunction with others to bring about a fusion<lb/> of disconnected societies.  He would thus effectually relieve<lb/> the necessitous&#44; and hinder imposition.  His sagacity was pu&#45;<lb/>&#45;blicly recognized by his selection as the first President of the<lb/> United Hebrew Charities.  Occupying the chair two consecu&#45;<lb/>&#45;tive terms&#44; he brought to bear on the discharge of an exceed&#45;<lb/>&#45;ingly difficult and delicate task&#44; administrative abilities<lb/> of a high order.  Were it not that I deem it in compa&#45;<lb/>&#45;tible with our occasion&#44; so sorrowfully solemn&#44; to dwell on<lb/> details&#44; I would explain how his personal exertions detected<lb/> deception of a long standing&#44; and searched out the indigent of<lb/> too retiring a disposition to mingle with common mendicants.<lb/>  Doubtless&#44; what I leave untold&#44; will be supplemented by the<lb/> history and obituary acknowledgments of the aforenamed orga&#45;<lb/>&#45;nization.  But I may appropriately add&#44; that not alone<lb/> in that department was the advise of our lamented brother<lb/> efficacious.  It was sought after with advantage&#44; when the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Mutual Benefit Company&#44; mainly Jewish in its consti&#45;<lb/>tuency&#44; was about to be formed.  Its interests S. W. A. greatly<lb/> promoted&#44; hence I have heard many an Israelite regret his removal<lb/> to New York.  In him was met a sensible leader and coworker&#44;<lb/> and a well educated associate.  As to myself&#44; since our brother<lb/> exchanged the city of his earliest endeavours for another&#44; I have been de&#45;<lb/>&#45;prived of the opportunity to judge of his proceedings&#44; socially or bene&#45;<lb/>&#45;ficially.  Yet&#44; assurances which I have repeatedly received&#44; embolden me<lb/> to venture a sentiment&#44; which I earnestly hope will neither wound&#44; nor<lb/> give room to <sic>misapprehions</sic>.  It was the eager wish of my deceased<lb/> coreligionist&#44; that his offspring might cling to the belief in which he<lb/> was born and raised and in which he has died.  Led by that impression&#44; I<lb/> unhesitatingly responded to the call which demanded of me this mortuary<lb/> service.  He whose heart beat Jewishly&#44; should obtain the last tribute of respect&#44;<lb/> which the living can tender the dead&#44; from a brother whose heart also throbs with<lb/> love for the olden faith.  Let it me say it then.  It will be joy to me to learn<lb/> hereafter&#44; that a perfect identification outwardly&#45;&#45;in a manner comformable to Jewish<lb/> usages&#45;&#45;&#44; as well as inwardly in honor of Israel&#39;s God&#44; was effected among all who<lb/> belong to S. W. A.  The affectionate intercourse of relatives can bring it pass&#44;<lb/> &#38; to them I look with anxious anticipations....Oh Parent of goodness&#44; compassio&#45;<lb/>&#45;nate Lord&#33; forgive trespasses&#44; reward merits&#44; console the afflicted&#44; bring the erring<lb/> humbly to Thy footstool&#44; and let the spirit of an intellectual creature now stand&#45;<lb/>ing before Thy judgment seat&#44; be uplifted by angels to the realms of<lb/> unending happiness.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
