<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Mendes, H. P.</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx3FF11_26</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Mendes, H. P.</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes">Morais, Sabato</addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet></placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1885-07" source="" attested="yes">5 July 1885</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx3ff11_25_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx3ff11_25_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx3ff11_25_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx3ff11_25_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx3ff11_25_3_1r_stitched.tif"></graphic>
                                <graphic url="smbx3ff11_25_3_1v_stitched.tif"></graphic>
                                <graphic url="smbx3ff11_25_4r.tif"></graphic>
                                <graphic url="smbx3ff11_25_4v.tif"></graphic>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>1 page on 1 sheet<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Sunday 5 July &#39;85<lb/></p>
            <p>My dear Mr Morais<lb/></p>
            <p>Many thanks for your<lb/> letter&#8212;I understand the man<lb/> concerning whose burial I wrote<lb/> you&#44; was not circumcised&#44; but inquiry<lb/> is to be made as to whether this is so or not.<lb/></p>
            <p>The proof had not arrived<lb/> why my letter to you was sent off&#45;&#45;<lb/> I enclose them now&#8212;you need not<lb/> trouble to return them&#45;&#45;<lb/></p>
            <p>Dr Kohler may even yet <lb/> turn out conservative&#44; simply from the<lb/> fact that he is a most erratic genius&#44; and<lb/> writes&#91;insertion made by author&#93; without thinking of facts on behalf of reform<lb/> <del>upon</del> His radicalism is mischievous<lb/> unless answered&#8212;it then becomes laughable.<lb/> I hope Dr  <sic>Kohert</sic> will persevere.<lb/></p>
            <p>With regards &#91;&#63;&#93;<lb/>
                H. Pereira Mendes<lb/></p>

            <p>Thanks for slips returned.<lb/></p>

            <p>To The American Hebrew.<lb/></p>
            <p>Dr. Kohler  recently published in the <emph rend="italics">New<lb/> York Herald</emph> a sermon in which he made mis&#45;<lb/>statements &#44; unjust insinuations against orthodox<lb/> Judaism&#44; and by representing that the orthodox<lb/> Hebrews did not sufficiently exalt moral law&#44; <lb/>supplied a weapon useful to those who still<lb/> nourish a prejudice against our nation. I an&#45;<lb/>swered in the same columns&#44; in order that<lb/> something might be done to correct the mischief<lb/> where it was perpetrated&#44; though it was very<lb/> distasteful to bring forward such topics in the<lb/> Christian press. Dr. Kohler replied to me&#44;<lb/> again in the <emph rend="italics">Herald</emph>. Sooner than continue the<lb/> struggle in the secular press I ask to use the<lb/> columns of THE AMERICAN HEBREW&#44; which of<lb/> all the Jewish papers&#44; has given most space to<lb/> this controversy. Dr. Kohler divides his letter<lb/> into numbered paragraphs&#58;&#45;&#45;I treat them ac&#45;<lb/>cordingly&#58;<lb/></p>
            <p>1. As to my charge that Dr. Kohler&#39;s asser&#45;<lb/>tion&#44; &#34; I do not think that to eat pork or oysters<lb/> is a sin that can in any way compare with lying<lb/> or cheating&#44;&#34; was with its context&#44; as much as to<lb/> say that the orthodox Jews did think so&#59; and<lb/> my remark that such an insinuation might pre&#45;<lb/> judice orthodox Jews in the eyes of Christians<lb/> reading it in the Herald.<lb/></p>
            <p>Dr. Kohler in his answer admits he does &#34;not<lb/> deal with the moral views of &#39;his&#39; orthodox co&#45;<lb/> religionists&#44; and had not the least intention of<lb/> speaking disparagingly of their condition in<lb/> comparison with reform Jews.&#34; I thank him<lb/> for this admission. But he ends this paragraph<lb/> I as follows&#58; &#34;I did not only insinuate but said<lb/> explicitly in my discourse&#44; &#39;According to the<lb/> Talmudic maxim&#44;  it was a greater crime to eat<lb/> pork or oysters than to lie and cheat.&#34; Ordi&#45;<lb/>nary readers will infer that the Talmud makes<lb/> this direct assertion. It is not the case. Why<lb/> mislead people into thinking so&#63;&#45;&#45;and especially<lb/> Christians&#63;<lb/></p> 
            <p>Paragraph 2  he devotes to an ingenious but<lb/> more than faulty method of reasoning&#44; to prove<lb/> that the Talmud regards moral law as inferior<lb/> to ceremonial. He admits it &#34;knows absolutely<lb/> as far as the practical noun &#40;Halacha&#41; goes&#44; of<lb/> no distraction between moral and ceremonial<lb/> law&#44;&#34; but he argues it from the relative punish&#45;<lb/>ment&#44; and especially cites those &#34;upon which<lb/>stands the penalty of thirty&#45;nine stripes.&#34; As a <lb/> matter of fact this punishment was afflicted not<lb/> only for eating pork and oysters&#44; as the Doctor<lb/> states&#44; that is to say&#44; not only for infringement<lb/> upon ceremonial law&#44; but for infringement<lb/> upon certain moral laws also &#40;see Maccoth 13 a&#41;.<lb/> <emph rend="italics">Qui concumbit cum sorore su<del>d</del> cum ar<del>c</del>ita&#44; cum   a<lb/> m</emph><lb/> <emph rend="italics">materata&#44; cum sorore uxoris etc</emph>. The Doctor<lb/> also states that &#34;he who eats leavened bread on<lb/> Passover is guilty of extermination.&#34; This is<lb/> incorrect. The penalty is excision. &#40;See Exod.<lb/> xii.&#44; 15&#44;19&#41;. What the punishment of excision<lb/> means is doubtful.  R. Bechai in Biur Nattorah<lb/> has something to say about it&#59; so has Abarbanel<lb/> in his comment on Numb. xx&#44; 30&#44; where he<lb/> speaks of the difference of opinion among our<lb/> sages on this point&#44; and quotes half a dozen.<lb/> Rashi&#44; Maimonides and Nachmanides and others<lb/> have their opinions also. But whatever it is&#44; it<lb/> is a penalty not only for eating leavened bread<lb/> on Passover&#44; for not observing circumcision&#44;<lb/> &#40;Gen. xv.&#44; 11&#44;14&#41;; on the Day of Atonement&#44;<lb/> &#40;Levit.xxiii.&#44; 29&#44;30&#41;&#44; etc.&#44; that is to say&#44; not<lb/> only for infringement upon ceremonial laws&#44; but<lb/> for infringement upon moral laws&#44; &#40;see Levit.<lb/>xviii.&#44; 29;xx.&#44; 17&#41; &#94; &#91;Added by author in margin in ink&#58; Thus the same punishment is applied to breach of ceremonial <hi rend="underline">and</hi> moral law&#93;. Dr. Kohler&#39;s argument on<lb/> the punishment basis does not&#44; therefore&#44; apply<lb/> here. But it is most startling to find the Doctor<lb/> soberly intimating that orthodoxy ever placed<lb/> insufficient stress on moral law&#44; when he knows<lb/> that all the &#34;ten commandments&#44;&#34; the very pith<lb/> of the whole Torah in orthodox eyes&#44; refer to<lb/> moral law&#59; even the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi>&#44; by its sanctification of<lb/> a day for moral culture.<lb/></p>
            <p>Paragraphs 3 and 4. Says Dr. Kohler&#58; &#34;I<lb/> cannot share the fear of the reverend gentlemen<lb/> that the statement which he forced me to make<lb/> will nourish  prejudice.&#34; I did not force him to <lb/> make any statements. Everything he said or<lb/> wrote was said or written before I even took up<lb/> the pen or spoke. And he is wrong to trust too<lb/> much to Beechers and Newtons&#44; or the press.<lb/> They do not prevent some of the aristocratic<lb/> private schools being closed to Hebrew children&#44;. Or the expression of unfriendly and illiberal sen&#45;<lb/>timent too often heard by Hebrew merchants<lb/> from Christian lips&#44; or the intolerant sentiment<lb/> too often heard by Hebrew merchants from<lb/> Christian lips&#44; or the&#93; intolerant sentiment ex&#45;<lb/>pressed in society so frequently.<lb/></p>
            <p>Paragraph 5. The famous &#34;pork and oyster&#34;<lb/> phrase. Dr. Kohler may&#44; if he likes&#44; trace our<lb/> food laws to customs of the &#34;idol worshipping<lb/> priests of Babylon&#44; India and Persia.&#34; This<lb/> may suit the modern rationalistic school&#44; but it<lb/> does not suit those who do not subscribe to it<lb/> and who are so irrational as to ask how could<lb/></p>
                
            <p>HP Mendes 2<lb/></p>
            <p>Moses adopt heathen customs when he so con&#45;<lb/>stantly warns us against such&#44; and his whole<lb/> idea is to make us a distinct people&#63;<lb/></p>
            <p>In Leviticus&#44; chap.xx. 23 to 26&#44; we find the<lb/> food laws are given to separate us from  the Ca&#45;<lb/> naanite nations&#8212;other passages can be quoted.<lb/> Dr. Kohler asks&#58; &#34;Are they &#40;the dietary laws&#41;<lb/> wise sanitra&#91;editorial mark inserted to reverse order of r and a&#93;y laws&#63;&#34; I assure him they are&#44; and<lb/> I &#91;added in margin&#58; h&#93;<del>S</del>ope to add&#44; in due time&#44; a few words to the<lb/> opinions of those scientists who assert the wisdom of the laws he questions.<lb/></p>
            <p>Paragraph 6. Dr. K. remarks&#58; &#34; I do not wish<lb/> to monopolize enlightenment and progress for my<lb/> reformed brethren.&#34; This is all I asked. For<lb/> this admission I am really grateful.<lb/></p>
            <p>Paragraph 7. &#34;I am ready to give the quanti&#45;<lb/>tative majority to Rev. H. P. Mendes.&#34; This is<lb/> all I asked. For Dr.K. intimated that the or&#45;<lb/>thodox were in the minority. I am again really<lb/> grateful. He concludes by saying that if I am<lb/> &#34;so wonderfully proud of the religious condition<lb/> of my orthodox section&#44; &#34; he for his part humbly<lb/> prays &#34; that the spirit of deeper piety and holier<lb/> zeal may take possession of his &#94; people&#44; nay of &#91;in margin&#58; &#91;&#63;&#93;&#93; <lb/> our whole age&#44;&#34; etc.&#44; etc. What one thing has to<lb/> do with the other is not quite clear to me. I really do not understand the logical connection.<lb/> But then I am not one of the modern rationalistic<lb/> school&#59; I am only&#44; very truly yours&#44;<lb/></p>
            <p>H. PEREIRA  MENDES.<lb/></p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
