<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF2_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff2_1_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>For Noah 50<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  Noah&#44; the patriarch whose history<lb/> forms the main subject of this sabbath&#39;s section&#44; has<lb/> been variously represented&#44; according to the dif&#45;<lb/>&#45;ferent impressions which his character left upon<lb/> the minds of thinkers.  While some have drawn portrayed<lb/> him in very brigh the brightest colours&#44; others have described his<lb/> qualities&#44; as negatively virtuous.  In the course<lb/> of my reading&#44; I have found noticed that there were<lb/> Talmudists who admiringly compared Noah to<lb/> a vial of most precious perfume&#44; which loses none of<lb/> its fragrance though placed among decaying<lb/> matter &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> and others&#44; again that certain Rabbis&#44; disparagingly&#44; likened him to<lb/> a youth that who needs continual watching&#44; lest he<lb/> wanders far away from a straight path.  Con&#45;<lb/>&#45;tradictory as those opinions evidently are&#44; they neverthe&#45;<lb/>&#45;less claim support from the same Biblical sentence.<lb/>  I will quote it in its original and translate it<lb/> literally in the vernacular &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Noah a fast man&#44; was perfect<lb/> in his generations&#59; with God Noah walked&#34;.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>In that I think&#44; that in the opening verse of our portion&#44; I think&#44; that<lb/> the scriptures aim to skew the patriarch in a<lb/> threefold manner.  Having previously told us of the wickedness which ran riot &#38; a corruption wide spread &#38; irredeemable they first point to him as<lb/> one who practically conformed with the principles<lb/> of rectitude&#44; at the same time that they tell us having previously told us<lb/> of the wickedness which ran riot&#44; and of a<lb/> corruption wide spread and irredeemable &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Under ordinary circumstances&#44; when the rules of<lb/> probity are regarded by society&#44; he that follows<lb/> a right path course&#44; without the slightest deviation&#44;<lb/> still deserves respect&#44; because self interest is an ill<lb/> adviser&#44; and means may be discovered to evade<lb/> the punishment of human courts of Justice.<lb/>  But a firm adherence to probity&#44; when no one<lb/> cares for honesty&#44; must challenge commendation<lb/> in a supreme very high degree&#44; and that praise&#44; I hold&#44; is<lb/> unquestionably due to the subject of our present<lb/> consideration.  For&#44; at no period of history we<lb/> meet with a state&#44; when every restraint upon<lb/> brutal passions had been universally cast aside<lb/> as in the days of Noah.  From the most sacred au&#45;<lb/>thority we learn &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>that evil alone governed men&#39;s imagination&#44;<lb/> that cruelty and depravity had ceased to be<lb/> a crime.  For the world &#91;Hebrew&#93; translated &#34;&#91;&#63;&#93;lence&#34; im&#45;<lb/>plies&#44; in Hebrew&#44; the commission of every act which<lb/> is atrociously bad.  Superior must then have<lb/> been the mind which&#44; while the whole earth was<lb/> filled with Chamas reeking with inequity&#44; still remained perfectly pure.<lb/>  Extraordinarily Strong&#44; beyond conception&#44; must have been the will<lb/> which resisted all the temptations of evil sur&#45;<lb/>&#45;roundings.  Therefore the Bible adds to its<lb/> first description of Noah&#44; a second delineation.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  It brings sets before us a being whose mo&#45;<lb/>&#45;rals remained unpolluted in his generations&#44; not&#45;<lb/>&#45;withstanding that he must necessarily have come<lb/> in constant contact with men persons lost to shame.  The<lb/> misdeeds of his contemporaries proved that with them<lb/> might was right.  His conduct proved&#44; on the<lb/> contrary&#44; that integrity had become his standard&#44;<lb/> and from it no enticement could make him swerve.<lb/>  To express this idea emphatically&#44; our text concludes<lb/> with a third and more significant portrait description&#58;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; that is&#44; Noah acted as if an<lb/> associate whom he revered&#44; and whose good will he<lb/> wished to retain&#44; accompanied his every step&#44;<lb/> and never suffered him to proceed alone without that the same the benign escort.  That soul<lb/> elevating thought&#44; held the patriarch steadfast<lb/> in his uprightness.  Had he need of counsel&#63;<lb/>  He turned to his right&#45;hand and immediately ob&#45;<lb/>&#45;tained it.  Did he fear his own frailty&#63;  He found<lb/> himself supernaturally sustained in virtue.  He<lb/> avoided the shares of vice and the meshes of crime&#44;<lb/> because he moved onward under the guidance lead of God.<lb/>  To the patriarch of the flood may therefore deser&#45;<lb/>&#45;vedly apply the sentence of the Royal Pslamist&#58;<lb/>  &#34;Blessed is the man who standeth not in the<lb/> way of sinners.&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>So far I have set brought to view the individual through<lb/> whose offspring the world was repeopled after the<lb/> deluge had swept away the inhabitants.  I be&#45;<lb/>&#45;lieve that I have represented him faithfully&#44; being<lb/> biased by none of the opinions advanced either in his<lb/> favor or against him by Talmudists and by critics.<lb/>  I have followed as my guide the plain words of Holy Writ.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Yet&#44; willing to stand by all that I have said&#44;<lb/> I notice in Noah a character only relatively good.<lb/>  The sacred pages which bear testimony to his right&#45;<lb/>&#45;eousness fail to record a single occurrence in which<lb/> his virtues shone brilliantly.  A legend exists&#44; tending<lb/> to prove his fidelity to a high mission received&#44;<lb/> but even that vague tradition would simply shows demonstrate that<lb/> he undertook to warn the a guilty people and preach<lb/> penitence&#44; after he had been specially directed to<lb/> do so by the Lord of mercy.  We search in vain<lb/> for an incident in his life reflecting lustre upon<lb/> it&#44; casting around it a halo of sanctity.  We<lb/> all honor a just man&#44; we all join in the lau&#45;<lb/>&#45;dation bestowed upon one who is absolutely perfect<lb/> as a moral being&#44; but we are forcibly attracted<lb/> towards him&#44; whose natural instincts are loving kind&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness and mercy charity&#44; whose words and actions reveal a<lb/> heart overflowing with charity sympathy&#59; a heart that yearns<lb/> after truth&#44; and which is ready to lay itself bare<lb/> even to the thrusts of the sword&#44; not to temper<lb/> with falsehood.  We admire and reverence him whose<lb/> devotion to a the noble cause he has espoused&#44; is enduring and<lb/> unbounded.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>In short&#44; Noah commands our esteem&#44; but the<lb/> patriarch of Ur Chasdim&#44; to whose rising our<lb/> Parasha refers towards its closing passages&#44; is the<lb/> illustrious personage towards whom we turn with feelings<lb/> akin to adoration.  Many like the son of Lemech<lb/> would have built an altar and laid upon it of&#45;<lb/>&#45;ferings in abundance&#44; when rescued from a uni&#45;<lb/>&#45;versal destruction&#44; but few&#44; like Abraham&#44; would<lb/> have torn themselves from parents&#44; the from the earliest and dearest asso&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciations&#44; and wander abroad to proclaim the name<lb/> of the only existing God he believed in.  Many<lb/> would serenely bear the trial of one year&#39;s con&#45;<lb/>&#45;finement in a floating vessel&#44; when comforted<lb/> by the thought that the sp ship is a certain<lb/> means of deliverance&#44; but few would face dangers<lb/> and jeopardize life in the defence of right.  Their<lb/> generosity towards strangers&#44; magnanimity towards<lb/> offenders&#44; kind solicitude for the unfortunate&#44;<lb/> deep concern for the sinful&#44; humility of depart&#45;<lb/>ment&#44; affection for all living&#44; regard for the dead&#44;<lb/> a faith ever active and ever glowing.  Yes&#44; such<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>such are were the sublime trials that place the son<lb/> of Terah in the foreground of Biblical history.<lb/>  Compared with him&#44; Noah must need ranks lower.  The<lb/> flaming blazing fire prepared meant as the legend narrates&#45;&#45;to<lb/> consume the overthrower of idols&#44; because a resplendent<lb/> luminary which eclipsed lesser lights.  We may<lb/> not hesitate to declare with an ancient writer&#44; that<lb/> Noah was just and perfect in his own generations&#44; but<lb/> that in the days when Abraham had arisen went forth on his mission he might have<lb/> passed unnoticed &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Both patriarchs acknowledged the Sovereign Creator.<lb/>  Both were strong believers&#44; but one offered a service con&#45;<lb/>&#45;tinuous and effective&#44; the other an occasional worship&#44;<lb/> yielding no ultimate advantage result.  One mounted high<lb/> and stood as a beacon light to heathens&#44; the others could<lb/> not correct the falsities of the idolaters of his age.  Of one it is recorded narrated<lb/> that he planted an orchard&#44; drawing thither his fel&#45;<lb/>low men&#44; that they might be taught the ways of the<lb/> Lord &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Of the other it<lb/> is chronicled&#44; that he planted a vineyard&#44; the fruit<lb/> of which&#44; though unintended by him&#44; brought shame<lb/> and sorrow to his household and the human family.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Abraham will remain to the end of time a shining<lb/> example of piety&#44; because his religiousness was enriched<lb/> with the qualities of the heart that endear its posses&#45;<lb/>&#45;sor to all humanity.  Noah will not be chosen as<lb/> a model&#44; because his character which represents the<lb/> principles of rectitude&#44; does not exhibit likewise traits<lb/> in which <sic>genialness</sic> and far reaching love for mankind<lb/> stand forth prominently. forth  Progeny of Abraham<lb/> the Hebrew&#33; rejoice in your father&#44; glory in the found&#45; restorer<lb/>&#45;er of that belief through which all the families of<lb/> the earth shall be blessed.  Let those who deny<lb/> him the most stupendous of all discoveries&#44; jeer at<lb/> our boasting in the man of Ur Chasdim.  Benan&#44;<lb/> the famous critic who casts Jewish history in a mould<lb/> of his own making&#44; changing and cutting off and ad&#45;<lb/>ding at pleasure to carry out suit his preconceived&#44; or<lb/> rather&#44; prejudiced notions&#59; the world wide renowned Ernest<lb/> Benan&#44; unaided unsupported by any historical support evidence&#44; asserts that<lb/> Monotheism was an instinct&#44; not even of a high order&#44;<lb/> with all Semetic races.  Max M&#252;ller&#44; the celebrated profes&#45;<lb/>sor of the science of languages at Oxford refutes Benan&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>and contends that Abraham while approaching with his intellect the heights of truth must have received<lb/> a Divine inspiration&#44; when that which amidst a pagan world<lb/> he attained the confirmed his understanding of the One Supreme Creator<lb/> and Ruler.  But neither the skepticism of the first&#44;<lb/> nor the ingenious admission of the second can affect<lb/> a people who have heard repeatedly psalmists and<lb/> prophets proclaim the truth verity that because of the merits<lb/> of Abraham&#44; the friend of God&#45;&#45;his seed became imperishable.  For if though<lb/> we do have through Noah&#44; a community of extract&#45;<lb/>&#45;ion with the children of Japeth and of Shem&#44; the<lb/> blood of the lineal descendant of Shem courses through<lb/> our veins.  Let that it quicken us to righteousness&#59; to<lb/> deeds of self denial&#44; so as to preserve undefiled the<lb/> creed of Abraham&#44; for it does yet demand of us<lb/> sacrifices.  Let us offer them upon the altar set up<lb/> by his spotless hands.  Let us prove ourselves worthy<lb/> of such an ancestry&#44; that we may hasten the day<lb/> when God will bring to pass his heavenly promises&#44;<lb/> as petitioned for predicted by Micah&#58; &#34;Thou wilt show thy<lb/> truth to Jacob&#44; Thy benevolence to Abraham&#44; as thou<lb/> didst swear to our fathers in the old days of old&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
