<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF1_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff1_2_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For Sabbath Rosh Codesh Elul.<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="2"/>
                <p>A Rabbinical legend tells us&#44; that when Adam<lb/> saw that the days grew perceptibly shorter&#44; he<lb/> was seized with dread.  He imagined that&#44;<lb/> because of his sin&#44; the world would soon be<lb/> enshrouded in darkness&#44; and change into &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> the chaotic state&#44; whence it issued forth.<lb/>
                    We have learnt that the sun moves only in part<lb/> from us&#44; to favor longer with its benign rays the<lb/> inhabitants of other lands.  We do not experience<lb/> a fear of impending destruction as this season draws<lb/> nigh.  Yet&#44; methinks that the quicker sinking<lb/> of the light of day in our horizon&#44; ought to awaken<lb/> serious reflections.  The month of Elul&#44; bringing<lb/> night upon us&#44; with a speedier motion&#44; should<lb/> serve as a reminder of our downward course in the<lb/> race of life.  Not to fill us with dismay&#44; but to<lb/> call our latent powers into action.  To fit us to<lb/> shine brilliantly hereafter in higher regions&#44; while the<lb/> light of our earthly existence&#45;&#45;like the sun in Autumn&#44;<lb/> inclines fast towards its setting.<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="3"/>
            <p>I do not know&#44; whether I stand alone in my<lb/> conjecture&#44; but I hold that the name itself of<lb/> the month&#44; whose entrance we have just greeted<lb/> with psalmody&#44; might be regarded as&#44; suggestive<lb/> of the conduct we ought to follow during that space<lb/> of time.  Elul&#44; bearing analogy to <hi rend="underline">Yalul</hi>&#44;<lb/> from which the term &#34;Yelalah&#44;&#34; &#40;wailing&#41; is derived&#44; might<lb/> signify that an Israelite&#44; should devote this period<lb/> of his year&#44; in lamenting the long days spent<lb/> in the pursuit of variety&#44; in lamenting the occasions&#44;<lb/> he allowed to glide by unimproved&#44; whereas he<lb/> might thereby have ennobled his character by<lb/> deeds of goodness and truth&#59; in lamenting those<lb/> circumstances&#44; which incited him to cast aside<lb/> duty&#44; to gratify the passion of or the whim of<lb/> the <del>moment</del> hour.  And in recalling events&#44; which<lb/> cause the expression of regret&#44; feel deeply that<lb/> man is false to his real interests&#44; when he listens<lb/> to the dictations of the flesh&#44; rather than hearken<lb/> to the dictates of the spirit.<lb/></p>
                <p>Yes&#44; my Brethren&#44; the feeling must correspond<lb/> with the utterance&#44; ere we can hope that<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="4"/>
            <p>the acknowledging of our backslidings&#44; may avail<lb/> us in the future.  The sentiment that it is un&#45;<lb/>&#45;manly always to <sic>yeild</sic> to the tyranny of sin&#44;<lb/> to voluntarily bend under the yoke which vice<lb/> imposes&#59; that sentiment&#44; I say&#44; must prevail&#44;<lb/> before we are capable of righteous resolves.<lb/></p>
            <p>And to arouse such feelings and such sentiments&#44; the<lb/> shrilling comet will resound&#58; Tomorrow evening will<lb/> its blasts echo forth.  Shall I interpret in advance<lb/> the meaning they convey&#63;  The <hi rend="underline">Shofar</hi> speaks so<lb/> to every Israelite.  &#34;Be true to thyself.  Act as it behooves<lb/> a being endowed with free&#45;agency.  Thou must own<lb/> that all thy actions are seen by the Omniscient God.<lb/>  <del>Now</del> They have been registered with exactness.  Now the<lb/> figures are drawn in the heavenly book&#44; and the infal&#45;<lb/>&#45;lible accountant is about to sum up.  One month<lb/> is given to make the merits exceed the demerits.  To<lb/> <sic>fretter</sic> away that time away is to seal one&#39;s condemnation&#44;<lb/> that is&#59; to meet with <del>&#91;&#63;&#93;</del> God&#39;s displeasure&#44; and its<lb/> attendant&#45;&#45;unhappiness&#34;.<lb/></p>
                    
                    <pb n="5"/>
            <p>I invite you all&#44; my Brethren&#44; to hear the voice<lb/> that so addresses us&#44; and to <del>make</del> respond thereto<lb/> by prayer.  It is my duty&#44; as it affords me<lb/> pleasure&#44; to see you congregate in our honor to our<lb/> Lord&#44; and join in entreaties for a year good and<lb/> propitious altogether.  But in craving for your<lb/> attendance here during the probationary month&#44; I drop<lb/> a word of Rabbinical <del>counsel</del> teaching&#44; which I bid you remem&#45;<lb/>&#45;ber&#44; as you enter our minor sanctuary.  It runs thus<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;Great is the<lb/> power of <hi rend="underline">Teshubah</hi>&#44; which averts from man&#44; immi&#45;<lb/>&#45;nent misfortune.&#34;  <del>Tshe</del> Tishabah in English is<lb/> translated penitence&#44; but we Hebrews know that<lb/> it means &#34;a return&#34;.  Dear coreligionists&#33;  Loud<lb/> petitions&#44; and the mentioning of ancestral piety&#44; will<lb/> prove of no value&#44; unless when here&#44; we determine<lb/> to return&#44; when there&#44; in the busy walks of life&#44; to<lb/> return to the path we have abandoned&#44; to the<lb/> way of justice and truth.  Then will we show<lb/> that our utterances are the offspring of a broker and<lb/> contrite spirit&#44; which God never despises.<lb/></p>
                    
                    <pb n="6"/>
            <p>A Jew who is not as jealous of his moral standing<lb/> as he appears zealous in his devotions&#44; treads the<lb/> way of perdition.  Praise be to God&#58; our belief<lb/> does not proclaim&#44; that we may purchase indulgences<lb/> and absolutions by the recital of a series of sup&#45;<lb/>&#45;plications.  No.  &#34;Teshabah and &#34;Maasim tobim&#34;<lb/> righteous deeds&#44;&#34; they can procure for us an easy<lb/> occasion to the realms of bliss.  They are our tutelary<lb/> angels &#91;Hebrew&#93; pleading for us in the hour<lb/> of judgment.  Heartfelt orisons can also bring<lb/> about a reconciliation between us and our offended<lb/> Parent&#44; provided they be accompanied with Teshubah.<lb/>  You all <del>are</del> have read&#44; that the people of Nineveh &#34;cried<lb/> to God mightily&#34;&#44; but you have also learnt&#44; that<lb/> when referring to the pardon obtained&#44; Holy Writ<lb/> states&#44; that &#34;God saw their works&#44;&#34; intimating<lb/> the by what agencies they warded off danger.<lb/>  And those instruments of salvation&#44; I earnestly<lb/> exhort you to seize&#44; while you possess the strength<lb/> to hold them&#44; &#38; the capacity to wield them in a<lb/> manner&#44; that it will <del>procure</del> secure for you an <del>everlasting</del><lb/> existence of abiding happiness.<lb/></p>
                    
                    <pb n="7"/>
                    <p>Dear Brethren&#33;  I stand before you this morning&#44;<lb/> like a physician&#44; who wishing to save his patient<lb/> from some threatening disease&#44; administers in time&#44;<lb/> a mild but efficacious medicament.  I offer to<lb/> you Teshabah&#44; which if you will accept this early&#44;<lb/> will deliver you on the day of reckoning.  Your<lb/> promptness&#44; will be ascribed to your merit.  It<lb/> is always a proof of wisdom in man not to postpone<lb/> an important undertaking.  Follow the same course<lb/> towards God&#44; as you would towards mortals.<lb/>  I believe that to keep up your character reputation<lb/> in commercial circle&#44; you make ready to meet your<lb/> obligations before the payment is due.  To show to<lb/> Him on whose will your life and the life of your children<lb/> depend that you desire to retain His love&#44; approach Him<lb/> early with a heart sincerely repentant&#44; with a steadfast<lb/> resolve to cast off impunity&#44; and put on righteousness.<lb/>  You must employ the month of Elul&#44; in reviewing<lb/> the past&#44; and if you discover that evil example<lb/> or vicious surroundings have led you astray&#44; muster<lb/></p>
                    
                    <pb n="8"/>
            <p>courage to overcome the difficulties by whom you are beset<del>ting your</del><lb/> <del>course of life.</del>  In the language of the Biblical<lb/> section we have <del>read</del> perused this Sabbath&#44; let me say&#58; though<lb/> your own brother&#44; the son of your mother&#44; or your son&#44;<lb/> or your daughter&#44; or the wife of your bosom&#44; or your <del>bosom</del> dearest friend<lb/> entice you&#44; consent not.  But resist allurements that you may<lb/> observe to do what is right in the eyes of the Lord your<lb/> God.  For then you will deserve to be called children<lb/> to the Lord.  So <del>illustrate this passage</del> do they who<lb/> taught us truth illustrate this passage.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> you deserve <del>to be styled what</del> the appellation the Bible  gives you&#44; so long<lb/> only <del>that</del> as you act <del>as</del> like obedient children towards their loving<lb/> Father.  And the Meshaic&#91;&#63;&#93; Sages adds. &#34;Highly honored favored have<lb/> the people of Israel been <del>by</del> when they were styled &#34;children of God.&#34;<lb/>  May you continue to deserve that name&#44; by a demeanour<lb/> which will draw towards you the respect of the noble&#45;<lb/>minded in the community&#59; <del>and whereby you will sanctify</del> For by honoring your religion<lb/> <del>in public</del> you will honor its heavenly <del>Giver</del> Donor&#44; and<lb/> exalt the people from whom you sprung&#44; and to whom&#44;<lb/> I hope and pray&#44; you will ever remain attached<lb/> and <del>whose welfare</del> among whom you will ever <del>promote</del> labor for<lb/> the cause of righteousness and truth.<lb/></p>   
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
