<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF6_38</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_38_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_38_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_38_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff6_38_2v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 1 sheet<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>a funeral oration<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            <p>A sad office is that which a minister of religion&#44; must&#44; on an occasion<lb/> like the present&#44; necessarily perform.  And I&#44; my sympathising friends&#44;<lb/> do feel it as such.  Yet&#44; I shrink not from the melancholy duty.  For&#44; if<lb/> it is incumbent on every Israelite to afford the dead an honorable burial&#44; he<lb/> that has devoted his life to religion the service of God&#44; should accompany man&#39;s mortal re&#45;<lb/>&#45;mains to their final home&#44; amid the solemnity of prayer.<lb/></p>
            <p>But the funeral rite&#44; always mournful&#44; fills my hear this day with<lb/> poignant grief.  O Noble youth&#33;  How soon the silvery cord that bound<lb/> thee with a world promising happiness&#44; was cut asunder&#33;  And<lb/> with thee&#44; what glowing anticipations&#44; what joyous hopes are laid into the<lb/> silent grave&#33;  Aye&#58; Bot the son and his loving parents&#44; stretching<lb/> their vision as far as human eye can see reach&#44; beheld a future upon earth serenely bright.<lb/>  Marcus Steppacher had scarcely attained his fourteenth year&#44; and his<lb/> mental development seemed to keep pace with his physical growth.<lb/>  For&#44; comely he was&#44; of graceful appearance&#44; of manly form&#59; and<lb/> his address bespoke him a gentleman&#44; his studious habits betokened<lb/> his refined task.  But that which I discovered and delighted in&#44; is the<lb/> disposition of that goodly youth to piety.  Ten months ago he had<lb/> stood before the Congregation&#44; and avowed his intention to become a<lb/> steadfast adherent to the law he read in public.  But different<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>from many of his coevals&#44; to whom that ceremony conveys no meaning&#44;<lb/> he seemed appeared to have been fully impressed with its importance.  From<lb/> the Sabbath he completed his religious majority&#44; he attended the worship<lb/> with commendable regularity.  His decorous demeanour in the house<lb/> of God might well be offered to others as a model.  Was I then<lb/> too sanguine&#44; when I&#44; prospectively&#44; judged him a faithful son<lb/> of Israel&#63;  An ornament to the community of his brethren&#63;  Has<lb/> not the wisest of men written that &#34;even a child maketh it known<lb/> by his doings&#44; whether his work will be pure&#44; and whether it will<lb/> be right&#63;  And is parents&#59; did they lack sound foundations&#44;<lb/> when they built upon the character of their beloved Marcus the fondest<lb/> hopes&#63;  What expectation would have been deemed rash inconsiderate&#44; when<lb/> predicated upon the religious and moral principles&#44; which guided already<lb/> that precocious lad&#63;  &#34;A plant&#44;&#34; say our Sages&#44; &#34;exhibits from<lb/> its incipient stage&#44; the effect which time will produce thereon.&#34;<lb/>  Alas&#33; that a puff gust of an adverse wind should have rooted out that<lb/> tender plant&#33;  A few days&#44; only a few days he that lies lifeless<lb/> before us&#44; was buoyant and vigorous.  His father prided himself<lb/> in the qualities he possessed.  She that gave him birth&#44; looked upon<lb/> his countenance and rejoiced.  But now....gloom overspreads<lb/> their minds.  Unutterable sorrow wrings their souls.<lb/>  Weep ye bereaved ones&#44; and let the tears of all these sympathising<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>friends blend with those that gush from your eyes.  There is none<lb/> but feels that your loss is very grievous.  How I did pray<lb/> that you might be spared it.  But after all&#44; I would be &#91;&#63;&#93; to<lb/> my charge&#44; if I advised giving vent to uncontrollable sorrow&#59;<lb/> to cherishing it long in your bosom.  No&#44; my duty and my own feelings<lb/> dictate that I deliver to you the message of God &#34;Among those that<lb/> are nigh unto me&#44; will I be sanctified.&#34;  Show&#44; my friends&#33; by<lb/> pious resignation to the will of your Maker&#44; that you are worthy of being<lb/> called his near and dear.  To obey His ordinances&#44; you have&#44; I know&#44;<lb/> made sacrifices.  He has now desired to put your faith to a still greater<lb/> trial.  Be equal to it.  Reason with yourselves&#59; consider that<lb/> your child&#39;s existence was&#44; as your own is&#44; in the hand of the Omni&#45;<lb/>&#45;potent.  He entrusted it to you&#44; until it was ripe for heaven.<lb/>  Let this be your comfort&#44; that you did not blight its growth.  That<lb/> your endeavours had been directed to improve the faculties with which<lb/> the Almighty had endowed your fondly loved Marcus.  That you<lb/> returned him to the Lord of all flesh in perfect innocence.  Does not<lb/> that reflection bring calm to your perturbed spirits&#63;  How many parents<lb/> yearn for that feeling&#44; but they cannot obtain it&#44; because their children&#39;s<lb/> deportment betray their improper training.  Cheerfully&#44; Gladly would<lb/> they have early surrendered at an early period what you have been asked to <sic>yeild</sic>; for&#44; then<lb/> our offspring will stand as their accusers on the day of judgment.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>But apart from that assuaging thought&#44; look around&#44; that you<lb/> may see and appreciate the blessings yet left for your enjoyment&#59;<lb/> dear children&#44; attached relatives to whom you are attached&#59; and friends.  True&#44; your circle has<lb/> been somewhat narrowed&#44; but the chain of affection is drawn<lb/> more closely together.  You will henceforth cling faster<lb/> to the survivors&#44; and to further arch others&#39; happiness will be<lb/> your study and delight.  The untimely loss you have sustained&#44;<lb/> may be the opening of a fountain of living&#45;water at which many<lb/> will slake their thirst and revive.  For&#44; it is after we ha ourselves<lb/> have suffered&#44; that our sense of commiseration becomes keener&#44; and we<lb/> long to benefit the unfortunates&#44; and solace the afflicted.<lb/></p>
            <p>Oh&#33; may the sweet memory of the departed be the agency of so much<lb/> good.  The means by which you will acquire a name and a glory<lb/> among the living&#59; an exalted place amid the blessed&#44; and the<lb/> light of God&#39;s countenance everlastingly.  For&#44; that is the goal<lb/> we all should strive to reach&#59; when pillowed on the bosom<lb/> of eternity&#44; we shall contemplate with a spiritual<lb/> eye Him that is the source of life&#44; and from by whose <sic>inspeakable</sic><lb/> goodness they whom death has separated&#44; will be reunited<lb/> unto the end of time.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
