<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF1_13</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_12_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_12_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_12_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_12_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_12_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_12_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_12_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_12_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_12_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_12_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_12_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff1_12_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>7 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For a Bar Mitzvah<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Rap &#34;Blessed are ye that sow<lb/> seeds beside all waters&#34;  Yes&#58; it is a merit and<lb/> a happiness to have searched and found the soil<lb/> which promises to reward our labor with a plentiful<lb/> harvest.  It is a merit&#44; because God&#39;s design in<lb/> giving existence to intelligent creatures was that by<lb/> a wise cultivation their longing souls might be gra&#45;<lb/>&#45;tified.  It is a happiness&#44; because the true enjoy&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment of life consists in the consciousness of having<lb/> proved ourselves useful to the world.  Behold now&#44;<lb/> my Brethren&#33; the cultivating ground I have chosen.<lb/>  A streamlet runs through it&#44; which neither the winter&#45;<lb/>frost&#44; nor the summer heat dries up.  Say then&#44; ought<lb/> I not to gather an abundance of fruit&#63;  I should certainly<lb/> taste some delicious products of my own tillage.  But<lb/> though I was fortunate in the selection of a well&#45;<lb/>&#91;&#63;&#93;gated spot&#44; I have not been equally successful<lb/> in planting in a direction where the rays of a genial sun might<lb/> always strike in&#44; quicken the seeds and cause<lb/> them to fructify.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>But to drop all figures of speech&#44; I will say.<lb/>  The Synagogue is the fittest place wherein to offer our<lb/> youths instruction.  The halo of sanctity encircling<lb/> the edifice&#59; the word of inspiration enshrined therein in its oracle&#44;<lb/> the imposingness of the worship&#44; all the surroundings<lb/> tend to create an impression.  But if Therefore the<lb/> teaching given therein&#44; may be compared likened compared in the me&#45;<lb/>&#45;taphorical language of Isaiah&#44; to the sowing of seeds<lb/> in a moist&#44; and hence suitable ground for cultivation.<lb/>  But if preaching within these hallowed walls is like<lb/> furrowing a virgin soil&#44; and casting in the precious<lb/> seeds&#44; it will nevertheless prove ineffectual&#44; when<lb/> parental example&#44; which acts as the beams of a vivifying<lb/> sun&#44; is wanting.  How many have been those upon<lb/> whom I looked as trees planted in the courts of our<lb/> Lord&#44; full of sap&#44; affording every hope of a healthful and vigor&#45;<lb/>&#45;ours growth&#44; whose degeneracy I now have oc&#45;<lb/>&#45;casion to lament&#33;  Fathers and mothers jointly<lb/> worked to eradicate what I endeavoured to root<lb/> deeply in.  Let me rejoice that in the instance<lb/> I am about to cite&#44; the parents&#44; will not&#44; I verily<lb/> believe&#44; pluck off with a rough hand what I tend with<lb/> care.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>The presence of the parents of our Bar Mitzva at each<lb/> Sabbath service&#44; in the dwelling of prayer&#44; and their absence<lb/> from the marts of trade&#44; answers well for Judaism my earnest efforts.<lb/>  To me it stands I interpret it as an assurance prognostic that he who celebrated<lb/> his religious majority in this Synagogue&#44; will bend latter<lb/> his steps even when manhood shall have given him<lb/> a mind and a will to act independently.  So great&#44;<lb/> I trust&#44; will be the force of constant religious example.<lb/>  Some may perhaps differ with me because of a<lb/> circumstance unusual on an occasion of this nature.<lb/>  They may contend that because our young brother did<lb/> not conform to the practice of reading a portion from <lb/>the Scriptures&#44; his conduct betrays indifference to<lb/> the Law and the precepts.  Should there be any among my hearers who<lb/> hold that opinion&#44; let me assure them that it is<lb/> erroneous.  The cause motive for a departure from<lb/> a customary ceremony in the present case I know well<lb/> and appreciate.  But speaking more in general&#44;<lb/> I will boldly assert that the sacred object connected with the perusal of the Law has been <sic>wofully</sic> misdirected&#44; that the sacred object connected with time&#45;honored usage of<lb/> the reciting of the Torah by the Bar Mitzva has lost its<lb/> significance&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>and might as well be altogether abolished.<lb/>  Whereas formerly it signified denoted a willing assent to the<lb/> commands embodied in the book of revelation&#44; and with<lb/> which the Jewish Hebrew lad had previously been made acquainted&#44;<lb/> now it means nothing.  No&#58; it does mean some&#45;<lb/>&#45;thing&#44; but mischievous.  It means that the memory<lb/> has been strained&#44; and forcibly compelled to retain certain<lb/> words not one of which is understood.  Even worse.<lb/>  It means that the time which might have been usefully<lb/> devoted to learn the duties which a Jewish child owes his<lb/> God and his people&#44; has been frettered away.  It means<lb/> that instead of studying the language in which we<lb/> address the Almighty&#44; and which is vitally essential<lb/> for us to preserve&#44; a mere drilling intended for a display<lb/> has been indulged in.  Thank God&#44; honorable except&#45;<lb/>&#45;ions may be &#91;&#63;&#93; out&#44; and those parents cannot be<lb/> sufficiently commended who impart solemnity to the occasions of<lb/> their sons&#39; confirmation&#45;&#45;to use a modern though inap&#45;<lb/>&#45;plicable word term&#45;&#45;by combining with the instruction<lb/> of a chapter from the Holy Writ&#44; the tuition<lb/> of higher and holier obligations&#59; even of the<lb/> living spirit and not of the dead letter.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>But the records stored up in my mind&#44; could<lb/> show instances in which a youths were led by fear of<lb/> parental displeasure to learn by rote&#44; and from English<lb/> characters&#44; unintelligible sentences.  It has been my<lb/> sad experience to see such a one present themselves before<lb/> the holy ark one Sabbath&#44; and never again meet their<lb/> fellow&#45;believers in the house of the Lord.  That is<lb/> what has bard bred defection&#44; that is what has made<lb/> room and given a plea for changes unending&#44; and<lb/> destructive.<lb/></p>
            <p>My dear Bar Mitzv&#225;&#33;  Had you been able to allowed to<lb/> gain the knowledge habitually acquired by those<lb/> who attain your age&#44; I would not have valued it&#44; un&#45;<lb/>less accompanied by a familiarity with the sense of the<lb/> scriptures&#44; and the dictates of religion.  Those whom<lb/> the Lord has appointed as guardians of your health and<lb/> welfare deemed it expedient advisable not to ask that you should<lb/> labor for that purpose.  But they doubtless wish<lb/> that you may endeavor to understand what is<lb/> demanded at your hands as a son of Israel&#59;<lb/> a child of the covenant and that having thoroughly understood it&#44; you<lb/> may summon moral courage to stand by it at all<lb/> hazards.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>You enjoy an inestimable advantage over &#34;Some of<lb/> your coevals in the religious consistency of your<lb/> parents.  For their desire that you should remain<lb/> an intelligent adherent of the ancestral belief is not<lb/> a vague thought&#44; an abstract idea.  It takes a real<lb/> form.  It is supported by an all important example.<lb/>  Their observance of the Sabbath.  You perceive&#44; my<lb/> brother&#33; that I lay much stress upon the latter ordinances.<lb/>  And the reason is apparent.  The seventh day is asso&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciated with public worship&#44; and thus with instruct&#45;<lb/>&#45;ion&#44; while both are the very essence of life&#45;giving element preserving Judaism.<lb/>  Profit then by what has been granted you&#44; and procure<lb/> thus to me the merit and happiness derived from having<lb/> sown seeds beside waters in a fruitful soul.  This is the spot I have<lb/> chosen for my young brothers&#39; culture.  Let me implant<lb/> sentiments of veneration for the Law you have publicly<lb/> blessed this Sabbath&#44; and may all fathers&#39; conduct<lb/> be the sun rays that will quicken and fructify<lb/> my planting.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
