<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF19_3</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_3_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_3_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_3_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_3_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_3_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_3_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_3_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_3_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_3_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_3_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_3_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_3_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>50</p>
            
            <p>About the proposition of establishing<lb/>
                Hebrew free schools North &#38; South<lb/>
                of Philadelphia.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> This Talmudical saying rendered in plain English&#44; would<lb/> read so&#58; School&#45;houses are a sure corrective&#59; what seems<lb/> worthless may be thereby converted into real excellence.<lb/>  A truth it is&#44; my Brethren&#44; which none will assent to<lb/> more readily than a people who live in America&#44; and<lb/> in that State of the Union teeming with institutes of<lb/> education.  For by these does Pennsylvania offer her<lb/> inhabitants and the world at large advantages intrin&#45;<lb/>&#45;sically more valuable than even by the riches of her exhaust&#45;<lb/>&#45;less minerals.  I never see the satchel or the strap&#45;<lb/>&#45;ped primers carried by children whose parents arrived here<lb/> poor and untutored&#44; without rejoicing in the anticipation<lb/> of the glories reserved for the country of school&#45;houses.<lb/>  Yet&#44; I cannot help feeling&#44; as a Jew&#44; that what is<lb/> taught at the desk and on the slate falls short of<lb/> my people&#39;s wants.  Sometime it has&#44; indeed&#44; a mis&#45;<lb/>&#45;chievous tendency&#44; cropping out of the guileless de&#45;<lb/>&#45;meanour of our little ones.  Sentences from volumes<lb/> read in the interest of the prevailing religion&#44; and songs<lb/> bending the heart to a belief we dare not entertain&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>are repeated within our hearing.<lb/></p>
            <p>It would be idle to cry against the practice of blending<lb/> sectarianism with secular instruction&#44; and complain<lb/> of the wrong done to a portion of the community that<lb/> help to keep up materially and morally the stand&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing of our public seminaries of learning.  Measures<lb/> ought to be devised to redress what is constitutionally<lb/> unjust&#44; but our voices are feeble and separate&#44; while<lb/> the voices of the church advocates are waxing power&#45;<lb/>ful and they sound in concert.  Enough evidences<lb/> have we received of late of the controlling force brought<lb/> to bear on the retention of things favoring denomina&#45;<lb/>&#45;tionalism&#44; to damp our hopes of checking that force.<lb/>  At all events&#44; we Israelites cannot rest satisfied with<lb/> only the knowledge imparted promiscuously.<lb/></p>
            <p>Our children may through it become cultured and<lb/> polished&#44; but not impressed with the grandeur of<lb/> the Mosaic legislation.  They may uphold with<lb/> dignity the character of citizens of the Republic&#44; but<lb/> they will not cherish withal the ancestral faith.  The<lb/> spirit of the Hebrew laws and the beauties of the Hebrew<lb/> language must be early unfolded before their eyes&#44; if<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>we mean in earnest that our offspring enroll them&#45;<lb/>&#45;selves to the service of the One God.<lb/></p>
            <p>This sentiment gave origin to the Hebrew Education<lb/> Society School.  My hearers are well acquainted<lb/> with the history of that institution&#44; with the struggles<lb/> it had to sustain&#44; with the sinking of the means lent<lb/> to prop it up.  That in its palmiest days it failed<lb/> to command popularity can scarcely be a cause of astonishment.  To the students of English&#44; facilities<lb/> more extensive and indiscriminately given&#44; were offered<lb/> in buildings open to the public.  The idea of keeping<lb/> aloof from the rest of the community&#44; lest too close<lb/> a contact influence us injuriously&#44; never met with the<lb/> concurrence of our people.  In many instances&#44;<lb/> no doubt&#44; indifference as to the result of mingling<lb/> every day among non&#45;Israelites and listening to unjewish<lb/> doctrines&#44; held back the patronage solicited&#59; but in<lb/> others the honest opinion that our special need could<lb/> be provided for in a less expensive manner&#44; prevented<lb/> a general cooperation.  That need&#44; my Brethren is about<lb/> to be supplied in a way that should call to its aid&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>all who have the permanence of Judaism in this<lb/> country at heart.<lb/></p>
            <p>The Education Society School has been made a centre<lb/> whence the knowledge of our belief and of the holy<lb/> language will proceed in various directions.  Reduced<lb/> by circumstances to a primary school with regard<lb/> to the tuition of the vernacular&#44; its chief aim will<lb/> be to afford the inmates of our Foster home and Orphan<lb/> Asylum religious instruction&#44; and to protect the<lb/> children of our race from the schemes of a propaganda<lb/> by drawing them North and South of our city<lb/> to places where Hebrew and Biblical lore will be<lb/> imparted.  The plan by which to raise the<lb/> necessary funds is not yet matured&#44; but I thus betimes<lb/> appeal to my brethren&#44; notably to those whose name<lb/> does not figure in the list of contributors to the Edu&#45;<lb/>&#45;cation Society&#44; to respond to the call as soon as<lb/> made and further with their mite&#44; which all can<lb/> and should give&#44; an endeavour essential to our distinct<lb/> preservation.  To act up to the maxim of our Sages<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> as I have rendered it.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Verily&#58; when I contemplate the increasing defection<lb/> among the humble classes of my people I am<lb/> seized with unutterable forebodings.  To them I have<lb/> been brought up to look for the nurturing of Judaism<lb/> into vigorous health.  When the Talmudists recom&#45;<lb/>&#45;mended special care to be bestowed on the children of the<lb/> poor&#44; as upon the promoters of religion &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; they summarized the history of the past.<lb/>  For from the obscure hovels of the needy burst forth<lb/> a light which illumined Israel.  Teachers&#44; poets and<lb/> philosophers sprang up from lowliness.  I feared nothing<lb/> so long as men not enervated by a luxurious life stood<lb/> by the old standard.  I felt sure it would not be made<lb/> to trail the ground.  But great is now a days the desertion&#44;<lb/> and greatly to be decoded by reason of the veil of<lb/> ignorance which darkens the intellects once so bright.<lb/>  It must be rent aside&#44; and the instrument wherewith<lb/> to tear it is religious training.  Not the mere<lb/> knowledge of words that catechisms contain&#44; and<lb/> which are soon blotted from memory&#59; not even that<lb/> of the ritual chanted after an approved of style&#44;<lb/> which people mistake for learning&#44; but the understanding<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>of the sacred tongue in its Grammatical and philological<lb/> construction&#44; of our Biblical and post&#45;biblical history&#44;<lb/> enabling the rising generation to appreciate what was<lb/> accomplished by their predecessors&#44; and how all the<lb/> vicissitudes we underwent&#44; led&#44; under Providence&#44; to<lb/> our continuance as missionaries of the grandest truths.<lb/>  It may be considered arrogant on my part to offer<lb/> a gratuitous criticism&#44; but because I am fully alive<lb/> to the necessity of saving Judaism in America by<lb/> proper schooling&#44; I venture upon a remark.  Hitherto<lb/> the method followed by most teachers has been faulty<lb/> in the extreme&#44; certainly not calculated to inspire<lb/> love for the Scriptures&#44; nor interest for the language<lb/> in which they were handed down.  A cold and mecha&#45;<lb/>&#45;nical imparting cannot arouse enthusiasm.  I remember<lb/> having heard one fully thoroughly qualified to communicate rare<lb/> information say that he labored like a journeyman&#44;<lb/> in accordance with the pay.  I admit that the<lb/> remuneration which the instructor of Hebrew receives<lb/> is generally so inadequate&#44; as to dampen the ardor<lb/> wherewith he may have undertaken his vocation.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>But the reflection that more than upon the preacher the<lb/> moulding of our children&#39;s minds depends on him who daily<lb/> gives &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;precept upon precept&#44;<lb/> line upon line&#44; a little here&#44; and a little there&#34;; that<lb/> reflection should keep up unquenched within the heart<lb/> of my coworkers&#44; the preceptors of Israel&#44; the fire of zeal.<lb/>  I go further&#44; and recommend that&#44; recognizing the want<lb/> of a change for the better&#59; they would&#44; as with one<lb/> consent&#44; discountenance a profitless practice&#59; that&#44; when<lb/> asked by parents to prepare their sons for the occasion<lb/> of their being for the first time called to the Law&#44; they<lb/> would point out the futility of the task&#59; I mean the devo&#45;<lb/>&#45;ting of months to the wearisome effort of learning by<lb/> rote a chapter&#44; rather than to the all&#45;important<lb/> object of gaining an insight into the annals&#44; or ordinances<lb/> of Judaism.<lb/></p>
            <p>And now I cannot dismiss the subject without alluding<lb/> to a Philadelphia institution&#44; venerable in age&#44; which<lb/> has been and can yet be instrumental in accomplishing<lb/> good.  The Sunday School was not intended to<lb/> supersede the tuition of Hebrew.  No one would have<lb/> felt more loth to foster that idea&#44; than the model<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Jewess who originated that weekly meeting of the<lb/> young offspring of her people.  But forty years ago<lb/> the number of our coreligionists in this city was small.<lb/>  Scarcely any opportunity could be offered for the cultivation<lb/> of our literature&#44; while constant intercourse with non&#45;<lb/>Israelites&#44; without a counteracting element&#44; foreboded<lb/> evils for the cause to which alone Rebecca Gratz was<lb/> wedded.  She then sought to form a centre round<lb/> which our little ones might gather&#44; and be reminded<lb/> by some simple recitations&#44; by a prayer by a hymn&#44;<lb/> by the rehearsing of the ten commandments&#44; or the creeds&#44; and<lb/> more than all by unrestricted association&#44; that they belonged<lb/> to a distinct race&#44; having a distinct mission and destiny.<lb/>  It was not the amount of learning gained&#45;&#45;confessedly<lb/> scanty&#45;&#45;that she looked for&#44; but the moral influence that<lb/> periodical assemblage exercised.  Who can be so bold<lb/> as to assert that it was ineffectual&#63;  I might show<lb/> that from it some&#44; whose home was destitute of any token<lb/> of Judaism&#44; drew strength to resist the allurements of<lb/> the Christian church.  But time has worked<lb/> mutations demanding a different system from the old&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>and he would be reprehensible who oppose its appli&#45;<lb/>&#45;cation.  Very probably&#44; if the decision at which the<lb/> majority will arrive is that Sunday mornings be set apart<lb/> for Hebrew tuition and the oral explaining of Holy Writ&#44;<lb/> the Sunday&#45;school attendance will be lessened&#44; but neither<lb/> the Superintendent of that in the Northern portion of our<lb/> city&#44; nor that of the Southern section will regret the<lb/> issue&#44; when assured that it may lead to the spread of sound<lb/> learning&#44; and with it to a stricter observance of the laws.<lb/>  Still&#44; a sense of justice&#44; resting on personal knowledge&#44;<lb/> impels me to say with the regard to the first&#45;names&#44;<lb/> that she has introduced improvements challenging ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;proval&#44; that the little ones over whom she watches&#44; are<lb/> not negatively <sic>benefitted</sic>&#44; but positively instructed on what<lb/> tends to familiarize them with the eventful past of<lb/> Israel&#44; and to a certain extent with the <sic>the</sic> language<lb/> rightly deemed an essential feature in the education of<lb/> our sons and daughters.  Hence&#44; it would&#44; according to my<lb/> judgment a questionable wisdom to overthrow what is a means<lb/> though humble&#44; to a righteous end.  I sincerely pray that<lb/> our heavenly Father&#44; whom we all wish to serve by our actions&#44; may<lb/> be our guide&#44; so that only what is a glory to His name and a blessing<lb/> to His people may proceed from the residue of Israel whose home is Philadelphia but whose<lb/> interest is identified with that which bonds the outcast of Judea together in one indissoluble&#44; eternal<lb/> covenant.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
