<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF29_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff29_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff29_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff29_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff29_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff29_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff29_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff29_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff29_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff29_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff29_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff29_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff29_1_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 3 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>14</p>
            
            <p>For Sabbath Haazinu<lb/>
                about the dogma of resurrection<lb/>
                connected with an address to a Bar Mitzvah.<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33; The sentence with which our young brother&#45;&#45;the<lb/> Bar Mitzvah&#45;&#45;concluded the portion he read from the Law&#44;<lb/> has been considered by Talmudical authors&#44; as one of the proofs<lb/> of a bodily resurrection.  I shall explain their argument<lb/> with great brevity&#44; adding a few remarks&#44; elucidating of the<lb/> subject.  Not to discuss  in any manner&#44; the character of<lb/> the dogma itself&#45;&#45;accepted by our nation at large as an<lb/> article of faith&#45;&#45;but simply to point out where it receives<lb/> support from Holy Writ.  You will have observed<lb/> that God speaking of His own absolute Omnipotence&#44; says<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> the real sense of which passage is the following&#58; &#34;See ye now&#44;<lb/> O house Israel&#33; since you have experienced numberless vicissitudes&#44; that<lb/> I&#44; I am He who doeth all things&#44; having a no co&#45;workers with me&#44;<lb/> I cause to die and make alive&#44; I wound and I heal&#44; and no<lb/> power can deliver a being out of my hand&#34;.  The Rabbis<lb/> reason thus&#58; Inasmuch as we are shown here&#44; the opposite<lb/> actions by which the Deity wishes that his omnipotence be<lb/> tested&#44; we should explain his words agreeably to their in&#45;<lb/>&#45;tended application&#44; and as common sense suggests.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>The Almighty is described as uplifting from and relieving from pains<lb/>&#45;&#45;I wound and I heal&#45;&#45;.  This contrary wording of the Divine power&#44;<lb/> must surely be felt by the same creature.  The tool cannot<lb/> mean that the Lord&#44; gives one occasion to suffer illness&#44; and another<lb/> the opportunities to recover his health&#59; for&#44; the contrast would<lb/> not then be so apparently striking.  Besides the phrase<lb/> would have read differently.  I chasten man with disease&#44;<lb/> and I help man in the bed of sickness&#44; would in all likeli&#45;<lb/>&#45;hood&#45;&#45;have read been the language chosen.  But &#34;I wound and I heal&#44;&#34; refers undoubtedly<lb/> to the doings of the Lord towards the same being.  We<lb/> met with a phrase parallel to this in Job&#44;&#45;&#45;a book<lb/> possibly written or compiled by Moses himself&#45;&#45;&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;He woundeth&#44; and His hands do heal&#34; As in that<lb/> instance the whole context clearly indicates that the effects<lb/> of the contrary actions&#44; is experienced by one individual&#44;<lb/> so it must evidently be in the case under our present con&#45;<lb/>&#45;sideration.  Now&#44; if it is so with regard to that<lb/> part of the sentence&#44; perused by our young brother&#44;<lb/> it must necessarily be so likewise&#44; respecting the<lb/> other part&#44; which immediately precedes it.  &#34;I cause<lb/> to die&#44; and I make alive&#44;&#34; must signify that God that grants<lb/> a new corporeal existence&#44; to him whose body had already perished.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>This doctrine this evolved from the sentence in Deuteronomy<lb/> which I have quoted&#44; is presented still more pointedly<lb/> to our views by in the prayer of Hannah at the sanctuary.<lb/>  She exclaims &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;the Lord causeth<lb/> to die&#44; and maketh alive&#59; He bringeth down to the grave&#44; and<lb/> bringeth up again.&#34;  Very pos probably the utterance of the overjoyed mother<lb/> is a mis metaphor&#44; exhibiting with much force he altered<lb/> condition.  She compares her former state&#44; when destitute of<lb/> a child to the solitude of the grave&#44; and her having given birth<lb/> to a son&#44; to a resuscitation.  Yet&#44; the simile would<lb/> not have suggested itself to her mind&#44; had the belief in<lb/> a resurrection&#44; been a thing unknown altogether in Jud among<lb/> her people.  This argument has been&#44; logically&#44; advanced<lb/> to refute certain objections raised by the opponents of the<lb/> dogma.  The latter contend that the beautiful apostrophe<lb/> of Isaiah &#34;Arise and sing ye that dwell in the dust......<lb/> the earth shall cast out the dead&#44;&#34; and the terrifically grand<lb/> vision of Ezekiel&#44; when he sees the dry bones in the valley<lb/> put on new sinews&#44; a new flesh&#44; and a new spirit&#59; or any<lb/> similar diction&#44; is to be understood symbolically.  That it is generally<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>a figure denoting the exaltation of the Hebrew race&#44; after<lb/> having been reduced to the lowest ebb of degradation.<lb/></p>
            <p>But the defenders of the doctrine&#44; admitting the correctness<lb/> of the interpretation&#44; claim nevertheless that our figurative<lb/> speaking is always a reproduction of objects in nature&#44;<lb/> or of abstract ideas notions of which the mind bases a conception.<lb/>  Thus&#44; for example&#44; we liken a man&#39;s strength to that of<lb/> the lion&#59; because we know that that animal possesses<lb/> great bodily vigour&#59; or we say that a horse has the velocity<lb/> of the wind&#44; because we can form an notion idea of the rapidity<lb/> of the air in motion&#59; but if neither the lion nor the air<lb/> existed&#44; the comparison would be an unintelligible jargon.<lb/>  Consequently when the prophets draw a parallel between<lb/> the elevation of our people and the uprising of deceased<lb/> bodies&#44; they must have believed in the possibility of a resur&#45;<lb/>&#45;rection.  And further to prove that the dogma was embodied<lb/> in our religion&#44; the its advocates cite the narratives in the<lb/> book of Kings&#44; where Elijah and his successor Elisha are<lb/> reported as having restored a child to life.<lb/></p>
                <p>I said at the outset&#44; that I do not intend to enter into the<lb/> merits of the question itself.  For&#44; I fear as I proceed&#44; difficulties al&#45;<lb/>&#45;most insurmountable would encompass me around&#44; and<lb/></p> 
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>instead of making the way clearer to others&#44; I might my&#45;<lb/>&#45;self become entangled involved into a maze.  for not u like the<lb/> blessed belief in the immortality of our souls&#44; does that of a bodily<lb/> corporeal resurrection&#44; find ready acceptance in human reason&#44;<lb/> nor do the writings of inspiration lend as such <sic>as</sic> much efficient help<lb/> in our researches after that truth.  We must mainly fall back<lb/> for support upon faith&#44; and the traditions of the fathers.  We<lb/> must deem it sufficient to know that nothing is impossible<lb/> to the Maker of heaven and earth.  We should indeed rest con&#45;<lb/>&#45;tented with the answer of a Rabbi of your to a skeptic of<lb/> his time &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;What had not existed at<lb/> all&#44; was brought into existence&#59; may it not happen<lb/> that what had once been a living creature&#44; may be restored<lb/> to its primitive state&#44; through the Omn illimitable powers<lb/> of the Deity&#63;&#34;  In fact the compilers of our liturgy have<lb/> placed based the creed of the resurrection on the Omnipotence of the<lb/> Lord.  The second benediction of our most important prayer&#44;<lb/> the Amidah&#44; commences so &#34;Thou art mighty for evermore&#44;<lb/> O Lord&#44; Thou reverest the dead.&#34;  And after having enumerated<lb/> the divine mercies bestowed on all the living&#44; it concludes.<lb/>  &#34;Who is like unto Thee&#44; Lord of mighty deeds&#44; and who can be com&#45;<lb/>&#45;pared unto Thee&#44; King who causest to die&#44; and who makest alive again&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Our ritual which&#44; whatever modern critics may write to the contrary&#44;<lb/> dates from many centuries back&#44; as represents the religious<lb/> views entertained by Ezra and his synod&#44; and carries with it<lb/> weighty authority&#44; confirming what Israel has accepted and<lb/> transmitted as a dogma of their faith.<lb/></p>
            <p>I have concisely said all I desired to explain for the general<lb/> information&#44; and but specially to draw therefrom a short<lb/> lesson designed for our young brother&#44; the Bar Mitzvah.<lb/>  My dear little friend&#33;  It would be very unkind in me to<lb/> dampen your joy by any allusion to melancholy events.  But<lb/> standing&#44; as you do this day&#44; at the threshold of a new career&#44;<lb/> you must receive hear words of counsel as well as encouragement&#44;<lb/> you have reminded us&#44; by your reading&#44; of one of our creeds&#59;<lb/> the resurrection of the body.  She who is now resuscitated<lb/> in spirit.  She who has learnt above&#44; more than we can<lb/> ever hope to understand while here below&#44; exhorts you<lb/> to adhere to the faith which Our people have inherited.<lb/>  From it she derived comfort&#44; and in it she longs&#44; that<lb/> you&#44; her beloved child&#44; may live happily.  With maternally<lb/> sweet accents she speaks to you of the beautiful laws of our<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Bible&#44; of the rules of kindness it inculcates&#44; of the principles of charity it<lb/> instills&#44; of the forgiveness it promises those who amend their<lb/> errors&#44; and she asks that you will not be willing to cast<lb/> off the olden religion&#44; because all it contains&#44; is not accessible<lb/> to our finite minds.  For if you will but study the vast<lb/> amount of practical knowledge it imparts&#44; you will receive<lb/> strength and stay for long years to come&#44; even till you shall<lb/> rejoin the blessed departed in the high heavens.  Attend then to the<lb/> instruction&#44; proceeding from sainted lips.  The abstract question<lb/> as to the manner in which it will please god to reward our<lb/> actions&#44; cannot affect in the least our relations as social<lb/> children&#44; as parents&#44; as citizens&#59; either as social beings&#44;<lb/> or as Israelites.  All nature proclaims that the Almighty<lb/> is wise and good.  And in the section&#44; a portion of which you<lb/> recited&#44; it is written &#34;a God of truth&#44; without inequity&#44; just<lb/> and upright is He&#34;.  That should prove the anchor of our<lb/> salvation&#44; who tossed up on the waves of <sic>harrassing</sic><lb/> doubts.  He who cares for the tiniest creature&#44; that moves<lb/> on earth&#44; will not forsake those he endowed with an intelligent<lb/> and immortal soul.  We may confidently leave to Him<lb/> how best to remunerate us for our deeds.  Certain that the<lb/> compensation will be according to the strictest justice&#44; and<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>equal to our deserts.  May your conduct&#44; my dear young<lb/> brother&#44; be always such that it will secure the approval of the<lb/> Almighty&#44; the respect of the good among the community&#44;<lb/> the increased affection of your father and relatives&#59; and the<lb/> delights arising from having led a life of usefulness and<lb/> of righteousness.  And let suffer me to finish with the regard<lb/> of God to the ancient leader&#44; who was to tread a new<lb/> career.  &#34;Let not the book of the Law depart from thy<lb/> mouth&#44; but meditate therein by day and by night&#44; so<lb/> that thou mayest keep to do all which is written in it&#44;<lb/> for&#44; there wilt thou make thy way prosperous&#44; and thou wilt<lb/> act intelligently.  Behold&#33;  I have commanded thee&#44; be<lb/> strong and of good courage&#44; be not dismayed nor terrified&#44;<lb/> for the Lord thy God is with thee&#44; withersoever thou shalt<lb/> go.&#34;  So may it be.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
