<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF8_13</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1889-01" source="" attested="yes">1889</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_13_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_13_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_13_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_13_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_13_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_13_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_13_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_13_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_13_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_13_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_13_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_13_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 6 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>150</p>
            
            <p>On the refuse of Galecian Hassidim<lb/>to accept Baron De Hirsch&#39;s proposition<lb/></p>
            <p>to establish secular &#38; industrial schools.<lb/>
                &#47;89<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>A Rabbinnical legend in connection with our fore&#45;<lb/>&#45;fathers&#39; state of mind&#44; when pursued by the Egypt<lb/>ptians&#45;&#45;as told in our Prashah&#45;&#45;fittingly applies&#44; in a moral sense&#44; to the con&#45;<lb/>&#45;dition of the Jews of our times.  The authors of a Midrash&#44;<lb/> arguing upon certain expressions of Moses&#44; supposes conclude that<lb/> some of the liberated slaves&#44; upon seeing their mas&#45;<lb/>&#45;ters rushing after them&#44; while before them a sea<lb/> was raging&#44; thought of surrendering themselves at once<lb/> to slavery &#91;Hebrew&#93; and others&#44; again&#44; were determined to purposed to rashly<lb/> venture into the swelling waves.  &#91;Hebrew&#93; In both cases<lb/> a cooler judgment would have suggested a dif&#45;<lb/>&#45;ferent resolve.  To return to bondage&#44; after the<lb/> experience of untold sufferings&#44; was to deliberately<lb/> meet go in quest of a slow death&#59; to plunge into surging bil&#45;<lb/>&#45;lows&#44; rather stand one&#39;s ground than he be directed by the heavenly pillars was to surely sink<lb/> out of sight into a whirlpool.  The archprophet<lb/> arose equal to the emergency and by his authority calmed the troubled spi&#45;<lb/>&#45;rits.  Not backward to a voluntary thraldom but forward to freedom&#44; not backward into downward but<lb/> a voluntary bondage into an abyss thraldom&#44; but forward to freedom under glory&#44;<lb/> the wise rule of Providence guidance&#44; the ideal people&#44; cho&#45;<lb/>&#45;sen to a purpose sublime end&#44; must ever proceed.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Brethren.  We do need beyond the power of expression&#44;<lb/> a Moses to exercise a blissful influence blissfully exert his influence over the<lb/> two camps into which&#44; as in the emergency exigency &#91;&#63;&#93; &#91;&#63;&#93; in the legend pictured<lb/> on our Parasha section&#44; Israelites are now unhappily divided.<lb/>  Ages of dire oppression persecution have done but too effect&#45;<lb/>&#45;ually with many of us their baneful work.  They<lb/> could not&#44; of course for certain&#44; rob Jews of talents&#44; which are<lb/> inborn with the descendants of legislators and poets&#44;<lb/> but they have crushed out of them a wish to ren&#45;<lb/>&#45;der those talents communally and nationally useful.<lb/>  They Political and social ostracisms have aroused the mischievous thought&#44; that<lb/> salvation to Israel&#39;s creed&#44; lies only in the isolation enforced by<lb/> an oppressive gentilism.  The unavoidable consequence<lb/> of such a belief conviction&#44; we are shown in the determined opposition<lb/> to progressive learning in general by a countless<lb/> number of our coreligionists&#44; scattered throughout<lb/> the countries of the old world.  They themselves<lb/> rivet the fetters&#44; which cruel masters have for&#45;<lb/>&#45;ged.  &#34;Secular knowledge is the ally of sin&#44;&#34; so<lb/> they cry whom Moses sought to elevate&#44; as a<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;a people wise and intelligent&#34;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  A people spiritually exalted.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Look Search for the proofs of that celestially designed<lb/> Ask them to prove that superiority&#44; and you<lb/> will with anguish of mind distance their spirit&#44; vastly you will detect instead a self&#45;willed inferiority.<lb/>  Thus to write in characters of the languages spoken by persons<lb/> of another faith&#44; is treason to the law of Sinai in the<lb/> eyes of millions.  They will use employ a conventional mode<lb/> of writing peculiar to themselves&#44; which may have<lb/> served a great purpose in olden days&#44; but which<lb/> breeds prejudice in our times.  In parts of Europe and in<lb/> Asia and in Africa Jews have their own exclusive cha&#45;<lb/>&#45;racters for common usage&#44; thus strengthening the cur&#45;<lb/>&#45;rent idea of the necessity of a an enjoined separation from the com&#45;<lb/>&#45;munity at large in every possible direction.  Having once<lb/> in my possession a book in Arabic&#44; I requested<lb/> an Eastern Rabbi who was paying me a visit&#44; to<lb/> explain its nature&#59; he acknowledged his ignorance.<lb/>  The rich literature of Islamism was to him a sealed book.  Yet&#44; though our medieval authors<lb/> may have used for convenience sake Hebrew characters&#44; as I am told by men who know&#44; it was<lb/> Yet in Arabic have our Grammarians and Lexico&#45;<lb/>&#45;graphers&#44; our philosophers and Talmudists in the<lb/> middle ages&#44; composed works which immortalized<lb/> their names.  Gentiles study such in colleges and<lb/> universities&#59; Israelites in Arabic&#45;speaking countries&#44; consider it<lb/> an offence to God even to learn the Arabic alphabet.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Who that thinks aright does not feel a deep<lb/> tinge sense of shame&#44; mounting up his face countenance when remem&#45;<lb/>&#45;bering that some ten years ago&#44; Sir Moses Montefiore&#44;<lb/> whose name will charge with &#34;reform&#34; tendencies&#44; had<lb/> the &#91;&#63;&#93; of money gold which he had sent to Palestine<lb/> for the founding of secular schools&#44; returned to Rams&#45; England&#63;<lb/> &#45;gate To accede to the wishes of the Baronet was to<lb/> promote an intercourse between the young in Israel<lb/> and the Mohammedans&#44; and cause an abandonment<lb/> of our ancestral belief.  In the segregation of a<lb/> mental slavery&#44; those men of our race see the only<lb/> salvation of means for preserving Judaism.  But what Judaism forsooth&#44;<lb/> not of the Bible&#44; which is a solemn hymn to know&#45;<lb/>&#45;ledge and wisdom&#44; not of the Sages even.  A Supersti&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion it may be&#44; religion never&#44; so long as it shuns<lb/> light.  I look back to the history of Talmudism<lb/> and clearly perceive that its authors personages who figure therein conspicuously were acquainted<lb/> not simply with the languages of the regions they<lb/> dwelt in&#44; but with sciences&#44; as far as they were then cul&#45;<lb/>&#45;tivated.  I come down to lager ages&#44; and whenever I<lb/> meet in the famous Rashi of the 11th century French<lb/> terms&#44; by which the great expounder sought to elucidate his text&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>or in Obadiah of B&#91;&#63;&#93; of the XIVth XVth century&#44;<lb/> Italian words to make his meaning intelligible&#44; I<lb/> discover that their Jewish contemporaries must have spoken understand&#45;<lb/>&#45;ingly the languages of their native lands.  Who<lb/> would dare to ch accuse those too two commentators<lb/> of fostering heresy&#44; because they followed approved of other stu&#45;<lb/>&#45;dies besides the Law and traditions&#63;  When they<lb/> lived&#44; France and Italy were not a Republic or<lb/> a constitutional monarchy&#44; tolerant&#44; liberal.  Feudalism<lb/> in one shape or the others till held sway&#44; and the Jew<lb/> was conditioned politically situated then worse perhaps that his coreligionists of<lb/> the XIXth century in Russia or Roumania.  But<lb/> in spite of an systematic position&#44; almost universal proscription&#44; the Jew of the<lb/> ghetto learned and taught&#44; when the haughty Barons<lb/> in their luxurious castles could not sign their own names.<lb/>  But a few Yet&#44; what violent oppression hatred had failed to accomplish&#44; a calm&#44; &#91;&#63;&#93; calculating &#91;&#63;&#93; system of degradation did the two centuries preceding the middle of the XVIIIth&#44;<lb/> inshrouded our people in a mental darkness as dense<lb/> as the atmospheric one by which Egypt was plagued.<lb/>  When Joseph II of Austria endeavoured to dissipate it&#44;<lb/> Israelites&#44; in unused to light&#44; protested.  The brightness<lb/> of the sun of progress hurt their vision.  They might become so<lb/> dazzled as to lose sight of the star of faith placed&#44; as a<lb/> they fancied&#44; for a guidance in their narrow horizon.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>In vain Hertz Wessels&#45;&#45;the noble&#45;heartedminded Hebraist of Hamburg&#45;&#45; arose to combat that er&#45;<lb/>&#45;roneous thought with sensible and heart&#45;appealing<lb/> writings letters addresses.  While Mendelsshon in Germany was bidding<lb/> his genius to break asunder the shackles which had kept<lb/> his brethren so long in thraldom&#44; a Baalshem&#45;&#45;the<lb/> founder of Hassidism in Poland&#45;&#45;was trying to<lb/> fasten them intricately indissolubly tight.  Who succeeded<lb/> better&#63;  The third Moses&#44; illustrious in Jewish an&#45;<lb/>&#45;nals&#44; made converts&#44; many of whom he would now<lb/> disown with all his soul&#44; as his followers.  The mys&#45;<lb/>&#45;tic Israel of Padolini&#45;&#45;a pseudo miracle performer&#45;&#44; counts<lb/> his disciples by the tens of thousands in Northern<lb/> and Central Europe&#44; all hostile to modern civilization&#44; all wed&#45;<lb/>&#45;ded to a belief&#44; as distant from pure Judaism&#44; as<lb/> the East is far from the West.  In Frankfort on the<lb/> Main&#44; a Samson Raphael Hirsch&#45;&#45;whose death intellectual<lb/> orthodoxy now laments&#45;&#45;might preach devotion to the Law<lb/> and traditions based on a knowledge of past history&#59; he might<lb/> logically write to oppose unscientific speculative theories subversive of our tenets&#44; Hassidism<lb/> heeds nothing of that sort.  Not even the Hildesheimers<lb/> of Berline and the Lehmans of Alaints find a hearing in Galicia.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Those worthies write use a correct German&#44; and understand<lb/> polite literature.  Can they be Orthodox&#63;  No&#44; the Jews en&#45;<lb/>&#45;slaved in mysticism&#59; the Jews who prefer a slow mental<lb/> death in isolation&#44; they are the faithful.<lb/></p>
            <p>To force them out into a live exercise of the faculties<lb/> still inherent in our race&#44; despite terribly adverse cir&#45;<lb/>&#45;cumstances&#44; in a man singularly generous&#44; made an<lb/> incomparable resolve.  Baron Maruice De Hirsch appropriated<lb/> twelve million francs to establish in various cities of<lb/> Galicia schools for of manual training and secular<lb/> learning for boys&#59; schools for of sewing and home industry for<lb/> girls.  If a sad calamity had befallen our people&#44;<lb/> the lamentations of the Hassidim&#45;&#45;so called now miscalled&#45;&#45;could<lb/> not be louder.  The man who gives away his riches away<lb/> to carry out so nefarious a scheme&#44; must not be allowed<lb/> to compass his object.  Quick a Zaddic&#45;&#45;Rabbi Ro&#45;<lb/>&#45;keach of the city of Belss&#45;travels to Vienna with a petition<lb/> to the Austrian government to prevent such an atro&#45;<lb/>&#45;city as that which the Austrian Baron intends to<lb/> perpetrate.  The Minister to whom the petition<lb/> was presented&#44; remarked that none will be compelled to<lb/> send their children to the schools established by the Baron<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Therefore all fears ought to be dismissed.  The Zaddic then<lb/> repelled rejoined&#58; &#34;Honorable Sir&#44; you will please&#44; remember the advice of<lb/> Balaam to Balak&#44; when he was not allowed to curse<lb/> our people the ancient tribes.  He offered a counsel which cost Israel dearly&#44;<lb/> for by sending strange women into our camp&#44; a crime was<lb/> committed which enkindled God&#39;s anger and thousands<lb/> were destroyed.  Could Balaam justify himself by saying&#58;<lb/> &#40;I did not ask you to sin&#63;&#34;  The Minister caught the<lb/> meaning&#44; and with evident sings of displeasure&#44; cut<lb/> short any further conversation&#44; and declared that the<lb/> government will not hinder the bestowing of large<lb/> means on what the Baron De Hirsch deems true charity.<lb/>  Rabbi Rokeach may enjoin wh upon his followers<lb/> to not to sin as the Hebrews offend like his fathers of olden times.  Such is<lb/> the Chillal Hashem&#45;&#45;the profanation of the name<lb/> of our God&#44; brought about by a pretentious sect that<lb/> assume the appellation of &#34;pious&#34;&#44; and give their<lb/> chief the title of &#34;righteous.&#34;  A piety which hugs<lb/> the chains of ignorance&#59; a righteousness which<lb/> hallows superstition invites persecution.  Back&#44; back<lb/> to Egypt those Galician Jews cry&#44; as some of our<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>forefathers <sic>of</sic> ancestors in the legend which I have quo&#45;<lb/>&#45;ted.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  Back to a servitude which keeps us<lb/> segregated&#44; for only in the legend isolation we<lb/> can remain Jews.  How I do wail over so<lb/> dreadful a misapprehension of our God&#45;given re&#45;<lb/>&#45;ligion&#33;&#44; but not less deplorable in its injury to<lb/> our faith&#44; is the sect of rationalists&#44; who&#44; as<lb/> in the legend&#44; exclaims &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;let us leave all<lb/> behind&#44; and plunge into a sea where the past<lb/> is obliterated&#34;  Aye&#58; I mean the impetuous ones<lb/> carried away by every wave of a rising theory&#44; to<lb/> be lost in agnosticism.<lb/>  I shall speak of such in my next lecutre.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>&#35;150&#45;&#45;ON REFULAL OF GALICIAN HASSIDIM TO ACCEPT BARON<lb/> DE HIRSCH&#39;S PROPOSITION TO ESTABLISH SECUALR INDUSTRIAL<lb/> SCHOOLS.<lb/></p>
            <p>attacks the Hassidim for refusing to accept secular<lb/> learning.<lb/></p>
            <p>While Wessley &#38; Mendelsohn tried to loose the shackles<lb/> of ignorance&#44; &#34;a BAALSHEM&#44; the founder of Hassidism in<lb/> Poland&#45;&#45;was trying to fasten them <sic>indissoloubly</sic> tight.&#34;<lb/>...The mystic Israel of Podolia&#44; a pseudo miracle<lb/> performer counts his disciples by the tens of thousands<lb/> in Northern and Central Europe&#44; all hostile to modern<lb/> civilization all wedded to a belief as distant from<lb/> pure Judaism as East is from West.  In Frankfurt on the<lb/> Main&#44; a Samson Raphael Hirsch&#45;&#45;whose death intellectual<lb/> Orthodoxy now laments&#45;&#45;might preach devotion to the law<lb/> and tradition based on a knowledge of past history&#59; he<lb/> might logically write to oppose speculative theories<lb/> subversive to our tenets.  Hassidism heeds nothing of that<lb/> sort.  Not even the Hildesheimers of Berlin and the Lehmans<lb/> &#40;Lehrmans&#41; of Maints find a hearing in Galicia.  Those<lb/> worthies use a correct German &#38; understand polite<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>literature.  Can they be Orthodox&#63;  No.  the Judaism<lb/> enslaved in mysticism<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
