<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF7_4</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1884-01" source="" attested="yes">1884</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_4_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_4_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_4_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_4_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_4_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_4_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_4_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_4_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_4_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_4_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_4_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_4_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_4_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_4_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_4_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff7_4_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>On Sir Moses Montefiore&#39;s<lb/>
                Centennial Birth&#45;day<lb/>
                Sabbath Lech Lecha<lb/>
                1884 5645<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Rabbi Berechijah was preaching according to the<lb/> system prevalent in olden times.  The book which he<lb/> undertook to explain in the legendary style&#44;&#45;&#45;so plea&#45;<lb/>&#45;sing to most hearers&#44; was that which has offered<lb/> a fertile imaginations the widest scope&#45;&#45;the book of<lb/> Canticles&#44; or Solomon&#39;s &#34;Song of Songs.&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;  Arrived at the<lb/> sentence in which the fragrance of the lover&#39;s breath name<lb/> is compared to delicious perfume&#44; the Rabbi remarked&#58;<lb/> A box chest of sweet aromatic spices tightly closed and laid in a<lb/> corner of the house&#44; will give emit no grateful odour.  Let it be opened<lb/> and carried from place to place and it will diffuse<lb/> its grateful sweet smell everywhere.  Then the preacher added&#58;<lb/> To that object our father Abraham may well justly be likened.<lb/>  The precious qualities inherent in his nature would not have<lb/> become known&#44; nor would they have received a full development&#44;<lb/> if he had not journeyed far from his native land&#44;<lb/> instead of remaining within its narrow borders.<lb/>  Brethren.  What the quoted Talmudist applied to the Hebrew<lb/> patriarch of Ur Chasdim&#44; fits with precision the<lb/> Hebrew patriarch of our own time days.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>I may be pardoned for sharing with the<lb/> Jews of Leghorn a degree of pride because in that<lb/> city Moses Montefiore&#45;&#45;a significant name and sur&#45;<lb/>name&#45;&#45;first opened his eyes to the light. of day.  I<lb/> was a youth in 1840&#44; but though I have grown<lb/> old in a country which I love&#44; but which is not lies thousands of miles away distant from that<lb/> where I learned to speak&#44; I can vividly recall<lb/> the joyfulness of that city of Italy&#44; my native town&#44; in when the<lb/> hero of peace entered it on his return from his merci&#45;<lb/>&#45;ful mission at Damascus.  My revered sainted teacher&#45;&#45;<lb/>&#45;&#45;afterwards Chief Rabbi of Leghorn&#45;&#45;Abraham Benedict<lb/> Piperno&#44; of sainted memory&#44; had written a psalm<lb/> in which the following sentiment was expressed&#58; &#34;Rejoice thou<lb/> city of Leghorn&#44; for thine is a superb and honorable<lb/> record.  Within thy walls was born the man<lb/> Moses&#44; so great in acts of sublime counsel and<lb/> intelligence discretion.&#34;  Yet&#44; I concede that if the parents<lb/> of him whose hundred years have flowed down in steady gentleness<lb/> and swelled into a stream of glories&#44; had raised their child in<lb/> Tuscan Italy and not in the capital of England&#44; their<lb/> Moses would not have <sic>developped</sic> so magnificently.<lb/>  The aroma of his goodness could not have spread thus far &#38; wide.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Even politically mild Tuscany&#45;&#45;comparatively mild in her government&#44; was not then the spot<lb/> where the man destined to accomplish splendid deeds<lb/> should have been cradled.  Italy&#44; said once Metternich&#45;&#45;<lb/>the Austrian Bismarck&#45;&#45;is a geographical blunder.<lb/>  Divided into seven inharmonious states&#44; it she com&#45;<lb/>&#45;manded no respect abroad&#44; and her Jewish children<lb/> at home could wield no appreciable influence.<lb/>  Enslaved Italy could not have raised brought forth the Maurogonatos&#44;<lb/> the Malvanos&#44; the Luzzattis&#44; the Jacurs&#44; the Dinas&#44; that<lb/> host of celebrities Hebrew notabilities which two decades of her free existence<lb/> have reared sufficed to rear.  But puissant Great Britain whose sails whiten in whose potency she has that for ages has sent her ships have for ages to furrow<lb/> every distant sea&#44; could train Montefiore for his mission in a school of self&#45;recognizedconscious manhood&#44; and<lb/> demand respect in every clime for one of her citizens whom<lb/> she delighted to honor.  What that Londoner<lb/> has achieved by journeying <sic>travelling</sic> from land to land&#59; how<lb/> the redolence of his name imparted diffused sweetness all over<lb/> the Jewish world&#44; I will not describe.  That picture<lb/> was set before your visions last Sunday evening in<lb/> beautiful lineaments.  My touches could not enhance<lb/> the comeliness of the portrait.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>But what is not best known save to<lb/> Tuscan Jews&#44;&#45;&#45;and is still I conceive to be deserving of a record narrative&#45;&#45;&#44;<lb/> may be listened to with some interest.<lb/></p>
            <p>The immediate family of Sir Moses had settled in England<lb/> and prospered as merchants long before he was happily given to the house of<lb/> Israel.  His birth in Italy Leghorn was merely accident&#45;<lb/>&#45;al&#45;&#45;his mother being on a visit in that city when<lb/> it happened the auspicious even occurred.  But near relatives of Sir Moses con&#45;<lb/>&#45;tinued permanently to reside in that Tuscan city&#44; and I knew<lb/> some several of them well.  Leon Montefiore was<lb/> the recipient of frequent and generous tokens of af&#45;<lb/>&#45;fection from his cousin&#44; whom Queen Victoria had knighted.<lb/>  Massood Racah was ever held in veneration by his<lb/> nephew&#45;&#45;for whom he had stood god&#45;father in the<lb/> humble dwelling facing the rear of the Synagogue&#44; No.<lb/> 10 via Reale on the second floor.  A stone over<lb/> the mortal remains of that pious Israelite&#44; lying in<lb/> the old Jewish burial ground at Leghorn&#44; records<lb/> that the grave is being kept in honorable preservation&#44; proper order&#44;<lb/> through the care by the direction and at the expense of Moses Montefiore&#44; the English<lb/> Baronet.  But he who <sic>prices</sic> Hebrew above<lb/> all languages&#44; and in it thrice a day he prays to God&#44; offers supplications&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>prides himself in Jacob Montefiore&#45;&#45;one of his Italian<lb/> ancestors who wrote a comment on the Masorah&#44;<lb/> or the correct reading of the Scriptural text.  That work<lb/> is religiously kept scrupulously preserved in the handwriting of its author<lb/> at the Ramsgate college&#44; constituted in memory of Lady&#45;&#45;a monument to conjugal tenderness.<lb/>  Judith Montefiore.  Most appropriately so&#44; Loving was the thought&#59; most appropriate the depository of the volume&#44; for it was<lb/> that Judith&#45;&#45;Yehudit&#45;&#45;a Jewess par excellence&#45;&#45;who inspired stimulated<lb/> our illustrious brother in faith to bring his far reaching<lb/> influence to bear on the cultivation of a study of the<lb/> sacred tongue&#44; that the word of God might never be forgotten.<lb/>  She habitually accompanied him on his visits to the schools<lb/> connected with the Sephardic Congregation of London&#44;<lb/> and she herself would&#44; at times&#44; question the pupils<lb/> on the Bible and its translation English rendition.  Thus was<lb/> I privileged to meet her occasionally face to face&#44;<lb/> besides my seeing her seated in the gallery of<lb/> the Synagogue at Bevis Marks.  For in that<lb/> ancient edifice our two exalted coreligionists often<lb/> made their devotions&#44; when they temporarily exchanged their villa<lb/> at Ramsgate for their mansion in Hyde Park.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>But an illustration of Moses Montefiore&#39;s<lb/> humbleness piety sterling piety pray God was presented to my views&#44; on<lb/> the eve of the great day of atonement.  I beheld<lb/> a man of commanding appearance occupying humbly doing the office<lb/> of the sexton.  The Baronet&#44; the friend of a queen&#44;<lb/> the honored guest of princes and of emperors&#44; was<lb/> lighting the hallowed structure&#44; which &#45;&#45;a structure that calls to<lb/> mind Menasseh Ben Israel in his pleading before for the re&#45;<lb/>Oliver Cromwell &#45;admission of his brethren into the soil which Cromwell ruled had liberalized.  That sight struck me ineffaciably.<lb/>  In my boyhood&#44; I had been given occasion to closely observe<lb/> the same man&#44; how when upon an evening of the week&#44;<lb/> he had sat himself in a retired spot of the large<lb/> synagogue at Leghorn to recite his prayers&#59; in later<lb/> years at London&#44; my opinion of his devotional na&#45;<lb/>&#45;ture was indelibly confirmed.  During a century&#44;<lb/> unparalleled in the changes it has wrought&#45;&#45;notably<lb/> in the practice of our faith&#44; when decline of orthodoxy&#44; has which<lb/> become with some many dare call a synonym for unprogressiveness&#44;<lb/> the same man has remained immoveably firm<lb/> in his adherence to parental precept and example&#44;<lb/> glorying to be hailed the champion of conservative<lb/> Judaism&#44; as he is a veritable champion of humanity.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Brethren.  Were it not that to tell further of my<lb/> personal experience on this subject more minutely might savor<lb/> of self&#45;praise&#44; I would gladly enlarge upon it.<lb/>  and I would cite even incidents of even occurred in festal conviviality cor&#45;<lb/>&#45;roborative of my assertion of that same man&#39;s loyalty faithfulness<lb/> to the history and traditions of Israel.  But his seventh<lb/> journey East in the ninety first year of his age&#44;<lb/> is the crowning proof of his fealty loyalty to his creed.  A report<lb/> prejudicial to the Hebrew inhabitants of the Holy Land<lb/> had been printed and widely circulated.  It charged<lb/> them with shortcomings&#44; which&#44; I fear&#44; were not destitute<lb/> of sound foundations.  Certain Rabbis who enjoyed<lb/> the confidence of the world renowned Jew&#44; strongly ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;pealed to him for defense.  Now let me acknowledge with pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;found respect regard for Sir Moses but in all candor that if a degree of<lb/> weakness has been ever detected in the character of our<lb/> famous philanthropist&#44; it lies in his overlooking of the<lb/> faults of Jerusalemites.  Believing that to tread walk the ground which prophets and sages walked trod upon is supremely meritorious&#44; our good Sir Moses has always shown<lb/> undue exceeding leniency towards a community largely depending on in a vast measure supported by<lb/> alms. giving.  None will dare to say that such a<lb/> course meets hi with his approval&#59; on the contrary&#44; he has<lb/> unequivocally deprecated it and endeavoured to alter it&#44; yet&#44; unwittingly his kindness<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>of heart has caused its continuance.  He The English Baronet has<lb/> spent treasures on for the amelioration of the ancient heritage<lb/> of our fathers&#44; but no adequate advantage was derived.<lb/>  Manual work&#44; the cultivation of the soil&#44; the acquire&#45;<lb/>&#45;ments of general learning&#44; are still foreign to the<lb/> main portion largest majority of our brethren in Western Asia.  Never&#45; Yet&#44;<lb/> &#45;theless Sir Moses sincerely holds that his personal<lb/> influence and the means he has lavished have benefit&#45;<lb/>&#45;ted Palestinian Jews very materially.  His own ac&#45;<lb/>&#45;count of his last voyage and forty days&#39; sojourn<lb/> goes far to prove it&#44; for towards the close of his book he tells us<lb/> with much considerable warmth that he has had again every<lb/> opportunity to convince himself of the worthiness<lb/> of the dwellers in Zion&#44; and the deserts of those who<lb/> have taken up their homes in the ancient cities of<lb/> Judah.  But that narrative which a cool minded<lb/> and dispassionate reader will accept with some grains mental<lb/> of deduction reservation&#44; evinces without notwithstanding nevertheless the intense earnestness<lb/> of the &#34;old man beneficent.&#34;  Aye&#44; fatigue&#44; even the<lb/> breaking out of the Cholera could not deter him<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>from responding to the appeal of brethren who<lb/> live where the Shekinah hovered above the golden<lb/> Cherubim.  Verily&#44; I believe that to satisfy also the<lb/> yearning of his soul&#44; the nonagenarian ventured upon so late in life on<lb/> a perilous journey.  For even as &#34;Jerusalem&#34; is em&#45;<lb/>&#45;blazoned upon his coat of arms&#44; so is the memorial of<lb/> &#34;the city of the Great King&#34; ever glowing before his mind.<lb/>  The narrative he wrote is a lucid mirror reflecting the<lb/> sentiments of an Israelite whose recollections of the glo&#45;<lb/>&#45;rious past of his people are fastened on entwined round the fibres of his<lb/> being.  Happily the heart wholly pervaded with<lb/> Jewish feelings&#44; discloses its sweetness in touches of uni&#45;<lb/>&#45;versal love.  Could the innumerable relics which Sir<lb/> Moses Montefiore has treasured be set in array for your in&#45;<lb/>&#45;spection you would enter into the secret chambers of his exalted nature.  Then Here  Among the objects he peculiarly valued you would see here here a scroll of the Land&#44; which it<lb/> took the scribe seven years to complete&#44; there a box con&#45;<lb/>&#45;taining a lock of the hair of young Jewess&#45;&#45;Dinah of Damascus who fell<lb/> pierced by the sword when defending her home and her honor<lb/> during the persecution at Damascus of 1840.  Here you would behold<lb/> a pair of philacteries supposed to have belonged to Judah<lb/> Hallevi&#44; the preeminent poet of the Synagogue&#44; there an<lb/> English Bible elegantly gorgeously bound&#44; which Christian era workingmen<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>presented.  Here a dagger which dropped from the<lb/> hand of the would be assassin who had aimed a blow<lb/> at the lips of our Moses&#59; there a roll of parchment<lb/> in which non&#45;Israelites thank the Hebrew of Hebrews<lb/> for his unsectarian charity.  You have read this week&#45;<lb/>&#45;memorable in the annals of the Jewish world&#45;&#45;the effusions<lb/> of a genuine love for mankind.  To an immense gathering of<lb/> his fellow gentiles fellow citizens who offered him the highest denizen of Ramsgate feli&#45;<lb/>&#45;citations on the completion of his centennial natal<lb/> day&#44; the noble son of our race said&#58; &#34;Dear&#44; dear old<lb/> Ramsgate&#44; there is not a boy or a girl&#44; I do not<lb/> pray for.  God bless you all&#34;.  May the lips<lb/> which gave forth those utterances of human affect&#45;<lb/>&#45;ion continue to move and propitiate blessings.<lb/>  May the patriarch of our days&#44; who&#44; like the patriarch<lb/> of old&#44; rejoices in the celestial assurance that he will<lb/> be gathered to his fathers in peace&#44; and be buried in<lb/> good old age&#44; abide still longer with us&#44; and let so that<lb/> the fragrance of his precious name shall diffuse its<lb/> sweet influence over the whole house of Israel.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>May in Moses Montefiore be fulfilled the<lb/> sentence in the prophetic section of this sabbath&#58;<lb/> &#34;They who wait upon hope in the Lord&#44; will acquire new<lb/> strength&#44; they shall wing their flight upwards<lb/> like eagles&#44; they shall run and be not fatigued&#44;<lb/> proceed onward and become not wearied.&#34;  So may<lb/> it be.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
