<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF5_6</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_6_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_6_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_6_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_6_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_6_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_6_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_6_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_6_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_6_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_6_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_6_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_6_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Post&#45;Biblical<lb/>
                Babylonian Schools<lb/>
                49<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>While trying endeavouring to draw attention to the schools that which<lb/> flourished in the country situated on the East of Palestine&#44;<lb/> I said&#44; that without denying their existence of institutions of learning in Babylon in<lb/> early ages&#44; it was nevertheless about the middle<lb/> of the third century of Christian reckoning&#44; that<lb/> colleges and academies gained there a reputation so far reaching that which<lb/> it has come down to our own days.  The two pupils<lb/> of Rabbi Judah the Prince &#40;&#91;Hebrew&#93; author of the Mishnahs&#41;&#44; who<lb/> were born in Babylon and returned home brimful<lb/> of learning erudition&#44; gave the first impulse to that extensive litera&#45;<lb/>&#45;ture which finally took a permanent shape in the Babylonian<lb/> Talmud.  This book&#44; if it is at all correct to call it so&#44;<lb/> has may not inaptly be likened to a vast hall court&#44; where<lb/> very many sharp witted lawyers are engaged in discussing points relating<lb/> to the oral traditions.  The disputants go by the name<lb/> of Emoraim&#44; meaning &#34;interpreters&#34;&#44; to distinguish<lb/> them from the sages of the Mishnah&#44; known<lb/> as Tannaim&#44; or &#34;instructors&#34;.  Abba&#44; of<lb/> whom I spoke last&#44; and who is deservedly titled&#44;<lb/> by way of eminence&#44; Rab or &#34;the Teacher&#44;&#34; occupies<lb/> a foremost position among those interpreters.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>But his fellow&#45;student&#44; his countryman and friend<lb/> Samuel&#44; is perhaps a character perhaps of more general interesting&#44; par&#45;<lb/>&#45;ticularly so in our days&#44; when a man&#39;s acquaintance<lb/> with one a single subject&#44; however deep and thorough&#44; does<lb/> not elicit ensure the same degree of respect appreciation&#44; as does his possession<lb/> of a varied knowledge will elicit.  Samuel son of Abba Cohen&#44;<lb/> combined with his religious learning&#44; that of secular sciences.<lb/>  He In his youth he had been taught by his own father&#44;<lb/> who was a silk merchant&#44; but withal a well educated<lb/> person.  It would seem that the lad&#39;s disposition inclination had<lb/> led him to search into the laws of nature&#44; not less<lb/> than into Jewish laws&#59; for&#44; previous to his sojourn<lb/> in Palestine&#44; he had already become a physician of<lb/> considerable skill.  It is related that Judah the Prince&#44;<lb/> whose health was very habitually constitutionally delicate&#44; suffered also greatly with<lb/> sore his eyes.  His scholar Samuel&#44; had prescribed<lb/> several remedies&#44; but the patient complained that he<lb/> could not bear even a wash&#44; intended to allay the inflam&#45;<lb/>&#45;mation.  At last&#44; the friendly Doctor prepared a sort of<lb/> perforated bag filled with different drugs&#44; which he<lb/> placed under the head of the sick man&#44; and brought<lb/> about his the needed relief.  It may easily be imagined<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>that the illustrious preceptor wished to evince gratitude&#44; by the promotion<lb/> of his kind pupil&#44; but for some reasons&#44; which have not<lb/> been explained&#44; he could not succeed in clothing Samuel<lb/> with the full authority of a Palestinian Sage&#44; or &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Samuel<lb/> who noticed how greatly very much the master regretted that<lb/> circumstance&#44; pleasantly remarked&#44; that it was all<lb/> right&#44; for he had examined a book of genealogy divinely given in advance<lb/> to Adam&#44; and there he read that he Samuel the pupil of Judah&#44; was not destined to<lb/> receive that such a distinction&#59; that but his reward glory should be to effect<lb/> the care of his loved teacher.  But if Samuel of<lb/> Babylon did not equal others among his contemporaries<lb/> in the possession of a the highest title bestowed in Judea&#44; he<lb/> surpassed many in sterling worth as a theologian<lb/> of broad and enlightened views.  Naardea<lb/> was his native place.  The fame of that al extensive important<lb/> city on the Euphrates&#44; had already attracted there Abba or Rab&#44; but as the<lb/> latter&#44; responding to the promptings of his humility gracious judgment meek disposition&#44; had<lb/> set up a school in the humble city of Sur&#224;&#44; Samuel<lb/> accepted the presidency of the college at Naardea&#44;<lb/> after the death of its former chief.  In civil laws&#44;<lb/> he became an indisputably leading authority.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Indeed&#44; he was called the king of jurisprudence.  It is We may<lb/> not unlikely surmise that his familiarity with the courts<lb/> of the existing gentile government.  Babylon&#44; which&#44;<lb/> as every one knows&#44; came under different dynasties in<lb/> the course of several centuries&#44; was now under the Neo&#45;<lb/>Persians&#44; who had conquered the Parthians.  Samuel<lb/> had been introduced to Sapor&#44; the new ruler&#44; and very<lb/> probably the illustrious Hebrew utilized that royal acquaint&#45;<lb/>&#45;ance in various ways in favor of his own coreligionists.  The Talmud<lb/> leads us to believe that at the outset the new master victors<lb/> showed a bitter hatred against Jews.  By reason of those feelings our ancestors were hampered in the observance of Sabbaths and festivals&#44; but those hostility<lb/> feelings gradually subsided&#59; no doubt Samuel&#39;s influence was<lb/> beneficial on that score.  Sapor told him once that he never was given<lb/> cause for judicially condemning an Israelite to death.  Still&#44;<lb/> Israelites are men&#44; and they have a right to their<lb/> political preferences.  When the inhabitants of<lb/> Cesarea in Asia Minor&#44; resisted the invading army<lb/> of Sapor&#44; many of our people who dwelt there&#44; joined<lb/> the ranks of the defenders&#44; and the conquerors did not<lb/> spare them.  I venture the opinion that in<lb/> order to win for his brethren the good will of the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Neo&#45;Persians and all the gentile world&#44; Samuel promulgated his famous rule&#44;<lb/> &#34;Dine De&#45;Malchutha Dina&#34;; that is&#44; Jews must<lb/> conform to the ordinances of the government under<lb/> which they live.  A just maxim it is&#44; that commends<lb/> itself to universal respect.  In fact&#44; its obedience has<lb/> made us the Hebrews a proverbially law&#45;abiding people&#44; wherever<lb/> our their lot was cast&#59; but some&#44; claiming great liberality&#44;<lb/> have given that maxim a construction&#44; against which<lb/> its author would surely have exclaimed.  Were we to<lb/> follow that novel interpretation&#44; the Sabbath we must abolish the hallowing of the seventh day of the Decalogue&#44;<lb/> where the law of the land is that Sunday or Friday be the day<lb/> of national rest&#59; or we must sanction marriages<lb/> and divorces performed by magistrates&#44; where civil<lb/> officers have the power to bind and loosen the bond<lb/> of matrimony.  But to do so would be treason<lb/> to our faith&#44; and an offence to the memory of<lb/> Samuel of Naardea.  A knowledge of the<lb/> Talmud&#44; will convince all the unprejudiced&#44; that<lb/> our teacher of old demanded simply a compliance with<lb/> regulations necessary for the maintenance of social<lb/> order&#44; for the support of the city and of the State&#44;<lb/> and of secular institutions.  In short&#44; Samuel<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>reported impressed upon us in different words the recommendation of<lb/> Jeremiah the Prophet who would that we seek the welfare<lb/> of the place of our dispersion and pray for its success.<lb/>  Judaism has always resisted an encroachment on<lb/> its sacred ordinances&#44; but it has ever conformed to<lb/> temporal rules of a municipal or national character.<lb/>  Hence&#44; its adherents have taken up their residence in<lb/> many lands&#44; and identified themselves with the main popu&#45;<lb/>&#45;lations thereof&#44; both socially and politically.  All<lb/> honor to the President of the Academy of Naardea<lb/> for his wholesome advice.  He showed also his<lb/> enlarged views by agreeing to the opinion of some of the Rabbinical coworkers&#44; that Israelites<lb/> need not stand in fear of ill&#45;luck.  At a time<lb/> when the false science of Astrology was in vogue&#44;<lb/> Samuel arose above it by the strength of his faith.<lb/>  He was intimately acquainted with a Chaldean called<lb/> Ablat.  The two had met and were walking together&#44; when Ablat<lb/> said to Samuel&#58; &#34;You see that yonder man crossing a pond&#59; he<lb/> will be beaten by a snake and die.&#34;  Samuel said&#58;<lb/> &#34;If he be an Israelite&#44; he will not die&#44; for we acknowledge<lb/> God and not the stars as the ruler of our destiny&#34;.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>When the man came back alive&#44; Ablat asked that<lb/> look through at his clothes he might search through his basket.  The story tells that a snake<lb/> cut in twain by a sharp pointed reed&#44; in the pond was<lb/> found there.  Samuel then inquired into the history of<lb/> the man&#44; who proved to be an Israelite&#44; and he learnt<lb/> that a state of poverty had not hindered the perform&#45;<lb/>&#45;ance of a thoughtful generosity&#44; as recommended by the<lb/> law of God&#59; Samuel then exclaimed&#58; &#34;very correctly has<lb/> Solomon written&#44; &#39;Righteousness delivereth from death.&#39;&#34;<lb/>  Our Babylonian preceptor did look into the stars&#44; but<lb/> not to predict events.  He aimed to further the interests<lb/> of a science greatly esteemed by our Sages.  In fact&#44; it<lb/> is recorded that he prided himself on his knowledge of<lb/> Astronomy&#44; and only regretted that he could not ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;plain the erratic course of the comets through the<lb/> sky.  A book bearing upon that science credited<lb/> to him has been lost&#44; but we were left enough con&#45;<lb/>&#45;cerning Samuel of Naardea&#44; to form a criterion of his<lb/> mental and moral calibre.  He certainly possessed<lb/> an keen understanding of human nature very keen&#44; a broad mind and a profound<lb/> sense of what constitutes human real greatness.  I will<lb/> illustrate my assertion with exceeding brevity.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>One day King Sapor said to Samuel &#34;You who are<lb/> so clever can tell me perchance the dream that I shall<lb/> have to&#45;night.&#34;  Samuel answered&#58; &#34;You will see the Ro&#45;<lb/>&#45;mans invade your country&#44; take you prisoner and treat<lb/> you with indignity.&#34;  The dread of such an event was<lb/> so wide&#45;spread&#44; that the king thought upon it all the<lb/> day long&#44; and naturally dreamed it.  The<lb/> Talmud abounds with speculative views about<lb/> the condition of the world&#44; after the advent of the<lb/> Messiah.  In the face of ideas most extraordinary and prevalent among<lb/> his contemporaries&#44; Samuel had the courage to state<lb/> that the world will be precisely then as it is now&#44; with<lb/> the only difference that the oppressors of Israel shall<lb/> have ceased to exist.  Let us remember this the following saying<lb/> of Samuel and take it as a guide&#58; &#34;Those who are modest<lb/> in their behaviour&#44; God will exalt&#44; but the pretentious<lb/> shall be lowered down.  They who crave for honors<lb/> will lose them&#44; but they who shun distinctions will<lb/> have attained them without solicitation&#63;  A wise<lb/> aphorism&#44; founded in borne out by experience&#44; and enhancing in our<lb/> estimation the character of Samuel Chief the important chief chief of the academy of Naardea.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
