<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF7_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff7_1_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>For Vayesheb<lb/>
                after one of I. D. Luzzatto&#44; to whom some<lb/>
                of the ideas belong.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Dear hearers&#33;  Nothing is more apt to draw youths aside from<lb/> the path of virtue than the sight of wickedness successful and<lb/> bast boastful.  The years of our life&#44; elapsing between<lb/> childhood and manhood are fruitful of the noblest sentiments.<lb/>  During that period it is that we will swear&#44; with unsullied<lb/> lips&#44; fidelity to all which is loveable in human nature.<lb/>  Then will we&#44; with glowing breasts&#44; devote time and mind to<lb/> learning&#44; in the anticipation of <sic>benefitting</sic> the world&#44; and<lb/> earning a deservedly good name.  But when arrived at<lb/> the age&#44; that brings us close to that world&#44; in which we dreamed<lb/> to find a realization of our ideals&#59; as we pass from the<lb/> school of fancy to that of reality&#59; from the association of<lb/> dead&#45;writers to that of living actors&#44; and notice here self&#45;<lb/>assurance clothed in garments which belong to sterling merit&#59;<lb/> there blatant talkers occupy seats which should have been<lb/> reserved for wise reasoners&#59; here hypocrisy supplanting<lb/> honesty of purpose&#44; there haughtiness ill&#45;using meekness&#59;<lb/> as we notice&#44; I say&#44; that the thoughts formed in the days<lb/> of guileless youth vanish like a golden streak in the sky<lb/> which murky clouds darken&#44; a soul&#45;withering belief lays hold of us.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>&#34;Righteousness was a shadowy mission&#44; which inexperience<lb/> raised&#59; unrighteousness has existence and strength and<lb/> influence&#34;.  So we tell ourselves&#59; and regretting the errors<lb/> of our early days&#44;&#45;&#45;as we then call the lofty aspirations<lb/> once found conceived&#45;&#45;&#44; we put on a mask and go about in<lb/> search of gain and popular applause.  What will<lb/> check us in that downward course to spiritual destruction&#63;<lb/>  Religion&#44; dear hearers&#33;  Religion&#44; giving the assurance that the<lb/> Almighty smiles upon the good&#44; and frowns on evil doers&#44;&#45;&#45;<lb/> that to appear not in disguise&#44; but as we actually are&#44; be&#45;<lb/>&#45;fore our fellow&#45;creatures&#44; and deal in all fairness with them&#44;<lb/> is to please our Creator and Father.  Religion alone can<lb/> steel youth in the practice of virtue&#44; and make daily attacks<lb/> upon its innocence totally powerless.  This va&#45;<lb/>&#45;luable teaching&#44; the portion of Genesis designated for to<lb/> day&#44; presents to view.  You may have heard me often<lb/> speak of a youth who figures grandly in the history<lb/> narrated in that book&#44; but so many are the qualities<lb/> which gave him distinction&#44; that we can choose his cha<lb/>&#45;racter&#44; as a frequent topic of our observations&#44; and yet<lb/> avoid the fault of repetition.  Joseph is the type of virtue<lb/> early set upon by the an unkind world&#44; but keeping unshaken through<lb/> the support of religion&#44; and receiving at the end the reward<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>to which it assured&#59; the glory of having <sic>benefitted</sic> that<lb/> world&#44; which had shown itself to him false and unjust.<lb/>  Let us glance at a single trait of that character&#58; The fear<lb/> of God.  Among our intellectual faculties that<lb/> of examining human actions and passing judgment on them&#44;<lb/> is the first <sic>developped</sic> in men gifted by nature with keen<lb/> discernment.  Unhappily&#44; occasions for disapproving what<lb/> we see are so numerous glaring that a person of perfect correct morals<lb/> will with much ease detect much which deserves blame<lb/> and reprehension.  From this circumstance arose the pri&#45;<lb/>&#45;mary cause of Joseph&#39;s trials&#44; as it arises for all crea&#45;<lb/>&#45;tures who cannot bear wrong&#44; and will loudly pronounce<lb/> a condemnation.  Joseph brought unto his father the<lb/> report of his brothers evil conduct.  He saw the sons of<lb/> Leah&#45;&#45;write our Rabbins&#45;&#45;treat the sons of the hand&#45;<lb/>maids unkindly &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; while he&#44; the child<lb/> of the beloved Rachel&#44; preferred their association&#44; to exalt their<lb/> manhood and make the slighted ones&#44; feel his equals<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  He saw the sons of Leah wanting<lb/> in the finer feelings of humanity&#44; using dumb&#45;animals cruelly&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;.  he saw them destitute of that sense<lb/> of chastity so prized by the pure&#45;hearted &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Too young to remonstrate with any hope of success&#44; he<lb/> sought paternal authority to effect a correction.<lb/>  But Joseph was ignorant of the world in which he<lb/> moved.  Carried up on the light wings of fancy&#44; he<lb/> had created to himself a world&#44; where he discovered<lb/> a high place set apart for his virtues.  He dreamed<lb/> what he believed in.  He dreamed that moral excellencies<lb/> raise man above the heavenly spheres&#59; that the sun and<lb/> the moon and the stars bow before a being truly righteous&#44;<lb/> and declare him king.  But he awoke in the real world<lb/> by which he was surrounded to find that jealousy and<lb/> envy will not suffer merit to be awarded the crown<lb/> of superiority&#59; that they forge&#44; on the contrary&#44; the chains<lb/> of bondage&#44; which must be dragged drudgingly along.<lb/>  Still the filters which tear the flesh&#44; cannot wear away<lb/> the majesty of the soul.  His He is a King who rules<lb/> his feelings.  What more sublime spectacle than to<lb/> behold a being who must bend far below his level&#44; cheer&#45;<lb/>&#45;fully work&#44; sustained by the thought that nothing is de&#45;<lb/>&#45;grading except sin&#63;  Call not a slave the man who<lb/> labors faithfully&#59; the menial office rendered is ennobled by the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>dignity of his character.  Joseph sold and sold again&#44;<lb/> is free&#44; because he does not part with the principles<lb/> of integrity&#59; because he can gloriously exclaim &#34;I am<lb/> the master of my passions.&#34;  How very exceedingly few those who can<lb/> give out forth that utterance&#33;  The very change of condition<lb/> from what is considered high to that which is deemed low&#44;<lb/> will suggest prevarications and deception and artifice.<lb/>  The wish to win favor&#44; or the fear to excite anger&#44; will<lb/> silence the dictates of unrighteousness uprightness&#44; and<lb/> lead virtue where it sinks and disappears.  In every stage<lb/> of life the preservation of our morals presents appalling<lb/> difficulties.  The world in which we live demands deception.<lb/>  The old and the rich&#44; like the young and poor are put un&#45;<lb/>&#45;der subjection.  They cannot emancipate themselves from<lb/> the worst of tyrannies&#44; social conventionalities.  But how<lb/> infinitely greater and more numerous are the difficulties<lb/> to be overcome by a creature just budding into manhood<lb/> with so beautiful in form and graceful in manners&#44; but compelled<lb/> to stoop to the will of others&#44; who can dispose of his life<lb/> with impunity&#63;  What will not a worldly policy ask<lb/> then in order that ease may be purchased&#44; and promotion<lb/> secured&#33;  Aye&#58; Every thing combined in removing the scruples&#44;<lb/>&#45;&#45;as the depraved world call them&#45;&#45;&#44; the scruples of conscience<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>entertained by the youthful and comely Joseph&#44; when his<lb/> virtue was put to a severe test.  He had not courted<lb/> sin&#44; but sin forced itself upon him.  If he <sic>yeilded</sic>&#44; pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;ferments would be placed at his disposal&#44; if he re&#45;<lb/>&#45;mained firm&#44; his future would be ruined in his future prospect. blasted.<lb/>  Again&#58; A veil which none could penetrate would be thrown<lb/> over the sin&#44; while the imputation of having been gently opt&#44;<lb/> would expose him to public indignation&#44; without the slightest means<lb/> of refuting the malicious charge.  Let us now observe<lb/> the working of that mind under a most searching trial.<lb/>  What feeling holds Joseph in the path of righteousness&#63;<lb/>  Gratitude&#63;  Certainly&#58; The Egyptian who owned him<lb/> <sic>a</sic> his slave had dealt gently with him&#59; but then the<lb/> Hebrew youth could might have reasoned in this manner &#34;My master<lb/> has shown me kindness&#44; because he found it advantageous.<lb/>  My industry has increased his substance&#44; both in his personal<lb/> property and his lands &#91;Hebrew&#93; I have so carefully<lb/> managed his estate&#44; and so <sic>thriftly</sic> conducted his affairs&#44; that<lb/> he is looked upon as one of the richest of Pharaoh&#39;s officers.<lb/>  He&#44; of course&#44; likes me for that&#44; but he still claims me as<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>his bondsman.  A <sic>whimmsy</sic> put into his hand the scour&#45;<lb/>&#45;ging rod.  Let me therefore prevent the possibility by<lb/> keeping on my side her who <sic>weilds</sic> unlimited influence&#34;<lb/>  Yes&#58; he might have so reasoned.<lb/>  But these reasonings thoughts which would seem almost &#91;&#63;&#93; to rise spontaneously did<lb/> not cross the mind of the virtuous son of Jacob.  He feared<lb/> not man&#39;s wrath and people&#39;s contempt.  He feared the<lb/> all&#45;seeing eye of Providence detecting him in crime.<lb/>  &#34;How can I do this great evil and sin against God&#63;&#34;<lb/>  That was the restrain restraining power which robbed sin<lb/> of its victory.  The idea that the perfect Being to whom<lb/> we are accountable for our deeds&#44; is offended when we hide<lb/> our moral infirmities depravities deformities under the cloak of f hypocrisy.<lb/>  &#34;How can I do this great evil&#34;&#63;  To betray confidence is a<lb/> crime&#44; but if the object betrayed does not know aught of the injury&#44; and<lb/> does not suffer materially&#44; why&#44; we need not then be deterred<lb/> by scruples to do what promotes our interest.  No&#58; it is a<lb/> great evil to wind oneself round a heart when ought to<lb/> bear us detestation.  &#34;How can I do this great evil and sin<lb/> against God&#63;&#34;  The reliance reposed on me by a mortal mas&#45;<lb/>&#45;ter may never be shaken despite my &#91;&#63;&#93; perfidiousness but the immortal Ruler will cast me<lb/> away from His presence as loathsomeness itself.  And<lb/> this feeling of reverence for the Sovereign Judge and witness&#44; at<lb/> the same time&#44; of our actions and thoughts&#44; can alone<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>uphold faiths and prevent its falling into precipices<lb/> met here below at nearly every step we take.<lb/>  The same feeling&#44; and not a philosophy teaching virtue by the rules of utilitaria&#45;<lb/>&#45;nism will insure to to society members able to benefit it&#44;<lb/> impelled by the love of humanity and not by egotism&#44;<lb/> members who will measure their doings not by the length of<lb/> their own advantage&#44; but by that which will inure to the hap&#45;<lb/>&#45;piness of mankind.  The fear of God will supply the world<lb/> with searchers after truth men&#44; employing their minds not to<lb/> dazzle the &#91;&#63;&#93; multitude&#44; but to guide many gently<lb/> in the way of a knowledge that breeds goodness and philan&#45;<lb/>&#45;thropy.  By that feeling will a youth keep virtuous&#44; not&#45;<lb/>&#45;withstanding corruptive surroundings&#44; and grow to become a<lb/> trusty servant&#44; or a benevolent master&#44; a staunch friend&#44;<lb/> or a reliable <sic>counsellor</sic>&#44; the agent of the Most High&#44; in<lb/> bestowing blessings on the community among whom he lives.<lb/>  And such was the Hebrew whom we glory to reckon in our<lb/> noble ancestry.  Would to God that we who so admire Joseph&#39;s<lb/> character&#44; copied it.  The name of &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;a holy people&#44;&#34;<lb/> would then be deservedly borne.  We would be instanced<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>as out for purity and uprightness&#44; for truthfulness<lb/> and charity.<lb/></p>
            <p>&#40;This lecture was continued at some length to address a Bar<lb/> Mitzvah&#44; an inmate of the Jewish Foster Home&#41;<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
