<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF13_10</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1897" source="" attested="yes">1897</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_10_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_10_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_10_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_10_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_10_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_10_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_10_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_10_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_10_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_10_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_10_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_10_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>97<lb/>
                Explanatory on Itr&#243;<lb/></p>
            
            <p>46</p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>To receive circulars and pamphlets is with me&#44;<lb/> and most likely with all ministers&#44; a circumstance<lb/> of constant occurrence.  To read them all&#44; would be&#44;<lb/> in many instances&#44; a perfect loss waste of time.  To ack&#45;<lb/>&#45;nowledge numerous letters is also a task not infrequently<lb/> irksome.  Still&#44; in order not to appear rude&#44; I<lb/> have invariably imposed upon myself the obliga&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion of invariably answering them all&#44; either verbally&#44; or in<lb/> writing.  Regarding circulars and pamphlets&#44;<lb/> I confess that unless I can discover at a glance<lb/> some points of interest&#44; I lay them aside.<lb/>  This week&#44; however&#44; a printed sheet of paper&#44;<lb/> was sent to my address&#44; the heading of which at&#45;<lb/>&#45;tracted my attention.  It related to one of the essen&#45;<lb/>tial precepts of our religion&#45;&#45;the fourth command&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment of the Decalogue&#44; which we have read this<lb/> Sabbath morning.  What surprised me in a measure&#44; is<lb/> that the paper appears seems to have emanated from the<lb/> Girard College&#44; in which institute&#44; I judge&#44; it was<lb/> also printed &#34;pro bono publico&#34; for the good of the public at large.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>I know that Stephen Girard was so decidedly opposed<lb/> to matters of faith denominational religion&#44; that he forbade even the mere<lb/> entering of visiting by of the college which he founded and munificently endowed by clergymen of any denomination into the col&#45;<lb/> &#45;lege which he munificently endowed.  He feared<lb/> that clerical influence might clandestinely thwart his<lb/> wishes.  But since the testator can no longer cannot personally object&#44; his executors did have allowed the institute<lb/> which he created&#44; has been to become altogether transformed.<lb/>  It has made ample room for Protestant christ&#45;<lb/>&#45;ianity.  Chapels services denominational lectures and books of instruction<lb/> aim to add to the number of believers&#44; who swear<lb/> by a man&#45;god.  So formidable is the power<lb/> of the majority&#44; that persons individuals and corporations entrusted with the<lb/> guidance of the college&#44; think it irreproachably<lb/> correct to ignore the expressed will of him&#44; whose immense<lb/> legacies created the said college and richly main&#45;<lb/>&#45;tain it to this day.  The paper sub&#45;<lb/>&#45;mitted to my perusal&#44; hinged upon the duty<lb/> of observing what he it calls &#34;the true Sabbath.&#34;<lb/>  Its author starts with the idea that by reason<lb/> of the spherical construction of the earth&#44; which<lb/> occasions a marked difference of time between different<lb/> parts of the globe&#44; it becomes absolutely impossible<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>for any race or sect to observe the same day as the a<lb/> sabbath.  To illustrate this point&#44; he drew a<lb/> diagram&#44; showing how starting from leaving behind a given meri&#45;<lb/>&#45;dian and <sic>travelling</sic> on&#44; we shall find for instance that when&#44;<lb/> the morning of Sunday dawns here&#44; it will be<lb/> Saturday evening in another place&#59; or that as the distance<lb/> increases about a whole day&#44; anticipating preceding or retarding succeeding the<lb/> Sunday sabbath will be noticed between the two far off<lb/> localities.  The argument is of course very correct.<lb/>  All understand it Neither we Jews&#44; dispersed throughout the world&#44; can<lb/> keep Saturday together&#44; as our Sabbath&#59; nor Christ&#45;<lb/>&#45;ians&#44; who miscall Sunday&#44; the Sabbath&#44; can cele&#45;<lb/>&#45;brate it simultaneously.  But as I am naturally<lb/> concerned only about the day which the fourth com&#45;<lb/>&#45;mandment of the Decalogue  has declared holy&#44; I<lb/> will say&#44; that latitude and longitude do not at all<lb/> affect its observance.  Let me explain.  In the<lb/> wilderness of sin&#44; our ancestors were first told for<lb/> the first time that God had originally sanctified the seventh day &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; and<lb/> that to pay it proper honor&#44; they should not then&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>go&#44; as usual&#44; go in search of manna&#44; for a double<lb/> portion thereof would be supplied on Friday.<lb/>  The question whether the patriarchs and their<lb/> offspring kept the Sabbath&#44; must remain<lb/> an open question.  The Bible is silent in that<lb/> regard respect.  The Talmudists do state that the se&#45;<lb/>&#45;venth day was always sanctified I am inclined&#44; by our olden predecessors.<lb/>  With due deference be it said&#44; I incline to doubt it&#44; particularly so&#44;<lb/> because during the centuries of Egyptian bondage&#44;<lb/> the enslaved would scarcely be allowed to rest one<lb/> day in seven.  We read &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;The task masters urged me them on&#44; saying&#44; <sic>fulfil</sic> your<lb/> works&#59; even your daily task.&#34;  Now&#58; when from the top of<lb/> Sinai the ordinance to remember the Sabbath day<lb/> was enjoined&#44; I think that the Divine Legisla&#45;<lb/>&#45;tor meant to allude to the instruction teaching given in<lb/> the wilderness of sin.  In fact&#44; the very object<lb/> assigned to the ordinance&#44; would show that God&#39;s<lb/> design was primarily to let all creatures&#44; rational and irrational<lb/> enjoy bodily repose a full day once a week.  The<lb/> idea is perhaps brought forth more forcibly by Moses in the repe&#45;<lb/>tition of the Decalogue in Deuteronomy &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>addressing our people&#44; before the conquest of the land&#44; the archprophet said<lb/> regarding the &#91;&#63;&#93; and scope of the Sabbath&#58; &#34;Thou shalt do no manner of work &#38;c.....<lb/> &#34;In order that thy man&#45;servant and thy maid&#45;<lb/>servant may rest like thyself.&#34;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Now&#44; let us reflect.  Even after the conquest of<lb/> Palestine&#44; when the tribes scattered about to enter into<lb/> the respective possession <sic>parcelled</sic> out to each&#44; it<lb/> became geographically impossible for all&#44; to ce&#45;<lb/>&#45;lebrate the Sabbath precisely at the same time.<lb/>  The author of the circular to which I have allu&#45; had reference&#44;<lb/> &#45;ded reasoning from a Christian stand point recognizing the impossibility of a simultaneous Sabbath&#44; argues<lb/> in favor of setting apart any one day out of seven&#44; and<lb/> be believes he considers that plan in that a sensible and righteous manner&#44; to carry out the fourth com&#45;<lb/>&#45;mandment of the Decalogue. will be performed.<lb/>  Not so&#44; we children of the covenant of Horeb argue.  For&#44;<lb/> we read it is written &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;But the seventh<lb/> day is a sabbath to the Lord thy God&#44;&#34; as to say&#58;<lb/> if the termination of the work of creation&#44; does not<lb/> suffice to teach thee the real day selected&#44; the miracle<lb/> of the manna demonstrably shows it.  Nor is<lb/> it because of the difference of latitude and longitude&#44; that<lb/> we Jews might f be permitted to choose one day<lb/> out of seven&#44; and call it &#34;Sabbath.&#34;  Never.  I know that<lb/> some in the advanced wing of radicalism fond of a Sunday service have so twisted<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>and perverted the sacred text&#44; so that it might tally<lb/> with their false interpretation.  But the definite<lb/> article &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;the seventh day&#34; gives them<lb/> the lie.  I am naturally asked&#58; how<lb/> do you then reconcile the national observance<lb/> of the one day with the marked distance of localities&#63;<lb/>  Surely And the querist adds the remark&#44; that very correctly&#44; that<lb/> when we greet the incoming of the Sabbath&#44;<lb/> in Eastern countries&#44; working time has already arrived&#44;<lb/> while in very far off Western countries&#44; it has not may not<lb/> yet arrived.  Well&#44; brethren.  Your Bible and mine<lb/> has reconciled the apparent discrepancy.  Each<lb/> Jewish community fixes the hours of Sabbath&#44; in<lb/> accordance with the established reckoning of time il in<lb/> its dwelling place.  So it This procedure was contemplated and permitted by the<lb/> heavenly Lawgiver.  A single quotation will suffice<lb/> to prove that verity.  In the twenty third chapter<lb/> of Leviticus&#44; where all sacred days or are enumerated&#44;<lb/> we read it is written&#58; &#34;Six days work may be done&#44; but the se&#45;<lb/>&#45;venth day is a Sabbath of solemn rest&#44; a holy convocation.<lb/>  Ye shall do no manner of work&#59; it is a Sabbath unto<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>the Lord&#44; in all throughout in every one of your habitations&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Clearly therefore&#44; we are right to count in<lb/> counting the coming in and the going out of that<lb/> sacred day&#44; conformably with the geographical position<lb/> of the earth&#44; in which we happen to dwell.  But because we<lb/> Now&#44; Israelites acknowledge a still higher motive for the institution of this sacred day&#44; I deem it fitting to close my explanatory<lb/> talk with a Rabbinical legend.  Says a Midrash&#58;<lb/> When The Almighty took counsel with the angels<lb/> that encircled His throne&#44; about the advisability<lb/> of imparting to the people just freed from bondage&#44;<lb/> guiding rules for their guidance of life.  Then&#44; the Torah&#44; clothed in wisdom&#44;<lb/> came forward and spoke thus&#58; O Lord of the Uni&#45;<lb/>&#45;verse&#33;  Might not man&#44; because compelled to till<lb/> the ground&#44; in order to bring forth what feeds his<lb/> body&#44; to reap and gather in the fruits he planted&#44;<lb/> to sell and earn a livelihood&#44; might he not by reason of that<lb/> neglect a study necessary to his spiritual welfare&#63;<lb/>  The Lord answered.  I have provided for that&#59; I have<lb/> destined one day in every week to reign as the queen<lb/> of religion &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Upon that day&#44; the recipients<lb/> of my benefactions under the reign of that Princess of spirituality will have the opportunity&#44; of<lb/> which they must avail themselves&#44; to bend their<lb/> thoughts on that which <sic>yeilds</sic> a lasting advantage<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>here on earth and thereafter.  Brethren.  I imagine<lb/> that Isaiah was penetrated with that truth&#44;<lb/> when he pronounced the Sabbath a delight&#44; a most<lb/> honorable precept of our creed&#59; when he called the<lb/> man blessed&#44; who takes good heed not to profane<lb/> the sabbath &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> when he promised every one who obeys that ordinance&#44;<lb/> and holds fast on that Divine covenant&#44; elevation<lb/> in the holy mountain of God&#44; joys in the upper&#45;<lb/>&#45;most dwelling of prayer.  Surely&#44; I would<lb/> be false to my avocation&#44; if I did not exhort<lb/> my brothers and sisters in faith who enter these<lb/> holy courts&#44; to leave behind on the seventh day what is temporal<lb/> and fleeting and centre their minds on the typi&#45;<lb/>&#45;cal precursor of that life where a Sabbath&#45;rest<lb/> is unalloyed and everlasting.  May That by our obedience to the 4th commandment&#44; each of us may<lb/> be allotted that heavenly inheritance&#44; is verily my supplication<lb/> to the gracious Lord of our fathers&#59; our Divine Legislator and so may it be<lb/> Amen. Protector.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
