<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF5_9</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_9_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_9_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_9_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_9_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_9_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_9_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_9_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_9_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_9_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_9_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_9_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_9_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_9_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_9_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_9_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_9_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. Fifth St.<lb/>
                Philadelphia&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Post&#45;Biblical<lb/>
                52<lb/>
                French school<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>In speaking of our coreligionists&#44; who lived in France<lb/> during the middle ages&#44; I necessarily pointed out one man&#44;<lb/> considered the greatest in his age time.  My sketch of Rashi&#39;s<lb/> labors in Hebrew literature&#44; tried to show in what he notably<lb/> excelled&#44; and why the name of the Sage of Troyes gained among<lb/> Jews an undying reputation.  He was not&#44; however&#44; alone<lb/> in disseminating learning&#44; for his immediate descendants&#44;<lb/> and a respectable number of their contemporaries and<lb/> successors&#44; cultivated the same field as the master had<lb/> most usefully worked at&#44; and they left as evidences of their<lb/> activity productions of acknowledged merit.  But a<lb/> sharp line must be drawn between two geographical<lb/> sections of France in medieval times ages.  In disposition<lb/> and preferences our French fellow&#45;believers of the North&#44;<lb/> where Rashi was born&#44; differed very strikingly from<lb/> those of the South.  While the former chose to<lb/> devote their minds principally to Talmud and kindred<lb/> writings&#44; the latter&#44; without excluding a study of the<lb/> traditions&#44; delighted in the Bible and its poetry&#44; in philology<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>and philosophy.  They imbibed from their close<lb/> neighbors in Spain&#44; a spirit of critical inquiry and<lb/> a deep love for the language in which our prophets<lb/> had transmitted the teachings of inspired genius.<lb/>  Provence became another Andalusia&#44; and Narbonne a<lb/> Cordova.  Especially after the &#91;&#63;&#93;&#45;&#45;a Christian<lb/> sect in south France during the thirteenth century&#45;&#45;rebelled against<lb/> Papal authority&#44; our people rose socially high by their<lb/> intellectual acquirements.  A family deserving of a<lb/> niche in the temple of fame&#44; is that called Petis&#44; but<lb/> best known by all as Kimchis.  Its members were<lb/> French by birth&#44; but their progenitors must have emi&#45;<lb/>&#45;grated from Spain&#44; probably by reason of some popular<lb/> outbreaks of which we have no account.  Still&#44; it<lb/> is worth mentioning as a curious fact&#44; that they and<lb/> others among their Jewish countrymen&#44; took pleasure in<lb/> styling themselves Sephardim&#44; or &#34;Spaniards&#44;&#34; simply be&#45;<lb/>&#45;cause of the prestige attached then to the Israelites who<lb/> made the Iberian peninsula famous by their intellectual learning<lb/> and the political height stations attained.  At all events&#44; we find<lb/> in the middle of the twelfth century Joseph Kimchi&#44; who<lb/> flourished in South France&#44; busily engaged in propagating<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>sacred lore.  To him is due the credit of having<lb/> been the first to compose a Hebrew grammar in a<lb/> Christian country land&#44; <sic>rivalling</sic> those of his coreligionists<lb/> who had excelled in that department in Moorish Spain countries&#44;<lb/> under the Moors.  He called his book Sepher Ha&#45;Zicaron&#44; or &#34;Memoranda&#44;&#34;<lb/> but though often quoted&#44; it has never appeared in print.<lb/>  It may exist yet in manuscript in some rare libraries.<lb/>  Joseph Kimchi was not more fortunate regarding his<lb/> Scriptural commentaries.  That he did write them ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;provedly&#44; there can be no doubt&#44; for so we gather from later<lb/> sources&#44; but posterity has not seen them.  A strange<lb/> fate would that even his translation form the Arabic<lb/> of the excellent work Chobath Ha Lebaboth &#34;the duty of<lb/> hearts&#34; by Bachy&#233; ben Pakoda did not come down to<lb/> us.  But destiny which stood in the way of the<lb/> father to prevent his giving us the fruits of this thoughts&#44;<lb/> was favorable to his sons&#44; Moses and David.  Of Moses<lb/> we possess a guide to Hebrew prose and poetry&#44; named<lb/> Mahalach Shebile ha&#45;da&#224;th and a valuable commentary<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>on the book of Proverbs&#44; but his brother David has<lb/> succeeded in gaining an reputation from later generations enviable notoriety<lb/> which will last while sacred literature finds students.<lb/>  I venture the opinion that second to Rashi&#44; Radak<lb/>&#45;&#45;which word forms the initials of Rabbi David Kimchi&#39;s name&#45;&#45;<lb/>is the author most affectionately thought of author by the bulk of<lb/> a scholars among our people.  And deservedly so&#44; for his<lb/> activity was unsurpassed only by his attachment loyalty to the<lb/> ancestral faith.  Earning but a scanty livelihood<lb/> by teaching children Talmud&#44; he devoted every hour that<lb/> he could spare&#44; regardless of fatigue&#44; to supply us with comments on<lb/> the Bible&#44; marked by an intelligent and impartial<lb/> understanding of the text.  Christian scholars<lb/> have objected to some of his elucidations&#44; because he<lb/> exposed the folly committed by the Church in distorting<lb/> the sense of scriptural passages to apply them&#44;<lb/> without foundation&#44; to the history of the man of Nazareth.<lb/>  But we Jews must admire his courage and his<lb/> acumen&#44; as manifested in giving a natural explanation<lb/> to narratives and sentences in Holy Writ&#44; and avoid&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing mysticism and far fetched allegorical meanings.<lb/></p>
            <p>As a grammarian and lexicographer&#44; David Kimchi<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>stands <sic>unrivalled</sic>.  Whether his system be unimpeach&#45;<lb/>&#45;ably correct or not&#44; I would not assume to decide&#44;<lb/> but all who pronounce the Hebrew&#44; as we&#44; of the Portu&#45;<lb/>&#45;guese ritual&#44; do&#44; have accepted him as our a guide&#44; and<lb/> I have read that how not a few among our Ashkenazim<lb/> brethren have trod endeavoured striven to prove that David Kimchi ought<lb/> to be followed universally in the rules he laid down for<lb/> reading the sacred language.  Those rules have been adopted<lb/> in colleges and universities among non&#45;Israelites&#44; wherever<lb/> a chair for Hebrew literature has was established.<lb/></p>
            <p>Kimchi&#39;s endeavours efforts are inestimable in every depart&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment wherein he labored&#44; and to this day men&#44; search&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing into ancient libraries&#44; seek for his hand writing and bring<lb/> to light what time had hidden away.  Schiller Szinessi<lb/> in Cambridge and Bar Goldberg in Paris have&#44; in<lb/> a measure&#44; succeeded in that department endeavour.<lb/></p>
            <p>But it is of the character of our David that I<lb/> wish briefly to speak&#44; so as to show how well<lb/> merited was the veneration which that French Jew<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>secured from his contemporaries and posterity.<lb/>  He who that prided himself in having descended from<lb/> a Spanish ancestry&#44; and who affixed to his signature<lb/> the title Ha Sephardi&#44; could not remain unconcerned&#44;<lb/> when the most famous among Spanish Jews was un&#45;<lb/>&#45;sparingly fought against.  Who has not<lb/> heard of Maimonides&#45;&#45;Rambam&#44; Moses Rabbi Moses<lb/> Ben Maimon&#45;&#45;&#63;  His biography has enriched every en&#45;<lb/>&#45;cyclopedia.  His works have found admirers and trans&#45;<lb/>&#45;lators almost everywhere.  If Moorish Spain had<lb/> produced only that man&#44; Sephardic Jews would have<lb/> good reason to boast of their extraction.  For a giant of<lb/> intellect was he&#44; and in theology&#44; in philosophy&#44; in<lb/> medicine&#44; in lucidness of expression&#44; in a methodical<lb/> presentation of every subject he treated&#44; Maimonides<lb/> has risen with the highest.  What he wrote in<lb/> Hebrew and in Arabic to systematise the traditions and<lb/> to cast a flood of light on the tenets and doctrines<lb/> of our religion&#44; is simply amazing.  And when we<lb/> bear in mind&#44; that&#44; obliged to leave Spain&#44; through religious fanaticism among Arabs&#44; he became&#44;<lb/> when abroad&#44; court physician to Saladin&#44; the reigning Sultan of<lb/> Egypt&#44; and that in so responsible a cpacity and hold&#45; while<lb/></p> 
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>carrying on a far reaching correspondence with the<lb/> learned of his age&#44; he still wrote profoundly and<lb/> immensely&#44; we must agree that that&#44; to call that Jew of the<lb/> twelfth century Ha&#45;Nesher Ha&#45;Gadol &#34;the great eagle&#44;&#34;<lb/> &#34;a second Moses&#34; is not to unduly exaggerate.<lb/></p>
            <p>But the greater the man&#44; the more readily will his errors<lb/> be detected and call forth will elicit public censure.  We indeed<lb/> ought so to say to wash bathe our lips with in rose water when<lb/> speaking of referring disapprovingly to the actions of one so immeasurably on  above our standing&#44;<lb/> but truth must nevertheless prevail.  In obedience to it&#44;<lb/> we cannot deny that Maimonides gave a reasonable<lb/> cause for opposition.  Thoroughly saturated familiar with Greek<lb/> and Arabian ideas&#44; prevalent predominant in his age&#44; he sometime was misled by them and allowed<lb/> the Bible to be enchained to the wheel of a destructive skeptical doubtful<lb/> philosophy.  Even during his life time the rumb&#45;<lb/>&#45;ling of the thunder which was to burst after his death<lb/> began to be heard&#44; a but at his demise&#44; when the influence<lb/> of his personality and his social position were no longer<lb/> immediately felt&#44; the antagonism held back&#44; broke forth with violence.<lb/>  In Northern France it made itself felt &#91;&#63;&#93; grew irrepressibly terrible&#44; among men<lb/> learned in Talmudism&#44; and unused to the mode of think&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing of their brethren of the south.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>A Rabbi Solomon of Montpellier and two of his pupils<lb/> created an excitement which was to end unhappily&#44; in<lb/> many respects.  David Kimchi was bent with years<lb/> and wore out by literary labors&#44; when he undertook a mis&#45;<lb/>&#45;sion in honor vindication of Maimonides.  He quitted his city and home and<lb/> his city to travel to Castiel&#44; where the distinguished  phy&#45;<lb/>&#45;sician and sage&#44; Judah Alphachar&#44; lived.  He wished to<lb/> interest that influential personage in the defense of our<lb/> second Moses.  He Alphachar should lead all Spanish Rabbis in the<lb/> way of terrifying the French Rabbis of the North into silence.<lb/>  But the zealous defender champion was taken very ill in Avila and<lb/> could not proceed further.  Grieved at that unexpected set<lb/> back&#44; he wrote Alphachar a letter&#44; apologising for<lb/> his inability to personally pay his respects.  That com&#45;<lb/>&#45;munication he sent through one of his nephews.  In it he<lb/> dwelt in the great services which Maimonides had ren&#45;<lb/>&#45;dered Judaism&#44; on the debt of gratitude which all<lb/> owed that celebrated Spaniard&#44; and on the arrogance of his<lb/> detractors.  But Alphachar sided with the latter&#44; and in<lb/> language bitter and burning disclosed his objections<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>to some of the teachings in the philosophical<lb/> writings of Maimonides.  The acrimonious correspondence continued<lb/> and finally the meekness of our David softened the asperity<lb/> of Judah&#39;s temper&#44; but Kimchi did not attain his<lb/> his goodly purpose.  The two parties widened<lb/> into two hostile camps&#44; equally fierce&#44; excomu&#45;<lb/>&#45;nicating one another and dragging their religious quarrels<lb/> to Christian courts&#44; greatly to the detriment of the<lb/> Jewish cause and the horror of many who suffered<lb/> martyrdom.  For the unfortunate dissension<lb/> put a sword into the hand of the enemies of<lb/> our faith.  The Christian clergy in South North France saw in<lb/> the contest waged about the orthodoxy or the &#34;rationalistic&#34;<lb/> views of Maimonides&#44; a suitable opportunity for<lb/> inducing the civil authorities to order the extermination<lb/> of all Hebrew books.  Liturgical and Talmudical&#44;<lb/> philosophical and philological&#44; all were seized and<lb/> delivered to the flames.  But alas&#33; many human beings&#44;<lb/> who lamented the sacrilege&#44; were also cast into the fire&#44; and&#44;<lb/> according to a report&#44; the original instigator of the dispute&#44;<lb/> Rabbi Solomon of Montpellier&#44; and one of his pupils<lb/> met with a fatal death.  Another pupil<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>who repented&#44; but too late&#44; of having defamed aspersed the<lb/> character of the illustrious Sage of Cordova&#44; resolved to go on a pil&#45;<lb/>&#45;grimage to Cairo&#44; and at the grave of Maimonides<lb/> beseech for pardon.  But on reaching Toledo he expired&#44;<lb/> after having endured bodily trials.  It is not at all<lb/> improbable that David Kimchi those sorrowful events<lb/> may have shortened the days of David Kimchi.  He<lb/> returned to Narbonne to bewail what had happened&#44;<lb/> and passed away from earth&#44; to leave behind a name<lb/> which will not die.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
