<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF8_13</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff8_13_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff8_13_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff8_13_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff8_13_2v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>4 pages on 1 sheet<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For a funeral<lb/></p>
            <p>Human sympathy&#44; like the quality of mercy&#44; is twice blessed.  It<lb/> blesses him that gives and him that takes.  The trials to which<lb/> life is unavoidably exposed are measurably lightened&#44; when we are made to feel<lb/> that creatures whose hearts swell&#44; with tender emotions stir up&#44; yearn with com&#45;<lb/>&#45;passion towards us in the hour of distress.  All that have<lb/> gathered here&#44; and a much larger number who are absent&#44; grieve now with a<lb/> the bereaved parent and his sorrow stricken family.  They would&#44; if it lay in<lb/> their power&#44; change this sad scene into one of serene calmness.  They<lb/> would for their own comfort and that of the disconsolate household remove the<lb/> funeral pall and point to joys of which death cannot deprive the<lb/> mortals.  But the suddenness of the stroke&#44; added to many<lb/> wounds repeatedly inflicted by misfortune&#44; paralyzes every effort<lb/> to relieve the pangs of this separation.  With the deepest<lb/> sympathy for the afflicted&#44; I myself fear to express my sentiments&#44;<lb/> lest I intensify pain rather than diminish it by words inadequate<lb/> to the purpose.  But is there nothing which that a<lb/> servant of God may say advantageously to the cause of religion&#44; that which<lb/> is his cause&#44; and to those who suffer at a moment and on an<lb/> occasion so harrowing like the present&#63;  The dear youth whom we<lb/> had hoped to have seen walk upon earth in the pursuit of happiness&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>might furnish ample matter on which to dwell.<lb/></p>
            <p>But I shall not speak of him&#44; nor of the end which&#44; according to<lb/> our finite judgment&#44; he indiscreetly hastened on.  As I believe<lb/> in a Being from whom nature has received the power of indistracti&#45;<lb/>&#45;bility&#44; and as I believe in the eternity of thoughts and feelings&#44; so<lb/> I believe also that I may trust what is immortal of Hyman Joseph<lb/> Levi to the disposition of his celestial Maker.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  &#34;The living&#45;kindness<lb/> of the Lord is from everlasting even to everlasting.&#34;  Forbearing<lb/> then from speaking of the dead&#44; I shall direct my utterances<lb/> to the living.  They who were shocked by the tidings that cast<lb/> a gloom over more than one home&#44; require at my hand such<lb/> assurances as will encourage them to proceed onward in the path<lb/> of usefulness despite drawbacks and hindrances and unkind thrusts.<lb/>  They must be told that in the sight of the Almighty and in<lb/> that of all the good and true&#44; we are clothed with the rank insignia<lb/> of nobility&#44; when we struggle against difficulties and over&#45;<lb/>&#45;come them with manliness&#59; that the glory of having<lb/> arisen superior to surrounding troubles is greater in pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;portion to the humbleness of our station&#44; and that in all<lb/> reality no higher pleasure can be attained by mortals&#44;<lb/> than that of knowing that they held up themselves aloft<lb/> and never sunk under the pressure of adverse circumstances.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>But how very very much it depends upon your&#44;<lb/> o children sons and daughter of Elias P. Levi to improve a melancholy past&#33;<lb/>  Because Take it as the advice of a friend who has been with you on<lb/> occasions of a varied characters&#44; if not as the counsel of a God&#39;s<lb/> servant.  Your father essentially needs your assistance in carrying the<lb/> burden&#44; which had just begun to be somewhat lightened<lb/> by the exertions of Hyman.  You can aid him effectually&#44;<lb/> perhaps not yet in the same manner and extent as the<lb/> dear son child with whom he has now to part&#44; but you can aid<lb/> him by a filial affection which studies how to sweeten life<lb/> on all days and at all hours.  He has claims on your<lb/> dutifulness and on upon an even conduct on your part&#44; attended<lb/> with domestic blessings.  I verily believe that this scene<lb/> with all its sadness will be productive of happiness&#44; if<lb/> it is capable of drawing now from you a tacit promise<lb/> that by unfailing kindness to one another&#44; by considerate<lb/> and delicate attention to all the members of your parent&#39;s<lb/> household&#44; and by tender love to him who labors steadfast&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly for your welfare&#44; you will render your home a habi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tation of tranquility and peace.  Let me pray that<lb/> the Almighty may inspire your hearts with such feelings&#44;<lb/> for your sake and the honor of the Jewish community.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Grant it O Eternal Lord&#33;  Great is the sorrow into<lb/> which this unforeseen event has plunged a family in<lb/> Israel.  Oh command celestial comfort to soothe grief.<lb/>  Be with the sorely tired father&#44; and endow him with<lb/> the capacity power to bear the stroke with pious resignation.<lb/>  Infuse into his children sentiments a spirit of godliness&#44; and vouch&#45;<lb/>&#45;safe to give the inmates of this habitation and all their<lb/> relatives a mind to join to in smoothing a path hitherto rug&#45;<lb/>&#45;ged and steep.  May in all one m of them be fulfilled<lb/> the sentence of Thy prophet &#34;I will turn their mourning<lb/> into joy and console them.&#34;  And for the dear<lb/> youth so suddenly brought before Thy august presence we<lb/> also pray.  May his shortcomings during his short few years&#39;<lb/> pilgrimage on earth be forgiven&#44; and an everlasting<lb/> life of beatitude be apportioned to him among the saints<lb/> who preceded his coming in to the regions of spirituality.<lb/>  May his entrance be greeted among amidst higher intelligences that<lb/> are imparadised in the contemplation of Thee&#44; O author<lb/> of all things&#44; Father of all mankind&#44; Protector and<lb/> Saviour of Thy people Israel.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
