<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF4_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1882-01" source="" attested="yes">1882</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_2_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>In behalf of the Y M H A<lb/>
                for Sabbath Ha&#45;gadol<lb/>
                1882<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren<lb/></p>
            <p>This is the Young Men&#39;s Hebrew Association day.<lb/>  It means that the Jewish pulpit at Philadelphia is&#44; by exercises and ceremonies of a fitting character shall direct general<lb/> special request to be devoted to the interests of an attention to an organization of commanding importance.  The pulpit has been<lb/> institution in our city which has for its aim the mental invited to take an active part&#44; and cast its influence on the side of learning.  Acknowledged<lb/> as a power&#44; the pulpit has been asked to labor in the interest of what that which aims at the<lb/> elevation of our youths&#44; through by the great moral lever&#45;&#45;know&#45; culture.<lb/> &#45;ledge.  The object is most holy&#44; and&#44; were it progressively carried<lb/> out to its full full extent&#44; the advocacy would give thereof on this a Sabbath impart a still would lend additional<lb/> sanctity to the Sabbath set apart for that purpose designated day.<lb/>  It would give to this day this a rightful title to the time&#45;<lb/>honored epithet of &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  For Nay&#58; if our ancestors called<lb/> it so because of the officiating Rabbi&#39;s urgnt urgent solicitation concerning<lb/> the observance of the forthcoming Passover our the present ministerial appeal would<lb/> have a still raise it still higher&#59; in importance&#44; since it concerns that appeal seeks itself not only<lb/> about the permanence of one precept of the Law&#44; but about the transmission to posterity of<lb/> all our religious the learning which should lead to a well&#45;founded piety.  But in obedience to truth&#44;<lb/> I acknowledge own that so far that comprehensive learning has been allowed<lb/> simply a subordinate place in the institution for which I plead.  The wish of<lb/> the right&#45;thinking that it might occupy the prominence station<lb/> to which it has a primary claim remains yet unfulfilled.<lb/>  I shall necessarily confine my remarks to that which applies to Philadelphia.<lb/>  The first year of the Association opened brightly.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Its promises were very encouraging inspiriting.  The second also<lb/> commanded elicited the active zeal approval of its members the intelligent.  But<lb/> the succeeding years failed to evince&#44; in its literary de&#45;<lb/>&#45;partment&#44; a gradual progression advancement towards a loftier standard.<lb/>  For&#44; admitting that the young men of our faith&#44; are not<lb/> essentially different form those of their age in other<lb/> denominations&#44; and hence that they ought to may with propriety be drawn towards<lb/> the our association by other various diversified various inducements&#44; besides those&#44;<lb/> which popular lectures on their history and literature<lb/> hold out&#44; still nevertheless it behooves us nevertheless to keep always in sight the chief main<lb/> features purpose of our organization.  It is undeniably certain that<lb/> entertainments and diversions&#44; such as are often given afforded us&#44;<lb/> may be procured otherwise beyond its pale&#59; not so&#44; however&#44; ample<lb/> information on the writings and writers of our people.<lb/>  And that the institution has &#91;&#63;&#93; pledged itself to give&#44; and that should be frequent and ample and thorough.....<lb/>  But who ought to charge with being a dereliction from remissiveness in the pursuit of<lb/> a duty&#63;  Can I in all honesty lay the sin of omission at<lb/> the door of the appointed officials&#63;  Should I Ought I to condemn them in your<lb/> presence as men incapable of appreciating their responsible task&#44;<lb/> or as half&#45;hearted in its performance&#63;  No&#58; I have rea&#45;<lb/>&#45;sons to believe that earnestness has never been wanting among<lb/> those to whose have had care the direction of the association was confided.<lb/>  to their care  I know that several have been the plans<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>devised for fostering and spreading far and wide<lb/> the learning culture which Jewish youths ought to possess.<lb/>  But the most energetic2 and conscientious1 must fail<lb/> in their endeavours&#44; when instead of meeting with encouragement&#44; they find by the way only they meet but indifference and<lb/> frivolity.  These&#44; I condemn&#44; these I do denounce and<lb/> profoundly lament.  as&#44; I grieve as I behold their prevalence of such feelings among<lb/> my young brothers and sisters in faith.  Apathy is<lb/> the clog which keeps back the wheel of progress which that<lb/> our association had set in motion by our association.  Senselessness prevents<lb/> a study necessary needful at all times&#44; but most imperative essential<lb/> now because needed requisite requisite now as an arm of <sic>defence</sic> against<lb/> false accusation&#44; tempting surroundings&#44; aspersions&#44; insinuations&#44;<lb/> taunts and jeers.  So long as our sons and<lb/> daughters prefer to not to acquire vulgarly set to ridicule a task for their<lb/> people&#39;s literature&#59; so long as they will rather laugh than<lb/> think&#44; be amused rather than be instructed taught&#44; institutions like<lb/> that in Philadelphia&#44; in whose behalf I am requested<lb/> to plead&#44; must disappoint fall short of the expectations of eager souls&#44; prayful souls that<lb/> anxious longing for the moral elevation exaltation of our race.<lb/>
                Who more than I has cause to sympathise with the<lb/> officials&#44; who labor in their stirrings to plant knowledge and make it fruitful&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Allow Suffer me to say it&#58; At home&#44; in schools&#44; and at<lb/> Synagogues&#59; in the mornings&#44; in the afternoons&#44; and<lb/> in the evenings&#59; at ay any season&#44; on any day&#44; and<lb/> at all hours I have placed myself at the disposal<lb/> of the Hebrew Community&#44; irrespective of congregational<lb/> preferences&#44; but few&#44; very few have cared to avail<lb/> themselves of my gratuitous offer.  When I Last<lb/> year&#44; when I announced my intention to deliver a course of<lb/> lectures on subjects which I considered useful&#44; some of<lb/> my coreligionists signified their approbation.  The at&#45;<lb/>&#45;tendance however was not so large such as to justify my belief pride<lb/> in the sincerity by reason of that commendation&#59; it was not calculated<lb/> to inspire infuse into me with fresh courage renewed vigour and hope.  This year my<lb/> historical series have hitherto created no perceptible change for the<lb/> better.  I hear persons occasionally remark&#58; &#34;The attend&#45;<lb/>&#45;ance was large today.&#34;  Perhaps so.  But not of the element to which<lb/> I most anxiously look for the perpetuation of our race and<lb/> religion.  That element is very thinly always represented scantily&#59; for<lb/> many a number many of our daughters are attracted to localities where<lb/> finery are is displayed&#44; and some of our sons&#44; who are enjoy<lb/> at leisure leisure&#44; have their minds engaged at the gaming<lb/> board.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>A number of the youngest do frequent&#45;&#45;to litt a certain age&#45;&#45;this dwelling<lb/> of prayer&#44; but not always to the honor of the Lord sacred divine worship.<lb/>  They often give me cause for mortification by their<lb/> leaving and returning with noisy steps&#44; And demeanour.  Only two<lb/> sabbaths ago&#44; I was deeply pained in noticing several<lb/> strangers of the Nazarene church calling each other&#39;s attention to our boys wran&#45; to their leaving &#38; returning at pleasure&#44; aye&#44;<lb/> &#45;glings and alterations and wranglings&#44; while the divine service was being<lb/> performed.  How to effect a reform in<lb/> the moral sense of our youths&#59; how to raise the future<lb/> representatives of Judaism to a higher plane&#45;&#45;that is<lb/> the burning question&#44; which I have studied long and<lb/> worried over.  It is not easy of solution&#44; but<lb/> God does not demand of us feeble&#45;handed creatures impossibilities.  We ought It is wrong<lb/> not therefore to reject as useless any aid whenever and wherever proferred.<lb/>  I shall never As to myself I shall under no circumstance&#44; counsel the extinction of established<lb/> organizations&#45;&#45;be they charitable&#44; religious or literary&#45;&#45;be&#45;<lb/>cause they did have not fully realized the expectations anticipations of their<lb/> founders.  Unless their the tendencies thereof are openly at variance<lb/> with the ostensible declared object of their creation I shall<lb/> welcome the small measure of their cooperative work.  For&#44; what one<lb/> institution cannot singly secure&#44; the united action of<lb/> many may bring about.  The school is a<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>fulcrum&#44; the synagogue a lever&#44; but young men&#39;s<lb/> Hebrew Associations are still also a force.  They We should be<lb/> hail them as an agency to uplift what is meanly low.<lb/>  Even as a medium of social intercourse&#44; bringing our offspring<lb/> together&#44; and withdrawing them from the allurements of an<lb/> exclusive companionship with non&#45;Israelites&#44; our organiza&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion may prove a power.  But it has accomplished<lb/> more than a negative good.  It has in those of our faith measurably encouraged elocu&#45;<lb/>&#45;tionary and musical talents in those of our faith&#59; it has occasionally called<lb/> forth the latent abilities of men and women of our the Hebrew race&#59;<lb/> it has repeatedly engaged the services of scholars in various departments&#44;<lb/>&#45;&#45;thus trying&#44; at least&#44; to awaken a task for religious and<lb/> secular culture&#59; it has formed a library to arouse excite a wish desire<lb/> for information&#59; and it has consolidated&#44;&#45;&#45;as far as it lay<lb/> within their its reach&#44; various branches of the organization and<lb/> it has opened thereby a useful interchange of thought by through the publication<lb/> of a bi monthly Bulletin.  I wish it therefore god&#45;speed&#44;<lb/> and say to its officials &#34;Persevere&#59; if but a few will<lb/> second your efforts&#44; the advantage will be on the side of a<lb/> noble cause&#45;&#45;the triumph of an intellectual religion Judaism.  But as the communication I received&#44;<lb/> asked that I should advise as well as plead for&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>I venture to suggest that our association institution be<lb/> for the present moderate in its aspirations.  More than elaborate lectures<lb/> on different topics&#44; addresses of a conversational character <sic>conversional</sic> addresses&#44; sittings at which<lb/> explanatory of the character of men&#44; of books and of doctrines&#44;<lb/> might are explained ought to be sought for chosen.  The adoption of that plan<lb/> might popularize a knowledge greatly needed.  by our youths In like manner&#44;<lb/> Some familiar talks about the Hebrew language&#44; its arrangement construction<lb/> and logical construction must composition syntax might also form a part of next year&#39;s<lb/> course of to as laid out by the Literary committee.  But this it should<lb/>  be remembered that this is composed of men&#44; and as such men they look for the sympathetic<lb/> support of brethren.  They will feel that their energies expand grow powerful&#44;<lb/> that their capacities to discover attractions for our sons and daughters of a refining and<lb/> elevating nature&#44; &#91;&#63;&#93; expand in proportion&#44; as our community will<lb/> prove its appreciation of well&#45;directed endeavours.  In the<lb/> hope to of stirring up general interest&#44; this Sabbath day was chosen set apart as<lb/> the Young men&#39;s Hebrew Associaion day. a special festivity.  The pulpit will have per&#45;<lb/>formed a sacred obligation&#44; if it succeeds in augmenting the<lb/> number of subscribers contributors and patrons to a literary institution organization.<lb/>  But it will have deserved well of Judaism&#44; and made rendered<lb/> this a truly &#91;Hebrew&#93; if it can rally our youths&#44;<lb/> round the organization institution in whose behalf it must appeal&#44;<lb/> with a new spirit&#59; opr if it can stripping them of a spirit<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>of indifference and frivolity&#44; and causing &#91;&#63;&#93; impell them to<lb/> put on a spirit of intelligence and serious application.<lb/>  When another year shall have passed rolled away and this season<lb/> will arrive&#44; the pulpit may have then a legitimate cause<lb/> cause for reason to glorying over its achievement&#44; pointing to<lb/> the improvements of the Y M H Association&#44; as reflected in the<lb/> culture&#44; moral standing&#44; and religious knowledge of its<lb/> thousnads vastly increased numbers.  Brethren.  Say Urge your offspring to say&#58; &#34;it shall bes so.&#34; and<lb/> and it will be.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
