<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF5_11</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_11_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_11_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_11_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_11_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_11_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_11_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_11_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_11_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_11_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_11_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_11_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_11_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_11_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_11_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_11_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_11_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>13 pages on 6 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Post Biblical<lb/>
                54<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>There are two personages&#44; figuring conspicuously in post<lb/> Biblical literature&#44; whose names&#44; represented by their<lb/> Hebrew initials&#45;&#45;as customary about Rabbis&#45;&#45;sound very<lb/> much alike&#44; but whose minds and temperament differ<lb/> greatly.  Rambam&#44; stands for &#34;Rabbi Moses son of<lb/> Maimon&#34;; Ramban signifies &#34;Rabbi Moses son<lb/> of Nachman.&#34;  All have recognized in the first<lb/> the man of universal fame&#45;&#45;Maimonides.  The<lb/> second has not gained so wide a reputation&#44; but in<lb/> the history of Rabbinism he occupies a lofty position.<lb/>  I have had occasion before to allude to the bitter<lb/> contest&#44; which the certain philosophical ideas advanced<lb/> by the Sage of Cordova&#44; stirred up among scholars both<lb/> in Northern France and in some cities on the Ebro and the Dal&#45;<lb/>&#45;quivir.  It may be remembered also the<lb/> zealous but fruitless endeavour of David Kimchi<lb/> to turn away wrath by soft answers.  Ramban&#44;<lb/> better known as &#34;Nachmanides&#44;&#34; had not been<lb/> an indifferent spectator at the exciting scenes which<lb/> attended a raging controversy.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Born at Gerona&#44; in Spain&#44; fifty or sixty years<lb/> after Maimonides&#44; that is&#44; in 1195 of the vulgar era&#44; he too had studied<lb/> Greek and Arabic philosophy&#44; but in his con&#45;<lb/>&#45;ception Aristotle and Avicenna should have had no<lb/> room&#44; where Moses and Judah the Prince sat as masters.<lb/>  He contended that our seeking support to the Law and<lb/> traditions by in the reasonings of men strangers to the<lb/> Jewish faith&#44; was objectionable.  Nevertheless&#44; Nach&#45;<lb/>&#45;manides honored the author of Moreh Nebuchim &#34;the<lb/> teacher of the perplexed&#44;&#34; and felt pained at the reviling<lb/> of so great a man.  Accordingly&#44; he addressed the<lb/> Synagogues of Aragon&#44; Navarre and Castile and exhorted<lb/> all to Judge calmly and dispassionately.  He held that trying<lb/> to belittle the giant of intellect who arose from<lb/> Cordova&#44; would be like imagining that the sun at its<lb/> meridian can be obscured by the outstretched wings<lb/> of a pigeon birds.  He argued that Maimonides may<lb/> have written the book which reflects Greek and<lb/> Arabic thoughts&#44; for persons who associated with<lb/> non Israelites in high office&#44; and who may need<lb/> arguments drawn from such sources to rebut<lb/> sophistry.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>In reality&#44; Nachmanides did not approve of many<lb/> a sentiment to which his illustrious predecessors<lb/> had given currency.  But neither would he join<lb/> the detractors of a Rabbi&#44; whose preeminent services<lb/> to Talmudical learning lore none dared ignore.  All the<lb/> persuasions of French and Spanish friends to <sic>enrol</sic><lb/> him among the adversaries of the son of Maimon availed<lb/> nothing.  He Nachmanides remained un<sic>yeilding</sic> in his deference<lb/> to the philosopher&#44; without sharing his views.<lb/>  And how could he&#44; who swore fealty to a speculative<lb/> science that had just begun to spread its influence<lb/> abroad&#44; agree with Maimonides&#45;&#45;a thinker methodic&#45;<lb/>&#45;al and gravely practical&#63;  For&#44; Nachmanides had<lb/> become an ardent follower of Kabbalism&#44; or as moderns<lb/> like to call it &#34;theosophy&#34;.  In it he saw the solution<lb/> of questions which obtrude themselves on the human<lb/> mind&#44; when reflecting upon natural and revealed religion.<lb/>  This is not the occasion on which I should discuss<lb/> the truthfulness or falseness of a science&#45;&#45;if we may<lb/> justly so term it&#45;&#45;that has&#44; to this day enthusiastic adherents<lb/> and determined opponents.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>But I may venture to say that while theoretic&#45;<lb/>&#45;ally Kabbalism can do society no harm&#44; to society practically it<lb/> has wrought abundant mischief.  All who<lb/> have read such descriptions as those in the &#34;Jews of<lb/> Barnow&#34; by Emil Carl Franzos&#44; may form an<lb/> idea of the ill effects of a pretentious wonder&#45;making working<lb/> Kabbalism.  Nachmanides was too strong in<lb/> knowledge to bend under the yoke of superstitions&#44;<lb/> but he sincerely accepted&#44; as religious verities mere<lb/> speculations&#44; about the Infinite and Unknowable.<lb/>  That sincerity we must respect.  As an<lb/> author&#44; our Moses was a prodigy.  When I first<lb/> met with a rhythmical composition of his in Ara&#45;<lb/>&#45;maic&#44; prefacing a book which he wrote in defence<lb/> of a great teacher in Israel&#45;&#45;Isaac Alphasi&#44; who abridged<lb/> the Talmud&#45;&#45;&#44; I could not persuade convince myself that it<lb/> had emanated from a lad in his fifteenth year.<lb/>  From early youth to an advanced age his the restless<lb/> pen of the Gerona Israelite was devoted to a single purpose&#45;&#45;to illustrate<lb/> the learning which Talmudism in its ritual depart&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment has treasured up.  Quite contrary to<lb/> Maimonides&#44; who wished simply to lay down the results<lb/> of Rabbinical discussions&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>and let debates and digressions go unrecorded or unstudied&#44; Nach&#45;<lb/>&#45;manides&#44; prompted by veneration for the Sages&#44; would<lb/> dwell and enlarge upon and add to that which regards<lb/> the argumentations held touching rites and observances.  He was well fitted for<lb/> the undertaking&#44; for his equipments in Jewish literature<lb/> were complete.  He showed that in his multifarious<lb/> productions and notably so in his critical annotations<lb/> on &#34;Sepher Ha&#45;Mitzvoth&#34;&#44; the book of precepts by<lb/> Maimonides.  A warm admirer of our<lb/> Moses of Gerona&#44; was the immortal Moses of<lb/> Dessau.  All are aware that Mendelssohn gave<lb/> German Jews a confessedly beautiful translation<lb/> of the Pentateuch.  But he enriched it with a<lb/> Hebrew commentary in which he was helped by several<lb/> scholars.  In that comment&#44; Nachmanides appears<lb/> conspicuously&#44; for many an elucidation and original borrowed of him by the German<lb/> idea expositor.  For&#44; barring Kabbalistic notions to which he<lb/> was wedded&#44; and to which all will not subscribe&#44; that<lb/> Spanish Jew must be credited with the possession of a<lb/> clear and searching understanding&#44; and he evinced it in<lb/> his Chiddushe Torah&#44; or &#34;explanations upon the Torah.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>But what must still endear the memory<lb/> of Nachmanides even to those who&#44; in our times&#44;<lb/> are incapable of appreciating his numerous writ&#45;<lb/>&#45;ings&#44; is the zeal he displayed for the preser&#45;<lb/>&#45;vation of his people&#39;s honor.  James I&#44; who<lb/> reigned in Aragon and in some parts of South<lb/> France&#44; was covered with the leprosy of sin.  How<lb/> should he cleanse away that moral filth&#63;  His<lb/> father confessor&#44; Raimond Poniaforte&#44; suggested the<lb/> course he must take.  Let Jews&#44; who deny the<lb/> efficacy of the vicarious blood&#44; said to have been spilled<lb/> in Calvary&#44; be presented.  The more they suffer&#44; of their blood is drawn&#44;<lb/> the purer will the profligate ruler become.  The<lb/> ultimate object was to compel apostasy by oppressive<lb/> measures.  As means to that end&#44; the father forerunner of<lb/> confessor Torquemada charged Paul Christian&#45;&#45;a renegade disciple<lb/> of his&#45;&#45;to go on a mission tour and preach the<lb/> gospel.  But Jews&#44; in their proverbial stiff necked&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness&#44; refused to turn&#44;  Disappointed&#59; the subtle<lb/> confessor begged his royal master to invite to the<lb/> court Nachmanides&#44; whose knowledge erudition and<lb/> influence had been acknowledged far and wide.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>There&#44; in the presence of all high officials&#44; he<lb/> should enter into a debate with Paul Christian.<lb/>  Like a thunder bolt was the summons to Nach&#45;<lb/>&#45;manides.  But he must obey.  Humbly he<lb/> besought the king to be allowed freedom of<lb/> speech&#44; that he might&#44; unconstrained&#44; rebut the<lb/> attacks upon his ancestral faith.  He was granted<lb/> the request.  Four long days&#45;&#45;from the 20th to the 24th<lb/> of July 1263&#45;&#45;the controversy went on continued.  The<lb/> opponent of Judaism set forth cited&#44; among other ar&#45;<lb/> &#45;guments sayings&#44; Talmudical legends and tales to prove<lb/> that Jews are cut off from all hopes of a<lb/> restoration to nationality&#59; that they are doomed to<lb/> remain scattered everywhere and dispersed unredeemed&#44; and because Nachmanides<lb/> frankly confessed that whatever the Talmud con&#45;<lb/>&#45;tains outside of traditional laws&#44; has no binding<lb/> force upon Israelites&#44; he was violently disputed<lb/> against and declared a heretic from a Jewish stand<lb/> point.  The accused did not flinch.  He bravely<lb/> stood his ground and came off victorious.  The<lb/> final issue&#44; however&#44; was sorrowful&#44; for the un&#45;<lb/>&#45;scrupulous confessor&#44; angered at having seen the Jew<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Courageously defend his own belief&#44; induced James<lb/> I. to compel Hebrews&#44; under his government&#44; to<lb/> admit Paul Christian in their synagogues and<lb/> colleges&#44; listen respectfully to the aspersions cast upon Judaism<lb/> and supply the apostate with all the books which<lb/> he asked for.  That plan&#44; often tried in later<lb/> ages to no purpose&#44; proved barren of any looked for the anticipated<lb/> fruits also in Spain and France of the 13th century.<lb/>  Cut to the quick&#44; the recreant preacher appealed<lb/> to the Papal Sec authority.  He asserted that the Talmud<lb/> blasphemes against the man of Nazareth and<lb/> the creed he founded&#44; therefore it ought to be<lb/> publicly burned.  Clemens IV. gave credence<lb/> to the imputation and ordered commanded that wherever copies<lb/> of the Talmud depository of our traditions were found&#44; they should be delivered<lb/> into the hands of learned priests for examination.<lb/>  If anything objectionable be detested&#44; a blazing<lb/> fire shall consume volumes&#44; that all good Christ&#45;<lb/>ians must hate.  James temporized.  Suspecting<lb/> the appointed censors&#44; he applied to Raimond Martin&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>a learned Catholic&#44; acquainted with Hebrew&#44;<lb/> Aramaic and Arabic.  The king would abide by<lb/> that priest&#39;s scholar&#39;s decision.  He is reported to have said<lb/> that&#44; while certain passages in the Talmud can be<lb/> construed as an attack on Christianity&#44; there are<lb/> others which may be interpreted as favoring it.<lb/>  He advised that the censor&#39;s pen cross off the form&#45;<lb/>&#45;er and urged that for the sake of the latter&#44; the work<lb/> ought to remain unscathed.  Nachmanides may have rejoiced at the past he took&#44; to vindicate Israel and but was he<lb/> Nachmanides Judaism&#44; but was he wise in issuing a pamphlet which<lb/> described his triumphant rebuttal of a recreant<lb/> adversary&#63;  Possibly discretion might have urged suggested<lb/> silence&#44; yet it was natural in the Rabbi who<lb/> loved his people and religion&#44; to let all know<lb/> that the Law of Sinai and its oral teaching<lb/> need not fear the venomous onslaughts of enemies.<lb/>  The news of that pamphlet reached Rome.  The high<lb/> Pontiff reproached King James with favoritism towards<lb/> Jews&#44; and claimed that Moses Ben Nachman was<lb/> allowed with impunity to defy Christianity&#44; by his<lb/> speech and by his pen.  The ruler feared the dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;pleasure of one&#44; who&#44; in those days could launch<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>an anathemas that dethroned monarchs&#44; and<lb/> ordered Nachmanides to bid country&#44; family&#44; and<lb/> pupils a lasting farewell.  Nearly three score years and<lb/> ten was the Gerona sage&#44; when forced to take up<lb/> the pilgrim&#39;s staff.  Since Spain cast him off&#44; what<lb/> land could be dearer to his heart than that where the<lb/> patriarchs lay buried and whose soil prophets had hallowed&#63;<lb/>  He wended his steps to Palestine.  The time was<lb/> unpropitious&#44; for the Mongols had shortly before<lb/> overrun the country&#44; and nothing but signs of<lb/> devastation met the eyes of the exile.  In a<lb/> letter to his son Nachman&#44; he draws a most dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;mal picture of the state of the cities through which<lb/> he passed.  But the aged servant of the Lord did not wash his last<lb/> years in useless repinings.  He gathered around<lb/> him apt scholars and those he instructed with<lb/> all the earnestness of his soul.  In<lb/> Jaffa Cayapha&#44; where Providence would that the Spanish<lb/> Rabbi should find a grave in his 75th year&#44; disciples<lb/> and admirers paid the learned and pious preceptor<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p>a tribute of profound veneration.  We<lb/> may regret that the reverence felt&#44; exceeded<lb/> the bounds of wisdom&#44; for whereas Nachmanides<lb/> descried that his adherence to the Kabbalah&#44;<lb/> or mystic science&#44; might not lead minds astray&#44;<lb/> some of his followers magnified his powers<lb/> after his decease&#44; the Rabbi had lain with his fathers by the report of miracles<lb/> which he had performed&#44; and but which no sober think&#45;<lb/>&#45;er would credit.  How sensible the<lb/> counsel of the author of Ecclesiastes&#45;&#45;that<lb/> book of the Apocrypha which is the best and the<lb/> most useful&#45;&#45;&#34;What is too far above the search<lb/> not&#59; what is too deeply hidden from thee&#44; seek<lb/> not&#59; reflect on that which thou art permitted<lb/> to grasp and busy not thyself with secret<lb/> things.&#34;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
