<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF10_4</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_4_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_4_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_4_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_4_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_4_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_4_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_4_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_4_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_4_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_4_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_4_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff10_4_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>About prophecy proven from<lb/>
                the unchanged existence of the<lb/>
                descendants of Ishmael.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>About twenty three years ago&#44; referring to a passage&#44;<lb/> which a brother&#44; as a lad&#44; had then recited for his Bar<lb/> Mitzva portion&#44; I summoned history to testify to the<lb/> truth of revelation.  The words with which the section<lb/> of this Sabbath concludes&#44; reminded me of that circumstance&#44;<lb/> and suggested the propriety of presenting to a new ge&#45;<lb/>&#45;neration ideas wherewith which they may never have met.<lb/>  Reducing into a narrow compass what I said in another<lb/> occasion at considerable length&#59; repeating&#44; knowingly&#44;<lb/> none of its phraseology&#44; I shall proceed to show how<lb/> a promise made to Abraham was fulfilled to the<lb/> very letter.  You all remember the vision in which<lb/> the patriarch was told that he would become the father<lb/> of a child&#44; with whose descendants the Deity designed to<lb/> enter into an everlasting covenant.  He appeared<lb/> incredulous about the consummation of that event.<lb/>  Happy in the possession of a son by Sarah&#39;s hand&#45;maid&#44; he<lb/> asked for no higher favor from his Maker&#59; and prayed<lb/> that Ishmael might live before the Lord&#59; meaning&#44; that<lb/> though Providence should not choose that child as the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>means of perpetuating the belief in the Unity&#44;<lb/> his descendants might nevertheless be a nation indestruct&#45;<lb/>&#45;ible.  That prayer&#44; which the purest lips breathed&#44;<lb/> stands yet before the throne of God.  It has lost none<lb/> of its efficacy.  In like manner&#44; as we&#44; the seed of<lb/> Isaac&#44; have existed for upwards of thirty five centuries to<lb/> prove the stability of the ancient covenant&#44; so has the<lb/> seed of Ishmael existed as a Divine fulfilment of<lb/> the petition made by a righteous parent.  Verily&#58;<lb/> this historical fact is one of the brightest illustrations of<lb/> the sentence enunciated in the Decalogue&#44; that God will<lb/> keep His kindness to the thousandth generation of those<lb/> who love Him and observe His commandments.  The sacred<lb/> inspired annalist&#44; penetrating the future&#44; registered in our<lb/> Parasha these memorable words &#34;In the face of all his brethren<lb/> he dwelt.&#34;  Aye&#58; Gifted with an imperishable life&#44; the progeny<lb/> of Abraham&#39;s first son&#44; saw face to face families and<lb/> nationalities that have played a noisy part on the<lb/> stage of the world&#44; but who have been hushed in a<lb/> grave from which there is no resurrection.  The so<lb/> called authorized version misapprehending the important<lb/> text&#44; translated &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;He died before all his<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>brethren&#34;&#44; forgetting that though the Hebrew term &#34;Nafal&#34; means<lb/> to fall&#44; it signifies also to spread oneself&#44; to expand one&#39;s<lb/> strength.  To whom does this Biblical allusion apply&#63;<lb/>  To whom&#44; but to the unconquered and unconquerable tribe<lb/> that rove at large in Arabia&#63;  The Bedouins owe<lb/> their independent existence from a remote age even unto<lb/> this hour&#44; to the declaration of him &#34;who is not a man<lb/> that he should lie&#44; nor a son of man that he should repent.&#34;<lb/>  Before their founder had been born&#44; an angel had typi&#45;<lb/>&#45;fied their character and history by the following graphic<lb/> description.  &#34;He will be a wild man&#44; his hand will be<lb/> against all&#44; and the hand of all against him&#59; but he<lb/> shall dwell in the face of all his brethren.&#34;  And when<lb/> the godly parent added his entreaty for his child&#39;s eternity<lb/> of name upon earth&#44; the Lord answered &#34;As for Ishmael<lb/> I have heard thee&#44; behold I have blessed him&#44; and I will<lb/> make him fruitful&#44; and multiply him exceedingly.......<lb/> I will make of him a great nation.&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>Tremendous have been the engines of destruction <sic>levelled</sic><lb/> against at the posterity of Hagar&#44; but the hand which<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>directed them was palsied.  Nattions considered<lb/> the pioneers of civilization&#59; others looked upon as bar&#45;<lb/>&#45;barians&#44; spent their energies in the vain effort of tying<lb/> to the yoke the freedom&#45;loving sons of the desert.<lb/>  Egypt in her palmy days dragged many a potentate<lb/> behind her triumphal chariot&#59; but the people shielded<lb/> by Abraham&#39;s prayer could not be so trailed through the<lb/> dust.  She who&#44; by her inventive genius&#44; raised pyra&#45;<lb/>&#45;mids&#44; which have defied time and its sweeping stream&#44;<lb/> could not lower down from their heights the rovers of<lb/> steep mountains.  From thence they saw her power decay<lb/> and perish.  Assyria&#44; the boastful&#44; who said<lb/> that with the sole of her feet she could dry up all rivers&#44;<lb/> and batter down beseiged cities&#59; the once famous country<lb/> of Semiranus&#44; which we Hebrews have had cause so much<lb/> to dread&#44; &#91;&#63;&#93; did not lift up the iron rod to scourge into submission the progeny<lb/> of Ishmael.  That thunder&#45;bolt of war&#44; Nebu&#45;<lb/>&#45;cadnezar&#44; at whose nod empires bowed obediently&#44; was<lb/> foiled in his attempt to reduce the vigour of the semi&#45;savage but<lb/> spirited Bedouins.  To Cyrus&#44; who placed upon<lb/> his head the double crown he wrested from his wicked<lb/> grand sire&#44; exceeding power was given in the name of the<lb/> Lord.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>For&#44; so wrote of him Isaiah&#44; a hundred and fifty years<lb/> before his birth &#34;Thus saith the Lord of His anointed to Cyrus&#44;<lb/> whose right&#45;hand I have holden&#44; to subdue nations before<lb/> him&#44; and loosen the loins of kings&#59; to open before him doors&#44;<lb/> and gates shall not be shut.  I will go before them him&#44; and make<lb/> crooked ways straight&#44; I will break in pieces the gates of<lb/> brass&#44; and cut in sunder the bars of iron.&#34;  But the Lord<lb/> who raised that Persian monarch for the sake of the seed<lb/> of Isaac&#44; whom he restored to liberty&#44; did not suffer him to<lb/> humiliate the seed of Ishmael.  Alexander mis&#45;<lb/>called the great&#44; who studied with Aristotle a philosophy<lb/> which could not check his brutal passions&#44; and learnt by from<lb/> the art of strategy to hold in the hollow of his hand a vast empire&#44;<lb/> which he left to be broken up&#44; had devised extensive plans<lb/> against Arabia&#44; and determined to exterminate the<lb/> Bedouins.  But death cut short all his resolutions.<lb/>  The Roman eagle that tore our flesh&#44; and carried us<lb/> bleeding to distant regions&#44; did not flap her terrific<lb/> wings over the mountains&#44; in the clefts of which the<lb/> descendants of Ishmael can make their habitations.<lb/>  Nor did the Asiatic princes who in turn ruled the East&#44;<lb/> completely subject these warlike and hardy sons of the desert.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>The elasticity of their nature is such&#44; that chained<lb/> down to day&#44; they break the fetters rebound to morrow&#44; and forge<lb/> the fetters into swords and spears against to strike therewith their conquerors.<lb/>  In habits&#44; in dress &#38; in manners thirty generations have wrought<lb/> among that nomadic tribe scarcely a change.  And if the<lb/> Sultan claims to have amalgamated them fused into the Ottoman<lb/> empire&#44; his mastery over them is but nominal.  It is<lb/> constantly defied&#44; or totally ignored.  Never will the posterity of<lb/> Abraham&#39;s first child be blotted out.  He who declared us<lb/> deathless&#44; promised also that our half&#45;brother&#44;&#45;&#45;because he<lb/> is our father&#39;s son&#45;&#45;shall remain indestructible.  To<lb/> the child of Sarah was given an eternity of spirituality&#44; to<lb/> be maintained at the cost of unequalled hardships&#44; &#38; suf&#45;<lb/>&#45;ferings and martyrdom&#59; to the child of Sarah&#39;s hand&#45;<lb/>maid&#44; was given an eternity of temporality&#44; despite a<lb/> worlds opposition.  &#34;He shall dwell in the face of all<lb/> his brethren&#34; an angel had said&#44; and to the entreaty of the<lb/> pattern of believers&#44; the Divinity had replied &#34;As for Ishmael<lb/> I have heard thee&#44; behold&#44; I have blessed him&#44; and I will<lb/> make him fruitful&#44; and multiply him exceedingly....<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>I will make of him a great nation.  Moses<lb/> recorded these incidents&#44; and peering into the future<lb/> wrote in our Parasha &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Before all<lb/> his brethren he spread himself.&#34;  Here stands his&#45;<lb/>&#45;tory.  Loudly and emphatically it proclaims the truth<lb/> of inspiration.  The proof it advances is not of yesterday.<lb/>  It is backed by the testimony of ages.  It is brought immedia&#45;<lb/>&#45;tely under our immediate vision.  They who refuse to believe must close<lb/> their eyes tight to a meridian sun&#44; and swear it does not shine.<lb/>  But to you&#44; Brethren&#44; who have been called &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> faithful children of faithful parents&#44; I will ask say.<lb/>  Brethren&#33;  Is the volume which contains that patent truth&#44;<lb/> worthy of our meditation&#63;  Or is it too antiquated for us<lb/> moderns&#63;  Shall we cast it into a new mould&#44; and<lb/> remodel it to suit the squeamish taste of some would&#45;be moralist&#44; or<lb/> shall we retain it as our unsophisticated predecessors&#44; the<lb/> Massorites&#44; endeavoured with the minutest accuracy to pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;serve it&#63;  I am none of those who hold in reverence the<lb/> bare wording of ancient writings. but in the I know that the<lb/> spirit and not the letter giveth life&#44; but in the book of books<lb/> nothing should ought to be slurred as of little significance.  The<lb/> Kabbalists assert that the whole of the Pentateuch should<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>be regarded with extreme sanctity because it comprises<lb/> numerically or by anagrams names of the Deity&#44; I affirm<lb/> that it comprises the wisdom and not the mere names of the<lb/> Lord&#44; and as such it behooves us&#44; especially O Israelites&#44; to<lb/> study it.  I stated it last Sabbath&#44; and as long as the gift of speech is granted me&#44; I will not grow<lb/> weary of repeating the lesson.  To oppose rampant changes<lb/> in Judaism&#44; we must be panoplied with knowledge.<lb/>  <sic>Wilful</sic> ignorance is worse than sin.  It is a surrendering<lb/> of our rights into the hands of a scheming few&#44; who may enslave us at<lb/> their pleasure.  All are priests in the church of our Lord.  All<lb/> will find therein the laver to cleanse their impurities.  In our hearts we<lb/> have our confessionals.  In our intellect the means of salvation.<lb/>  Let us not <sic>yeild</sic> these precious privileges.  We shall attend to<lb/> instruction wherever it is imparted&#59; but if it conflicts clashes with an<lb/> authority universally acknowledged&#44;&#45;&#45;the Bible&#45;&#45;&#44; we shall let<lb/> our enlightened judgment war against it.  In short&#44; my<lb/> dear hearers&#33;  Let us study that we may confound the unbeliever&#44;<lb/> let us study that we may understandingly serve our God.<lb/>  Let us study that we may effect the will of the Supreme&#44; in giving<lb/> us a spiritual existence&#44; which commenced with Abraham in &#91;&#63;&#93; of the Chaldeans and<lb/> will end when time shall be no more.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
