<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF3_20</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_20_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_20_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_20_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_20_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_20_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_20_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_20_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_20_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_20_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_20_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_20_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_20_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Post&#45;Bibblical Lecture<lb/>
                20.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>The wisdom of Moses the inspired lawgiver was rightly appreciated by<lb/> the men&#44; who framed the Constitution of the United States<lb/> of America.  They established that only a native<lb/> born citizen could be eligible to the highest executive of&#45;<lb/>&#45;fice in the government.  Even so we read in Those far&#45;seeing legislators <sic>profitted</sic> by the sentence in Deuteronomy&#58;<lb/> &#34;Thou art not allowed to set over thee an alien who is not<lb/> one of thy brothers.&#34;  It is natural to suppose that<lb/> a person who first saw the light of day in the land<lb/> where his parents dwelt&#59; whose first utterances were<lb/> in the language of that land&#44; and whose first associations<lb/> were contracted within its borders&#44; must feel a deeper<lb/> interest in its welfare the social and political welfare thereof&#44; than a foreigner.<lb/></p>
            <p>Antipater&#44; the pretended friend of Hyrcanus II was an<lb/> Idumean&#45;&#45;converted affiliated to Judaism by the mistaken policy<lb/> of John Hyrcanus I&#45;&#45;but still a stranger to the<lb/> feelings that urge the sacrificing of self&#45;interest upon<lb/> the altar of patriotism.  Intensely egotistical&#44;<lb/> he cared nothing that Judea be chained to the triumph&#45;<lb/>&#45;al car of Rome&#44; if it was the vehicle which for<lb/> carrying his family to the seat of power.  The wife<lb/> of Antipater was likewise an alien.  The blood coursing<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>through her veins had not flowed down<lb/> from Isaac&#45;&#45;the child of promise&#45;&#45;but from Ishmael<lb/> the father of the Arabian nation.  Possibly she belonged to the tribes of Itureans&#44; whom Antigonus&#44; brother of Aristobulus mistakenly again compelled to embrace the Hebrew faith.  Thus her offspring<lb/> issued from a stock engrafted upon ours&#44; but not ge&#45;<lb/>&#45;nuinely Jewish.  Hence And therefore post&#45;biblical history testifies<lb/> to the want of love for Israel and the Law in her<lb/> four sons&#44; Phasael&#44; Herod&#44; Joseph&#44; and Pheroras&#44; and in<lb/> her daughter Salome.<lb/></p>
            <p>Antipater after the fall of his friend Pompey&#44; lost<lb/> no time in turning to the winning side and ingratiating<lb/> himself with Julius Caesar.  He rendered the suc&#45;<lb/>&#45;cessful triumvir valuable services by dispatching<lb/> an army of auxiliaries to Egypt&#44; where the Roman<lb/> general was fighting.  Egypt had been since<lb/> the days of Alexander and Ptolemy Soter thickly<lb/> populated with Jews.  These also Antipater brought<lb/> over to the assistance of Caesar&#44; by producing a<lb/> writing from the high&#45;priest at Jerusalem&#45;&#45;Hyrcanus<lb/> the Asmonean&#45;&#45;in which Caesar was described as a<lb/> friend of favoring the Jewish nation.  Antipater reaped<lb/> a large reward.  He received the title of citizen of<lb/> Rome&#44; and Governor of Judea&#45;&#45;Hyrcanus retaining&#44; besides<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>the high&#45;priesthood&#44; a shadow of royalty.  Now could<lb/> the Idumean grasp the sword with which to strike<lb/> the Asmonean race irrecoverably.  In vain Antigonus<lb/> son of Aristobulus II prayfully asked for redress.  His<lb/> father had been poisoned by the hirelings of Pompey&#44;<lb/> his brother Alexander met with an ignominious death by<lb/> the same treacherous agency.  Antipater was believed to have been the secret<lb/> instigator of those atrocious deeds.  But remonstrances<lb/> availed nothing.  Caesar had been effectively aided by<lb/> Antipater&#44; and him the Roman declared his faithful<lb/> friend.  The Idumean&#44; strong in the protection<lb/> of Rome&#44; began to parcel out the country among his<lb/> children.  He appointed Phasael his oldest&#44; commander<lb/> in Jerusalem and its vicinity.  To Herod&#44; his second son&#44;<lb/> he entrusted the whole mountainous region of Galilee.<lb/>  The character of Herod is strikingly brought to view at once.<lb/>  He was bold even to arrogance&#44; unscrupulous even to<lb/> ferocity&#44; from his early youth.  No sooner had<lb/> he been placed in possession of his office&#44; than he<lb/> showed his irrepressible temperament.  It would<lb/> be very difficult for any one to decide&#44; whether Herod was<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>always wrong on the severe course he followed stern measures he chose.<lb/>  Thus&#44; For instance&#44; if it were true that a certain Hezekiah and<lb/> his party&#44; when he arrested and put to death&#44; infested<lb/> Galilee and committed outrages&#44; we should suspend<lb/> our condemnation of the severe means used to rid the coun&#45;<lb/>&#45;try of a lawless faction.  But our ancestors had<lb/> a right to look upon such doings with suspicion<lb/> and dread.  Here was a descendant of the stranger&#44;<lb/> ignoring all existing authorities&#44; and arbitrarily assuming to inflict&#45;<lb/>&#45;&#45;ing the severest extreme penalty of the law.  To day it<lb/> was&#44; perhaps&#44; a band of robbers that Herod killed with&#45;<lb/>out a trial&#59; to&#45;morrow the innocent may might be sum&#45;<lb/>&#45;marily executed to gratify personal jealousies and<lb/> animosities.  Alarmed by what happened in<lb/> Galilee&#44; some of the most influential in the country&#44;<lb/> called on the feeble&#45;minded Hyrcanus.  They spoke<lb/> words which kindled&#44; for a moment&#44; sparks of self&#45;respect<lb/> in the breast of the shadowy king.  He heard moreover the<lb/> cries of the mothers and widows of the victims of Herod&#39;s<lb/> arbitrariness.  They came to the Temple&#44; and asked pitifully entreated for<lb/> justice at the hands of him who was an Asmonean&#44; a<lb/> ruler&#44; and a president of the Sanhedrin.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Hyrcanus <sic>yeilded</sic> to the strong pressure&#59; he summoned<lb/> Herod before the highest tribunal in the land.<lb/>  But the son of Antipater did not comply&#44; till he could<lb/> secure a shield&#44; which would prove beyond doubt be<lb/> prove his deliverance defence.  He applied to Sextus Caesar&#45;&#45;a near<lb/> relative of Julius Caesar&#44; who was the Governor of<lb/> Syria&#44; and signified the necessity of Roman protection intervention.<lb/>  That official wrote to the impotent Hyrcanus to<lb/> beware of the dealings of take heed of how the Sanhedrin dealt towards his favorite Herod.<lb/>  Emboldened by that letter&#44; the son of Antipater executioner of the Galileeans put<lb/> on his audacious looks and entered the presence of his judges<lb/> like a soldier ready for the battle.  At that unusual sight&#44;<lb/> no one found could summon master the courage to speak.  Dead silence continued for<lb/> a while.  At last&#44; one arose and addressing the court and<lb/> Hyracanus said&#58; &#34;O ye that are my colleagues&#44; and thou who<lb/> art our king&#44; have you ever seen a man about to be tried<lb/> by us on the charge of murder&#44; present himself in such<lb/> a a manner&#63;  Does not every person coming here evince in his<lb/> behaviour humility&#44; as if impressed with awe&#63;  But this<lb/> Herod comes in his military garments&#44; with his shining helmet&#44;<lb/> accompanied by his troops&#44; as if to intimate that he will<lb/> slay us all&#44; if we dare pass sentence upon him.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Now&#44; I am not surprised at his defying the law to<lb/> save his life&#44; but my compliments is are with you&#44; where my<lb/> colleagues and with our King&#44; for having suffering such an<lb/> act of insolence.  But know you ye all that there is a great<lb/> God&#44; and that this very man&#44; whom through Hyrcanus<lb/> you mean to acquit&#44; will one day punish you and your<lb/> king.&#34;  The effect of that speech became visible.<lb/>  But when Hyrcanus saw perceived that Herod would have been<lb/> condemned to death&#44; he hindered the proceedings&#44; and oc&#45;<lb/>&#45;casioned a delay&#44; so as to adjourn the meeting.  In the<lb/> night a secret message was conveyed to Herod&#44; that he<lb/> must stealthily leave the city to avoid danger.  Herod burning<lb/> with wrath rage went straightway to Syria&#44; and bought<lb/> of Sextus Caesar a title to a territory near Judea.<lb/>  He determined frm there to enter Jerusalem at the head of an<lb/> army and take revenge on Hyrcanus&#44; who had com&#45;<lb/>&#45;pelled him to appear before the Sanhedrin like a<lb/> culprit.  He would have carried out his cruel purpose&#44; if his<lb/> father and his brother Phasael had not gone forward to meet<lb/> him. and Their arguings dissuaded him from proceeding to an act of rash&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness which might have compromised them all with the Romans dictator.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Enough if the Jews at the capital had been shown learnt<lb/> of what how terrible it is was to offend Herod.<lb/></p>
            <p>But the conduct of the fearless member of the Jewish<lb/> tribunal&#44; who attempted at least to chastise insolence and<lb/> vindicate right&#44; contrasts so nobly with the behaviour of<lb/> his cowardly colleagues&#44; that a wish is felt to know more<lb/> concerning that man.  Josephus calls him &#34;Sameas&#44;&#34; and<lb/> severla have been the conjectures about his historical identity.<lb/>  Most writers&#44; however&#44; incline to think that Sameas of<lb/> Josephus is &#34;Shemajah&#34; of whom honorable mention is<lb/> made in the Mishna treatise Aboth&#44; and to whom the fol&#45;<lb/>&#45;lowing maxim is attributed.  &#34;Love work&#44; hate the assumption<lb/> of authority&#44; and seek not to be known by men in power.&#34;  This<lb/> aphorism&#44; which the condition of affairs in Judea may<lb/> have elicited&#44; offers a slight idea of the character independent spirit of the<lb/> Sage.  A lamentable change had taken place.  Since<lb/> the wily Antipater and the violent Herod had become the<lb/> real masters of the country&#44; the wisest policy was to be<lb/> content with humbly earning a daily livelihood by the<lb/> sweat of one&#39;s brow.  A lowly station in the enjoyment of security was<lb/> preferable to a lofty station which could only be gained<lb/> through corruption and servility to Rome.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>But a circumstance told in the Talmud&#44; sets She&#45;<lb/>&#45;majah even more fully in the same light of an undaunted teacher of<lb/> truth&#44; as he had showed himself in the hall of the Sanhedrion.<lb/>  Both he and his colleague Abtalion&#44; were descendants of<lb/> families that have embraced converted to Judaism&#44; but both were<lb/> nevertheless upright correct in their doings&#44; and sincere in<lb/> their sentiments convictions.  At the expiration of a day of<lb/> atonement&#44; the high priest&#44; who probably was a creature<lb/> of Herod&#44; having performed all the ritual services&#44; was<lb/> accompanied home&#44; as customary&#44; by a vast concourse<lb/> of people.  Shemajah and Abtalion also left the Temple&#44;<lb/> intending to call upon him&#44; who had officiated in the Holy<lb/> of Holies.  But so greatly were the two Sages respected&#44;<lb/> that many among that throng fell back to follow them.<lb/>  This token of deference manifests towards men he deemed his inferior&#44; excited the jealousy of the Pontiff&#44; and he vented<lb/> his spleen as soon as the distinguished visitors arrived at his house.  &#34;Let the<lb/> progeny of heathens come in peace&#34; was the caustic greeting.<lb/>  To which Shemajah and his colleague promptly answered&#58;<lb/> &#34;The progeny of heathens who copy the deeds of Aaron&#45;&#45;loving<lb/> peace and pursuing peace&#45;&#45;have a right to be welcome&#59; not<lb/> so the progeny of Aaron the priest&#44; who deviate from the example of their pious ancestor.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>A scathing rebuke well deserved by a minister at<lb/> the altar whose tribe with unworthy of his office.  For with &#91;&#63;&#93; the founder of his tribe the Lord established an enduring<lb/> covenant for the noblest holies purpose&#59; that the priest might<lb/> stand in fear of wrong and teach the law of truth&#59; walk<lb/> uprightly and turn away a multitude from the path<lb/> of sin.  No doubt&#44; it was when they who<lb/> had a divine claim to the office of national preceptors<lb/> fell from the lofty standard designed by Moses&#59; when<lb/> they degenerated into sycophants&#44; and prided them&#45;<lb/>&#45;selves in the wearing of the golden breast plate and<lb/> mitre&#44; but not in shining virtues&#44; not in serving as models of right&#45;<lb/>&#45;eousness&#59; it was then that the Sages drew towards<lb/> themselves the affectionate reverence of the people.<lb/></p>
            <p>The despotic Herod made and unmade Pontiffs<lb/> to subserve his wicked ends&#44; but if he exposed<lb/> thereby to disgrace the Temple and its ceremonials&#44;<lb/> he could not rob the Torah of its dignity.  The<lb/> Rabbis and their disciples held it high.<lb/></p>
            <p>We have thus far reached only the threshold of the<lb/> history of the son of Antipater.  The further we proceed&#44; the<lb/> deeper will be our abhorrence of the man set over us&#44;<lb/> who was not one of our brothers.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
