<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF13_9</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1888" source="" attested="yes">1888</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_9_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_9_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_9_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_9_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_9_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_9_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_9_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_9_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_9_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_9_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_9_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_9_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_9_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_9_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_9_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_9_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>On Itr&#243; 88<lb/></p>
            <p>45</p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  By a singular coincidence the prophetic<lb/> section which was read in the synagogues this<lb/> Sabbath&#44; formed the text of a sermon which a clergy&#45;<lb/>&#45;man delivered in a church last Sunday.  An abstract<lb/> choicely worded that came under my notice&#44; carried<lb/> my thoughts back to the history connected with the<lb/> sublime vision that had suggested the Christian<lb/> minister&#39;s semi&#45;meataphysical sermon.<lb/></p>
            <p>Uzziah&#44; or Azariah&#44; as he was also called&#44; mounted early<lb/> in life the throne of Judah&#44; which the misrule of<lb/> some of his predecessors had <sic>imperilled</sic>.  A King at<lb/> sixteen years of age&#44; needed sound instruction.  He<lb/> must be surrounded by men free from the taint<lb/> of selfishness&#59; men filled with awe at the Majesty<lb/> of the holy Law&#44; and eager to hold the Sovereign and<lb/> his subjects in virtue&#44; by unswerving fealty to the<lb/> Sinaic constitution.  The new monarch had no<lb/> lack of soul&#45;inspiring mentors.  Contemporary with<lb/> him were prophets&#44; whose wisdom is yet the &#91;&#63;&#93;<lb/> of God&#45;loving Israelites.  Amos&#44; the <sic>plebean</sic> shepherd&#44;<lb/> dauntless&#44; direct&#44; incisive in his denunciations of wrongs&#59;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Hosea&#44; who summoned all to repentance &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> calling with clarion blasts that did not grow<lb/> faint &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Perhaps Micah and Joel also&#44; an&#45;<lb/>&#45;nouncing the glories of Zion&#44; resurrected by means<lb/> of righteousness and Jonah also may perhaps have witnessed Uzziah&#39;s<lb/> coronation.  But the book which dwells<lb/> on the deeds of that monarch&#44; makes special<lb/> mention of a Zechariah&#44; possessed of a Divine un&#45;<lb/>&#45;derstanding &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  He led the royal<lb/> youth aright&#44; his devotedness <sic>levelled</sic> down the path that<lb/> might conduce to godliness.  Thus straightforwardly<lb/> directed&#44; prosperity attended every step of the<lb/> willing disciple of prophetism.  Warlike<lb/> tribes journeyed as vassals to the capital of<lb/> Judea with rich tributes.  Buildings&#44; lifting<lb/> their high turrets&#44; fortified and <sic>embelished</sic> Jeru&#45;<lb/>&#45;salem.  Uninhabited deserts resounded with the<lb/> strokes of the laborer&#39;s hammer&#59; mountain peaks<lb/> echoed forth the songs of vintagers&#59; valleys were<lb/> enlivened with the music of gurgling streams.<lb/>  For to broaden the country when Providence<lb/> had destined him to rale&#59; to gild it all around<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>with might and beauty was Uzziah&#39;s noble ambition.<lb/>  He could rely on an army&#44; that he had splendid&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly equipped&#44; to follow his command&#59; he could de&#45;<lb/>&#45;pend on the love of a nation&#44; whose welfare he<lb/> had sought to promote.  Nothing seemed<lb/> wanting to restore what previous misgovern&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment had dragged to the verge of destruction&#59;<lb/> nothing to renew the days&#44; when <sic>tranquillity</sic><lb/> within&#44; and power without made Judea happy<lb/> and respected.  Nothing was wanting&#44; save the<lb/> quality which we all are so apt to leave be&#45;<lb/>&#45;hind&#44; as we ascend the steps of fortune&#39;s lad&#45;<lb/>&#45;der&#45;&#45;humility.<lb/></p>
            <p>Observe.  A solemn festival is held at the Tem&#45;<lb/>&#45;ple.  A Vast multitudes have their looks revit&#45;<lb/>&#45;ted on a new corner.  The King steps forward&#59; he<lb/> wears no regal garments&#59; strange is his attire.<lb/>  Clothed as a priest&#44; he advances.  He waves<lb/> a censer to lay the morning national offering<lb/> on the golden altar that stood before the Holy<lb/> of Holier.  The diadem which had long fitted<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>his bro well&#44; did not suffice his ambition<lb/> any more.  He must don the ephod and<lb/> the mitre.  A struggle ensued.  The daring<lb/> Ruler was bid to desist&#59; not to presume to<lb/> usurp an authority belonging&#44; according to the<lb/> ordinance of Moses&#44; to the progeny of Aaron.<lb/>  He resisted and threatened&#59; his wounded pride<lb/> might have reenacted the crime of which<lb/> Saul became guilty against Ahimelech and his<lb/> sacerdotal followers&#44; in the madness of an un&#45;<lb/>&#45;conquering jealousy.  But.....suddenly the<lb/> Temple shook&#59; its roof rent asunder&#44; and<lb/> through the breach&#44; the sun poured down<lb/> floods of light&#44; to show the affrighted assembly<lb/> a ghastly sight&#59; most hideous.<lb/></p>
            <p>Terrific was that earthquake&#44; never forgotten<lb/> in Jewish annals&#44; always recalled by poste&#45;<lb/>&#45;rity as a memorial of God&#39;s displeasure<lb/> with human haughtiness. &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  For refulgent beams through the<lb/> crevices&#44; revealed the disfigurement of the Mo&#45;<lb/>narch immediately to be cast out of the com&#45;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>&#45;munity and buried in the solitude of men&#44; that<lb/> are plagued with leprosy.  In the opinion<lb/> of the Sages&#44; it was the hour in which the<lb/> thrilling episode which I have narrated took<lb/> place&#44; that the burden of prophecy rested on<lb/> Isaiah&#44; and he was vouchsafed the grand<lb/> vision recorded in our Haftorah&#44; and which the<lb/> Christian clergyman selected as the text of his<lb/> semi&#45;metaphysical discourse.  We read<lb/> that the sublime vision opened to the gaze<lb/> of the sun of Amoz in the year that King<lb/> Uzziah died.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Now&#44; ac&#45;<lb/>&#45;cording to the Talmudists&#44; among those whose<lb/> life may be considered a moral death&#44; we must<lb/> reckon the lesser of olden times&#44; as all will rea&#45;<lb/>&#45;lize who are familiar with Holy Writ.  In<lb/> fact&#44; history relates that from the moment<lb/> that the loathsome malady laid hold of the<lb/> presumptuous monarch&#44; he was cut off from<lb/> the association of the Congregation &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> The gifted being to whom magnificence of speech<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>and a sublime imagery came from on high&#44;<lb/> may have felt the shock that rocked the sanct&#45;<lb/>&#45;uary&#59; he may have seen the sovereign of Judah<lb/> hastened away like pollution from the sacred<lb/> shrine.  Then before his illumined soul the<lb/> veil which separated the oracle with the Cherubim<lb/> from the Temple proper&#44; was flung aside.  Isaiah<lb/> beheld the King of the world loftily enthroned.<lb/>  Seraphic creatures wove His royal crown &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;  their hymns of praise made the<lb/> hallowed edifice tremble&#59; a sweet scented oblation<lb/> darkened the house from sill to dome with wreathes<lb/> of perfume &#91;Hebrew  he looked and lo&#33; the<lb/> God&#45;extolling archangels had six wings&#59; with two<lb/> each covered his face&#44; with two each covered his<lb/> feet&#44; and with two each &#91;&#63;&#93; upward.<lb/></p>
            <p>Let all apply that appendage of the Seraphs as<lb/> they deem best.  To me it has the deepest signi&#45;<lb/>&#45;ficance&#44; when taken to typify the character of<lb/> men exalted by Providence as exemplars&#59; as<lb/> messengers of the Almighty&#44; in any capacity.<lb/>  Profound reverence is the prerequisite of such<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Whose spoken teaching&#44; or written<lb/> instruction and demenaour must shape the minds<lb/> of multitudes.  Let us confess it without<lb/> ambiguity.  By the highest flight of our<lb/> intellects we cannot reach God&#39;s understanding.<lb/>  How much less dare we imagine that His Essence<lb/> can be mirrored forth in our souls&#63;  If minis&#45;<lb/>&#45;tering angels hide their countenance&#44; when<lb/> in the presence of their Sovereign Lord&#44; how can<lb/> mortals stand forth and audaciously say&#58;<lb/> &#34;We have discovered the secret powers of creation&#44;&#34;<lb/> &#34;and we demand popular acceptance.  Rising<lb/> generation&#33; hearken unto us&#59; do not heed the<lb/> lessons of the past&#59; they are the offspring of<lb/> abject errors.  Your fathers groped in the dark.<lb/>  We have entered the council chamber of the<lb/> Deity&#44; and brought you a knowledge fault&#45;<lb/>&#45;less.&#34;  No&#44; Israelites&#44; modesty&#59; a suspi&#45;<lb/>&#45;cion that our premises may be groundless&#44;<lb/> and our conclusions false&#44; should inspire us<lb/> with fearful caution &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;God<lb/> detects deficiencies in His Angels&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>&#34;How much more so in those that dwell in houses<lb/> of clay&#34;&#63;...&#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;Who die away without<lb/> wisdom.&#34;  Reverence&#44; profound reverence must<lb/> pervade our soul always&#44; but most intensely while<lb/> in the act of rendering public homage to the<lb/> author of worlds&#44; the Universal Father&#44; reverence<lb/> in thoughts&#44; reverence in language.  Let all re&#45;<lb/>&#45;member Uzziah&#39;s fate&#59; let Hebrews chiefly remember<lb/> that ere Isaiah went forth to preach&#44; his lips<lb/> were purified with a sacred fire &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            <p>But we learn likewise that the Seraphim<lb/> covered their feet with their wings.  Have<lb/> we &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; &#34;Kingdom of priests and holy<lb/> nation&#44;&#34; we&#44; the appointed missionaries of a belief<lb/> destined to humanize and unify mankind&#44;<lb/> run after worldly goods&#59; rushed headlong<lb/> to attain a goal&#44; where plaudits and approving<lb/> smiles awaited us&#63;  Let us pause and bethink<lb/> ourselves&#44; and feel abashed before the Master&#44;<lb/> whose work we should have sped on&#59; let<lb/> us blush that our feet were quickened by the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>clinking of perishable gold&#44; and stood<lb/> still at the call of duty.  Position and<lb/> fame and honors&#44; are nothing in comparison with<lb/> the obligation of doing the mission assumed&#44; blissf<lb/> blissfully.  Typical of perseverance in the<lb/> pursuit thereof are our feet on which the body<lb/> rests for all its movements&#58; The archangels&#44;<lb/> presenting a human shape&#44; covered theirs.  Even<lb/> they&#44; fearing to have fallen short of their allotted<lb/> task&#44; hid their forms.  But each of them could<lb/> rise higher by two wings &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  What<lb/> were those agencies of their elevation&#63;  I repeat it&#44;<lb/> my brethren&#44; reverence&#44; profound reverence and<lb/> self&#45;distrust before the Lord.  The lowly shall be exalted.<lb/>  Finite indeed is our understanding&#59; fallible<lb/> is our judgment&#44; yet in the same manner<lb/> as when we thrice proclaim the Lord of Hosts Kadosh&#44;<lb/> we essay to model our action after that of<lb/> the celestial beings&#44; who encircle His throne &#38; reverently do Him honor&#44; so<lb/> we may like them become spiritually uplifted&#44;<lb/> by copying the archangels in their awe for<lb/> the Omnipotent and their self&#45;abasement in His<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>Divine presence.  Every Jew who bows<lb/> meekly to a Supreme Ruler&#44; whose power and<lb/> goodness we behold in His handiwork&#44; but<lb/> whose existence and ways are unfathomable&#44;<lb/> every Jew who admits his incapacity to<lb/> perform God&#39;s will in absolute perfectness&#44;<lb/> but who strives to reach up to that goal&#44; is<lb/> God&#39;s angel&#44; lifting high his own nature&#44; and<lb/> hallowing his great Master.<lb/></p>
            <p>And here I may not be taxed with unworthy<lb/> motives&#45;&#45;surely I can have none when<lb/> I confess that the actions of brother&#45;Israelites&#44;<lb/> who&#44; during the week in which we are Biblic&#45;<lb/>&#45;ally reminded of our Sinaic charge&#44; dealt thought&#45;<lb/>&#45;fully&#44; justly and compassionately towards fel&#45;<lb/>&#45;low creatures&#44; who became involved in the con&#45;<lb/>&#45;sequences of an intoward event&#59; that the<lb/> action&#44; I say&#44; of a Philadelphia firm of our<lb/> persuasion&#44; in its endeavours to mitigate the<lb/> evils attending an enforced inactivity&#44; was a<lb/> cause of unfeigned satisfaction to me.  For I<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>interpreted the demeanour a Kiddush Ha&#45;<lb/>shein&#44; a sanctification of the name of Him<lb/> whom we adore and must extoll among gen&#45;<lb/>&#45;tilism.  It is thus that we illustrate the<lb/> Divine choice made at Sinai&#59; it is thus that<lb/> we verify our attestation&#44; when&#44; like the Seraphim&#44;<lb/> we proclaim&#58; &#34;Holy&#44; holy&#44; holy is the Lord<lb/> of hosts&#44; the whole earth is full of His glory&#34;<lb/> May we ever be imbued with such sentiments&#44;<lb/> and may we deserve God&#39;s approval&#59; and the<lb/> good&#45;will of all the sainted and the right&#45;<lb/>&#45;eous.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
