<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF19_4</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_4_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_4_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_4_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_4_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_4_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_4_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_4_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_4_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_4_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_4_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_4_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_4_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>An appeal on behalf<lb/>
                of the Hebrew Sunday&#45;school.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Women that are at ease&#44; rise&#44; listen to my voice&#59; daughters that<lb/> have no cares&#44; give ear to my speech.&#34;  I hope that this<lb/> address&#44; apparently very bul blunt&#44; will not be deemed by<lb/> some of my hearers&#44; an undue liberty.  Searching for a text&#44; my mind<lb/> lighted upon that sentence of Isaiah.  I disclaim any design<lb/> to abuse the privilege accorded to me&#44; as the holy man&#44;<lb/> I quoted&#44; would disavow any intention to treat his sisters<lb/> in faith slightingly.  Indeed&#44; if what the Talmudists<lb/> write&#44; is correct&#44; the prophet meant his words&#44; as a good<lb/> omen.  Let me tell it.  Our women would encourage<lb/> among our men the knowledge of religion&#44; and thus&#44; at length&#44;<lb/> become perfectly tranquil about the future of the Community.<lb/>  Their exertions would cause the national stability&#44; des&#45;<lb/>&#45;cribed at the end of the same chapter.  &#34;My people shall<lb/> dwell in a peaceful habitation&#44; in secure abodes&#44; and in<lb/> undisturbed resting&#45;places.&#34;  I invite the<lb/> Jewesses of all Congregations in our city but mainly those whom my<lb/> voice immediately reaches&#44; to promote the object&#44; said to<lb/> have been furthered by their mothers of old.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>The opportunities for acting so meritoriously are<lb/> numerous&#44; yet&#44; none presents itself just now in so ur&#45;<lb/>&#45;gent a manner&#44; as that which suggested my&#44; seemingly<lb/> unceremonious&#44; address.  Advisedly I directed my<lb/> speech to women that enjoy ease&#44; for&#44; those on whom<lb/> the government of a household entirely depends&#44; cannot<lb/> well enter a sphere&#44; which would withdraw them from duties<lb/> of primary importance.  To wif wives and mothers all<lb/> will be secondary to the obligation of preparing a &#34;sweet<lb/> home&#34; for the loved inmates.  That obligation the once<lb/> assumed before God and society at large&#44; must be dili&#45;<lb/>&#45;gently performed.  But what should hinders a Jewess<lb/> unrestricted by such sacred calls on her time&#44; from giving<lb/> her people two hours a week&#63;  Two hours a week&#44; only&#44;<lb/> O women of Israel&#44; to advance the cause of the religion in<lb/> which we were born.  Two hours a week to counter&#45;<lb/>&#45;act the effects of an ever&#45;busy and crafty spirit of<lb/> proselytism&#44; represented by mission&#45;schools&#44; and mission<lb/> aid societies.  Two hours a week to keep in our fold<lb/> what rightly belongs to it&#33;  &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Daughters that<lb/> have no cares&#33;&#34;  He The Hebrew Sunday&#45;school counts<lb/> its attendants by hundreds&#44; but it can reckon the assiduous<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>teachers with the fingers.  Nay&#58; to speak with an open<lb/> mind&#44; I will say&#44; that whereas to hold high the stand&#45;<lb/>&#45;ard of the institution&#44; which became the parent of kind&#45;<lb/>&#45;red organizations&#44; a large corps of efficient instructors<lb/> is indispensable&#44; extreme necessity compels a frequent<lb/> acceptance of the offices of the kindly disposed&#44; by but young<lb/> and inexperienced.  To this untoward circumstance&#44;<lb/> has lately been added the loss of several&#44; who for reasons<lb/> of various of characters&#44; have ceased altogether to im&#45;<lb/>&#45;part knowledge.  It would be idle&#44; and it might elicit<lb/> invidious remarks to seek into the motives of that <sic>withdrawl</sic>;<lb/> but I can&#44; without hesitation&#44; say&#44; that an unavoidable loss&#44;&#45;&#45;<lb/>and that which is most sensibly felt&#44; deprives a well&#45;<lb/>arranged infant class department of the tuition of its ca&#45;<lb/>&#45;pable directress&#44; and adds <sic>embarassement</sic> to a super&#45;<lb/>&#45;intendent already severely tested in the prosecution of<lb/> her task.  How to meet the difficulties arisen&#44; how<lb/> to afford all applicants the advantage of free instruction<lb/> in the holy book&#44; and supply the increasing want of<lb/> teachers&#44; is a subject which I submit to the serious reflection<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>of my female coreligionists.  They have to<lb/> determine&#44; whether a school which serves as a soul&#45;<lb/>refreshing &#91;&#63;&#93; to our offspring&#44; as school to which<lb/> our little dears resort in crowds and with pleasurable motions&#44; ought to<lb/> be denied the gift of two hours a week&#59; be suffered to<lb/> languish and for the lack of personal support&#44; and<lb/> finally become extinct.  I cannot believe that those<lb/> who are at ease&#44; deem what I crave for them a heavy<lb/> burden&#44; that those who enjoy freedom from pressing cares at<lb/> home&#44; are careless of a high duty abroad.  I will<lb/> not so malign the women of my people.  No&#58; I will<lb/> rather attribute the evil of which I complain to the<lb/> absence of essential requisites on my part&#44; as well<lb/> as on the part of individuals warmly interested in the<lb/> future of Judaism in America.  Preaching may<lb/> effect some good&#44; but personal efforts&#44; hold out the hopes of<lb/> a greater and speedier success.  A visit to each<lb/> family&#44; among whose members intelligent and well&#45;<lb/>trained females are numbered&#44; ought to be made&#44; and<lb/> we might be provided with what we imperatively need.<lb/>  The undertaking is arduous.  It demands unwearied perse&#45;<lb/>&#45;verance&#44; and a willing submission to rebuffs and refusals&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>but these are the very requisites which I and others<lb/> ought to possess&#59; these are the qualities that must<lb/> be put in practice&#44; to prevent the decay of an institution&#44;<lb/> with which the memory of sainted sisters&#44; who labored long<lb/> and faithfully is associated.  Possibly&#44; we<lb/> might enlist in its behalf the voluntary services of<lb/> young men&#44; but without denying the latter the privilege<lb/> of working usefully in a sacred undertaking cause&#44; I am of<lb/> opinion&#44; that my sisters in faith&#44; will&#44; as a rule&#44; prove<lb/> more acceptable.  They naturally possess the power<lb/> of drawing the tender hearts of our children to religion by<lb/> with the chords of affection.  Gentleness is in itself a<lb/> grand educator.  Sweetness of manners can command<lb/> discipline and attention&#44; better than the stern looks of<lb/> authority.  A lad&#44; apt to rebel against his rigid male<lb/> teacher&#44; will scarcely show a sign of insubordination<lb/> when remonstrated with by a female preceptor.  But<lb/> another and a very important consideration confirms me<lb/> in the views I have advanced.  Patience&#44; which we<lb/> men soon exhaust&#44; will be exercised almost2 uncon&#45;<lb/>&#45;sciously and at1 great length by a woman.  She will<lb/> lead the dull of comprehension step by step to a higher<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>degree of understanding&#44; rejoicing at in her achievement&#59; and&#44;<lb/> rather than grow restive&#44; when asked perplexing questions&#44;<lb/> she will ponder thereon&#44; search into a sensible solution&#44;<lb/> and thus improve herself while <sic>benefitting</sic> the cause she<lb/> desires to promote.  Dear hearers&#63;  The toad&#45;<lb/>&#45;yism vulgarly exhibited towards the female sex is fo&#45;<lb/>&#45;reign to my nature.  I do not indulge in unbecoming<lb/> flattery&#59; I am in sober earnestness when I assert that<lb/> some of our teachers are remarkably endowed with the<lb/> qualifications just delineated&#59; yet a much larger num&#45;<lb/>&#45;ber of the same stamp&#44; must be procured&#44; to keep from<lb/> dissolution our Hebrew Sunday&#45;School.<lb/></p>
            <p>Once more will I exclaim with Isaiah &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Women that are at ease&#44; rise&#44;<lb/> listen to my voice&#44; daughters that have not cares&#44; give ear<lb/> to my speech&#34;.  You are those whom we imperatively need.<lb/>  Upon you I call to work for the stability of Judaism in<lb/> our land.  Do not smile incredulously&#44; as if I so<lb/> spoke to gain a point.  No&#44; respected hearers&#33;  The Sunday<lb/> school can be made even a more powerful agent of<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>religious progress than the pulpit&#44; because it is<lb/> a laboratory of the mind&#44; because simple and love&#45;inspiring<lb/> words will sink more deeply than all set discourses.  But<lb/> allow me to be candid&#44; as well as justly appreciative.<lb/>  The institution in whose behalf I plead&#44; will e productive<lb/> of abundant good only when intelligent and God&#45;fearing<lb/> women of Israel shall set at the head of the classes&#44; and<lb/> vivify the dead letter with the breathing of the Spirit.<lb/>  We want less of the sentences of a printed catechism&#44;<lb/> and more of oral explanations&#44; of plain and soul&#45;penetra&#45;<lb/>ting language.  We want less studying and more<lb/> comprehending.  We want our young sons and daughters<lb/> early buoyed up by the teachings of a religion of<lb/> light and truth&#44; and not wearied with the drudgery<lb/> of memorising quotations.  In short&#44; we want many<lb/> inspired kindled with love for their glorious faith&#44; to help effectively<lb/> the our two zealous superintendents&#44; securing a perfect order&#44;<lb/> which dignifies the instruction&#44; enhancing the usefulness<lb/> of the instruction by kindness and sincerity.  To them<lb/> will be applied the concluding sentence of the chapter<lb/> I have cited from the prophet of old &#34;Happy<lb/> ye that sow sees besides all waters.&#34;  The soil<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>is fruitful fertile&#44; when well irrigated.  Who can carefully<lb/> tend it better than the women of Israel&#63;  Come and labor&#44;<lb/> dear sisters in faith&#33; for your people and your God.<lb/>  And Thou&#44; heavenly Lawgiver&#33; who hast chosen us as<lb/> missionaries of truth&#44; and who madest a covenant that<lb/> Thy spirit and Thy revealed words would never depart<lb/> from among us&#44; nor from among our progeny&#44; raise fit<lb/> helps for the holy work.  We sadly need the invi&#45;<lb/>&#45;gorating influence of woman&#44; to raise up what man<lb/> wantonly destroys.  Oh&#33; grant that as time rolls on&#44;<lb/> the power of woman&#39;s unflinching perseverance and<lb/> abiding affection may be seen in a revival of Judaism&#44;<lb/> pure and undefiled from the dross of false theories and<lb/> of gentilism.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
