<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF2_5</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_5_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_5_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_5_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_5_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_5_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_5_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_5_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_5_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_5_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_5_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_5_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_5_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>81</p>
            
            <p>A lecture explanatory<lb/>
                of the 53d chap of Isaiah.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  As the time draws near for suspending<lb/> the weekly sermon&#44; limiting myself to an English<lb/> prayer&#44; so that I may not detain the attendants<lb/> at the Synagogue longer than tis compatible with<lb/> the heat of the season&#44; my mind recalls the promises<lb/> made during the term&#44; which begins in Autumn<lb/> and ends the following summer.  I said once<lb/> that I would freely express my thoughts in a lecture<lb/> regarding the object of preaching&#59; and on another<lb/> occasion alluding to the Nazarene belief&#44; I told<lb/> my hearers&#44; that I would explain the real sense<lb/> of the 53d chapter of Isaiah&#44; on which our gentile<lb/> neighbors mainly lean for support.  The two sub&#45;<lb/>&#45;jects can be blended into one&#44; and I will now<lb/> offer a few remarks on both&#44; in order not to<lb/> leave a duty entirely unperformed.<lb/></p>
            <p>A fault common among us&#44; preachers&#44; is to look<lb/> for self&#45;satisfaction&#44; rather than for that which may<lb/> popularly impart religious knowledge.  Being<lb/> privileged to stand above a silent audience&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>we like to ventilate our favorite ideas&#44; or to display<lb/> learning&#44; and make a public exhibition of a pretended<lb/> command of language.  The fault&#44; however&#44; does not<lb/> lie altogether at our doors.  It proceeds also from<lb/> some of the congregation.  Practical teaching plainly<lb/> set forth appears to them flat and insipid.  That<lb/> which is sensational&#44; high&#45;wrought&#44; and sharply contro&#45;<lb/>&#45;versial they will be attracted by&#59; that they will praise<lb/> the most.  The preacher unwilling to be considered a<lb/> bore&#44; yields at times his conviction of what duty de&#45;<lb/>&#45;mands that he may secure attention.  But in reality<lb/> what was said did not carry out the object of his mi&#45;<lb/>&#45;nisterial calling.  I hold that the pulpit should prin&#45;<lb/>&#45;cipally aim to facilitate an understanding of the mean&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing and spirit of Holy Writ&#44; and of the basis of ancestral<lb/> traditions&#44; just as it may be necessitated to deprecate<lb/> measures leading to a break up of our religious union&#44;<lb/> and to encourage projects promotive of righteousness.<lb/>  If there existed colleges&#44; where all who wish to learn<lb/> would in their leisure days and hours be welcome as<lb/> formerly in foreign countries&#45;&#45;the pulpit might confine<lb/> itself to an occasional discourse on topics&#44; not immediately<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>connected with the written and oral laws.  But as<lb/> the Synagogue is yet&#44; and it is likely to remain<lb/> still longer&#44; the chief vehicle for transmitting re&#45;<lb/>ligious information&#44; the preacher ought to bring him&#45;<lb/>&#45;self less with rhetoric and more with homily in&#45;<lb/>struction.  Acting upon this principle&#44; I shall<lb/> detain you a brief while with some observations use&#45;<lb/>&#45;ful to a number&#44; at least&#44; of my hearers.  By<lb/> them all may be enabled to see&#44; how groundless<lb/> are the notions of those who read in one of our pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;phets the dogma of atonement for an original sin&#44;<lb/> through the sufferings of a man&#45;god.  The Naz&#45;<lb/>&#45;renes assert with positiveness that Isaiah spoke<lb/> of it clearly and in detail in the 53d chapter<lb/> of his book.  I shall not disprove the assertion<lb/> by repeating&#44; knowingly&#44; what English readers can<lb/> find in several works&#44; but specially in &#34;Faith<lb/> strengthened&#44;&#34; as translated by Moses Mocatta<lb/> of London.  I prefer taking a general view of<lb/> the subject&#59; throw some addition light upon it&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>affording information perhaps&#44; not possessed by<lb/> all within reach of my voice.<lb/></p>
            <p>The division of the Hebrew Scriptures into chapters&#44;<lb/> is&#44; comparatively&#44; of modern date&#45;&#45;The old manu&#45;<lb/>&#45;scripts were without it&#44; and a writer in the 16th century<lb/> of the vulgar era relates that the system was adopted<lb/> by the first publisher of our Bible&#45;&#45;after the art of<lb/> printing had been introduced discovered&#44; to conform with the<lb/> usage introduced by the gentile translators of Holy<lb/> Writ.  The division being then arbitrary&#44; it hap&#45;<lb/>&#45;pened not infrequently that the it was unw unwisely<lb/> made.  I am inclined to think that in a few<lb/> instances it was designed by the originators to bolster<lb/> up some Doctrines peculiar to their Church.<lb/></p>
            <p>Whether it was so or not in the case I am about to cite&#44; there<lb/> can be no doubt that the prophecy begins not<lb/> where the chapter is marked&#44; but three verses<lb/> before it&#44; namely &#34;Behold&#33; my servant shall<lb/> prosper&#44; he shall rise high&#44; be extolled&#44; and gain<lb/> excellency.&#34;  The spirit by which the son of<lb/> Amoz was pervaded&#44; showed him Israel&#45;&#45;repeatedly<lb/> called in his language &#34;the servant of God&#34;<lb/> &#43; It was made in the XIII century by Cardinal Hugo<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>emerging from a state of the deepest misery into an<lb/> exalted condition.  So complete would be the transition&#44;<lb/> that Kings and their subjects would look at each other<lb/> astounded and mute&#59; never having admitted the<lb/> possibility that such a people would take a front<lb/> rank in the domains of civilization.  To account for<lb/> so great an amazement&#44; the prophet proceeds to des&#45;<lb/>&#45;cribe minutely the trials both physical and moral<lb/> to which the <sic>worshippers</sic> of the Unity would long be<lb/> exposed.  With dramatic effect he Isaiah introduces the op&#45;<lb/>&#45;pressors themselves and draws a confession that they have<lb/> struck and wounded&#44; vexed and reviled&#44; plundered and<lb/> killed&#44; reduced to the lowest ebb of degradation&#44; a servant<lb/> of the Lord who meekly suffered what their his persecutors<lb/> deserved&#44; who bore all not to rebel against a decree the ordination<lb/> of Providence&#44; but to hold fast&#44; for the sake of the world&#44;<lb/> to that entrusted to his safe&#45;keeping.  Then is<lb/> the voice of God heard soothingly to speak.  It says that<lb/> the sorrows endured will be the darkness which<lb/> precedes the brightest morning&#44; that because no attempt<lb/> was made to return the wrongs of ages&#44; but forgiveness<lb/> was rather shown to the offenders&#44; and prayers were<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>offered for the atonement of their sins&#44; therefore would<lb/> the lowliest servant share a portion with the noblest<lb/> of the earth.  I do not&#44; my Brethren&#33; presume to have given the literal meaning of<lb/> every sentence.  I am not expected to do so&#44; nor are you prepared for it&#44; but I have epitomized the sense with fidelity<lb/> after mature reflection.<lb/>  Now it rests with me to prove that the chapter has been<lb/> unduly strained in its sense to make it answer an epi&#45;<lb/>&#45;sode in history which has none of the features therein pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;sented.  The epithet &#34;Servant of the Lord&#34; could not<lb/> apply to the founder of the Christian religion&#44; for whom his<lb/> followers claim a much higher prerogative.  The uggly<lb/> portrait of a being despised and shunned by all&#44; cannot be<lb/> that of the Galilean preacher&#44; who drew crowds of all willing<lb/> listeners&#44; and until within a few days hours that he was tried and found guilty of blasphemy&#44; ac&#45;<lb/>cording to existing laws&#44; and he walked the streets of Judea<lb/> at large&#44; and sometime accompanied by ovations.  Then<lb/> we may appropriately wh ask&#44; &#34;where can the cir&#45;<lb/>&#45;cumstances of the life of the man of Nazareth&#44; as<lb/> narrated by his own disciples&#44; illustrate the expression<lb/> that he was oppressed&#44; and opened not the mouth&#44; and<lb/> that nations and their rulers attributed his affections<lb/> to a divinely deserved punishment&#63;&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>But the most valid demonstration that the chapter<lb/> cannot be forced to give the meaning attached thereto<lb/> by the adherents of a new creed&#44; is the reward promised<lb/> to God&#39;s servant for having yielded his existence un&#45;<lb/>&#45;murmuringly.  He would outlive his sufferings&#44; and per&#45;<lb/>form his heavenly mission&#59; or to say it exactly in the words<lb/> of Isaiah &#34;He shall see seed&#44; prolong his days&#44; and the<lb/> pleasure of the Lord shall prosper through his hand.&#34;<lb/>  I am fully aware that the saying has been figuratively<lb/> explained.  The allegorizers have asserted that to &#34;see<lb/> my seed&#44; and prolong days&#34; are allusions to the<lb/> spread of the Nazarene belief&#44; and to its influence<lb/> over the destiny of unborn generations.  But every<lb/> unprejudiced Hebraist will own that such an inter&#45;<lb/>&#45;pretation is an abuse of language&#44; unwarranted as it<lb/> is incorrect.  And in that light it has been regarded<lb/> by the most distinguished German scholars&#44; of whom<lb/> some are avowed adherents of a trinity.  Still&#44; not<lb/> to dismiss the subject summarily&#44; I will direct your<lb/> attention to one circumstance&#44; and that will suffice to<lb/> show that expressions like that just quoted stand<lb/> in our Bible to signify solely and exclusively&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>what they literally convey&#59; that is the enjoyment of<lb/> a temporal existence&#44; and the pleasure of perceiving<lb/> that when we die we love an essence leave descendants.  Each of the<lb/> patriarchs was promised life and children&#44; but surely<lb/> that declaration was not intended to express the idea<lb/> that their belief in one God would be perpetuated.<lb/>  Another&#44; and most emphatic&#44; saying was employed<lb/> to signify that spiritual boon&#44; to wit&#44; &#34;through<lb/> you and your seed all the families of the earth will<lb/> be blessed.&#34;  Who that has understanding will deny<lb/> that all the declarations given to our forefathers have<lb/> been verified in us&#63;  Aye&#58; Israel is the servant that<lb/> has suffered martyrdom and survived it&#44; who still bears<lb/> resignedly the stripes and wounds of a benighted world&#44;<lb/> rather than lose his identity with Abraham.  Israel has<lb/> given his check to the strikers&#44; and his back to the<lb/> treader on smiter&#44; still praying and hoping&#44; that all may<lb/> see their evil ways&#44; and assign to him the glory<lb/> of having hallowed principles&#44; and sanctified Al&#45;<lb/>&#45;mighty God.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
