<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF5_6</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_6_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_6_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_6_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_6_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_6_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_6_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_6_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_6_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_6_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_6_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_6_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_6_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>For Chaye&#39; Sar&#225;h<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;Abraham was old&#44;<lb/> well stricken in years and the Lord had blessed Abraham<lb/> in all things.&#34;  &#34;A useless repetition&#44; mere tautology.&#34;<lb/>  So well may many call may some of my hearers may exclaim on reflecting upon the second part of the sentence&#44;<lb/> which I have just quoted from our section of the Pentateuch.<lb/>  They will argue so&#58; We meet a person whose looks betray old age&#44; and<lb/> naturally we infer that great numerous many have been the summers<lb/> which have passed over his head.  What necessity<lb/> was there for the sacred historian&#44; after having<lb/> informed us that the founder of the Hebrew people<lb/> had grown old&#44; to add that he was full of years&#63;<lb/>  This question&#44; which any one a tyro slightly acquainted with the<lb/> sacred holy language could easily solve&#44; by showing the<lb/> phrase to be&#44; as it actually is&#44; a Bibleical idiom&#44;<lb/> was propounded put likewise also by the Rabbis&#44; with the view to<lb/> point a moral.  They wisely remark that<lb/> not all who appear to have reached the extreme<lb/> end of this earthly existence&#44; and to be on the<lb/> verge of the grave&#44; are really old&#44; nor do all whom we<lb/> might at first sight judge to be yet far from making attaining<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>the allotted term&#44; have youth still in their<lb/> possession.  Some <sic>wilfully</sic> anticipate quicken the working decomposing process<lb/> of nature&#59; some deliberately hasten their bring on decrip&#45;<lb/>&#45;tude&#44; or&#44; as the Talmudists express it&#44; cause old age<lb/> to take a sudden jump leap and tightly fasten upon<lb/> them &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Frequently Unfortunately those reckless ones&#44;<lb/> by wasting their energies and by misapplying destroying<lb/> their faculties in the prime of life&#44; often involve other beings in their own<lb/> fate&#44; and occasion cause other beings to experience<lb/> the effects of an untimely decay.  Those heedless<lb/> ones are old in looks&#44; old in feelings&#44;&#45;&#45;which is<lb/> infinitely incomparably worse&#44; because they sought only what<lb/> would procure the gratification of a passing hour&#44;<lb/> without allowing the second sober thought to act<lb/> as a curb preventing the results of rashness&#44; which<lb/> are sure to be felt for many days and years.  &#34;Those who sow wrong doing will reap the same.&#34;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  They are<lb/> old because their interests were centred in them&#45;<lb/>&#45;selves and they did not go in quest of the ever<lb/> returning and ever refreshing pleasure of allaying<lb/> misery&#44; of promoting the happiness of their<lb/> neighbors.  They are old&#44; because the softening<lb/> and yet &#91;&#63;&#93; strengthening influences of religion&#45;&#45;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>&#45;&#45;prayer and meditation&#45;&#45;have been kept at a distance as useless and<lb/> futile.  You may&#44; my Brethren&#44; have met<lb/> with such in your walks of life&#44; and recognized<lb/> the fact that they are not stricken in years&#44;<lb/> but withered by the blasting wind which their<lb/> restless unruly passions have forcibly raised.  For them the<lb/> book of Proverbs wrote &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;the years of<lb/> <sic>of</sic> the unrighteous are shortened.&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>But you have doubtless seen also persons whom<lb/> you know to have <sic>travelled</sic> on this terrestrial<lb/> journey beyond the ordinary boundaries&#44; and who<lb/> show no signs of weariness.  They enjoy the<lb/> capacity of satisfying nature&#39;s wants because they have been chary not to abuse&#44; nature &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Happy our soul&#44; that has not showed our old age&#44; exclaim the sages.  they derived<lb/> constantly renewed pleasure from laboring to further<lb/> the welfare of individuals and of communities&#44; because<lb/> selfishness was brought by them under control&#44; while<lb/> their sacred ammonious and a firm reliance on Providence imparts elasticity to<lb/> their limbs&#44; and buoyancy to their minds.<lb/>  Those young&#45;old persons win veneration as a richly<lb/> earned reward&#59; for in the same book of Proverbs<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>it&#39;s written &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;old age<lb/> is a crown of glory&#44; it will be found in the way<lb/> of righteousness.&#34;<lb/>
                Now you can understand the teaching which our Rabbis<lb/> meant to convey&#44; by their comment on the sentence<lb/> which  I have cited.  &#34;Abraham was old&#44; well stricken<lb/> in years&#44; and God had blessed Abraham in all<lb/> things&#34;.  Pure in morals amidst a corrupt genera&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion&#44; which did shameless violence to foreigners&#44;<lb/> both in their persons and in their honor&#44; as evinced by the in&#45;<lb/>habitants of Sodom Egypt&#44; of Sodom and Gerar&#59;<lb/> yearning with an affection so great deep for all mankind<lb/> that urged him to offer earnest entreaties even<lb/> for the atrociously wicked&#59; mighty in that faith&#44;<lb/> which earned gained for him the just title of Chief<lb/> of believers &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; the father of the Hebrew<lb/> race saw years glide by without feeling that<lb/> they carried away his powers to do good.  Thus I<lb/> construe the closing part of the sentence.  &#34;The Lord had<lb/> blessed Abraham in all things.&#34;  For what sweeter<lb/> blessing can man experience gift can the Almighty bestow on man than that of retaining<lb/> the warmth of sentiments in the winter of his<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>existence&#63;  The Talmudists&#44; however&#44;<lb/> differ in their views about the proper application<lb/> of that expression.  Some suppose it to signify that<lb/> the fruits of the patriarch&#39;s industry did not decrease&#44;<lb/> when he could no longer labor till the ground labor&#44; through for the watching eye<lb/> of a Ruling Providence rested thereon.  Others&#44; surmise that it alludes<lb/> to his having overcome the ten trials of &#91;Hebrew&#93; to which he had been in a most re&#45;<lb/>markable manner the ten trials &#91;Hebrew&#93; to which he had been exposed.  But of all the various opi&#45;<lb/>&#45;nions advanced&#44;&#45;&#45;each of which may point to a<lb/> moral&#45;&#45;I prefer that which explains God&#39;s bene&#45;<lb/>&#45;diction to have been a foretaste of the bliss of<lb/> eternity&#44; while yet on this side of the grave.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  In what did such a beatitude consist&#63;  In<lb/> the satisfaction of knowing that his child of promise<lb/> would be his worthy successor&#59; in having discovered<lb/> in Isaac a dispositoin to hold fast to and spread further<lb/> the religious ideas imbibed in the parental home.  Hence&#44;<lb/> the anxiety evinced exhibited that those principles might not<lb/> be lost <sic>imperilled</sic> through an ill&#45;matched assorted alliance match&#59; hence&#44; the great<lb/> care taken that Sarah&#39;s son should not bring to the<lb/> tent made vacant by his mother&#39;s death&#44; a woman<lb/> whose blood had been tainted by the sins of the peoples<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>steeped in revolting idolatry.<lb/></p>
            <p>Let me draw your attention to the wording of<lb/> the oath which the Master exacted from the<lb/> trusty servant to whom he gave a was committed a delicate and responsible<lb/> charge.  &#34;I will make thee swear by the Lord&#44;<lb/> the God of the heaven and the God of the earth&#44;<lb/> that thou wilt not take a wife for my son out<lb/> of the daughters of the Canaanites&#44; in whose land<lb/> I dwell&#34;.  The mission which the founder<lb/> of our religion assumed was one clearly defined.<lb/>  He would establish the Kingdom of God among men and let<lb/> the ruled recognize their Ruler.  What in the<lb/> phraseology of Christian books bears the name of<lb/> the lord&#39;s prayer&#44; is nothing more than a wish&#44;<lb/> for the realization of that which Abraham first<lb/> endeavoured to bring about. and for which For that we<lb/> ourselves petition in the oft repeated Kedush&#225;&#44;<lb/> and more expressively so in that of our Ashkenazic<lb/> brethren&#44; viz &#34;May we hallow Thy name in the<lb/> world&#44; as it is hallowed in the highest heavens&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Gentilism of antiquity believed that the heavens Empyrean<lb/> was inhabited by immortal beings&#44; whom they<lb/> called gods deities&#44; bu divinities but that the mortals should be<lb/> taken knowledge of by One Supreme Being&#44; that<lb/> the government of nations and individuals should<lb/> fall under the immediate supervision of One all&#45;seeing<lb/> and all&#45;regulating God&#44; was an idea which their intellect could<lb/> not grasp.  Even master the elevated minds of an Ari&#45;<lb/>&#45;stotle in Greece and of a Cicero in Rome remained stran&#45;<lb/>&#45;gers to the sublimest of thoughts&#44; which long centuries<lb/> before&#44; the shepherd of Ur Chasdim conceived and pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;pagated.  Abraham taught the truth that the Creator<lb/> is intimately related to His creatures&#44; that He tenderly cares<lb/> for them&#44; and helps them to choose right when<lb/> they incline their hearts are inclined to do right.  The Talmudists<lb/> discovered the embodiment of our patriarch&#39;s mission&#44;<lb/> in the oath which I have quoted.  Thus spoke the master<lb/> said to his servant.  The God to whose guidance<lb/> I commend thy steps for the happy issue of your<lb/> journey&#44; is He whom I have proclaimed as the God<lb/> of the earth.  Before Ere I had preached my doctrine&#44; he was<lb/> feared as a king of the sky.  I have set up for Him<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>a throne in the world wherein we move&#44; that<lb/> He may ultimately be <sic>worshipped</sic> as the Monarch<lb/> of all the &#91;&#63;&#93; habitable globe.  That confiding<lb/> trust which animated and sustained the father of<lb/> the faithful&#59; that abiding reliance in the spread<lb/> of righteousness&#44; which rejuvenated and beautified the<lb/> life of our patriarch&#44; is the inheritance which we left for our<lb/> enjoyment.  May we value it&#44; and not as its primitive owner&#44;<lb/> and meet him where he abides gloriously&#44; for so write our sages.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> On the mountain of the Lord&#44; in the holy place&#44; which<lb/> they enter who are clean of hands&#44; and pure of hearts&#44;<lb/> who have never sold undelivered sold their souls to vanity&#44;<lb/> nor stained their lips with falsehood&#44; there Abra&#45;<lb/>&#45;ham stands.  He whom the Lord blessed in all<lb/> things&#44; while alive on earth&#44; dispenses cl celestial blessings<lb/> to all who have taken chosen him as their exemplar.<lb/>  and present the The venerable Hebrew ushers in into salvation&#44; those all<lb/> May we be reckoned among those hereafter who have sought<lb/> their deliverance beneath the shield of Abraham.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
