<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF21_4</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1895" source="" attested="yes">1895</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff21_4_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff21_4_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff21_4_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff21_4_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff21_4_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff21_4_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff21_4_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff21_4_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff21_4_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff21_4_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff21_4_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff21_4_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>S. MORAIS.<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET.<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;&#95;1895<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            
            <p>38</p>
            
            <p>On forbidden food<lb/>
                Sabbath Shemini<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>In conversation with an eminent physician&#44;<lb/> I learned to my surprise that a certain article<lb/> of food almost universally prized as a delicacy&#44;<lb/> has been discovered to possess qualities injuring the<lb/> health of those who eat it.  I had often<lb/> read that persons who indulged in it&#44; suffered bo&#45;<lb/>&#45;dily pains and&#44; at times&#44; paid even with their lives<lb/> as a penalty for having partaken of it immoderately.  But<lb/> I attributed such evil results to the abuse&#44; not to<lb/> the use of that dainty.  Now&#44; I have the testimony<lb/> of medical science to prove the contrary of what<lb/> most people believe.  The portion of the Penta&#45;<lb/>&#45;teuch assigned for our instruction this Sabbath&#44;<lb/> brought back to my memory the conversation I had<lb/> with a friend&#44; who ranks high in the medical<lb/> faculty.  Our Parasha devotes a whole lengthy<lb/> chapter to the subject of the Jewish diet.  I will<lb/> not deny that the prohibitory laws which we<lb/> have read concerning various species of living things<lb/> on whose flesh people ordinarily feed&#44; aim<lb/></p> 
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>largely to set draw a distinction between Israel and<lb/> gentilism and to serve likewise as reminders to those<lb/> whom the God of Sinai separated set apart for a spirit&#45;<lb/>ual purpose&#44; that they must to avoid gross all sorts of food<lb/> likely to affecting the mind as well as the body.  This<lb/> seems clear from the repeated expression. &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;It is unclean to you&#34;&#44; it is forbidden to you&#44;<lb/> it is an abomination to you.  And again&#58; Ye<lb/> shall be holy&#44; for I the Lord am holy.  Ye shall<lb/> not therefore pollute your souls with impure<lb/> animals&#59; with things that creep on the ground.<lb/>  The entire eleventh chapter of Leviticus advances<lb/> the same idea throughout.  And its closing<lb/> sentence tells demands of all Hebrews to make a difference<lb/> between the what is unclean to them and the what is clean&#44; between<lb/> the living thing that they may be eaten and the<lb/> living thing that may they dare not be eaten.<lb/></p>
            <p>But the question a doubt has arisen in the minds of<lb/> some&#44; who would not&#44; I think&#44; deliberately<lb/> transgress for the sake of gratifying the<lb/> appetites.  They questioned whether certain creatures furnished with<lb/> shells&#44; instead of fins and scales were contemplated<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>by the inspired legislator&#44; when he penned<lb/> the chapter to which I have just referred.<lb/>  I have listened with interest to discussions<lb/> on that point&#44; not&#44; of course&#44; when the question<lb/> was treated with levity and flippancy&#44; not when ribaldry<lb/> vulgarly said that Moses would not have pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;hibited a toothsome bit&#44; if he had known of it or had<lb/> ever tasted it.  From that talk I turn away<lb/> with utter disgust.  But serious persons have contend&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed that no provision is made in the five<lb/> holy books about things that can exist out<lb/> of the water&#44; and are though science still includes them in the category<lb/> of fishes.  The oyster&#44; for instance&#44; that at&#45;<lb/>&#45;taches itself to situations places which are left dry<lb/> by the retiring tide&#44; some would consider as be&#45;<lb/>&#45;longing rather to the vegetable kingdom.  But insuf&#45;<lb/>&#45;ficient&#44; indeed&#44; as my reading on that topic is&#44;<lb/> I differ&#44; because I learn that except in water&#44;<lb/> or the vicinity of water&#44; or where water had<lb/> been flowing&#44; the oyster cannot live&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>and I hold that to it and similar living creatures&#44;<lb/> the following text in our Parasha meant to<lb/> point.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;All that have not fins and scales&#44; in the seas<lb/> and in the streams&#44; all that moves in water and<lb/> every living creature that is in the water&#44; are an<lb/> abomination to you.&#34;  Curiously enough&#44; while<lb/> reflecting upon what a medical friend of mine had stated&#44;<lb/> my attention was drawn to an article written<lb/> in Hebrew.  It related that London phy&#45;<lb/>&#45;sicians had strongly advised all persons<lb/> to abstain from that palatable food luxury&#44; as<lb/> apt to occasion engender a species of typhus.  Ac&#45;<lb/>&#45;cording to the same journal&#44; the sale of that<lb/> article of food which had always been immense&#44; has<lb/> decreased so perceptibly that whereas formerly three<lb/> hundred fishermen were engaged at the seasonable time of the year in dredging to<lb/> supply the market&#44; now comparatively few are employed<lb/> in it&#44; so that the sale what heretofore realized<lb/> over two thousand pounds sterling weekly&#44; it<lb/> does not yield now at present more than a few some hundreds.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Possibly&#44; the writer author of that Hebrew article<lb/> does not possess very accurate and reliable<lb/> information.  Possibly also his feelings led him<lb/> to overdraw the picture&#44; for I notice that in<lb/> citing the case of a Purim festivity in New<lb/> York&#44; where the attendants banquetted on<lb/> shell fish&#44; he declares that they sinned more<lb/> grievously than Jews who publicly desecrate the day of<lb/> atonement.  I would not go that length&#44;<lb/> but I agree upon recognizing the act as un&#45;<lb/>Mosaic&#45;scriptural&#44; supporting myself upon the prohibition<lb/> of eating &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; which I so interpret Any living thing<lb/> which needs lives moves in water&#44; but has neither fins nor though it may continue to exist on the ground as amphibia.<lb/> scales.  Contrary to my<lb/> opinion is that of the &#34;American Israelite&#34; in<lb/> its issue of the first week in April.  It<lb/> writes&#58; &#34;There has been said so much lately as<lb/> to whether the Law of Moses permits or pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;hibits oysters&#44; that it may be proper to state<lb/> that according to the Talmud&#44; Moses did not<lb/> forbid them.  There can be no doubt that the<lb/> shell of the oyster&#44; is the same to all intents<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>and purposes&#44; as the scales are to clean<lb/> fishes.&#34;  Against this specious manner<lb/> of arguing&#44; we may point to the fact that<lb/> Moses repeatedly mentions fins and scales as in&#45;<lb/>dispensable to Israelites to make a creature in the water per&#45;<lb/> &#45;missible allowable to an Israelite&#44; the world all over&#44; and not once does he point refer to an object<lb/> which&#44; according to the editor of the American<lb/> Israelite&#44; is equivalent to fins and scales.  But<lb/> the weekly periodical ventures further and as&#45;<lb/>&#45;serts that both the Talmud and Maimonides per&#45;<lb/>&#45;mit shell fish&#44; since nature has provided it<lb/> with what stands in lieu of fins and scales.<lb/>  I have diligently searched through those author&#45;<lb/>&#45;ities&#44; but failed to find what would justify the edit&#45;<lb/>&#45;or&#39;s declaration.  Perhaps&#44; the wish was<lb/> father to the thought&#44; for all will remember<lb/> that at the graduation of the first five rabbis<lb/> issued from the Western Union College&#44; the guests<lb/> were regaled with a variety of shell fish&#44; and<lb/> when the president of the institution whose motto<lb/> is &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;for the Law and the Testimony&#44;&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>was asked for an explanation of that ano&#45;<lb/>maly&#44; he bluntly answered that he was is<lb/> not the keeper of orthodox stomachs&#45;&#45;a<lb/> reply scarcely admissible in an English phrase&#45; Lexicon<lb/> &#45;ology&#44; as an elegant phrase.  Surely&#44; if one were inclined<lb/> to overlook deviations from scriptural Biblical and tradi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tional ordinances in persons not possessed of<lb/> Rabbinical titles&#44; he cannot wink at actions<lb/> clearly at variance with the written and oral<lb/> Law&#44; when committed by men whom Malachi<lb/> would that they proceed straight forwardly<lb/> and turn many away many from wrong doing transgression.  The<lb/> last of our prophets would thus reproach back&#45;<lb/>&#45;sliders in the American rabbinate &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;ye have caused many to stumble in the<lb/> Torah.&#34;  Oh teachers of in Israel&#33;  Beware of the<lb/> sin of presumption.  Nadab and Abihu&#44; the<lb/> two elder sons of Aaron arrogated to them&#45;<lb/>&#45;selves undue authority.  The consequence of their<lb/> immodesty is recorded in the section of the Penta&#45;<lb/>&#45;teuch designated for this Sabbath.  I have read<lb/> that Epictetus&#44; a celebrated teacher of ethics moralist among<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>the Greeks&#44; lay down a maxim&#44; to follow<lb/> which is to approach human perfectibility&#58;<lb/> &#34;bear and forbear.&#34;  We cannot benefit God by<lb/> overcoming our selfish inclinations and controlling<lb/> our appetites&#44; but by doing acting so&#44; we can bring do<lb/> upon ourselves an incalculable amount of<lb/> good.  Hence the wholesome rule restrictions of our reli&#45;<lb/>&#45;gion&#44; some of which we have perused of this morn&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing&#44; useful as applicable to every Israelite.  Pulpit instructors&#44;<lb/> however&#44; ought to keep ever present the injunc&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion of the prophet&#44; who preceded Epictetus by<lb/> many centuries.  Micah recommended that man<lb/> should walk humbly with God.  How much<lb/> more so the ought ministers of God to setting an example<lb/> of abstemiousness and moderation&#44; which will<lb/> react upon the people at large&#44; who observe<lb/> and cite the conduct of such&#44; as wear the<lb/> sacerdotal garment of preceptors in in the shrine of dedicated to the Torah.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
