<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF2_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1893" source="" attested="yes">1893</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff2_1_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS.<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET.<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44;	189<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>67</p>
            <p>Forth For the Penitential Sabbath 1893<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>A commercial house has collapsed&#59; a savings<lb/> fund has sunk&#59; a mechanics&#39; Bank has<lb/> burst&#59; a life insurance company has become<lb/> insolvent.  By such news tidings readers of daily<lb/> papers were startled two some three months ago through the<lb/> length and breadth of this land.  Men noted for<lb/> their self&#45;possession&#44; appeared bewildered.  You<lb/> asked for the reason of so painful a change&#44; and<lb/> the invariable answer was &#34;the stringency in<lb/> the money market&#44; caused brought about by unforseen failures<lb/> among us and abroad.  That is enough to upset<lb/> people&#39;s mind.&#34;  But he who thinks aright&#44;<lb/> or rather he who thinks righteously reflects<lb/> and is saddened.  He reasons argues Persons who make for them&#45;<lb/>&#45;selves gods of silver and gold&#44; will show signs<lb/> of a disordered intellect&#44; when those false deities<lb/> manifest prove their inability to save &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; For God is the sole sovereign Ruler&#44; says the Rabinist.  He<lb/> has not delegated His power to objects which<lb/> mortals are apt to consider all&#45;mighty.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>We may <sic>sympathise</sic> with human creatures<lb/> in their trials and doubtless many and sore<lb/> have been of late those endured in business circles&#44; but ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;perience joins religion in teaching that nothing is<lb/> a sport to dead chance&#59; that a Supreme Ruler<lb/> Power Being has ordained causes and He directs their effects<lb/> more unerringly than the skilful pilot steers his<lb/> ship&#59; that the infallible Guide lets makes events that<lb/> happen carry out the principles of absolute justice.  To<lb/> say tell it with in the language of the Rabbis.  The Lord wishes us to<lb/> know understand &#91;Hebrew&#93; that there is a<lb/> Judge who apportions to us all our due.<lb/></p>  
            <p>Life both national and individual has a mission and when we are too slow&#44; or<lb/> too slothful in its performance&#44; we need be<lb/> spurred on by a thrust.  What some call mis&#45;<lb/>fortune&#44; believers will recognize as a heavenly ordination<lb/> to subserve beneficent ends &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> For God does not afflict willingly to aggrieve the<lb/> children of man.  In that belief we&#44; my<lb/> fellow&#45;Israelites have been were born and bred.  We bless<lb/> the invisible Hand when it strikes&#44; as when it dis&#45;<lb/>penses gifts&#44; because from the cradle we learned<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="5"/>
                <p>to look upon it with the eyes of an enlightened<lb/> faith&#44; which see correctly.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Know that every thing is reckoned with pre&#45; exact<lb/>&#45;cision &#45;ness.  Such is the decision of wisdom drawn<lb/> from the Fountain Head of Truth.  The house of Israel<lb/> has accepted that decision&#44; therefore do its members<lb/> yearly hold a convocation of the deepest solemnity.<lb/>  The day of atonement&#44; observed in all lands countries where<lb/> the outcasts of Judea have their domicile&#44; stands<lb/> forth to illustrate that doctrinal point of<lb/> the Jewish religion&#44; namely&#44; God&#39;s Omniscience<lb/> and his retributive justice.  Our festivals&#44; my<lb/> brethren&#44; have all an historical basis.  At one season&#44;<lb/> we celebrate the traditional anniversary of the birth<lb/>day of creation&#59; at another the Mosaic computing<lb/> of the dawn of our nationality.  Now we rejoice<lb/> over our father&#39;s safety through howling wildernesses&#44;<lb/> anon we are made mentally to stand at the foot<lb/> of Sinai.  The thwarting of our enemies&#39; plans<lb/> and our signal victory over ungodliness in ancient<lb/></p> 
                
                <pb n="6"/>
                <p>times&#44; call for f our devotional gatherings.<lb/>  Kippur alone bears a dogmatic significance.<lb/>  It means this.  A judicial sentence is pronounced<lb/> on human actions at a faultless tribunal and<lb/> it is carried out here as well as hereafter.  The<lb/> congregation of Jacob fast upon the day of atonement<lb/> because self&#45;denial is the parent of is the germ typifies a return to it the very the seminal principle of virtue.  They<lb/> pray for the forgiveness of sin&#44; because they<lb/> acknowledge sin to be the actual parent of suffering<lb/> alike temporal and moral.  They realize that<lb/> to repent of misdeeds is to put on the armor<lb/> of righteousness shielding from sufferings.<lb/>  Happy we&#44; happy our homes&#44; our communities and<lb/> our country&#44; if the anguish of mind which commercial<lb/> reverses have occasioned served to awakened a sense of dependence<lb/> on righ virtue and righteousness for salvation&#59; if those<lb/> vicissitudes impressed all deeply with the lesson<lb/> of Holy Writ that not gold but God reigns for<lb/> ever&#44; that &#91;Hebrew&#93; He who rears his<lb/> fortress upon riches&#44; builds on quick sand.<lb/>  So convinced&#44; we would endeavour to be lifted up<lb/> on impregnable rocks&#44; rather than heedlessly<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="7"/>
            <p>lean for support on decaying matter.  We would<lb/> bestow more attention than we do on the means<lb/> of ennobling our character&#44; <sic>spiritualising</sic> our existence life.<lb/>  We would pay less homage to a despotic ruler&#45;lucre&#45;<lb/>and more to the merciful Ruler Adonai.  Not<lb/> to despise the comforts which a well earned competence procures&#44;<lb/> but to employ it as a servant.  Yes&#44; as a servant obe&#45;<lb/>&#45;dient to our intelligent will and human instincts.<lb/>  But so long as we allow it lucre to tyrannize over us&#44;<lb/> demanding our every day&#39;s attendance&#44; not infrequently<lb/> levying a tax on the hours&#44; which we should devote to<lb/> rest&#44; and those which we should entirely give to the<lb/> sweets of domestic life&#59; so long as we voluntarily sur&#45;<lb/>&#45;render our free agency to an imaginary deity that<lb/> cannot save&#44; we run counter to the object of our<lb/> existence and therefore become unmanned when losses<lb/> are sustained.  I fancy that I can hear some<lb/> who had sacrificed the purest delights&#44; the endear&#45;<lb/>&#45;ments of wife and children&#44; the association of the<lb/> generous and liberal large hearted&#44; the intercourse of the<lb/> sincerely devout&#44; all that to ceaselessly watch the<lb/> turning of the wheel of Fortune&#44; I fancy I can<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="8"/>
                <p>hear them each cry out against himself &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Behold a man who<lb/> did not make God his strength&#44; but trusted in<lb/> abundant riches&#44; and made himself strong in wrong&#34;.<lb/></p>
                <p>Let none rejoice because when the ways of the Lord<lb/> are thus vindicated.  Heartless must be that being he be&#44;<lb/> who withholds his sympathies from his neighbor<lb/> mentally distressed.  The skepticism store philosophy which breeds<lb/> indifference to the ills affecting mankind&#44; has<lb/> no harbor within the borders of Judaism.<lb/>  Nor dares a Hebrew set himself up as Judge<lb/> against about the shortcomings and unwise acts of his<lb/> fellow mortals &#91;Hebrew&#93;  Do not<lb/> condemn others&#44; till thou art placed in the<lb/> same situation&#44; is the charitable maxims of a Sage&#44;<lb/> who would check a disposition to fault finding&#45;&#45;<lb/>so prone to it we all unhappily are&#33;  But re&#45;<lb/>&#45;ligion whose ways lead to pleasantness&#44; and<lb/> whose all paths are conducive to peace &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> religion utters truths&#44; suggestive of an instruction that<lb/> may reclaim the incautious.  At this time<lb/> of our year That beneficent mentor&#44; that Divine<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="9"/>
                <p>Messenger is sent among men to declare an overweening love<lb/> for money&#44; a sin bearing the seeds of chastisement<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  There are riches&#44; says<lb/> the oldest preacher&#44; kept by the owner thereof to<lb/> his injury.  Suasively religion appeals<lb/> to our intellects&#44; that we may not recklessly<lb/> defeat the object of our having been created for<lb/> immortality.  Religion proclaims that &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; the heavens&#44; even the heavens<lb/> are the Lord&#39;s&#44; and the earth He gave to the<lb/> children of man&#44; not that the last e revered from<lb/> the first&#44; but that it may progr prove a progressive<lb/> step to our higher ascent.  Religion tells us that the<lb/> earth is the school of human advancement.  In it we<lb/> must diligently work for our perfectibility and from<lb/> it we shall rise spiritually&#44; if our aspirations had been<lb/> spiritual.  Religion draws a moral from the heart&#45;<lb/>&#45;burnings occasioned by a misapplication of our<lb/> faculties&#59; by the centering of our powers on the attain&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment of fleeting goods.  And in order to guide<lb/> our spirits upward&#44; it pictures a confiding trust in<lb/> the Almighty as a central pillar in the upholding<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="10"/>
                <p>of our character&#44; contentment as the wealth of<lb/> our soul.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  He is rich&#44; who<lb/> enjoys his allotted portion.  How enamored<lb/> we ought to be with a religion&#44; whose maxims<lb/> are radiant lights to lead us on safely&#44; through<lb/> the intricate paths of our earthly career.  How gra&#45;<lb/>&#45;teful we ought to be to a religion&#44; which gives us<lb/> the assurance that should we even have strayed<lb/> away&#44; we can regain the way of salvation&#44; if we<lb/> lay hold of the rod of self correction&#45;&#45;the staff of re&#45;<lb/>&#45;pentance.  Israelites. that religion addresses each<lb/> of us at this solemn period of our year.  It speaks<lb/> in inspiring acts accents of God&#39;s forgiveness and love.<lb/>  It reaches the joyous assurances which we have<lb/> read in the prophetic lesson of this penitential<lb/> Sabbath &#34;I will heal their backslidings&#44; I will<lb/> love them freely&#44; for My anger is turned away<lb/> from them.  I will be as the dew to Israel.  He<lb/> shall blossom as the lily and cast forth his<lb/> roots as Lebanon.  His branches shall spread<lb/> and his beauty shall be as the olive tree&#44; and<lb/> his fragrance like that of Lebanon.<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="11"/>
                <p>May it be so&#44; O Lord of our salvation.  Calm<lb/> the agitation of human hearts&#59; restore to them<lb/> the Joys of confidence and contentment.  Bid<lb/> sickness flee apace&#44; command a lasting cure<lb/> for those who suffer.  May the mourners<lb/> look up to Thee with eyes whose tears faith<lb/> in immortality has wiped away&#44; and vouch&#45;<lb/>&#45;safe to destine for American success as a reward<lb/> for her children&#39;s self denying patriotism&#44; security<lb/> at home&#44; good will and honors abroad.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
