<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF5_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_1_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>An explanatory lecture<lb/> on Chay&#233; Sarah<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33; I do not at all wonder that many of the<lb/> sayings of our ancient teachers have furnished a &#91;&#63;&#93; for<lb/> ridicule.  They are so odd&#59; they present themselves before<lb/> our minds in so strange a form&#44; that one may be led to con&#45;<lb/>&#45;sider them sheer absurdities.  Yet&#44; if we will take pains<lb/> to think&#44; and will not dismiss with a scornful smile what is<lb/> found among lessons unquestionably wise&#44; derision will often<lb/> give room to admiration.  I will not claim for the<lb/> Rabbis infallibility&#44; but surely it is not exacting too much to ask<lb/> that they be judged by the same standard that other men are<lb/> judged.  Let us reason&#58; I have made the acquaintance<lb/> of a person&#44; who speaks sensibly upon all subjects.  I consult<lb/> him and receive a good advice&#44; I seek information about matters<lb/> pertaining to the history of religion&#59; to the developing<lb/> of arts and sciences&#44; as far as the investigations of the time<lb/> could can reach&#44; and learn what affords me both pleasure and<lb/> instruction.  But this same individual will occasionally<lb/> startle me with a quaint remark.  Ought I to set it<lb/> down as a sheer vagary&#44; rather than ponder&#44; and ascertain<lb/> whether it does not cover some deep meaning&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>My experience shows that he who gave utterance<lb/> to it has a well&#45;balanced mind&#44; and that he is moreover<lb/> an acute observer of human nature.  I must therefore&#44; in<lb/> justice to my acquaintance&#44; pause before pronouncing an<lb/> opinion to his disparagement.  Such a course&#44; I think&#44;<lb/> it behooves us to follow regarding the singular expressions<lb/> emanating from the Sages of Israel.<lb/></p>
            <p>Maimonides&#44; whom no one will charge with being incap&#45;<lb/>&#45;able of forming a dispassionate judgment&#44; says&#44;&#45;&#45;though<lb/> not precisely in these words&#45;&#45;&#44; that the thoughtless will read<lb/> some of the sayin expressions of the Rabbis&#44; and turn away<lb/> from them&#44; as being the issue of folly&#59; the thoughtful&#44;<lb/> on the contrary&#44; will discover therein&#44; by dint of meditation&#44;<lb/> a depth of wisdom&#44; worthy of the authors.  Jewish<lb/> literature must be lament&#44; that the celebrated writer just<lb/> named&#44; either left his promise unfulfilled&#44; or&#44; if he did write<lb/> a book explanatory of those obscure utterances of our ancient<lb/> instructors&#44; he omitted to publish it to the world.  For<lb/> by its means&#44; we might unravel what seems enigmatical&#44; and&#44;<lb/> at times&#44; ludicrous&#44; and thus silence the Eisenmengers&#44; the<lb/> Chiarcius&#44; and the Mc&#39;Calls&#44; the writers of Rabbinism.<lb/></p>  
            <p>Dear hearers&#33;  This train of thoughts was suggested<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>to my mind&#44; as I searched in a Talmudic volume for some elucidation to<lb/> a passage in our Parasha.  We read that &#34;Abraham<lb/> was old&#44; well stricken in years&#44; and the Lord had blessed<lb/> Abraham in all things.&#34;  By that we are made<lb/> to understand&#44; that the patriarch when far advanced in life&#44;<lb/> enjoyed complete happiness.  But shortly before that<lb/> statement&#44; the scriptures relate that he had been greatly<lb/> saddened.  Every word of his recorded in that narrative&#44; proves And the sacred records prove<lb/> how keenly he felt the bereavement sustained.  I was revolving<lb/> that fact on mind my mind&#44; when I met with a singular saying&#44;<lb/> attributed to R. Simeon son of Eleazar&#44; one of our Mishnic<lb/> Sages.  He states&#44; that Abraham was made happy by<lb/> the possession of a bright Jewel&#44; hanging round his neck.<lb/>  For whosoever&#44; being sick&#44; looked upon it&#44; was restored to<lb/> health.  After Abraham had died&#44; God took that precious stone&#44;<lb/> and hung it round the luminary of the day &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> The saying is indeed exceedingly strange&#44; and&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> taken in its literal sense&#44; it must be regarded as the creation<lb/> of a heated brain&#44; but who will assert that such is its origin&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Our knowledge of the learning and standing of him who<lb/> pronounced it&#44; should prompt us to seek for the hidden<lb/> meaning it must undoubtedly contain.  In the absence<lb/> of a traditional explanation expounding&#44; we are all at liberty to choose<lb/> that which strikes us as the most rational construction.  I therefore submit<lb/> what to me appears as an illustration of the character of<lb/> Abraham our father.  Truly a bright Jewel was<lb/> that conspicuity of a virtuous conduct&#44; which drew from<lb/> heathens the acknowledgment that our patriarch was a<lb/> &#34;prince of God.&#34;  An ornament it was&#44; made visible to<lb/> all eyes.  There may be some&#44; dear friends&#33; who are<lb/> endowed with noble qualities&#44; yet they remain latent&#59; the<lb/> occasions by which they may practically be brought into<lb/> action happen to be rare.  But Abraham stood forth<lb/> prominently as a model of goodness and righteousness.  His<lb/> whole intercourse with the men of his age marked him out as<lb/> illustrious.  Thus&#44; his having fostered his orphaned nephew&#44;<lb/> was a circumstance possibly unknown beyond his own<lb/> circle.  But the kindly&#44; the fatherly manner in which he<lb/> effected a peaceful separation from Lot&#59; the &#91;&#63;&#93; he gave him to<lb/> choose the richest land for the pasture of his flock&#44; the<lb/> salvation he wrought for his distressed relative&#44; when a<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>prisoner in the hand of a marauding horde&#44; were<lb/> deeds in which many of his contemporaries saw the principles<lb/> that guided the great believer.  So likewise&#44; his intercessorceding<lb/> for the sinful people of Sodom&#44; may have been a secret com&#45;<lb/>&#45;munion of his soul with the Most High&#44; but his risking life<lb/> and property to deliver the captured and the plundered&#59; his<lb/> refusal to accept aught of what&#44; by the laws of war&#44; he could<lb/> claim as entirely his own&#44; mirrored forth the excellencies of<lb/> his nature.  In the figurative language of R. Simeon son<lb/> of Eleazar&#44; those traits so clearly exhibited&#44; formed the bright<lb/> jewel adorning his person.  Abraham was rendered happy<lb/> by the assurance that his uprightness would accomplish a blessed<lb/> end.  Even as That it would bring healing to many spiritually<lb/> diseased.  Even as a sparkling gem&#44; reproduced the object<lb/> that looks into it&#44; in the beauty or in the unsightliness thereof&#44;<lb/> so would the gentiles of old by contemplating the character of<lb/> the patriarch&#44; detect their own deformities&#44; and grow better and<lb/> wiser.  For verily one good man eminently stationed&#44;<lb/> can improve his surroundings by the force of his example&#44;<lb/> better than thousands of stringent laws.  If we needed<lb/> proofs that associate with Abraham&#44; was followed by<lb/> those results&#44; we should but attentively read the section of this<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Sabbath&#44; and we would become enlightened.  For the trusty<lb/> servant&#44; whom the patriarch had gotten from Damascus&#44;<lb/> obviously reflected in his demeanour the virtues of his master.<lb/>  Relying upon God for the choice of a woman worthy to<lb/> become Isaac&#39;s wife&#44; he who had been rightly schooled&#44; still<lb/> asked as a token of her fitness&#44; a remarkably kind disposition.<lb/>  To him&#44; a stranger&#44; she was voluntarily to profer services<lb/> which demanded labor&#44; and loss of time.  Legends are not<lb/> wanting as evidences of the fact that Abraham stood among the<lb/> people of his age&#44; as a central figure&#44; to which all eyes were directed&#44;<lb/> but without having recourse to the fictitious or fabulous&#44; we are shown in Holy<lb/> Writ that noble form&#44; lovely in all its lineaments.  The description<lb/> given by the pages of truth&#44; of the godliness of Abraham&#39;s character&#44;<lb/> warrants the bold smile of Rabbi Simeon.  Whosoever looked<lb/> on the jewel that the father of the faithful wore&#44; namely<lb/> his unsurpassing virtues virtuous life&#44; the illness under which he suffered&#44; dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;sappeared&#59; that is&#44; he became a being morally and spiritually<lb/> regenerated.  The conviction that his existence was the agency<lb/> of salvation&#44; infused into the aged patriarch a calmness of<lb/> spirit&#44; a serenity which partook of the celestial&#59;<lb/></p> 
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>and which the Scriptures signify by the words&#44; &#34;And<lb/> the Lord blessed Abraham in all things.&#34;  He experienced a fortune of general felicity<lb/> upon earth&#44; because the spring of human happiness is kept will never<lb/> fresh stagnate&#59; as long as it circulates in every direction that many may<lb/> draw&#44; from its refreshing waters.  But good and exalted as<lb/> the father of our race was&#44; he must share the lot of all beings.<lb/>  He laid to lay down and died&#59; yet&#44; the effects of his virtues survived<lb/> his mortality.  Before David had pointed to the heavens&#44; as<lb/> the narrators of the glory of God&#44; Abraham made them speak<lb/> of the existence of the Creator within the hearing of mankind.<lb/>  What nature had revealed to his soul&#44; he had imparted to the<lb/> world.  When his lips could no more call on invoke the name of<lb/> the Lord before the gentiles&#44; every rising sun&#44; would mirror forth<lb/> the power&#44; the wisdom&#44; the goodness of Abraham&#39;s God.<lb/>  Hence did R. Simeon say that after the patriarch had been<lb/> gathered to his fathers&#44; the bright stone he wore&#44; was hung<lb/> round the luminary of the day&#44; in order to effect the care<lb/> of the diseased.  The handiwork of the Divine Maker&#44;<lb/> was to recalled men from their errors&#44; as His great missionary<lb/> had taught striven to do by words precepts and by example.<lb/>
                Dear Brethren&#33; I have given you the interpretation of<lb/> a curious saying of a Rabbi.  It is not improbable&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>that I may have failed to dive into the signification&#44;<lb/> it intended to convey&#59; but my object was to correct<lb/> a false impression too prevalent among even our people&#59;<lb/> that the writings of our Sages need not be heeded&#44; for&#44; they are destitute of merits.  Speak<lb/> to them of the Bible&#44; and they will&#44; unless tinctured with<lb/> Deistic notions&#44; accept its dictates with veneration.  But<lb/> name to them the custodians of the Bible&#44; the self&#45;denying<lb/> guardians of our history and traditions the Rabbis&#44; and they will eye you<lb/> askance.  They will not scruple to wince their antipathy<lb/> for whatever savors of Rabbinical teaching.  Yet&#44; without&#44;<lb/> as I have stated before&#44; claiming for the Rabbis infallibility&#59;<lb/> conceding their inability in some instances to rise above their<lb/> pernicious surroundings&#44; I declare in all truth&#44; that the<lb/> knowledge they bequeathed to us is an inexhaustible treasure&#59;<lb/> that despite all the contumely heaped upon the Talmud&#44;<lb/> it stands after eighteen centuries as the greatest work of human<lb/> sapience&#44; and that what we meet in it and collateral<lb/> works shrouded in enigmas&#44; deserves to be meditated upon&#44;<lb/> as the emanation of superior minds.<lb/></p>
            <p>&#40;Here follows an address to a lad&#44; who completed his 13th year&#41;.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
