<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF5_8</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_8_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_8_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_8_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_8_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_8_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_8_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_8_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_8_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_8_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_8_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_8_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff5_8_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. Fifth St.<lb/>
                Philadelphia&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>P. B Historical lecture<lb/>
                51<lb/>
                French School<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>It is now some years since I gave a series of lectures<lb/> on post&#45;biblical history.  At that time neither the &#34;outlines&#34;<lb/> by Mrs Magnus&#44; nor an English translation of Graetz&#39;s<lb/> comprehensive history&#44; existed.  To make the Sabbath&#45;<lb/>morning <sic>worshippers</sic> in this Synagogue&#45;&#45;more especially<lb/> the young&#45;&#45;acquainted with what they could not read&#45;<lb/>&#45;ily find in a condensed and popular form&#44; I under&#45;<lb/>&#45;took my task.  I prepared an account of leading<lb/> events in our annals from the restoration of the exiles of<lb/> Chaldea to the Holy Land&#44; to the closing of the Babylonish<lb/> Talmud under direction of the famous Rab Ash&#233;.<lb/>  Only fifty lectures of nearly the same length I<lb/> delivered at short intervals&#44; but my original intent&#45;<lb/>&#45;ion had been to proceed till as closely as possible to the age in which we<lb/> live.  Why I did not then carry out the plan&#44; I<lb/> can scarcely explain to myself.  Perhaps&#44; I consti&#45;<lb/>&#45;tutionally lack a determined perseverance in literary<lb/> labors.  Perhaps also&#44; I may have detected a slacking<lb/> in the attendance of those I particularly wished to reach&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>on the absence of general interest in the audience&#44;<lb/> and I relinquished my design.  Be that as it may&#44;<lb/> I have thought it now of some use to resume it&#44;<lb/> for a while&#44; at all events&#44; because the work of Mrs<lb/> Magnus&#44; however adapted for Sunday School classes&#44; is<lb/> too fragmentary&#44; and that of Dr Graet&#45;&#45;a short portion<lb/> of which alone has yet appeared in our vernacular&#45;&#45;is<lb/> too extended for most readers.  Passing from<lb/> the East to the West&#44; that is&#44; from Palestine and Babylon<lb/> to the European continent&#44; we may rest our vision<lb/> on France.  The view to which your attention<lb/> may be drawn&#44; was &#45;&#45;formerly opened in the first by a number of the learned&#44;<lb/> was widened in our days by Elyakim Carmoly&#44; followed<lb/> more recently by Isidore Loeb&#44; and at present by<lb/> Madame Darmesteter.  It is not venturing<lb/> too much to surmise that Jews entered France&#44; with<lb/> the Roman legions that spread everywhere in the<lb/> world known by to the ancients.  If the state&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment of some historians&#44; that as early as a century<lb/> before the Christian era&#44; Jews were found in Narbonne&#44;<lb/> be correct&#44; members of our religion may have fought<lb/> among or against the army of Julius Caesar in his<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>in his war upon Gallia&#45;&#45;as France was then called.<lb/></p>
            <p>Their social condition varied according to the<lb/> spirit of the time&#44; controlled by men in authority.<lb/>  At certain periods&#44; Jews were looked upon with favor&#44;<lb/> because of their medical skill and commercial know&#45;<lb/>&#45;ledge&#44; utilized by persons highly stationed&#59; but the<lb/> years of suffering and persecution greatly exceeded<lb/> in number those of comparative ease.  What<lb/> supported sustained our predecessors in their affliction&#44; when<lb/> allowed at all to live in France&#63;  The study of<lb/> the Law and traditions.  Hooted at when walk&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing abroad&#44; pointed at with the finger of scorn every&#45;<lb/>&#45;where&#44; they sought refuge and comfort in the cultivation<lb/> of that literature which their own Sages broadened<lb/> by incessant activity.  The mention of one<lb/> of them will suffice as an illustration.  Who<lb/> has not heard of Rabbi Solomon Ben Isaac&#44; known<lb/> best by the initial of his name and that of his father&#44;<lb/> as Rashi&#63;  Among Jews he enjoys<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>a notoriety wider perhaps than any of our writers&#44;<lb/> excepting the inspired authors of the Hebrew Bible.<lb/>  Among Christians some have made copious extracts<lb/> of his commentaries in Latin and in other languages.<lb/>  That very great man&#44; too humble minded to be con&#45;<lb/>&#45;scious of his greatness&#44; did us lasting services with<lb/> a pen that never tired.  Naturally&#44; round the<lb/> name life of one so celebrated&#44; legends of various kinds<lb/> have clustered.  I believe none of them.  Some<lb/> are absurd&#44; others refute themselves.  Thus&#44; for<lb/> example&#44; it is not credible that Godfrey de Bouillon&#44;<lb/> should have consulted our Rabbi about the probable<lb/> issue of his military campaign for the recovery of<lb/> the sepulchre of the deified man of Nazareth in Jeru&#45;<lb/>&#45;salem.  And who could conceive it possible that Rashi<lb/> who preceded Maimonides by a century should have<lb/> held an interview with his immortal successor at<lb/> Cairo in Egypt&#63;  Some&#44; again have thought to<lb/> exalt Rashi by representing him as a philosopher<lb/> and a poet.  He was neither&#44; but he stands alone<lb/> and <sic>unrivalled</sic> in the course that he chose to give<lb/> us instruction.  Rashi was born in Troyes<lb/></p> 
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>in Northern France&#44; towards the middle of the eleventh<lb/> century of the common era.  He must therefore have<lb/> seen the cruelties practised against his coreligionists by<lb/> the blood thirsty crusaders&#44; kindled into unruly fanati&#45;<lb/>&#45;cism by his countryman&#44; Peter the hermit of Amiens.<lb/>  Taught that suffering is the badge of our tribe&#44; the<lb/> Jewish Sage did not hurl invectives&#44; but bent his whole<lb/> mind upon furnishing his people with a learning&#44;<lb/> that might prove of interest and of use.  For it can&#45;<lb/>not be denied that his commentary&#44; on the Pentateuch<lb/> possesses that double quality.  He may originally<lb/> have intended at the outset to give us a plain elucidation of the text&#44;<lb/> and occasionally he does so&#44; but certain it is that most<lb/> of it the commentary is founded upon allegories and parables of the<lb/> Talmudists&#44; so pleasing to multitudes.  One cannot<lb/> help admiring his thorough familiarity with them&#45; our Aggadists &#38; Midrashists&#45;&#45;<lb/> a familiarity unsurpassed&#59; still I confess that I would<lb/> not base the universal fame which Rashi has gain&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed&#44; upon his comment on the five books of Moses.<lb/>  He himself admitted to a learned grandson of his&#44; that<lb/> if time had been at his disposal&#44; he would have devoted<lb/> it to write according to the literal sense of the original.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>What I consider priceless among the productions<lb/> of that French Jew&#44; is not his numerous scriptur&#45;<lb/>&#45;al commentaries&#44; though comprising&#44; with a single exception&#44;<lb/> the entire Bible&#44; nor his erudite solution of casuistic&#45;<lb/>&#45;al questions reduced into book form.  In my mind&#44;<lb/> Rashi has put the students of Rabbinical literature under<lb/> eternal obligation by his incomparable notes&#44; or<lb/> explanations on the text of the Talmud.  Not a<lb/> superfluous word in them.  The glossary is always<lb/> brief&#44; but always clear&#44; undeviatingly faithful to the<lb/> original.  The latter would have remained incom&#45;<lb/>&#45;prehensibly obscure in countless instances&#44; but for<lb/> the light thrown upon it by the Prince of commentators&#59;<lb/> our Rashi.  At times&#44; when he fears not to have<lb/> conveyed the meaning of a term explicitly enough&#44;<lb/> he helps himself with the vernacular which he must<lb/> have known well.  By way of example&#44; he meets<lb/> a word rarely used&#44; he calls to his aid the French spo&#45;<lb/>&#45;ken at in his time&#44; to render the signification sense obvious<lb/> to the reader.  That a man could singly<lb/> labor so extensively and so successfully&#44; even if<lb/> he did reach the ripe age of seventy five&#44; must seem extraor<lb/>&#45;dinary&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>but that was not legendary&#59; it was a patent fact&#44;<lb/> bordering on the miraculous.  He very nearly com&#45;<lb/>&#45;pleted the commentaries of the immense works&#44; contain&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing Mishnah and Gemara&#44; and the little which death<lb/> made him leave unfinished&#44; was taken up and sup&#45;<lb/>&#45;plemented by such as had drawn knowledge from<lb/> the fountain of his exhaustless erudition.  For&#44; his<lb/> grandsons and relatives were among the first to pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;ceed in the same line of studies which the illustrious<lb/> Sage of Troyes had planned out.  The want<lb/> of male descendants was not felt by Rashi.  His<lb/> three daughters had given birth to personages&#44; whose<lb/> superior scholarship their literary labors incontestably<lb/> attest.  He had married one to a certain Meir<lb/> of Romero and she became the mother of Samuel&#44; Jacob<lb/> and Isaac&#44; all of them authors of high repute&#44; all posses&#45;<lb/>&#45;sed of the qualities&#44; which had so distinguished their grand&#45;<lb/>parent&#44; &#45;&#45;unwearied activity in the field of sacred lore<lb/> and deep humility.  Another daughter was wedded to a Judah<lb/>&#45;&#45;the last an unworthy husband of a Jewish maiden righteously<lb/> brought up.  Those who issued from Rashi on his daughter&#39;s side founded the School of Tosaphists&#44; or writers of appendixes in his comments.  Taking now a general survey<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>of Rashi&#39;s character&#44; we must discover<lb/> the causes of the deep veneration in which he has<lb/> been held ever since&#44; so that his comments occupy a<lb/> place in Hebrew schools and colleges that none other<lb/> have obtained.  The French Jew was the embo&#45;<lb/>&#45;diment of ideas which have stood as a shield&#44; covering<lb/> our people against the attacks of irreligion.  While<lb/> growing philosophy and science in the middle ages<lb/> threatened to shake the foundations of revelation&#44;<lb/> while they made converts to skepticism&#44; that meek<lb/> writer of the eleventh century kept the bulk of of our<lb/> scattered race within the bounds of  traditional Judaism&#44;<lb/> by his multifarious writings and his exceptionally noble personality.<lb/>  Chiefly by reason of that&#44; I judge&#44; his name came<lb/> down to posterity with a halo of sanctity&#44; and the pro&#45;<lb/>ductions of his pen are regarded with religious pious veneration.<lb/>  I think I am correct in saying that Italy&#44; where Hebrew books began to be<lb/> published&#44; shortly after the discovery of the art of printing&#44;<lb/> in the middle of the fifteenth century&#44; honored Rashi&#39;s<lb/> memory by making his commentary on the Pentateuch the<lb/> first&#44; or surely among the very first that issued from the press.<lb/>  Eight hundred years may have lessened the influence<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>once <sic>weilded</sic> by that exemplary Israelite&#59; his name may<lb/> not be so universally celebrated as formerly&#44; but so long<lb/> as Talmud will form constitute a study of the Synagogue preach&#45;<lb/>&#45;er&#45;&#45;and it ought to be his earnest study in order to entitle him to the appellation of<lb/> Rabbi&#45;&#45;so long will the services of Rashi be recognized<lb/> as invaluable&#44; and his name will call forth a blessing.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
