<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF2_3</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_3_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_3_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_3_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_3_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_3_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_3_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_3_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_3_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_3_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_3_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_3_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_3_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_3_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_3_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_3_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff2_3_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>13 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>On the character of Jonathan<lb/>
                the son of Saul.<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Round the brows of many illustrious dead&#44; garlands have<lb/> been set&#44; which an admiring world has woven.  They fit well<lb/> the brave who bled for their kindred and their country.  They<lb/> become the generous&#44; who <sic>benefitted</sic> the human race.  But where<lb/> is the chaplet to adorn the Chief among the noblest&#63;  Has<lb/> it not been yet prepared&#63;  Ah&#33; let me crown the<lb/> king of virtue&#44; Jonathan the impersonation of self&#45;<lb/>sacrificing friendship.<lb/></p>
                <p>Dear hearers&#33;  In describing sentiments absolutely free from<lb/> the dross of egotism&#44; our ancient teachers present to the<lb/> minds two Biblical characters &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;What is love nurtured by no personal interest&#63;&#34; ask the<lb/> Sages in one of their books of morals&#44; and in answer to that<lb/> query&#44; they station set before us David and Jonathan.  But<lb/> with all the veneration due to the authorities just cited&#44; I<lb/> feel impelled to reverse transform the picture.  I place the royal<lb/> heir of the house of Saul first&#44; and the shepherd hereafter.<lb/>  I let Jonathan stand forth in bold relief&#44; because to him<lb/> has been given preeminence assigned superiority in the soul&#45;touching<lb/> episode&#44; a portion of which the Haftarah of this Sabbath<lb/> graphically delineates.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Would that a more skilful hand raised a being clothed<lb/> in righteousness to the place eminence which his merits entitle<lb/> him to occupy&#44; to a place where all might behold<lb/> excellencies rare among mortals.  But let your minds<lb/> supply my inefficiencies&#44; let your minds elevate to<lb/> the highest pinnacle of moral greatness that scion of the Hebrew<lb/> race&#44; if I am too feeble to lift him above lowliness.<lb/></p>
            <p>David had rolled away the shame&#44; which a heathen<lb/> warrior fastened on his people.  The giant who defied<lb/> the tribes and cursed the living god&#44; was silenced in death<lb/> with a stone whirled by the most dexterous slinger.<lb/>  The head of Goliath perched upon his own trenchant<lb/> sword&#44; was brought to the camp of Israel&#44; and the daring<lb/> conqueror laid the trophy at the feet of his king.  The<lb/> sight was inspiring inspired.  Joyous songs&#44; mingled with blithe&#45;<lb/>&#45;some dancing.  The playing of timbrels and enlivening<lb/> instruments echoed through the air.  The shouting of<lb/> victory rent the sky.  But amidst that stirring scene&#44;<lb/> one man looked in ecstasy&#44; and listened most intently.<lb/>  He felt that what he saw and heard had suddenly<lb/> transformed him into another being.  Jonathan expe&#45;<lb/>&#45;rienced felt a stream of the purest love opening within his heart&#59;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>or&#44; to say it as the Bible pithily most forcibly expresses it &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;his soul was knit with the soul of David&#34;<lb/> At that hour&#44; he vowed eternal devotion to the avenger<lb/> of his nation&#39;s honor.  The mantle which showed his<lb/> rank&#44; the raiment apparel which distinguished his person&#44; he<lb/> put upon the victor.  The sword he had already unsheathed<lb/> in defence of his native land&#44; he offered unto the son of<lb/> Jesse as a token of a lasting covenant&#59; nay&#44; he even encircled<lb/> his loins with the girdle which he himself had long manfully<lb/> worn.  David became his ideal.  To fight at<lb/> the side of the valiant youth for home and for religion&#44;<lb/> to be enkindled with patriotic zeal at the sound of the<lb/> harp which he&#44; above all could handle with a masterly touch&#44;<lb/> was Jonathan&#39;s highest aspiration.  And these sentiments<lb/> ever fresh and copious and overflowing&#44; deepened in<lb/> proportion as inconstant fortune ceased to smile<lb/> upon the champion of Israel.<lb/></p>
            <p>Profane history is not barren of instances&#44; proving that<lb/> men can be mutually bound with the strongest ties of affection.<lb/>  Every child has read the incident related of two famous individuals<lb/> in ancient Syracuse.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>We all can remember&#44; when the story of Damon and<lb/> Pythias&#44; said to have been eager to die for one another&#44;<lb/> affected us sensibly.  Yet But&#44; Jonathan the Hebrew&#44;<lb/> has distanced those model characters.  Jonathan has<lb/> outshone all bright exemplars of human friendship.<lb/>  The deeds single him out among the greatest.  For&#44; we<lb/> may brave dangers&#44; jeopardize life&#44; crave for death to<lb/> save one whom we dearly love&#44; but ot bear for his sake the<lb/> anger&#44; the soul&#45;harrowing rebuke&#44; the public contu&#45;<lb/>&#45;mely&#44; the exeration curse of a father&#59; to be exposed to the<lb/> murderous assault of an envious king&#58; aye&#59; to endure<lb/> that and gladly yeild relinquish position and the glory of an<lb/> hereditary crown for a friend&#44; is a virtue partaking<lb/> of the celestial.  And a divine virtue it was<lb/> that knit the soul of Jonathan with the soul of<lb/> David.  Divine&#44; because founded upon religious<lb/> faith. In the name of Israel&#39;s God was their enduring<lb/> affection pledged.  It drew inspiration from on high&#44;<lb/> hence it was mighty&#44; immutable and true.  For&#44;<lb/> that is the vital element of friendship.  To be durable&#44;<lb/> it must be kept fresh by a heavenly source.  Then will<lb/> it survive the object for whom it is cherished&#44; extending<lb/> far into the future&#44; even among our his posterity.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>None who have given the subject due reflection&#44; will<lb/> confound mere personal regard or good&#45;will with friendship&#44;<lb/> nor consonance of sentiments with that feeling&#44; which per&#45;<lb/>&#45;vades and governs our life.  Friends will&#44; of course&#44; abide<lb/> together in harmony&#44; experience reciprocal esteem and wish<lb/> one another well&#44; but not all those who so act&#44; can be<lb/> considered enkindled by that heavenly spark which I<lb/> call friendship&#44; and of which we have been given a sublime pattern<lb/> in our Haftarah.  And what shall I say of that<lb/> so styled friendship among the worldly&#63;  The friendship nou&#45;<lb/>&#45;rished by convival repasts&#44; the friendship formed upon the<lb/> brimful cof cup&#44; or in the resorts of wanton pleasures&#59;<lb/> that sensation restless&#44; fickle&#44; clinging only to the ima&#45;<lb/>&#45;gination&#33;  Is that to assume the name of the all&#45;en&#45;<lb/>&#45;nobling sentiment&#44; so steady and constant&#44; which is fastened<lb/> to the very strings fibres of our hearts&#63;  Will any draw a com&#45;<lb/>&#45;parison between what grows stronger and sweeter with years&#44;<lb/> and that which lasts till time works certain changes&#44; when<lb/> it takes itself wings and flies away&#63;  As well might we<lb/> liken a meteor to the luminary that rules the day&#44; or a night&#45;<lb/>blooming flower to the sturdy oak&#33;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>No&#58; real friendship gives offers sustenance and comfort and<lb/> ornament to this earthly existence&#44; but that which<lb/> inappropriately takes its name often vexes&#44; and stains<lb/> and finally destroys human life.  The former faces<lb/> difficulties&#59; bears humiliation&#44; even public contempt for the being<lb/> loved&#44; as a father will bear all for the sake of his<lb/> child&#44; or as a wife will endure pangs of death for<lb/> him who has plighted his 2 sacred honor and faith in1 her behalf&#59;<lb/> but the latter&#44; the latter&#44; O youthful hearers&#33; will hold<lb/> you by the hand while all around shows security&#44; but let<lb/> a sea of trouble rise&#44; and it will seize the first plank<lb/> whereon to reach the shore safely&#44; leaving you behind<lb/> to struggle with the angry waves.  But no illu&#45;<lb/>&#45;stration of the subject treated&#44; can &#40;the poverty of&#41; my intel&#45;<lb/>&#45;lect bring forth equal in pathos to that which we have<lb/> read this Sabbath.<lb/></p>
            <p>The intrepid valor of David&#44; which had awakened popu&#45;<lb/>&#45;lar enthusiasm&#44; stirred up irreconcilable hatred in the<lb/> bosom of a Ruler for whom he had gallantly fought.<lb/>  He that had put the Philistines often frequently to flight was<lb/> forced to flee apace from parents &#38; from home.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Hotly pursued&#44; he sought a temporary refuge&#44; where<lb/> Samuel lived.  &#40;Surrounded there by royal officers&#44;&#41; he<lb/> succeeded in eluding detection&#44; and in searching and finding<lb/> his faithful Jonathan.  Utterly dejected&#44; trembling at terror&#45;stricken by the sword<lb/> which hung by a hair&#45;breadth above his head&#44; the exile<lb/> pours out in that meeting his soul full of sorrow and of<lb/> dread.  &#34;Thou shalt not die&#44; forbid it God&#34; exclaims<lb/> the loving Jonathan with all the ardor of his glowing na&#45;<lb/>&#45;ture.  &#34;It cannot be&#44; my father would not hide from<lb/> me so atrocious a purpose.  He does not harbor it.<lb/>  Trust me David.&#34;  But the latter speaks.  In accents<lb/> full of tenderness he assures Jonathan that only a<lb/> narrow step separates him form the yawning grave&#59; that<lb/> he will deem a thrust of his friend&#39;s sword into his breast&#44;<lb/> if merited by reason of faults committed&#44; a kindly favor&#44;<lb/> for it will deliver him from the dagger of the assassin.<lb/>  You know&#44; my Brethren&#33; how the son of Saul endea&#45;<lb/>&#45;voured to reassure the agitated son of Jesse.  You<lb/> are acquainted with the plan which was to reveal<lb/> the mind of the king&#44; and apprize the exile of his<lb/> safety or his danger.  You reca can recall the banquet&#44;<lb/> at the palace&#44; the pointed question&#44; the pre&#45;arranged answer&#44;<lb/> the kings royal threat&#44; and the escape.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>But have you noted how inimitably grand in its<lb/> unselfishness is the language of Jonathan at the in&#45;<lb/>&#45;terview <sic>secretely</sic> held in the forest&#63;  &#34;By the Lord God<lb/> of Israel I will sound my father about to&#45;morrow&#44; or<lb/> the day after&#58; if it pleases my father to do thee harm<lb/> I will inform thee&#44; that thou mayest depart and go<lb/> away in peace.....And thou&#44; wilt thou not&#44; if I am<lb/> yet alive&#44; show me the loving kindness of the Lord&#44; that<lb/> I may not die&#63;  Thou wilt not withdraw thy<lb/> favor from my household for ever&#44; when the Lord shall<lb/> have destroyed David&#39;s enemies&#44; every one form off the<lb/> face of the earth.&#34;  The heir apparent to the<lb/> crown of Israel&#44; craves for the enduring attachment<lb/> and protection of a youth straining then his looks to find<lb/> a shelter.  He in whose power it was&#44; at a stroke<lb/> to have cut off every hope in a rival to reach the throne&#44;<lb/> entreats the trembling fugitive to cherish even towards his<lb/> children sentiments of generous affection.  Nay&#58; more&#44;<lb/> in that hour of intense gloom to David&#44; Jonathan brightens<lb/> his horizon&#44; and opening before his vision a glorious future&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>makes him swears again to him a friendship deep and end&#45;<lb/>&#45;less&#59; for&#44; adds the inspired historian &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;he loved him like his own soul.&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>Prince of virtue&#33; illustrious son of our race&#33;  Thine was<lb/> a heart that angels bathed in purity.  Envy feared to<lb/> approach it&#44; for it swelled with emotions repelling what<lb/> is ignoble in nature.  The sceptre lay within<lb/> thy reach&#59; O Jonathan&#33; yet&#44; thou didst encourage him<lb/> to seize it&#44; whom thou chosest as deemedst thy superior.<lb/>  To set him forward&#44; thou wouldst voluntarily with&#45;<lb/>&#45;draw into obscurity.  Too ethereal was thy being<lb/> to abide long in a terrestrial tenement.  The Mount<lb/> of Gilboa drank thy precious blood spilt for thy country and<lb/> religion&#44; but the a hand from above early lifted thee<lb/> into that sphere of love&#44; fresh and perennial as that<lb/> which thou didst cherish.....But has man raised<lb/> no monument to thy virtue&#44; upon earth&#63;  Didst thou<lb/> leave a world&#44; which thy excellencies adorned&#44; unre&#45;<lb/>&#45;corded by posterity&#63;  No&#58; immortal as thy spirit&#44;<lb/> is the statue erected to thy name&#44; O noble loving Jonathan&#33;<lb/>  It stands in a spot&#44; which neither the worms can<lb/> can corrode&#44; nor the elements wear away.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>In the book of books.  Thy friend David placed it in that eminence.<lb/>  And we&#44; his lineal posterity still gaze thereupon&#44; in<lb/> admiration of his genius&#44; and of thy sublime character.<lb/>  Brethren&#33;  Choose the softest of modern languages&#44;<lb/> even that of poesy and of song&#44; and it will fail to reproduce the intensity of affect&#45;<lb/>&#45;ion&#44; which a plaintive sentence in the Hebrew breathes out.<lb/>  &#34;Thou was very sweet to me&#59; thy love for me surpassed a woman&#39;s<lb/> love&#34; are words full of pathos&#44; but they fall short of<lb/> the beauty which the original represent &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  And yet the Hebrew is the<lb/> language which American Israelites cast aside<lb/> as unadapted for prayer and for praise.  The tongue language<lb/> in which the Shepherd bard lamented the death of<lb/> his friend in accents incomparably grand&#44; is rejected&#44;<lb/> and those whose duty it is to touch it foster its culture are demanded&#44;<lb/> with a sacrilegious hand to thrust it out of the<lb/> Synagogue&#33;  Strangers to Jonathan and David&#44; must<lb/> read and take delight in the poetical effusions of our<lb/> Bible&#44; but those to whom it the volume of inspiration was bequeathed as an<lb/> inheritance must deem consider its study profitless and irksome.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>But you&#44; my young brother&#44; Bar Mitzvah&#44; listen not<lb/> to those who will advice the discontinuance of a study<lb/> which has enabled you this day to stand before the<lb/> congregation of Israel.  The knowledge you have<lb/> acquired&#44; will&#44; besides its religious advantage&#44; prove to<lb/> you&#44; wherever you may go&#44; a word of recognition among<lb/> the millions who believe in One God&#44; and revere the<lb/> volumes&#44; a portion of which you have just publicly<lb/> read.  I would not discourage your seeking an acquain&#45;<lb/>&#45;tance with other branches of learning.  Let your object<lb/> be to become enlightened&#44; refined and exalted by means<lb/> of a varied instruction.  But do not despise what is holy&#59;<lb/> do not join the band of J unjewish Jews&#44; who through<lb/> overweening conceit&#44; discard objects in which their predecessors<lb/> took pleasure&#44; believing that whatever is old is effete&#44;<lb/> and only what is novel bears the seeds of perfection.<lb/>  Be loyal to your religion&#44; fond of the grand language&#44;<lb/> in which it was imparted to us by prophets and Sages&#44;<lb/> and attached to the precepts&#44; which&#44; as you have acknow&#45;<lb/>&#45;ledge this Sabbath&#44; contain divine truths&#44; and lead to a life<lb/> eternal.  In that promised existence a righteous Judge<lb/> will reward His creatures&#44; according to the manner in which<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p>they have exercised their faculties.  Therefore I earnestly<lb/> pray that you may ever employ yours to the honor<lb/> of your faith&#44; and to the credit of a father and a<lb/> family&#44; who are happy that you have been spared<lb/> to celebrate your religious majority&#44; in the house of the<lb/> Lord God of Israel.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
