<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF13_5</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_5_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_5_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_5_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_5_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_5_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_5_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_5_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_5_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_5_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_5_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_5_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff13_5_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>On the observance of the Sabbath<lb/>
                For Sabbath Itr&#242;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>I have read with emphasis&#59; nay&#58; I have chanted.<lb/>  It is not hypocrisy to pay a passing compliment<lb/> to what is constantly despised&#63;  Israelites.  In<lb/> sorrow and not in anger&#44; do I speak.  My lay<lb/> brethren have joined hands in digging a pit dark and<lb/> deep&#44; and some of our clergymen have put on their<lb/> canonicals to perform the funeral obsequies.  The<lb/> object to be cast in its that which I have sung for.<lb/>  Not a song but a dirge it should have been.  I ought<lb/> to have suppressed the passage&#44; or to have recited it mourn&#45;<lb/>&#45;fully.  For the fourth commandment&#45;&#45;the central<lb/> Jewish figure in the Decalogue&#45;&#45;is all but dead.<lb/>  My hear sinks within me&#44; when I think that my<lb/> house is built on the grave of my religion.  Why<lb/> pay a teacher to pray and preach&#44; when the sanctity<lb/> of the Sabbath&#44; he is bound to uphold&#44; has been pu&#45;<lb/>&#45;blicly declared by his constituents&#44; an impossibility&#63;<lb/>  Call it treason in a Rabbi to divest our queen of her<lb/> crown and place it on the head of her rival.  It is&#44;<lb/> in all truth&#44; foul treason to one&#39;s trust to transfer the halo<lb/> with which the creating God encircled the day&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>typical of the completion of His handiwork&#44; to a<lb/> day symbolical of the pretended resurrection of a<lb/> man&#45;god.  Yet&#44; who can deny what treacherous mi&#45;<lb/>&#45;nisters declaim on their pulpits&#63;  Hear it&#58; Our children<lb/> will be raised grow in ignorance of Judaism&#44; because the voice<lb/> which resounds in the Synagogue can never reach their<lb/> ears&#44; so long as it is echoed forth on Saturdays&#44; while<lb/> the chiming of the church bell on Sundays&#44; invites them<lb/> within the pale of Christendom.  Gloomy<lb/> is the contemplation of the future of those who have<lb/> children&#44; and most gloomy to the God&#45;fearing&#44;<lb/> whose offspring spurn the idea of idling away<lb/> an existence&#44; which may earn for them a competence<lb/> and civic or political honors.  They may be<lb/> high spirited and conscious of their abilities to rise<lb/> by their earnest exertions.  What an alternative on<lb/> the very threshold of their manhood&#63;  To reach attain<lb/> the objects end of their aspiration&#44; they must overstep<lb/> the limits set by the heavenly Lawgiver&#33;  Parental<lb/> education&#44; early surroundings may have inspired reverence<lb/> for the enunciation of Sinai.  The Sabbath lights&#44;<lb/> the hymns and pslams&#44; the choicer meal at the family<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>board may have left a profound impression.  But<lb/> interest is a motive power&#44; impelling on with a force<lb/> almost irresistible&#44; even when the sentiments raise power&#45; strong<lb/> &#45;ful obstacles.  How many who trembled at the<lb/> thought of sitting behind the  desk&#44; of handling the pen&#44;<lb/> or the meteyard or the chisel on the Sabbath&#44; finally<lb/> <sic>yeilded</sic> to an ambition&#44; which I scarcely dare <sic>stigmatise</sic><lb/> as unholy&#33;  For&#44; just as the revealed Word is the ema&#45;<lb/>&#45;nation of Supreme wisdom&#44; so is the natural impetus<lb/> that leads us to give our faculties full scope&#44; a fiat<lb/> from the Eternal.  Must I check that impulse&#63;<lb/>  Yes&#58; I must curb it among my own&#44; though to do<lb/> so it may entail privations and sore trials.  Honestly&#59;<lb/> fidelity to my trust demands it at my hands&#59; but can I demand<lb/> it of others&#63;  Can I say to yonder youth&#58; thou art<lb/> endowed with exceptional talents&#59; they will develop<lb/> brightly by appliances brought to hear thereupon&#44; but<lb/> thou must not go in quest of them&#44; because the sa&#45;<lb/>&#45;credness of the seventy day forbids it&#63;  And would<lb/> I indeed be heeded&#44; were I to speak thus in the face<lb/> of a pressures tremendous in their its character&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>I am not so presumptuous as to believe that<lb/> what weighs heavily upon my mind&#44; does not<lb/> occupy that of some among my coreligionists.  I know<lb/> fathers and mothers&#44; who shed scalding tears the first<lb/> Sabbath that&#44; after long and painful struggles&#44; they<lb/> said to their aspiring sons&#58; &#34;go&#44; work&#44; it cannot be helped.&#34;<lb/>  Those words were thrusts in their heart&#39;s core&#59; but a<lb/> choice was to be made between a life of inactivity<lb/> and the violation of the fourth commandment.  That<lb/> sons have sought employment among those&#44; who<lb/> like himself&#44; are sworn to stand by the covenant&#44; but<lb/> Alas&#33; where one may have admired his principles&#44; hun&#45;<lb/>&#45;dreds had only cold pity for his qualms of conscience.<lb/>  For it is a notorious fact&#44; that no religious sympathy<lb/> is shown to the consistent Jew by his brother Jew<lb/> of America.  Only a few days since&#44; I casually<lb/> met a young Israelite&#44; whom I did not recognize.<lb/>  He gave me his name&#44; and said that he had attended<lb/> synagogue and the Sunday School.  The lessons early<lb/> imbibed have not been were not forgotten&#44; but their application<lb/> had grown to be beyond his control.  He was in<lb/> humble circumstances.  To provide for himself&#44; and aid<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>those who have a claim on his assistance&#44; he<lb/> felt compelled to set aside what he was taught to<lb/> consider essential to the maintenance of his faith.<lb/>  He had strenuously endeavoured to avoid that issue<lb/> by asking his coreligionists to allow him the pri&#45;<lb/>&#45;vilege of following up his convictions&#44; but he dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;covered that he could preserve the latter&#44; only at<lb/> the sacrifice of a livelihood.  Who will cast<lb/> the first stone upon that Sabbath breaker&#63;  Not I&#44;<lb/> who have the deepest commiseration for the poor&#44;<lb/> fearfully tempted to transgress.  But with the<lb/> rich I contend.  If those of my race who possess<lb/> influence in commercial circles and in the money<lb/> market&#44; were to enter into a covenant of righteousness&#44;<lb/> and&#44; forming themselves into a committee of the whole&#44;<lb/> were to carry out this motion&#58; &#34;Whereas the Law of Sinai<lb/> is <sic>imperilled</sic> by our recklessness&#44; and whereas by reason<lb/> of it our children walk on the brink of apostasy&#44; there&#45;<lb/>&#45;fore be it resolved that the Sabbath shall be kept<lb/> by us henceforth and always on the day which the Creator stamped with<lb/> the seal of heaven&#34;&#58; If those who have gathered tens<lb/> even hundreds of thousands more than they actually need&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>were so united in a holy bond&#44; a fresher and<lb/> enduring life would be allotted to Judaism in<lb/> America.  That resolution would shed greater<lb/> glory upon our name&#44; than even the endowing of<lb/> beneficial institutions.  &#34;The most splendid<lb/> bequest of the wealthy is their giving to God&#44; what<lb/> belongs to God.&#34;  This Such was my remark to a<lb/> well&#45;meaning Israelite&#44; who believed that posthumous<lb/> charities cover a multitude of sins.  Benefi&#45;<lb/>&#45;cence is a most noble trait&#44; but the Almighty<lb/> knows how far we are able to extend it.  He will<lb/> not reckon a sin it a crime our dispensing it in small<lb/> measures a crime&#44; when we cannot&#44; in justice to our families&#44;<lb/> distribute it largely&#44; but He will surely visit<lb/> upon us the iniquity of having deliberately defied<lb/> His expressed will.  For so it is written&#58; Verily ye shall<lb/> keep the Sabbaths&#44; for it is holy unto you.  Whoso&#45; a sign between Me and between<lb/> &#45;ever profanes it shall be put to death&#44; for you through your generations....Whosoever<lb/> does any work therein&#44; that soul shall be cut off<lb/> from among the people....Wherefore the children of<lb/> Israel shall keep the Sabbath throughout their generations<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>as an everlasting covenant&#34;  The question<lb/> now lies between belief and disbelief.  They who<lb/> regard the utterances of Sinai as a breathing of<lb/> the Most High&#44; as a fiat imprescriptable&#44; should<lb/> seek every means imaginable to give it perpetuity.<lb/>  Those who look upon the promulgation from the<lb/> pinnacle of Horeb as a fiction&#44; may proceed to<lb/> break the fourth&#44; with the same indifference as<lb/> they will violate the third&#44; when they curse and<lb/> blaspheme&#44; and the sixth eighth&#44; when they deal fraudulently&#44;<lb/> and all the Decalogue whenever it suits their<lb/> material interests insatiable greed of gain or carnal longings.  You<lb/> have not&#44; I trust&#44; made a league with the im&#45;<lb/>&#45;pious.  You have not taught your minds to dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;card as an imposture what our fathers inherited&#44;<lb/> as a heaven&#45;imparted truth.  I ask then that you<lb/> will ponder on my humble words and act consistently with your professions.<lb/>  I ask it in the name of Moses and the prophets&#59;<lb/> I ask it for the sake of the house of our Lord&#59; I ask it<lb/> principally in the spiritual interest of our children&#44; whose<lb/> happiness here and hereafter is our ardent wish and fervent prayer.<lb/>  &#40;Here followed a prayer&#41;<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
