<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF4_3</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1890-03" source="" attested="yes">March 1890</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_3_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_3_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_3_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_3_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_3_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_3_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_3_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_3_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_3_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_3_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_3_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff4_3_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. Fifth St.<lb/></p>
            <p>Philadelphia&#44;		<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>For Sabbath Ha&#45;gadol<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Philadelphia&#44; March &#47; 90<lb/></p>
            <p>Brethren.  The <del>extraordinary</del> unusual home&#45;service of Passover&#44; which a time&#45;honored custom has<lb/> made universal among observant Israelites&#44; may be divided<lb/> into three sections&#59; namely&#44; the historical&#44; the legendary and&#44; the devotional.<lb/>  The latter bears the palm in my judgment for fitness and for beauty.  Na&#45;<lb/>&#45;turally&#44; the young who are supposed to follow the head of the family in<lb/> the recital of the events which gave occasion to the com&#45;<lb/>&#45;memorative bread lying then upon the table&#44; will feel interested&#44;<lb/> the the most&#44; in the stirring narrative of the suffering of bondmen&#44; of in that of their redemption<lb/> and the onward march to freedom. in the folk lore which it has brought forth originated.  Childish as the<lb/> idea may seem&#44; I would even approve of a pictorial book&#44;<lb/> illustrating various passages read from the Pentateuch in the<lb/> home service&#44; so as to create a lasting deeper impression.  Some of<lb/> my hearers&#44; may perhaps&#44; remember how <sic>rivetted</sic> was their<lb/> attention in their early days upon the woodcuts&#44; representing&#44;<lb/> for instance&#44; Joseph&#45;&#45;&#44; not ashamed of his descent parentage and connections&#44; introducing his old father&#44; and some five<lb/> of his shepherd brothers to the mighty King of Egypt&#59; or the<lb/> burdens of the Hebrews under a new dynasty carrying heavy burdens&#44; or the<lb/> commanding looks of Moses in the act of lending<lb/> forth the enslaved miraculously enfranchised tribes&#59; or the Rabbis sitting the whole night to discuss God&#39;s miracles.  Whatever is calculated to keep<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>alive among our offspring the memory of the common origin and<lb/> <sic>marvellous</sic> preservation of a people&#44; that reckons its age<lb/> by thousands of years&#44; is highly commendable&#44; in my judgment from a Jewish stand point.<lb/>  Still&#44; I consider as in my judgment I consider as the most important part of the<lb/> home service&#44; is that in which all the participants&#44; raising<lb/> the brimful cup&#44; jointly say&#44; &#34;let us sing before God<lb/> the national song&#58; Hallelujah &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; The six magni&#45;<lb/>&#45;ficent psalms&#44; to which the Talmudists rightly applied<lb/> the name title of &#34;Hallel&#34;&#45;&#45;hymn of praise&#45;&#45;&#44; have not come<lb/> down to posterity with the name of their author&#44; or authors.<lb/>  Accordingly&#44; the Sages differ in their opinon in their opinions as to the<lb/> persons from whose genius those poetical effusions issued emanated.<lb/>  At this distance of time&#44; we do not feel specially dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;posed to search with critical acumen&#44; whether David<lb/> wrote them&#44; as well as he undoubtedly penned very many others&#44;<lb/> embodied in the Psalter whatever the German school may assert to the contrary&#44; or whether those compositions<lb/> date from later periods.  Enough&#44; that we are mortal&#45;<lb/> &#45;ly raised heavenward with our minds by the sublimity of thoughts and purity of<lb/> diction and being So and for my being so &#38; because we are so devotionally influenced&#44; we recog&#45;<lb/>&#45;nize the wisdom that set those productions apart<lb/> as a prominent feature in the ritual of Israel&#44; on<lb/> very memorable days in our annals. even the Hallel<lb/> </p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>What struck me forcibly in perusing the Talmudical<lb/> discussions upon the authorship of the Hallel&#44; is a sen&#45;<lb/>&#45;tence which evidences a broadness of views in the Sages&#44;<lb/> that few would be ready to give them credit for.  I will<lb/> tell relate the circumstance as stated.  Rabbi Ishmael&#45;&#45;<lb/> highly esteemed among his learned colleagues&#45;&#45;was taken<lb/> ill.  Till a certain Until he had attained a mature age&#44; he had sat at the feet of a<lb/> parent&#44; whose sayings had become authoritative.  Hence a<lb/> lively wish was entertained by his successors to get become acquaint<lb/>&#45;ted with all much which the departed Sage had taught his son.  Judah<lb/> the Prince&#45;&#45;who laid out the plan for perpetuating the<lb/> oral law as in the Mishnah&#45;&#45;upon hearing of that Rabbi<lb/> Ishmael in sickness his teacher was college academical associate&#44; was sick&#44; sent anxious inquiries with this<lb/> message&#58; &#34;Since you are unable to come to the college&#44;<lb/> I beg that you will tell us two or three of the sayings<lb/> in which your illustrious parent excelled.&#34;  Rabbi<lb/> Ishmael answered&#58; &#34;My father&#44; commenting on the<lb/> shortest of all psalms&#45;&#45;which is the fifth in the Hallel&#45;<lb/>made the following remarks&#58; &#39;It is not clear<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>why the inspired author should have invited hea&#45;<lb/>&#45;thens to sing to Israel&#39;s God&#44; and ot have urged<lb/> them to do so for the motive that he alleges&#44; as we<lb/> read&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Praise the Lord all ye nations&#59; extol him all<lb/> ye peoples&#44; for because His loving kindness towards us is<lb/> surpassingly great&#44; and the truth of the Lord endureth<lb/> for ever.&#34;  Is it reasonable to believe that those who<lb/> denied the One God we adore&#44; who oppressed us and sought our extermination for that very motive&#44; will thank<lb/> the Arbiter of human affairs&#44; because their unrighteous schemes<lb/> did not succeed&#44; and we have outlived all manner of per&#45;<lb/>secutions&#63;  Aye&#58; even so&#44; a time shall arrive when<lb/> nations that held us in bondage thraldom will come hesistatingly forward&#44;<lb/> doubting if we will consent to accept their offer of fraternal<lb/> conciliation&#44; but we will welcome it&#44; just as read&#45;<lb/>&#45;ily from such&#44; as&#44; like the Egyptians&#44; tyrannized<lb/> over us&#44; as from others that did not deny us all &#91;&#63;&#93; from<lb/> human right&#44; and allowed us to thrive treat us so vilely&#34;.  Brethren.  A noble<lb/> thought was this to which Rabbi Jose father of R.<lb/> Ishmael gave utterance&#45;&#45;a thought scarcely to be<lb/> expected from a Sage who lived in times when<lb/> nations&#44; boasting of their enlightenment&#44; called<lb/> all peoples&#44; except their own&#44; &#34;barbarians&#34;.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>If we have a cause to admire the author of the<lb/> psalm&#44; who anticipated of by many centuries for having enunciated the<lb/> sublime principle of a final universal brotherhood&#44;<lb/> flowing from a the knowledge of a Divine fatherhood&#44; which Christianity<lb/> unjustly unwarrantedly claims as its own creation&#44; we must give all<lb/> honor to the expositor of the psalm for the broad&#45;<lb/>&#45;ness of his views.  In his mind gentilism and<lb/> Judaism will in future ultimately finally sit together in unison<lb/> of feelings to rehears the glory of the One all&#45;<lb/>saving God&#44; heralded throughout the world by a race &#91;&#63;&#93; unjustly proscribed.  &#91;Hebrew&#93; I admit that the Rabbis<lb/> subsequent qualification&#44; seem to destroys in a measure<lb/> his liberalism&#44; for after having shown that<lb/> Israel&#44; restored to salvation by the enduring truth<lb/> of the Lord&#44; will forget past wrongs and harmonize<lb/> with its former oppressors&#44; he sets a limit to that<lb/> cosmopolitan idea&#44; by excluding one nation from<lb/> that universal fraternization&#45;&#45;Rome&#44; under the<lb/> pseudonym of Edom.  But in order to account<lb/> for that exclusion&#44; we must recall back to memory<lb/> what Rome was then to Judea.  Egypt had<lb/> indeed enslaved us cruelly from for fear that as we increased in number we might<lb/> ally ourselves to her foreign enemies&#44; yet&#44; Moses<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>recommended not to despise the Egyptian&#44; since<lb/> our ancestors found once a home in his land &#91;Hebrew&#93; Assyria&#44;<lb/> and Babylon her successor&#44; had dragged us into exile captivity&#44;<lb/> through to punish a shortsighted policy which led our ancient<lb/> rulers to make a league with the political foes<lb/> of those formidable Powers&#59; yet&#44; Isaiah declared our<lb/> captors God&#39;s handiwork &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; but the boastful<lb/> mistress of the known world in the days of antiquity<lb/> from wicked Rome&#45;&#45;had forced herself by stealth upon our own<lb/> country&#44; trod on our liberties with an iron heel&#59; send sent her cohorts to trample on our dearest<lb/> rights.  Her spies were ubiquitous to discover imaginary causes<lb/> which might incite carnage a slaughter.  Who more ferocious than Pilate at the rising leader of Christianity&#59; who more monstrous than &#91;&#63;&#93; Rufus&#44; the procurations of Judea&#44; slaughtering cutting down our people when flocking from all parts of the land to the Temple on Passover and &#91;&#63;&#93; other high holidays.  Mothers carried to the<lb/> rack&#44; would be asked&#58; Of what crime they had have you been<lb/> convicted&#63;&#44; and the reply was&#58; &#34;We determined that our<lb/> male children shall enter the covenant of Abraham.&#34;  Aged&#44;<lb/> Sires&#44; subjected brought to the cross&#44; would answer to the querist&#44;<lb/> that they suffered martyrdom because they preferred to<lb/> obey the law of God rather than submit Moses to the despotic<lb/> ordinances of a Trajan or a Hadrian.  Rabbi Jose him&#45;<lb/>&#45;self&#44; the Talmudical expositor of the psalm to which<lb/> I have referred&#44; escaped torture and death by flight.<lb/>  Under circumstances so insufferable&#44; it would have been<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>more than human to have looked upon the tyrannic<lb/> empire which throttled Judaism&#44; with kindly&#44; with friendly<lb/> sentiments.  For the maxims that we must love our<lb/> enemies&#44; and pray for them that persecute us&#44; sounds<lb/> glorious sublime most glorious in theory&#44; but it is impracticable&#44; and there&#45;<lb/>&#45;fore it has no room in the Hebrew cannon&#59; it<lb/> belongs to the impossibilities of the new testament&#44;<lb/> though it is absolutely untrue that we have been Moses has asked us to hate our enemies.<lb/>  An intelligent young acquaintance of mine remarked<lb/> last week in my presence&#44; while speaking of the home ritual for the Passover evenings&#44; that he strongly objected<lb/> to a sentence <sic>occuring</sic> in it&#44; namely&#58; &#34;Pour forth Thy<lb/> wrath upon heathens who know Thee not&#44; and upon<lb/> kingdoms who call not on Thy name.&#34;  He consider&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed it that utterance as dictated by a spirit of vindictiveness&#44; ill&#45;agreeing<lb/> with the teachings of our Bible&#44; urging us to assist<lb/> him that hates us to unload his burden&#44; to give him<lb/> bread if he is hungry&#44; and water if he is thirsty&#44;<lb/> but I drew the attention of the youth who objected&#44;<lb/> to the origin of that verse&#44; emanating as it did originally at first from Jeremiah &#38; copied<lb/> from by an Hebrew who lamented exile who naturally most keenly felt the destruction of his<lb/> native land and a cruel banishment&#44; for so the passage<lb/> ends in psalm 79th.  &#34;They have consumed Israel Jacob<lb/> and made his comely habitation desolate.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>We cannot&#44; without sinning of hypocrisy&#44; use endearing terms towards those who<lb/> occasioned our national or personal ruin&#44; though we must<lb/> try to suppress our feelings of resentment&#44; in order to help such when<lb/> in distress.  The compiler of the Hagadah may have<lb/> introduced that sentence&#44; for which&#44; however&#44; he did<lb/> not have Talmudical authority&#44; because unhappily Pass&#45;<lb/>&#45;over was in his time&#44; and is even now in some benighted<lb/> localities&#44; a plea for devouring our people&#39;s substance and<lb/> overthrowing tearing down their homes&#44; under an infamous blood accusation.<lb/> But we American Jews&#44; reading that Biblical verse<lb/> simply in conformity with the accepted ritual&#44;<lb/> have no allusion even to the Antisemites&#44; to &#91;&#63;&#93;&#44; to &#91;&#63;&#93;&#44; to &#91;&#63;&#93; who fain<lb/> would put us <sic>ostracise</sic> us and drag force us into ghettos.  In the language of attributed to their man god we exclaim &#34;Father forgive them&#44; for they know not what they do.&#34;  Joyful for the fran&#45;<lb/>&#45;chises here enjoyed&#44; thankful to Providence for<lb/> blessings innumerable in this country consecrated to liberty&#44; we raise the typical cups<lb/> of wine at our festive board&#44; saying to one another &#34;let us sing together the<lb/> national song Hallelujah.&#34;  May we always<lb/> so extol the Lord&#44; whose truth endureth for ever&#44;<lb/> for His gracious favor unto us so has been surpassingly<lb/> great&#44; and may joyfull the triumphant day speedily dawn&#44;<lb/> when men of all nations&#44; recognizing the truths<lb/> in our sake keeping&#44; will shall say&#58; &#34;We will go with you<lb/> for we have heard that God is with you.&#34;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
