<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF15_3</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_3_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_3_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_3_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_3_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_3_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_3_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_3_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_3_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_3_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_3_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_3_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_3_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_3_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_3_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_3_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff15_3_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>On the existence of God<lb/>
                No. 3d.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  The question in which I have endeavoured<lb/> to interest you of late&#44; is of an importance so pa&#45;<lb/>&#45;ramount&#44; that I deem it advisable to proceed very<lb/> slowly in order to make it clear&#44; while attempting<lb/> to solve it.  In my first lecture of the series&#44; I made reference<lb/> to the Atomic theory&#44; or the idea of some Atheists<lb/> that certain particles of matter which they consider<lb/> to have always existed&#44; succeeded in during the course lapse of untold<lb/> ages to combine together and produce the universe.  I<lb/> appealed to your reason for a rejection of that pr pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;posterous notion&#44; and offered an illustration of my views<lb/> as it suggested itself then to my mind.  In the<lb/> course of my reading I have found since&#44; that a Rabbi<lb/> who lived in the eleventh century of the common era refutes in nearly the<lb/> same manner the absurd belief that the formation of<lb/> all things depended on resulted from a mutual attraction of molecules.<lb/>  Bachy&#233; ben Bakoda was a philosopher of the Arabo&#45;<lb/>Spanish school.  The soul&#45;stirring confessions which are<lb/> a becoming appendix to his celebrated work&#44; show him wor&#45;<lb/>&#45;thy of being titled &#34;the pious&#59;&#34; but many of his arguments<lb/> to prove the existence of a Creator&#44; our dependence on a<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>watchful Providence&#44; and our bounden obligations<lb/> to bow to the will of the all&#45;wise God are mere reproductions.<lb/>  He doubtless possessed a full knowledge of the writings<lb/> of his contemporaries andf predecessors&#59; still nevertheless&#44; in using<lb/> them to a sacred noble purpose&#44; he often evinced also a singular<lb/> independence of thought.  Explaining in the<lb/> first treatise of his book&#44; called &#34;the duties of the hearts&#44;&#34;<lb/> the necessity of admitting an active Intelligence in<lb/> the creation of the world&#44; Backy&#233; tries to elucidate<lb/> his subject in this wise.  A paper with rules<lb/> drawn across symmetrically is presented to our vision.<lb/>  On each of those lines&#44; characters have been legibly<lb/> traced.  The document is altogether clear and handsomely en&#45;<lb/>&#45;grossed.  Now&#58; to hold that an inkstand was by<lb/> accident spilt upon that same paper and thus were<lb/> the fine lines and well shaped characters produced&#44;<lb/> would be too palpable an error to meet acceptance any&#45;<lb/>where among rational beings.  Yet&#44; this comparison<lb/> of the sagacious Rabbi falls far&#44; exceedingly far<lb/> below the point which he seeks sought to illustrate.  For&#44;<lb/> creation is a not an infallible testimony of the existence<lb/> of a Sovereign Intellect&#44; simply because of its wonderful<lb/></p> 
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>regularity and beauty and adaptation to the designed<lb/> end&#44; but&#44; as our author himself further observes&#44; because<lb/> of the countless variety of objects which constitute the<lb/> universe&#44; and which form an unbroken chain of golden<lb/> links.  A thinker of our times has come&#44; in a degree&#44;<lb/> nearer to the point by his illustration.  He Luzzatto compares<lb/> the belief in the creative power of atoms to that of a man<lb/> who has before him a collection of poems&#44; of different nature&#44;<lb/> and of diversified metre.  Some lyric&#44; others epic&#44; and<lb/> quite a number didactic&#44; &#38; pastoral&#44; but exhibiting<lb/> withal unity in the choice language&#44; in the lofty ideas&#44;<lb/> in the richly flowing versification.  He sees that magnificent<lb/> production and admires it&#44; but attributes it to the chance<lb/> that a case of printer&#39;s types fell over some sheets of paper<lb/> and they placed themselves in the precise order which pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;duced that splendid collection of poems.  Yes&#44; dear young<lb/> friends.  We might more readily embrace that mad thought&#44;<lb/> than look up to the sky&#44; or survey the ground and<lb/> then say &#34;no active intelligence has been at work in the<lb/> construction of the universe.&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>I am myself a stranger to science&#44; but without entering<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>its domains&#44; we all&#44; who have&#44; in the least&#44;<lb/> considered the physical conformation of animals&#44; must have<lb/> felt the conviction&#44; entertained by the Edomite of old&#44; force<lb/> itself into our minds.  &#34;Ask the beasts&#34; says Job to one of his<lb/> reproaching upbraiding friends.  &#34;Ask the beasts and they shall teach thee&#59;<lb/> the fowls of the air and they shall tell thee&#59; the fishes<lb/> of the sea and they shall declare it to thee.  Who knows not<lb/> through all these that the hand of the Lord wroth wrought it&#63;&#34;.<lb/>  Mark&#44; my friends.  Hundreds are the species of far four&#45;footed<lb/> creatures&#44; but one&#44; nearly almost alike&#44; is their organization.  Hundreds<lb/> are the species of birds but upon one similar plan has their or&#45;<lb/>&#45;ganization been drawn.  Hundreds are the species of fish&#44;<lb/> but one analogous model is presented by their organi&#45;<lb/>&#45;zation.  Hence There must have been then a preconceived<lb/> method in their construction&#44; there must have been will<lb/> and wisdom and power.<lb/></p>
            <p>But what is nearer to us than ourselves&#63;  We need only<lb/> lay our hands on our hearts&#44; feel those throbbings<lb/> which with rapidity send a vital fluid to our whole<lb/> frame through a <sic>marvellous</sic> texture of arteries and<lb/> veins&#59; pause a moment and ask inquire of our reasoning minds&#44;<lb/> whether insensible matter could have <sic>yeilded</sic> such a prodigious<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>result.  It is related that when<lb/> Galen&#44; the famous physician of Ancient Rome&#44; was pre&#45;<lb/>paring his medical works&#44; being he became so profoundly being impressed by<lb/> his own description of the outward and inward structure of<lb/> man that he glowingly exclaimed&#44; &#34;My books will give greater glory to<lb/> the Deity than altars reeking with incense.  But<lb/> in his days the English Harvey had not yet appeared to<lb/> reveal what the position and of the veins and their valves<lb/> disclosed to his bright intellect.  I mean&#44; that stupendous<lb/> arrangement by which the blood continually circulates and&#44;<lb/> absorbing the nutritious portions of our food sustains and<lb/> warms our bodies to the hour of their dissolution in death.<lb/>  Ah&#33; What A noble piece of mechanism is this human<lb/> heart&#44; which never ceases moving beating.  A world in miniature.<lb/>  Who set it first in motion&#63;  With sorrow I speak&#58;<lb/> It was reserved for a Jew to answer that question and others of a kindred quest&#45; character<lb/>&#45;tion by a series of wretched <sic>syllogysims</sic>.<lb/></p>
            <p>Benedict Spinoza&#44; born in Holland in the seventeenth<lb/> century&#44; has systematised a philosophy most dangerous<lb/> because most insidious.  On opening his work<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>which he styled &#34;Ethics&#44;&#34; and meeting there the<lb/> name of God with more than Biblical frequency&#44; the<lb/> reader is led to infer that the author recognizes every&#45;<lb/>&#45;where a Primary Cause worthy of our adoration.  But<lb/> let a single page of that volume be critically exa&#45;<lb/>&#45;mined&#44; and that god&#44; with apparent reverence so very often<lb/> mentioned&#44; vanishes under a c mist of perplexing pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;mises and conclusions&#44; to make room for Nature as self&#45;<lb/>&#45;creating and self&#45;reproducing.  For Spinoza teaches<lb/> that all things have emanated from a substance&#44; which<lb/> he&#44; for the sake of convenience&#44; or to deceive the unwary&#44;<lb/> calls &#34;God&#34;.  That infinity of objects which constitutes<lb/> the universe is not the effect of choice&#44; for the original<lb/> substance does not act from a foreknowledge of ultimate<lb/> results&#44; but from absolute necessity.  Thus&#44; to make<lb/> the theory somewhat clearer to your understanding&#44; I will<lb/> say&#58; The Sun is the source of light&#44; but it was not<lb/> made so designedly.  Light became a property of its<lb/> nature by necessity.  Again&#58; our eyes receive the<lb/> vision sight through a most delicate organism&#44;<lb/> but their shape was not formed for that purpose.  They<lb/> took it naturally from an undefinable necessity.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>The same has happened with regard to the construction<lb/> of our ears by which sounds the vibrating of the air strike within and we hear sounds&#44;<lb/> and so likewise respecting the sense of smell&#44; conveyed<lb/> by the olfactory nerves and enabling us to enjoy what<lb/> gives out fragrance&#44; and avoid offensive odors.  All is<lb/> the work of a Necessity&#44; says the Dutch philosopher.  It<lb/> could not have possibly been otherwise&#44; for the primitive<lb/> substance&#45;&#45;the God of Spinoza&#45;&#45;has no power of will.<lb/>  Its perfection consists in obeying its own eternal laws&#44;<lb/> namely&#44; an incomprehensible necessity.<lb/></p>
            <p>Revolting to reason as this system is&#44; because it flatly denies a Mind that has voluntarily predetermined upon<lb/> the best means conducive to the best ends&#44; it is still more <lb/>shocking because of its baneful consequences upon the estate<lb/> of social morality.  There being no cause outside<lb/> of blind necessity&#44; it follows that the sentiments of justice&#44; of<lb/> pity&#44; of love&#44; of spirituality&#44; are not the reflection of the<lb/> soul of the universe on our soul&#44; but rather weaknesses<lb/> inherent in our nature flesh.  And so does the author of<lb/> the Ethics understand those qualities&#44; when he write&#58; &#34;The<lb/> first&#44; the only foundation of virtue&#44; or the rule of living<lb/> right&#44; is the pursuit of that which is truly useful to us.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>with him calculating reason is the highest good to<lb/> man.  He calls his book morals&#44; and lays<lb/> down principles of great sublimity&#44; but their exercise is<lb/> urged by him upon the understanding as the final issue of a<lb/> studied egotism.  Consistently with his philoso&#45;<lb/>&#45;phy&#44; Spinoza finds it unreasonable to be moved by com&#45;<lb/>&#45;miseration.  The State&#44; he contends&#44; rather than the indi&#45;<lb/>&#45;vidual ought to care for the poor and afflicted.  Hu&#45;<lb/>&#45;mility he does not consider a virtue&#44; but a reprehen&#45;<lb/>&#45;sible passion.  And to that son of Israel the Jewish<lb/> world has every motive to look with humiliation for<lb/> another work of a destructive tendency&#59; for his theologico&#45;<lb/>political treatise in which the ancestral religion is exposed<lb/> to obloquy.<lb/></p>
            <p>I have detained you&#44; my brethren&#44; longer upon this point of<lb/> my subject than I had intended&#44; because it has become<lb/> a fashion even among Rabbis ministers on the pulpit&#44; to sing the praises of<lb/> Spinoza&#44; to name him with Moses&#44; with Maimonides&#44; and<lb/> Mendelssohn&#44; as a genius shedding lustre upon Ju&#45;<lb/>&#45;daism&#44; so that some of our youths&#44; misled by their<lb/> guides&#44; confound the way of truth with that of falsehood.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>The God of the Bible&#44; distinct from nature&#44; of<lb/> which He is the architect and sole Director&#44; becomes in<lb/> their minds a myth.  The God of the Bible&#44; who created<lb/> the cre world for love&#44; and who rejoices in the happiness<lb/> of His creatures&#44; is changed in their conceptions into an object<lb/> that was&#44; is and will ever be passive&#44; without mind&#44; or<lb/> will&#44; or choice&#44; indifferent to the destiny of nations and<lb/> individuals.  To deliver you&#44; my young friends&#44;<lb/> from such heresies fatal to your interests as moral &#38;<lb/> responsible beings&#44; and fatal to society at large&#44; I have presented<lb/> to view my impressions of Spinozism and its consequences.<lb/>  I am aware that the partisans of that world&#45;renowned Pan&#45;<lb/>&#45;theist&#44; to whose memory a monument has recently been<lb/> erected at the Hague&#44; in Holland&#44; charge his opponents with<lb/> ignorance of his real meaning.  And I confess that it cost<lb/> me great fatigue to follow him in his philosophical wind&#45;<lb/>&#45;ings&#44; but I could not mistake see such expressions as<lb/> this&#58; &#34;If things could have been of another nature than<lb/> they are.....the nature of God also would have been diffe&#45;<lb/>rent&#34;.  Hence&#44; God and nature are identical.  Nor could I mis&#45;<lb/>apprehend this axiom &#34;The self&#45;preservative effort is the first<lb/> and only foundation of all virtue.&#34;  It is clearly an insult<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>to what must ennobles on man&#59; the denial of self<lb/> for a high aim&#44; for charity&#44; for righteousness&#44;<lb/> for patriotism.  Contrast such materialistic and<lb/> utilitarian principles with the instruction of a philosopher<lb/> who was a Jew&#44; but not simply by the accident of birth.<lb/>  He writes&#58; A virtuous person is one who rules over<lb/> his senses&#44; who leads his physical mental and spiritual<lb/> faculties aright...He acting as if he were the ruler general<lb/> in chief whom all must obey.  His limbs respond to<lb/> the will of their guide&#44; they are not kept back by the fear<lb/> of suffering or less when duty calls.<lb/></p>
            <p>My young hearers.  I recommend you to shun the works of Spinoza&#44; &#38; I commend to your study the<lb/> works of Judah Hallevi&#44; the Jewish philosopher<lb/> and sublime poet.<lb/></p>
            <p>This is rather a paraphrase<lb/></p>
            <p>&#38; not a literal quotation of a passage<lb/>
                in the Cuzari<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
