<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF5_3</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_3_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_3_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_3_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_3_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_3_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_3_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_3_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_3_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_3_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_3_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_3_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_3_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>7 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>Against reform<lb/> for Sabbath Chay&#232; Sar&#225;h<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> 
                &#34;Rabbi Akiba was proceeding in his lecture&#44; but his auditors fell<lb/> into a slumber.  He sought to awaken them by a startling assertion&#44;<lb/> and said&#44; &#34;Esther&#44; the Jewish queen&#44; reigned over one hundred and twenty<lb/> seven provinces&#44; because Sarah&#44; from whom she descended lived one<lb/> hundred and twenty seven years.&#34;  All eyes opened&#44; every<lb/> ear was stretched to listen to the explanation of so singular an idea.<lb/>  The Rabbi obtained his object.  The subsequent remarks elicited commanded<lb/> undivided attention.  I&#45;&#45;the least among the disciples of the<lb/> Rabbis&#45;&#45;will try the same experiment.  Brethren&#33; our vener&#45;<lb/>&#45;able mother is to be thrust through&#44; in our city&#44; by thirteen<lb/> conspirators....You do look astounded&#44; and cannot understand the<lb/> drift of my speech.  I simply desired that your feelings might<lb/> be aroused.  Not that you should attend to the words I may<lb/> utter&#44; but that you should heed the cry of ill&#45;used Judaism.<lb/>  Yes&#58; it is old&#44; but ought therefore its sworn defenders to turn traitors&#44;<lb/> and plot against its life&#63;  Know&#44; O fellow Israelites&#33; that<lb/> on Wednesday next&#44; thirteen Rabbis will assemble in Philadelphia&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>to deal a deadly blow against the existence of the religion&#44; in<lb/> whose bosom we and they have been nurtured.  I have had<lb/> occasion I should rather have said the misfortune&#45;&#45;to read<lb/> a discourse which one of those overthrowers recently delivered.<lb/>  The law which&#44; with apparent solemnity&#44; he&#44; on each revolving<lb/> Sabbath&#44; takes from the ark&#44; and a portion of which he recites<lb/> for the edification of his audience is described by his own pen&#44;<lb/> as an old&#45;dame&#44; in whose countenance the traces of decrepitude<lb/> are discernible.  And because she cannot disguise the wrinkles<lb/> that furrow her cheeks&#44; she grows jealous of her rival&#45;philosophy&#45;&#45;<lb/> of her rival so fresh and blithe&#44; the acknowledged mistress of an<lb/> enlightened world.  Principles of honesty would dictate that<lb/> they who believe&#44; should voluntarily descended from the pulpits<lb/> they occupy.&#44; that they should put off this ministerial robe&#44;<lb/> which ought to weigh on their bodies as heavily as lead weighs.<lb/>  Yet&#44; rather than thus lighten the burden of their conscience&#44;<lb/> they endeavour to persuade themselves that the powers wherewith<lb/> their Rabbinical preceptors <sic>inveiled</sic> them are becomingly exercised.<lb/>  Nay&#58; that through their exertions alone is prejudice against the<lb/> Hebrew race famishing apace&#44; and monotheism spreading amazingly<lb/> fast.  But is my mind so obtuse&#44; that it cannot discover<lb/> what they so clearly see&#63;  Brethren.  When the discourse<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>to which I have just alluded found its way in the secular<lb/> press&#44; a christian remarked that Israel cannot be considered<lb/> any longer the people&#44; through whom all the nations of the<lb/> earth will be blessed&#44; for&#44; infidelity is being enlisted in their<lb/> ranks&#44; and the chieftains welcome it.  Alas&#33; we may well<lb/> exclaim with the plaintive bard &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Those who handle the law&#44; know me not&#59; the shepherds have<lb/> rebelled against me&#34;.  Have not their undertakings been<lb/> daring&#63;  They assume the title of Rabbis&#44; but scarcely a<lb/> vestige of Rabbinical enactments have they left&#33;  The<lb/> Pentateuch is still enshrined in the temples&#44; wherein they<lb/> conduct an ostensibly Jewish worship&#44; but its ceremonial<lb/> percepts have been declared unsuited to the age&#44; and therefore<lb/> unbinding&#59; and now&#44; we are led to infer from their manifesto&#44;<lb/> that their meeting will effect this end.  It will be decided that<lb/> a matrimonial alliance with gentiles is no longer to be disallowed&#59;<lb/> that a marriage before a temporal magistrate&#44; has equal validity<lb/> as that performed by a Hebrew minister&#59; that the state alone<lb/> must grant divorces&#59; that the levirate law is abolished.<lb/>  What more is needed&#44; but to cry out &#34;American Israelites&#44; Judaism<lb/> is extinct&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>The grave is being dug&#44; wherein it may be consigned to oblivion.<lb/>  Will you help to fill it with dust&#63;...Dear hearers&#33; Let not<lb/> a spirit of curiosity incite you to seek admission into that<lb/> assemblage of the unrighteous.  Discussion will not&#44; I conceive&#44;<lb/> be permitted to the laity&#44; and your presence will may be interspersed<lb/> as a trait approval of an act&#44; which your soul should abhor.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Ponder on these words of the royal psalmist.  &#34;Blessed in the<lb/> man&#44; who walketh not in the counsel of the ungodly&#44; nor standeth<lb/> in the way of sinners&#44; nor sitteth in the seat of the scornful.&#34;<lb/>  It does not suffice that we reject the teachings of wickedness&#59;<lb/> it is not enough that we shun the association of habitual<lb/> transgressors&#59; we must also avoid being seen in the meeting<lb/> of those who scoff at religion.  Disclaiming the intention to<lb/> be personal&#44; I assert&#44; that the conference to be held in Phila&#45;<lb/>&#45;delphia is of a character&#44; that no one&#44; in whose breast a spark<lb/> of affection for Judaism still burns&#44; ought to countenance.<lb/>  They who projected it&#44; should discover that their specious<lb/> reasonings fall upon the ears of but few listeners&#59; then&#44; they<lb/> may perchance  be restrained&#44; if they will not retrace their steps<lb/> from the pernicious career they are pursuing.  For&#44; what<lb/> encouraged the advocates of radical changes in our religion&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>What&#63; but the &#91;&#63;&#93; of a well administered rebuke<lb/> at the hands of the community&#63;  They addressed themselves to multitudes&#44; incapable to determine&#44; whether<lb/> the application of the theories advanced&#44; would be conducive to the goal&#44; professedly aimed at.<lb/>  Meeting with no resistance&#44; those designing men&#44; ventured upon that which&#44; in all likelihood&#44;<lb/> they thankfully never imagined could be possibly accomplished.  For&#44; not at once did<lb/> reform&#45;&#45;erroneously so termed&#45;&#45;present the bold font&#44; which<lb/> it now exhibits.  At first&#44; it appeared in the garb<lb/> of sanctimoniousness.  The ritual must be altered&#44; in order<lb/> to ensure devotion.  The people assented.  The Synagogue<lb/> must be modernized&#44; to elicit the respect of gentile visitors.<lb/>  The people tamely <sic>yeilded</sic>.  The division&#44; which restriction<lb/> on our diet has maintained between us and the rest of the<lb/> world&#44; must be removed&#44; not to expose Israel to the derision of<lb/> the enlightened.  The people demurred&#44; but at length agreed<lb/> to disregard the injunction of their ancient leader&#44; and heed that<lb/> of their new shepherds.  And now casting aside the mask<lb/> which concealed its hideous features&#44; now&#44; reform sallies forth<lb/> armed with the weapon where to strike at the vitals of Judaism.<lb/>  Brethren&#33;  If the congregations&#44; which the thirteen Rabbis&#44; who<lb/> will assemble in our city represent&#44; accept the results of the<lb/> conference&#44; the state of our religion will become so anomalous&#44;<lb/> that an open schism&#44; as like Caraism&#44; would be infinitely better.<lb/>  Questions will may ensue&#44; that no conscientious minister will<lb/> be able to solve&#44; without necessarily widening the breach<lb/> wh which&#44; unhappily&#44; already a exists.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>The legality of marriages&#44; the legitimacy of children their claim<lb/> to the name of Jews&#44; may be among the vexatious questions<lb/> that will arise from the adoption of the schemes in contemplation.<lb/>  I hope that the community will&#44; with one mind&#44; execrate them.<lb/>  I pray that the God of Israel may frustrate the sense of<lb/> the unrighteous.  But to you&#44; over whose religious honor I am<lb/> bound to watch&#44; I will say.  Brethren&#33;  Frown upon the<lb/> attempt of to overthrow the fundamental principles of Judaism.<lb/>  Rebuke it by eschewing the conventicle of scoffers.  Let it<lb/> not be reported abroad that your presence lent it force.<lb/>  To yo each of you&#44; through whose instrumentality&#44; under Providence&#44;<lb/> the standard of Biblical and traditional Judaism will never be suffered<lb/> to trail the dust&#44; to each of you I will say concerning reform&#44; in<lb/> the language of Scripture &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Incline not thy heart to her ways&#44; go not astray after her<lb/> paths.&#34;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;  &#34;For many hath she<lb/> caused to fall down&#44; and mighty ones have been all those she<lb/> has killed.&#34;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;Her house leadeth<lb/> to the way of perdition&#44; rescendin going down to the<lb/> chambers of death.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
