<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF13_9</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_9_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_9_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_9_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_9_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_9_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_9_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_9_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_9_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_9_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_9_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_9_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_9_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>7 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>A few words about the Revd S. M. Isaac&#39;s<lb/>
                decease<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>It was my intention&#44; as to have spoken this sab&#45;<lb/>&#45;bath at some length&#44; and I had prepared some various points<lb/> in my mind to that effect.  The more inclined I<lb/> felt to to address you longer than ordinarily&#44; because<lb/> I wished to pay a well merited tribute to the me&#45;<lb/>&#45;mory of an excellent Jew&#44; an exemplary citizen&#44;<lb/> and a distinguished minister.  But the whole of<lb/> yesterday the state of my health would not permit<lb/> me to arrange my thoughts systematically&#44; so that<lb/> I might do the subject the full justice it deserves&#44; and<lb/> acquit myself creditably.  Sometime&#44; indeed&#44;<lb/> notwithstanding the greatest care bestowed upon<lb/> the topic about to be discussed&#44; and all the pains<lb/> taken to present it in an intelligible and agreeable<lb/> diction&#44; it happens&#44; either through not being heard<lb/> distinctly&#44; or through a defective accent on the part<lb/> of the speaker&#44; that what he says is <sic>wofully</sic> mis&#45;<lb/>&#45;understood.  Should his discourse be then printed from a<lb/> copy made by a reporter sitting at a distance&#44; it will<lb/> excite the laughter of an intelligent reader&#44; because<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>of its illogical composition&#44; its <sic>totology</sic> and<lb/> ludicrous wording.  This has precisely occurred<lb/> in the publication of the address I was called upon<lb/> to deliver at the funeral of the Reverend Samuel<lb/> M Isaacs of New York on Wednesday last.  The<lb/> Jewish Messenger of the week&#44; or rather its blunder&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing reporter makes me say what I never uttered&#44;<lb/> omits much that was said&#44; and puts the whole<lb/> together in a form unbeseeming the solemnity of<lb/> the occasion&#44; unworthy of the deceased&#44; and unbecoming<lb/> to the panegyrist.  For&#44; if the Latin proverb<lb/> that of the dead we should speak only what is<lb/> good is a charitable maxim&#44; and greatly to<lb/> be commended&#44; and to be followed&#44; as far as practicable&#44;<lb/> I hold that exaggerations ought&#44; by all means&#44; to<lb/> be avoided&#44; not to stain oneself with the sin of flat&#45;<lb/>&#45;tery towards the living.  The real merits of the<lb/> subject should be presented&#44; as a lesson&#44; in a digni&#45;<lb/>&#45;fied but simple manner.  The late minister<lb/> of the Shaar&#232; Tephilla Congregation&#44; was conspi&#45;<lb/>&#45;cuous not so much for the brilliant acquirements<lb/> of the mind&#44; as for the tender qualities of the heart.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Having undergone privations in his early days&#44; when<lb/> his father reduced to straitened circumstances&#44; emigrated<lb/> from Holland to England&#44; my colleague had fellow&#45;<lb/>feelings with those who suffered want.  and His exertions<lb/> to alleviate misery were unabated during the whole<lb/> of the thirty nine years he filled a sacred office.<lb/>  But effective as he was in pleading for the poor and<lb/> the afflicted&#44; his preaching&#44; did not&#44; as a rule&#44; create<lb/> enthusiasm by reason of its commanding eloquence&#44; or<lb/> for the striking thoughts it unfolded.  How could I<lb/> then have said that people would come from all<lb/> parts of America&#44; to hear him&#44; and that even from<lb/> beyond the ocean men would crowd round the fane where<lb/> he officiated&#63;  Knowing likewise that the op&#45;<lb/>&#45;portunities by which my revered friend could gain<lb/> a perfect mastery of Hebrew literature had been<lb/> withheld from him&#45;&#45;since in London half a century<lb/> ago no college existed&#44; and scarcely any school for<lb/> high branches&#45;&#45;how could I have asserted that he<lb/> bestowed upon Israel the benefit of his extensive learning&#63;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>No&#58; I acknowledge very cheerfully that what<lb/> he had attained was excellently put into use&#59; that<lb/> Mr Isaacs employed his talents to the very utmost<lb/> in strengthening historical Judaism&#59; that he was<lb/> a sincere adherents of the ancestral faith&#44; and he<lb/> preached it without fear of becoming staking unpopularity.<lb/>  For the good minister tried to gain secure the approval<lb/> of God&#44; and not the smile of man.  Duty and<lb/> the spiritual welfare of his flock became his polar<lb/> star.  He lived indeed up to his principles&#44; and<lb/> no shadow of suspicion ever rested upon the purity<lb/> of his character.  But while I admit all that<lb/> with gratitude to his memory&#44; I opine that to<lb/> style him an eminent scholar&#44; and a leading prea&#45;<lb/>&#45;cher would be a hyperbole scarcely pardonable.<lb/>  I stated neither&#44; though I am indeed anxious that<lb/> a pious and most conscientious Jew should be held<lb/> in high estimation.  Painful as it is to see one&#39;s<lb/> words misquoted&#44; and one&#39;s sentences mutilated&#44; and<lb/> distorted as to be scarcely recognizable by the author&#44;<lb/> I do not appreciate any the less the sterling worth<lb/> of the deceased&#44; nor the honor conferred upon this<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Congregation by the bereaved family and the<lb/> trustees of the congregation Shaar&#232; Tephilla&#44; when I<lb/> was onl invited to deliver the funeral address.<lb/>  Little did I imagine nine months ago&#44; when I<lb/> lamented on this pulpit the loss of an upholder of<lb/> orthodoxy that another&#44; and I may add the last<lb/> of any standing in New York&#45;&#45;&#44; would so soon be<lb/> snatched away&#44; leaving a void not likely to be filled.<lb/>  But the ways of the Lord are true and righteous<lb/> altogether.  We must bow to the will of Him who<lb/> has set a law that man&#39;s term on earth should not<lb/> exceed by far a great length three score and ten years.<lb/>  To Samuel M. Isaacs&#44; His faithful servant&#44; God<lb/> granted the happiness of reaching beyond that pe&#45;<lb/>riod&#45;&#45;and not in a state of decrepitude&#44; which ren&#45;<lb/>&#45;ders old age a burden&#44; but in the fruition of bodily<lb/> and mental activity.  Only within a few weeks&#44;<lb/> almost a few days previous to his being summoned<lb/> to his reward&#44; my venerated colleague continued<lb/> to labor on earth as a model to his exemplary fa&#45;<lb/>&#45;mily&#44; as an advocate of the needy&#44; and a benefactor<lb/> of the people&#44; he loved with his whole heart.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>May the Almighty assign to his soul a high<lb/> seat among the beloved perfect righteous.  May<lb/> angels of peace greet his entrance into the regions<lb/> of bliss in the language of the prophet.  &#34;Let him<lb/> come in in peace&#44; rest upon his destined couch&#44;<lb/> for he has walked uprightly.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
