<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF4_20</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_20_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_20_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_20_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_20_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_20_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_20_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_20_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_20_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_20_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_20_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_20_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_20_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Post&#45;Biblical<lb/>
                40<lb/>
                on the schools of Palestine &#38; their Chiefs<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  When I last year&#44; I suspended the series<lb/> of my post&#45;biblical history lectures&#44; because of the approach&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing summer season&#44; I had reached a period in our history which<lb/> closed entirely altogether the political life of our people.  The<lb/> disastrous end of the last heroic struggle at Bither&#44; un&#45;<lb/>&#45;der the lead of Bar Cocheb&#224;&#44; forced upon the minds<lb/> of our unhappy ancestors the conviction that any<lb/> attempt to regain recover country and independence must<lb/> inevitably fail.  Consequently&#44; they wise&#45;hearted bent their<lb/> energies upon retaining that which would give<lb/> Israel permanence on earth and solace in trouble.<lb/>  They felt that the cultivation of the Law and tra&#45;<lb/>&#45;ditions must ensure secure their national eternization&#45;&#45;so<lb/> high was the morality inculcated in their sacred books committed to their guardianship&#44;<lb/> so grand sublime the leading principles of Judaism&#44; which<lb/> the martyred Akiba had recently sealed with his<lb/> precious blood.  Our progenitors believed that as<lb/> God&#44; who inspired prophets to teach heavenly truths&#44;<lb/> is eternal immortal&#44; so the adherents of those verities must<lb/> be immortalized imperishable.  Zion the capital of their land&#44;<lb/> had been razed to the ground.  Upon its ruins<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>another city was built&#44; whose appellation<lb/> recalled names detested by a every Jew&#45;&#45;Celia Caputo&#45;<lb/>&#45;lina&#44; from Alius the family name of the emperor<lb/> Hadrian and from Jupiter Capitlinus.  In honor<lb/> of this false god&#44; a temple arose was made to rise where the She&#45;<lb/>&#45;kinah had hovered between the Cherubim&#44; and a<lb/> statue to the impious Hadrian was set up.<lb/>  Heathens&#44; peopled Jerusalem&#44; pagans&#44; <sic>revelled</sic> in<lb/> holy precincts surroundings.  To add insult to injury&#44;<lb/> a marble figure of the &#91;Hebrew&#93; the hated swine&#44; was engraven<lb/> on one of the gates of the city of David&#44; forbidden thenceforth thereafter<lb/> to the children descendants of Israel Judah.  The privilege to enter<lb/> it only once a year&#44; on the anniversary of their<lb/> national calamity in order to weep and pray by the Western<lb/> wall&#44; was purchased by the exiles&#44; the sorrow stricken exiles purchased had to purchase at the rich price of<lb/> rich gold.  But Israel did not draw his<lb/> vitality from the soil which had been his in&#45;<lb/>&#45;heritance.  Palestine must indeed possess always<lb/> the power to awaken deep emotions in hearts that<lb/> are not dead to a sense of religious patriotism.<lb/>  For The Hebrew acquainted with his eventful history&#44;<lb/> realizes that from that spot true civilization spread.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>It was more than a poetical flight of the imagination<lb/> which elicited from Judah Hallevi the idea that<lb/> the Holy Land is to the world at large&#44; what the<lb/> heart is to the human body&#45;&#45;the source of existence&#44; so&#45;<lb/>&#45;cially and spiritually.  I even incline to think<lb/> that Ezekiel considered it so&#44; when he wrote in the name of the Lord&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;This Jerusalem I have set in<lb/> the midst of nations&#44; and countries are round about it.&#34;<lb/>  Centrally placed in from a geographical point of view&#44;<lb/> situated on the western coast of the Eastern continent&#44;<lb/> accessible through the <sic>Mediterannean</sic> sea that washes<lb/> it&#44; to Europe on the North&#44; to Asia on the East&#44;<lb/> and to Africa on the West&#44; it is the channel<lb/> from which flowed a soul regenerating knowledge&#45;&#45;<lb/> that the incomparable knowledge imparted in the heavenly inspired volumes of inspiration.<lb/>  But Jews while still bending still in prayer towards that spot&#44;<lb/> where the light of prophecy to illumine mankind<lb/> brightly shone&#44; Jews scattered everywhere recognize<lb/> nevertheless the fact that their separate continuance&#44; is not<lb/> the effect of a former residence in a the land of promise&#44; but that<lb/> it it is solely due to the maintenance of the Torah.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>All honor then&#44; all thanks to Rabbinism&#44;<lb/> that prevented its extinction.  Brethren.<lb/>  In previous lectures I alluded to Johanan Ben<lb/> Zacka&#239;.  I related that when to fight Rome successfully&#44;<lb/> against Rome appeared seemed to his judgment a hopeless<lb/> attempt undertaking&#44; he left Jerusalem by stratagem&#44; and<lb/> on entering the presence of Vespasian&#44; asked a favor.<lb/>  He requested that he might be allowed to establish<lb/> a school of learning in Jabn&#232;&#44; or Jammia&#45;&#45;a town<lb/> not far from Jaffa.  The granting of that wish&#44;<lb/> apparently of no significance&#44; was the gift of an delivering into our hands of a<lb/> impenetrable shield against which the javelins of<lb/> a Roman soldiery&#44; and the rifles of all the sworn inveterate enemies of<lb/> Judaism struck in vain.  The study and applica&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion of ancestral laws&#44; suiting our changed condition&#44;<lb/> was our salvation.  Going back seventy years in<lb/> the narrative which concluded my last post&#45;biblical lecture&#44; I<lb/> purpose speaking very briefly at intervals with great brevity of the colleges<lb/> founded in various cities of Palestine&#44; after our<lb/> political downfall under Titus&#44; of their nature of<lb/> and of that the characters of their leaders.<lb/></p>
            <p>At Jammia gathered the disciples of the great Sage&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>immortlized in Talmudical literature.<lb/>  In like manner as Johanan Ben Zaccka&#239; had<lb/> imbibed the principles governing his peace&#45;loving teacher&#44;<lb/> Hillel the elder&#44; so did he try to infuse sentiments of<lb/> loving&#45;kindness into the hearts of his own pupils.  All may<lb/> have read in the splendid excellent book&#44; called &#34;Aboth&#34; or&#44; &#34;the<lb/> Ethics of the fathers&#44;&#34; how fond was Johanan of his scholars.<lb/>  Five have received there particular mention&#44; and they<lb/> helped in carrying out the work of reconstruction. forming They constituted<lb/> with others a Synod&#44; or Sanhedrin by whom rules&#44; principally regard&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing a uniformity of system in establishing the new moon and festivals and synagogual service&#44;<lb/> were enacted.  We may form an idea of the cha&#45;<lb/>&#45;racter of That Rabbi Ben Zaccka&#239;&#44; from some of his actions and<lb/> his ingenious utterances.  It is asserted in<lb/> the Talmud that he was invariably the far first to<lb/> affably greet his neighbor&#44; whether this was a<lb/> Jew or a Gentile &#91;Hebrew&#93; when he noticed that<lb/> much knowledge might create boastfulness&#44; he<lb/> would check it by showing that to study and improve is every<lb/> man&#39;s duty &#91;Hebrew&#93;  One day&#44; after the Temple<lb/> had been delivered to the flames&#44; Johanan&#44; accompanied<lb/> by his pupils Joshua Ben Hananiah&#44; was walking<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>through the desolate places deserted streets ruins of Jerusalem.  Joshua<lb/> wept and said&#58; &#34;Alas&#33; what will atone for our sins<lb/> now that the altars have been overthrown&#63;&#34;&#44; to which<lb/> the teacher answered&#58; &#34;My son&#44; do not lament&#44; we<lb/> have been left what will ensure forgiveness&#45;&#45;beneficence charity&#34;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  The same thought he expressed on ano&#45;<lb/>&#45;ther occasion.  Seeing a woman&#44; whom he recognized<lb/> as the daughter of a once wealthy Israelite&#44; gathering<lb/> some grains of corn to make a meal&#44; he enchained remarked&#58;<lb/> &#34;Right is the common proverb&#44; that the salt with which<lb/> to preserve money&#44; is charity beneficence&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  To<lb/> discover the disposition of his scholars&#44; the Sage would<lb/> put to them questions on morals.  &#34;Think consider well&#44;&#34; he<lb/> would say to them&#44;&#34; and tell me what is best for a<lb/> person to possess acquire.&#34;  He listened to their views&#44; but ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;proved the opinion of Eleazar Ben Arach&#44; who thought<lb/> that a good heart is the noblest possession.<lb/>  At the death of a child of the greater preceptor&#44;<lb/> he was visited by his five favorite pupils.  Some<lb/> endeavoured to comfort the bereaved father by point&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing out similar losses sustained by Biblical personages&#44; which Biblical personages had sustained&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>but Eleazar Ben Arach alone afforded him<lb/> consolation.  He spoke thus&#58; &#34;A man had a precious<lb/> jewel entrusted to his care.  He His Such a responsibility<lb/> gave him concern.  He did not know whether he<lb/> could no give it back restore the object to its owner its being in the least without any being injured in the least.  Thy<lb/> child was that dear object&#44; and whom thou hast just returned to God.<lb/>  Be comforted because thou hast given back in all the original purity&#44; free from any blemish what<lb/> be then comforted&#34; was committed to the guardianship care custody custody and thou didst guard well.&#34;  Verily worthy of a narrative&#44;<lb/> thou hast given me comfort&#34; said the Master.<lb/> is the last hour of the illustrious Rabbi.  He was<lb/> lying very ill&#44; when his pupils visited him.  Looking<lb/> on them he shed tears.  They said cried&#58; &#34;O light of Israel&#44;<lb/> O sustaining pillar of the faith&#44; why dost thou weep&#63;&#34;<lb/>  The teacher answered&#58; &#34;Were I to be taken before a human<lb/> king&#44; whose anger cannot outlast his mortal existence&#44;<lb/> or whom I might conciliate by words or by gifts&#44;<lb/> I still would feel a certain dread.  Now&#44; I am<lb/> about to be ushered into the presence of the King<lb/> of Kings&#44; who is&#44; who is eternal&#44; and so also<lb/> might be also His wrath which I can never appease<lb/> by words or gifts.  I see two ways lying<lb/> before me&#44; one leading to joy&#44; another to sorrow grief.<lb/>  I do not know which I am deserving to tread.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Ought I not to weep&#63;  The disciples who could<lb/> testify to their master&#39;s virtues and did not entertain his<lb/> dread&#44; and feelings said &#34;Oh give us thy parting blessing.&#34;  He<lb/> answered&#58; &#34;May you fear God&#44; as you fear men &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>&#45;&#45;&#34;Why&#44; nothing more&#63;&#34; they unitedly exclaimed&#59; and<lb/> he repiled replied&#58; &#34;No&#44; for most persons&#44; when com&#45;<lb/>&#45;mitting a sin of which they are ashamed&#44; the take<lb/> good heed not to have human witnesses&#44; forget&#45;<lb/>&#45;ful of God who is Omnipresent.&#34;<lb/></p>
            <p>My Brethren.  It was excessive humility&#44; that<lb/> excited feelings of apprehension in the great eminent teacher&#44;<lb/> not want of trust in the compassionate Lord&#44; as a<lb/> prejudiced Christian writer asserts alleges.  If any doubt<lb/> could exist respecting that&#44; the last parting words of Johanan<lb/> would dispel it.  Before breathing his last&#44; he<lb/> said cried &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  &#34;Prepare a chair seat for<lb/> H Ezekiah King of Judah&#44; who has come&#44;&#34; mean&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing that the righteous ruler of old will would be my his escort to<lb/> paradise.  Few have obtained so<lb/> glowing a record in the Talmud&#44; as the founder<lb/> of the Rabbinical college in Jammia.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>His learning has been described as immeasur&#45;<lb/>&#45;able.  Besides the written and oral law of which<lb/> he was a perfect master&#44; Johanan had grasped and<lb/> retained all the knowledge that was accessible<lb/> in his age&#44; and he used it most advantageously<lb/> in behalf of his religion.  The Mishnah rehearsing<lb/> the praises of departed Sages writes&#44; that with the<lb/> death of Ben Zaccka&#239; &#34;the splendor of wisdom<lb/> disappeared.&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Providence raised that<lb/> new Ezra when Judaism was <sic>imperilled</sic>&#44; endowed<lb/> him with a broad judgment to plan&#44; with a<lb/> mighty will to act&#44; with a spirit of goodness<lb/> to win the affection and cooperation of scholars.<lb/>  To whom him we ough owe under God the survival of the Torah<lb/> and our imperishable existence&#44; All honor to as missionaries of<lb/> those Rabbis. world&#45;regenerating truths&#44; where country and inde&#45;<lb/>&#45;pendence were forced away from us.  Rome&#44; our<lb/> destroyer&#44; has sunk into a grave&#44; and is remembered<lb/> in history alone&#44; the Jew lives&#44; because Rabbinism<lb/> made him imperishable.  All honor then&#44; all<lb/> thanks to teachers in Israel&#44; like filled with the spirit of our Johanan<lb/> Ben Zaccka&#239;.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
