<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF3_14</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_14_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_14_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_14_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_14_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_14_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_14_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_14_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_14_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_14_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_14_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_14_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_14_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Post Biblical lecture<lb/>
                14th<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  To take up the thread of my post&#45;<lb/>Biblical lectures&#44; I will call back to your memory<lb/> the imprisonment of Jonathan&#44; through the treachery<lb/> of Tryphon&#44; the Syrian general.  Intense as the<lb/> mental suffering of our valiant chief at his abject<lb/> confinement&#44; must have been&#44; it scarcely could<lb/> have exceeded that endured by his brother Simon.<lb/>  The latter burnt with the wish to make the traitor<lb/> feel how sharp was yet the Asmonean sword was yet&#44; and<lb/> how severely it could punish iniquity.  But he<lb/> was obliged to act with great prudence.  He knew that<lb/> unhappily many Jews&#44; fond of the loose habits practices of<lb/> the Greeks&#44; sided with the enemy&#44; and that they would<lb/> not scruple to sacrifice the honor of their religion and<lb/> country.  Consequently&#44; he undertook forthwith to<lb/> render Jerusalem strong secure within and without&#44; and raise<lb/> an army brave strong enough to oppose Tryphon.  This<lb/> wily Syrian was not long to move on towards the<lb/> capital of Judea&#44; but discovering that he would have<lb/> met with a determined resistance&#44; he had recourse once more<lb/> to deception.  He pretended to be as very anxious for peace&#59;<lb/></p> 
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>and sent word that if one hundred talents&#44; which&#44;<lb/> he alleged&#44; Jonathan owed him were paid&#59; he would<lb/> release the prisoner and go back.  The proposition<lb/> cause Simon anguish of soul spirit&#59; the more so&#44; because the<lb/> perfidious Tryphon&#44; insisted on having two sons of Jona&#45;<lb/>&#45;than as hostages&#44; to make it sure that their<lb/> father&#44; when at liberty&#44; would not go again to<lb/> war against the Syrians.  Simon felt convinced that<lb/> a vile trick was intended.  He felt convinced that by paying<lb/> the sum asked&#44; he would not save the life of Jonathan&#44;<lb/> but risk also that of his children.  The alternative<lb/> was terrible.  He either must refuse&#44; and be open to<lb/> the charge of having occasioned his brother&#39;s death&#44; or he<lb/> must agree comply&#44; regardless of the results which he dreaded.  He did what public<lb/> opinion demanded.  One hundred talents were sent forwarded by<lb/> means of the two sons of Jonathan.  But alas&#33;  Simon&#39;s<lb/> suspicions were too sadly realized.  Not alone Tryphon<lb/> did not free Jonathan&#44; after having received the ful required amount&#44;<lb/> but he would have stealthily attacked Jerusalem at night&#44; if a<lb/> heavy fall of snow had not providentially hindered<lb/> the movements of his cavalry&#44; and compelled him<lb/> to leave his wicked devices unfulfilled.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Angry because of this unexpected check to on his plans&#44;<lb/> the traitor upon his returning to CaloSyria murdered Jona&#45;<lb/>&#45;than and his two sons in cold blood&#44; and ordered that they<lb/> be given an ordinary burial.  The news that he whom<lb/> the faithful in Israel regarded as a deliverer&#44; had died like a &#91;&#63;&#93;<lb/> culprit&#44; grieved the nation to the core.  Israel They Our people had la&#45;<lb/>&#45;mented E over Eleazar&#44; and Judah and Johanan&#44; but still they<lb/> had fallen with sword in hand.  Jonathan was killed while<lb/> dragging the chains of a slave.  But Simon did not<lb/> allow the precious body to continue unhonored among hea&#45;<lb/>&#45;then foes.  He went in search thereof&#44; and having <sic>disin&#45;<lb/>&#45;interred</sic> it&#44; carried the corpse&#44; amdist the tears of a grateful<lb/> people&#44; to Modin&#44; where his parents and their heroic sons<lb/> lay.  History has left a description of the<lb/> magnificent tombstones erected by Simon over the remains<lb/> of the Asmonean family.  It is recorded that the marble<lb/> was so perfect&#44; and the architecture so unique and superb&#44;<lb/> that for ages those mausoleums were objects of general<lb/> admiration.  But the last survivor of Mattathia&#39;s<lb/> sons&#44; glorified the name he bore&#44; more highly than by<lb/> rearing splendid monuments for the dead.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>His victories on the battle field and his statesmanship in the Senate chamber gave the living<lb/> independence.  Whilst he exercised power&#44; Judea<lb/> paid no more tributes to Greek&#44; or Egyptian or Syrian<lb/> rulers.  In acknowledgment of his services&#44; the re&#45;<lb/>&#45;presentatives of the nation&#44; at a grand assembly&#44; pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;claimed Simon prince&#44; as well as high priest of Judah&#44;<lb/> and to perpetuate the memorial of this event&#44; a copper plate<lb/> with an inscription signifying the people&#39;s will&#44; was<lb/> conspicuously placed in the Temple.  So deep and<lb/> universal was the regard paid to the successful Asmonean&#44;<lb/> that all public documents were dated thus&#58; &#34;On such a day of<lb/> the month from such a year of the rule of Simon&#44; the benefactor of the<lb/> Jews and chief of the nation.&#34;  So Josephus tells us.<lb/>  It is certain&#44; however&#44; that money was struck in Simon&#39;s time<lb/> by his authority&#44; bearing the Phoenician characters then in use<lb/> for coinage&#44; and having different engravings.  Some had presented one<lb/> one side the name of Simon&#44; and on the other &#34;Such a year of<lb/> the deliverance of Zion&#59;&#34; some had &#34;shekel of the sanctuary&#44;&#34;<lb/> or &#34;holy Jerusalem&#44;&#34; and so forth or similar devices.  Of those coins<lb/> a number exists still in European libraries and museums&#44;<lb/> and it is not impossible that American institutions of<lb/> learning may have procured also possess them.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>For eight years the noble working influence of the last child of<lb/> Mattathias was felt throughout the land.  He dispersed<lb/> the enemies of Israel&#44; and raised powerful friends&#59; gave<lb/> liberty with law&#44; and watched over the preservation of<lb/> both&#59; inspired his people with self&#45;respect&#44; and drew<lb/> towards them the respect of even their opponents.  Never<lb/> was Judea&#44; during the second Temple&#44; freer and mightier safer<lb/> than when governed by Simon&#44; and therefore no sadder<lb/> calamity could have befallen it&#44; than to have lost its guide<lb/> and exemplar.  If the our nation had wept bitterly<lb/> at the unnatural end&#44; which Jonathan had met through<lb/> heathen treachery&#44; it must have become wild with horror&#44;<lb/> when told that Simon was assassinated by a Jew&#45;&#45;and that<lb/> a very near relative.  He had married his daughter to<lb/> a man called one Ptolemy&#44; whom he appointed governor of<lb/> Jericho.  Simon usually <sic>travelled</sic> from city to city to ascertain<lb/> by personal inspection its conditions and wants.  He visited<lb/> Jericho&#44; in company with his wife and two of his sons&#44; and<lb/> received a welcome&#44; apparently as hearty as it was royal.<lb/>  Ptolemy invited his father and mother in law and their children<lb/> to the gorgeous castle he had built.  A sumptuous feast was<lb/> made ostensibly to do them honor&#44; but while all was pleasure<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>and mirth&#44; Simon was murdered and his wife and sons were<lb/> dragged into a dungeon.  Thirst for power had goaded<lb/> on Ptolemy to the commission of that shocking crime&#44;<lb/> and as he was immensely rich&#44; he believed that foreigners<lb/> could be bribed to assist him in carrying out his ambitious<lb/> schemes.  Once that Simon was dead&#44; he could would make him&#45;<lb/>&#45;self absolute king of Judea.  But there lived yet a son<lb/> of the murdered Asmonean&#44; who would fully able to avenge his father&#44; and<lb/> overthrow the plans of the murderer.  Ptolemy knew that&#44;<lb/> and therefore dispatched hired men mercenaries hired miscreants to slay John Hyrcanus.<lb/>  But the latter was quick in entering Jerusalem&#44; announ&#45;<lb/>&#45;cing the awful tragedy&#44; and calling on the people to rise and<lb/> repel his treacherous relation.  The Jewish inhabitants<lb/> at in the capital rose at responded vigorously to the summons.  Ptolemy and<lb/> his troops were forced to flee in great haste and take<lb/> refuge in the castle of Jericho.  There he was beseiged&#44;<lb/> and he would surely have perished&#44; but for a shield he had kept<lb/> in his possession&#44; and which he used with horrid adroitness.<lb/>  That shield was his mother and brothers in law.  Whenever<lb/> John Hyracanus drew near to the castle to storm it&#44; Ptolemy&#44;<lb/> with refined cruelty&#44; would place his prisoners front on the ramparts&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>and strike beat them fiercely.  That sight would<lb/> so overcame the son and brother&#44; that he was compelled to<lb/> desist.  The aged mother made expressive signs&#44; and as if entreating that<lb/> he would punish the assassin&#44; even if she was to be thrown<lb/> down from the wall&#44; but filial love always prevailed&#44;<lb/> and the castle continued long to be beseiged but not in a state of <sic>seige</sic>&#44; without being taken.<lb/>  Meanwhile&#44; the Sabbatical year&#44; during which it seems that no offensive<lb/> wars doom were not waged&#44; arrived&#44; and Ptolemy escaped abroad&#44; after<lb/> having kill stained <sic>imbrued</sic> his hands in the blood of the wife and<lb/> two sons of Simon.<lb/></p>
            <p>I have thus briefly narrated what every Jew who prides<lb/> himself on reckoning among his ancestors the children<lb/> of Mattathias the priest&#44; must feel an interest to<lb/> know.  From what I have sketched&#44; it will be<lb/> have been noticed observed that all the five were brave&#44; all<lb/> alike self&#45;denying for the sake of their religion.  Most<lb/> admirable we should consider the fidelity with which<lb/> they carried out the parting counsel of their aged<lb/> father&#44; acting in accord of sentiments&#44; aiming uni&#45;<lb/>formly to secure the independence and elevation of<lb/> Israel.  If in reading their history&#44; we natu&#45;<lb/>&#45;rally deplore the causes&#44; which denied each of them<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>a peaceful death on a bed surrounded by loved objects&#44;<lb/> we may nevertheless rejoice that it was no domestic strife<lb/> which brought any of them to an untimely grave.  The<lb/> names of those five <sic>heros</sic> have been transmitted to<lb/> their descendants unsullied as honest and virtuous pa&#45;<lb/>&#45;triots.  Yet&#44; posterity has reason to lament a<lb/> circumstance in the life of Jadah&#44; and which was copied reproduced<lb/> by in that of Jonathan and Simon.  Not in condemnation of<lb/> that famous triad of our immortal liberators I say it&#44; but in sorrow<lb/> for the consequences of which their entangling al&#45;<lb/>&#45;liances brought on occasioned.  They did not&#44; nor could they then&#44;<lb/> forsee the interposition and friendship good services offices of Rome&#44; which<lb/> they eagerly sought would be fatal prove evil in other extreme evils in the end&#59; nevertheless we that<lb/> still suffer from it that fatal error&#44; cannot suppress this confession.<lb/>  Our Maccabean deliverers indirectly sold us to the cruel Power<lb/> of on the seven&#45;hilled city.  They invited it to mingle with<lb/> the affairs of our nation&#44; and showing our weak points&#44;<lb/> led it to pounce upon us&#44; faster its blows upon our bodies&#44; tear up the country of our inheritance and<lb/> scatter our people&#44; like chaff throughout the habitable<lb/> globe.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
