<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF19_5</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_5_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_5_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_5_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_5_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_5_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_5_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_5_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_5_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_5_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_5_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_5_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff19_5_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>An appeal for the<lb/>
                Hebrew&#45;school.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  I have been requested to announce that on<lb/> the second day of the ensuing week&#44; the school esta&#45;<lb/>&#45;blished by the Hebrew Education Society will reopen.<lb/>  They&#44; however&#44; who direct it and have its progress at<lb/> heart&#44; desired likewise that I would avail myself of<lb/> the opportunity&#44; to render my hearers acquainted with the<lb/> advantages which that Institution enjoys&#44; and with others<lb/> which a more general cooperation would secure.<lb/>  I have accepted the mission&#58; and the more readily&#44; because<lb/> the obstacle which had debarred our Hebrew School from<lb/> obtaining the popularity it deserves&#44; has at length been<lb/> overcome.  The pupils who frequent it will&#44; henceforth&#44;<lb/> if they so choose&#44; be immediately transferred thence to our city high<lb/> school.  The tedious process to which they were heretofore<lb/> subjected&#44; will no longer be demanded.  Their proficiency<lb/> in English studies will be regarded&#44; as if acquired by<lb/> having passed through the various public establishments<lb/> preparatory to the highest one.  It cannot be<lb/> denied&#44; my friends&#33; that until this concession could be<lb/> drawn&#44; a cause did exist which militated against<lb/> the spread of Jewish education among all classes.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Many who might have preferred that the early<lb/> instruction of their offspring should combine the<lb/> religious with the secular&#44; were deterred from selecting<lb/> the institution which affords it.  They knew that<lb/> its being considered sectarian&#44; might&#44; in after years<lb/> expose its attendants to a vexatious ordeal&#44; and they<lb/> sought to spare their children the mortification.<lb/></p>
            <p>But The prevalence of such feelings among parents&#44;<lb/> urged the directors of the Hebrew school to renewed<lb/> efforts.  And they succeeded in having the disability<lb/> removed.  Accordingly&#44; they anticipate that the<lb/> appreciation of so good a result&#44; will be evidenced<lb/> by a large accession in the number of pupils.<lb/>  They believe that the advantage of a Hebrew and En&#45;<lb/>&#45;glish education with the privilege of a transfer to a<lb/> higher public school&#44; will commend the Institution to their<lb/> Philadelphia brethren.  They reasonably hope that<lb/> those among us&#44; who are unable constantly to su&#45;<lb/>&#45;pervise the religious training of their young offspring&#44;<lb/> will seek coadjutors where the knowledge of the<lb/> Law is jointly taught with other branches of learning.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>But they claim as a right the support of the<lb/> community for a society which gratuitously procures<lb/> the indigent and orphans&#44; instruction in both the sacred<lb/> and the vernacular language.  My friends&#33;  It<lb/> scarcely could be credited abroad&#44; that in a city where<lb/> the Israelites are counted by the thousand&#44; only one hun&#45;<lb/>&#45;dred and forty are they who annually subscribe for<lb/> the maintenance of a Hebrew School.  Indeed&#44;<lb/> had not the munificent gift of the late Judah Touro come<lb/> to its rescue&#44; it must have languished and perhaps ceased<lb/> now to exist.  And&#44; if I judge correctly&#44; it is to prevent<lb/> a total consumption of his bequest&#44; that periodical calls<lb/> for donations have been made upon the wealthy.<lb/></p>
            <p>Yet&#44; if the cause of Jewish learning&#44; commanded the<lb/> patronage to which it is entitled&#44; no individual personal<lb/> appeal or pulpit exhortation would be needed in this<lb/> instance.  The number of contributors of would swell<lb/> proportionately to the wants of our school and the<lb/> designs of its Directors.  For it must be acknowledged&#44;<lb/> that the anticipations formed by the lovers of Hebrew<lb/> lore&#44; have hitherto failed to be effected.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Unto this day&#44; only a primary step has been taken<lb/> towards the entrance of the vast field of biblical literature.<lb/>  True&#44; some who otherwise might have never been able<lb/> to decipher the Hebrew Alphabet&#44; have become qualified&#44;<lb/> through the Education Society&#44; to join in the ritual&#44; and<lb/> at times to recite also a portion from the prophets&#44; but<lb/> this is confessedly too slight a success to satisfy our<lb/> desires.  It certainly does not reflect lustre upon an<lb/> institution of learning.  But the force that should have<lb/> urged a more forward movement had been wanting withheld&#44; and<lb/> the result could only be commensurate with the scantiness<lb/> of the means at our disposal.  But Happily however&#44; the endeavours of<lb/> the friends of education seem now about to have received fresh countenance<lb/> &#38; support.  American Israelites have at last become alive<lb/> to their true interests.  Anxious to rear ministers of religion<lb/> from among those born in their own country&#44; they have<lb/> been seriously agitated the question&#44; of establishing a<lb/> college.  The Board of Delegates&#44; in which our Congre&#45;<lb/>&#45;gation is represented&#44; has warmly espoused the cause&#44;<lb/> and it labors indefatigably to reach the great end.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>But the difficulties that naturally attend the ac&#45;<lb/>&#45;complishing of so important an undertaking&#44; have<lb/> suggested the idea of preparing the minds of the<lb/> future pupils of the College by the formation of a<lb/> high school.  No plan has yet been definitely<lb/> decided upon&#44; but we may surmise that a course<lb/> of scriptural exegesis&#44; and polite literature will be<lb/> mainly pursued.  The directors of the Education<lb/> Society from whom the thought has emanated&#44; can<lb/> and will employ for that purpose talents fully<lb/> equal to the task&#44; but larger emoluments than those<lb/> which they have hitherto offered&#44; will be demanded and<lb/> justly expected.  Books that cannot be procured<lb/> at a moderate price will be required&#59; while to encourage<lb/> attendance&#44; some youths straitened in their circumstances<lb/> will needs receive some suitable aid.  To meet<lb/> all this indispensable expenditure&#44; a more general<lb/> and hearty cooperation is solicited.  Shall it be<lb/> forthcoming&#63;  Brethren&#33;  I conceive that several<lb/> among you have already evinced their sympathy<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>for the object submitted this morning to your kind<lb/> consideration.  Their animal subscriptions and occasional<lb/> gratuities may have effectually contributed in advancing<lb/> it&#44; but there remains a vast number of individuals<lb/> in our Community&#44; who have continued passive.<lb/>  To them would I fain send you as missionaries.<lb/>  Exercise in your commercial &#38; familiar circles the in&#45;<lb/>&#45;fluence you possess&#44; and the donors or at least the<lb/> set subscribers of our institution of learning will<lb/> increase to a most remarkable degree.  All will&#44; at<lb/> your instance&#44; give their mite for not so holy a<lb/> purpose.  I have always held the opinion that<lb/> when pulpit&#45;oratory and elaborately&#45;written circulars<lb/> will avail naught&#44; the exertion of our princely renowned<lb/> Hebrew merchants will <sic>yeild</sic> abundant success.  I will<lb/> then commit the cause into your hands.  And if the<lb/> aphorism of our Sages be true&#44; which it certainly is&#44; your<lb/> actions will have doubly merited the favor of the<lb/> Supreme.  &#34;Greater is the he &#34;they say&#34; that causes others to do<lb/> good&#44; than the person who performs it.&#34;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>Dear hearers&#33;  <sic>I</sic> my last address I exhorted you<lb/> to let the propitiatory prayers during the month<lb/> be accompanied with deeds of charity&#44; and I sincerely<lb/> believe that no nobler or more lasting charity can<lb/> be dispensed than that which upholds religious<lb/> learning knowledge.  Seize therefore the occasion<lb/> offered and benefit your souls.  If you are<lb/> already counted among the supporters patrons of learning&#44;<lb/> enlist in the same cause the heart of your friends<lb/> and relatives.  Let your and their efforts tend to<lb/> promote the knowledge of the useful and the true<lb/> in Israel.  Let existing institutions where the law<lb/> of God is imparted w wax strong through your<lb/> agency&#44; and others be called into being and liberally<lb/> sustained.  Labor strenuously to <sic>dispell</sic> ignorance&#44;<lb/> the parent of superstition and infidelity.  Sow<lb/> bo broad&#45;cast the seeds of piety&#59; you will have<lb/> opened a treasure of happiness for a generation yet unborn&#44;<lb/> and a perennial spring of joy for your immortal<lb/> spirits in the abode of the saints.  So may it be.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
