<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF6_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1854-01" source="" attested="yes">1854</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff6_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff6_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff6_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff6_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff6_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff6_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff6_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff6_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff6_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff6_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff6_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff6_1_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff6_1_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff6_1_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff6_1_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff6_1_8v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff6_1_9r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff6_1_9v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff6_1_10r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff6_1_10v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff6_1_11r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff6_1_11v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff6_1_12r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff6_1_12v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>17 pages on 6 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>154</p>
            <p>a farewell address.<lb/>
                1854<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Dear Brethren&#33;  Is it not natural that in addressing you<lb/> this morning&#44; conflicting sentiments should agitate my heart&#63;<lb/>  If in fulfilling my official duties I had aimed solely at those<lb/> which I have contracted with your representatives&#59; if I had been <lb/>merely your reader in the Synagogue&#44; but a stranger to all of you<lb/> our of the Synagogue&#44; I should perhaps at this moment be<lb/> perfectly calm and passive.  If I had not &#40;suffer me to say it&#44;<lb/> for it affords me some comfort&#41; if I had not strenuously sought in<lb/> the narrow limits of my capacity&#44; to promote your religious and<lb/> moral <sic>welbeing</sic>&#44; if I had neither sympathized with you when<lb/> in sorrow&#44; nor rejoiced at your gladness&#44; and above all if I had<lb/> not obtained unmistakable evidences that my humble efforts<lb/> have been affectionately reciprocated by many&#59; kindly and indul&#45;<lb/>&#45;gently received by the majority of you&#44; I perchance should now<lb/> feel unmoved and unconcerned&#59; but when I bear in mind&#44; that<lb/> although under stirring circumstances&#44; our intercourse for upwards<lb/> the of three years&#44; has been remarkably peaceful and mutually<lb/> satisfactory&#44; when I remember that often when my courage<lb/> failed&#44; in the arduous task I undertook&#44; the friendly counsel of<lb/> some of you came to my aid&#59; ought not my breast to heave with<lb/> quickened throbs in delivering a parting address&#63;  Yes&#44; my friends.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>I do feel&#44; deeply and sincerely feel much pain in bidding you even<lb/> a temporary farewell.  Nor is my regret counterpoised altogether by<lb/> the joyful consideration that I shall once more hail my parental<lb/> roof.  Surely it is unutterable pleasure to embrace an aged<lb/> father after a long absence&#59; it is delightful to breathe anew the<lb/> air of your native sky&#44; it is sweet to warmly press the hands of<lb/> the friends of your youth&#44; but it is harrowing to a sensitive<lb/> heart to behold withal millions of intelligent creatures crushed<lb/> beneath an iron yoke.  Aye&#44; when I contrast the condition of<lb/> this land&#44; in which your happy lot was cast&#44; with that of the<lb/> country I now design to revisit&#44; I cannot but feel sorely depres&#45;<lb/>&#45;sed.  Italy which gave birth to many a noble heart&#44; and where<lb/> civilization reigned&#44; when almost everywhere barbarism predomin&#45;<lb/>&#45;ated&#59; Italy where Jewish learning flourished&#44; where Aben<lb/>&#45;Ezra wrote&#44; Abarbanel taught&#44; and Del Medegs disseminated<lb/> Rabbinical <sic>phylosophy</sic>; Italy is at present reduced to the<lb/> lowest ebb of degradation&#59; and the one hundred thousand of<lb/> our brethren who inhale its genial air&#44; are nearly through&#45;<lb/>&#45;out the peninsula a mark to opprobrium and persecution.<lb/>  They are vilified because they adore the Only One of Israel&#44;<lb/> they are contemned because they reject doctrines repugnant<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>to the religion of Sinai&#44; they are plundered&#44; and caged like<lb/> ravenous animals because they cling to the faith which we<lb/> revere.  It is therefore&#44; as I have said&#59; when I contrast the<lb/> freedom&#59; the happiness of which you are here made to partake&#44;<lb/> with the sorrowful existence of our co&#45;religionists in that land<lb/> of their captivity&#44; that I doubly regret leaving your midst.<lb/>  Yet although the picture which I have delineated is unfortunate&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly too correct&#44; although to compare your condition in these<lb/> goodly regions&#44; with that of our brethren in those benighted climes&#44;<lb/> would be to liken mid&#45;day with to the dead of night&#44; refulgent light with to<lb/> lurid darkness&#44; nevertheless&#44; I must candidly confess that in one<lb/> peculiar point &#40;and a very essential one to every <sic>hebrew</sic> man&#41;<lb/> you would&#44; my friend&#44; suffer in comparison with those co&#45;religionists<lb/> of ours&#59; yes&#44; in one respect&#44; not only they would not rank lower<lb/> than you&#44; but they would be declared your superiors&#45;&#45;I mean&#44;<lb/> in the diligent observance of many religious injunctions.<lb/>  Not that you are second to any in attending to the principles<lb/> of morality which emanate from the heavenly volumes&#59; not<lb/> that in your connexion as fathers and husbands&#44; as mothers<lb/> and as children&#44; you relax in the discharge of your obligations&#59;<lb/> far be it from me&#44; to impute to you so &#91;&#63;&#93; reprehensible a<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>negligence&#44; but&#44; my beloved friends&#44; we must not only be moral<lb/> creatures of God&#59; we must be Israelites.  That which<lb/> suffices to secure to our fellow&#45;citizens of another creed the bles&#45;<lb/>&#45;sing of heaven here below&#44; and felicity hereafter&#44; cannot render<lb/> our lives acceptable in the sight of our God&#59; for whilst their<lb/> duties are limited to the performance of the seven Noachite<lb/> precepts&#44; our belief imposes upon us six hundred and thirt<lb/>&#45;een ordinances&#59; whilst they can <sic>conscienciously</sic> labor on the<lb/> sabbath day proclaimed on Sinai&#44; we&#44; must&#44; not to incur the<lb/> just wrath of the Eternal&#44; forbear in it from pursuing<lb/> after our work.  Whilst they can gratify their desires with<lb/> any viand for which they long&#44; we are restricted in that<lb/> by many prohibitory laws.  Whilst their holidays are few&#44; and<lb/> are principally a time for relaxation and merriment&#44; our festi&#45;<lb/>&#45;vals are solemn periods of our year&#44; which we must employ<lb/> in exercises purely religious.  Whilst they can dress their food<lb/> at their option&#44; eat the blood of animals&#44; and leave uncovered<lb/> that of winged fowls&#44; whilst they can array themselves in gar&#45;<lb/>&#45;ments of diverse sorts&#44; whilst they can enjoy the productions<lb/> of their soil at all times and under all circumstances&#44; our<lb/> Torah gives us prescriptions which relate to each of the aforenamed&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>and to all the minutest actions of our lives.<lb/></p>
            <p>And no one&#44; my brethren&#44; who is sealed with the covenant of<lb/> our father Abraham&#44; no one who wishes to remain a Jew&#44; can<lb/> with impunity infringe upon those commandments&#44; for<lb/> the same Omnipotent voice which promulgated that sublime code<lb/> of moral laws&#44; that wrought so wonderful a change in the &#91;&#63;&#93;<lb/> of men&#44; taught us also&#44; those ceremonial ordinances intended to<lb/> remind us continually of our eventful origin and of the mission<lb/> entrusted to us&#59; no where in the pages of scripture are they pronounced<lb/> to be of a minor importance&#44; nor has their practice been2 ever1 abrogated.<lb/>  True&#44; there are a portion of men who differ from our views&#44; and<lb/> who profess that the doctrines which constitute Judaism&#44; were<lb/> preparatory to a milder dispensation&#44; which was to exonerate<lb/> men from those tenets which concern the individual in his<lb/> outward worship.  But without striving now to refute<lb/> their assumption&#44; or dissuade them from their notions&#44; I will<lb/> ask you&#44; children of my people&#33; can we believe that God who<lb/> is prescient&#44; ubiquitary and Most Wise&#44; could have bestowed on<lb/> us&#44; a law which would succumb to the effects of time&#63;  A law which&#44;<lb/> emanating from the source of all perfections&#44; should in sub&#45;<lb/>&#45;sequent ages be declared imperfect&#63;  &#34;Is God a man that<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>should deceive&#44; or the son of man&#44; that He should repent&#63;&#34;<lb/>  But if it had been his blessed&#44; will that our fathers should only<lb/> receive a temporary law&#44; why is it not so recorded in Holy Writ&#63;<lb/>  Why did the Deity&#44; on the contrary&#44; promise that after we should have<lb/> expiated our delinquencies in exile&#44; He would vouchsafe to restore<lb/> us to our pristine glory&#44; provided we sedulously attended to all<lb/> the behests which He then imposed on us&#63;..Hear my brethren&#44;<lb/> they are the words of our God &#34;When thou shalt return and obey<lb/> the voice of the Eternal and perform all his commandments&#44;<lb/> which I command thee this day&#44; then shall the Eternal thy God<lb/> make thee plenteous in every work of thine hand&#44; in the<lb/> fruit of thy body and in the fruit of thy cattle&#44; and in the<lb/> fruit of thy land for good&#44; because the Eternal will again<lb/> rejoice over thee for good&#44; as he rejoiced over thy fathers.&#34;<lb/>  &#40;only&#41; If thou shalt hearken unto the voice of the Eternal thy<lb/> God&#44; to keep his commandments and his statutes which<lb/> are written in this book of the law.&#34;  Do we need a<lb/> clearer exposition touching the permanency of all our laws&#63;<lb/>  Can any man ascribe to the fountain of all knowledge&#44; ignorance<lb/> of future events&#44; when the whole chapter from which<lb/> we have quoted&#44; refers to our present state among<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>the gentiles&#44; and to the era of our promised restoration&#63;<lb/>  Can any son of Israel after perusing the verses I have cited&#44; bill<lb/> the reproaching voice of his conscience by saying that whilst he<lb/> pursues a moral course in his communion with his fellow&#45;<lb/>beings&#44; he can dispense with the other statutes of his professed<lb/> religion&#63;  Can he pacify his mind by the thought that<lb/> his numerous <sic>connexions</sic> with individuals of another creed&#44; or<lb/> his engrossing commercial intercourse are an extenuation for<lb/> his disregard of the ceremonial laws&#63;  No&#44; he is not a son of<lb/> Israel who argues so&#59; he is not a son of Israel who for lust<lb/> of gain&#44; for fear of ridicule&#44; or in order to pander to the wish<lb/> of the ungodly&#44; wittingly slight any of the injunctions inscribed<lb/> in the Mosaic code.<lb/></p>
            <p>And yet incredible as it may seem&#44; we have heard men&#44;<lb/> who not alone bear the name of Jews&#44; but who assume to teach<lb/> Judaism&#44; boldly assert that the omission of many of our<lb/> tenets is no longer to be considered a sin&#44; that when they<lb/> clash with our mercantile or scientific enterprises&#44; they must<lb/> not be heeded&#44; that since the light of <sic>phylosophy</sic> has shone<lb/> upon us&#44; we have become convinced of the inutility of some of<lb/> the Biblical and most of the <sic>Rabinical</sic> enactments.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>That to enforce in this enlightened age antiquated laws which<lb/> only suited our fathers who dwelt in different climes&#44; is a<lb/> futile attempt&#44; bordering on insanity.  Such are the doctrines<lb/> which these new expounders of our faith inculcate&#44; such prin&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciples they instil by their own example&#44; sustaining withal<lb/> that they alone comprehend the spirit of Judaism&#44; that neither<lb/> our Sages of old&#44; nor nay of their adherents&#44; could perceive the<lb/> light of progress which it emits.  If it be so then&#44; my<lb/> brethren&#44; and we for centuries have sought to please our Maker by<lb/> practices which are vanity&#59; if our teachers have led us in the way<lb/> of error if we have been groping in total darkness&#44; let us hail this new light now offered to our gaze&#59; let us<lb/> cease to be Jews.  Repair ye no longer on the Sabbaths<lb/> of the Lord and on the festivals to this consecrated spot&#44; for<lb/> it is detrimental to your wordly interest.  Indulge freely<lb/> in whatsoever your soul yearns for&#44; since f both the<lb/> clean and the unclean were created for your gratification&#59;<lb/> never afflict yourselves by fasting&#44; lest your health might<lb/> be impaired.  Rear your offspring in the knowledge<lb/> of that which may prove to them pecuniarily advantageous&#44;<lb/> but do not subject them to the abstruse study of dogmas which<lb/> have become lifeless&#59; of a language which is perfectly dead.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>But will you&#44; my beloved friends&#33; consent to a change so subversive<lb/> of all the lessons you have imbibed from your infancy&#63;  Oh ye descendants<lb/> of those who without demur declared before their Legislator and Saviour<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; that they would execute and obey&#44; will you repudiate this<lb/> holy Torah&#44; because it is a bridle to the appetites&#44; because it<lb/> curbs the immoderate passion for lucre&#63;; will you wantonly reject<lb/> it&#44; because it demands some sacrifice&#59; while its preservation has cost<lb/> the lives of myriads&#63;  Will you lay an impious hand upon the word<lb/> of God&#44; and alter it at will&#44; in order that its injunctions may<lb/> not impede the furtherance of your ambitious schemes&#63;<lb/>  Let it not be said so of you O &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Hope of Israel&#34;.......<lb/> Before the holy ark towards which we turn in offering our<lb/> supplications&#44; and wherein the standard of truth is deposited.  On<lb/> this doubly sacred day&#44; with whose solemnity you are impressed<lb/> let us promise that we will not swerve from the dictates<lb/> of the law&#59; that we will readily relinquish temporary enjoy&#45;<lb/>&#45;ments and the fleeting goods of the world&#44; to implicitly<lb/> perform the will of our Father who is in heaven&#44; let us<lb/> promise that we will maintain intact the precious heritage<lb/> of our fathers&#44; that the religion of Sinai shall be the rule<lb/> of all our actions&#59; our sole guide when we sit in our houses&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>to instill imprint it into upon the tender minds of our children&#59; when<lb/> we walk by the way&#44; in the pursuit of our daily occupations&#44; so<lb/> that probity and justice may actuate &#91;&#63;&#91; us&#59; in the pursuit<lb/> of our daily occupations&#59; when we lie down&#44; that we may ask our&#45;<lb/>&#45;selves whether we have advanced or retrograded in the path of<lb/> virtue&#59; when we rise up&#44; that we may be reminded of the duties<lb/> we owe to Him who granteth slp sleep to our wearied limbs&#44; health<lb/> and vigour to our frame&#44; sustenance to our bodies.<lb/>  Ah yes&#44; my friends&#44; keep the truth in your heart&#44; and suffer<lb/> me to repeat it once more.  He is not an Israelite who<lb/> would not resign a single gratification to <sic>fulfil</sic> the religion<lb/> of promulgated by the Eternal.  He is not of the stock of Abraham who<lb/> abandons this imperishable treasure entrusted to us&#44; to rashly<lb/> embrace new fangled doctrines.  You may become proficient<lb/> in learning&#44; and men will call you wise and erudite&#44; but<lb/> believe me there is no human science so capable of inspiring<lb/> you with the true love for good&#44; so able to maintain<lb/> you steadfast in the career of virtue&#44; as the glorious religion<lb/> which is peculiarly ours&#59; for it prescribes salutary laws for<lb/> all the human actions.  No terrestrial prosperity will<lb/> render you happy&#44; if you disdain to abide by the directions of God&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>for&#44; unless you are totally depraved&#44; that still&#45;small voice that<lb/> whispers to our conscience will will ultimately be heard&#44; and the years will draw nigh<lb/> when you shall say &#34;I have no pleasure in them&#34;.  Without your<lb/> religion which affords at once light and warmth&#44; light to<lb/> illumine the mind&#44; and warmth to quicken the sentiments&#44; no<lb/> weal can be durable&#59; for without such a religion as that granted<lb/> to Israel&#44; which while it guides us from the cradle to the grave&#44; it points<lb/> out to us the way of salvation&#44; and it ensures us a temporal<lb/> blessing and a spiritual felicity&#44; without such a religion&#59; virtue&#44;<lb/> morality and piety would be names without signification.  Aye&#44;<lb/> it was your religion&#44; my brethren&#44; that instructed mankind in<lb/> the knowledge of the Supreme Author of all good&#44; it was the<lb/> Jewish religion that taught lessons of benevolence and mercy towards<lb/> our neighbor&#44; of respect to his property&#44; of obedience to our parents&#59;<lb/> It was the Jewish religion that had an eye of compassion over all<lb/> the creatures of God nay even over the dumb animals&#59; and to enforce<lb/> the principles of morality so early taught pure&#44; it instituted ceremonial<lb/> observances&#44; which are a watchful guard in the walks of life that<lb/> our steps may not be diverted from the rightful path.  And shall<lb/> we forsake a religion so sublime&#44; or would it in a fashion that may suit<lb/> all the whims of mortals&#59; shall we make the immutable word God yeild<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p><sic>yeild</sic> to the infinite numberless changes of human society&#63;  Never&#44; never will we<lb/> postpone it to the rebellious impulses of the flesh&#44; to the hallucination of<lb/> the mind&#44; or to the advice of the ungodly.  We will keep undefiled<lb/> this divine religion&#44; faithfully observe the laws of Horeb which were&#44; are&#44;<lb/> and will everlastingly be the glory of Israel. Ɵ My friends&#33; once<lb/> more ere I quit your circle&#44; I feel it a stringent duty to exhort you<lb/> with all the energy of my soul to adhere unwaveringly to the practical<lb/> as well as to the moral injunctions of the book of books&#59; to walk in<lb/> the light which it emits&#44; to abhor the darkness of error&#44; to shun and<lb/> detest vice and crime&#44; to cling to the religion of our fathers&#44; as to the only anchor of your eternal salvation.  And if sinners strive to entice you from it&#44;<lb/> the religion of our fathers&#44; consent not.  If they say&#44; come with us&#44;<lb/> we will walk in the way of progress&#44; you shall acquire renown&#44;<lb/> honour&#44; and wealth&#44; listen not to them.  Suffer not your feet<lb/> to follow the their steps&#44; for they run to evil&#44; their minds devise<lb/> but sin&#44; their hearts conceive but perverted sentiments.<lb/></p>
            <p>&#34;Woe to them who are wise in their own eyes&#34; exclaims the prophet.  They<lb/> abandon the spring of living waters&#44; to dig for themselves broken cisterns&#44;<lb/> but they shall fall into the pit they have dug&#44; unheeded and<lb/> disconsolate.  &#34;Woe to their souls&#34; continues Isaiah &#34;because they have awarded<lb/> evil for themselves.&#34; for&#44; the impious live in a perpetual war with<lb/> themselves&#44; and whilst they would persuade others to follow their<lb/> example&#44; they know not how to persuade themselves that they<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="14"/>
            <p>act rightly.  Whilst they endeavour to appear learned and to acquire<lb/> the name of leaders of civilization&#44; they are constrained to our own to<lb/> their hearts&#44; that their science is rottenness to their bones and destruction<lb/> to their spirit.  They are compelled to acknowledge to their inward selves&#44; that as religion<lb/> is a supreme want of man and that as all religions are founded<lb/> upon the revelation of Horeb&#44; to which reason and intellect must<lb/> bow2 reverently1&#44; all their philosophical disquisitions are useless&#44; and<lb/> that far better it is to be guided by the religion of our fathers than&#44;<lb/> to adore God in child&#45;like faith&#44; than to lose oneself in a maze<lb/> of subtle ratiocinations.  Nay&#44; the irreligious fig envy the<lb/> righteous&#44; to whom that sun of truth&#44; without which we should frequently<lb/> slide in the devious paths of life&#44; is a beacon light&#59; and they also<lb/> willingly would be led by that unquenchable light&#44; but pride<lb/> holds them tight in its grasp&#44; and on to its altar shrine they are<lb/> forced to sacrifice their happiness and that of their posterity.<lb/>  Let it not be so of you&#44; my beloved ones&#33; let religion be your sovereign<lb/> virtue&#44; let it be the mast and the sail the compass by which you steer<lb/> toward your bark through this stormy sea of life&#44; let it be a comfort to your souls<lb/> among so many and so frequent &#91;&#63;&#93; trials to which mortals are<lb/> exposed&#59; let religion be your supreme delight at all periods and<lb/> under all circumstances.  And in bidding you a hearty<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="15"/>
            <p>farewell&#44; let me leave your midst do so with the assurance firm conviction<lb/> that you will remain Israelites in practice as well as in spirit&#59;<lb/> and that you will keep the charge of the Lord your God&#44; to walk<lb/> in his ways&#44; to perform his statutes&#44; his judgments&#44; his commandments&#44; his<lb/> judgments and his testimonies as it is written in the law of Moses&#44;<lb/> that you may prosper in all your doings&#44; and in whatsoever you<lb/> undertake&#44; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Great all All&#45;mighty God&#33;  Grant that thy word&#44; like the morning<lb/> dew which irrigates and fertilizes the earth&#44; may enter our hearts&#44; and<lb/> become our <sic>consellor</sic> and our guide.  May it be light to our feet&#44; that<lb/> we may walk uprightly in the way of thy precepts for &#34;thy law is<lb/> perfect and converteth the soul&#44; thy testimony is sure&#59; and maketh the<lb/> simple wise&#34; May the brightness it emanates irradiates illumine our spirits&#44; that<lb/> we may never abandon justice and charity.  Allow not iniquity<lb/> to dwell within us&#44; and save us O God&#33; from the errors of such who&#44;<lb/> elated by worldly knowledge&#44; raise presumptuously their voice against<lb/> the dictates of Thy wisdom.  Grant that amidst the trials&#44; the dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;sapointments&#44; the sorrows of life&#44; thy word may prove to us a strong&#45;<lb/>&#45;hold whither we shall take refuge and obtain repose.  May it<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="16"/>
            <p>be the beacon light that shall lead us securely to the possession<lb/> of that eternal inheritance which is in the land of the living.<lb/></p>
            <p>Merciful God&#33;  I humbly beseech Thee for the sake of these<lb/> thy children who stand in awe to receive thy blessing.  Be to them<lb/> a strength every morning a daily and an hourly support&#44; also their salvation in the time of trouble.<lb/>  Shield them against pestilence that walketh in darkness&#44; and destruction<lb/> that wasteth at noon.  Bereave them not of their beloved children<lb/> whom they teach to adore Thy name.  Deign to bless the husbands and<lb/> their wives who jointly labor for the religious education of their off&#45;<lb/>&#45;spring.  Strengthen them in Crown with success their laudable undertaking&#59; grant to<lb/> them their daily wants&#44; that theirs may be called the abode of <sic>tranquillity</sic>.<lb/>  Assuage the sorrows of the afflicted&#44; and inspire them with resigna&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion to thy will&#44; by the hope of an ampler requital in the dwelling<lb/> of the immortals.  Bless the youth of this holy community&#44; and<lb/> may they early learn that to steadily follow thy law&#44; will afford them<lb/> a delight more durable than that of mundane gratifications.  Bless<lb/> the aged and may their piety&#44; suavity and calmness&#44; teach us by their<lb/> examples that the latte rend of the life of the righteous is serenity calmness and peace.<lb/>  Bless me also O Eternal in whom I trust&#44; may I&#44; though unworthy of thy and may thy boundless mercy<lb/> grace&#44; shead shed &#91;&#63;&#93; tears of joy&#44; in clasping to my heart my gray headed pardon me&#44; thy fatherly compassion shield me&#44; thy gracious goodness<lb/> parents&#44; the sisters whom I love&#44; the brother of my affection&#44; the friends favour me now and evermore.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="17"/>
            <p>of my sweet recollection.  May Thy mercy pardon me&#44; thy<lb/> compassion save me&#44; thy goodness favor me.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
