<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF5_8</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1863-11" source="" attested="yes">November 1863</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_8_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_8_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_8_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_8_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_8_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_8_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_8_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_8_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_8_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_8_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_8_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_8_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_8_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_8_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_8_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_8_8v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_8_9r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_8_9v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_8_10r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff5_8_10v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>19 pages on 6 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>A thanksgiving sermon  1863<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>You will pardon me&#44; respected hearers&#33; if while searching for<lb/> a text on which to descant&#44; my reflections involuntarily suggested<lb/> one of lament.  As I pondered on the vicissitudes which America<lb/> has recently undergone&#44; I beheld that venerable parent of<lb/> a once happy race&#44; wallow in ashes&#44; exclaiming in the lan&#45;<lb/>&#45;guage of Job &#34;Oh&#33; who will give me back the months that<lb/> &#34;have passed&#59; the days when God guarded me.  When his lamp<lb/> &#34;shone upon my head&#44; and by its light I could walk in darkness.<lb/>  &#34;As I was in the days of my youth&#44; when the counsel of God go&#45;<lb/>&#45;&#34;verned my tabernacle.  When the Almighty was yet with me&#44;<lb/> &#34;when my children stood round about me.&#34;  Affected to tears<lb/> by that vision&#44; I strove in vain to evoke the joyous thoughts<lb/> wherewith the yearly celebration was wont to inspire me.<lb/>  My harp struck but plaintive strains&#59; I hung it on my<lb/> drooping heart.  Aye&#59; let me weep over the sad fare<lb/> of this asylum of the oppressed.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Taught by Israel&#39;s religion and Israel&#39;s history to love freedom.<lb/>  Devoted to it by a strong natural tendency&#59; doubly impressed<lb/> with its inestimable worth&#44; because of the sufferings endured<lb/> through its absence&#59; I have&#45;&#45;&#40;without irreverence be it said&#41;&#45;&#45;stood with my mind on the summit<lb/> of Pisgah to survey this land of promise&#44; which has beckoned<lb/> to her hospitable shores the weary of all nations and climes.<lb/>  More festivals than the immortal Seer of old&#44; I have been<lb/> permitted to enter this new Canaan&#44; every spot of which is<lb/> sanctified by the footsteps of revolutionary heroes.  I have often<lb/> gazed upon the precious fane&#44; whence issued the word that<lb/> struck tyranny with dismay&#44; and the world with admiration.<lb/>  I have contemplated the stupendous work of the founder of<lb/> American greatness&#44; whose memory alone ought to have blended<lb/> the feelings of all those he <sic>benefitted</sic>&#44; into one of indissoluble<lb/> brotherhood.  I have witnessed&#44; under its auspices&#44; the gigantic<lb/> strides taken towards social equality&#44; and towards the perfection<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>of all arts and sciences.  I have seen the hand of a beneficent<lb/> God&#44; scatter through these fields&#44; those plains and meadows the<lb/> seeds of plenty and boundless wealth&#44; and I said&#44; &#34;Surely this is<lb/> the tabernacle of peace&#44; the temple where happiness is enthroned.&#34;<lb/>  My soul was then ravished with delight.  Every fibre of my<lb/> heart thrilled with joy&#44; when at each recurrence of the present<lb/> occasion&#44; one chorus of national thanksgiving rent the sky from <lb/>the vale to the mountain&#45;peak&#44; from the Hudson to the Red&#45;<lb/>River&#59; and I&#44; joining in the anthem&#44; extolled the Living Deliverer Redeemer<lb/> of America.  But now.....I&#45;Chabod&#44; my Brethren&#44; I&#45;Chabod&#59;<lb/> I sorrowfully cry like the dying mother who was apprized<lb/> of her nation&#39;s dishonor in of her own bereavement.  For&#44; the glory that lent orators their<lb/> burning eloquence&#44; the glory painted pi depicted so glowingly in the halls<lb/> of legislation&#44; so blazoned in the forum and on the pulpit&#59; that<lb/> glory&#44; alas&#39; has been tarnished by our polluted hands.  The<lb/> world looks <sic>agast</sic>.  It cannot believe that this palladium<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>of human rights has been deliberately dragged down from its lofty<lb/> stand by its own custodians.  For&#44; the testimony of time has shown<lb/> that on its preservation depended the <sic>welbeing</sic> of generations<lb/> yet unborn.  The world finds not among its records a<lb/> parallel to the towering eminence rapidly attained by the nation<lb/> of Washington&#44; while knit together by the laws he enacted.<lb/></p>  
            <p>Nay&#44; I may venture to assert&#44; that those achievements have exceeded<lb/> the most sanguine calculations of the Sages of the revolution.<lb/>  The idea that three millions of human beings burthened with<lb/> debt&#44; would in the course of a man&#39;s life&#45;time&#44; swell up to<lb/> the number of upwards of thirty millions&#44; and become the most<lb/> prosperous among the nations under the canopy of heaven&#44; seems<lb/> too hyperbolical to be contemplated even by those far&#45;sighted<lb/> minds.  Yet&#44; such was the effect of that broad Constitution<lb/> concocted by their wisdom.  Its benign influence grew<lb/> irresistible.  It attracted with more than magnetic force<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>now votaries to its shrines.  Identified with the original posses&#45;<lb/>&#45;sors of that sublime charter&#44; by the fruition of equal rights&#44; the<lb/> welcome stranger brought all his energies to bear on the develop&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment of the exhaustless riches of the soil that had received him.<lb/>  The stalwart arm upturned the earth that hid treasures in its<lb/> bosom.  His industry enlarged the sphere of that which is<lb/> useful and convenient to society.  As years rolled on&#44; so the<lb/> tide of immigration increased amazingly&#44; until the native<lb/> element commingled with the foreign&#44; attained an herculean<lb/> power.  But mark this well&#44; my beloved hearers&#33;  It was<lb/> not a power that crushes beneath its ponderous weight the<lb/> feeble and the <sic>defenceless</sic>.  It was not like that Power which prides<lb/> itself on being the arbiter of nation&#39;s fate&#44; and the dictator of<lb/> minor sovereignities&#59; but a power that gloried in diffusing<lb/> the blessings of civil and religious liberty&#44; in securing education<lb/> to the masses&#44; temporal advantages and honorable positions to<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>whomsoever was governed by its beneficent rules.  Hence&#44; does the<lb/> civilized world look with amazement&#44; hence &#34;hath my harp<lb/> turned to mourning&#44; and my organ lyre into sound of weeping.&#34;<lb/>  For&#44; say ye my friends&#33;  Ought not a power so gracious and<lb/> so benignant to have continued on its lofty stand&#44; until the<lb/> sun ceases to illumine the earth&#63;  Ought not the breast<lb/> of every being to whom it secured inestimable immunities&#44; to have been<lb/> its bulwark&#63;...Oh eternal ignoring&#33;  Repeat it not&#59; the<lb/> hand  it had filled with good&#44; lowered it from its height.<lb/>  Merciless ambition has very nigh cast it at the foot of<lb/> despotic thrones.  Methinks I hear the oppressors of man&#45;<lb/>&#45;kind deridingly ask &#34;Is that the clime&#44; which was called<lb/> &#34;the completion of beauty&#44; the delight of all the earth&#63;&#34;  Aha&#33;<lb/> &#34;this is the day for which we have longed&#44; it hath arrived&#44; we<lb/> &#34;have seen it&#34;  Man&#33; behold the effects of liberty&#34;.  The ea&#45;<lb/>&#34;&#45;pons of destruction are furbished&#44; the coursers are prancing on<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>&#34;the battle&#45;field&#59; thousands are marshalled in mortal array&#44;<lb/> &#34;not to repel the invading stranger&#44; but to drench a common country<lb/> &#34;in fraternal blood&#34;.  Brethren&#44; friends&#33;  what shall we answer<lb/> to their taunts&#63;  Can thou be any any motive extenuated to the flagetious<lb/> deed that plunged a whole nation in utter misery&#44; and caused<lb/> freedom to blush&#63;  No&#44; let us enter these holy courts&#44; not<lb/> with triumphant looks&#44; but with subdued thoughts and humiliation.<lb/>  Let us bedew the altar of our Lord&#44; with tears of contrition&#44; for&#44; the<lb/> heavenly boons vouchsafed unto us have been foully abused.  The<lb/> matchless prosperity we enjoyed&#44; seduced us away from the<lb/> path marked out by the noble founders of this Republic.<lb/>  The grand idea embodied in the formation of this government has<lb/> been lost sight of&#44; while craftily scheming municipal or state<lb/> enlargement&#59; while we sought the gratification of contemptible jea&#45;<lb/>lousies.  We grew mighty&#44; and with it selfish&#44; restless&#44; dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;satisfied with our happy lot.  The simplicity that characterized<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>the primeval days of our nationality&#44; was deemed unbecoming a this more<lb/> self styled&#45;&#45;enlightened age.  Luxury fostered general degeneracy&#44; satiety en&#45;<lb/>&#45;gendered the corruption of our habits&#44; vice and pride were linked<lb/> together&#44; and the incestuous alliance gave birth to the serpents<lb/> that have poisoned our vitals&#45;&#45;perjury2&#44; fraud1 and rebellion.<lb/></p>
            <p>But hear now what the word the Lord saith&#34;  For the evil of your hands<lb/> &#34;do you expect good&#63;  The chieftain demandeth bribe&#44; and<lb/> &#34;the judge acteth for pay&#44; and the great man is only speaking<lb/> &#34;the mischievous desire of his soul &#38; clings to it.  Piety best doing is like a briar&#44; the goodness is sharper than a thorn&#45;edge&#59; therefore the day of thy retention requital &#40;thy &#91;&#63;&#93; hath come&#44; now shall they become perplexity seize them&#34;  &#34;Shall1 I count thee pure<lb/> &#34;with the wicked balances and with the bag of deceitfulness&#63;&#34;<lb/>  Ah&#33;  My Brethren&#33;  Our national iniquity has at length is being visited upon<lb/> us&#59; we are requited only commensurately with our delinquencies.<lb/>  Alas&#33; that the messenger of divine wrath has not been permitted&#44;<lb/> like in the days of yore&#44; to pass over the houses marked with the<lb/> tokens of innocence.  Death and dearth have with pitiless indi&#45;<lb/>&#45;scrimination gathered their spoil.  Many&#44; many hearths where<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>joy reigned&#44; are overspread with gloom.  The mother whose<lb/> promising son lies entombed in the ensanguined battle&#45;field&#59; the<lb/> wife whose agonizing thoughts follow her life&#45;copartner now to<lb/> the wearisome march&#44; anon to the fierce conflict&#59; the sister whose<lb/> brother languishes in a dungeon&#44; where patriotism is exposed to a fiery<lb/> ordeal&#44; they&#44; who are not amenable before the heavenly tribunal for the<lb/> crime that has brought on this land a terrible scourge&#44; they uplift their<lb/> souls unto God in utter anguish and pray for comfort and deliverance.<lb/>  For their sake must we jointly this day address the throne of<lb/> grace.  The Chief Executive of our beloved Union&#44; has been<lb/> specially mindful of the sorrows of &#34;the widows and orphans&#44; of<lb/> &#34;the mourners and sufferers because of the lamentable civil strife in<lb/> &#34;which we are unavoidably engaged.&#34;  He has expressed the desire<lb/> that we should &#34;commend them to the tender care of our beneficent<lb/> &#34;Father who dwelleth in the heavens&#44;&#34; but our <sic>intreaties</sic> my beloved hearers&#33; must<lb/> be accompanied by deeds of charity.  It is highly due to them<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>and imperative on us that we should evince active sympathy<lb/> towards the <sic>relicts</sic> and offspring of those who flew to the rescue<lb/> of a common mother when verging on death a precipice.  It is incumbent<lb/> principally on us to lighten the burthen of such among them&#44; who<lb/> need human succour.  I say on us&#44; as denziens of Pennsylvania&#44;<lb/> because our obligation to them is greater perhaps than that<lb/> of any other state.  Their sacrifice at the shrine of American<lb/> honor has purchased our safety.  Twice have the arms of<lb/> the dear objects&#44; who tore themselves from their embraces to respond<lb/> to their country&#39;s call&#44; averted from these shores borders impending dangers.<lb/>  The calamity which an assailing host urged to desperation&#44; would<lb/> have entailed upon our Community&#44; exceeds any calculation.<lb/>  To the stigma which its success would have indelibly stamped on<lb/> our escutcheon&#44; would have also been added the certain<lb/> de&#45;<lb/>&#45;pletion of our granaries&#44; and the drainage of our vast<lb/> resources.  &#34;The inimical sword would have destroyed without&#44; and terror made havoc within&#44; both of the youth man &#38; the virgin&#44; the suckling infant with the man of gray hairs.&#34;  Shame &#38; penury&#44; and devastation &#38; horror would have been<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>the vestiges of a long contemplated and adroitly planned<lb/> invasion.  But the vigilance of our brave defenders was our<lb/> shield and buckler.  It effectually thwarted the devices of our<lb/> adversaries&#44; and saved us and our children as at this day.<lb/>  Let us then prove ourselves worthy of the deliverance they wrought we experienced&#59; worthy of the self&#45;denial and brotherly affection that have wrought it.<lb/>  But our sense of thankfulness to mortals&#44; should not abstract<lb/> our minds from the debt of gratitude we owe the Immortal Protec&#45;<lb/>&#45;tor of our existence&#45;&#45;the Sovereign of the Universe.  Amidst<lb/> trials most severe and of unequalled magnitude&#44; occasioned by our own<lb/> perversity&#44; we experienced His paternal compassion.  He made<lb/> us palpably feel that man&#39;s wickedness did not quench the<lb/> love He has ever borne to America.  Though we have reasons to<lb/> lament&#44; with the words of my text&#44; that &#34;His lamp has not shone<lb/> over our heads as in the years that have gone by&#44; when at by its light<lb/> we could walk in darkness&#34;; though a veil raised by our<lb/> misdeeds&#44; separated us from our Eternal Creator&#44; still&#44; the rays of<lb/> His mercy pierced it&#44; and we were not chilled with despair.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p>We ate at His luxuriant table&#59; He made our cup brimful with<lb/> new oil.  If the last season reduced us to lassitude&#44; the present<lb/> diffused through our bodies its balmy and invigorating effects.<lb/>  The Author of nature amplified the resources placed at our disposal.<lb/>  He stimulated labour&#44; and gave a stranger impulse to the wheel of<lb/> commerce.  But why shall I trespass on your time&#44; by<lb/> the reiteration of that which has been most fittingly set forth&#63;<lb/>  My beloved hearers&#33;  The motives which ought to prompt your<lb/> loyal hearts souls to pour forth thanks and praises in the presence<lb/> of Almighty God&#44; have been well discussed in the proclamations of<lb/> both your Governor &#38; President.  They are innumerable&#44; and&#44; under the<lb/> existing deplorable circumstances&#44;&#45;&#45;most cheering to the cause<lb/> we all have at heart.  But it would ill comport with my<lb/> station&#44; as it surpasses my capacity&#44; to describe the exploits<lb/> achieved at Vicksburg or on the Rapid&#91;&#63;&#93; &#38; Port&#45;Hudson.  On the plains of Gettysburg or at Chattanooga.  To portray the<lb/> indomitable courage exhibited by our army&#44; and the all&#45;conquering<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="14"/>
            <p>perseverance of our Navy.  It is to me a source of extreme joy<lb/> when I perceive that &#34;the theatre of our military conflict has been<lb/> greatly contracted&#34; and the ensign of order waves over the ramparts of<lb/> disorganization&#44; for&#44; such progress is the dawn announcing the sun<lb/> which will bring healing in its wings to our national troubles&#59; still<lb/> the task of dilating upon those momentous events&#44; must be left<lb/> to better abler and more suitable speakers.  But there is a point in<lb/> the history of the year which is near its close&#44; that has not been adverted<lb/> to&#44; but in which we&#44; as Pennsylvanians&#44; ought greatly to glory.<lb/>  When I recall to mind the scenes of blood enacted in a neighbouring<lb/> state&#59; the loose passions that found vent in the slaughtering of<lb/> a hapless and inoffensive men caste of men&#44; the combining of all sinister<lb/> devices to oppose the application of the law&#44; I believe I utter<lb/> but the truth when I say that our state is not alone the<lb/> Keystone of the Union&#44; but the brightest gem of its crown.<lb/>  In her midst the majesty of the law is considered inviolable.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="15"/>
            <p>She is a bright exemplar of self&#45;government&#44; the best exponent of loyalty.<lb/>  Let this gratifying thought be an additional incentive to our thanksgi&#45;<lb/>&#45;ving.  Pennsylvania will never swerve from the path of national<lb/> rectitude she has voluntarily chosen.  The Mistress of inexhaustible<lb/> treasures&#44; she will not rear with them a structure to state&#45;pride&#44;<lb/> but generously pour them out for the preservation of the Monument<lb/> raised to Federalism Unity.  Faithful to the ancient original covenant&#44;<lb/> she will share with her sisters&#44; the burthen necessarily laid upon<lb/> her&#44; as she was&#44; in happier days&#44; the participant of their greatness.<lb/>  The historian that shall transmit to posterity the records of<lb/> our intestine war&#44; will point her out as the sustaining power<lb/> of the old&#44; matchless and masterly constitution.  Ascribe glory<lb/> then to the Most High God&#44; ye inhabitants of this noble Common&#45;<lb/>&#45;wealth.  Offer Him thanks that your lot has been cast in so fa&#45;<lb/>&#45;vorable a region.  Beseech Him to engraft in the breasts<lb/> of yall your fellow&#45;citizens the sentiment of loyalty that<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="16"/>
            <p>distinguishes you.  To breathe new life into the dry&#45;bones moulde&#45;<lb/>&#45;ring under the influence of a meridional sun&#44; to infuse a new spirit<lb/> into them&#44; that they may rise with a single will to vindicate the<lb/> honor of a common country&#44; to reestablish its supremacy lofty position among the family of nations&#44; to bring in<lb/> everlasting peace&#44; union and prosperity to all those whose immortal<lb/> ancestors taught the the world the value of civil and religious liberty.<lb/>  Then will the years&#44; whose departure I have lamented&#44; return to us<lb/> with fulness of joy.  God Himself will be the Custodian of our immunities.<lb/>  His lamp will perennially shine over us&#44; at by its light we shall walk<lb/> in darkness.  And like the primeval days of their guileless<lb/> simplicity&#44; all the children of fre regenerated America will set on her head<lb/> a crown of glory.  She shall be called the &#34;Joyous&#59;&#34; the &#34;Happy.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <p>Eternal God&#33;  The heavens upon which Thou hast impressed<lb/> the seal of Thy infinite power&#44; attest that Thou art their only<lb/> author&#44; and all created nature&#44; in harmonious strains<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="17"/>
            <p>reechoes that truth.  But like Thy might&#44; so is Thy wisdom<lb/> traced in the footsteps of the universe&#44; and glorious is indeed<lb/> the lot of those&#44; who can follow them with a discerning eye.<lb/>  They will enter the palace of the Supreme King&#44; who is holds<lb/> in His hand the threads of sublunary events.  In every ill beneath<lb/> which nations succumb&#59; in all the vicissitudes they endure&#44; they<lb/> will behold Thy unchangeable providence O Lord&#33; directing man&#45;<lb/>&#45;kind to its destined goal.  But we&#45;&#45;limited in our mental<lb/> vision&#44; cannot rise to so exalted a standard.  We frail beings&#44; are<lb/> tossed all&#45;day on the waves of terrestrial incidents.  Where shall<lb/> we then&#44; in our human infirmities&#44; seek strength and comfort&#63;.....<lb/> Unto Thee O Father we will pour out our souls&#44; and Thou wilt<lb/> soothe them with the balm of divine hope.  We pray that<lb/> ere another cycle of twelve months be carried into the bosom of<lb/> eternity&#44; the dire calamity which afflicts our land&#44; may<lb/> be counted among things that have passed.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="18"/>
            <p>We pray that like the genial light sun&#44; which at this season brightens our<lb/> horizon&#44; so may a softening influence from above pervade the national<lb/> sky overspread with clouds&#44; and restore its serenity.  Send O Our Creator&#33;<lb/>  A heavenly beacon&#44; to guide America aright into the path of social<lb/> progress.  &#40;Suffer not the scorching rays of a meridional sun to consume a Then will all Thy creatures rejoice in Thee&#44; &#38; Thy name be glorified upon earth as it is in the heavens.<lb/> fair portion of our heritage&#44; but grant that its intensity be subdured&#44; and<lb/> we may bask again in its gentler heat. &#40;Then will Thy creatures rejoice in<lb/> Thee&#44; and Thy name be ever glorified in our midst.&#41;  Beneficent King<lb/> who healest the broken hearted and bindest up their wounds&#44; deign to send<lb/> a speedy cure to the moral pangs borne by the lovers of this country&#44;<lb/> and to the physical sufferings of its noble defenders.  Let Thy countenance<lb/> O Most High God&#33; shine upon our patriots and soldiers&#44; it will comfort them and assuage<lb/> their sorrows.  Unto the mourners also&#44; whom this greatly to be deplored<lb/> war has bereaved of dear relatives&#44; grant a power of resignation to<lb/> Thy inscrutable will.  Let them be soothed by the thought of<lb/> a happier hereafter&#44; where no heart aches&#44; and no soul is anguished&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="19"/>
            <p>but calm and joy reigns supreme.  We implore Thee O Most High Omnipotent&#33;<lb/> to vouchsafe the continuance of Thy mercy to the Commonwealth&#44; in<lb/> which our portion has been cast.  Grant it salubrious air&#44; that we<lb/> may breathe perfect health&#44; a fertile soil that we may be<lb/> nourished with abundant food&#59; faithful and vigilant guardians<lb/> that we may lie down in peace&#44; and our repose be not interrupted<lb/> by the clamour of inimical hosts.  And for the needy and hapless<lb/> children&#44; we fervently beseech Thee O Gracious Lord&#33; Hasten to their succour<lb/> in these troublous times.  Let charity&#45;&#45;that heavenly virtue&#45;&#45;strike a<lb/> sympathetic chord in our breasts&#44; and that they will may melt at the sight of<lb/> tribulation that they will may not shrink within themselves&#44; appalled at the pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;spect of reverses&#44; but that committing the future into Thy merciful hand&#44; thy<lb/> creatures will may freely dispesne of their own to their indigent brethren&#44; for&#44; &#34;he that<lb/> hath pity on the poor&#44; lendeth unto Thee&#34; and Thou wilt reward him ten&#45;<lb/>&#45;fold from the treasures of Thy illimitable goodness.  May this be Thy pa&#45;<lb/>&#45;ternal will O God&#44; &#38; bring it soon to pass for the sake of those who confide in Thy<lb/> name and daily await for Thy deliverance.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
