<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF10_9</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1855" source="" attested="yes">1855</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff10_10_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff10_10_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff10_10_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff10_10_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff10_10_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff10_10_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff10_10_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff10_10_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff10_10_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff10_10_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff10_10_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff10_10_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>7 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>A funeral address<lb/>
                1855<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#34;Oh&#33; let me die the death of the righteous&#44; and let my latter end be<lb/> like hers&#34;  Whoever you are&#44; that prompted by veneration<lb/> have gathered around the mortal remains of Esther Hart&#44; come<lb/> nigh unto me&#44; whilst I&#44; with a grievous heart&#44; perform the<lb/> obsequies of one so dear.  Look upon this coffin&#58; in the<lb/> body confined therein&#44; there dwelt a noble soul&#59; there dwelt a<lb/> soul that beat panted for every thing which is holy&#44; good and true.<lb/>  Religion in its purest sense&#44; charity in its widest sphere&#44; knowledge<lb/> of the useful to an unparallelled degree&#44; were the possessions of that<lb/> animating spirit.  Yes&#44; I can unhesitatingly say that Esther<lb/> Hart was religious&#44; but her religion bore no comparison with that<lb/> of such&#44; who scrupulous in the minutest observance&#44; look with<lb/> scorn or hatred upon others that follow a different course&#59; for&#44;<lb/> although she herself implicitly abided&#39; alike by the written and<lb/> by the oral law&#44; yet was she liberal towards the professors<lb/> of other creeds&#44; and tolerant towards her coreligionists who relaxed<lb/> in their duties.  Too late in her life&#45;time&#44; it was my good fortune<lb/> to form her delightful acquaintance&#44; and then her advanced<lb/> age could not suffer her to betake herself as formerly to the<lb/> house of God&#44; but this much I can avouch for&#44; that this<lb/> righteous woman&#44; thrice very day poured forth her prayers<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>before the God of Israel.  Nor were those pious habits<lb/> that she had acquired from her youth&#44; and never abandoned&#44; the<lb/> sole virtue which endeared our deceased friend to every heart&#58; she<lb/> was charitable.  When in the vigor of life&#44; she had watched<lb/> over the bed of the sick&#44; and soothed the last pang of the<lb/> dying.  She had sought the hut of the miserable&#44; and con&#45;<lb/>&#45;veyed thither sustenance and comfort&#44; aye&#44; I have learnt it<lb/> and from an undoubted authority&#44; that she had visited the<lb/> dungeons of those whom society discards as the offscouring of the<lb/> human family&#44; and granted them also relief and counsel.<lb/>  But you have seen my ever&#45;to be lamented friend&#33;  Tell me then&#44;<lb/> was not the pure spirit within brightly reflected on her placid<lb/> countenance&#63;  Can you forget that benevolent smile that<lb/> greeted your approach&#44; and the pressure of the hand that bid<lb/> you farewell&#63;  Those eyes that spoke sympathy for ever sufferer&#44;<lb/> and that forehead which betokened an inquiring and a well regulated<lb/> mind&#63; for&#44; notwithstanding that the one whose loss we moan was<lb/> not conspicuous for literary attainments&#44; she was netherl nevertheless<lb/> endued with abundant sense&#44; and to the very last stage of her<lb/> existence she thirsted for knowledge and drank it with ardour from<lb/> whatsoever source it came.  And to me&#44; she would oftentimes<lb/> propound queries&#44; whose solution required much pondering and study&#59;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>to me&#44; to whom &#40;because she bore me motherly affection&#41; she would allow to<lb/> visit her even when the power of speech had nearly forsaken her.<lb/>  But now Alas&#33; she whom I loved and venerated&#44; she whom you<lb/> all respected&#44; is gone from us.  Her benignant look will no more<lb/> revive our spirits&#44; her suavity of manners&#44; exhibited even at periods<lb/> when sorely tried &#40;for God did severely try his servant&#41; her serene and<lb/> tranquil mien will no more be to our children a pattern worthy<lb/> of imitation.  In vain will we come on the Sabbaths and<lb/> on the days of solemnity to seek her place&#59; we shall not find<lb/> her there&#44; for&#44; the hand which rested upon our heads&#44; death has<lb/> <sic>paralized</sic>&#44; the morl mouth which was wont to pronounce over us<lb/> the threefold blessing mentioned in the law of the Eternal&#44; will com&#45;<lb/>&#45;mune no longer with the living.  A void is felt in our<lb/> hearts&#44; a gloom has been cast over our Community.<lb/></p>
            <p>But if the loss sustained by in the demise of Esther Hart whelms<lb/> her friends with grief&#44; what must be the feelings of her own<lb/> flesh and blood&#44; those&#44; to whom she ever was an indulgent and<lb/> a forgiving parent &#38; for whose sake she sacrificed every gratification which<lb/> the outward world proffers&#63;  How very acute must be the<lb/> pain which at this moment tears their breasts&#63;..........<lb/>  And what will assuage that deep sorrow&#63;  What will console<lb/> them&#63;  Will effect it the thought that their mother had<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> outlived the existence allotted to humanity effect it&#63;  No&#44; for although<lb/> stricken in years&#44; she was the joy&#44; the light&#44; the blessing of<lb/> her household&#59; and that delightful &#38; devoted daughter&#44; whose very breath<lb/> seemed to depend upon the breath of her venerable parent&#44;<lb/> might feel the truth of but could not be tranquillized by<lb/> that mere consideration.  But will perchance a long<lb/> argument on the uncertainty of life&#44; and on the natural exhaust&#45;<lb/>&#45;ion of the human frame&#44; succeed better in wiping away the tears<lb/> that bedew the couch of the desolate children&#63;  No&#44; the<lb/> mind will be be satisfied by the force of that reason&#44; but when<lb/> the heart bleeds&#44; stronger appliances are needful in order to heal<lb/> its wounds.  Come then&#44; thou holy religion&#44; and<lb/> pour thy balmy unction over the mourners.  Speak to them<lb/> of the heavenly habitation where the souls of the righteous are<lb/> imparadised.  Call to their perturbed mind the promise that<lb/> they who fear God before all men&#44; shall delight in immensity<lb/> of goodness in a life of immortality &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#45;&#45;Tell them that that excellent<lb/> mother&#44; that most beloved friend&#44; that kind mistress&#44; whose<lb/> irreparable loss they bewail&#44; is yet alive where death dares not<lb/> enter&#44; that her spirit hovers over them&#44; watches them and<lb/> beckons them to pursue her career&#44; if they desire to obtain<lb/> eternal salvation.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Yes&#44; thou blessed soul of my departed friend&#44; thou art<lb/> surely happy in the contemplation of truth&#59; thou art beatified<lb/> at the footstool of mercy&#59; thou art glorious among the saints&#44;<lb/> because thus have the Sages that thou hast revered expressed<lb/> themselves&#34;  Happy shall be the man that laboreth to understand<lb/> the law&#44; that he may do that which pleaseth his Maker&#59; he that<lb/> enjoyeth a good name in life&#44; and departeth hence with a good<lb/> repute&#44; for&#44; of such a one did Solomon in his wisdom say&#44; that the<lb/> day of the death is better than that of the birth&#34;  Aye&#44; it was<lb/> a glorious day for thee&#44; when <sic>untrammelled</sic> from this mortal coil&#44;<lb/> thou didst take a flight to that abode&#44; where thy reward awaited<lb/> thee.  From thence&#44; gentle spirit of Esther Hart&#44; pray for<lb/> thy children&#44; whom thou hast left inconsolable in this vale<lb/> of misery&#59; pray that they may seek comfort and hope only<lb/> from the Rock of Jacob&#44; the sole Power of salvation&#59; pray that<lb/> the memory of thy piety may prove to them a shield against the<lb/> attack of <sic>hereticks</sic> and unbelievers&#59; pray&#44; as we beseech the Lord<lb/> for thy everlasting repose&#44; that they who bore thee love and<lb/> veneration may deserve a blessing from above.<lb/></p>
            <p>And now thou body senseless clay&#44; which for a long series of years hast been<lb/> the receptacle of an angelic soul&#44; go to thy last destination&#59;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>for&#44; &#34;the dust shall return to the earth as it was&#44; and the spirit<lb/> shall return to God who gave it&#34;&#45;&#45;&#45;&#45;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
