<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF13_13</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1896" source="" attested="yes">1896</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_13_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_13_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_13_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_13_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_13_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_13_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_13_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_13_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_13_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_13_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_13_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff13_13_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>96<lb/></p>
            <p>On the death of Baron<lb/>
                De Hirsch<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>The death of Baron Maurice De Hirsch&#44; does indeed call for expressions<lb/> of heartfelt sorrow.  I hold entertain no doubt&#44; that wherever<lb/> our people congregate&#44; pulpits will now resound echo forth<lb/> with mournful elegies sounds.  I sincerely think hope that<lb/> none will withhold a elegies and eulogies from the great departed&#44;<lb/> because his adherence to the ordinances of his ancestral<lb/> religion&#44; cannot&#44; in all honesty&#44; be declared strong.<lb/>  If it be true&#45;&#45;as I firmly believe&#45;&#45;that charity covers a<lb/> multitude of sins&#44; every mark trace of transgressions<lb/> against the ceremonial Laws marked upon the soul of that<lb/> crowned prince of philanthropy&#44; the merciful hand<lb/> of a merciful God has will have already blotted out.<lb/></p>
            <p>An occasion occurrence did happen once&#44; which forced out a censure<lb/> from the Jewish ministry clergy.  As The For different reasons the report circulated through&#45;<lb/>&#45;out the world and never denied contradicted&#44; irritated for different reasons all minds&#44; but the minds of<lb/> both orthodox and heterodox but Ministers&#44; but had the incautious word which a sensational journal<lb/> attributed to Maurice De Hirsch issued in reality from<lb/> his lips&#44; it still would still deserve a universal pardon.<lb/>  No&#58; The one whose loss we have just lost cause to bemoan&#44; was not the<lb/> promised Messiah&#44; as absurdly announced by the flashes of<lb/> the submarine wires&#44; but he has proved a redeemer from<lb/> misery and from ignorance to myriads of those of his own race.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>To assert that the fountain of his beneficence<lb/> flowed incessantly and with a copiousness un<sic>equalled</sic><lb/> by any single individual is not to deal cannot be ascribed to a desire of indulging in hyperboles.<lb/>  Perhaps True&#44; no private Israelite has perhaps ever succeeded in<lb/> amassing a colossal fortune&#44; approaching any&#44; near that ga&#45; which<lb/> &#45;thered by Maurice De Hirsch gathered but that circumstance<lb/> does not lessen a tittle of the nobility of a mind<lb/> intent f upon eradicating deep rooted evils&#59; redressing<lb/> social wrongs&#44; a mind ever wakeful&#44; mind keeping a vigilant watch on events&#44; that<lb/> might further his plans whereby to purchase freedom for those<lb/> whom tyranny enchains&#44; to open a way to light unto<lb/> them that abide in the gloom of darkness.<lb/></p>
            <p>To so me was given the opportunity of testing the<lb/> generous instincts of the heart&#44; which has unhappily<lb/> ceased to throb.  Nearly nine years ago&#44; a pe&#45;<lb/>&#45;tition addressed to the Baron was brought to my house.<lb/>  The memorialists had written it upon parchment in<lb/> the Hebrew language&#44; and I was asked to add a word of approval.  They sought They asked for the  Assistance<lb/> was sought which might prevent a Russian colony from sink&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing into a state of decay&#59; I was urged &#91;&#63;&#93; charged with Mine was the mis&#45;<lb/>&#45;sion of forwarding the writing to my never to be forgotten school&#45;mate&#45;&#45;Emanuel Felice Veneziani&#45;&#45;the<lb/> trusty almoner of the Baron.  The response to my signature was a<lb/> <sic>a</sic> draft of five thousand dollars in aid of the cause.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>That the results eagerly looked for by myself and others&#44;<lb/> whom I sought appointed as my associates&#44; was fell very short of the<lb/> anticipation&#44; I shall ever regret.  For&#44; I had deemed the deep profound<lb/> interest which Veneziani had exhibited&#44; on reading my endor&#45;<lb/>&#45;sement of the request&#44; as auspicious.  It had at all events reopened<lb/> between us a sweet correspondence&#44; interrupted during a<lb/> series of years.  Alas&#33; that it soon ended&#44; when death tore<lb/> away the good steward from the midst of his labors of love.<lb/>  Bereft of that dear friend of my youth&#44; I then began to exchanges<lb/> letters on the same subject of the Carmel Colony with another son of our people&#44;<lb/> as large&#45;hearted and public spirited as he was learned.<lb/>  I have reference to Isidor Loeb&#44; during many years the<lb/> secretary of the Alliance Israelite Universelle&#59; the Israelite in whose<lb/> ripe judgment the Baron implicitly confided.  In that<lb/> Israelite Hebrew without guile&#44; I met a wise and perfectly polished gentle&#45;<lb/>&#45;man&#59; I valued his letters greatly.  But as if a fatality<lb/> attended my endeavours&#44; Isidor Loeb did not long<lb/> survive Veneziani&#44; nor was Giacomo Montefiore&#44; Veneziani&#39;s<lb/> pro private secretary&#44; who was wont to apprize me<lb/> of the Baron&#39;s benefactions long permitted to walk this<lb/> earth long after his two senior coworkers had<lb/> passed away from it.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>And now the supreme Chief&#44; whose commanded <lb/> Him also appearing it in height and comeliness like the a cedar<lb/> of the Lebanon&#44; the sc scythe of the fell destroyer soon mowed<lb/> down.  And now the supreme chief&#44; who commanded<lb/> legions to prepare the path leading to the conquest of<lb/> humanity&#44; lies lifeless.  The daily papers<lb/> have commended some of the countless deeds of kindness&#44; extend&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing almost illimitably in every region and clime&#44; where<lb/> suffering&#44; affliction&#44; the mortals Jews endure tribulations&#44; but not all know that<lb/> during the Russo&#45;Turkish war &#38; the Franco Prussian war&#59;<lb/> whenever the pitiless sword decimated a population&#44; where&#45;<lb/>&#45;ver widows and orphans multiplied and the earth <lb/>was redeemed with human blood&#44; Veneziani was the<lb/> angel commissioned by his master to go in search<lb/> of the spots&#44; in which the groaning of the hapless could<lb/> be heard&#44; and there quickly to scatter the seeds of comfort.<lb/>  Did pestilence break out stalk abroad&#59; destruction maladies waste at noon&#63;  Maurice De Hirsch<lb/> strove with might to chase it destruction away by the agents of<lb/> his goodness&#44; who supplied timely and effectual<lb/> cures remedies.  Nor was the manifestation of that<lb/> loving kindness cramped by local or racial prejudice.<lb/>  The Mohemmedan and the Christian shared with<lb/> his brother the Jew the advantage of a charity&#44;<lb/> unstinted and universal.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>If the Baron bade did bid his mind bend wetted specially<lb/> on the interest of the scattered members of the<lb/> house of Israel&#44; it was because a cruel world<lb/> denies them the inalienable rights of life&#44; liberty<lb/> and the pursuits of happiness.  A Alike in<lb/> brutal Russia&#44; and in prejudiced Austria&#44; he would<lb/> fain have distributed lavished scores of his golden millions for the creation<lb/> of schools&#44; whence all&#44; irrespective of creed&#44; might<lb/> benefit.  But not to do Cossacks alone good and antise&#45;<lb/>&#45;mites pleasure would he bestow his open unfasten the treasuries<lb/> of his munificence.  The manhood of the Jew<lb/> must be recognized&#44; his feelings must be respected&#59;<lb/> despotic governments must place sheathe into the scabbard<lb/> the sword of Damocles suspended over the heads of<lb/> his powerless defenceless brethren&#44; before he will enrich them those governments with<lb/> his the abundance exuberance of his wealth.  But Let at all events&#44; this<lb/> notable fact ought tender all circumstances to be proclaimed at the sound of ten stringed<lb/> instruments.  The Universal Israelitish Alliance&#44;<lb/> which the Baron first endowed with a millions francs<lb/> to set up schools of learning&#44; schools of industry&#44;<lb/> schools for males and females in the Orient&#44; might annually<lb/> shrink in the extention work of its unabated activity&#44;<lb/> if Maurice De Hirsch did not invariably pr hinder<lb/> that evil&#44; by filling up replenishing the exhausted funds.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>In one aspect of their lives&#44; we may draw a<lb/> comparison between Sir Moses Montefiore the munifi&#45;<lb/>&#45;cent philanthropist of Munich and the far&#45;famed<lb/> Jew English <sic>centennarian</sic> Jew of Ramsgate.  When Sir Moses Montefiore had<lb/> accumulated more than a sufficiency&#44; he counselled<lb/> with his wife&#44; as to his future proceedings.  Ought<lb/> he to embark in farther enterprises in ode order<lb/> to hoard up millions&#44; or should he remain satis&#45;<lb/>&#45;fied with what had been already amply acquired&#44;<lb/> and devote what could be legitimately spared to<lb/> the relief of mankind and the well being fare of Israel&#63;<lb/>  The wise woman&#44; who had imbibed in the parental<lb/> home principles of practical religion&#44; gave her noble<lb/> husband advice.  The habitable globe&#44; knows the<lb/> the issue.  Baron De Hirsch&#39;s wife&#44; born of a Bi&#45;<lb/>&#45;shofshein&#45;&#45;a family noted for its enjoying the reputation of close attachment to<lb/> to the Divine precepts&#44; copied her sister in faith<lb/> of the house of Cohen.  She also&#44; is&#45;&#45;imbued with<lb/> pious sentiments inspired her life&#45;copartner with devotion to charity &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#45;&#45;By the authority of a reliable<lb/> correspondent&#44; I can assert that the <sic>Baronness</sic><lb/> has been a helpmate to the Baron in diverse<lb/> and most efficacious manners.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Not alone did she serve him as amanuensis&#44; when<lb/> innumerable missives of undivulged mercy went were to<lb/> be sent far and wide&#44; but her resignation to the will<lb/> of the God she adores&#44; proved a strong incentive<lb/> to the unparalleled munificence generosity that her made<lb/> her husband famous.  The only child to whom<lb/> she had given birth&#44; she buried untimely.  The<lb/> grief was poignant&#44; and for a period almost soul&#45;<lb/>crushing&#44; but she arose above it the distressful thought and her resignation fortitude<lb/> stimulated acts which mankind can never adequate&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly praise.  We upon earth&#59; we Jews especially&#44;<lb/> cannot avoid lamenting the deep loss sustained&#44; for<lb/> had Maurice De Hirsch been granted the allotted<lb/> term of existence here below&#44; his gigantic under&#45;<lb/>&#45;taking in our behalf aid of his people his subj sublime projects to become to them a redeemer&#44; might<lb/> have reached a goal&#44; magnificently stupendously great.  South<lb/> America and the East of Europe&#44; North Africa<lb/> and Asiatic Turkey might have opened a home of<lb/> security to those of our race&#44; now trodden down<lb/> under the heel of barbarity.  In the book<lb/> whose lines the finger of eternal justice has traced&#44; it<lb/> was decreed that the earth be bereft of the King of philan&#45;<lb/>&#45;thropy.  Let us bow to the inscrutable sentence&#44; with heartfelt for suppli&#45;<lb/>&#45;cations for the paradisual heavenly joys of the great great departed and the consolation of<lb/> his weeping widow.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
