<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF17_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff17_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff17_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff17_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff17_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff17_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff17_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff17_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff17_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff17_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff17_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff17_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff17_1_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>On Vayakel<lb/>
                Shaped and molded<lb/>
                From one of Solis Della Torre<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  Israelites have been charged with want of<lb/> love for the aesthetic&#44; with unfitness for the liberal arts.<lb/>  Our coreligionists of modern times have disproved the charge.<lb/>  They have made palpable facts stand forth&#44; confront and<lb/> shame the imputation accusers.  But even the history of antiquity<lb/> shows the accusation imputation to be false groundless&#44; or&#44; at least&#44; too sweeping.<lb/>  Let us before proceeding further&#44; premise a just remark.<lb/>  All nations have not been widowed with received from nature the same aptitudes&#44;<lb/> any more than all individuals with the same disposition and<lb/> tendency.  All could not manifest an equal fondness for<lb/> arts and sciences&#44; or the capacity to cultivate these with<lb/> equal success&#44; and contribute in an equal manner to<lb/> the <sic>developping</sic> of civilization.  Providence intended all<lb/> peoples of the earth&#44; to participate in the great under&#45;<lb/>&#45;taking&#59; but each was assigned a special task&#44; so that<lb/> by the combination of separate efforts the social edifice<lb/> might be raised high.<lb/></p>
            <p>The ancients also had their shares in the admirable work.<lb/>  Some were apportioned the fine arts&#44; as the Greeks&#59; some<lb/> the formation of civil governments&#44; as the Romans&#44; and<lb/> others&#44; the experimental solution of political problems&#44; as the Italian<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Republics of old.  Israel was given from the outset<lb/> that part which joins all into one&#44; and crowns the<lb/> &#40;complete&#41; labor.  Israel was given Religion for its task&#59;<lb/> religion&#45;&#45;which&#44; as the name denotes&#44; is&#44; or rather ought to<lb/> be&#44; a common bond of union among the children of the<lb/> Universal Creator.  All other parts in the work&#44; became<lb/> of secondary importance&#44; not to be set aside entirely&#44;<lb/> for they are powerful agencies in promoting civili&#45; human pro&#45;<lb/>zation gress&#44; but to be exercised only so far as they do not<lb/> interfere with the main task&#44; to be performed in up&#45;<lb/>&#45;holding the Unity&#44; and which must be kept steadily<lb/> in view.<lb/></p>
            <p>But another remark will be appropriate on this sub&#45;<lb/>&#45;ject.  Fine arts&#44; in order to flourish must have op&#45;<lb/>&#45;portunities and facilities.  Our ancestors were seldom<lb/> afforded the state of <sic>tranquillity</sic> necessary for an assi&#45;<lb/>&#45;duous application to them.  The infancy of our people<lb/> was spent in slavery&#44; and in wandering through deserts&#44;<lb/> then to be trained in a crucible the way of trials for its future destiny.<lb/>  The opening of its political life was almost anar&#45;<lb/>&#45;chical&#44; without Union and Unity&#44; as in the days of the<lb/> Judges&#44; each doing what <sic>what</sic> pleased in his eyes&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>and hence exposing the nation to the aggression of strangers.<lb/>  When the consolidation of the tribes took place&#44; it lasted<lb/> only during the reigns of three kings&#59; the first of which<lb/> was of short continuance&#59; the second stormy through<lb/> frequent wars&#44; so that David the leading spirit was not<lb/> allowed to build a structure in honor of God&#44; because his<lb/> hands had shed too much blood.  The third may solely be<lb/> &#91;&#63;&#93; called a quiete quiet period&#59; the golden age of<lb/> Jewish history&#44; when all sat under their vines and fig&#45;trees&#44;<lb/> with none to make them afraid.  But soon the un&#45;<lb/>&#45;fortunate division occurred&#44; to be followed by intestine<lb/> quarrels&#44; and finally by the Babylonian exile.<lb/>  At the restoration&#44; the political condition had not improved<lb/> very materially.  Tributary to Persia&#44; to Macedonia&#44;<lb/> to the Egypt of the Ptolemies&#44; to Rome&#59; struggling<lb/> against the latter for independence&#44; the stay of<lb/> our people in Palestine was not amidst the enjoy&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment of peace.  Then came the long and wide spread<lb/> dispersion&#44; and the horrors of the middle&#45;ages&#44; when<lb/> with rare exceptions&#44; the existence of Israel hung upon a thread. with<lb/> rare exceptions&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>And yet note the remarkable fact&#44; notwithstand&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing so many the untold vicissitudes&#44; so the many obstacles&#44; an&#45;<lb/>&#45;cient Hebrews far from being strangers to a sense<lb/> of the beautiful in the arts&#44; showed considerable<lb/> fondness for it&#44; and no mean knowledge thereof.<lb/>  The tabernacle erected in the wilderness&#59; Solomon&#39;s<lb/> temple&#44; and that of Herod&#44; said to have surpassed<lb/> the former in architectural grandeur&#44; bear testimony<lb/> to artistic capacities of not little value.  And<lb/> who does not know the skill displayed by our pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;genitors in music and poetry specially in the lyric&#44;<lb/> as evinced in the sublime poems David&#39;s outpourings&#44; rehearsed in<lb/> the Church and the Mosque not less than in the<lb/> synagogue&#44; and as proved from by the name of numerous<lb/> instruments recorded throughout Holy Writ&#63;<lb/>  We might venture further&#44; and assert that the<lb/> Cherubim hovering above the ark of the covenant&#44;<lb/> and several figures in the sanctuary at Jerusalem&#44; as<lb/> the twelve brazen oxen bearing the molten sea&#44; would<lb/> justify the supposition that our ancestors could also<lb/> handle the chisel and the pencil&#59; but candour forces<lb/> us to confess that we have no positive proofs evidence of their<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>acquaintance with Sculpture and painting.  Nor can<lb/> they&#44; by reason of that&#44; be accused of unfitness<lb/> for the aesthetic&#44; when it is remembered that the<lb/> art of making figures in marble or upon canvass&#44;<lb/> had its origin in heathen religions.  The master&#45;pieces<lb/> of Grecian artificers&#44; were inspired by pagan super&#45;<lb/>&#45;stitions.  While families lived in rough cabins&#44; they<lb/> would raise superb edifices&#44; where the images of war&#45;<lb/>&#45;riors drawn in colours&#44; or cut in stones were paid homage<lb/> to.  What wonder then that the Hebrews preferred<lb/> to cultivate the arts which might enhance the<lb/> service of the one incorporeal God&#44; and they cared little<lb/> for those connected with polytheism&#63;  the prohi&#45;<lb/>&#45;bition of representing the Almighty under any form&#44;<lb/> banished almost entirely Sculpture and painting almost &#91;&#63;&#93; from<lb/> among Israel of yore.<lb/>    A believe uncompromisingly spir&#45;<lb/>&#45;ritual and moral&#44; discountenanced what might have<lb/> given rise to the deification of material objects&#44; or<lb/> to sensual feelings.  But the fear of such a<lb/> result&#44; gradually abated&#44; when heathenism and its<lb/> debaucheries&#44; began to lose the powerful hold it once<lb/> had upon the mind of men&#59; and when the Jewish<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>worship itself was greatly simplified&#44; it being<lb/> reduced to the reciting of prayers and the explaining<lb/> of the Scriptures&#44; in places of no great architectural<lb/> <sic>pretentions</sic>.  A perceptible change was<lb/> then wrought.  To a natural incentive which<lb/> leads to the cultivation of all the liberal arts&#44; as<lb/> refining the taste&#44; and imparting a high tone to the<lb/> intellect&#44; was added the approval given by Holy<lb/> Writ.  For&#44; in alluding to different pursuits<lb/> needed for the building of the Tabernacle&#44; it styles<lb/> the individuals capable of performing labors which<lb/> demanded required ingenuity and skill&#44; men gifted with<lb/> a divinely illumined mind.  Thus we read in<lb/> the section of this Sabbath &#34;Moses said to the child&#45;<lb/>&#45;ren of Israel&#58; see&#44; the Lord has called by name Be&#45;<lb/>&#45;zalel son of Huri&#44; son of Hur of the tribes of Judah&#44; and<lb/> has filled him with a spirit of wisdom&#44; with knowledge<lb/> and understanding and with ability for every work&#44;<lb/> to devise new designs and execute them in gold<lb/> silver&#44; copper&#44; and in setting precious stones&#44; in<lb/> carving wood&#44; in doing all sorts of <sic>ingenius</sic> labor.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>In this language does the book of books proclaim<lb/> the arts a heavenly creation.  And how could<lb/> genius and industry be set on a higher plane&#44; than by<lb/> receiving God&#39;s declaration that they are inspired by Him&#63;  Nay&#58;<lb/> by in ascribing the invention of tools and of instruments&#59; of<lb/> music and of agriculture&#44; to the remotest days even before Noah&#44;<lb/> the Bible signifies their great worth&#44; as objects of use&#45;<lb/>&#45;fulness and refinement.<lb/>
                But if the religion of the Hebrews honored every art&#44; state<lb/> regulations made the exercise of many of the arts a<lb/> necessity.  In fact&#44; the Constitution being based upon<lb/> Agrarian laws&#45;&#45;as each family owned a tract of land&#44;<lb/> which was inalienable&#45;&#45;it followed that the culture of<lb/> the ground must have been diligently attended to.  Now&#44;<lb/> our progenitors could not have carried on their usual<lb/> pursuits without the aid of many implements&#44; to plough&#44;<lb/> to level the soil&#44; to cut the grass&#44; to <sic>winow</sic> the rain&#44; to<lb/> press the grapes&#44; to crush the olives&#44; nor could they<lb/> dispense with the manufacturing of weapons of de&#45;<lb/>fence against hostile tribes surrounding them.<lb/>  So that of national poetry reflects the character of a<lb/> people&#44; and the figures of speech employed by the poets writers<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>represent give us an insight into its public and private life&#44; the mention often<lb/> made of a diversity of instruments tools&#44; manifests a con&#45;<lb/>&#45;stant and steady application to the arts.<lb/></p>
            <p>Let none therefore repeat the heresy&#44; that Jewish hands<lb/> were not shaped to do work of mechanical skill&#59; to<lb/> wield the square and compass&#59; that an inventive<lb/> genius in sculpture and painting has not fallen<lb/> to our shares.  For admitting that a vast deal<lb/> produced by the chisel and by the pencil would ill&#45;<lb/>become the adorers of one God&#44; and the adherents of a<lb/> law of purity&#44; yet much is left in which Israelites<lb/> could <sic>excell</sic>&#44; without clinging to commerce or even<lb/> to a professional career.  Would that my<lb/> American coreligionists had loved traffic less and the<lb/> aesthetics more&#33;  They might not have <sic>ammassed</sic><lb/> wealth as readily&#44; but they would not have lost it<lb/> as quickly.  I could not better illustrate what I<lb/> have endeavoured to prove than by citing also the<lb/> portion of the prophets designated for this peculiar Sab&#45;<lb/>&#45;bath&#59; for&#44; there&#44; as we as in the section of the Pentateuch&#44;<lb/> we are shown our fathers engaged in a variety of callings&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>which demanded proficiency in the mechanical and<lb/> in the liberal arts.  May the time soon arrive&#44;<lb/> when our youths will learn the dignity of labor&#44;<lb/> will appreciate the glory of rising by natural<lb/> talents devoted to the <sic>developping</sic> of the beautiful&#44;<lb/> when they will intensely feel that the acquiring<lb/> of excellency in the domains of the intellectual&#44; brings affords<lb/> greater and more lasting contentment than the<lb/> accumulation of gold.<lb/></p>
            <p>And may like the righteous king Joash&#44; who<lb/> incited his subjects to employ their capacities to<lb/> a noble end may those who are loftily stationed&#44; urge<lb/> others in a humbler circumstances&#44; to exercise<lb/> their abilities to the honor of their faith&#44; and to the<lb/> advancement and permanence of the worship of<lb/> the One God.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
