<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF3_13</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_13_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_13_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_13_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_13_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_13_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_13_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_13_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_13_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_13_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_13_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_13_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_13_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>13th lecture on post&#45;biblical history<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  In the series of short post&#45;biblical lectures&#44;<lb/> that I delivered at different intervals&#44; during last<lb/> winter&#44; I had arrived at the period&#44; in which<lb/> the memorable events&#44; that we have just celebrated&#44;<lb/> took place.  I acknowledge my vanity.  As I<lb/> intend leaving those lectures&#44; wit ha few more of<lb/> writings of my pen behind me&#44; in the hope that<lb/> they may prove one day of some use to Philadel&#45;<lb/>&#45;phia Israelites&#44; I had designed resuming my<lb/> course last Sabbath.  I believed that the season<lb/> would make it then fitting to enter into details<lb/> about the characters of the venerable priest of the<lb/> house of Hashmona&#239;&#44; or Asmonean&#44; and his five<lb/> heroic sons.  But on reflection&#44; I changed my<lb/> mind.  I remembered that the main incidents<lb/> that gave origin to the Hanuccah festivity&#44; are<lb/> familiar to all my hearers.  I therefore feared<lb/> that a minute account might be wearisome.<lb/>  Should&#44; however&#44; kind hands undertake hereafter<lb/> to collect any of my published or unpublished writings&#44;<lb/> and shape them properly to give them permanence&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>many lectures on the Macabees will be found<lb/> among my papers&#44; wherewith to form a connecting<lb/> historical link between what has been said before<lb/> and what will follow.<lb/></p>
            <p>Still&#44; without speaking more particularly of the<lb/> difficulties which Judah and his brothers grap&#45;<lb/>&#45;pled with and overcame after their father&#39;s<lb/> death&#59; of the wars they waged and the victories they<lb/> won&#44; I wish to leave a special record of the end&#44;<lb/> which those benefactors of our people met&#44; in<lb/> the pursuit of the noblest cause.<lb/></p>
            <p>The battle of Bethsura manifested the intense<lb/> earnestness of patriotism.  The Syro&#45;Grecians&#44; mar&#45;<lb/>&#45;shalled by a general of consummate skill&#44; had<lb/> brought upon the field a <sic>redoutable</sic> army.<lb/>  It displayed a hundred thousand infantry&#44;<lb/> twenty thousand cavalry&#44; and thirty two elephants&#44;<lb/> from the towered back of which <sic>combattants</sic><lb/> hurled their javelins with a fatal aim.<lb/>  Suddenly&#44; one man is seen to break from<lb/> the Judean ranks&#44; and approach the hugest<lb/> of those monstrous animals.  He has opened<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>himself a way in the midst of troops&#44; which<lb/> his sword mows down like grass&#44; and&#44; crouching&#44;<lb/> stabs the hideous beast&#44; and is crushed under<lb/> its ponderous body.  Who was that soldier<lb/> that so rashly went going in search of a certain<lb/> death&#63;  Why did he seek it in so strange a<lb/> manner&#63;...No rashness prompted that act.<lb/>  Love of Liberty impelled it.  In the veins of that<lb/> soldier ran the blood of Mattathias&#44; the priest and<lb/> and champion of his race.  Eleazar erroneously<lb/> thought that the elephant of immense size&#44; whose<lb/> trappings bore royal devices&#44; held on its back the<lb/> young Ruler of the Power which oppressed Israel.<lb/>  Samson&#45;like he would cause by his fall a destruction havoc<lb/> among his enemies.  To die that Judea be free&#44;<lb/> and Judaism safe&#44; was the irresistible impulse<lb/> of that brave Asmonean.  He of the fine va&#45;<lb/>liant brothers&#44; was the first to lay his life upon the<lb/> altar of his faith&#44; as a voluntary offering.<lb/></p>
            <p>What Eleazar longed for&#44; Judah&#44; the indomitable Mac&#45;<lb/>&#45;cabee&#44; finally gained.  The land of the patriarchs<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>after having been convulsed by the agonies of a<lb/> threatened extinction&#44; enjoyed for a while com&#45;<lb/>&#45;parative ease.  But a fierce storm unexpectedly<lb/> burst upon it.  Our lion hearted deliverer was<lb/> then ill prepared to weather it.  Three thousand<lb/> men only were at his disposal&#44; when a fresh army<lb/> led by Bacchides marched on Jerusalem&#44; spreading terror<lb/> and woes as it advanced.  Defeat stared the those<lb/> fighting thousands in the face.  They could not be<lb/> stirred up fro the unequal strife.  Judah was<lb/> implored to spare himself for better times&#44; and seek<lb/> safety by flight.  &#34;Never shall the rising sun behold<lb/> so inglorious a sight&#34; answered the fearless warrior.<lb/>  &#34;Never shall it behold an Asmonean showing the<lb/> foe his back.&#34;  If this be my last struggle&#44; posterity<lb/> shall not say that I have stained by cowardice<lb/> the record of an illustrious past.&#34;  Eight hun&#45;<lb/>&#45;dred clung to our hero.  Desperate but terrific<lb/> is the onslaught.  The daring few rush on the<lb/> right wing of the opposing army&#44; break its centre&#44;<lb/> and force it to a hasty retreat.  Judah and his<lb/> phalanx performs deeds of prodigious valour&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>but the left wing has discovered the disorder with which<lb/> the right was thrown.  Quickly it closes upon the<lb/> Maccabee&#59; many a enemy lies at his feet.  At<lb/> length&#44; overpowered by number&#44; but still grasping<lb/> his sword he falls where his precious blood crimsoned<lb/> the soil he gallantly defended.<lb/></p>
            <p>Profane history has handed down names&#44; to which all<lb/> instinctively pay homage.  WE bow to the memory of an Aristides and a Cincinnatus&#44; of a Robert<lb/> Bruce and a Gustavuas Adof Adolphus&#44; but our Judah<lb/> claims the highest honor&#44; because his prowess hammered<lb/> down the citadel of Falsehood&#59; his loyalty to Truth<lb/> rescued a nation from debauching idolatry.  Judah<lb/> deserved eternity on earth&#44; and a living monument has<lb/> been reared to him in the hearts of the eternal people he<lb/> benefitted.  His body&#44; recovered by his surviving brothers&#44;<lb/> received interment in the burial place of the noble sire&#44;<lb/> amidst the tea sobs and tears of grateful myriads.<lb/></p>
            <p>But the cause for which the bravest of the Asmoneans<lb/> sacrificed his existence&#44; could not be lost&#44; so long as any<lb/> of Mattathias&#39; sons lived.  Jonathan assumed the command&#44;<lb/> and rallied the patriots to the defence of country and creed.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Discreet and full of caution&#44; he perceived that he<lb/> was unable&#44; for a time&#44; to measure arms with the<lb/> Syrians.  He therefore withdrew to a place of safety&#44;<lb/> and as an act of prudence&#44; sent&#44; by means of his<lb/> brother Johanan&#44; the military equipage and baggage&#44;<lb/> to the safe&#45;keeping of a friendly tribe of Arabs.<lb/>  Johanan led the troops&#44; which conveyed those im&#45;<lb/>&#45;plements of war&#44; through the wilderness.  They<lb/> were proceeding straight towards their destination&#44; when<lb/> a horde of hostile Arabs surrounded them in a man&#45;<lb/>&#45;ner which precluded a manly resistance.  The free&#45;<lb/>&#45;booter slaughtered every person&#44; and plundered all<lb/> property.  Thus another member of an immortal<lb/> family&#44; stamped his name with the seal of mar&#45;<lb/>&#45;tyrdom to patriotic duty.  But his blood did not<lb/> remain unavenged.  Jonathan vowed to make<lb/> the marauding tribe pay dearly for their treachery.<lb/>  As they had done to his brother&#44; so would he deal<lb/> with them.  Lying in ambush&#44; he wished upon a<lb/> large party&#44; who escorted a princess to the city of<lb/> the prince&#44; her wedded lord&#59; cut it off&#44; and seized a<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>rich booty.  The martial spirit&#44; &#43;<lb/> not all the military genius&#44; of Judah&#44; shone upon<lb/> Jonathan.  Associated to the wise&#45;hearted Simon&#44; be<lb/> compelled victory to perch on his banner.  The faith&#45;<lb/>ful Judeans he inspired with fresh vigour&#59; the faith&#45;<lb/>&#45;less he humbled to the dust.  He rooted the Syro&#45;<lb/>Grecians and shamed Jewish Grecianists.  He challenged<lb/> respect and made veteran generals own that valor<lb/> dwelt yet with the descendants of David.  He studied<lb/> opportunities&#44; and with masterly ability lay laid hold<lb/> thereof in the interest of his land and his people.<lb/>  Jonathan ought to have died full of years upon a bed<lb/> of honored <sic>tranquillity</sic>.  But fate decided otherwise.<lb/>  A fouler treachery than that which had set sent Johanan<lb/> to an untimely grave&#44; put an end to the life of<lb/> Jonathan.  He&#44; naturally sagacious&#44; and exceedingly<lb/> chary&#44; was entrapped in a snare which Perfidy had<lb/> spread out.  I Tryphon&#44; an unscrupulous<lb/> chief&#44; who had raised on the throne of Syria a young<lb/> son of his former master&#44; with the ulterior motive<lb/> to dispossess him of it to his and make himself king&#44; re&#45;<lb/>quested an interview with our hero.  Jonathan<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>agreed&#44; but he arrived at the appointed place with forty<lb/> thousand soldiers under his orders.  Tryphon was not<lb/> prepared for that significant greeting&#59; Hence he simulated<lb/> friendship.  His tokens of regard were royal.  He lavished<lb/> gifts&#44; and promised a surrendering of fortresses garrisoned<lb/> hitherto by Syrian troops.  He asserted that to settle<lb/> that amicably&#44; he had requested a personal interchange<lb/> of thoughts.  As a pledge of sincerity&#44; he invited the<lb/> Asmonean to accompany him with a small retinue&#44; as<lb/> far as Ptolema&#252;s&#44; or Acco&#44; promising to return that sea&#45;<lb/>&#45;port town to the Judeans.  The deception proved but too<lb/> successful.  Jonathan believed.  Dismissing his soldiers&#44;<lb/> he chose a thousand as an escort and entered Ptolema&#239;s.<lb/>  Fatal error&#33;  The gates were shut on him&#44; and<lb/> not one of his thousand men was left to tell that their<lb/> mighty leader lay enchained in a dungeon.  But Nevertheless&#44;<lb/> the dire event soon spread like a wild fire&#44; and every<lb/> patriot grasped the hilt of his sow sword.  How to avenge<lb/> the execrable wrong&#44; without exposing the beloved defender<lb/> of his race to an ignominious death&#44; was the harassing<lb/> thought.  A nation grieved to the core and perplexed&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>turned their eyes to a great <sic>counsellor</sic>.  Simon&#44; whom<lb/> the aged father had declared a first in wisdom&#44; was<lb/> sought after.  While Judah leaded a small but<lb/> invincible band of fellow believers to the field of honor&#44;<lb/> Simon had stood as his brother&#39;s adviser.  While<lb/> Jonathan scattered the adversaries of Israel like<lb/> chaff&#44; Simon had lent his sabre and his pen.<lb/>  Now that the hour had struck&#44; when he must sum&#45;<lb/>&#45;mon his arm and his intellect to the salvation of Judaism&#44;<lb/> Simon the Asmonean was not found wanting.  Addressing his<lb/> compatriots&#44; he promised fealty to the grand cause<lb/> for which his sire and his four brothers had freely<lb/> bled.  Then&#44; as an earnest of his determination to<lb/> thrust back the wretchedly vile Typhon&#44; and&#44; rescue<lb/> Jonathan&#44; he took vigorous measures to fortify and<lb/> guard all assailable points.<lb/></p>
            <p>In my next lecture of the course&#44; I shall refer to what<lb/> followed that soul&#45;stirring event&#44; and&#44; briefly describing<lb/> the administrative abilities and success of Simon&#44; I<lb/> shall narrate his tragic end. and the character of<lb/> his successor.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
