<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF3_8</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1896" source="" attested="yes">1896</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_8_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_8_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_8_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_8_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_8_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_8_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_8_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_8_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_8_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_8_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_8_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_8_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>96<lb/></p>
            <p>Anniversary of my 45th year<lb/>
                with the Cong. M. I.<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Whatever Philadelphia papers may have written&#44; or<lb/> represented in connection with in effigy&#44; regarding the completion of the forty<lb/> fifth year of my services to the Mickve Israel Con&#45;<lb/>&#45;gregation&#44; did not emanate&#44; from was not prompted by the least intimation<lb/> given by myself received from me.  At no time&#44; on no occasion have<lb/> I considered it of the slightest interest to importance that my constituents&#44;<lb/> and much less to the Hebrew community at large&#44; to should<lb/> learn what concerns my and person or my immediate household.<lb/>  If notwithstanding my taciturnity habitual silence on that point&#44;<lb/> that which I what I would prefer to have concealed&#44; was revealed at different times periods&#44;<lb/> of my career&#44; the fault must be sought looked for outside of my own self.<lb/>  person. However&#44; It is not an assumed virtue that draws<lb/> out an open confession this morning day&#44; which may be the<lb/> last anniversary of my induction into office the ministry<lb/> My brethren may as well know me once for all.  Circumstances<lb/> have played upon my nature an ungracious trick.<lb/>  From the very earliest days years of my life&#44; which I can recall&#44; I<lb/> remember myself a shy&#44; easily scared creatures&#44; trem&#45;<lb/>&#45;bling all over at the idea of being brought forward&#59;<lb/> preferring solitariness to merry company.  Perhaps&#44;<lb/> I learned discovered rather too early soon the narrow range<lb/> of my capacities&#44; and I  mistrusted them very greatly&#44; so<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>as to prevent their so that they might not attempting the impossible.<lb/>  Yet&#44; contradictory as it surely is&#44; I dared study for a voca&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion&#44; demanding uncommon abilities.  But could I set<lb/> my face directly in opposition to the will of the one&#44; who<lb/> made the anxious request&#63;  In my boyhood&#44; the thought of<lb/> raising a son to in become a rabbi&#44; was joy to a mo&#45;<lb/>&#45;ther&#39;s heart.  The merit secured in the other world&#44;<lb/> would be beyond surpass all measure&#59; such was the hope.  Never mind about<lb/> the weight of the brains.  Experience may have<lb/> taught mothers that it was not singular in my mother mine<lb/> to imagine our her son equal to any in mental calibre.<lb/>  I have often detected the same weakness elsewhere&#44; and I did not<lb/> undeceive a parent who saw a prodigy&#44; where only<lb/> mediocrity existed.  However&#44; I fought against odds.<lb/>  I studied under tremendous drawbacks.  Filial af&#45;<lb/>&#45;fection on one side&#59; poverty in the other&#44; were the<lb/> incentives.  The anxiety eagerness to be of use&#44; mostly to<lb/> my mother&#39;s children&#44; lent a will with which I had<lb/> not believed to progress credited myself.  When scarcely of age&#44;<lb/> I allowed myself to be was persuaded into accepting<lb/> the invitation of an ancient and respectable<lb/> Sephardic congregation to try for the position<lb/> of associate Hazan.  It was The venture proved a failure&#44; and I returned home&#44; rather crest&#45;fallen.  But again&#44; Again the necessity of<lb/> assisting those whom I deemed entitled to my assistance&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>held my timidity under control&#44; and I was seen<lb/> once more on the banks of the Thames. agreeably<lb/> to the advice of some Italian Jews in London&#44; who were my advisers.<lb/>  They fancied that I might teach Hebrew in a congre&#45;<lb/>&#45;gational Orphan School.  How I could ever act<lb/> so rashly&#44; is a wonder inexplicable to this very day.<lb/>  Without the knowledge of a word of English&#44; I pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;sumed to instruct English born in the English translation of<lb/> the Bible. in their own vernacular.  Truly&#59; necessity<lb/> is the mother of inventions.  I must earn a livelihood.  With the aid of a diction&#45;<lb/>&#45;ary and a grammar&#44; I succeeded in gaining a smat&#45;<lb/>&#45;tering that answered my purpose for sometime&#44;<lb/> that is&#44; till towards the end of the year 1850.<lb/>  For&#44; then an English Jewess&#44; who had visited her<lb/> married daughter in Philadelphia&#44; having gone back to<lb/> London sent for me.  She inquired whether I would apply for the<lb/> situation which I now occupy.  I answered nega&#45;<lb/>&#45;tively&#44; but again Italian friends were urged urgent&#44;<lb/> and I finally submitted.  The task undertaken was comparatively<lb/> easy&#44; as far as the requisites in the contract into which I entered<lb/> with the Congregation Mickv&#232; Israel.  Even if Even<lb/> the times&#44; when I was expected to ascend this sacred<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>desk&#44; to lead my brethren in prayer&#44; were fewer<lb/> than I have made them&#44; and regular t lectures were rarely not<lb/> delivered expected looked for nor asked for.  In fact&#44; my predecessor in office&#44; who&#44;<lb/> I think&#44; introduced pulpit preaching in America<lb/> among Israelites&#44; spoke only at intervals&#59; but<lb/> he was master of the situation&#44; and I in all reality&#44;<lb/> was unused to public speaking.  The frightful question then arose.  To continue or discontinue the delivering of a discourse.  To abolish what<lb/> he had been successfully begun&#44; would have been was regarded by me a step<lb/> backward and a reflection on me and all who such as had<lb/> seen fit to entrust me with the a holy charge.<lb/>  So I compelled failing courage to hold me up&#44; but though<lb/> I read word for word from the manuscript&#44; the effort caused a trouble and<lb/> trepidation.  I am not astonished at having<lb/> been told&#44; that what an attendant at the Cherry<lb/> Street Synagogue&#44; more candid than generous&#44;<lb/> had said&#44; that she was of opinion that I ought not to attempt what<lb/> she on her part could not make out.  Perhaps&#44; if she my departed sister in faith were<lb/> now among the living&#44; she might change her opinion.<lb/>  But I have reasons to surmise&#44; that she was not<lb/> alone in holding such entertaining unfavorable views of my preaching.  But Still&#44; I may<lb/> make lo bold to say that time has wrought<lb/> some changes for the better.  If I cannot boast<lb/> like Caesar&#44; that &#34;I came&#44; I saw and conquered&#34;<lb/> I may say&#44; that I guarded against a retrogressions.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>But it may pertinently be asked&#44; what means this<lb/> rigamarole of mine as she a chosen the address of chosen for the forty fifth<lb/> anniversary of my ministry.  Well&#59; it means that<lb/> I never overrated my powers&#44; and that therefore to<lb/> represent me as &#34;a force in the Community&#44;&#34; as an &#34;a brilliant<lb/> intellectual&#34; athlete&#44; as a &#34;a versatile linguist&#44;&#34; and I know not<lb/> what else&#44; is to impose upon people&#39;s credulity.<lb/>  It means that&#44; as I would decline post mortem eulogies&#44;<lb/> &#45;&#45;generally fulsome&#45;&#45;<lb/> I think it unfair to pronounce antemortem exag&#45;<lb/>&#45;gerated laudations.  Yet&#44; Nevertheless I do rejoice to be in the loving<lb/> thought of my brothers and sisters in faith Israel&#44; and<lb/> especially in the thought of those whom I try to<lb/> serve conscientiously.  I am not indifferent to<lb/> praise&#44; for&#44; then I would be not be human.  The<lb/> appreciation of my exertions in any direction&#44; is<lb/> a <sic>stimulous</sic> to proceed onward and upwards.  It<lb/> is solace amidst disappointments&#59; the removal upraising of<lb/> depressed spirits&#44; when depressed&#44; either through ministerially and or domestically trials.<lb/>  May I always win that gift from the children of the<lb/> stock of Abraham&#44; who share with me&#44; creed&#44; history<lb/> and destiny.  It may sound very liberal<lb/> to advertise to the world&#44; that we embrace in our<lb/> activity&#44; all human speaking beings&#44; Jews&#44; Christians&#44; Negros<lb/> Indoos&#59; that we prepare for every one a home of delight&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>food for the body&#44; food for the mind&#44; a study of the ethics of human equality &#38; fraternity.<lb/>  During my long stay in this city of my pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;ference&#44; Philadelphians may have had occasions to<lb/> be consumed ascertain discover that I harbour no prejudice&#44; against re&#45;<lb/>&#45;ligions and races different from Judaism and the Jews&#59;<lb/> that I honor respect honesty of conviction wherever met&#59; but neither my<lb/> ability nor my mind physical nor my mental ability is equal to the far reaching<lb/> task contemplated by a singularly self relying<lb/> rabbi.  If they Were they I even equal to that athletic exploit I would con&#45;<lb/>&#45;sider the undertaking it altogether beyond the line of my duty.<lb/>  I live among my poeple&#44; work for my<lb/> people&#44; and yearn for the good will of my peo&#45;<lb/>&#45;ple.  If more is conceded to me&#44; I value it<lb/> highly&#44; but I do not seek it.  This&#44; how&#45;<lb/>&#45;ever&#44; I do seek&#44; a proof that four decades and<lb/> a half of steady labor have <sic>yeilded</sic> some durable fruits.<lb/>  Very many have are they whom I have taught&#59; I could not reckon<lb/> the number of individuals whom I have endeavoured<lb/> to cheer in affliction&#44; to heighten home joys in<lb/> days of gladness&#44; to give counsel of peace and<lb/> reconciliation&#44; but the reward which I most longed<lb/> for I have missed.  It is to have lend multitudes to the<lb/> Sanctuary of the Lord&#44; to have inspired multitudes with<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>unabated attachment&#44; for to the culture of Hebrew&#44; culture&#44; to promote have created<lb/> a sense of solidarity which is attended with a uni&#45;<lb/>&#45;versal affiliation to every object having promotive of the wel&#45;<lb/>&#45;fare of scattered Israel.  Many that I had photo&#45;<lb/>&#45;graphed as it were&#44; on my mental vision as future pillars<lb/> of the Judaic edifice&#44; withdrew their support.  Many&#44;<lb/> too many&#44; whom I had esteemed as public spirited&#44;<lb/> have preceded me to the land of silence&#44; but a vast<lb/> number of their offspring&#44; who could speak and act<lb/> well&#44; have deserted the cause espoused by the fathers&#44; so that the ances&#45;<lb/>&#45;tral faith faring whilom standing comparatively well<lb/> in this city of our affection&#44; is allowed to be dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;figured beyond recognition.&#44; and Nay&#44; those who have deformed it secure unwonted honors are<lb/> paid to men who deform it&#44; as enlightened bene&#45; They are extravagantly remunerated as factors of communal progress.<lb/> &#45;factors  Yet&#44; I will not despair&#44; a few are left<lb/> to champion legitimate Judaism.  I pray this day&#44;<lb/> &#45;&#45;which is to me a day of memorial&#45;&#45;for their continuance of such as representatives of an intelligent<lb/> Conservatism.  That It is the citadel which we have built.<lb/>  Let us raise on upon it our ensign &#34;the hope of Israel&#34;.  In<lb/> letters of fire the words of the prophet shall be<lb/> emblazoned on its folds &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> O Adona&#239;&#44; Thou art the Hope of Israel&#44; all<lb/> who go astray from Thee&#44; shall be covered with clothed in<lb/> shame&#34;; but the defenders of the Torah shall wear a the mouth of<lb/> glory.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
