<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF5_7</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_7_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_7_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_7_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_7_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_7_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_7_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_7_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_7_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_7_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_7_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_7_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_7_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>
                An address on the Parasha &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Dear Brethren&#33;  The section of the Pentateuch which we have perused this mor&#45;<lb/>&#45;ning&#44; does not offer passages&#44; that require elucidation&#59; for&#44; whether it be<lb/> understood from the original&#44; or from the vernacular rendering&#44; the<lb/> context is sufficiently obvious.  Nevertheless&#44; let no one imagine that<lb/> because it simply contains narratives&#44; the importance of which appears<lb/> but secondary in the chain of biblical history&#44; that we cannot draw<lb/> therefrom useful lessons.  To us&#44; who justly pride ourselves in our<lb/> patriarchal descent&#44; the demeanour exhibited by our pious fore&#45;fathers&#44;<lb/> even in usual private occurrences&#44; must be of national example.<lb/></p>
            <p>In fact&#44; it is my firm conviction&#44; that the inspired writers have<lb/> given place in Holy Writ to events&#44; which&#44; at first sight&#44; might<lb/> be judged unessential to the Hebrew annals&#44; solely as a source of<lb/> instruction to the progeny of the righteous Abraham.  The distance<lb/> and vicissitudes of time may occasionally hide from our comprehension<lb/> the purport of those ancient records&#44; but a mature reflection will ulti&#45;<lb/>&#45;mately reveal the object assigned to them.  Accordingly&#44; I shall<lb/> this day&#44; solicit your attention to a few remarks&#44; or&#44; to be more accurate<lb/> in my expression&#44; to one pertinent observation on our Parash&#225;&#44; for&#44;<lb/> though I might detain you long by dilating on several incidents&#44; which<lb/> display the virtues possessed by the first parent of our nation&#44; I prefer<lb/> discussing a point on which the 23d Chapter of Genesis turns.  In that<lb/> we are apprized of a transaction consummated between Abraham and<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>an affluent Hittite.  Yet&#44; by some&#44; who are captiously inclined&#44; that account<lb/> may be deemed of no moment&#44; and the judiciousness of the act itself<lb/> be disputed.  It may be argued&#58; that it certainly reflects credit on<lb/> the husband&#44; who pays the last tribute of affection to the partner of<lb/> his life&#44; by seeking an honorable interment for her remains&#44; but<lb/> that inasmuch as the body will eventually dissolve itself into its<lb/> various elements&#44; it matters little where it lies entombed&#59; conse&#45;<lb/>&#45;quently the extreme eagerness evinced by Abraham in procuring a<lb/> distinct possession of a burial&#45;place&#44; was unwarranted&#44; while the<lb/> gold expended for its acquisition&#44; was illy bestowed.  Such&#44; however&#44;<lb/> is not our opinion.  He who had learnt to raise his mind from<lb/> nature up to natures&#39; God&#44; knew how properly to regard even<lb/> what is perishable&#44; for the sake of the immortal spirit&#44; of which it<lb/> had long been the noble repository.  And as he could not ignore<lb/> that the future abode of the soul&#44; varies in accordance with the purity<lb/> of actions fulfilled through the agency of the body&#44; so he considered<lb/> it correct that a separate sephulchre should distinguish the ashes<lb/> of the God&#45;fearing Sarah&#44; from those of the heathen Canaanites.<lb/>  But the design of the patriarch&#44; would have been imperfectly attained&#44;<lb/> by the purchase of one soul grave.  He felt persuaded&#44; that the seed<lb/> of Isaac&#44; would perpetuate the precious truths&#44; which he had striven<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>to disseminate&#44; and he endeavoured to secure for his immediate suc&#45;<lb/>&#45;cessors a spot&#44; totally apportioned for the remains of the righteous&#44;<lb/> who were destined to usher a pure faith into the world.<lb/></p>
            <p>That such was Abraham&#39;s scheme&#44; we unmistakably deduce from<lb/> subsequent facts.  Not alone did his bones&#44; rest beside those of<lb/> his lamented Sarah&#44; but also his second son&#44; in whom&#44; the celestial<lb/> declarations vouchsafed unto him&#44; were verified&#45;&#45;was together with the beloved<lb/> Rebecca&#44;&#45;&#45;consigned to the cave of Machelah.  And if we further<lb/> examine&#44; we shall discover from the words uttered by Jacob&#44; that only<lb/> the sorrowful circumstance of her sudden death&#44; deprived Rachel of<lb/> the honor of being interred with the other mothers of Israel&#59; for&#44;<lb/> waiving the opinion of commentators&#44; who aver that&#44; for a twofold<lb/> reason&#44; Providence had doomed Rachel to a solitary grave&#44; we may<lb/> infer from the literal sense of the text&#44; that the sad fate was occasioned<lb/> by the difficulty of the journey&#44; which her household were then pursuing&#45;<lb/> &#34;As for me&#44; when I was coming from Padua&#44; Rachel died by me&#44; in<lb/> the land of Canaan&#44; in the way&#44; when yet there was a space of land<lb/> to reach Ephrath&#44; and I buried here there in the way of Ephrath&#44;<lb/> which is Beth&#45;Chem.&#34;  But while the doting husband&#44; grieved<lb/> at that inevitable issue&#44; he was forcible in entreating that his body&#44;<lb/> should be conveyed to the spot consecrated by the ashes of his ancestors.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Fearful that the execution of his will&#44; might be impeded by<lb/> Egyptian authority&#44; he tranquillized his mind&#44; by exacting a<lb/> solemn oath from his faithful Joseph.  And so greatly did the<lb/> fathers of our race&#44; deprecate a burial <sic>sepulture</sic> among such who did not<lb/> profess their faith&#44; that even the powerful dignitary last&#45;named&#44;<lb/> besought that he might be exhumed from the land of his exaltation&#44; to<lb/> be entombed amid those who adored the everlasting Creator.  The example<lb/> of Abraham left an impress upon his children&#44; which time deepened<lb/> in their thoughts.  However&#44; it was not narrow prejudice that<lb/> influenced the righteous patriarch in the act to which I have referred&#44;<lb/> for&#44; his whole life belies the imputation.  His confederates&#44; were three<lb/> men&#44; with whose religious conviction history leaves us unacquainted&#44;<lb/> but which probably partook of the prevailing gentile notions.<lb/></p>
            <p>Abimelek&#44; with whom he established a compact of durable amity&#44;<lb/> had not embraced his belief.  The individuals&#44; whom he rescued<lb/> from war and rapine&#44; were not his followers&#59; those for whose<lb/> salvation he implored the Deity&#44; did not acknowledge the truths<lb/> wherewith he was imbued.  No&#44; my friends&#44; it was not contempt for<lb/> the bulk mass of mankind&#44; that prompted Abraham to secure for himself &#38; his<lb/> offspring the possession of the cave of Machpelah&#44; but as he was<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>contradistinctly styled &#34;the Hebrew&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#34;&#44; the scion of the<lb/> God&#45;like Eber&#59; the one who designed the formation of a peculiar<lb/> tribe&#59; the one who in life had religiously severed himself from the<lb/> heathen would that surrounded him&#44; so would he also&#44; in death&#44; be<lb/> singled out from among those that had <sic>worshipped</sic> false deities.<lb/>  Hence I conceive it to have arisen the practice universally preserved in<lb/> Israel&#44; to devote a tract of land for the special interment of their<lb/> deceased.  Not that they lightly regard the sepulchres of their non&#45;<lb/>co&#45;religionists&#44; not that the tombs of their own brethren&#44; when<lb/> blended with the former&#44; would fail to arouse a serious thought touching<lb/> their duties and final destination&#59; but because the religious opinions they<lb/> entertain&#44; the laws they obey&#44; and the usages they follow&#44; render<lb/> it necessary that they should&#44; under all circumstances&#44; be singularly<lb/> pointed at&#44; as the posterity of him who proclaimed a Truth&#44; which<lb/> yet&#44; they alone daily acknowledge.  The time will sure arrive&#44; when<lb/> every knee shall bend to the Great God&#44; who has infused within<lb/> us&#44; our immortal soul&#44; but until that Messianic era dawns&#44; the<lb/> Hebrew people&#44; must cling to such customs&#44; which&#44; without injuring<lb/> society&#44; particularize them in its midst.  It is&#44; my friends&#44; to our<lb/> peculiar habits that we owe the preservation of our nationality&#44; for&#44;<lb/> abstract ideas may become obliterated when in contact<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>with others&#44; which hold predominance&#44; but if supported by outward<lb/> aids&#44; they can never suffer extinction.  The utility of the latter<lb/> has been frequently demonstrated to us&#44; in the hours of persecution&#59; and<lb/> it redounds to our glory&#44; that by a steadfast adherence into them&#44;<lb/> has2 also the1 sublime verity which we were summoned to propagate&#44; been3<lb/> upheld.  The God of our fathers grant that the effect of freedom<lb/> be not the abjuration of that&#44; which exile and martyrdom could not<lb/> even suppress&#44; for&#44; step by step we are descending from the scale in<lb/> which we were stationed&#44; and the uncontrollable mania of imitation&#44;<lb/> threatens to cast thoroughly away the land&#45;&#45;mark set by the ancient<lb/> fathers of our race.  We now cavil at this&#44; anon scoff at that&#44; and<lb/> nothing gratifies our vitiated mind&#44; but a community of deeds and usages<lb/> with the denizens of the country wherein we sojourn.  Beloved children<lb/> of my faith&#33;  If tears drawn by that inauspicious sight could divert<lb/> the inconsiderate from their purpose&#44; I should weep and moan&#44; for&#44;<lb/> truly my heart is full of sorrow&#44; but as I feel my utter incapacity<lb/> to accomplish so much good&#44; I shall uplift my eyes to the Dweller<lb/> above&#44; and Him pray&#44; fervently pray&#44; like Elijah on Carmel&#44; to send<lb/> down a heavenly fire&#44; which may again vivify the dormant spirits of<lb/> Israel&#44; till they again unitedly and sincerely exclaim &#34;The Lord&#44; he is<lb/> God&#44; the Lord he is God&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93; Oh&#33; answer me O Lord&#44; answer me&#44; and for the sake of the<lb/> righteous that he entombed in the land of our ancient heritage&#44; inspire<lb/> Israel with love to Thee and to thy laws.  For the sake of Abraham&#44;<lb/> who&#44; in the years of decrepitude&#44; hastened to seal his flesh with thy<lb/> covenant&#44; grant that his children may ever imitate his example.<lb/>  For the sake of Isaac&#44; who was willing to be immolated in honor to<lb/> thy name&#44; grant that his progeny may sacrifice to religion their<lb/> evil propensities.  For the sake of Jacob&#44; who vowed to consecrate<lb/> to thy worship a portion of his wealth&#44; grant that his descendants<lb/> may devote time and affluence to the service of thy holy house.<lb/>  And as the God&#45;fearing Joseph&#44; amid the grandeur which surrounded<lb/> him&#44; forgot not his extraction and thy divine promises&#44; so grant<lb/> that his posterity&#44; while <sic>enjoing</sic> the excellencies of freedom&#44; may be<lb/> also alive to the unity of faith and hopes which bend them with<lb/> their scattered brethren.  And may all of them that bear the ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;pellation of Hebrews&#44; join heart to heart and hand to hand in<lb/> deeds of virtue and charity&#44; for&#44; then shall thy name be sanctified<lb/> among the nations of the earth&#44; and we shall acquire merit in<lb/> thy heavenly sight for evermore.  May it even be so.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
