<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF9_18</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1891-06" source="" attested="yes">June 1891</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_18_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_18_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_18_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_18_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_18_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_18_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_18_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_18_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_18_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_18_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_18_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_18_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>89<lb/>
                June&#47;91<lb/>
                On Russian persecutions<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>In the thirty third canto of Dante&#39;s first part of his &#34;Divine Comedy&#34; &#34;Hell&#44;&#34; Count<lb/> Ugolino&#44; being about to tell the agonies of his own<lb/> soul and the suffering of his children&#44; when left to starve<lb/> to death in a the loneliness of a town&#44; says&#58; &#34;E se non<lb/> piangi di che pianger suoli&#63;.&#34; which means &#34;If thou<lb/> weepest not at this&#44; what will make thy tears flow&#63;&#34;<lb/>  Of that distressful lament I was reminded and &#91;&#63;&#93; intensely grieved as I ran<lb/> over the leaves of a book which has just issued from the press.<lb/>  It is an octavo volume containing upwards of four<lb/> hundred pages.  In there I saw a pen picture of the<lb/> pangs of our brethren&#44; immured in a dismal dungeon&#44;<lb/> called &#34;Russia&#34;.  Translated largely from the English&#44;<lb/> and reproduced in part from French writings&#44; it is<lb/> in the language of the latter&#44; that the reader of the book<lb/> is given an exhaustive graphic narrative of refined <sic>barbaraties</sic>&#44;<lb/> foretokeningshadowing the judicial murder of the <sic>defenceless</sic>.<lb/>  Yes&#58;&#44; to the ineffaceable shame of Christendom&#44; &#34;defen&#45;<lb/>&#45;celess&#34;.  What avail meetings&#44; resolutions and me&#45;<lb/>&#45;morials&#44; since a heartless diplomacy seals the lips<lb/> that might speak words of deliverance&#63;  I know<lb/> that if a handful of the followers of Jesus of Na&#45;<lb/>&#45;zareth&#44; in some remote corner of Asia or Africa&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>felt the lash of Mohammedanism&#44; an alarm<lb/> would sound from the gulph of Bothnia to the<lb/> Mediterranean sea&#59; its echo reaching where the At&#45;<lb/>&#45;lantic and the Pacific lie.  But blandishments only<lb/> proceed whence protests should go earnestly forth.<lb/>  The accredited champion of human rights is urged on&#44;<lb/> but it remains motionless.  Baker and Cummings and<lb/> Hilt remonstrate&#44; now strongly again anon mildly&#44; even<lb/> in a whisper&#45;&#45;lest the hearer be offended object all.  To no purpose.  The government at<lb/> our Capital does not hear has ears for nothing&#44; save that which affects its<lb/> temporal advancement.  Might not the Autocrat<lb/> knit his brows&#63;  Why venture his displeasure&#44;&#45;&#45;hurting<lb/> our interests&#45;&#45;&#44; for the sake of...Jews&#63;  A brother<lb/> in faith&#44; supposed to be in the confidence of our Se&#45;<lb/>&#45;cretary of State&#44; gave me his assurance that the chance<lb/> was closely watched for a friendly interposition&#63;.  What<lb/> chance&#63;  Rapine and rape and rain run at each<lb/> other&#39;s heels&#44; and the opportunity has not yet<lb/> arrived for an expression of disapproval&#59; for an<lb/> amicable suggestion&#33;  Perhapschance&#44; the gentle hint is<lb/> deferred until young and old blown at the mouth of<lb/> the cannon&#44; or driven out at the point of the bayonet&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>cease to pollute holy&#40;&#63;&#41; Russia with their presence.<lb/>  So Says the book&#44; which has impressed me deeply&#58;<lb/> &#34;If a red line were drawn across a map delineating<lb/> Jewish districts throughout Russia&#44; where atrocities are<lb/> perpetrated&#44; the whole of that geographical chart would<lb/> seem dipped in blood.&#34;  Not a spot but in which the<lb/> bludgeon&#44; and the scourge and human infamy mark<lb/> out every hour of the day &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;The grand old man&#34;<lb/> in England&#44; was all fire to help Greece to burn away<lb/> the bands that Turkey in 1877 had thrown around her limbs&#44;<lb/> and how ardent his wish in 1877 that the Russo&#45;Turkish<lb/> war would end in planting the Cross on the minarets<lb/> of Constantinople&#33;  But now the famous statesman&#44; and author&#44; and orator of whom I would speak deferentially&#44; Mr. Gladstone&#44; pleads<lb/> a loss of influence with his once most Christian fa&#45;<lb/>&#45;vorite&#44;&#45;&#45;Russia.  He Now that we are concerned&#44; he laments the circulating reports&#44;<lb/> advises a careful investigation&#44; and approves of a<lb/> settlement of Jews in Palestine.  Thanks&#58; Great<lb/> Britain fears a foreign invasion of underpaid workers.  Let her keep<lb/> calm&#59; the homeless will not seek swarm crowd<lb/> her borders.  The land beyond the Ocean can shelter<lb/> and feed and feed strengthen the soul&#45;harassed outcasts.  Thither<lb/> will they wend their weary steps.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Oh&#33;  May not the narrow spirit which has disgraced<lb/> the Hebrews of Chicago spread its bane farther&#63;  I am feel<lb/> unspeakably humiliated at the thought that men&#44; who<lb/> probably reached our shores in a plight not unlike<lb/> that of the hapless refugees fugitives from Russia&#44; now since<lb/> that they have gathered abundance&#44; refuse brothers<lb/> in misery even the gleanings of the rich fields they<lb/> have planted.  I have read that after the ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;pulsion from Spain and Portugal&#44; the Jews of<lb/> some Italian cities sought to influence the local<lb/> authorities against the admission of the exiles.<lb/>  That cruelty&#44; may have a slight extenuation in the<lb/> difficulty of making room and affording sufficient<lb/> scope for trade and commerce as the Italian peninsula covers a very small area of ground&#44; and eve in 1492 its available means were limited&#45;&#45;but boundless al&#45;<lb/>&#45;most in size and exhaustless in its resources is this God&#45;<lb/>favored country.  To deny the oppressed admission<lb/> is unpardonable selfishness.  Poverty stricken<lb/> the refugees may be&#44; but they do not carry&#45;&#45;as alleged truthfully or falsely against other foreigners&#45;&#45;wea&#45;<lb/>&#45;pons of destruction.  They carry their sinewy arms&#44;<lb/> and a heritage of &#91;&#63;&#93; indefatigable industry.  I do not<lb/> hail their arrival.  I deplore the causes which com&#45;<lb/>&#45;pel an exodus unparalleled in extent since the dispersion.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>I would that a political overthrow of the wret&#45;<lb/>&#45;ched rule of despotism should give issue my brethren<lb/> the inalienable rights of &#34;life&#44; liberty and the<lb/> pursuit of happiness.&#34;  But that devoutly to be<lb/> hoped for event is not within sight.  Shall<lb/> the gates of America&#44; that owes her prosperity<lb/> very largely to the toil and thrift of her foreign<lb/> population&#44; be shut her gates in the face of the unfortunates&#63;<lb/>  Oh&#33; may not our lawmakers an evil counsel in Washington determine had to<lb/> upon a course so contrary to the guiding principles<lb/> being at the basis of the generous Northern Republic&#44; and so inhuman&#33;<lb/>  I have no faith in the Southern Republics upon<lb/> this Western Continent.  Turbulent&#44; unsteady and jealous of<lb/> one another&#44; they might look askance on an element<lb/> strange to them in appearance in language&#44; and<lb/> religion&#44; and bearing the reputation of being sharp&#45;witted.  Catholic Spaniards and Portuguese are<lb/> not the heirs of a national love to the believers<lb/> in the Unity.  Minds such as an Emilio<lb/> Castelar&#44; a Sagosta&#44; a Lopez de la Pusa may<lb/> rise above the prejudices of centuries&#44; but the po&#45;<lb/>&#45;pulace are too priest&#45;ridden to welcome foreigners&#44;<lb/> who do not go to give a wide berth a wide berth the confessional but and worship in a<lb/> Synagogue.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>What tidings the commissioners of Baron de<lb/> Hirsch will bring from Brazil and the Argentine<lb/> Confederation I cannot divine&#44; but not every<lb/> report in the name of the uniquely Jewish phi&#45;<lb/>&#45;lanthropist of our age&#44; can be accepted as a fact.<lb/>  I cannot credit&#44; for instance&#44; that he&#44; so sagacious&#44;<lb/> considers the Czar innocent of the shocking indig&#45;<lb/>&#45;gnities practised on millions of Jewish subjects&#59;<lb/> that governors&#44; inspectors&#44; policemen&#44; foully abuse the<lb/> power vested in them&#44; to tear out the life of the Jew&#44;<lb/> to rob his wife and daughters of their honor&#44; to<lb/> plunder and destroy and chase away&#44; and that the<lb/> royal master is left in utter ignorance of those<lb/> demoniac outrages.  But if it be so&#44;&#45;&#45;and daily accounts re&#45;<lb/>&#45;fute the theory why does he determinedly peremptorily refuse to<lb/> become enlightened&#63;  The petition consequent upon<lb/> the famous meeting at Guildhall on the 10th<lb/> of December last&#44; aimed humbly to relate some of<lb/> the hardships endured by the Hebrews.  The empe&#45;<lb/>&#45;ror was implored in touching language to look<lb/> benignantly into the misery of millions&#59;&#45;&#45;the memorialists asserting<lb/> that they are deserving of compassionate consideration&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>that they are patriots&#44; though reckoned aliens&#44;<lb/> that the number of the soldiers they furnish to the Russian army&#44; ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;ceeds in proportion that of from the midst of the<lb/> dominant religion&#59; that Jews&#44; obedient to their<lb/> ancient laws pray in their houses of worship for the<lb/> crowned ruler and his family.  But notwithstand&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing that&#44; the memorial was couched in the hum&#45;<lb/>&#45;blest terms&#44; and that the Czar was exonerated by<lb/> every speaker&#44; at that now henceforth historic meeting&#44; from<lb/> the crimes committed in his name dominions&#44; Alexander III&#44; would<lb/> not learn what he &#91;&#63;&#93; declared ingeniousness or policy declares him to be unacquainted with.<lb/>  He returned the memorial petition unread.  None shall dare<lb/> stand between his rod and his victims to parry<lb/> the blow.  To me the proposition attributed<lb/> to the Baron appears to border on insanity.  The<lb/> munificent Israelite manifestly admits that the<lb/> Czar has enjoined promulgated the edict of expulsion&#44; and yet<lb/> he is asked to allow thousands to expatriate at<lb/> a time&#44; expecting that the rest&#44; left behind&#44; will en&#45;<lb/>&#45;joy the principal possession of their homes&#44; till their<lb/> turn arrives to be driven away.  What poor know&#45;<lb/>&#45;ledge of human nature&#59; no&#44; what poor knowledge of the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>inhuman nature of the Cossack the Baron<lb/> must have to entertain such anticipations&#33;  A<lb/> people held at sufferance&#44; to be abide tranquilly in a<lb/> country that has doomed them to banishment captivity&#33;<lb/>  Our understanding must stamp the idea as a self evident<lb/> absurdity&#44; but our hearts&#44; O fellow believers&#44; must recognize<lb/> the fearful duty of the hour.  We must rise equal<lb/> to the importance of this appalling episode in our history.  &#91;Inserted from page 9&#58; I ask it of you&#44; I beg it of you&#44; at this season&#44; in the name of the fathers<lb/> who stood at the foot of Sinai in accord of sentiments&#44; in unison of creed&#44;<lb/> feeling that the Torah was destined to make them a people eternized to<lb/> the service of One God.  Do not shrink from the obligation which that glo&#45;<lb/>&#45;rious past imposes.&#93;<lb/>  We You must prepare for an avalanche&#44; as it were&#44; of the<lb/> poor indigent and distressed.  They may present a figure at which<lb/> you&#44; of America&#44; shrank start back.  Let us Do not repel them.<lb/>  The abjectness of some&#44; the ignorance of others&#44; the ill&#45;<lb/>founded notions of many&#44; are the inevitable effects of<lb/> a mind&#45;poisoning atmosphere.  Bear with the evil&#45;&#45;<lb/>for such it will prove for a period&#45;&#45;You will pluck it<lb/> off&#44; when you strive to plant good.  Through the<lb/> children&#44; you may uplift their parents&#44; and yours<lb/> will be the merit of having saved the largest portion of<lb/> martyred Israel from extinction&#44; or apostasy.  In the<lb/> language of Hosea&#44; as in the prophetic lesson of this Sabbath&#44;<lb/> I cry&#58; &#91;Hebrew&#93;  &#34;Say of your brothers &#39;My<lb/> people&#39;&#44; and of your sisters &#39;they are rescued by mercy&#39;.&#34;.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>&#40;Here followed an address to a Bar Mitzvah on the 31st an&#45;<lb/>&#45;niversary of the 7th st Synagogue&#41;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
