<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF4_23</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_23_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_23_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_23_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_23_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_23_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_23_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_23_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_23_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_23_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_23_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_23_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_23_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_23_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_23_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_23_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_23_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Post Biblical<lb/>
                43.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>A lecture of the same nature as that which<lb/> I delivered last Sabbath&#44; may not be<lb/> uninteresting.  As I admit the propriety<lb/> of dealing with live issues&#45;&#45;of letting the <sic>pupit</sic><lb/> enchain the draw attention to current events of a<lb/> religious&#44; communal or national importance&#44;<lb/> I was hindered by such events allowed incidents of that kind to hinder me from presenting<lb/> historical subjects&#44; during the term now draw&#45; approaching<lb/> &#45;ing to to its close&#44; with as much frequency as<lb/> heretofore.  Hence my resolve to compensate in a measure by referring to day<lb/> to the character of a Talmudical Sage&#44; contem&#45;<lb/>&#45;porary of to Simeon Ben Gamliel II&#44; of whom I<lb/> last spoke very recently.  Were it not that the person&#45;<lb/>&#45;age of whom I purpose now to speak&#44; on this sabbath<lb/> is one of the most conspicuously figures stands preeminently in Rab&#45;<lb/>binical literature&#44; I would have passed him by<lb/> and proceeded further.  For I never meant have not undertaken to write<lb/> the biographies of our illustrious post biblical<lb/> men.  Such a task would exceed the limits<lb/> I have assigned to my endeavour&#44; which is main&#45; as I seeking mainly<lb/> &#45;ly to offer a sketch of the heads of our ancient schools<lb/> of learning.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>But to ignore Rabbi Meir would<lb/> be to leave a wide historical gap.  He<lb/> was not the chief of the principal academy<lb/> of his time&#44; set up in Obsha&#44; but among the very many<lb/> pupils of our martyred Akiba Ben Joseph&#44; he<lb/> ranked foremost in the double character of had no rival as<lb/> a Mishnic authority and a model of piety.<lb/>  I shall not decide the question regarding<lb/> his descent and place of birth.  some have assert&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed that Meir&#39;s ancestry was not Jewish&#44;<lb/> nor was his native land Palestine.&#44; but that  He may have<lb/> he was been born&#45;&#45;for aught I know&#45;&#45;in Asia Minor of parents in whose<lb/> veins course the blood of heathens converted to<lb/> our faith during the first century of the common<lb/> era.  But those who study people&#39;s conduct and<lb/> not people&#39;s extraction or country&#44; will con&#45;<lb/>&#45;sider that point quite entirely irrelevant.  Meir<lb/> might have issued from a King of Judah&#59;<lb/> and he might have first long rested his infant looks continually long on Zion&#39;s<lb/> temple&#44; and yet have been nevertheless undeser&#45;<lb/>&#45;ving of an honorable mention in the annals<lb/> of our Hebrew literature.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>For&#44; as he himself tells us in one of his wise<lb/> maxims&#44; sentient beings creatures who bear the image of<lb/> their Maker are to be measured only by the line of<lb/> duty they perform.  The scriptures say that<lb/> man will live by the observance of God&#39;s<lb/> precepts &#91;Hebrew&#93;  Mark it&#58; &#34;Man&#34; is<lb/> a word&#44; of universal application.  It does not<lb/> refer to any specially privileged caste.  &#34;man&#39;s a man for all that.&#34;  Let it be a non&#45;Israelite. Even<lb/> a non&#45;Israelite He who&#44; in his moral relations&#44; is<lb/> guided by the Divine Law stands as loftily in<lb/> the social scale as a high priest &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  So taught the broad minded Rabbi Meir.  How<lb/> forcibly he exemplified that wholesome liberal lesson&#44;<lb/> we are shown in his intercourse with a Greek<lb/> philosopher called Nymus&#44; or Nemonymus.<lb/>  The latter&#44; appreciating the Pentateuch and the<lb/> Prophets&#44; made use of them Holy Writ in support of the<lb/> ideas advanced by the famous Pythagoras<lb/> and Plato.  Meir&#44; who prized learning<lb/> wherever found&#44; did not disdain the friendly asso&#45;<lb/>&#45;ciation of a gentile who that recognized the greatness of the<lb/> greatest book.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>The difference of worship did not pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;vent him&#44; any more than our patriarch Abraham&#44; clude<lb/> from performing the exercise of mutual acts of human kindness.  It<lb/> is recorded that when Nymus lost buried his parents&#44;<lb/> the Jewish Rabbi paid the mourner a visit&#44;<lb/> and offered tokens of heartfelt brotherly condolence.<lb/>  But noble as it is to acknowledge man&#39;s worth<lb/> irrespective of creed&#44; it is still nobler to try to approach<lb/> reclaim the worthless and try to acclaim them to virtue.  The sentiments which<lb/> stirred within the breast heart of the godly Meir were<lb/> never more strikingly manifest than in his<lb/> behaviour towards Elisha son of Abua.<lb/>  That depraved Jew is only the a single instance in post<lb/> biblical history of a Rabbi having deserted his religion.<lb/>  Meir had studied under the apostate&#44; when this<lb/> was yet sound in theories and unfaltering in<lb/> practice&#59; the guileless Meir he had sat at the feet of the false Rabbi before the loose games and wanton<lb/> songs of Greece&#44; in which he indulged&#44; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; had perverted his mind&#44; and corrupted<lb/> his morals.  Then all spurned the contact of one him who<lb/> had cast soiled with a foul blot on the escutcheon of Rabbi&#45;<lb/>&#45;nism.  All refused to mention the name of the renegade.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Meir could not forsake the man from to whom<lb/> he had received owed most valued instruction.  On a certain<lb/> Sabbath he met the recreant riding on horse back.<lb/>  He followed the impious one Jew on foot and engaged in the discussion of se&#45;<lb/>&#45;rious objects.  When they had reached a distance beyond<lb/> which Meir would not walk on the holy day&#44; Eli&#45;<lb/>&#45;sha&#44; who knew the rule well&#44; halted&#44; and&#44; looking bending<lb/> down said to Meir&#58; &#34;Turn back now.&#34;  The anxious<lb/> pupil&#44; using the same expression looked up and said in return&#44;<lb/> &#34;Oh&#33;  Turn back thou also to the path of religion.&#34;  The apos&#45;<lb/>&#45;tate declared to have gone too far to hope for reform&#45; retract<lb/> ation and persisted in doing evil.  It grieved Meir and that one so intellectually so brilliant should <sic>yeild</sic> his soul to destruction.  A legend tells that Meir he would allow himself no rest till by he<lb/> supplicating for by his own merits he propitiated Divine mercy and delivered his<lb/> master from the sufferings of a world to come.<lb/>  When asked how he could consistently be seen<lb/> in company with one so wicked&#44; a man&#44; Meir pi&#45;<lb/>&#45;thily answered&#58; &#34;I found a pomegranate&#44; sucked<lb/> its juice&#44; and threw away the rind&#44;&#34; meaning<lb/> I drew useful information from one who was brim&#45;<lb/>&#45;ful of learning&#44; but rejected cast aside as too bitter in its results what was vicious in his<lb/> conduct.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>A perfect master was2 Meir1 of figurative<lb/> speaking.  Extensive as the his knowledge of Rabbi<lb/> Meir was in of the oral traditions was so that the<lb/> Mishnah was subsequently formulated after his<lb/> plan&#44; he surpassed all in his aptness to em&#45;<lb/>&#45;ploy figures of speech&#44; allegories and proverbs<lb/> with striking effect.  The Talmudists could<lb/> not bestow a higher praise of on Meir by reason of that ability&#44; than when<lb/> they wrote that at his death&#44; the ability capacity to speak<lb/> in parables ceased to exist &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> But all his parables always conveyed a deep meaning.<lb/>  I will cite one&#58; &#34;When man laments his f having<lb/> fallen low and incurred the penalty of his offences&#44;<lb/> a voice cries exclaims &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#39;Woe to my head&#44; woe to my arm.&#39; It is the Divinity weeping cries <sic>crieing</sic> as one in great bodily pain&#58; that<lb/> is the Almighty does not take pleasure in the<lb/> punishment of the wicked &#91;Hebrew&#93; mortals ought therefore men ought therefore so ought we to detest crime&#44; but pity the guilty.<lb/>  Beautiful is the description which Meir left us<lb/> of the virtuous who Jew.  He studies God&#39;s law to a sublime<lb/> purpose not for selfish uninterested motives ends.  He studies to become righteous.  He learns to love his fellow creatures&#44; and<lb/> he is loved in return&#59; he is a comfort to man&#44; and<lb/> a delight to God.  Humble minded he is he just&#44;<lb/> true&#44; loyal&#59; he keeps away from vice evil&#44; draws nigh<lb/> to goodness&#44; becomes useful in counsel&#44; and<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>and gains dignity and authority&#44; and while<lb/> he grows in wisdom like a fountain flowing with<lb/> ever increasing force&#44; he is modest without&#44; tolerant<lb/> and forgiving.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> If I wished desired to dwell long on my subject&#44; I could prove that he who drew that picture&#44;<lb/> mirrored it forth in his own person very splendidly.  For admirable as Rabbi Meir is in his pu&#45;<lb/>&#45;blic capacity as a teacher in Israel&#44; equally<lb/> so he is in his private relations.  All know<lb/> that he was fortunate in the possession of<lb/> a wife&#44; cultured and pious.  All have<lb/> heard how having lost two sons on a Sabbath<lb/> day&#44; during his absence from home&#44; his wife<lb/> Beruria greeted his return in the evening&#44; with<lb/> all the calmness she could command&#44; and&#44;<lb/> waving his eager inquiries about his children<lb/> till he had recited his prayers and eaten a meal&#44;<lb/> she told him that the owner of two precious gems&#44;<lb/> once entrusted to their care of both&#44; had sent and claimed<lb/> his own&#59; that God who had given&#44; had also<lb/> taken away.  Meir loved cherished the woman who could so<lb/> consoled his heart in the hour of affliction&#59; he<lb/> respected the woman&#44; who&#44; when her husband&#44;<lb/> exceedingly annoyed  by vile persons in his neighbor&#45;<lb/>&#45;hood&#44; and<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>wished them dead&#44; quoted the psalmist to<lb/> show her husband that he ought to pray for<lb/> the reformation and not for the extermination of<lb/> the wicked &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  To rescue<lb/> from enforced shame the sister of the woman<lb/> he honored&#44; Meir undertook a voyage to<lb/> Rome&#44; and at a great danger delivered the object<lb/> of heathen licentiousness.  Among Tal&#45;<lb/>mudical celebrities&#45;&#45;and there are many of a<lb/> saintly life and far&#45;reaching learning&#45;&#45;Meir<lb/> occupies a position seldom attained.  That<lb/> he was called pointed at by a colleague to his townsmen as an Israelite &#34;great&#44; holy and<lb/> chaste&#34;; that even his opponent Simeon<lb/> Ben Gamliel&#44; President of the Obsha Academy&#44; and<lb/> tenacious in the assertion of his own official dignity superiority&#44;<lb/> should speak of Meir deferentially&#44; is not at<lb/> all surprising&#44; but if it the uninitiated will deem it passing strange<lb/> that together with a vast deal of high toned<lb/> writings&#44; calculated to enhance the character to enhance heighten our estimation<lb/> of our subject&#44; legends should have been chronicled<lb/> incompatible with the station whole course of one so estimable noble.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>I may therefore fittingly suitably remark that<lb/> with what is elevating in Rabbinical volumes&#44;<lb/> an admixture is may occasionally be found of what is sayings and stories re&#45;<lb/>&#45;pugnant to refined feelings.  This regrettable<lb/> fact has been maliciously used by the enemies<lb/> of traditional Judaism to expose it to contempt.<lb/></p>  <p>Students must exercise a discriminating judgment<lb/> in the acceptance of what is legendary&#44; or hyperboli<lb/>&#45;cal&#44; lest great injustice wrongs be done to our teachers of<lb/> old.  for without claiming for any of them<lb/> what belongs only to God&#45;&#45;perfection&#45;&#45;we have<lb/> just cause to pride ourselves on our literature and<lb/> those who created it.  As to Meir&#44; we must re&#45;<lb/>cognize in him a model of industry&#44; frugality&#44;<lb/> loving&#45;kindness and sterling piety.  Depend&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing on his rare penmanship for a humble&#45;&#45;as a copyist&#45;&#45;for a<lb/> livelihood&#44; he devoted two thirds of his earn&#45;<lb/>&#45;ings to the maintenance of his family&#44; and<lb/> with one third he assisted the poor among his<lb/> associates and pupils.  To bring about do&#45;<lb/>&#45;mestic reconciliation&#44; he would voluntarily submitted to voluntary indignities<lb/> at from which many would have revolted shrunk.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>The living he <sic>benefitted</sic>&#44; the dead he would<lb/> ensure an honored burial &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> I will conclude by quoting a recommendation which<lb/> Rabbi Meir frequently gave in the name of<lb/> the Lord he served&#58; &#34;<sic>Mortall</sic>&#34; determine with<lb/> all thy heart and with all thy soul to understand<lb/> my ways&#44; and eagerly to follow the directions<lb/> of my Law.  Hold that Law near thy heart&#44; and<lb/> let the fear of Me be present to thy mind.  Guard<lb/> thy lips from uttering sinful words&#44; be pure and<lb/> keep aloof from transgression trespasses and crime.  Then will<lb/> I be with thee&#34;.  May our youths inscribe<lb/> that direction on the tablets of their own hearts&#44; and<lb/> God will be with them.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
