<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF8_12</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1889-01" source="" attested="yes">1889</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_12_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_12_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_12_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_12_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_12_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_12_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_12_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_12_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_12_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_12_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_12_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff8_12_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>A contrast between 1789 in France<lb/>
                &#38; 1789 in America &#47;1889<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  Innumerable are the important events which that the world<lb/> has witnessed during the age of startling discoveries<lb/> and inventions&#44; in which we live.  But of all occur&#45;<lb/>&#45;rences that happened two have affected mankind most strikingly.<lb/>  They have just called forth national celebrations.<lb/>  How very different&#44; however&#44; those two events in their<lb/> surroundings&#44; and how different in their results as<lb/> regards the Jewish people&#33;  I have read that in<lb/> 1789 when the Bastille&#45;&#45;tyranny&#39;s stronghold&#45;&#45;was<lb/> stormed by enraged insurgents&#44; its keys were<lb/> sent to America&#44; to be finally deposited in the<lb/> Capitol of the city&#44; which bears the name of America&#39;s great&#45;<lb/>&#45;est son.  If so&#44; let them remain there as a trophy<lb/> of popular self&#45;avenging.  But the tearing down<lb/> of the fortress&#44; where persons suspected of political<lb/> offences were mysteriously put away&#44; was not<lb/> the Bunker hill of France.  The freedom which<lb/> the country between the Alps and the Pyrenees<lb/> tried to rival one hundred years ago&#44; had nothing little<lb/> in common in the working out of its system with that<lb/> which the genius of George Washington blissfully<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>wrought for the United States.  The<lb/> situation was unlike because European traditions made it so&#44; and because the temper of men&#39;s<lb/> mind was so&#44; hence the means employed were<lb/> altogether unlike.  Here&#44; liberty was purchased<lb/> by the blood of the ba brave&#44; sacredly gladly shed upon<lb/> the field of pure patriotism&#44; there&#44; a reign of<lb/> terror preceded liberty&#44; and caused streams of inno&#45;<lb/>&#45;cent blood to flow despotically in the name of<lb/> liberty.  Here the stars and stripes symbolized<lb/> humanity&#44; there the red&#44; white and blue meant<lb/> for a time the guillotine.  The bitterest opponents<lb/> of royal claims and aristocratic <sic>pretentions</sic> cannot<lb/> but shrink with horror at the account of dark<lb/> deeds which &#91;&#63;&#93; blackened the pages of<lb/> the revolutionary history of revolutionary France.<lb/></p>
            <p>As to the Israelites who dwelt there at about<lb/> that period in small numbers&#44; having attempted<lb/> stealthily to return every now and then&#44; since their<lb/> expulsion under Phillip the Fair in the beginning of<lb/> the fourteenth century&#44;&#45;&#45;indignities met them on<lb/> all sides.  Compelled to pay a capitation tax&#44; as<lb/> if they were beasts of burden&#44; forced to live apart<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>from the rest of the community&#44; they were<lb/> publicly looked upon with contempt as intruding<lb/> aliens.  Strange Anomalous as it may seem&#44; the famous<lb/> Voltaire&#44; quoted for his liberal ideas views&#44; had not a<lb/> kind word for an ill&#45;used race.  In his multi&#45;<lb/>&#45;farious writings&#44; rudeness and invectives against<lb/> the Hebrews are  easily traced. deliberately indulged in.  He did them and<lb/> their books wanton injustice&#44; and strange to say&#44; it was left to<lb/> a christian churchman&#45;&#45;L&#39;Abbe&#39; Guen&#233;e&#45;&#45;to ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;pose the inveterate prejudice of the great poet and<lb/> essayist and novelist&#44; and prove his actual ignorance of<lb/> our history and literature.  The good priest did so accomplished that<lb/> task in a series of epistles under the assumed title of<lb/> &#34;letters of certain Jews to Monsieur Voltaire.&#34;  But<lb/> the highest merit of having championed the cause<lb/> of the Jews our brethren in France&#44; and advocated their emanci&#45;<lb/>&#45;pation is due to another Christian prelate.  Eleven<lb/> years before the agitations which culminated into<lb/> the revolution of 1789 began to break out&#44; L&#39;Abbe&#39; Gregoire<lb/> had the courage to publish a work on &#34;the ame&#45;<lb/>&#45;lioration of the condition of the Jews.&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>He was not single&#45;handed in the praiseworthy<lb/> undertaking&#44; others raised arose in helped to vindicate of justice&#44; but he pleaded with such logical<lb/> force&#44; such humanitarian broad sentiments and so un&#45;<lb/>&#45;waveringly that he deserves signally to be pointed<lb/> out.  He asked for the Jews equality before<lb/> the laws of the land&#44; their political promotion&#44;<lb/> their acknowledged right to find wide open every<lb/> avenue which might lead to their industrial<lb/> prosperity.  He never changed sides&#44; when<lb/> France&#44; mad with fanatical atheism&#44; persecuted<lb/> all phases of religion&#44; and terrorized some who<lb/> had ministered in at the Church altar&#44; into a bending before<lb/> the false goddess Reason.  L&#39; Abbe&#39; Gregoire<lb/> kept firm to his convictions.  Uncompromi&#45;<lb/>&#45;singly democratic&#44; he refused even to bow to the<lb/> will of Napoleon Bonaparte&#44; when the wily Corsican dared change<lb/> the consulate into an empire.  We&#44; as Israelites&#44;<lb/> owe that prelate gratitude&#44; and our coreligionists<lb/> of France&#44; holding him in kind remembrance&#44; con&#45;<lb/>&#45;tributed largely a few years ago&#44; when a monu&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment in honor of L&#39; Abbe&#39; Gregoire was raised at Lune&#45;<lb/>&#45;ville&#44; near which city he was born.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>But in America of 1789&#44; when the father<lb/> of his country &#91;&#63;&#93; swore jealously in all solemnity to keep a vigi&#45;<lb/>&#45;lantly eye on watch over the palladium of liberty freedom the Consti&#45;<lb/>&#45;tution&#45;&#45;the Jew had no need of an Abbe&#39; Gregoire.<lb/>  The chiming of the bell on the Philadelphia State<lb/> house&#44; which 15 years before had rung &#34;liberty throughout the land<lb/> unto all the inhabitants thereof&#44;&#34; was had already been the soul&#45;cheer&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing announcement of his our emancipation.  It was<lb/> not by hard struggles and fierce parliamentary<lb/> debates&#44; and the convening of a would be Sunhe&#45;<lb/>&#45;drin under the auspices of an insatiably ambitions<lb/> emperor&#44; that Israelites Hebrews gained human rights in<lb/> the United States.  The declaration which al&#45;<lb/>&#45;lowed all the pursuit of happiness&#44; invited them<lb/> to the feast of sober Reason&#44; not of intoxicated<lb/> Altruism.  Hence&#44; no country in the world has<lb/> seen in a single century so vast an increase of<lb/> Jewish population as free America.  One of her<lb/> cities alone contains more than twice the number of all the Jews throughout France.  Unham&#45;<lb/>&#45;pered in their undertakings&#44; they have reached a degree<lb/> of prosperity scarcely <sic>equalled</sic> anywhere&#44; regarding<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>the number of those who have attained it.<lb/>  If in some State&#44; like New Hampshire&#44; the privilege<lb/> of holding municipal offices had formerly been<lb/> denied to withheld from the Israelite&#44; the proscriptive ruel<lb/> was expunged from the statute book&#33;  At all events&#44; the Hebrews<lb/> who might have settled there&#44; if any existed were not subjected to moles&#45;<lb/>&#45;tation&#44; any more than in any whatever part of these far&#45;reaching climes.  While even this day in Republican France a<lb/> Drumond may issue a second edition of his out&#45;<lb/>&#45;rageous book&#44; here the obscure anonymous scribbler who<lb/> plagiarized Drumond finds his stupid concoctions<lb/> stopped short&#44; as a libel against an unwarrantable attack on an integral portion<lb/> of the American nation.  Let Jews inhabiting the<lb/> fair country upon the Seine and the Loire celebrate the fall<lb/> of the Bastille with a splendid international exposition.<lb/>  We send them greetings and wish them happiness&#44; but&#44;<lb/> as Jews&#44; we have had greater a juster cause to commemorate<lb/> in devotional union the uplifting into the first<lb/> Presidential dignity of the man who so answered responded to the<lb/> Israelites congratulatory address of Savannah after having taken his oath Israelites&#58;<lb/> &#34;May the same wonder&#45;working Deity who long<lb/> since delivered the Hebrews from their Egyptian<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>oppressors&#44; planted them in a promised land&#44; &#38;<lb/> whose Providential agency has lately been conspicuous<lb/> in establishing these United States as an independent<lb/> nation&#44; still continue to water them with the dews<lb/> of heaven&#44; and make the inhabitants of every de&#45;<lb/>&#45;nomination participate in the temporal and spiritual<lb/> blessings of that people&#44; whose God is the Eternal Lord.&#34;<lb/>  That pious wish of the founder of the greatest Repu&#45;<lb/>&#45;blic has been fulfilled.  The seed of Abraham has<lb/> struck root in these genial regions and grown richly<lb/> fruitful.  Admit it&#44; prejudice against the Jew our people<lb/> the Jew exists here also.  and We notice it especially as it creeps out of its hiding place each<lb/> summer season.  How can it be fought against&#63;  Are<lb/> polemics the weapons we shall resort to&#63;  Recrimi&#45;<lb/>&#45;nations and re to against criminations&#44; remonstrances and retalia&#45;<lb/>&#45;tions&#63;  Not so.  We may disarm prejudice&#44; first&#44;<lb/> by a procedure perfectly consistent&#44; avoiding tables<lb/> against which Mosaism protests.  Secondly&#44; by an at&#45;<lb/>&#45;titude proving a high degree of self&#45;respect&#44; which<lb/> must challenge public respect.  In France&#44; Christ&#45;<lb/>&#45;ians do not scruple openly to disregard all the rules of<lb/> their faith.  Unfortunately Generally as spirit of incredulity<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>is astir there&#44; among all classes&#44; and the<lb/> sensible ones who see in the discarding of religious<lb/> restraints great dangers looming up&#44; sound the tocsin.<lb/></p>
            <p>In Paris it has been found necessary to organize an<lb/> anti&#45;atheistical society&#44; of which our illustrious Octo&#45;<lb/>&#45;generian fellow&#45;religionist&#45;&#45;Adolph Francel&#45;&#45;is the chosen President.<lb/>  But in America reverence for attachment to religion&#44; commands the<lb/> regard of even those who do not follow its ceremonial precepts.  Our peo&#45;<lb/>&#45;ple&#44; when away from home&#44; mostly neglect the ob&#45;<lb/>&#45;servances of their belief&#44; and some leave behind the sense<lb/> of propriety which demands deference to our neighbors&#39;<lb/> opinion.  The Jewish Sabbath and the Christian<lb/> Sunday find them engaged in doubtful amusements.<lb/>  In more than one instance the retiring habits&#44; charac&#45;<lb/>&#45;teristic of our mothers&#44; are exchanged for a self&#45;assert&#45;<lb/>&#45;ion that ill&#45;becomes mannerly persons.  Then the loud<lb/> converse&#44; the untidy or gaudy attire&#44; the game and<lb/> the drink&#59; all that conspires to attract unfavorably&#44;<lb/> and breed create antipathies.  Ill&#45;bred persons are met<lb/> in every class of society.  They will be shunned&#44; but<lb/> not pointed at as votaries of a creed denounced as encouraging<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>vulgarity.  We know that its is a <sic>wofully</sic><lb/> worn wrong construction&#44; that it is a libel against Ju&#45;<lb/>&#45;daism which requires of its adherents a modest and consi&#45;<lb/>&#45;derate demeanour &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Be exceedingly humble&#45;minded before every person&#34;<lb/>  But it is not enough that we know it to be really so.  We must<lb/> show it beyond peradventure.  And I would be remiss<lb/> in my duty if I denied that the conduct of some<lb/> of us does provokes adverse criticism&#44; and reflects on the<lb/> reputation of our sacred faith.  On this Sabbath<lb/> when two young brothers of ours attain their reli&#45;<lb/>&#45;gious majority&#44; let me beg of them to be extreme&#45;<lb/>&#45;ly chary that their deportment hereafter and as long as they live may not imperil<lb/> our good name&#44; but that through them Israel<lb/> may be exalted&#44; and considered declared worthy of the<lb/> liberty and independence here enjoyed in this match&#45;<lb/>&#45;less land Republic Republic.<lb/>  &#40;Here an address to the two Bar Mitzva followed&#41;<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
