<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx10FF9_7</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1890-11" source="" attested="yes">November 1890</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_7_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_7_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_7_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_7_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_7_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_7_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_7_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_7_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_7_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_7_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_7_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx10ff9_7_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>7 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. Fifth St.<lb/></p>
            <p>Philadelphia November &#47;90<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>90<lb/></p>
            
            <p>About woman&#39;s position in the synagogue<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;A word in time how good it is&#33;&#34;  So taught an Orient&#45;<lb/>&#45;al king in a book essentially Oriental in language&#44;<lb/> in style&#44; and in the figures of speech profusely employed.<lb/>  The book of Proverbs&#44; whose every maxim almost&#44; has<lb/> a priceless value&#44; personifies wisdom in a woman&#39;s<lb/> from.  Represented in that guise&#44; it placed her<lb/> preeminently as in the act of persuading men to fol&#45;<lb/>&#45;low her touching guide and thus attain happiness &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  Now.  &#34;I lead in the way of righteousness&#44; within the path of justice&#34; she cries.  If but<lb/> that only &#91;&#63;&#93; circumstance could be cited&#44; it would suf&#45;<lb/>&#45;fice to disprove the charge that a female in Israel<lb/> was considered a being inferior to man in social standing rank.  For does it<lb/> stand to reason that an author would use an object&#44;<lb/> looked upon by all as ignoble&#44; for a type of what is<lb/> Divinely noble&#45;wisdom&#63;  Still&#44; Christianity&#44; or<lb/> rather Christians&#44; will persist in declaring that until<lb/> their creed spread far and wide&#44; woman was held<lb/> in a state of degradation.  According to that theory&#44; That untenable theory is grounded on<lb/> the idea that the mother of him who died on Calvary&#44; had those of<lb/> her sex who paid him homage during his life&#45;time&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>raised the female in the estimation of the world&#44;<lb/> and compelled the recognition of her worth.  Well&#58;<lb/> Now&#44; my continuation is not with strangers to my<lb/> faith&#44; though I could easily show that their posi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion lacks foundations.  For&#44; reading without bias the books which<lb/> the Nazarenes regard as sacred&#44; I find that according to their teachings woman<lb/> must acknowledge man as her superior&#59; that she<lb/> must be debarred from speaking&#44; or even praying aloud<lb/> in public&#44; that she must keep her head covered<lb/> in deference to man who is above her in rank in short but namely<lb/> she must obey him as her master.  That those rules are nowhere carried<lb/> out in Christendom&#44; it does not destroy set aside the fact of their existence.<lb/>  However&#44; I have said it&#58; I am not do not feel as if I were called upon to <sic>criticise</sic> my neighbors&#44;<lb/> who are beyond the pale of Judaism.  I shall let<lb/> them enjoy hold to the mistake under which they labor&#44; if it so pleases them.<lb/>  It surely does not harm society.  I will not enter their church to prove them<lb/> in error.  But my positive duty is with those<lb/> who claim to belong yet to the Synagogue.  Their<lb/> minds I must disabuse in to the vindication of truth Jewish truths.  Therefore I say repeat with Solomon &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;A word in time&#44; how good it is&#33;&#34;  When my<lb/> brethren in Israel are categorically told that persons<lb/> who adhere to Oriental usages&#44; depreciate woman&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>and that to raise her to a higher plane&#44; as she<lb/> deserves&#44; we ought to break down the bridge that connects the past with the present and act like men who live in<lb/> the West and not in the East&#44; a disproval of such assertions is<lb/> seasonable and fitting.  I ask&#58; why expose conservative Jews to contumely&#63;  Why point so<lb/> triumphantly to our separation of the sexes in the synagogue&#44; as a re&#45;<lb/>&#45;flection on our mothers our wives&#44; and sisters our wives and daughters as an indication of man&#39;s contempt&#44; when<lb/> it is solely and simply an endeavour to allow<lb/> the mind to be centred on the worship&#44; and prevent&#44; as far<lb/> as possible&#44; to prevent its being directed to human<lb/> objects mutually attractive&#63;  Let us consult history.  Was it because<lb/> women were despised&#44; that Miriam drew those<lb/> of her own sex after her&#44; rehearsing the burden<lb/> of the song to which the men had previously attuned<lb/> their hearts&#63;  Or was it because women were<lb/> deemed unworthy of hailing the conquering hero&#44; as with<lb/> well as men man&#39;s national pride&#44; that they came forth with timbrels&#44; and<lb/> sang &#34;Saul slew his thousands&#44; and but David his<lb/> tens of thousands&#34;&#63;  No&#58; the Oriental usage is not<lb/> to be stigmatised as a vestige of barbarism&#44; in the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>face of such precedents&#59; in the face of demonstrable evidences of equality of the sexes as<lb/> our Scriptures produces&#59; in the face of such historic<lb/> personages as our Hannah&#44; our Deborah our Hannah and<lb/> Haldah&#45;&#45;leading characters in Holy Writ.  No<lb/> disparagement indeed is intended meant by us&#44; who<lb/> welcome woman as a coworshipper.  The Synagogue<lb/> system which we left unchanged as traditionally received&#44; is not meant<lb/> as a debasement by us&#44; who value her woman&#39;s influence<lb/> in communal work.  It offends hurts me<lb/> to hear the would be liberals call us unprogressive&#44;<lb/> Orientals by reason of a benediction&#44; which our ritual<lb/> has embodied&#44; as if when I pronounce it I in&#45;<lb/>&#45;tend to disgrace her to whom I owe my earthly exist&#45;<lb/>&#45;ence&#44; my earliest sustenance&#44; the endearments of my<lb/> childhood&#44; her whom I gratefully most reverentially acknowledge as<lb/> my first guide&#44; educator&#44; and most trustiest friend.<lb/>  Forbid it God&#33;  Just because I know the pains&#44; an&#45;<lb/>&#45;xiety&#44; sacrifices which my mother had to endure&#44;<lb/> and because her nature shut against her pursuits<lb/> which man can follow at pleasure&#44; and because the<lb/> observance of a number of religious practices&#44; that man<lb/> alone can perform&#44; were not within unavoidably placed beyond her reach&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>therefore I conform to the Rabinnical saying&#44; ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;pressing thanks for my not having been created a woman.<lb/>  Were I absolutely ignorant of what the oriental authors of<lb/> the benediction which apparently so scandalizes our Occidentals&#44; have<lb/> written in the to the exaltation of woman&#44; I might brand<lb/> that benediction in our prayer book as an insult to a Jewess&#44; but the<lb/> same writers have left imparted lessons so deferential to the female&#44;<lb/> that I can never accuse them of exposing her to con&#45;<lb/>&#45;tempt.  Are they Is it not the Rabbis who said<lb/> that a man&#39;s wife must elicit from her hus&#45;<lb/>&#45;band the highest degree of respect&#63;  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;  To guard against giving a wife oc&#45;<lb/>&#45;casion for grievance&#44; is recommended by them under in<lb/> the consideration of the fact that the tenderness of her feelings<lb/> intensifies her moral sufferings.  To be heedful<lb/> of our obligations to the main guardian of our<lb/> home&#44; is another of their aphorisms&#44; for they<lb/> wisely contend that blessings rest on the house&#45;<lb/>&#45;hold through the exertions of the wife.  It were<lb/> well that those who boast of their Occidentalism&#44;<lb/> followed in their da relia relations of life such ma&#45;<lb/>&#45;xims as have reached us from the Orient.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>But without fatiguing my hearers with numerous quotations<lb/> to in support of my argument&#44; I shall draw attention<lb/> to the prophetic section Haftorah of this Sabbath&#44; as that<lb/> which offers a conspicuous illustration of my position. decisive proof of support the soundness of my reasoning.<lb/>  At Shunem&#44; a city belonging to the tribe of Josachar&#44;<lb/> lived an Israelite and his wife.  They deservedly enjoyed a competence&#44;<lb/> and for at a period which our sacred annals describe as one<lb/> of general defection from religious duties&#44; that man and<lb/> the woman of his affection kept faithful.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> or hospitality&#44; was had been a prominent trait in the<lb/> conduct of the founder of our people.  Abraham&#44; the<lb/> noble Oriental&#44; who generously entertained strangers&#44;<lb/> taught us that virtue&#44; which has ever since distinguish&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed his seed&#44; though largely scattered through the Occident.<lb/>  Shunem was a resting place to Elisha&#44; who <sic>travelled</sic><lb/> in the interest of the faith&#44; when God&#39;s ministry meant<lb/> more than a stationary office in a specific spot.  The<lb/> married wealthy &#91;&#63;&#93; Jewess of means at Shunem&#44; had noticed the venerable<lb/> prophet as he passed through her city&#44; and had sent<lb/> a message&#44; telling that her home was open to him&#44; and<lb/> that she would feel honored to have him so distinguished a guest and his attendant<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>seated at her table.  Elisha accepted the offer.<lb/>  Shortly after&#44; the woman&#39;s kindly instincts suggested<lb/> a better manner to pay homage to the distinguished illustrious<lb/> visitor.  She proposed to her husband to have a room<lb/> purposely built&#44; with suitable furniture&#44; and to<lb/> present it to the prophet for his exclusive use&#44; when&#45;<lb/>&#45;ever he stopped at Shunem.  All know the<lb/> sequel&#59; how Elisha&#44; touched by her goodness&#44; exercised and moved by and illumined by his<lb/> prophetic powers vision&#44; promised the barren wife that her<lb/> advancing years would be gladden cheered by the love of a child&#59;<lb/> how the boy having grown&#44; fell suddenly sick to death&#59; to his how the mother<lb/> mother&#39;s suppressed her keenest sorrow&#44; how and without telling acquaint&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing her husband with the sad event&#44; she bid him farewell for the day<lb/> and went in search of Elisha&#59; how moved by his <sic>intreaties</sic>&#44;<lb/> the prophet accompanied the afflicted mother parent to the city&#44;<lb/> and how the lad was restored to life.  But the<lb/> point to which I specially wish to submit is the<lb/> fact strikingly evident through the whole narrative.<lb/>  The wife is the central figure in the entire transaction.<lb/>  She is represented by the historian as the leading<lb/> spirit in the house.  She suggest&#44; she advises&#44; she acts&#44; and<lb/> her husband&#44; with implicit reliance&#44; approves.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>How untrue then it is that as an deliberately odious segregation&#44; origi&#45;<lb/>&#45;nating in the Orient&#44; we&#44; conservative Israelites&#44; place<lb/> women behind lattices&#44; and forbid them all contact with<lb/> sacred things&#33;  Eastern Islamism has veiled the face<lb/> of woman&#59; it has made of her a &#91;&#63;&#93; or a slave.<lb/>  Not to Judaism&#45;&#45;the Judaism of our Bible and traditions.<lb/>  That system of religion to which we adhere has allowed<lb/> women the free exercise of volition within the limits<lb/> of discretion and suitably to the dictates of wisdom.  From the days of the mother of our race&#44;<lb/> concerning whom the voice of inspiration said advised &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Whatever Sarah sayeth to thee&#44; hearken<lb/> unto her voice&#44;&#34; even to our own days&#44; the Jewess has<lb/> proved the main factor in the right government of the<lb/> household.  There she must be acknowledged queen&#59; there she has ruled among Jews&#44; not because of the boasted Occidental pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;gress but in conformity with our Oriental origin and<lb/> Hebrew civilization.  The accusation against we us&#44; we heed may worry<lb/> not some.  It is vexatious&#44; but we can stand the bantering charge&#44; in the conviction that our<lb/> coworshippers who are not males&#44; believe that we duly<lb/> value their every exertion in behalf of our common<lb/> faith belief faith&#44; and of all which is promotive of edu&#45;<lb/>&#45;cation and of the real exaltation of Israel.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>Here followed an address to a Bar Mitzvah.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
