<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF10_4</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_4_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_4_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_4_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_4_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_4_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_4_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_4_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_4_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_4_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_4_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_4_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_4_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_4_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_4_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_4_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff10_4_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>14 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>On the childhood of Moses<lb/>
                for Parashat Shemot<lb/>
                &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>The birth of Hezekiah was announced in language<lb/> that thrilled a nation with joy.  Prophecy&#44; which the<lb/> plastic mind of Isaiah&#44; moulded in a form unequally unsurpassingly<lb/> sublime&#44; so described the nativity of Judah&#39;s righteous king&#58;<lb/> &#34;The people that walk in darkness&#44; have seen a great light&#44;<lb/> upon them that dwell in the land of the shadow of death&#44;<lb/> brightness hath shone.&#34;  But who announced the birth<lb/> of the Crowning glory of mankind&#63;&#45;&#45;Of that being whose<lb/> brow wore a sparkling diadem set thereupon by the<lb/> hand of the Divinity&#63;  Methinks&#44; the morning stars must<lb/> have then sung together&#44; Cherubim and Seraphim must have made<lb/> the vaults of heaven ring with their shouting.  Yet&#44; on<lb/> earth an ominous silence kept unbroken.  In the<lb/> streets of Goshen none dared breathe the tidings &#34;A son<lb/> has been given to Amram.&#34;  Suppressed sobbing ushered<lb/> into the world that doomed child.  His mother had ar&#45;<lb/>&#45;dently wished that sorrow might come not night to her<lb/> home.  For a daughter she doubtless besought the God of life&#45;&#45;<lb/>For a daughter&#44; whom fierce tyranny would not snatch from<lb/> her breast&#44; and cast into the Nile.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Human shortsightedness&#33;  How often thou lookest<lb/> for happiness&#44; when unhappiness lies hidden.  How<lb/> very often what thou wouldst that it be driven back<lb/> as an unmitigated evil&#44; carries in its train incalculable good&#33;<lb/>  A divine <sic>fulfilment</sic> of Jochebed&#39;s <sic>prayful</sic> longing&#44; might<lb/> have hindered for ages the march of civilization.<lb/></p>
            <p>The wheel of progress&#44; rolling now with unwonted ra&#45;<lb/>&#45;pidity&#44; might still be clogged through ignorance of<lb/> the grand principles established for its motion by him<lb/> who stood on the top of Sinai.  Fellow&#45;Israelites&#33;  Not<lb/> alone we&#44; the acknowledged disciples of Moses&#44; but the en&#45;<lb/>&#45;lightened millions&#44; who owe their national advancement to<lb/> the moral code he promulgated&#44; must bless the hour in<lb/> which that mother gave birth to that son.  None<lb/> could then in fitting language proclaim the momentous<lb/> event&#44; but a light that suddenly burst forth became the<lb/> herald of a glorious future.  That light which&#44; as an<lb/> olden legend tells&#44; illumined the dwelling of Amram&#59; that<lb/> light&#45;&#45;typical of the Mosaic revelation&#45;&#45;has spread far and<lb/> wide&#59; and it will finally reach the darkest spots on earth&#44; till<lb/> all the inhabitants thereof walk in its reflection.  Then<lb/> will men will call themselves &#34;brethren&#34; in the true spirit of the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>legislator who taught the unity of the Great<lb/> Creating Cause&#44; and the unity of the human race.<lb/>  It is Israel&#39;s privilege to reckon in the line of a noble<lb/> ancestry&#44; the noblest creature that ever woman bore.<lb/>  And as a loving child delights to relate what the has<lb/> heard of the early days of his sires&#44; so does my mind<lb/> feel prompted by what we have just perused to dwell<lb/> awhile on the infancy of our deliverer&#44; leader and law&#45;<lb/>&#45;giver.  Let us&#44; my friends&#44; recall this day what we<lb/> have learnt in the opening pages of the second book of inspi&#45;<lb/>&#45;ration.  I am aware that the history of every<lb/> individual&#44; whose genius or military prowess influenced<lb/> mankind&#44; has always received a high colouring from a pencil<lb/> dipped in fiction.  But notwithstanding that Josephus<lb/> gives currency to many a tale derived from popular traditions<lb/> concerning the childhood of Moses&#44; and that Philo the Jew<lb/> presents it in a mystic garb&#44; I will divest it of whatever<lb/> may sound fabulous&#59; yet&#44; I believe that Jochebed&#39;s infant<lb/> son must have shown signs of supernatural greatness&#44; and<lb/> that they became a direction to his mother in the course she pursued.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>The time arrived&#44; when she could no longer elude<lb/> the watching of Pharaoh&#39;s cruel officers&#44; and she resolved<lb/> that she would&#44; herself&#44; entrust the existence of her babe to<lb/> those waters&#44; which had bereaved many a Hebrew mothers.<lb/>  But gazing upon that countenance so calm&#44; and so deeply<lb/> expressive&#44; a flash of her son&#39;s latent spirit flitted before<lb/> her vision.  She had doubtless heard&#44; how God had in the days<lb/> of yore&#44; had delivered a righteous man from an overwhelming<lb/> flood&#44; and she prepared with her own hands&#44; an ark&#44; which&#44;<lb/> like that of Noah&#44; might remain afloat.  What feelings<lb/> struggled within her bosom &#91;inserted above&#58; breast&#93;&#44; when seeking the winding shore&#44;<lb/> she clasped the smiling boy to her bosom&#44; pressed upon his lips a soft ma&#45; the warmest<lb/> &#45;ternal kiss and laid him on the Nile&#44; mothers alone can tell.<lb/>  But faith stood beside her&#44; and whispered comfort hope.<lb/>  Call it a presentiment&#44; apply to it whatever name your<lb/> minds suggest&#44; but certain it is that events have hap&#45;<lb/>&#45;pened&#44; which were foreshadowed to our soul&#44; while not yet<lb/> <sic>developped</sic>.  An inward voice&#44; which Jochebed inter&#45;<lb/>&#45;preted as a message from on high&#44; assured her that<lb/> the billows would not sweep away the frail vessel&#44; which<lb/> held her dearest treasure.  Strengthened by so comforting a<lb/> belief&#44; she had ventured upon a course&#44; which&#44; under ordinary<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>circumstances&#44; would must have rendered the death of her darling<lb/> greatly more painful.  For&#44; to pine away for want of natural<lb/> food&#44; would have been infinitely worse than to find a grave<lb/> quickly in the deep.  But she did not fear so fatal<lb/> an issue.  Mark&#44; my Brethren&#33;  It is not said written that she<lb/> set her young daughter afar off to learn&#44; what would be<lb/> the end of her infant brother.  No&#58; she felt that he would<lb/> be spared&#59; that an invulnerable shield encompassed his existence.  His speaking eyes had so said&#44; but throbbingly she awaited to hear &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;What would be done with him&#34; that is&#44; by what extraor&#45;<lb/>&#45;dinary means would his deliverance be wrought.  You<lb/> know the sequel.  But can you tell what force was<lb/> that which impelled a princess to openly disregard the<lb/> will of her royal parent&#63;  Had she not been taught<lb/> that compassion for the Hebrews was treason to the State&#63;<lb/>  That the unprecedented increase of that people of foreign<lb/> descent&#44; had become a torment to all Egyptians&#59; their<lb/> constant dread&#33;  Aye&#58; Pharaoh&#39;s daughter may have<lb/> shared the inimical spirit which had enslaved a noble<lb/> race of men&#44; and now sought their extermination&#44; but<lb/> she could not resist the power of that angel&#45;like countenance upturned towards hers.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>Marvellous features&#44; that could so deeply affect<lb/> a being trained in an Egyptian palace&#33;  Was it their beauty&#44;<lb/> which exercised that mighty influence&#63;  The lo comeliness<lb/> of the child&#39;s form might have attracted the attention of<lb/> the princess&#44; but she would not&#44; assuredly&#44; have braved&#44;<lb/> because of it&#44; the wroth of her father.  For&#44; by adopting<lb/> as her own son&#44; the scion of a stock he had determined to<lb/> root out&#44; she had set the Ruler of Egypt at defiance&#44;<lb/> and stirred up the hearts of his subjects to rebellion.  But<lb/> prudence&#44; expediency&#44; cool reason&#44; whatever might have dictated<lb/> a different course was set cast aside.  A look of that eyes a visage<lb/> which a heavenly fire illumined&#44; overpowered all other sen&#45;<lb/>&#45;timents save that of becoming a mother to that machless&#91;sic&#63;&#93;<lb/> child.  The allegorical saying of our ancient teachers&#44; can<lb/> truly in this instance be applied to the letter.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; Pharaoh&#39;s daughter beheld the Divinity at<lb/> the hour she first met the face of Moses.  Feelings to<lb/> which she may hitherto have been a stranger&#44; seized her<lb/> powerfully mightily.  That Hebrew infant held her irresistibly<lb/> in his control.<lb/></p>
            <p>The disciples of a school&#44; that attribute to chance whatever sees no Divine interposition in the<lb/> befalls affairs of mankind&#44; deny unto Moses any supernatural gifts.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>They insist that he owed his safety to an instinct<lb/> natural to human creatures&#44; and the renown acquired in<lb/> after&#45;life to the exceptional manner in which he was<lb/> educated.  I readily admit the efficacy of both those<lb/> agencies.  I concede that pity did mingle with the feelings<lb/> that moved the princess to rescue a babe from impending<lb/> danger&#44; for we are so explicitly told in Holy Writ &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;she had compassion on him&#34; I grant likewise&#44; that the<lb/> teaching obtained at the royal courts must have ripened<lb/> all his high faculties&#44; for&#44; the Sages assert that &#34;prophecy<lb/> can rest only upon the wise&#45;hearted&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> But I maintain withal that unless a spark of a<lb/> heavenly flame had shone upon the visage countenance of him destined<lb/> to humanize the world&#44; he would not have become the<lb/> object of the the most cherished solicitudes of from a despot&#39;s daughter&#59;<lb/> nor would Moses have gained an instruction reserved solely<lb/> for a privileged caste.  Nothing short of a peremptory<lb/> command from the princess&#44; would have forced open for<lb/> him doors most jealously guarded.  For&#44; it is well<lb/> known&#44; that the priests of Egypt were the exclusive<lb/> possessors of learning.  Shrouded under a veil of<lb/> impenetrable mystery&#44; they suffered none but their<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>own numbers to enter their assemblies.  The books they<lb/> wrote were hidden from the people.  The rights of the<lb/> latter consisted in blindly following sacerdotal ordinances.<lb/>  But what was kept from the multitude&#44; became un&#45;<lb/>&#45;folded before the mind of that divinely gifted youth.<lb/>  He fathomed what was profound in science.  He studied<lb/> much and learnt much.  But he sucked the honey<lb/> and not the poison of priestly culture.  His knowledge<lb/> was not that which inspired comp contempt for the masses&#44;<lb/> and makes the heart swell with pride.  Not that knowledge<lb/> which is the arm of tyranny against the humble classes<lb/> and the illiterate&#44; but a knowledge drawn from the book<lb/> of nature&#44; more than from the ponderous volumes of human<lb/> theories and human researches speculations&#44; a knowledge teaching to recognize<lb/> in all men the same origin&#44; the same capacity for moral<lb/> elevation&#44; a knowledge that pleads for the right of every<lb/> sentient being to be enlightened when ignorant&#44; assisted<lb/> when poor&#44; defended when maltreated.  That knowledge<lb/> pervaded the soul of Moses&#44; and rendered him the fitted ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;ponent of the will of a Universal God&#44; who loves goodness&#44; and<lb/> hates inhumanity.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>Imbued with it&#44; the inmate of a palace preferred went<lb/> seeking the lowly&#44; those who suffered&#44; to rather than associating with those<lb/> who <sic>weilded</sic> the scepter or the sword.  His advice to the<lb/> latter&#44; might go unheeded&#44; but his kindly words to the<lb/> former might would bring comfort and solace.  Do you then<lb/> wonder&#44; that his anger kindled at the sight of unendurable<lb/> oppression&#63;  Could he calmly look on&#44; while his brother in<lb/> faith&#44; bent under a heavy burden&#44; had his flesh torn by<lb/> the rod of a task&#45;master&#63;  Was it not a righteous indi&#45;<lb/>&#45;gnation that incited him to seize the weapon which might&#44;<lb/> in return&#44; strike down that monster&#44; and deliver his fellow&#45;<lb/>Israelite&#63;  Aye&#58; he who was subsequently directed by<lb/> the Lord to write in his code of laws &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Thou<lb/> shalt not stand idly&#44; when thy neighbor&#39;s blood is spilt&#44;&#34;<lb/> could not&#44; without concern&#44; behold the crushing of the inno&#45;<lb/>&#45;cent and the triumphing of the wicked.  Indeed&#44; wherever<lb/> his judgment showed him wrongs&#44; his high nature prompted<lb/> him to rise to their its vindication.  The same spirit of justice<lb/> which made him upbraid the Hebrews&#44; who without provocation gave vent to his<lb/> was about passions by smiting his own coreligionist&#44; stirred up the soul of the noble youth which<lb/> Jethro&#39;s daughters were forcibly held back by the shepherds<lb/> at the well.  It was only when his deeds might have<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>won for him renown&#44; that he would fain have continued<lb/> inactive.  Full of vigour&#44; &#38; of indomitable courage he<lb/> always was&#44; when his Arm could shield the helpless&#44;<lb/> but lowly in spirit and timid to a fault&#44; when sought<lb/> after that he might assume authority.  But humility&#44;<lb/> write our sages&#44; is the sure forerunner of of greatness.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  The monarch of Egypt by<lb/> whose absolute will&#44; millions were trodden down&#44; stood in<lb/> awe before One man.  He dares not aim a blow at his<lb/> life&#44; he dares not even threaten.  His aspect terrifies<lb/> the Ruler&#44; and yet fills him with reverence.  That coun&#45;<lb/>&#45;tenance upon which a majesty divine had been from at the birth&#44;<lb/> been imprinted&#44; that countenance which had animated<lb/> Jochebed and fo strengthened her in faith&#44; that countenance<lb/> which had melted the heart of Pharaoh&#39;s daughter&#44; and made<lb/> her postpone to one of its smiles country and parentage&#44;<lb/> that countenance could not be looked upon without &#91;inserted above &#40;in pencil&#41;&#58; that countenance which at the age of 120 was not furrowed with the marks of decrepitude&#93;<lb/> experiencing profound veneration. &#91;inserted above &#40;in pencil&#41;&#58; but kept fresh and unfaded&#93;  Moses confronted the<lb/> oppressors of his brethren&#44; he warned&#44; he condemned&#44; he<lb/> punished&#44; but none ventured to lay hand upon him.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>And if on the eve of that terrible night&#44; in which<lb/> the angel of death made havoc among the Egyptians&#44;<lb/> their kind bid Moses never reenter his presence&#44; the answer<lb/> given obviously shows that the tyrant who wore a crown<lb/> was powerless&#44; and the messenger of an avenging Deity<lb/> was arrived with in dreaded superhuman strength&#59; as Holy Writ testifies<lb/> when it says &#34;that man Moses was very great in the sight<lb/> of Pharaoh&#39;s servants&#44; and in the sight of the people&#34;.<lb/>  And has he ever ceased to be great&#63;  Search&#44; my Brethren&#44;<lb/> ancient and modern history&#44; call back the names that<lb/> grace the roll of fame&#59; summon together the men of<lb/> a gigantic mind&#44; the <sic>heros</sic>&#44; the statesmen&#44; the poets&#59;<lb/> assemble together the potentates of the East&#44; and the<lb/> sovereigns of the west.  Their glory will pale before the<lb/> halo which surrounds that child of the Hebrew&#45;race.<lb/>  Moses is still great&#44; and his greatness lies in the monu&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment which inspiration has raised to his name.<lb/>  A monument is that which looks down from the distance<lb/> of thirty five centuries&#44; standing unscathed amidst the<lb/> wrecks of monarchies and the crush of empires.  How<lb/> many the forces that combined to destroy it from the<lb/> foundations&#33;  But the missiles of heathenism&#44; the darts<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="13"/>
            <p>of Atheism&#44; and the barbered arrows of infidelity have<lb/> not demolished it.  Human science has been set up<lb/> over against it upon a lofty pedestal&#44; to lessen by contrast<lb/> the height of that venerable monument.  But it still<lb/> towers above all structures that fallible man has raised.<lb/>  Nay&#58; the more intently will the mind gaze upon that<lb/> monument&#44; the more will its surpassing magnificence<lb/> become visible unfurled.  Modern The philosophy of this maternal age bent upon<lb/> stripping Moses of his glory supernatural power&#44; quoting the laws of Mandou<lb/> and Confucius to exhibit therein an equal degree of<lb/> wisdom and of goodness progressive humanity will stop short their investi&#45;<lb/>&#45;gations&#59; they will see and feel that to the son of<lb/> Jochebed preeminently belongs the glory of having&#44; under<lb/> God&#44; cast down the idols of human fancy&#44; and raised<lb/> upon their ruin an altar to the Creator of the universe.<lb/>  That he tore the walks that which divided human beings into<lb/> castes&#44; that he wrenched the weapon of despotism&#44; and<lb/> set an example for freedom loving to follow. a people free.  In a word&#44; Moses was Israel&#39;s first<lb/> instructor in the art of war&#44; first in the art of peace&#44;<lb/> and but he woul was and will ever be the first beacon&#45;light<lb/> leading all to the way of salvation truth and of salvation.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="14"/>
            <p>Faithful disciples of the son of Amram and<lb/> Jochebed&#44; bow in reverence to the memory of one<lb/> so great and so good&#33;<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
