<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx8FF13_25</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx8ff13_25_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx8ff13_25_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx8ff13_25_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx8ff13_25_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx8ff13_26_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx8ff13_26_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx8ff13_27_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx8ff13_27_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx8ff13_27_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx8ff13_27_2v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 3 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>7  I have frequently read that the sagacity and natural<lb/> abilities of our brethren&#44; induced Italian potentates to<lb/> employ them in the days of yore&#44; as superintendents of<lb/> finance&#44; ambassadors at foreign courts&#44; family physicians<lb/> etc&#44; but for want of books that treat on the subject&#44; I<lb/> could not venture to enlarge thereupon.  I can however state&#44;<lb/> with full knowledge&#44; that in 48 Pincherle was secretary<lb/> of Manin&#44; &#38; his selection was not due to his wealth&#44; but to<lb/> his wisdom in counsel &#38; to his patriotism.  The same may<lb/> have happened elsewhere in the Peninsula&#44; yet it is not<lb/> improbable that wealth may in a measure have occasioned<lb/> the advancement&#59; for Mammon has votaries everywhere.<lb/></p>
            <p>9.  The general sky of Italy &#38; its fertile soil have an ir&#45;<lb/>&#45;resistible charm on <del>her</del> its Jewish inhabitants&#59; and though<lb/> heretofore exposed to great vexations&#44; it has not been habitu&#45;<lb/>&#45;al with them to abandon <del>that</del> the dear land of their birth.  But<lb/> when circumstances constrain them to quit it&#44; they generally<lb/> betake themselves to Africa.  To that in Alexandria&#44; Cairo<lb/> Tripoli&#44; Innes&#44; <del>Algeria</del>&#44; the Italian language is consider&#45;<lb/>ed an indispensable acquisition&#44; and is taught alike at the schools<lb/> and privately.  I am not aware of any legal impediments<lb/> to emigration.  None at all events exists in Tuscany&#44; though<lb/> there may be a law to that effect&#44; in the Papal states.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>10.  Hitherto the Italian Jews were wont to purchase<lb/> their exemption from military service by paying for a<lb/> substitute.  And in many cases when the conscript<lb/> was needy the Congregation procured his release.<lb/>  In fact it is doubtful whether the petty kings of Italy<lb/> would entrust the security of their dominions into the<lb/> hands of &#34;unbelievers&#34;&#44; though they were ready to overtax<lb/> them on all occasions.  But a thorough change has<lb/> lately taken place.  Since he has been made to participate<lb/> in the privileges enjoyed by other citizens&#44; the Hebrew<lb/> man feels it a stringent duty to defend his native<lb/> soil&#59; and in the last wars he signalized himself<lb/> by deeds of valour and self&#45;denial.  the &#34;Educatore<lb/> Israelita&#34; a journal devoted to Jewish interests and publish&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed in Vercelli&#44; often chronicle the names of our Sardinian<lb/> Lombard or Tuscan brethren who have been promoted to<lb/> high ranks in the army.<lb/></p>
            <p>11.  It is not an empty boast of the Israelites to<lb/> style themselves &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;the merciful children<lb/> of merciful parents&#34; for whenever they congregate they<lb/> palpably show that charity reigns among them.<lb/>  In Italy&#45;&#45;like in every part of the world&#44; to which<lb/> Providence has sent them&#45;&#45;our brethren support their own<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>poor.  Each city has its various associations&#44; purport&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing of course to perform a different task.  Some have<lb/> for their object the alleviation of bodily suffering&#44; &#38; with<lb/> that design their members devote in turn several hours<lb/> by day and night in attending on the sick.  Some afford<lb/> widowed mothers their maintenance&#44; by procuring for them<lb/> some easy work&#44; for the execution of which they are com&#45;<lb/>&#45;pensated above its actual worth&#59; or if unable to<lb/> ply the needle&#44; through household duties&#44; they are provi&#45;<lb/>&#45;ded with the necessary ailment.  In many instances also<lb/> old individuals and children in their tender years are<lb/> placed in an asylum&#44; and protected against the ills<lb/> concomitant with their ages.  But that which more<lb/> particularly evinces the benevolent disposition of our<lb/> coreligionists in Italy is their free offering for the endow&#45;<lb/>&#45;ments of numberless institutions.  On mournful as well<lb/> as well as on joyful occasions&#44; they esteem it meritorious<lb/> to benefit with their liberal gifts their less favored<lb/> brethren.  It is to thy benign spirit that edu&#45;<lb/>&#45;cational establishments owe their origin and support.<lb/>  It is to it that the son of the indigent&#44; obtains not<lb/> alone food raiment &#38; instruction&#44; but the means to earn<lb/> a respectable livelihood&#44; if he be virtuously inclined.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>It so through it&#44; that in a country when the<lb/> resources are comparatively small&#44; and the Jewish population<lb/> large&#44; we are never shocked by the sigh of the misery which<lb/> is commonly witnessed among the professors of other creeds<lb/> Then again scarcely does a wealthy Israelite forget in<lb/> his will the Congregation to which he has been attached and<lb/> its public Charities.  To convince oneself of this truth&#44; it<lb/> is requisite but to cast a glance against the walls of some<lb/> synagogues&#44; and institutes of learning or beneficence.  Then<lb/> we will read the names of hundreds&#44; who paved their way<lb/> to everlasting happiness as acts of real piety.  Nor can<lb/> the charge of entertaining contracted views touching the<lb/> bestowal of charity be imparted to the Italian Jews&#59;<lb/> for it is not unusual to find that <sic>christians</sic> have<lb/> been the legatees of large bequests.  An instance which<lb/> just now occurs to my mind is that of a Mrs Dillareal<lb/> who <del>left</del> ordered that at her death the sum of about two<lb/> thousand dollars should be distributed among <del>the</del> some<lb/> needy Catholics who resided at Leghorn &#38; Pisa.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>12.  Each city holds in reverence the men whose<lb/> active zeal was productive of moral good to the<lb/> entire community.  Of such&#44; thank God&#44; there has never<lb/> <del>always</del> been a lack in Italy.  But while the<lb/> Avigdor of Nice&#44; the Gallichi of Florence&#44; the Alatra of<lb/> Rome&#44; the Francheth of Leghorn&#44; &#38; so forth&#44; are<lb/> highly respected for the lively interest they evince in<lb/> the welfare of our nation&#44; it would be difficult for<lb/> me ot single out one man&#44; who is dear to the hearts<lb/> of one hundred thousand coreligionists.  Luzzato<lb/> professor at the Rabbinical college of Padua&#44; ought<lb/> certainly to be the pride of the Italian Jews.  Sir<lb/> Moses Montefiore&#44; who was born at Leghorn&#44; &#38; from<lb/> there taken to England&#44; when very young&#44; should<lb/> also be&#44; as <sic>Rabby</sic> Piperno wrote&#44; the glory<lb/> of our peninsular brethren&#44; but I could not confi&#45;<lb/>&#45;dently avouch that such is <del>the</del> a universal feeling.<lb/>  Nor do I remember <del>any</del> among the dead any<lb/> whose memory is revered throughout Italy.<lb/></p>  
            <p>8  My personal experience would prompt me to<lb/> believe that the Hebrew who has attained eminent<lb/> positions&#44; do not abjure their ancestral faith&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>for I am acquainted with a Nunes Vais&#44; physician<lb/> of the Bey of Innes&#44; with a Lombroso&#44; with a Castel Nuove<lb/> and a few others&#44; who have reached in foreign climes the<lb/> station they could never attain in their native country&#44;<lb/> and still acknowledge themselves Jews&#44; and act<lb/> up to the behests of the law.  But my experience is<lb/> not sufficiently extensive to serve a true basis of an<lb/> irrefutable argument&#44; and consequently it is useless.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>&#91;...&#93;took place in Tuscany&#44; may serve as a cri&#45;<lb/>terion to judge of the political condition of the Jews<lb/> in other less favored  <del>Philadelphia 12<hi rend="sup">th</hi></del> <del>1860</del> states.<lb/> But the <del>Dr A. Herchel</del> barrier which separated our<lb/> brethren from their catholic fellow&#45;citizens&#44; has been<lb/> thrown down by the stalwart arms of the Sardinian<lb/> King.  Under his constitution&#44; the Hebrews enjoy<lb/> great immunities&#44; &#38; it will&#44; I believe&#44; depend mainly<lb/> on their own exertions to attain the highest position&#44;<lb/> when all Italy shall&#44; God willing&#44; become one consolid&#45;<lb/>ated power.  They have so far deserved well of their<lb/> adopted country.  They have profusely shed their<lb/> blood&#44; and spend their wealth to free it from<lb/> foreign yoke&#44; &#38; whenever that noble object has been<lb/> compressed&#44; they were rewarded by the recognition of<lb/> their rights&#44; and political preferments.<lb/></p>
            <p>5  So long as priest&#45;craft &#38; Jesuitism bear rule&#44;<lb/> the Hebrew denizens of Italy&#44; cannot hope to be<lb/> estimated only by the standard of their worth&#44; and<lb/> be admitted everywhere into the social circle of men<lb/> how entertain different views on religious dogmas.<lb/>  On the other hand we can easily account for a certain<lb/> reluctance evinced by our brethren to open a free<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>intercourse with the reputed adversaries of our race&#44; but<lb/> if the masses do not associate to the extent <sic>practised</sic><lb/> in other countries&#44; the so called upper class mingle<lb/> together without restraint.  However&#44; the daring<lb/> patriot&#44; who is now working out the final eman&#45;<lb/>&#45;cipation of Italy&#44; will virtually procure her enfran&#45;<lb/>&#45;chisement also from priestly sway.  When with<lb/> the extinction of Popery&#44; the bigotry &#38; fanaticism<lb/> of men will become imbued with more rational &#38; softer<lb/> <del>sinkments</del>.<lb/></p>
            <p>6.  The Italian Jews have acquired excellency in<lb/> all branches of Hebrew literature.  Witness it&#44; the<lb/> Talmudical lexicon of R. Nathan of Rome&#44; the<lb/> commentary of R. Obadiah of Bartenorn on the Mishna<lb/> the Grammatical elucidations of R. Elijah the Levite&#44;<lb/> called the young.  The expositions of Ifarus on<lb/> the Pentateuch.  The learned researches on theology&#44;<lb/> on history &#38; various other topics by Azariah de Rossi.<lb/>  The <sic>phylosophical</sic> work of Del Medego.  The<lb/> ethical productions of Moses H. Luzzatto.  The<lb/> poetical effusions of the same author&#44; and those<lb/> of his highly gifted lineal descendants&#44; down to the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>celebrated David I. Luzzatto of Padua&#44; famous not<lb/> less for his vast erudition&#44; than for his natural talents.<lb/>  Witness it also the versatile genius of Emanuel&#59; and<lb/> that of Leon De Modena.  The disquisitions of David<lb/> Nieto&#44; a theologian and poet&#59; the creations of Aben<lb/> Castello eloquent on the pulpit&#44; &#38;  chaste in Hebrew<lb/> <del>versication</del> composition.  Those of Joseph Almanzi&#44; whose metrical<lb/> biography of Abrabanel&#44; would alone have secured him<lb/> a high rank among modern writers&#59; those of Isaac I.<lb/> Reggio&#44; whose tenderness &#38; elegance of diction have but<lb/> few rivals&#59; and a host of others&#44; who flourished at dif&#45;<lb/>&#45;ferent periods&#44; but tended with <del>almost</del> equal success<lb/> the immense field of our literature.  Nor are the<lb/> Italian Jews strangers to that &#34;del bel passe la&#39;dove<lb/> il si Quona&#34; for many of the aforenamed left incon&#45;<lb/>&#45;testable evidences of their ability in it.  True&#44; they<lb/> cannot boast of a Dante&#59; none of them was even<lb/> crowned with laurels at the Capitol&#44; but they can<lb/> cite a Deborah wife of R. Joseph Ascarelli&#44; who&#44;<lb/> four centuries ago could translate a Hebrew poem into<lb/> the purest Italian.  A Solomon Florentino the sublime<lb/> elegest&#44; honored by the friendship of the greatest literati<lb/> of his age&#44; and a great many more&#44; whose names<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>history has recorded and awarded to them a well earned deserved<lb/> commendation.  And like in literature&#44; so have the Italian<lb/> Jews attained eminence in diverse branches of science&#44;<lb/> especially in medicine&#44; which indeed seems to have been<lb/> with them a favorite study both in ancient &#38; modern times.<lb/>  In commerce they stood prominently wherever they were<lb/> not hampered in its exercise&#44; for instance&#44; in the republic<lb/> of Venice&#59; In Tuscany under the auspices of the Midras<lb/> and even under the dukes of the house of Loraine&#44; the last of<lb/> whom &#40;we hope&#41; was Leopold the second&#44; who deserted his<lb/> past through cowardly fear in the year 1859.<lb/>  The art of printing was scarcely discovered&#44; when the proses<lb/> of Toncino &#38; Bomberger furnished the world with biblical<lb/> rabbinical and secular works.  At the same time ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;peared the famous Ferrara Bible&#44; and to this day<lb/> at Leghorn many volume on various subjects issue<lb/> forth from the Jewish printing offices of Ottolenghi&#44;<lb/> Beltorte &#38; Tubiana.  It would be impossible for me<lb/> to enter into further details on this interesting topic&#44; the<lb/> more so because I chiefly depend on memory for its <sic>descry&#45;<lb/>&#45;sion</sic>&#44; but enough&#44; I trust&#44; has been said to prove that the<lb/> Italian Jews have ever been equal to the requirements<lb/> of the age they lived in &#38; that their labor reflects credit on their<lb/> coreligionists.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
