<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF2_6</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1865" source="" attested="yes">1865</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_6_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_6_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_6_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_6_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_6_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_6_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_6_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_6_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_6_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_6_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_6_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff2_6_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>For the fifth anniversary<lb/>
                of<lb/>
                the 7th st Synagogue<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;  &#34;We will not forsake the<lb/> house of our God&#34;.  Brethren&#33;  The tenth chap&#45;<lb/>&#45;ter of Nehemiah enumerates certain promises&#44; made<lb/> in a solemn assembly&#44; by a large body of liberated<lb/> Hebrews.  It is my opinion that we would greatly<lb/> benefit by meditating on the purport of each of them&#44;<lb/> but as the last of those declarations&#44; fitly stands as a text<lb/> for the subject I propose to discuss&#44; I have quoted it to<lb/> the exclusion of all the others.  The occasion&#44; whose<lb/> anniversary moves me to speak at the present season&#44;<lb/> is yet fresh in your memory.  For&#44; you participated<lb/> in its festivity.  Five years ago we devoted<lb/> this handsome edifice to the service of Israel&#39;s God.<lb/>  The ceremony accompanying the dedication was impo&#45;<lb/>&#45;sing&#59; the number of eager attendants unprecedentedly<lb/> large.  But what promises did the important<lb/> occurrence draw from the vast multitude&#63;<lb/>  Did they also vow never to forsake the house<lb/> of our God&#63;...My friends&#33;  Past circumstances<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>suggest a ready answer&#44; but I fear to express it&#45;&#45;<lb/> It is&#44; seemingly&#44; my misfortune to shape English<lb/> sentences in a manner open to misconstruction.<lb/>  Hence is the influence I much desire to exercise for<lb/> good&#44; altogether denied me.  Shall I then give<lb/> utterance to what may produce a contrary effect<lb/> to that intended&#63;  No&#44; I will rather let your own<lb/> hearts give the correct reply.  Justice&#44; however&#44;<lb/> impels me candidly to state&#44; that the marked improvement<lb/> in the hitherto declining finances of the Congregation&#44;<lb/> is due more to the energetic exertions of a few&#44; than to<lb/> a spirit of pious zeal generally felt.  When<lb/> ruin stood menacing at the gates of our minor<lb/> sanctuary&#44; the strenuous efforts of those few&#44; precluded its<lb/> entrance.  To them will I therefore commend the<lb/> future independence of our venerable institution.<lb/>  Let them stir up among our members who enjoy<lb/> affluence&#44; a determined will to loosen undo the heavy<lb/> burthen which yet weighs it down.  To cancel&#44; I say&#44;<lb/> an obligation the existence of which robs God of a portion<lb/> of that which we professedly to have entirely and absolutely<lb/> offered in honor to His name.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Verily&#44; if their endeavours prove now a failure&#59; they<lb/> will never meet with success.  The fluctuation in the<lb/> monetary system of this country&#44; and the uncertain<lb/> issue of impending events&#44; which last year were alleged<lb/> by some&#44; as a reason for their refusing rejecting my humble appeal&#44; can<lb/> no more withhold the hand of liberality.  Yet a short<lb/> while&#44; and the promissory notes of our stable government&#44;<lb/> will be accepted in preference to the coinage of precious<lb/> metals.  Let those who have command over that<lb/> spring of wealth&#44; be therefore exhorted to incline it toward<lb/> this hallowed spot.  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>  &#34;Bring ye all the tithes unto the treasury&#44; that there<lb/> may be provision in my house&#44; and prove me now by this&#44;<lb/> sayeth the Lord of hosts&#59; if I will not open for you the<lb/> windows of heaven&#44; and pour you out a blessing&#44; which<lb/> exceeds all limits.&#34;  Essay it&#44; O my beloved hearers&#33; and<lb/> your expectations will not be frustrated.  The opulent<lb/> will then experience the satisfaction of having gratefully<lb/> remembered the author of their temporal promotion&#44; and we<lb/> who stand here to supplicate the throne of grace&#44; will<lb/> exalt&#44; because this dwelling shall be in all truth&#44; the house<lb/> of our God.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Such is&#44; my Brethren&#44; the cherished desire of my<lb/> heart&#44; and its accomplishment I deem also essential<lb/> to the preservation of our character and standing&#59; never&#45;<lb/>&#45;theless it is not so all&#45;absorbing&#44; as to render me oblivious<lb/> of other important requisites in our conduct towards this<lb/> Synagogue.  The Sages of Israel prescribe as<lb/> the means of prolonging life&#44; an early attendance<lb/> at public worship &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/>  But apart from the merit which our eagerness in<lb/> sowing the Creator&#44; may obtain for us&#44; a sense of<lb/> propriety ought to urge the necessity of that course.<lb/>  To join in the prayers after the Reader is far advanced<lb/> in their recital&#44; evinces a heedlessness prejudicial to our<lb/> children&#39;s cl religious habits.  It likewise abstracts the<lb/> mind from its devotion&#44; by involuntarily directing it to those who<lb/> are passing before us&#44; or pressing us around.  It&#44; not<lb/> unfrequently&#44; creates feelings that jar with the<lb/> sentiments which a consecrated spot ought to engender&#44;<lb/> and that&#44; by reason of the title claimed by the<lb/> last comer to a seat already occupied.  It detracts<lb/> from the solemnity of our holy communion&#44; whereby<lb/> the unction we might derive from it&#44; is never experienced.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>These reflections&#44; however&#44; do not appear to have<lb/> struck the mind of many among my audience&#44;<lb/> else the constantly varying scene of fresh visitors&#44;<lb/> would not be witnessed there where a uniformity of attend&#45;<lb/>&#45;ance is demanded.  To remedy this evil&#44; which<lb/> has become rife in our midst&#44; it occurred to me&#44; that<lb/> when I announce the hour at which Sabbath commences&#44;<lb/> I might opportunely remind then my brothers and<lb/> sisters of the hour at which the morning service<lb/> of the seventh day begins&#44; for&#44; really it might be<lb/> presumed that they act wrongly through ignorance&#44;<lb/> or that they have forgotten the existing regulations.<lb/>  Know ye&#44; my friends&#33; that those who enter our sacred<lb/> habitation at eleven o&#39;clock have delayed too long<lb/> the performance of their duty&#59; they who present them&#45;<lb/>&#45;selves hither at ten&#44; are also dilatory&#44; but that<lb/> punctuality&#44; according to the rules of this Congregation&#44;<lb/> means&#44; to bow reverently towards our holy oracle&#44; as<lb/> the clock strikes nine.  Is the appointed time so<lb/> unseasonable that it encroaches on that of our<lb/> natural rest&#63;  On the contrary&#44; those who are con&#45;<lb/>&#45;versant with Rabbinical laws&#44; will rightly say&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>that its lateness is an infringement of them.<lb/>  It may be now inexpedient to alter it&#44; but none should<lb/> be absent when it arrives.  Cases may exist in which<lb/> a conformance with even so convenient a regulation&#44; will<lb/> be found impossible&#44; but though we may be willing<lb/> to overlook such&#44; as unavoidable exceptions&#44; we must<lb/> condemn tardiness when it has become a general practice.<lb/>  It is but little that we can offer in return for unceasing<lb/> favors.  Let us show&#44; at all events&#44; readiness in offering<lb/> homage to the Guardian of our existence.  We have<lb/> reared to His glory this comely habitation&#44; we must <sic>fulfil</sic><lb/> the duties flowing from its existence.  Brethren&#33;<lb/>  Your early calls at this shrine&#44; shall be preceded by<lb/> free&#45;will offerings for its maintenance&#59; then you will<lb/> have proven beyond refutation that&#44; like your ancestors&#44;<lb/> the contemporaries of Nehemiah&#44;&#45;&#45;it is your steadfast<lb/> resolve never to forsake the house of our God.<lb/>  But not less than punctuality is regularity likewise<lb/> a primary requisite in our demeanour towards the<lb/> Synagogue.  To visit these devoted courts at intervals&#44;<lb/> it is not to exhibit affection for Him&#44; whose Divine<lb/> presence sanctifies them.  The objects we love&#44; we seek<lb/> with earnest constancy.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;I rejoice when they say unto me&#44; let us go to the<lb/> house of the Lord&#44;&#34; exclaims the royal shepherd.<lb/>  Not the fear of impending dangers&#44; not the strokes of<lb/> affliction&#44; but the joyous thought of raising our voice<lb/> with that of a vast multitude&#44; exalting their heavenly Father&#44;<lb/> should induce us to wend our steps towards this Tabernacle<lb/> of the Lord.  With unutterable satisfaction<lb/> I discover the removal of one great obstacle against<lb/> the increase of our faithful attendants.  And I as I contem&#45;<lb/>&#45;plate the happy change I bless them who has moved<lb/> the heart of some among my hearers&#44; to set a higher value<lb/> upon the Divine word than on perishable goods.<lb/></p>
            <p>Verily&#44; my Brethren&#33; every revolving Sabbath shall add<lb/> a gem of ever&#45;shining lustre to the crown reserved<lb/> for your spiritual glorification.  You have repressed your mortified covetous&#45;<lb/>will&#44; for the sake of the Lord&#44; &#45;ness to please your Maker&#44; and you shall be counted among<lb/> the his righteous servants.  But in order to obtain that priceless re&#45;<lb/>&#45;ward&#44; you must employ the day you honor&#44; agreeably<lb/> to its sacred origin.  Our religion does not demand<lb/> that it shall be devoted entirely to deep meditation&#44;<lb/> but we are recommended to render the sabbath a delight&#44;<lb/> by ceasing thereon from worldly pursuits&#44; by raising<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>our thoughts above material gain&#44; by being entertained<lb/> with higher subjects than earthly vanities.  And surely<lb/> you cannot better carry into action this advice of the inspired<lb/> Isaiah&#44; than by joining betimes these weekly gatherings of<lb/> Israelites.  Here will your hearts be warmed by devotional<lb/> fervor&#59; your minds be enlightened by words of instruction.<lb/>  For none is so pure that cannot benefit from the ardency<lb/> of prayer&#44; none so learned that cannot profit from the<lb/> lessons drawn at the fountain of truth.  If you are strong<lb/> in faith&#44; you will be confirmed therein.  If you are<lb/> possessed of knowledge&#44; you may hear perhaps what will<lb/> awaken a new and wholesome ideas.  But unto<lb/> your sons and daughters will your regular and punctual<lb/> attendance at the synagogue&#44; be hereafter of infinite advantage.<lb/>  The presence of their parents&#44; whose all doings nature<lb/> taught them to believe perfect&#44; will inspire with inextin&#45;<lb/>&#45;guishable love for the day of the Lord&#44; and with reverence<lb/> for public worship.  It will create in them feelings of<lb/> obedience to Scriptural behests&#44; and of brotherly union with<lb/> their people.  Impressed by your example&#44; they will in<lb/> turn strive that a decorous demeanour and a liberal<lb/> spirit may establish the foundation of our holy house&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>and exalt the dwelling of the God of Jacob.<lb/>  Your memory will then be perpetuated in your children&#39;s<lb/> goodly deeds&#44; while their own happiness will be enhanced<lb/> in proportion as they adhere to your early tuition &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;When thy offspring are taught<lb/> of the Lord&#44; their peace will greatly augment&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;Not only thy Hebrew children shall they alone be called&#44;&#34;<lb/> say the Rabbins&#44; &#34;but parents and architects of Jewish<lb/> greatness among the family of nations.&#34;  So may it be.<lb/> Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
