<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx13FF16_8</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_8_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_8_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_8_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_8_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_8_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_8_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_8_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_8_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_8_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_8_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_8_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx13ff16_8_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>8 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>To urge youths to attend service<lb/>
                during Omer time.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  On Sunday last&#44; on announcing the hour of<lb/> service for the week&#44; I expressed the desire that during the<lb/> period intervening between the end of Passover and the festival<lb/> of Pentecost&#44; the requisite number with whom to hold divine<lb/> service every evening might not be lacking.  That wish&#44; however&#44; has<lb/> thus far been unfulfilled&#59; hence I venture to give it utterance<lb/> once more.  I can readily understand the motive &#91;&#63;&#93; causes which<lb/> they against hinder the assembling of our people in this country here for<lb/> devotional purposes on working days&#44; and it would be un&#45;<lb/>&#45;reasonable in me&#44; who appreciate those motives&#44; to persistently<lb/> ask for what is not feasible&#44; or&#44; for that which&#44; at least&#44;<lb/> presents serious difficulties.  When Israelites&#44; connected<lb/> with the congregation&#44; resided nearer to the then existing<lb/> synagogue&#44; then attending it daily when at the season of counting Omer<lb/> did not involve occasion fatigue&#44; nor the disturbing of domestic ar&#45;<lb/>&#45;rangements.  After the evening meal&#44; some among<lb/> my coreligionists joined me in prayers that last a very<lb/> short time.  But now those the men of our faith&#44; scattered through<lb/> this extensive city&#44; having reached their distant home&#44; at<lb/> the end of a day&#39;s labor&#44; feel naturally inclined to remain<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>among the family circle.  And I&#44; admitting the<lb/> claims of the syna house of God to our personal efforts&#44;<lb/> consider it righteousness likewise to give the house in<lb/> which one&#39;s children live the benefit of the presence of its<lb/> head and mine support.  Would his presence exercised promoted<lb/> always a beneficial end&#33;  Would it exercised a happy<lb/> influence&#33;  Not even for the sake of securing public<lb/> worship would I induce a parent to withdraw from holy<lb/> surroundings.  Yet&#44; I am anxious to prevent an old&#45;<lb/>established usage of our religion to full altogether into disuse&#59;<lb/> specially so because when we discontinue it the practice&#44; it<lb/> becomes virtually extinct&#59; for we are those who have alone<lb/> kept it in force.  Formerly&#44; there could be found<lb/> some individuals of our persuasion so situated that their daily attendance<lb/> at the synagogue did not clash with other duties&#44; and<lb/> they seemed to derive pleasure from being enabled to<lb/> complete the necessary number.  But most of them<lb/> have gone to their long home&#44; and their departure has<lb/> left quite a gap in our midst.  To whom shall I<lb/> then turn for cooperation in my endeavours to fill up<lb/> that void&#63;  I know of none who can better give<lb/> me assistance on that score than our young brethren<lb/> who have within late years assumed the performance<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>of our religious ordinance&#59; I mean&#44; our numerous Bar<lb/> Mitzvah lads.  They might devote a half hour at the<lb/> closing of the day to the continuance of one of our obser&#45;<lb/>&#45;vances&#44; even if by so acting they would be compelled to<lb/> set up later than ordinarily&#44; or to rise earlier&#44; in order to<lb/> finish their school task.  It is a slight free&#45;will offering to the<lb/> belief with which they have been initiated&#44; and I crave<lb/> it at their hands as an evidence of their willingness to<lb/> profit by the privilege obtained of being deemed qualified<lb/> to the help in holding up the national worship.  I verily<lb/> think that if some who can reach this sacred spot in a<lb/> few moments&#44; told their companions the character of<lb/> their errand in the evenings of this season&#44; and in the month<lb/> preceding the &#91;&#63;&#93; Jewish New Year&#44; many might fall in the<lb/> line&#44; and I would not have any further cause for<lb/> waiting&#44; often in vain&#44; till one or two needed&#44; came to<lb/> complete the number ten.  For&#44; example is contagious&#44;<lb/> a in good not less than in evil purposes.  Youths will<lb/> copy one an each other in almost every habit&#44; so that we will<lb/> be likely to see those who as associate with the piously&#45;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>inclined grow devout&#44; whereas such who as make friends<lb/> with the heedless and ungodly&#44; will show the effect<lb/> of that baneful circumstance in their general conduct.<lb/>  I therefore call now upon the good&#44; who&#44; I trust are<lb/> not rare among my young hearers.  I call upon them to<lb/> make the exertion of I crave for&#44; in the anticipation that their<lb/> demeanour will be largely imitated.  Specially I address<lb/> myself to him who has stood in your presence this morning.<lb/>  For with that Jewish lad I am intimately acquainted&#44; and<lb/> long have I watched his behaviour.  To him will I therefore speak of a subject which concerns me as well as himself.  My dear young<lb/> brother&#33;  Today you must trod take leave of childhood&#44; and press<lb/> onward to the path of manhood.  Light manners in<lb/> the house of God&#44; the leaving going away and returning at pleasure<lb/> while in it&#44;&#45;&#45;a practice indulged in by some of your<lb/> coevals&#45;&#45;&#44; must be discarded by you from now and hence&#45;<lb/>&#45;forward&#44; as unbecoming of a son of Israel&#44; who has made<lb/> public confession of his belief.  In some old synagogues<lb/> a Rabbinical motto is inscribed over the tablets of the<lb/> ten commandments&#44; standing above placed above the holy Ark.  It<lb/> reads so.  &#34;Know before whom thou standest.&#34;  And in<lb/> the book of books it is written &#34;serve ye the Lord with<lb/> fear&#34;.  Immediately as you bend your head at the<lb/> entrance of this consecrated building&#44; let the knowledge<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>of the all&#45;present Lord who presi promised to be<lb/> with us and bless us&#44; wherever His holy name is mentioned&#44;<lb/> occupy your thoughts&#44; to the exclusion of all foreign ideas.<lb/>  You will be certain then not to break any of the rules<lb/> of propriety.  I said that the topic interests me<lb/> also&#59; and that because the censurable habits and<lb/> attitude of those of your age in the synagogue has been<lb/> commented on&#44; and have been shown as an illustration<lb/> of my incompetency to enforce decorum&#44; and that degree<lb/> of solemnity which ought to exist in our assemblages.<lb/>  But besides your displaying a praise&#45;worthy conduct<lb/> during the worship&#44; you should attend it regularly and<lb/> punctually&#44; for a reason additional to that which<lb/> other youths have for doing so.  You have mentioned<lb/> to me&#44; that your parents design to withdraw you from<lb/> the School&#44; wherein you have learnt the rudiments of the<lb/> sacred tongue&#44;&#45;&#45;of that language which more than any<lb/> other tie has bound strongly together the scattered members<lb/> of our race&#59; and that they wish you thus early to aid them<lb/> in their earl daily pursuits.  Well&#44; then&#44; the Synagogue<lb/> must serve you a double purpose.  It must be the means<lb/> of your communing with the Lord&#44; and also the agency<lb/> of your learning better the language in which national entreaties<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>are poured forth.  Try to follow the Reader&#59; and<lb/> listen attentively to the section of the week&#44; from the<lb/> five books of Moses.  If I am not saying what<lb/> may savor of arrogance&#44; I will assert that that will<lb/> be an excellent exercise&#44; and by it you will acquire<lb/> the facility to mingle your voice with that of your bre&#45;<lb/>&#45;thren in singing rehearsing correctly the Psalms of our David&#44; and<lb/> the compilation of our Ezra.  Follow the advice which<lb/> is now offered from disinterested and kindly motives.<lb/>  Aid me in a holy task&#59; and let me exhort you to<lb/> look upon this day as very important so that its impression may be very lasting&#44; and&#59; without whenever<lb/> you recall it&#44; you may feel as if you had taken a<lb/> pledge upon it to practice justice and righteousness<lb/> towards all your fellow&#45;<sic>travellers</sic> in this pilgrimage<lb/> of life&#44; and to consistently abide by the peculiar di&#45;<lb/>&#45;rections whose observance is binding upon our race&#44;<lb/> as the chosen witnesses of the One God&#44; and the<lb/> standard&#45;bearers of  His truths.  May you also<lb/> experience that one day in these courts is better than a<lb/> thousand elsewhere&#59; you quaff at the pure waters<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>gushing forth from the dwelling of your Lord&#44; even<lb/> the habitation of His Divinity.  And may the<lb/> eyes of the Almighty be open continually upon it by day<lb/> and by night&#44; that no mishaps may occur.  May<lb/> the schemes of the wicked be thwarted&#44; and their evil<lb/> machinations come at naught.  Grant O Lord that<lb/> the place spot in which we gather to offer Thee adoration<lb/> may not again be the scene of plunder.  &#40;The Synagogue<lb/> in 7th St having been robbed of several Sepharim&#45;cloaks&#44; belts &#38;c<lb/> &#38;c on the night of 27th Nissan 636&#41;.  May the hand<lb/> of liberality&#44; restore in its fullness what the hand<lb/> of iniquity has taken away.  Breathe into the<lb/> attendants at this Synagogue&#44; a spirit of generosity<lb/> and they will enrich it with their free&#45;will offerings.<lb/>  And may the prophecy concerning the second Temple be<lb/> verified likewise about our minor Sanctuary&#59; namely<lb/> that the glory of the &#34;I will fill this house with glory saith the Lord of hosts&#34; the<lb/> sliver is mine&#44; and the gold is mine&#44;......and to this<lb/> place will I give peace.&#34;  So may it be&#44; and let us.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
