<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF15_2</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_2_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_2_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_2_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_2_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_2_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_2_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_2_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_2_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_2_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_2_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_2_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff15_2_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>On Terumah<lb/> About schools &#38; synagogues.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
                <p>When this Congregation <sic>worshipped</sic> on Cherry<lb/> street near Third&#44; I expressed at various times a strong wish that<lb/> the Synagogue existing there since the year 1782&#44;<lb/> might be changed for another more suitable&#44; as to<lb/> size&#44; appearance and locality.  Naturally&#44; I<lb/> quoted at some length in supported of my desire David&#39;s sayings and doings.<lb/> in support of my desire For&#44; we are told in the<lb/> scriptures that the shepherd king contrasted&#44; in self<lb/> condemnation&#44; the beauty of his own palace&#44; built of<lb/> choice cedar wood and costly marble&#44; which master<lb/> craftsmen of Phoenicia had prepared constructed for him&#44; with the<lb/> modest Tabernacle set up in the days of Moses&#44; as re&#45;<lb/>&#45;corded in our Parashah.  All familiar with the<lb/> Bible have read also a psalm&#44; in which the sin of<lb/> Jesse&#44; mentions the his vow he had taken not to allow his eyes to<lb/> sleep&#44; nor his eyelids to slumber&#44; until he had sought<lb/> out a fitting spot in honor of the Mighty One of<lb/> Jacob &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> All that are familiar with the Bible have likewise<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="4"/>
                <p>read towards the end of the first book of Chro&#45;<lb/>&#45;nicles&#44; how munificent was David in his gifts<lb/> for the preparation of a gorgeous Temple.  With<lb/> so luminous an example&#44; shining before my memory&#44;<lb/> I considered myself fully justified to urge a<lb/> change for the better.  But soon I had occa&#45;<lb/>&#45;sion to regret my request&#44; for&#44; this comely edifice&#44;<lb/> which I have learnt to love&#44; by reason of a long<lb/> association&#44; was not set up reared&#44; in the manner that I had<lb/> anticipated and hoped for.  I mean&#44; by profuse donations and free&#45;<lb/>will offerings.  Its owes its origin and conti&#45;<lb/>&#45;nuance to borrowed sums&#44; claiming a semiannual<lb/> interest.  I lamented that circumstance and<lb/> my repeated complaints&#44; unwarrantably misin&#45;<lb/>&#45;terpreted&#44; were the cause motive for my being more than once cut to the quick.<lb/>  However&#44; I am grateful to God&#44; because time has<lb/> very largely&#44; if not completely&#44; removed the object<lb/> of my sad disappointment&#44; over three decades and<lb/> a half ago.  But today&#39;s section of the<lb/> Torah has given additional force to the conviction<lb/> that I now entertain.  Brethren.  We do not honor the Al&#45;<lb/>mighty by handsome synagogues.<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="5"/>
                <p>We can glorify the Creator in a humble habitation&#44;<lb/> more acceptably perhaps than in very stately structures.<lb/>  The Midrash relates that when the archprophet<lb/> was commanded to build erect a sanctuary for the Lord<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; Moses was amazed and<lb/> dismayed &#91;Hebrew&#93;.  He asked himself. &#34;Can Dare mortals dare suppose that they can raise<lb/> a dwelling for Him&#44; whose spirit the Universe<lb/> in its measureless vastness cannot hold&#63;&#34;<lb/>  But a voice from on high was heard.  It said. &#34;Not as<lb/> thou thinkest in the ordinance given.  Suffice<lb/> twenty boards on the North side&#44; two on the<lb/> South&#44; and eight on the West.  Over that nar&#45;<lb/>&#45;row circumference&#44; the Sheckinah will hover and<lb/> bid benedictions to rest.&#34;  In fact&#44; immediately<lb/> after the delivering of the Decalogue&#44; we were<lb/> taught that simply an earthen altar&#44; on which<lb/> we might choose to lay our offerings&#44; would<lb/> find acceptance from God &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> for&#44; heavenly blessings were promised to descend&#44; wherever<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="6"/>
                <p>the name of the Lord is mentioned invoked in pure<lb/> sincerity &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Let me not be misunderstood.  I do not deprecate<lb/> the grandeur of the Jerusalem Temple described in the Haftarah to correspond with the Parasha.  That holy shrine It was<lb/> awe&#45;inspiring&#44; but I cannot ignore the circum&#45;<lb/>&#45;stance that after the death of the illustrious son<lb/> of David who reared it&#44; our people chafed under a yoke&#44; too<lb/> heavy to bear.  In very truth&#44; Solomon&#39;s am&#45;<lb/>&#45;bition to embellish his realm with buildings&#44;<lb/> that might ire with each other in surpas&#45;<lb/>&#45;sing magnificence&#44; brought about a disrupt&#45;<lb/>&#45;ion of the compact nation&#44; which his father&#39;s<lb/> heroism had consolidated.  It is plainly so<lb/> stated in Holy Writ&#44; namely&#58; &#34;This is the reason<lb/> of the levy which King Solomon raised&#58; to build<lb/> the house of the Lord and his own house&#44; and &#91;&#63;&#93;<lb/> and the walls of Jerusalem and Chazo and Mi&#45;<lb/>&#45;gidd&#243; and Gezer&#34;...Again&#58; &#34;Solomon built also<lb/> the Nether Choron and Baalath&#44; and Tadmor &#40;in<lb/> Palmyra&#41; in the desert&#44; and all the store cities that<lb/> he had&#44; and cities for his chariots and for his<lb/> horsemen&#44; and whatever Solomon desired to build<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="7"/>
                <p>for his pleasure in Jerusalem and in Lebanon&#44; and<lb/> in all the land of his dominion.&#34;  Neither can<lb/> I ignore the more lamentable circumstance&#44; that<lb/> in later ages the Temple became a misleading<lb/> <sic>fetisch</sic> in the belief cherished by of heedless Israel&#44; who fancied<lb/> that so long as the sacred shrine remained&#44; God<lb/> would not exact justice from a degenerate gene&#45;<lb/>&#45;ration of false notion which just as Jeremiah deplored in his forceful language.<lb/>  &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#34;Ye come and stand before me in this house&#44; on which<lb/> my name is called&#44; and ye say&#44; we are safe to go on<lb/> committing all abominations.&#34;<lb/>  Now to Brethren to change subjected and speak of what concerns our own time and our this land&#58;<lb/> I am often invited to dedicate a Synagogue&#44; and I<lb/> never refuse&#44; if I can&#44; ritually speaking&#44; comply<lb/> with proper consistency.  But though ready to do so&#44; I&#44; as<lb/> frequently&#44; question myself as to the propriety of that<lb/> compliance.  What&#44; if the edifice bearing the ap&#45;<lb/>&#45;pellation of a certain congregation &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#44; does not belong<lb/> to it&#44; even in part&#63;  What&#44; if the ownership can<lb/> be claimed by some organizations&#44; likely Christian&#44;<lb/> or by many private individuals&#63;  A case<lb/> in point was one in which I very lately assisted&#45;&#45;<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="8"/>
                <p>to hold a consecration.  Mark this&#58; within a stone&#39;s<lb/> throw from of that synagogue&#44; another for the<lb/> purpose of daily worship exists&#44; but either<lb/> the ambition of men to of obtaining some high sounding<lb/> title among that Jewish body&#44; or some trifling<lb/> differences in the liturgy&#44; prevented the amalga&#45;<lb/>&#45;mation.  In that instance&#44; our coreligionists&#44; who<lb/> are in humble circumstances&#44; burdened themselves<lb/> with an unnecessary&#45;&#45;and to my mode of think&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing&#45;&#45;with a humiliating indebtedness.  But<lb/> I am assured&#44; that many a pretentious&#44; so<lb/> called &#34;temple&#44;&#34; for the use of rich Hebrews of America&#44; is<lb/> also nearly crushed under the weighted of unbecom&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing mortgages.  These were contracted solely to<lb/> raise splendid buildings&#44; abounding in luxurious<lb/> <sic>accomodations</sic>&#44; resounding with most elaborate<lb/> instrumentation and choral songs&#44; having a nu&#45;<lb/>&#45;merous corps of officials in the rendition of<lb/> the service&#44; so that those splendid buildings are<lb/> literally groaning under a tremendous load.<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="9"/>
                <p>Not such was the aim and scope of our an&#45;<lb/>&#45;cestors&#44; who&#44; in their wisdom&#44; established the<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;&#45;&#45;&#34;the synagogue&#44;&#34; for a popular<lb/> assemblage&#44; either &#45;&#45;as the name denotes&#45;&#45;they h they did so perhaps during the first captivity in<lb/> Babylon as the Talmud asserts&#44; but surely ar afterward everywhere&#44; during the<lb/> second Temple.  Simplicity was to be its character&#45;<lb/>&#45;istic&#44; hence the people were not unreasonably<lb/> taxed for the privilege of attending the Divine<lb/> service&#44; and listening to a religious discourse.<lb/>  But while with a view of not exposing to the<lb/> world at large the shame of an extraordingary ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;penditure to support a place&#44; ostensibly set apart<lb/> for honoring Israel&#39;s god&#44; levies are resorted to&#44;<lb/> institutions of a really sacred nature are suffered<lb/> to languish.  Our sages who felt that with&#45;<lb/>&#45;out learning there cannot be sterling piety&#44; attached<lb/> a higher sanctity to the School House than to the<lb/> Synagogue &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> and with many such maxims&#44; the Talmud teems.<lb/>  A legend tells that Rabbi Tarphon&#44; who was ex<lb/>&#45;ceptionally wealthy&#44; did not dispense benefactions<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="10"/>
                <p>proportionately to the large means at his<lb/> disposal.  Rabbi Akiba&#44; the incomparable<lb/> patron of Jewish lore&#44; know nevertheless and<lb/> appreciated more than all others persons&#44; the striking qualities of his<lb/> contemporary and colleague.  The two Sages met.<lb/>  Akiba said to Tarphon&#58; &#34;I can make for you a very<lb/> advantageous investment&#44; if you will supply the<lb/> requisite amount.&#34;  Tarphon agreed.  Sometime<lb/> elapsed before the two came across with each other.<lb/>  Finally&#44; the opulent Rabbi called and to inquired about the<lb/> investment.  The Rabbis walked out together&#44; Aki&#45;<lb/>&#45;ba promising to show the estate which he had<lb/> procured.  Suddenly he made a full stop.  &#34;Come<lb/> in friend&#34; said Akiba.  They had halted at in front of a school<lb/> house.  A number of young pupils&#44; receiving<lb/> there instruction&#44; were chanting psalms.  The<lb/> two stood listening.  When the youths reached<lb/> a sentence which reads thus &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;He hath dispensed his wealth&#44;<lb/> he hath given of it to those who need it&#44; his<lb/> beneficence will endure for ever&#44; his height elevation shall rise up<lb/> gloriously&#34;&#44;<lb/></p>
                
                <pb n="11"/>
                <p>Tarphon embraced his friend and said&#58; &#34;Aki&#45;<lb/>&#45;ba thou art my teacher and noble moral associate&#34; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
                <p>Brethren&#44; were I blessed with affluence&#44; I would<lb/> destine a tithe thereof&#44; as prescribed in the Torah&#44;<lb/> not to embellish synagogues and secure eloquent<lb/> speeches makers and mellifluous songstresses at a heavy cost&#44; but I would plant<lb/> schools&#44; seminaries&#44; academies of learning&#44; acces&#45;<lb/>&#45;sible to a rising generation&#45;&#45;a generation&#44; alas&#33;<lb/> now growing in our midst&#44; utterly destitute of<lb/> the knowledge of our national literature.<lb/></p>
                <p>All honor to Jacob H. Schiff&#44; who is cre&#45;<lb/>&#45;dited with <sic>lifthing</sic> his great the yealry increase of his wealth in such portions<lb/> that the needy&#44; the untutored&#44; and the ambitious<lb/> to rise by their talents&#44; are <sic>benefitted</sic>.<lb/></p>
                
                <p>&#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
