<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF3_1</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_1_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_1_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_1_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_1_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_1_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_1_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_1_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_1_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_1_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_1_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_1_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_1_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_1_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_1_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_1_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_1_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>On the anniversary of my 25th year&#39;s<lb/>
                of ministry.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Dear Brothers and sisters in faith&#33;  I really believed&#44; that<lb/> when this year and this Sabbath arrived&#44; what I had to relate&#44;<lb/> might have taxed your patience to listen to&#44; so much<lb/> and so varied in character&#44; I imagined it would have been.<lb/>  But several times&#44; during the last few days&#44; I tried to centre<lb/> my mind upon the subject of the 25th anniversary of<lb/> my first entering your Sanctuary to act therein as a ser&#45;<lb/>&#45;vant of God&#44; and after searching into the past&#44; I dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;covered nothing remarkably noteworthy on which I might<lb/> with appropriateness dwell.  You bore with me&#44; when<lb/> I was more imperfect than I am now&#44; and I&#44; did my<lb/> utmost to overcome difficulties&#44; and to meet with the<lb/> approval of you all&#44; while satisfying my conscience.<lb/>  I cannot claim that my efforts were always successful.<lb/>  On the contrary&#59; I have had often cause to lament my<lb/> shortcomings.  Often have I been distressed at the thought<lb/> that you could perhaps have placed of at the head of your<lb/> venerable Congregation&#44; a person whose qualifications<lb/> might perhaps have drawn to this Synagogue a<lb/> larger number of <sic>worshippers</sic>&#44; and proved advantageous<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>from a temporal as well as a spiritual point of view.<lb/>  Your President&#44; the first among my American coreligionists<lb/> whom I saw&#44; when arrived in your city&#59; the brother Israelite<lb/> with whom I have had&#44; from that day to the present&#44; inti&#45;<lb/>mate official relations&#44; can testify&#44; that the fear of being<lb/> unequal to my undertaking and your requirements&#44; impel<lb/>&#45;led me more than once to form a resolution&#44; which he for&#45;<lb/>&#45;cibly urged me to recall&#44; offering encouragement under<lb/> depressing circumstances.  But now that I have spent<lb/> my best years among you&#59; now that&#44; like the great teacher<lb/> in our ancient Commonwealth&#44; I may say &#34;I have become old<lb/> and gray&#44; and my children&#44; behold&#33; they are with you&#44; and<lb/> I have walked before you&#44; from my youth even until this<lb/> day&#34;&#44; now&#44; let me hope that I have succeeded in securing<lb/> a reciprocation of the feelings I experience for all the Hebrews&#44;<lb/> whose lot has been cast in this favored land&#44; but specially<lb/> for those who deemed me fit to be entrusted with a holy<lb/> ministration.  Let me hope&#44; I say&#44; that the assurance<lb/> of being well thought of by many&#44; will reconcile me to<lb/> the idea of ending my life&#44; while officiating at this sacred<lb/> desk.  Understand&#44; dear hearers&#33;  I do not speak so&#44; be&#45;<lb/>cause I have conceived of late an aversion for my calling.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>No&#58; it is that to which a sainted mother destined me&#59;<lb/> and I have learnt none other.  But I mean that relying on<lb/> the sentiments I have inspired&#44; I may hereafter be more at<lb/> ease&#59; that I may let your broad kindliness bear the weight<lb/> of my imperfections.  For&#44; the comparatively few&#44; among<lb/> my senior coevals who have been Providentially kept alive&#44;<lb/> during the last quarter of a century&#44; and whom I delight still<lb/> to greet in the Sanctuary of our Lord&#44; will remember with<lb/> what trepidation I ascended the pulpit just vacated by<lb/> a divine&#44; whose labors in the fields of Judaism&#44; had won<lb/> for him great renown.  They can tell that it was not<lb/> assumed modesty&#44; common among aspirants after a<lb/> public office&#44; which prompted me to declare myself un&#45;<lb/>&#45;prepared to come up to the expectations of my constituents.<lb/>  I was then very indifferently acquainted with the language&#44;<lb/> in which I ventured to address an English&#45;speaking<lb/> people.  And though in exerting myself to discharge accept<lb/>&#45;ably&#44; the duties attending my station&#44; I have acquired to<lb/> in some degree the facility to impart religious knowledge&#44; yet&#44;<lb/> my natural timidity has clung to me tenaciously.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>And that by itself may justly be viewed as a defeat<lb/> in an individual called upon to lead multitudes.  Indeed&#44;<lb/> were it not that I confidently trust in your affection&#44; I<lb/> would even after 25 years&#44; during which a new generation<lb/> arose who know me thoroughly&#44; I would this very Sabbath<lb/> crave for the continuance of your indulgence on that score.<lb/>  But depending&#44; as I do&#44; on your attachment&#44; I ask neverthe&#45;<lb/>&#45;less&#44; for no undue consideration.  I would not designedly<lb/> place myself as an impediment against your following a<lb/> way&#44; where I could not honestly go.  Think me not so<lb/> unpardonably selfish.  But if you are willing to adhere<lb/> to the traditions and time&#45;honored practices&#44; if&#44; to say it<lb/> with Jeremiah&#44; you will heed and inquire for the old paths&#44;<lb/> where lies the right&#45;course&#44; for us&#44; a missionary people to<lb/> pursue&#44; and will walk therein&#44; then I may hazard to<lb/> assert that my defect will not be felt by you as an<lb/> injury.  For&#44; however painfully my reservedness may<lb/> affect me personally&#44; I did not yet&#44; nor will I ever<lb/> allow it to be detrimental to the interests of our sacred<lb/> cause.  The past may be a guarantee for the future.  For&#44;<lb/> when silence and retirement conflicted with my duty&#44; I inva&#45;<lb/>&#45;riably compelled myself to stand forth and boldly to speak.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>And I shall not let any occasion arise&#44; on which the<lb/> tongue or the pen must be used fearlessly&#44; without endea&#45;<lb/>&#45;vouring to be equal to the emergency.  Possibly&#44; my zeal<lb/> may be apt to lead my judgment astray&#44; and by reason<lb/> of that I may already have been unfortunate to offer offence&#44;<lb/> when I simply sought to <sic>fulfil</sic> solemn obligations.<lb/>  Brothers and sisters&#33;  If this tardy disavowal of any desire<lb/> purposely to inflict pain&#44; will suffice&#44; I will make it now<lb/> freely and openly.  But it is&#44; of course&#44; beyond human<lb/> powers never to be misunderstood&#44; never to be misguided.<lb/>  I will cite as an illustration an incident somewhat curious&#44;<lb/> but to me grievous.  Some years ago&#44; being at a lodge<lb/> of a Jewish order&#44; a fellow&#45;Israelite who sat himself next<lb/> to me&#44; addressed me in this manner.  &#34;Do you kn remember&#44;<lb/> Sir&#44; that you once insulted me grossly&#63;&#34;  I was startled&#44;<lb/> for the man was an utter stranger.  I asked how I could ever<lb/> have been guilty of what he imputed to me&#44; since I did not<lb/> know him even by sight.  He answered&#59; That he was<lb/> visiting a house of mourning&#44; where I officiated&#44; and as<lb/> he came forward to speak to a member of the family then<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>in affliction&#44; I motioned him back.  All arguments&#44;<lb/> all representations&#44; could not convince him who bore me<lb/> ill&#45;will that he must be laboring under an error&#44; that the<lb/> charge brought against me was unmerited.  He persisted<lb/> in his opinion that I had deliberately treated him with indi&#45;<lb/>&#45;gnity.  And yet after mature reflection&#44; I surmised<lb/> that my accuser might have been right in part&#44; though<lb/> certainly wrong in his impression.  As&#44; when the occurrence&#44;<lb/> to which he alluded took place&#44; he was&#44; by his own ad&#45;<lb/>&#45;mission&#44; a foreign stranger just arrived in this country&#44; and con&#45;<lb/>&#45;sequently ignorant of its habits and usages&#44; he may have<lb/> tried to converse with some of the mourners&#44; while I was<lb/> reading the prayers&#44; and I may have meant by my sign&#44;<lb/> to request that he would wait till I had concluded the<lb/> service had been concluded.  Now&#44; that instance of mis&#45;<lb/>&#45;apprehension&#44; may not&#44; very likely&#44; be a solitary one.<lb/>  Notwithstanding my keen sense of what is due from a<lb/> teacher in Israel&#44;&#45;&#45;permit me so to speak&#45;&#45;&#44; to all<lb/> his coreligionists.  Notwithstanding that my nature and<lb/> my holy office have prescribed for me a rule to which<lb/> I have essayed to hold fast&#44; namely&#44; to show no in&#45;<lb/>&#45;vidious distinction between the foreigner and the native&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>the lowliest and the high&#45;stationed&#44; but to be seen in the<lb/> hovel of the poor and in as well as in the mansion of the rich&#44; to welcome<lb/> all in the Sanctuary of our Lord&#44; to offer them all a word<lb/> of comfort in sorrow&#44; and to enhance their joy by praying my<lb/> Divine Master for its duration&#59; notwithstanding that I<lb/> would rather be publicly contemned ten times&#44; than shame or<lb/> harm the least of my fellow&#45;mortals once&#44; still&#44; during<lb/> so many long years&#44; an unguarded expression may have<lb/> escaped my lips&#44; an impassive gesture may have drawn<lb/> upon me the displeasure of brethren whose good&#45;will I<lb/> prize.  This I would regret&#44; and I trust&#44; that if it exists&#44; it will be removed on the<lb/> Sabbath&#44; which forms an epoch in the history of the Mickve<lb/> Israel Congregation.  For that respectable body of American<lb/> Hebrews organized already very nearly a century&#44; sees for the<lb/> first time its spiritual leader celebrate the 25th anniversary of<lb/> his ministerial connection therewith.  I am the Hazan who uninterruptedly stood before it that whole period.  My immediate pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;decessor remained with it only only till the 21t year of his incum&#45;<lb/>&#45;bency was nearly completed&#44; and all others served a much<lb/> shorter term.  Yet&#44; it is not by the length of time<lb/> that the relations between the shepherd and his flock must<lb/> be measured.  I claim nothing at your hands&#44; because<lb/> of the sheer circumstance of having stood before you a quarter of<lb/> a century.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>I might now celebrate the golden anniversary so to say&#44; instead of<lb/> the silver anniversary of my alliance I made with my constituents.  What<lb/> if looking back we discovered naught but a blank&#63;<lb/>  What&#44; if I had merely kept merely the letter of a written<lb/> contract&#44; whose demands on the exertions of the Hazan<lb/> are indeed very light&#59; and you had adhered to your<lb/> part of the same contract&#44; by paying me a stipulated<lb/> sum for the reading the prayers &#34;according to the custom<lb/> of the Portuguese Jews&#34; on Sabbaths and Holidays&#44; and<lb/> for being allowed&#44; on some extraordinary occasion&#44; to deli&#45;<lb/>&#45;ver&#44; I if I chose&#44; an English discourse&#63;  The<lb/> scaled document would have insured me against a<lb/> summary discharge&#44; and you could not have dared to<lb/> find fault with my rolling in idleness.  Let me<lb/> then congratulate myself this day&#44; that I have not<lb/> cared a little about paper agreements&#44;&#45;&#45;save so<lb/> far as they apply to rules&#44; whereunto I have affixed<lb/> my signature&#44; and which I am in honor bound to<lb/> obey&#44; as a salaried officer&#45;&#45;.  Yes&#44; let me rejoice with<lb/> you&#44; dear Brothers and sisters&#44; that I have tried&#44; at least&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>to be alive to the interests of our holy inheritance&#44;<lb/> that I have not fallen asleep at my post&#44; nor have<lb/> I deserted it&#44; to run headlong after the paltry pelf<lb/> which allures and debases.  Let me rejoice that if I have<lb/> not succeeded in setting the hearts of my American<lb/> coreligionists all ablaze with religious ardor&#44; I have&#44;<lb/> at all events&#44; prevented the light of our faith from being<lb/> extinguished from the midst of this Congregation.<lb/>  To you&#44; O youths&#44; I owe my thanks&#44; for the good<lb/> name&#44; I flatter myself&#44; to have won&#44;&#45;&#45;and which is<lb/> to me and mine infinitely more precious than rubies&#44;<lb/> to you&#44; because an eager wish to retain Israel&#39;s sons and<lb/> daughters in the sacred fold&#44; supp spurred me to action.<lb/>  May you be found in it&#44; glorying in the belief of your<lb/> fathers&#44; when the voice which now speaks shall have<lb/> been hushed in the cold grave.  To you also&#44; aged<lb/> Jews and Jewesses&#44; my gratitude is due.  For&#44; when on<lb/> the Sabbath &#34;Ki Tissa&#34; of the year 5611&#44; you looked<lb/> favorably upon a trembling stranger&#44; young and inexpe&#45;<lb/>&#45;rienced&#44; you endowed him with strength to carry out<lb/> a maternal wish and a filial promise.  May blessings<lb/> flow down upon you&#44; perennially&#44; from the Rock of all ages.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>May in each of you be verified the sentence of the good<lb/> old book &#34;Length of days&#44; and years of life&#44; and peace<lb/> shall be added to thee.&#34;</p>
            <p>O everlasting Lord&#44; whose appellation is &#34;Adona&#239; Shalom&#44;&#34;<lb/> Set Peace as the sentinel of the homes of all the people&#44;<lb/> and of this Dwelling&#45;place&#44; the centre of their brother&#45;<lb/>&#45;hood.  Let Thine eyes be open upon a residue of<lb/> Thy tribes&#44; and upon the spot&#44; whence their joint sup&#45;<lb/>&#45;plications ascend Thy throne&#44; as the ancient burnt&#45;<lb/>offerings.  Bid the Spirit of Union be the tutelary<lb/> angel of both the Sanctuary and of them that worship<lb/> therein.  Increase the number of the latter&#44; and en&#45;<lb/>&#45;hance the glory of the former by the solemnity and the<lb/> decorum reigning within its courts.  Grant O Lord&#33;<lb/> that Israel of America&#45;&#45;sensible of their common descent and<lb/> identity with all the outcasts of Judea&#44; may declare them&#45;<lb/>&#45;selves thy covenant&#45;children&#44; even until the feet of<lb/> him that bringeth good tidings&#44; and publisheth salvation&#44;<lb/> shall tread mount Zion.  But grant that there<lb/> may arise&#44; now and ever from our midst&#44; a spontaneous<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>outburst of feelings&#44; finding expression in<lb/> the words elicited by the prophet Elijah at<lb/> Carmel&#44; and which we hope to repeat with our<lb/> last breath&#34; Adona&#239; hoo hahelohim&#44; Adona&#239; hoo<lb/> habelohim.&#34;  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
