<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx11FF3_6</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="1894" source="" attested="yes">1894</dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_6_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_6_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_6_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_6_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_6_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_6_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_6_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_6_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_6_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_6_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_6_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx11ff3_6_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>10 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>S. MORAIS&#44;<lb/>
                546 N. FIFTH STREET&#44;<lb/>
                PHILADELPHIA&#44; PA.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>For the 43rd anniversary of my ministry<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>Sincerely attached as I am to the country&#44; in which I have<lb/> dwelt uninterruptedly made my home permanent home these forty three years&#59; glad as I have<lb/> felt to serve here the cause to which I consecrated myself life<lb/> forty three years ago&#59; fortunate as I consider it myself to be<lb/> well kindly thought of by&#45;&#45;not by very few&#44; I hope&#44; among my not very few I hope brothers and sisters in faith&#44; who<lb/> constitute the congregation Mickv&#233; Israel&#44; to whom I<lb/> have ministered forty three long consecutive years&#44; had yet&#44; I must nevertheless make a disappointing confession.  Had I imagined<lb/> ever so remotely that I was doomed to see the Samuel<lb/> Holdsheims&#44; the David Friedlanders&#44; the Aaron Choriners<lb/> transferred to Philadelphia&#44; I would have returned&#44;<lb/> whence I came after this first Sabbath of my first probation&#44; whence I came.<lb/> The position of Hebrew master&#44; which I had filled<lb/> in London&#44; had been left purposely open by the<lb/> directors of the Orphan School&#44; who waited to hear<lb/> that I preferred England to America.  In real&#45;<lb/>&#45;ity&#44; viewed from an orthodox stand point&#44; the me&#45;<lb/>&#45;tropolis of Great Britain offered strong inducements<lb/> to a young man cradled in a nursery of piety.<lb/>  The prestige of Moses Montefiore&#44; vastly contributed<lb/> to keep Jews in the famous city on the Thames&#44; steadfast in their<lb/> adherence to the Law and traditions.  The grand<lb/> nephew of the immortal philanthropist was not born there.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>Claude Montefiore&#44; doubtless clever&#44; well meaning<lb/> and public spirited&#44; had not arisen yet to associate<lb/> himself with Israel Abraham&#44; the scholarly descend&#45;<lb/>&#45;ant of devout and learned sires&#44; and to advocate intermar&#45;<lb/>&#45;riages between our sons and daughters and the offspring<lb/> of non&#45;Israelitish parents&#44; as pleaded for in some late<lb/> numbers of their &#34;Quarterly Review.&#34;  Admit&#44; in<lb/> religious culture London did not compare in the days of my youth&#44; with Le&#45;<lb/>&#45;ghorn&#44; which had supplied it its ancient Congregation of Sephardim&#44; with Rabbis and<lb/> teachers&#44; but it <sic>rivalled</sic> my native place in the<lb/> observance of time honored practices.  And we have been<lb/> told by the Sages&#44; that not erudition&#44; but devotion to the Torah&#44;<lb/> is most commendable &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> Now&#44; the truth must be spoken.  Philadelphia fell<lb/> short of the requirements that give a title right to the<lb/> name title of &#34;religious.&#34;  Still&#44; forty three years ago&#44; it<lb/> was the home residence of many an Israelite who took a pride<lb/> in raising rearing his children after the standard of Biblic&#45;<lb/>&#45;al and Rabbinical Judaism.  The charge<lb/> flippantly made that Judaism in this city of ours&#44; was lifeless&#44;<lb/> that a lurid darkness overspread it until light<lb/> shone upon it from the West&#44; is a libel&#44; unless the<lb/> disappearance sinking of scripturalism&#44; deserves to be interpreted<lb/> as the dawning of a soul illumining Orb.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Mark it well.  Forty three years ago&#44; Philadelphia<lb/> possessed a well consistently conducted Jewish organ a moderately gotten up Jewish publication society&#44; it<lb/> had a called point to a Hebrew Education Society and a Hebrew Sunday<lb/> School&#44; the pioneers of similar institutions elsewhere throughout the Union.  Forty three<lb/> years ago the two&#44; who subsequently claimed to have breathed<lb/> a new spirit into the dry bones of the ancestral creed&#44;<lb/> had not <sic>travelled</sic> beyond the precincts of the New York State.<lb/>  Dr Lilienthal was then so pronouncedly conservative&#44; as<lb/> to commend and recommend the practice of wearing Te&#45;<lb/>&#45;fillin&#44; or phylacteries&#59; as all can ascertain who have read consult<lb/> early numbers of the Phildelphia Occident.  In those<lb/> days&#44; the genial Dr. did not think correct it suitable for a Rabbi to tell<lb/> his interviewer that he&#44; the defender of the Tefillin<lb/> rite&#44; had intended to unfurled the banner of a modernized Judaism&#59;<lb/> a meaningless phrase&#44; if it does not signify<lb/> the playing of Judaism&#44; with Judaism out.  The<lb/> other claimant to a resurrecting power&#44; a new Elijah&#44;<lb/> who&#44; in an outburst of material admiration styled his<lb/> associate a Ben Zacka&#239;&#44; while he was called in turn<lb/> Moses Ben Hanach&#44; Dr I. M. Wise&#44; forty three<lb/> years ago&#44; wrote for the conservative Asmonean of<lb/> New York&#44; and for the orthodox Occident of Philadelphia.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Only in Charleston&#44; South Carolina&#44; an attempt had previously been<lb/> made to introduce unauthorized changes in the govern&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment of the Synagogue.  But Poznansky&#44; the Polish foreign<lb/> Jew who threw a fire brand to kindle the flame<lb/> of discord&#44; which disrupted a venerable and influential intellectual<lb/> Sephardic community&#44; did not go further than the<lb/> first step towards the transformation of our tenets and<lb/> regulations.  As a body&#44; Philadelphia Israel&#45;<lb/>&#45;ites continued <sic>stauch</sic>&#44; uninfluenced by the example of<lb/> Charleston&#44; which the West brought in later times to a culmination<lb/> not dreamed of&#44; forty three years ago.  Samuel<lb/> Holdsheim sanctified Sunday to oblige German Jews&#44;<lb/> too broadly liberalized to keep Saturday holy&#59; David<lb/> Friedlander would have entered with compromises to roll<lb/> away the odium which German Christians heaped<lb/> upon his people&#59; Aaron Choriner sought to meta&#45;<lb/>&#45;morphose every thing&#44; in order to prove that the outcasts<lb/> of Judea have their Jerusalem in the lands that grant<lb/> their toleration.  But in Philadelphia of to day&#44; Sunday<lb/> is a Jewish apostleship to Christianity.  It has already<lb/> converted Christian maidens into an affectionate regard<lb/> for Jewish youths&#44; and has ripened into a matrimonial<lb/> alliance the esteem of Christian gentlemen for the<lb/> fair daughters of Israel.  I do not malign indeed throughout make insinuations with malice aforethought.<lb/>  Current events will free me from the imputation.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>As to compromises for the sake of showing the world<lb/> that we have broken with the past&#44; let rituals which<lb/> have very nearly suppressed all Hebrew&#44; expunged from the pages national<lb/> hopes and aspirations let must will demonstrate them.  Temples inviting placing trinitarians to speakers<lb/> speak and hiding the forward while the diminutive scroll of the Law from their pre&#45; hides backward&#44;<lb/> &#45;sence must demonstrate them.  And now a voice re shrill sound echoes<lb/> from the West.  &#34;Tear off into shreds the parch&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment&#44; wipe off the writing&#59; cease to carry in<lb/> procession what you idolize.  It is only the tanned<lb/> skin of an animal&#44; with some characters unintel&#45;<lb/>&#45;ligible to the present generation.  Do you wish<lb/> still to read what you do not observe&#63;  A printed page<lb/> will answer the purpose better.&#34;  Thus vehemently<lb/> cry the iconoclastic braggarts radicals of the West.  We<lb/> may prophesy that before long the advice will be eagerly<lb/> followed accepted in Philadelphia the East&#44; on the plea of a general<lb/> longing for a modernized Judaism.  &#34;Insane&#33;  You<lb/> forget that the glory of Judaism lies in its hoary anti&#45;<lb/>&#45;quity.  When I raise the Sepher Torah&#44; when I read the<lb/> Sepher Torah&#44; when I simply look at the Sepher Torah&#44;<lb/> my memory instinctively goes back to the restorer of the<lb/> Torah to Ezra our zealous scribe &#91;Hebrew&#93; even to Ezra&#44; our veritable Reformer&#44; if not to still remoter ages.  Been<lb/> When I simply look at the Sepher Torah Ben Teradion&#44; our martyr&#44; derisively cruelly wrapped by inquisitorial Rome&#44;<lb/> in the sacred scroll that he loved&#44; to be burned with it at the stake&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>rises before my vision.  He The venerated martyred Sage calls them recreants&#44; who<lb/> lay an impious a sacrilegious hand upon that venerated scroll. to commit a sacrilege....<lb/> &#34;No&#58; thou shalt not be rent apart into rags&#44; so long as I watch<lb/> on th yonder shrine.  But can we vouch for the Sooner would I tear the grey hair<lb/> failure of her that gave me birth.&#34;  But can we<lb/> vouch for the future&#44; in amidst the deliberate ignorance enforced<lb/> of the language of the scroll&#44; enforced by a contemptuous<lb/> indifference apathy for what is venerably old in the religion<lb/> of Israel&#63;  Let me tell it.  At the first sign of a falling off&#44;<lb/> I interposed&#44; with using the slight influence which my seniority<lb/> in the ministry lent me&#44; to prevent ward off a greater decline.<lb/>  I prayed for firmness and warned several&#44; who put on the sacerdotal<lb/> garment here and in New York.  I welcomed later on&#44; others<lb/> whose antecedents and public speeches pronused augured well<lb/> for an intelligent conservatism&#44; but the a vacillating<lb/> characters&#44; of some&#44; the love of ease which gold pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;mises&#44; became an all&#45;destroying mildew in the field<lb/> of our a conservative religion.  I cannot say with positiveness&#44; that<lb/> that the inconsiderate demeanour is now sorrowed<lb/> for&#44; but I do know that firmness steadfastness would have pre&#45;<lb/>&#45;vented much that we lament&#44; much that has en&#45;<lb/>gendered schisms and occasioned irremediable incurable heartburnings.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>Certainly This is certain This however&#44; is most certain&#59; I would not have imagined it possible forty three<lb/> years ago that on the first Purim&#44; when I arrived&#44; that forty three years later the Purim greetings from some<lb/> who bear the title of Rabbis&#44; would have been an<lb/> invitation to participate in a projected convention<lb/> of Universalists&#44; ethic culturists&#44; unitarians and<lb/> similar liberals&#44; with the view of effecting a co&#45;<lb/>&#45;alition among various beliefs.  But even that<lb/> has actually come to pass&#44; and it would be rash<lb/> to predict that the axe will not be applied still<lb/> more radically to uproot out the Judaic tree altogether beyond the power of replanting.<lb/>  Perp Perhaps&#44; we shall be allowed to pick up a<lb/> few stray leaves dropped by a freer Christianity and show<lb/> them off as the laurels of wherewith a modernized Judaism is crowned.<lb/>  &#34;Do you remain at your post still&#44; notwithstanding such<lb/> provocations&#63;&#34;  I am asked.  I do&#44; whelmed with shame.<lb/>  Not indifferently&#44; I assure all&#44; not indifferently I remain&#44; but humi&#45;<lb/>&#45;liated by the happenings that have robbed me of any my utter incapacity to stem the swelling current of turbulent waters which carry<lb/> capacity for good. every thing before it into an ocean of oblivion.  Consummate hypocrisy&#44; it would<lb/> be in me to say that I am ready to following abdicate&#44; imitating following the ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;ample of the Baptist minister of our city&#44; who&#44; a<lb/> few weeks since&#44; insisted upon the acceptance of his<lb/> resignation by the people whom he had served much less<lb/> time than I have served mine.  His plea was age and in&#45;<lb/>ability to make clerical visits among his flock.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>I could not imitate the course which the Baptist<lb/> clergyman pursued&#44; without inflicting upon myself<lb/> and mine an irreparable injury&#44; though I do ask<lb/> indulgence for having greatly reduced my calls by reason of because of age and infirmities&#44; ex&#45;<lb/>&#45;cept to on the sick and the mourners&#44; to whom I may<lb/> bring messages of comfort.  What I most crave for&#44;<lb/> during my continuance in office&#44; is the encouragement which<lb/> a larger attendance&#59; a harmonious mingling of voices&#44;<lb/> of the young in prayer&#44; inspires.  To that end I coo&#45;<lb/>&#45;perate with the teachers in our Congregational schools&#44;<lb/> and with all&#44; wherever my instruction and counsel are sought<lb/> after.  If the few years that I may<lb/> reasonably expect to  be yet vouchsafed to me&#44;<lb/> can accomplish that small measure of good&#44;<lb/> if during my latter days I shall not bear be spared the<lb/> grief of hearing others in this consecrated edifice&#44;<lb/> because my strength to serve has vigour shall have failed&#44; and my<lb/> memory proved treacherous&#44; I will return thanks<lb/> to my creator&#44; as the psalmist of yore &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;I will bow down at my holy oracle for Thy mercy and Truth&#44; &#91;Hebrew&#93;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;On the day that I called&#44; Thou<lb/> didst answer me&#44; thou hast raised me up with strength<lb/> in my soul&#34;  So may it be.  Amen.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
