<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF4_17</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_17_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_17_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_17_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_17_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_17_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_17_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_17_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_17_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_17_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_17_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_17_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_17_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_17_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_17_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_17_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff4_17_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>12 pages on 5 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>Post&#45;Biblical<lb/>
                37<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Before we part altogether with Josephus&#44; and give direct<lb/> our attention to the narrative of events drawn from later sources&#44; some<lb/> remarks are necessary.  In the short post&#45;biblical lectures&#44;<lb/> delivered here at intervals&#44; and principally for the instruction<lb/> of the young in this congregation&#44; the character of our&#44;<lb/> confessedly great&#44; historian&#44; has been brought set to view in<lb/> an unfavorable light.  He was shown to have lacked<lb/> patriotism&#44; though he was not wanting in courage and<lb/> military skill&#59; to have cared more for his literary<lb/> fame than for the honor of his unfortunate brethren.<lb/>  Nevertheless&#44; justice demands that the charge of apos&#45;<lb/>&#45;tasy against him should not go uncontradicted.<lb/>  Some Early Christian writers have unwarrantably represented<lb/> Josephus as a convert to the new religion&#44; founding<lb/> their arguments upon certain passages in his books histories.<lb/>  The most striking would be the most damaging&#44; if<lb/> it were genuine&#44; but that it is forged&#44; any reader<lb/> who will stop to think&#44; can easily discover.<lb/></p>  
            <p>In the 18th book of his &#34;Jewish Antiquities&#44;&#34; our histo&#45;<lb/>&#45;rian gives an account of oppressive measures&#44; which<lb/> made Pontus Pilate&#45;&#45;the Roman proconsul in Judea&#45;&#45;hateful to the Jews&#44; and which caused political<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>disturbances.  To this narrative there follows a para&#45;<lb/>&#45;graph of only four sentences concerning Jesus&#44; who is<lb/> described as &#34;a door of wonderful works&#44;&#34; and as &#34;having<lb/> come back to life according to divine promises.&#34;  Then im&#45;<lb/>&#45;mediately after comes we are told a long story of concerning touching a disgraceful act<lb/> perpetrated in the temple of the Egyptian deity<lb/> Anubis at Rome.  Now&#58; can any one that is at all acquainted with the style<lb/> of Josephus&#44; believe that he&#44; who habitually descants<lb/> on even trifling occurrences&#44; would have so quickly<lb/> disposed of an incident&#44; which he is credited to have<lb/> interpreted as the advent of a prophetically predicted Messiah&#63;<lb/>  Or that he can it be credited that an historian devote to it such an episode merely a few lines thrust<lb/> between two narratives entirely disconnected with it&#63;<lb/>  Clearly&#44; that and the like statements are interpolations made by<lb/> Christians&#44; who pretend that the destruction of the<lb/> Temple and the consequent dispersion were punish&#45;<lb/>&#45;ments for having refused to worship a man&#45;god.  To<lb/> be consistent in their pious fraud&#44; they Nazarenes make Josephus&#44;<lb/> who has often denounced his own people&#44; a convert<lb/> to the newly born creed.  But in all truth&#44; if Jose&#45;<lb/>&#45;phus was not disloyal to his country&#44; he surely did<lb/> not disown his religion.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>In one of his dissertations&#44; added to the end of his history&#44;<lb/> he boasts of the undying attachment of Jews to their laws&#44;<lb/> despite all changes of fortune.  Viewing it the subject also<lb/> in the light of self&#45;interest&#45;&#45;and who more egotistical than<lb/> Josephus&#63;&#45;&#45;&#44; the favorite of the Flavian family&#44; whose<lb/> name he took&#44; would not have <sic>benefitted</sic> by his apostasy.<lb/>  For &#34;the tribes of Christians&#44;&#34; as he is supposed to have called<lb/> the comparatively few followers of Jesus in his time&#44; were severely persecuted at<lb/> Rome.  Their having kept aloof from their former<lb/> coreligionists&#44; during the <sic>seige</sic> of Jerusalem did not<lb/> ensure for them a kind treatment on at the part hands of the<lb/> heathen conquerors.  On the contrary&#44; the veil of <sic>secresy</sic><lb/> they threw cast over their worship&#44; excited suspicion&#44; and exposed<lb/> the devotees to the rising belief of the rising Nazarene church to the ill will of a popu&#45;<lb/>&#45;lation&#44; who feared that fancied to see conspiracies everywhere&#44; and whose demoralising<lb/> polytheism rendered them it fiercely cruel.<lb/></p>
            <p>I have felt prompted to say all this&#44; as a caution to the young of my<lb/> faith&#44; who either at schools or at home read histories<lb/> which&#44; instead of filling them with arousing profound admira&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion for a heroic ancestry&#44; inspire contempt for men<lb/> whom inveterate prejudice calls deicides and infidels.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>For what is noble daringness in others&#44; is obstinacy<lb/> in the Jew&#44; what is religious firmness in the followers<lb/> of the man of Nazreth&#44; is incredulity disbelief in the adherents<lb/> of the Unity.  But verily if only the last episode handed down<lb/> by Josephus had been penned&#44; an unbiased posterity must should<lb/> have awarded to the Hebrews the palm for <sic>unequalled</sic> bravery<lb/> supported by unwavering belief.  After the conquest by Titus three fortres&#45;<lb/>&#45;ses had not yet fallen into the hands of failed to be captured by the Roman<lb/> legions.  Heordion&#44; Macharus and Masada.  Incre&#45;<lb/>&#45;dible as it may seem appear&#44; still notwithstanding the fall<lb/> of Jerusalem and the overthrow of the Temple&#44; a few<lb/> thousands still remained up in arms in those strongholds.<lb/>  Herodion not being in a position to offer a stout resistance&#44;<lb/> submitted to the sad fate and opened its gates to the<lb/> enemy.  Macharus&#44; which was situated on a rugged<lb/> ro cliff&#44; surrounded by by ravines of great length and<lb/> depth&#44; struggled hard for a time.  After many attacks and repulses<lb/> it was finally taken&#44; through the imprudence of a too<lb/> fearless youth&#44; named Eleazar.  He was always the first<lb/> to throw the arrow at the adversary&#44; and the last to<lb/> stop pause.  Sometimes&#44; he would check single&#45;handed the<lb/> advancing host&#44; till he could safely beat a retreat.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>One day relying on his prowess&#44; he ventured outside<lb/> of the walls gates.  An Egyptian&#44; serving in the Roman<lb/> army&#44; stealthily watched the daring youth.  Being<lb/> of a clo colossal strength&#44; he sprung upon the Jewish<lb/> hero&#44; and holding him tight as in a vice&#44; bore him triumph&#45;<lb/>&#45;antly to the Roman camp.  There he was stripped<lb/> and unmercifully whipped scourged.  From the top of the walls&#44;<lb/> a cry of distress broke forth.  The Jews saw their<lb/> champion vilely treated.  They saw a cross set up for<lb/> having him crucified&#44; according to the barbarous usage<lb/> of Rome.  Unable to witness the ignominious<lb/> death of the man who had formed their pride&#44; they<lb/> promised to surrender&#44; if only Eleazar&#39;s life was<lb/> spared.  He was restored to his family and the gar&#45;<lb/>&#45;rison capitulated.  But many among the inhabitants<lb/> who tried to leave the city by night&#44; evading the<lb/> vigilance of the Roman sentinels&#44; were caught and<lb/> killed.  Some were pursued into the woods&#44; where<lb/> they had sought a hiding place&#44; but found death.<lb/>  But The Masada still held firm&#44; and there the last scene in that bloody drama was enact&#45;<lb/>&#45;ed. at Masada  The Its fortress seemed destined to baffle<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>any attempt to capture it.  Not unlike<lb/> Gamala&#44; its steps and precipices made one giddy to look at<lb/> them.  Nothing but rocks and chasms met the<lb/> eye.  The city however rose a on fairy&#45;like upon a height.  Picturesque it was and<lb/> beautifully laid out.  The soil though mountainous<lb/> was received a carefully cultivation&#44; and it supplied provision<lb/> in plenty.  Masada had been originally built by<lb/> Jonathan the Maccabean.  In later years Herod I had<lb/> bestowed on it vast means to render it impregnable<lb/> and withal magnificent and fertile.  When the<lb/> Roman general Flavius Silva undertook to storm<lb/> the stronghold&#44; its commander was a certain Eleazar&#44;<lb/> a descendant of that Judah &#38; Galilee&#44; who had pro&#45;<lb/>&#45;claimed it a crime to pay tributes to a foreign power.<lb/>  He emboldened the people with resistance&#44; and with<lb/> a military genius deserving of a better success&#44; kept<lb/> the foe at bay&#44; and made the battering rams im&#45;<lb/>&#45;potent.  But the element&#44; which had destroyed<lb/> the capital and its sanctuary&#44; conspired also against<lb/> this band of heroes.  The be<sic>seiged</sic> had run up a double<lb/> wall&#44; the posterior of which was so ingeniously constructed that the more it<lb/> was battered beaten against the more solid it became.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>The Roman general perceiving the impossibility<lb/> of gaining his point by war inquiry&#44; ordered that fire brands be thrown<lb/> upon the inner wall&#44; made which was consisted of immense beams of<lb/> timber felled covered all over with earth.  The wind which at<lb/> first had blown into the face of the Romans and dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;concerted their plans&#44; suddenly changed and the for&#45;<lb/>&#45;tress of Masada was delivered to the flames.  The<lb/> same night the commander assembled the defenders and<lb/> spoke thus&#58; &#34;Since we long ago&#44; my generous friends&#44;&#34; re&#45;<lb/>&#45;solved never to be servants to the Romans&#44; nor to any<lb/> other than to God Himself&#44; the time has now come that<lb/> obliges us to put that resolution into practice.&#34;  He then<lb/> reminded his hearers companions of the tenacity with which they had<lb/> clung to their principle&#44; and how they were had to the very last to<lb/> dealt a blows at a despotic power&#44; though with no<lb/> avail&#44; through a dispensation of Providence.<lb/>  They should crown their firmness steadfastness by a desperate but<lb/> necessary deed.  They should setting all their property on fire that it might not enrich the enemy&#44; killing<lb/> their wives that they might not be defiled by a loose<lb/> Roman soldiery&#44; their children that they might not be<lb/> sold at the market place as slaves&#44; and then slaying<lb/> one another.  As he Eleazar noticed that at his proposition<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>some strong men wept and looked yearningly towards their wives those they loved most&#44;<lb/> and children&#44; Eleazar he portrayed in vivid touches the a<lb/> free existence in immortality&#44; far to be preferred<lb/> to a life of shame and abject bondage.<lb/></p>
            <p>It is certainly incredible that Eleazar the commander should have<lb/> delivered at such a time&#44; the lengthy and learned dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;course reported by Josephus&#44; who was not present&#59;<lb/> but it is beyond doubt that the impassioned words<lb/> of the chief struck a responsive chord.  The men<lb/> clasped to their hearts their wives and children&#44;<lb/> gave them the warmest kiss&#44; then plunged the<lb/> weapon into their breasts.  Having chosen by<lb/> lot ten of their number to act as executioners&#44; they<lb/> offered their necks to receive the fatal blow.  Then<lb/> nine of the ten fell by each other&#39;s hand&#44; and the<lb/> last setting fire to the palace and the most va&#45;<lb/>&#45;luable objects collected therein&#44; drove the sword<lb/> into his own body.  Early in the morn&#45;<lb/>&#45;ing the Romans scaled the walls&#45;&#45;None resisted.<lb/>  They entered the city&#45;&#45;silence remained unbroken.<lb/>  They met nothing&#44; they heard nothing not a sound&#44; save the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>crackling of the flames still burning.  A<lb/> shout went up as if to awaken those wrapped<lb/> in deep sleep.  The noise brought out two wo&#45;<lb/>&#45;men and five children.  They had crept into a<lb/> cave and escaped the voluntary slaughter.<lb/>  Some One of the women females&#44; related the act of self&#45;sacri&#45;<lb/>&#45;fice by which nine hundred and sixty had<lb/> perished.  The Romans refused to believe&#44; but<lb/> having partly extinguished the fire&#44; and opened<lb/> a way into the palace&#44; they beheld the closing tragic<lb/> scene of a nation&#39;s political death.  Who<lb/> dares deny the Jew a freedom loving soul&#63;<lb/>  Involuntary perhaps&#44; Josephus pays a tribute<lb/> to those unhappy votaries of liberty&#44; though when in the pages which<lb/> he wrote he very nearly close his narratives.  But when he wrote to immortalize our heros martyrs&#44; he was himself was enjoying ease at Rome.  All<lb/> lands in the country of his birth were ordered by<lb/> the twin emperors at Rome in the eternal city to be put up for at<lb/> sale a public sale&#44; but the favorite of Vespa&#45;<lb/>sian and Titus was granted other and larger posses&#45;<lb/>&#45;sions.  His coreligionists were condemned to pay<lb/> for the rebuilding of the temple of Jupiter Capitolnius&#44;<lb/> which had been also devoured by the flames&#44; the<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>same tax which they had given for the support of<lb/> the temple at Jerusalem&#44; but Josephus was exempt<lb/> from all taxation&#44; was declared a Roman citizen&#44;<lb/> and received a yearly stipend.  Having<lb/> married a third time&#44; after having divorced his two for&#45;<lb/>&#45;mer wives&#44; he settled under the aegis of the empire&#44;<lb/> with his three remaining sons&#44; among a people that<lb/> was not had destroyed his own people.  The boast he makes in<lb/> his autobiography does not raise him in our<lb/> estimation as an impartial historian.  That<lb/> his writings bore the mark of an imperial appro&#45;<lb/>&#45;bation is not a recommendation to his outraged<lb/> people brethren&#59; that what he said of the Jews and their<lb/> wars&#44; pleased Agrippa II is rather a cause of<lb/> displeasure ot us&#44; who know how degenerate<lb/> was that would Jewish king&#44; of the Jews&#44; and how he and<lb/> his sister Berenice have forfeited for ever the<lb/> respect of posterity.  Nevertheless&#44; the lovers the authors<lb/> student of history does miss the well connected and elegantly penned narratives of Josephus&#44;<lb/> when obliged to search into a variety of works for<lb/> an account of events subsequent to the conquest of Titus.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="12"/>
            <p>To scholars who have labored unweariedly to<lb/> enlighten us on that important subject&#44; Hebrews<lb/> are greatly beholden.  To German Israelites of the<lb/> present age&#44; who have excelled in that branch of<lb/> literature&#44; as in many other departments of human<lb/> knowledge&#44; all honor is due.  To them thanks must their be<lb/> coreligionists rendered thanks by their coreligionists who<lb/> are eager to learn the stirring vicissitudes which<lb/> befell Israel in the days that have gone.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
