<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx12FF3_6</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_6_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_6_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_6_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_6_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_6_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_6_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_6_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_6_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_6_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_6_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_6_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx12ff3_6_6v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>9 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="typescript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>       
                                

                <pb n="1"/>
            <p>6th Lecture on post&#45;biblical history.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren.  While a reconstructed nation was peacefully<lb/> developing its powers under the new system introduced<lb/> by the men of the constitution the great Synod&#44; or &#34;Keneseth Ha&#45;gedolah&#34;; that is&#44; under<lb/> the system of Synagogal worship and the government of an august Senate&#44;<lb/> another nation&#44; un scarcely known till then heretofore in history&#44; was unfolding<lb/> its powers terrifically.  It The people latter people belonged to the Greek family&#44;<lb/> always at variance&#44; and&#44; as such&#44; it had been exposed to the inroads of its strong&#45;<lb/>&#45;er brother&#45;tribes.  But at last&#44; it gathered sufficient<lb/> force to repel attacks aggression&#44; and extend its boundaries.  It was&#44;<lb/> not however&#44; only after Philip took in his hands the reins of the king&#45;<lb/>&#45;dom that Macedonia grew gigantic.  But Macedonia<lb/> might have remained for ever a stranger to the Judeans&#44;<lb/> if Philip had not begotten a son&#44; whose territorial ambition was knew no was<lb/> beyond all bound.less  Alexander&#44; not undeservedly called<lb/> &#34;the Great&#44;&#34; had early displayed the warlike spirit by<lb/> which he was ruled.  When almost a mere lad&#44;<lb/> he had already signalized himself in his father&#39;s army&#44;<lb/> but at twenty two years of age he mounted the throne at twenty years of age with<lb/> plans designs illimitably vast&#44; with a mature project plans for<lb/> pushing his conquests from the small country he had inherited in a corner<lb/> of Europe&#44; to the very heart of Persia Asia.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>The wish to humble Persia&#44; that since the days of<lb/> Cyrus had become the terror of nations subjugated almost the whole Eastern hemisphere&#44; was not peculiar<lb/> to Alexander.  It had been shared harbored by his predecessors<lb/> and by all Greece&#44; but he carried out that desire triumphantly.<lb/>  The empire which had commanded the Euphrates like the<lb/> Tigris&#44; the Ganges Indus as the Mediterranean sea was completely<lb/> broken by the staggering blows of the young Macedonian King.<lb/>  To hope that the Holy Land would have remained uninjured<lb/> by the thunder of war was to have expected a miracle.<lb/>  Alexander had come near the spot&#44; which our ancestors in&#45;<lb/>&#45;habited&#44; in an angry mood.  For he had spent a longer<lb/> time and had met with a more obstinate determined resistance<lb/> in a fighting a Phoenician city&#44; than he had could have antici&#45;<lb/>&#45;ated.  The famous Tyre&#44; or Zor of the Scriptures&#44;<lb/> whose merchants Isaiah called styled conferred to &#34;princes&#44;&#34; and whose traders<lb/> he styled &#34;the honorable of the earth&#34;; that Zor on wh the description of<lb/> whose commercial resources&#44; Ezekiel bestowed the sublimest<lb/> outpourings of his inspired genius&#44; did not surrender with<lb/>&#45;out a tremendous fierce struggle.  The fortified city was stormed&#44;<lb/> but not without having every inch of ground was &#91;&#63;&#93; desperately disputed&#44;&#45;&#45;<lb/> a dear was its conquest to the Macedonian&#44; who lost full six many a<lb/> months in battling for it&#44; and left upon the field some of his bravest soldiers.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>&#91;&#63;&#93; Exasperated at this unusual check to his rapid movements&#44;<lb/> Alexander marched on to Syria and from thence sent an imperious message<lb/> to the Judeans to prepare to open their gates to his army&#44; to<lb/> supply it with provision&#44; and hand over a large rich tribute.<lb/>  He surely did not expect a check drawback in that quarter section of the world.<lb/>  The people of Judea were remarkably peaceful&#59; and what they cared most for was the<lb/> preservation and exercise of their ancient laws.  But Alexander who had<lb/> imbibed knowledge from Aristotle&#44; had not learnt that one<lb/> of those Jewish laws&#44; sacredly kept observed in all ages&#44; was that of commanded never<lb/> to violating an oath.  Since the days of Cyrus&#44; their liberator<lb/> and benefactor&#44; the dwellers of the Holy Land had paid an an&#45;<lb/>&#45;nual tribute to Persia.  They could not voluntarily go<lb/> over on the side of the conqueror&#44; because Darius Codomanus<lb/> had been defeated.  The force of altered circumstances might<lb/> compel them so to do&#44; but they could would not&#44; of their own accord&#44;<lb/> break recall the fealty once sworn and long kept.  The The Macedonian&#44; Master of<lb/> Western Asia&#44; who was felt and feeling and certain of sitting himself emperor of<lb/> the world habitable globe&#44; the Macedonian was not accustomed<lb/> to refusals.  He made the people at Jerusalem to understand<lb/> that they might get ready for the worst.  Old historians say<lb/> nothing farther about this issue of his determination. to destroy<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>Josephus is the only one who tells how the intended<lb/> extermination was averted.  All my hearers are acquainted<lb/> with the episode which he has related&#44; and which the Talmud<lb/> substantially reproduces.  I will shall repeat it therefore very<lb/> briefly.  Dread seized every heart at the approach<lb/> of a foreign <sic>redoutable</sic> army&#44; formidable and thirsting for spoil&#59; but<lb/> a vision at night revealed to the high priest the means of<lb/> deliverance.  He Awaking&#44; he ordered that the city of Jerusalem be garlanded<lb/> with flowers&#59; that all the priests in their white robes form<lb/> a procession which he himself would lead&#44; arrayed with his breast&#45;<lb/>plate on which the twelve precious stones were resplendent&#44; beamed forth brilliant rays&#44; and<lb/> the mitre&#44; on which whereon the words &#34;holiness unto Adona&#239; shone<lb/> in pure gold.  Alexander saw that procession as it<lb/> moved imposingly from Sapha&#44; an eminence from which whence<lb/> the Temple could be loomed high.  At that sight&#44; the<lb/> proud monarch fell upon his face and bent his knees. low.  Asked<lb/> by one of his generals an as explanation for so singular an<lb/> act of adoration on the part of the hero who never bowed to man&#44;<lb/> Alexander answered that he prostrated himself before the<lb/> God whom that priest represented served&#59; that what stood before<lb/> his eyes at that moment had appeared to him in a dream&#44; when<lb/> about to undertake the conquest of Asia&#44; and had assured him of the victory.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>Now&#44; it can scarcely hardly be doubted credited that Josephus would<lb/> have so far compromised his veracity reputation as to invent that nar&#45; story&#44;<lb/> &#45;rative in order to glorify his people nation belief.  Still&#44; the silence of Greek<lb/> historians has caused many to deny the whole narrative.<lb/>  To us who know the ill&#45;will of the Hellenic people against to the<lb/> Jewish people&#44; that islence is not surprising&#44; since even the<lb/> wars of the Maccabees have no mention in the pages wh of<lb/> those who wrote writings that have expatiated on the greatness of exploits of ancient Greece.  Yet It is however&#44; beyond cert&#45;<lb/> &#45;tain doubt&#44; that whether from genuine respect reverence or from a crafty calculating<lb/> policy&#44; Alexander passed from through Palestine over to Egypt&#44; without<lb/> having molested the Jews.  The principal difficulty<lb/> in the event just related is about the person who officiated at the time<lb/> as high&#45;priest&#59; for while Josephus calls him Jaddua&#44; the<lb/> Talmud asserts that it was Simeon&#44; the Just&#44; the last survivor<lb/> of the &#34;Keneseth Ha&#45;gedolah&#34;.  I shall not attempt to<lb/> reconcile the discrepancy&#44; though it is not impossible that the<lb/> same person individual may have borne the two names of Jaddua and Simeon.<lb/></p>
            <p>And we furthermore we<lb/> possess documents proving that a large number of our coreligionists<lb/> was attracted to the renowned city built by Alexander the great and<lb/> called after his name&#44; and that in Alexandria&#44; a Hebrew colony<lb/> had at its own option some districts assigned to it with &#91;&#63;&#93;&#44; to it&#44; and was where it enjoyed a generously treatment.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>But as the latter occupies a very honorable prominent position<lb/> in post&#45;biblical history&#44; I will allude to some of his<lb/> actions and of his pithy sayings.  That Hebrew priest<lb/> sensibly believed that to enjoy the goods of this world<lb/> with moderation&#44; is wise correct&#44; and that to deprive oneself of<lb/> these what is permissible is a mistaken piety.  Accordingly&#44; he disapproved<lb/> of the Nazarite vow&#44; which forbid any liquid made of the<lb/> juice of the grapes&#44; and prohibited also the eating of the fresh<lb/> or dry fruit of the vine.  Only in one occasion he signified<lb/> his approbation of that destructive pledge.  A handsome young she&#45;<lb/>&#45;pherd looking at his own reflection in the limpid brook to<lb/> which he had led his flock&#44; felt that vanity was a bout<lb/> to master his nature&#44; and by luring his steps to sinful paths&#44; unfit him for his calling the duties of life.  He<lb/> then resolved to become a Nazarite&#44; which demanded of its involved the ne&#45;<lb/>&#45;cessity of letting the hair of the head grow wildly long&#44; and<lb/> shaving it off entirely and burning it on the altar at the<lb/> expiration of the time for which the pledge was taken&#44; or on having touched some impure subject.<lb/>  Simeon inquired into the cause of the vow&#44; and having<lb/> heard it&#44; kissed the youth of on his forehead&#44; and said&#58;<lb/> &#34;May of such as you are be all Nazarites in Israel.<lb/>  To you applies the sentence of the Scriptures &#34;to be abstinent in honor<lb/> of the Lord&#33;&#34;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>But that noble Sage disclosed revealed to us his mind most<lb/> splendidly by his favorite maxim.  Simeon used<lb/> to teach that the world stands on a threefold basis&#59;<lb/> &#91;Hebrew&#93; &#34;upon religious instruction&#44; public worship<lb/> and personal kindness.&#34;  Religious instruction is indispensably<lb/> needful for a proper understanding of our obligations as moral<lb/> beings agents&#44; accountable of for our deeds in our private domestic and social<lb/> relations&#59; public worship&#44; is most very important as a reminder<lb/> of men&#39;s common origin and destination and of their utter<lb/> dependence on a universal Father for health&#44; sustenance and happiness&#59;<lb/> personal kindness is essential&#44; because through it all creatures<lb/> bear with the ills of life and even death&#44; the rich in the hour of distress not<lb/> less than the poor in their constant want&#44; the &#91;&#63;&#93; we through by the expectation of a last tribute<lb/> of respect received&#44; affection&#44; and the living&#44; who may have survived a general misfortune&#44;<lb/> disaster by the sympathy of fellow&#45;mortals.  That the absence of a righteous training&#44;<lb/> a refusal to humbly unite in prayers&#44; and indifference to human<lb/> sufferings will finally destroy a community is a truth&#44;<lb/> which Simeon the Just aimed to inculcate into the minds of<lb/> his contemporaries&#44; and which stands good in every age and gene&#45;<lb/>&#45;ration.  Probably the Sage of yore dwelt upon his maxim&#44;<lb/> by reason of the changes which the advent of Alexander in<lb/> Judea may ahve begun to effect among his contemp our ancestors.  For whereas formerly<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>they had scarcely held any communication with the foreign<lb/> people and its ruler to whom they paid a yearly tribute&#44;<lb/> now the Macedonian wars had brought Greeks near&#44; and<lb/> with them the danger of imbibing ideas destructive of Jewish<lb/> society.  Indeed&#44; if such had been the fears of entertained by Simeon the<lb/> Just&#44; they disclosed in him a very keen foresight.  For it was<lb/> not long after&#44; that our shepherds and tillers of ground in Judea sought<lb/> affluence in commerce&#44; and at Alexandria many they left the pious moral chaste<lb/> and simple habits of their fathers to adopt the loose and<lb/> heedless manners of the stranger.  At home also Nor was Grecianism harmless at home.  There also the teachings<lb/> of the Rabbis were by some displaced set aside for the philosophy of Epicurus&#44;<lb/> so that gradually the corruption which reached its crisis in the<lb/> days of Jason and Menala&#252;s&#44; and a to purify the country form which the im&#45;<lb/>&#45;mortal Asmoneans fought and conquered&#44; drew its poisonous origin<lb/> from the contact of the Jewish Hebrew with the Hellenic people element.<lb/>  But I must not anticipate events.  When I speak again on<lb/> post&#45;biblical history&#44; I shall point out the results of a civilization&#44;<lb/> whose end is not which &#91;&#63;&#93; did not did not have for its basis threefold basis a religious training&#44; piety&#44; and beneficence&#44;<lb/> but an artificial education&#44; sensual pleasure and selfishness&#59;<lb/> even the civilization of ancient Greece.<lb/></p>
            </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
