<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?> <TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>[no title given]</title>
                <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                <editor/>
                <sponsor/>
                <funder/>
                <principal/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition/>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp/>
                    <name/>
                </respStmt>
            </editionStmt>
            <extent>[information about file size goes here, information about extent of physical
                item comes later]</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Unpublished manuscript</publisher>
            </publicationStmt>
            <seriesStmt>
                <p>Not part of a series</p>
            </seriesStmt>
            <notesStmt>
                <note/>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <!-- catalog entry goes here -->
                    <monogr>
                        <imprint>
                            <dateLet/>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
                <msDesc>
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>USA</country>
                        <region>PA</region>
                        <settlement>Philadelphia</settlement>
                        <institution/>
                        <repository>CAJS</repository>
                        <collection>Dropsie</collection>
                        <idno>SMBx9FF5_5</idno>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                        <msName/>
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head/>
                    <letHeading>
                        <author attested="yes" accepted="yes" signature="yes">Morais, Sabato</author>
                        <addressee editor="false" attested="yes" accepted="yes"></addressee>
                        <deliverer/>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp/>
                            <name/>
                        </respStmt>
                        <placeLet>Philadelphia, PA</placeLet>
                        <placeRec></placeRec>
                        <dateLet when="" source="" attested="yes"></dateLet>
                        
                    </letHeading>
                    <msContents>
                        <msItem>
                            <author/>
                            <editor/>
                            <respStmt>
                                <resp/>
                                <name/>
                            </respStmt>
                            <title/>
                            <decoNote/>
                            <listBibl>
                                <bibl/>
                            </listBibl>
                            <filiation/>
                            <textLang/>
                            <figure>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_5_1r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_5_1v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_5_2r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_5_2v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_5_3r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_5_3v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_5_4r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_5_4v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_5_5r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_5_5v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_5_6r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_5_6v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_5_7r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_5_7v.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_5_8r.tif"/>
                                <graphic url="smbx9ff5_5_8v.tif"/>
                            </figure>
                        </msItem>
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc>
                            <supportDesc>
                                <support>
                                    <material color="" lined="false" paper_type="" size=""
                                        >print</material>
                                </support>
                                <extent>11 pages on 4 sheets<dimensions/>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation/>
                                <collation/>
                                <condition fragment="false"></condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout/>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc script="manuscript">
                            <handNote/>
                        </handDesc>
                        <decoDesc>
                            <decoNote/>
                        </decoDesc>
                        <additions/>
                        <bindingDesc>
                            <binding>
                                <decoNote/>
                            </binding>
                        </bindingDesc>
                        <sealDesc>
                            <seal>
                                <p></p>
                            </seal>
                        </sealDesc>
                        <accMat/>
                        <envDesc occ="false"/>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin/>
                        <provenance/>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source/>
                                <change/>
                            </recordHist>
                            <availability status="free">
                                <p>Unrestricted</p>
                            </availability>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent/>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates/>
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                    <msPart>
                        <altIdentifier>
                            <idno/>
                        </altIdentifier>
                    </msPart>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <projectDesc>
                <p/>
            </projectDesc>
            <samplingDecl>
                <p/>
            </samplingDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <correction>
                    <p/>
                </correction>
                <normalization>
                    <p/>
                </normalization>
                <quotation>
                    <p/>
                </quotation>
                <hyphenation>
                    <p/>
                </hyphenation>
                <segmentation>
                    <p/>
                </segmentation>
                <stdVals>
                    <p/>
                </stdVals>
                <interpretation>
                    <p/>
                </interpretation>
            </editorialDecl>
            <tagsDecl>
                <rendition/>
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                    <tagUsage gi=""/>
                </namespace>
            </tagsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="" replacementPattern=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit=""/>
            </refsDecl>
            <classDecl>
                <taxonomy>
                    <category>
                        <catDesc/>
                    </category>
                </taxonomy>
            </classDecl>
            <appInfo>
                <application ident="" version="">
                    <desc/>
                    <label/>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <creation/>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
            <textClass>
                <keywords scheme="unknown">
                    <list>
                        <item/>
                        <item/>
                    </list>
                </keywords>
                <classCode scheme=""/>
                <catRef/>
            </textClass>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change/>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb n="1"/> 
            
            <p>An explanatory lecture<lb/> for Chay&#232; Sar&#225;h<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="2"/>
            <p>Brethren&#33;  It is usual with preachers&#44; to select from<lb/> the scriptures such characters&#44; that as may be usefully<lb/> exhibited before their hearers.  Innumerable are the<lb/> sermons&#44; written to teach lessons of piety by descanting on the life of<lb/> the patriarchs&#59; or of simplicity&#44; through a description<lb/> of their manners and habits.  I have no doubt<lb/> that if what divines have spoken&#44; concerning eminent<lb/> men of the Bible&#44; could be were collected together&#44; it would fill<lb/> up a space as extensive as that of the largest library.<lb/>  But I do not remember to have heard&#44; nor have I ever<lb/> read&#44; a discourse which purported to extol the character<lb/> of a heathen slave&#44; that figures prominently in sacred<lb/> history&#58; I mean&#44; an address&#44; that will afford us instruction<lb/> by the example of Elizer&#44; the trusty servant of his master<lb/> Abraham.  And yet&#44; he is truly a noble specimen of<lb/> human virtue.  The qualities which distinguished him that bondsman&#44;<lb/> are brought out&#44; in bold relief&#44; as it were&#44; by a contract with<lb/> the mean spirit of individuals&#44; whom the world would<lb/> &#91;&#63;&#93; consider&#44; by far&#44; his superiors.  Attend&#58;<lb/> the portion of the Pentateuch designated for this Sabbath&#44;<lb/> has preserved the account of the first business transaction<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="3"/>
            <p>ever known among the ancients.  Through it&#44; we<lb/> are made acquainted with a wealthy owner of real<lb/> estate.  Abraham anxious to purchase a tract<lb/> of land&#44; in which his lately lamented wife could be<lb/> interred&#44; and which he might bequeath as a burial<lb/> place for his descendants&#44; addressed a company of Hittites&#44;<lb/> at that time rulers of the city of Hebron&#44; that they might<lb/> induce a townsman of theirs&#44; to part with a certain lot<lb/> he possessed.  It happened that Ephron&#44; the opulent rich<lb/> owner thereof proprietor&#44; whom Abraham knew only by reputation&#44;<lb/> was sitting among the assembled multitude.  He had heard<lb/> the generous offer made to the Hebrew patriarch by<lb/> the men there convened.  They would not entertain<lb/> the thought of receiving a compensation for the piece<lb/> of ground he needed.  Everyone had expressed him&#45;<lb/>&#45;self wiling to allow him the choicest spot in his<lb/> family cemetery.  But as that offer had been<lb/> thankfully declined&#44; and Abraham seemed to have set<lb/> his heart upon securing the cave of Macpelah&#44; as a<lb/> burial place exclusively of his own&#44; Ephron assumed<lb/> a virtue of which he was entirely destitute.  he professed<lb/> the highest regard for him that stood there&#44; as petitioning<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="4"/>
            <p>for a boon&#44; though ready to pay any amount&#44; for<lb/> what he desired to obtain.  He Ephron would show that his<lb/> generosity exceeded that of all others.  Accordingly&#59;<lb/> he urged the free acceptance not alone of the cave<lb/> asked for&#44; but also of the field which surrounded it.<lb/>  But Hollow however were those proffers of friendship.  He<lb/> who had made them&#44; experienced only one feeling&#58; supreme<lb/> egotism.  He was anxious to create abroad an im&#45;<lb/>&#45;pression&#44; that his liberality had no parallel&#44; but in order<lb/> the better to succeed in promoting his own interest.<lb/>  Ephron was a dealer of consummate cunning.  Such<lb/> a man&#44; not unfrequently rarely met in the high walks of<lb/> life&#44; who&#44; being rich and widely known&#44; would make<lb/> you believe that he is showering down favors upon you&#44;<lb/> while the love of self is the main spring of his actions.<lb/>  So that wily Hittite declared&#44; with feigned lips that the<lb/> sum of four hundred shekels&#44; which the trust of land&#44; required&#44;<lb/> would be worth&#44; was too insignificant a sum to cause Abraham<lb/> to hesitate in accepting it as a gift.  He designedly<lb/> exaggerated the value of his property&#59; but the patriarch fa&#45;<lb/>thomed his object purpose&#44; and paid without demur the price set<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="5"/>
            <p>on the spot he was eager to possess.  Abraham&#39;s discer&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment must&#44; at that hour on that occasion&#44; have revealed to him this truth&#59;<lb/> namely&#58; that the qualities of the heart are not enhanced<lb/> in proportion as we rise on the scale of human temporal greatness&#44;<lb/> for they can be seen in all their genuine beauty among<lb/> the humble grades of society.  The offer made to him<lb/> by the unpretending multitude&#44; was earnestly meant&#59;<lb/> that of the most wealthy individual in their midst was<lb/> insincere and deceitful deceptive.<lb/></p>
            <p>But the lesson of this week&#44; contrasts very forcibly the<lb/> character of a man in a lowly condition with that of<lb/> others in affluence and independence&#44; when it first<lb/> introduces Laban to our notice.  Why does he<lb/> run so swiftly quickly to meet Abraham&#39;s servant&#63;  Is he<lb/> impelled by a wish to hospitably entertain a stranger&#63;<lb/>  The question is solved by the simple words of Holy Writ.<lb/>  &#34;It came to pass&#44; that when he saw the ring and the<lb/> bracelets&#44; that he ran out to the man.&#34;  The glittering<lb/> of the jewels which adorned his sister&#44; lent agility to<lb/> his feet.  That smoothed his tongue and dictated<lb/> pleasing agreeable words.  Nor was the love of gain&#44;<lb/> the only exhibited more glaringly at a later period of his history&#44; passion that lurked within Laban&#39;s breast.<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            <p>He possessed also a domineering spirit.  His mind swelled<lb/> with the ideas of his own superiority.  He enjoys a competency&#44; hence he must needs be wise&#44; he must be the essence of knowledge.  We hear him<lb/> speak&#44; when not without being consulted.  He advances his opinion<lb/> before either of his parents&#59; and he would defer the<lb/> consummation of the object&#44; which Eliezer had so much<lb/> at heart&#44; by unnecessarily detaining his sister Rebecca&#44; a year or &#91;&#63;&#93;.<lb/>  Let us now&#44; my Brethren&#33; place opposite to the<lb/> portraits of the two men of high social standing&#44; whose<lb/> traits I have delineated&#44; that of one in the humblest walks<lb/> of life.  He is a slave&#44; bound to the will of his master&#59;<lb/> but no trace of objectnession rests upon his countenance.<lb/>  Humility may be seen in the slight bent of his head&#59; but<lb/> that is a reflection of the soul of the man be served.<lb/>  He does not deem it a degradation to be absolutely at his<lb/> disposal.  For he knows of no pleasure&#44; except that which<lb/> is felt by Abraham.  He has no interest&#44; save in in<lb/> promoting that of Abraham&#59; his exertions are directed with<lb/> a singleness of purpose to heighten the happiness<lb/> of Abraham.  For&#44; the hand which ruled him&#44; had<lb/> never weighed heavily upon his manly form.  It was<lb/> a beneficent hand.  By it he was persuasively gently led into the way<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="7"/>
            <p>of truth&#44; and it alone pointed out to him where human<lb/> exaltation does exist.  He Eliezer learnt from his righteous<lb/> master&#44; that to labor with fidelity in whatever position<lb/> Providence may have placed us&#44; is an honor and a virtue.<lb/>  And to the performance of that duty he bent his whole<lb/> mind energy.  Therefore was he entrusted with the govern&#45;<lb/>&#45;ment of the household of Abraham.  Therefore<lb/> he became the confidential friend of the godly patriarch.<lb/>  Do you not think&#44; my Brethren&#33; that under such circum&#45;<lb/>&#45;stances the gradual awakening of a feeling of self&#45;importance&#44;<lb/> might be almost anticipated&#63;  Verily&#44; we could excuse<lb/> that sense of pride&#44; which seeks to conceal a lowly condi&#45;<lb/>&#45;tion in life&#44; when a higher one could might be safely assumed.<lb/>  But I cannot behold&#44; without admiring it&#44; the striking honesty<lb/> of Eliezer&#44; that knows of no prevarication&#44; of no evasion.<lb/>  He is charged with a mission which Abraham would<lb/> assign to no other man.  He is sent forth as the<lb/> representative of an opulent Chief&#44; desirous of forming<lb/> a matrimonial alliance for the noble scion of his flock.<lb/>  Objects of great value are given him&#44; to prove the reality of his errand.<lb/>  He meets with success.  The fmaily of the damsel<lb/> he has chosen in his own mind&#44; as the wife of his master&#39;s son&#44; receive<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="8"/>
            <p>him s in a manner suiting a person of rank.<lb/>  A table is immediately spread before him out&#44; that he<lb/> may refresh himself after a weary fatiguing journey.  But he<lb/> refuses to eat.  He must first tell the purpose for why<lb/> which he had come from a distant land.  They all listen attentively.<lb/>  He speaks.  &#34;I am Abraham&#39;s servant.&#34;  Oh&#33; faith&#45;<lb/>&#45;ful Eliezar&#33; thou mightest have said with equal<lb/> propriety.  &#34;I am the most ultimate friend of your rich<lb/> relative.&#34;  I am he that enjoys his entire confidence&#44;<lb/> and to a vast degree his affection.&#34;....But no&#44; he valued<lb/> what his virtues had carried for him&#44; only in proportion<lb/> as he could thereby do his master some service.<lb/>  The humility which had drawn from the lips of the patriarch<lb/> the confession that he was but &#34;dust and ashes&#44;&#34; found its a bright<lb/> parallel exemplification in that son of the stranger bro reared under the<lb/> roof of a god&#45;fearing man.  He assumed nothing.<lb/>  He disclaimed the possession of any merit.  When<lb/> he petitions the Lord for the success of his undertaking&#44;<lb/> he asks it for the sake of Abraham.  When he discovers<lb/> that he has been divinely favored&#44; he ascribes it to<lb/> the goodly deeds of Abraham.  When He wishes that<lb/> the family of Rebecca acquiesce in his request&#44;<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="9"/>
            <p>he craves it as an act of kindness to Abraham.<lb/>  As to himself&#44; he believes he is not entitled to any<lb/> consideration.  He has but discharged an imperative<lb/> duty.  But to duly fully appreciate the &#91;&#63;&#93; excellency<lb/> of Eliezar&#39;s character&#44; we should bear in mind in what<lb/> relation he once stood to Abraham his master.  The founder of<lb/> <sic>of</sic> our nation&#44; had a vision&#44; in which God promised him<lb/> an exceedingly great reward.  But that celestial de&#45;<lb/>&#45;claration failed to gladden his heart.  It&#44; on the<lb/> contrary&#44; elicited a complaint.  The patriarch la&#45;<lb/>&#45;mented&#44; that whatever boon he might receive could<lb/> not be bequeathed to one&#44; who would perpetuate his<lb/> name.  For&#44; he was childless&#44; and Eliezer of Damascus&#44;<lb/> his steward&#44; would&#44; by the right acquired from constant<lb/> fidelity&#44; become his heir.  But it was otherwise dis&#45;<lb/>&#45;posed by the Deity.  Sarah bore a son in her old<lb/> age.  On him did his father &#91;&#63;&#93; all mainly bestow his love&#59; and<lb/> for his special enjoyment he left what he possessed.<lb/>  Eliezer&#44; who may have divined the intentions firstly<lb/> entertained by his master&#44; saw now his expectations<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="10"/>
            <p>frustrated.  But it mattered not to him.<lb/>  Covetousness had never intruded upon his feelings.<lb/>  Duty and not more was the star that guided<lb/> him through life.  To that he looked&#44; and the con&#45;<lb/>&#45;sciousness of having performed his task well&#44; was his<lb/> reward.  Aye&#58; the very child&#44; whose birth had deprived<lb/> him of worldly advantages&#44; became the object of<lb/> his solicitude.  To forward his domestic happiness he <sic>travelled</sic><lb/> far&#44; and prayed long&#59; and when the damsel destined to<lb/> share with Isaac all his substance&#44; descrying him from a<lb/> distance&#44; asked for his name&#44; the meek and affectionate<lb/> Eliezer answered &#34;he is my master.&#34;  But Eliezer<lb/> was not a slave.  He was a nobleman.  I call<lb/> him a slave&#44; who drudges incessantly that others may<lb/> gather what he has sown&#59; him that cannot give<lb/> his mind rest&#44; for fear that what he holds in his<lb/> grasp may make itself wings and fly away.<lb/>  No man who has a high aim before his mental vision&#59; and<lb/> strives to attain it by patient labor&#44; and hones exert&#45;<lb/>&#45;ions&#44; let his sphere be what it may&#44; is honorable &#38; praise&#45;worthy.<lb/>  and honorable.  Ephron with all his land pos&#45;<lb/>&#45;sessions&#44; was contemptibly low.  Laban whose eyes<lb/></p>
            
            <pb n="11"/>
            <p>glistened with delight only at the sight of<lb/> gold&#44; was servilely abject.  Eliezer was their<lb/> superior in whatever distinguishes an intelligent<lb/> and responsible being from an irrational animal.<lb/>  Therefore have I placed his character as a mirror<lb/> before you.  Men in humble circumstances&#33;<lb/>  Look in it and be upheld in virtue.  You are<lb/> not inferior to those who need your stalwart arms.<lb/>  Idleness and <sic>mendicity</sic> will lower you in the scale<lb/> of social standing.  Work&#44; hard&#44; or even what is some&#45;<lb/>&#45;times miscalled menial&#44; work&#44; can not never be debasing.<lb/>  Only be faithful to those who employ you&#44; true to<lb/> yourselves&#44; dignified though humble&#44; and let a sense<lb/> of duty be the impelling force of all your actions.<lb/></p>
            
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
